<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Justices' 6-to-3 Ruling on Aid to Parochial Schools</title>
    <meta content="Y29ETE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EED71E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Justices' 6-to-3 Ruling on Aid to Parochial Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Supreme Court ruling upholding federal program that places computers in parochial school classrooms</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the Supreme Court ruling today that a federal government program that places computers in parochial school classrooms does not violate the constitutional separation between church and state. The vote in Mitchell v. Helms was 6 to 3. Justice Clarence Thomas wrote the majority opinion; Justice David H. Souter wrote the dissent.</p>
        <p>FROM THE DECISION  By Justice Thomas</p>
        <p>As part of a longstanding school aid program known as Chapter 2, the federal government distributes funds to state and local governmental agencies, which in turn lend educational materials and equipment to public and private schools, with the enrollment of each participating school determining the amount of aid that it receives. The question is whether Chapter 2, as applied in Jefferson Parish, La., is a law respecting an establishment of religion, because many of the private schools receiving Chapter 2 aid in that parish are religiously affiliated. We hold that Chapter 2 is not such a law. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the Supreme Court ruling today that a federal government program that places computers in parochial school classrooms does not violate the constitutional separation between church and state. The vote in Mitchell v. Helms was 6 to 3. Justice Clarence Thomas wrote the majority opinion; Justice David H. Souter wrote the dissent.</p>
        <p>FROM THE DECISION  By Justice Thomas</p>
        <p>As part of a longstanding school aid program known as Chapter 2, the federal government distributes funds to state and local governmental agencies, which in turn lend educational materials and equipment to public and private schools, with the enrollment of each participating school determining the amount of aid that it receives. The question is whether Chapter 2, as applied in Jefferson Parish, La., is a law respecting an establishment of religion, because many of the private schools receiving Chapter 2 aid in that parish are religiously affiliated. We hold that Chapter 2 is not such a law. . . .</p>
        <p>The Establishment Clause of the First Amendment dictates that ''Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion.'' We have consistently struggled to apply these simple words in the context of governmental aid to religious schools. As we admitted in Tilton v. Richardson, ''candor compels the acknowledgment that we can only dimly perceive the boundaries of permissible government activity in this sensitive area.''  . . . Considering Chapter 2 in light of our more recent case law, we conclude that it neither results in religious indoctrination by the government nor defines its recipients by reference to religion. We therefore hold that Chapter 2 is not a ''law respecting an establishment of religion.''</p>
        <p>As we indicated in Agostini, and have indicated elsewhere, the question whether governmental aid to religious schools results in governmental indoctrination is ultimately a question whether any religious indoctrination that occurs in those schools could reasonably be attributed to governmental action. We have also indicated that the answer to the question of indoctrination will resolve the question whether a program of educational aid ''subsidizes'' religion, as our religion cases use that term.</p>
        <p>In distinguishing between indoctrination that is attributable to the state and indoctrination that is not, we have consistently turned to the principle of neutrality, upholding aid that is offered to a broad range of groups or persons without regard to their religion. If the religious, irreligious, and areligious are all alike eligible for governmental aid, no one would conclude that any indoctrination that any particular recipient conducts has been done at the behest of the government. For attribution of indoctrination is a relative question.</p>
        <p>If the government is offering assistance to recipients who provide, so to speak, a broad range of indoctrination, the government itself is not thought responsible for any particular indoctrination.</p>
        <p>To put the point differently, if the government, seeking to further some legitimate secular purpose, offers aid on the same terms, without regard to religion, to all who adequately further that purpose, then it is fair to say that any aid going to a religious recipient only has the effect of furthering that secular purpose. The government, in crafting such an aid program, has had to conclude that a given level of aid is necessary to further that purpose among secular recipients and has provided no more than that same level to religious recipients. . . .</p>
        <p>As a way of assuring neutrality, we have repeatedly considered whether any governmental aid that goes to a religious institution does so ''only as a result of the genuinely independent and private choices of individuals.''</p>
        <p>We have viewed as significant whether the ''private choices of individual parents,'' as opposed to the ''unmediated'' will of government, determine what schools ultimately benefit from the governmental aid, and how much. For if numerous private choices, rather than the single choice of a government, determine the distribution of aid pursuant to neutral eligibility criteria, then a government cannot, or at least cannot easily, grant special favors that might lead to a religious establishment.</p>
        <p>Private choice also helps guarantee neutrality by mitigating the preference for pre-existing recipients that is arguably inherent in any governmental aid program, and that could lead to a program inadvertently favoring one religion or favoring religious private schools in general over nonreligious ones. . . .</p>
        <p>Applying the two relevant Agostini criteria, we see no basis for concluding that Jefferson Parish's Chapter 2 program ''has the effect of advancing religion.'' Chapter 2 does not result in governmental indoctrination, because it determines eligibility for aid neutrally, allocates that aid based on the private choices of the parents of schoolchildren and does not provide aid that has an impermissible content. Nor does Chapter 2 define its recipients by reference to religion.</p>
        <p>Taking the second criterion first, it is clear that Chapter 2 aid ''is allocated on the basis of neutral, secular criteria that neither favor nor disfavor religion, and is made available to both religious and secular beneficiaries on a nondiscriminatory basis.''</p>
        <p>Aid is allocated based on enrollment: ''Private schools receive Chapter 2 materials and equipment based on the per capita number of students at each school,'' and allocations to private schools must ''be equal (consistent with the number of children to be served) to expenditures for programs under this subchapter for children enrolled in the public schools of the L.E.A. [local education agency].''</p>
        <p>L.E.A.'s must provide Chapter 2 materials and equipment for the benefit of children in private schools ''to the extent consistent with the number of children in the school district of [an L.E.A.] who are enrolled in private nonprofit elementary and secondary schools.''</p>
        <p>The allocation criteria therefore create no improper incentive. Chapter 2 does, by statute, deviate from a pure per capita basis for allocating aid to L.E.A.'s, increasing the per-pupil allocation based on the number of children within an L.E.A. who are from poor families, reside in poor areas, or reside in rural areas. But respondents have not contended, nor do we have any reason to think, that this deviation in the allocation to the L.E.A.'s leads to deviation in the allocation among schools within each L.E.A., and, even if it did, we would not presume that such a deviation created any incentive one way or the other with regard to religion.</p>
        <p>Chapter 2 also satisfies the first Agostini criterion. The program makes a broad array of schools eligible for aid without regard to their religious affiliations or lack thereof. We therefore have no difficulty concluding that Chapter 2 is neutral with regard to religion. . . .</p>
        <p>Finally, Chapter 2 satisfies the first Agostini criterion because it does not provide to religious schools aid that has an impermissible content.</p>
        <p>The statute explicitly bars anything of the sort, providing that all Chapter 2 aid for the benefit of children in private schools shall be ''secular, neutral, and nonideological,'' and the record indicates that the Louisiana S.E.A. [State Education Agency] and the Jefferson Parish L.E.A. have faithfully enforced this requirement insofar as relevant to this case.</p>
        <p>The chief aid at issue is computers, computer software and library books. The computers presumably have no pre-existing content, or at least none that would be impermissible for use in public schools. . . .</p>
        <p>In short, Chapter 2 satisfies both the first and second primary criteria of Agostini. It therefore does not have the effect of advancing religion. For the same reason, Chapter 2 also ''cannot reasonably be viewed as an endorsement of religion.'' Accordingly, we hold that Chapter 2 is not a law respecting an establishment of religion.</p>
        <p>FROM THE DISSENT  By Justice Souter</p>
        <p>The First Amendment's Establishment Clause prohibits Congress (and, by incorporation, the States) from making any law respecting an establishment of religion. It has been held to prohibit not only the institution of an official church, but any government act favoring religion, a particular religion, or for that matter irreligion. Thus it bars the use of public funds for religious aid.</p>
        <p>The establishment prohibition of government religious funding serves more than one end. It is meant to guarantee the right of individual conscience against compulsion, to protect the integrity of religion against the corrosion of secular support, and to preserve the unity of political society against the implied exclusion of the less favored and the antagonism of controversy over public support for religious causes.</p>
        <p>These objectives are always in some jeopardy since the substantive principle of no aid to religion is not the only limitation on government action toward religion. Because the First Amendment also bars any prohibition of individual free exercise of religion, and because religious organizations cannot be isolated from the basic government functions that create the civil environment, it is as much necessary as it is difficult to draw lines between forbidden aid and lawful benefit. For more than 50 years, this court has been attempting to draw these lines. . . .</p>
        <p>There may be no aid supporting a sectarian school's religious exercise or the discharge of its religious mission, while aid of a secular character with no discernible benefit to such a sectarian objective is allowable. Because the religious and secular spheres largely overlap in the life of many such schools, the court has tried to identify some facts likely to reveal the relative religious or secular intent or effect of the government benefits in particular circumstances. In all the years of its effort, the court has isolated no single test of constitutional sufficiency, and the question in every case addresses the substantive principle of no aid: what reasons are there to characterize this benefit as aid to the sectarian school in discharging its religious mission? Particular factual circumstances control, and the answer is a matter of judgment. . . .</p>
        <p>The prohibition that ''Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion'' eludes elegant conceptualization simply because the prohibition applies to such distinct phenomena as state churches and aid to religious schools, and as applied to school aid has prompted challenges to programs ranging from construction subsidies to hearing aids to textbook loans. Any criteria, moreover, must not only define the margins of the establishment prohibition, but must respect the succeeding clause of the First Amendment guaranteeing religion's free exercise. It is no wonder that the complementary constitutional provisions and the inexhaustibly various circumstances of their applicability have defied any simple test and have instead produced a combination of general rules often in tension at their edges. If coherence is to be had, the court has to keep in mind the principal objectives served by the Establishment Clause. . . .</p>
        <p>At least three concerns have been expressed since the founding and run throughout our First Amendment jurisprudence. First, compelling an individual to support religion violates the fundamental principle of freedom of conscience. . . . Second, government aid corrupts religion. . . . Third, government establishment of religion is inextricably linked with conflict. . . .</p>
        <p>These concerns are reflected in the court's classic summation delivered in Everson v. Board of Education, its first opinion directly addressing standards governing aid to religious schools:</p>
        <p>''The 'establishment of religion' clause of the First Amendment means at least this: Neither a state nor the federal government can set up a church. Neither can pass laws which aid one religion, aid all religions or prefer one religion over another. Neither can force nor influence a person to go to or to remain away from church against his will or force him to profess a belief or disbelief in any religion. No person can be punished for entertaining or professing religious beliefs or disbeliefs, for church attendance or nonattendance.  No tax in any amount, large or small, can be levied to support any religious activities or institutions, whatever they may be called, or whatever form they may adopt to teach or practice religion. Neither a state nor the federal government can, openly or secretly, participate in the affairs of any religious organizations or groups and vice versa. In the words of Jefferson, the clause against establishment of religion by law was intended to erect 'a wall of separation between church and state.' '' . . .</p>
        <p>In rejecting the principle of no aid to a school's religious mission the plurality is attacking the most fundamental assumption underlying the Establishment Clause, that government can in fact operate with neutrality in its relation to religion. I believe that it can, and so respectfully dissent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
