<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Ruling Fuels Debate On Vouchers For Education</title>
    <meta content="Y29EDU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT: THE IMPACT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Clarence (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DA1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Ruling Fuels Debate On Vouchers For Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Educators and advocates weigh how broadly Supreme Court decision allowing some federal aid for parochial schools can be applied; Justice Clarence Thomas used case to write strong opinion supporting school vouchers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For educators and advocates, the question prompted by yesterday's United States Supreme Court decision allowing some federal aid for private and parochial schools is, How broadly can it be applied?</p>
        <p>If the government can buy computers, books and audio-visual equipment for religious schools, as six justices ruled, how about bricks and mortar for buildings? Why not have states pay the salaries of Catholic-school teachers of a secular subject like mathematics? And, perhaps most important, can public money be used to offset tuition at schools sponsored by religions?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For educators and advocates, the question prompted by yesterday's United States Supreme Court decision allowing some federal aid for private and parochial schools is, How broadly can it be applied?</p>
        <p>If the government can buy computers, books and audio-visual equipment for religious schools, as six justices ruled, how about bricks and mortar for buildings? Why not have states pay the salaries of Catholic-school teachers of a secular subject like mathematics? And, perhaps most important, can public money be used to offset tuition at schools sponsored by religions?</p>
        <p>''What this fits into is a growing sense that public education can take place outside of the public schools,'' said Clint Bolick, litigation director for the Institute for Justice, a leading advocate of school vouchers that would allow taxpayer money to be used at private and parochial schools. ''This kind of decision makes public policy much more flexible in terms of aid following students rather than aid to the public school system exclusively.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday's ruling, in a case from Louisiana, concerns a narrow program providing instructional materials, but Justice Clarence Thomas took the opportunity to write a strong pro-voucher opinion focused on a neutrality test: whether aid is equally available to students regardless of where they study. Three justices joined his opinion.</p>
        <p>Two others, Sandra Day O'Connor and Stephen G. Breyer, voted only to uphold the purchase of computers and other equipment but declined to join Justice Thomas. They drew a distinction between direct aid to schools for materials and funneling money through parents in the form of vouchers that are used for religious as well as secular studies.</p>
        <p>That left something for both sides to celebrate.</p>
        <p>''There is a real silver lining,'' said Marc D. Stern, a lawyer for the American Jewish Congress, which  promotes separation of church and state and has helped fight voucher programs. ''Had Thomas gathered five votes for his opinion, vouchers would be constitutional. Since he didn't, it leads me to think that vouchers are unconstitutional.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolick, for his part, said, ''I understand they are trying to grasp at silver linings, but the cloud is puffy and white.''</p>
        <p>The ruling is the sixth in a row by the Supreme Court to uphold using public money in parochial schools. At the same time, opponents of vouchers have won victories in state supreme courts and lower federal courts, including rulings over the last year declaring voucher programs in both Florida and Cleveland illegal.</p>
        <p>The Cleveland case, in which arguments were heard by the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit last week, is expected to be reviewed by the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>''There have been mixed signals coming out of the courts,'' said Howard Fuller, an administrator at Marquette University and an architect of Milwaukee's 10-year-old school voucher program. ''Until there's an actual decision on a program like Ohio or Wisconsin, we just have to hold out hope.''</p>
        <p>Whatever it portends for future cases, the decision raises broad questions about public education.</p>
        <p>To Jeanne Allen, president of the pro-voucher Center for Education Reform, based in Washington, the court has endorsed her belief that ''educating children is no less a public endeavor just because the child is in a private school.''</p>
        <p>But Julie Underwood, general counsel for the National School Boards Association, said that ''public schools are fundamentally different from private schools'' and that ''we need to get people to recognize that there is incredible value in the public-school system.''</p>
        <p>In addition to rekindling the political debate over vouchers -- an issue that promises to persist in the presidential campaign -- yesterday's ruling is likely to spur many requests by parochial schools for equal funding in other government programs.</p>
        <p>''Public money that we wish would stay in public schools, that we think is needed in the public schools, as a constitutional matter is going to be able to go to the sectarian schools,'' said Robert Chanin, a lawyer representing the nation's largest teachers' union, the National Education Association, in the voucher cases.</p>
        <p>Leonard DeFiore, president of the National Catholic Education Association, said the decision should clear the way for a Clinton administration program that would connect every classroom, including those in private schools, to the Internet.</p>
        <p>''The Internet is a global classroom to which all students -- public and private -- must have entry,'' Mr. DeFiore said in a statement. ''This decision is justice served because it assures that these advantages will be accessible to all children.''</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT: THE IMPACT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
