<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking at a France That's Seldom Seen</title>
    <meta content="27RIDI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernier, Bertrand</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampiero, Dominique</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">It All Starts Today Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDB1F3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking at a France That's Seldom Seen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on veteran French film director Bertrand Tavernier's latest film It All Starts Today, written with son-in-law, Dominique Sampiero, about poverty-striken school in northern France, which opens on September 8; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR all of Bertrand Tavernier's reputation for being politically ''engage,'' the veteran French director's latest film did not begin with the ''big idea'' of denouncing poverty and unemployment hidden behind France's stolidly bourgeois facade. Rather, its genesis was an anecdote heard one evening over dinner with his 33-year-old daughter, Tiffany, and her husband, Dominique Sampiero, a poet who had spent 15 years teaching in public schools in run-down communities in the north of the country.</p>
        <p>''Dominique told the story of a woman who couldn't afford the monthly contribution to her children's school because she needed the 30 francs'' -- $4.50 -- ''for food,'' Mr. Tavernier, 59, recalled. ''I was taken aback. I said I hadn't heard that in any French movie. The year 2000 was approaching and I felt people needed to know that this was happening in France today, that things like that were happening just one hour from Paris.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR all of Bertrand Tavernier's reputation for being politically ''engage,'' the veteran French director's latest film did not begin with the ''big idea'' of denouncing poverty and unemployment hidden behind France's stolidly bourgeois facade. Rather, its genesis was an anecdote heard one evening over dinner with his 33-year-old daughter, Tiffany, and her husband, Dominique Sampiero, a poet who had spent 15 years teaching in public schools in run-down communities in the north of the country.</p>
        <p>''Dominique told the story of a woman who couldn't afford the monthly contribution to her children's school because she needed the 30 francs'' -- $4.50 -- ''for food,'' Mr. Tavernier, 59, recalled. ''I was taken aback. I said I hadn't heard that in any French movie. The year 2000 was approaching and I felt people needed to know that this was happening in France today, that things like that were happening just one hour from Paris.''</p>
        <p>From this conversation, then, was born ''It All Starts Today'' (''Ca Commence Aujourd'hui''), Mr. Tavernier's 19th feature film, which opens Sept. 8. The movie, which the director wrote with Mr. Sampiero and Ms. Tavernier, revolves around the young head of a kindergarten in a depressed suburb of the northern city of Valenciennes. And it is through this intense and idealistic man, Daniel Lefebvre, played by the rising stage and screen actor Philippe Torreton, that Mr. Tavernier makes his political point.</p>
        <p>In reality, the movie does little more than portray a few months in the life of an ''ecole maternelle'' whose very young pupils -- between the ages of 2 and 5 -- come from poor families. The school, however, cannot isolate itself from a social environment scarred by unemployment, alcoholism, malnutrition and child abuse. And, as Daniel finds himself drawn into the problems of the children and their parents, he grows increasingly frustrated by the inadequate response of welfare workers, school inspectors and the local mayor.</p>
        <p>Perhaps inevitably, the movie has strong echoes of a documentary, not only because it was shot in a kindergarten in Anzin, outside Valenciennes, with an existing class cast as Daniel's pupils, but also because improvisation is unavoidable when filming tiny children. Even more important, Anzin's story is identical to that of the film's fictional community. Having once stood at the heart of both France's coal industry and heroic battles by miners for better conditions (Emile Zola's epic novel ''Germinal,'' which Claude Berri made into a movie in 1993, was set there), Anzin has sunk into a depression over the past 30 years. And local residents who play small parts or act as extras in the film know first hand what this has meant.</p>
        <p>''There was always misery, but there was hope because there was work,'' Mr. Tavernier explained in the office of his production company, Little Bear. ''The jobs were badly paid, but there were union struggles, strikes that lasted for months, that gave hope. In the darkness, there was always light at the end of the tunnel. But now, in this region, people have no hope. The mines have closed, there are no jobs, there are no unions, people feel abandoned. There's a deep sense of demoralization. That's what I felt there. People have grown used to having no importance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tavernier is not alone in finding inspiration in the rawness of life in France's post-industrial north: among other recent films, Erick Zonka set ''The Dream Life of Angels'' and Bruno Dumont ''La Vie de Jesus'' in that territory. There is also the interesting parallel with England, where social blight in the north provided the backdrop for such movies as Mark Hermann's ''Brassed Off'' and Peter Cattaneo's ''Full Monty.'' Yet just as ''up north'' is a remote land for many Londoners, few Parisians know northern France. Indeed, even Mr. Tavernier, whose recent films include ''De l'Autre Cote du Periph'' (''The Other Side of the Tracks''), a documentary about drug problems in a poor Paris suburb, only discovered this world through his encounter with the ''ecole maternelle'' in Anzin.</p>
        <p>''I can now analyze things politically, but it didn't start out like that,'' he said. ''I knew nothing about life in a kindergarten, but then I saw that it spoke deeply about the country. Slowly, in talking to the children, I understood that we were talking about the state of one entire region of France. Later, after a screening, someone told me: 'The kindergarten is the birth of a nation.' I thought that was magnificent. All the problems at birth, if not dealt with, become dramatic. And that was the drama of the kindergarten. It lacked the resources to deal with all the problems it confronted.''</p>
        <p>Still, in his film, Mr. Tavernier leaves viewers to draw their own conclusions. He is more interested in the personalities involved in the kindergarten's life. Among them are Daniel's girlfriend, Valeria (Maria Pitaressi), an artist who earns her keep working as a waitress; a sympathetic social worker, Samia (Nadia Kaci); the school inspector (Didier Bezace); the mayor (Gerard Giroudon); and several of the school's teachers, including the experienced Madame Delacourt (Francoise Bette). A half-dozen children also feature in the incidents that run through the film, including that of the mother who needs her last 30 francs to feed her family.</p>
        <p>By good fortune, Mr. Torreton, who also starred in Mr. Tavernier's ''L627,''  ''Fresh Bait'' and ''Capitaine Conan,'' proved to be a natural kindergarten teacher, leading the children in songs and games, reacting instinctively to their interruptions and moods, hugging and teasing them with the ease and experience of a man, well, whose mother was a kindergarten teacher and who has children of his own, aged 3 and 7.</p>
        <p>''I was eager to meet the kids without any special preparation, because that's the fate of thousands of young teachers at the start of every school year,'' said Mr. Torreton, who is 35. ''I placed myself in the skin of a young teacher called Philippe Torreton, who was assigned to a kindergarten in Anzin. I had prepared classes and activities like any teacher, but I saw no point in going to other schools. I just told the children: 'Look, I'm an actor playing a teacher called Daniel. It's easy for you because you have to remember only one name. I have to remember 33.' Within two days, I was Daniel.''</p>
        <p>Being an actor also prepared him to perform in front of a class. But being a teacher, he said, was more challenging.</p>
        <p>''A teacher is never forgiven,'' he said with a laugh. ''As actors, we perform in front of people who have bought tickets and, even if they're bored, they're unlikely to make a fuss because they have paid good money. But for a teacher facing pupils who don't want to be there and are thinking only of recreation, the smallest mistake, the tiniest slip of attention, is punished. It's a terrible exposure.''</p>
        <p>Yet while the children are frequently on screen, as passive observers of the dramas surrounding them, they are not the real stars of the movie. Rather, ''It All Starts Today'' is an undisguised homage to France's teachers, with Daniel and his colleagues cast as Don Quixotes whose valiant combat the French should support and admire. Not everyone did, however.</p>
        <p>When the film was released in France 18 months ago, not a few critics said Mr. Tavernier had opted for melodrama and sentimentality. The left-of-center Paris daily Liberation complained that he had portrayed Daniel as a saint -- to which the director responded testily that there were 5,000 saints like Daniel in French schools. Le Monde's critic Jacques Mandelbaum asked whether a kindergarten director could be a hero of classical cinema -- to which Mr. Tavernier retorted that Michele Niewrzeda, the real director of the ''Behind the Hedge'' kindergarten at Anzin, was even more heroic.</p>
        <p>THERE were journalists who said it was all exaggerated,'' Mr. Tavernier went on. ''But for the people in the north, it was all very real. I received 2,000 letters from people saying, 'This is my life, it's like that, thank you for giving me courage.' It's not a film without hope. It's an energetic film that encourages people not to be passive. Even a psychiatrist told me that he uses the film to treat teachers suffering from depression.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tavernier was above all reassured -- and surprised -- by the public response. By his own admission, he had worried whether there was a market for a film that could even distantly be considered political. He noted that political films made by foreign directors did well in France (the British director Ken Loach is a case in point), but that the same fare by French directors usually flopped. With ''It All Starts Today,'' which cost $3.5 million to make, the film was set to break even if it sold 450,000 tickets. In practice, it sold twice as many in France and another 450,000 in Spain alone (''Even the King of Spain asked to see it,'' Mr. Tavernier exclaimed).</p>
        <p>In Mr. Torreton's view, what saved the film was that Mr. Tavernier did not set off with a political mission.</p>
        <p>''He works a lot through curiosity and the joy and anger provoked by his curiosity,'' Mr. Torreton said. ''He is above all someone with an appetite to see, to understand, to listen, to become involved. But when he makes a film, he has a sense of spectacle, no matter the subject, whether social drama or total romance. Too many filmmakers in France think that to offer some spectacle is to be commercial. Cinema is commerce. It's a commercial art.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Tavernier, however, more than the response of critics and audiences, there is something that convinced him that he got things right.</p>
        <p>''They have renamed the school in Anzin after me,'' he said, beaming with pride. ''It is now the Ecole Maternelle Bertrand Tavernier.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
