<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Correction Officers Ratify New Contract</title>
    <meta content="27JAIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DA1731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Correction Officers Ratify New Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Correction officers in Westchester County, NY, ratify new labor contract that eliminates contentious rule on disability leave (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FIVE-YEAR wait for pay raises is over for about 770 Westchester County correction officers after rank-and-file members ratified a new labor contract that eliminates a contentious rule on disability leave.</p>
        <p>''I would say that nobody won or lost: this was not a win-lose situation,'' Robert Goodstein, the lawyer for the correction officers' union, the Correction Officers Benevolent Association, said last week. ''I think everybody won.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FIVE-YEAR wait for pay raises is over for about 770 Westchester County correction officers after rank-and-file members ratified a new labor contract that eliminates a contentious rule on disability leave.</p>
        <p>''I would say that nobody won or lost: this was not a win-lose situation,'' Robert Goodstein, the lawyer for the correction officers' union, the Correction Officers Benevolent Association, said last week. ''I think everybody won.''</p>
        <p>Under the six-year agreement, which was accepted on Aug. 17 by a vote of 501 to 160, the officers will receive 25 percent raises through the end of 2001 -- or about 4 percent each year, officials said. The base salary for the average officer with five years on the job will jump to $60,188 from $47,050, Mr. Goodstein said.</p>
        <p>As a trade-off, officers at the County Jail in Valhalla will no longer receive a lucrative but controversial perquisite that allowed them to put themselves on disability without first having to prove any injury.</p>
        <p>The union held tightly to the benefit even as it caused contract negotiations to sputter for more than four years and the jail became tainted by the arrests of many officers for job-injury fraud, sexual abuse of female inmates and other charges.</p>
        <p>County Executive Andrew J. Spano called the injury policy bizarre and said that since it was negotiated in 1989 it had cost taxpayers millions of dollars in overtime and contributed to the jail's being $24 million over budget in the last decade.</p>
        <p>The issue sparked a bitter and at times hostile relationship between officers, their union and the county administration and heightened tensions in the jail where some officers were forced to work mandatory overtime shifts to cover for as many as 113 colleagues each day who were out on disability.</p>
        <p>Last week both sides expressed relief that the issue seems to be settled and predicted that a new era of compatibility and productivity was about to begin. The proposal still needs a vote by the county's 17-member Board of Legislators, where a  majority vote is needed for approval.</p>
        <p>''We established the beginning of a new positive environment at the jail that is good for morale, good for the union and good for county taxpayers,'' Mr. Spano said through a spokeswoman. ''Our goal is to treat our correction officers like professionals, and we expect them to act in the same way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Goodstein refused to discuss details of the new job-injury benefit, but he said it was quite complex and took up 20 pages in the labor agreement whereas the old benefit was written in six pages. Susan Tolchin, Mr. Spano's spokeswoman, said officers will now use their own sick time or vacation days while out on injury until a review board can rule on whether the claim is legitimate.</p>
        <p>''The officer has to prove it,'' she said, adding that if officers cannot prove a disability their days off will not be returned. She and Mr. Goodstein said the policy was adopted from a similar one in use in Suffolk County.</p>
        <p>Lois T. Bronz, the vice chairwoman of the Board of Legislators, said it is likely that the new contract will be submitted to lawmakers by the next meeting in mid-September.</p>
        <p>''I think that there is a likelihood of passing this,'' Ms. Bronz said last week. ''I think that there is a sense among legislators that it is time we reached a contract. It's been a long time, and there have been morale problems and the legislators feel we can move ahead.''</p>
        <p>With the settlement with the correction officers at hand, the county now has agreements with six of its seven municipal unions, representing more than 5,000 employees. Establishing a new agreement with the Superior Officers Association, a bargaining unit that represents 123 supervisors at the County Jail, will now take precedence, officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
