<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amy Feind, Todd Randolph</title>
    <meta content="27FEIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEIND, PATRICIA AMY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RANDOLPH, BREWSTER TODD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0DD1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amy Feind, Todd Randolph</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patricia Amy Feind and Brewster Todd Randolph were married yesterday by the Rev. Francis Geer at St. Philip's Episcopal Church in the Highlands in Garrison, N.Y. Msgr. Carl D. Hinrichsen took part in the service.</p>
        <p>The couple, both 37, work in Boston, where the bride, who is known as Amy, is a strategy and electronic commerce consultant with the college division of the Houghton Mifflin Company, the publisher. The bridegroom, who is known as Todd, is a vice president and account director at Krom Interactive Communications, an Internet marketing and technology firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patricia Amy Feind and Brewster Todd Randolph were married yesterday by the Rev. Francis Geer at St. Philip's Episcopal Church in the Highlands in Garrison, N.Y. Msgr. Carl D. Hinrichsen took part in the service.</p>
        <p>The couple, both 37, work in Boston, where the bride, who is known as Amy, is a strategy and electronic commerce consultant with the college division of the Houghton Mifflin Company, the publisher. The bridegroom, who is known as Todd, is a vice president and account director at Krom Interactive Communications, an Internet marketing and technology firm.</p>
        <p>The bride, who will continue to use her name professionally, graduated cum laude from Wellesley College and received an M.B.A. from Dartmouth. She is a daughter of Marguerite Feind of Basking Ridge, N.J., and the late Frederic L. Feind Jr., who was vice president in charge of operations for the Bamberger's division of Macy's.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom received bachelor's and master's degrees in English literature from the University of Virginia at Charlottesville. He also holds an M.B.A. from Columbia. His mother, Jane Freeland Williams of Burlington, Vt., is the executive director of the Vermont Commission on National and Community Service, a state agency in Montpelier. His father, James K. Randolph of Roanoke, Va., works there as a real estate finance and acquisitions consultant.</p>
        <p>In January of last year, there was a party for the Community Consulting Team, a volunteer organization that puts M.B.A.'s to work pro bono for nonprofit organizations in the Boston area. Ms. Feind had once been a board member of the group and still had friends in the organization. One of those friends, the woman who organized the party, told Ms. Feind she should show up, because there would be a couple of ''cute single men'' there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Randolph, who was single at the time, allows that he was not one of the men the hostess had in mind.</p>
        <p>''But I moved faster,'' he said.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
