<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Mahopac and Mahopac Falls; Former Resort Is Still Taking Life Easy</title>
    <meta content="27LIVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mahopac (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prevost, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Putnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DB1F3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Mahopac and Mahopac Falls; Former Resort Is Still Taking Life Easy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA PREVOST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prevost, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Mahopac and Mahopac Falls, NY, as place to live; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first thing newcomers should know about Mahopac and Mahopac Falls, two lake-studded hamlets in the town of Carmel in Putnam County, is how to pronounce their names. The most popular pronunciation of Mahopac rejects the word's Algonquin roots in favor of MAY-o-pac. But the natives beg to differ.</p>
        <p>''It's really always been Ma-HOE-pac,'' said the Carmel town historian, Allan Warnecke, who grew up in Mahopac Falls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first thing newcomers should know about Mahopac and Mahopac Falls, two lake-studded hamlets in the town of Carmel in Putnam County, is how to pronounce their names. The most popular pronunciation of Mahopac rejects the word's Algonquin roots in favor of MAY-o-pac. But the natives beg to differ.</p>
        <p>''It's really always been Ma-HOE-pac,'' said the Carmel town historian, Allan Warnecke, who grew up in Mahopac Falls.</p>
        <p>The precise meaning of Mahopac is more tricky to decipher. Big Peaceful Water, Big Pond and Snake Lake are among the various translations of a word that almost certainly refers to the 593-acre body of water that distinguishes the hamlets: Lake Mahopac. The land around the lake is all privately owned and dense with houses, save for a small wooded area the town hopes to convert into a public park. But for nearly 100 years Lake Mahopac shone as the centerpiece of a grand summer resort for overheated New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Elegantly outfitted vacationers took in the lake breezes from the verandas of sprawling hotels. They came by rail, arriving at the station in nearby Croton Falls and taking stagecoaches to the lake, until a station went up in Mahopac in the 1870's.</p>
        <p>But by the 1950's New Yorkers no longer relied on rail for vacation travel and the fading hotels of Mahopac gradually lost  appeal. Over time, all the hotels burned or were torn down, and Mahopac evolved into the year-round community it is today.</p>
        <p>Still, the hamlets' location within the Croton Falls Reservoir watershed has enabled them to retain the relaxed feel of a community far removed from the fast pace of metro-area living. Development throughout Mahopac is strictly regulated. So, aside from a new Kmart, big-box retail stores as well as glitzy office parks are conspicuously absent. The main road, Route 6, is still only two lanes wide. And Mahopac center, with its independently owned pharmacy and prominently placed Launderaid, looks much the same as it did 40 years ago. The boundaries of Mahopac and Mahopac Falls are not precisely defined, Putnam officials say, but are larger than the census designation.</p>
        <p>Town officials say the area needs more commercial development -- a hotel, perhaps, or a department store. But for the most part people like it the way it is, said Michael Catalano, the sales manager at Prudential World Homes Realty in Carmel. ''There's a mentality here against chain development,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Much like the New Yorkers who moved to Mahopac in the 70's and 80's, the many families moving in these days from bordering Westchester County are looking for lower housing prices and a quieter way of life. ''Here they can get the new center-hall colonial they want on more land for half the price,'' Mr. Catalano said.</p>
        <p>Take Ray Lawrence, 39, and his wife, Pam, 35, who in May moved to Mahopac from Bedford in Westchester where they rented and where they searched vainly for a year for an affordable house to renovate. ''It was so bad that if somebody dropped a pack of cigarettes on the ground, somebody was renovating it within minutes,'' said Mr. Lawrence, who sells commercial office furniture in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In Mahopac, however, the couple found a new 4,500-square-foot colonial about a third of a mile from the lake priced about $200,000 less than similar properties just over the county line. ''I couldn't even think of buying this property anywhere else,'' Mr. Lawrence said. ''I was already riding the train for 55 minutes. For an extra 10 minutes on my commute, I can live right off the lake and go bass fishing at night after work.''</p>
        <p>PRICES are rising quickly, however. According to Mr. Catalano, just last year buyers could still find a new house in one of Mahopac's small subdivisions in the mid-$300,000 range. But demand has since pushed starting prices for some new construction above $400,000. And with the town looking to restrict future residential development, prices are likely to continue to climb.</p>
        <p>According to Frank J. Del Campo, Carmel's town supervisor, residential growth is straining the town's roads, schools and water supply. The Town Council is planning a six-month moratorium on residential development, beginning next month, while it amends the zoning code. A proposal to increase the minimum lot size to three acres has come under fire for its potential to put Mahopac (as well as other parts of Carmel) out of the reach of low- to middle-income homebuyers. But Mr. Del Campo points out that the prices of new houses are already high and that plenty of existing homes are still in the $200,000 to $300,000 range.</p>
        <p>''No one wants to stop someone from coming,'' he said, ''but at some point you have a certain obligation as an elected official to look at the total good and the quality of life.''</p>
        <p>Some of the highest prices in Mahopac are found on the north shore of the lake. Mansions, both historic and new, many with private tennis courts, can be glimpsed through the trees along North Lake Boulevard. One, a 3,000-square-foot stone carriage house, was recently listed at $990,000. Adding to the boulevard's prestige is the Mahopac Country Club, a 102-year-old private golf club.</p>
        <p>On the lake's east shore, the boulevard divides more modest homes from their lake frontage. Owners carefully stake out lakefront parcels with fences and trees. Many  parcels have docks, as motorboating is permitted on the lake. Slip rentals and mooring services are also available through MacDonald Marine and Mahopac Marina.</p>
        <p>The homes surrounding Mahopac's other lakes, including Secor, MacGregor and Casse, tend to be smaller and older. A four-bedroom ranch on Lake Casse was recently listed at $229,000.</p>
        <p>Children in both hamlets attend school in the Mahopac Central district. The 4,900-student district is struggling to keep up with population growth, which has lately averaged about 4 percent a year, according to the superintendent, Joseph P. Sabatella. Last year voters approved a $28.7 million bond issue to build additional classroom space at the high school, middle school and two of the district's three elementary schools.</p>
        <p>All kindergarten students attend a specially designed early childhood learning center. At the Austin Road, Fulmar Road and Lakeview elementary schools, early intervention programs provide extra help to lagging readers before they fall too far behind. Mahopac Middle School also helps  underachievers by using a team teaching approach. About five teachers in different subjects are grouped into a team that has 100 to 150 students.</p>
        <p>''The research is now saying that in order to make schools more effective, you need to take larger schools and break them down into smaller units,'' Dr. Sabatella said.</p>
        <p>The computer curriculum begins in kindergarten and continues through high school. Some science teachers at the high school even answer students' questions and help with homework assignments over the Internet in the evening. ''A lot students like to get online and converse with the teacher  between 9 and 11 p.m.,'' Dr. Sabatella said. ''And they help each other.''</p>
        <p>MAHOPAC HIGH SCHOOL offers 13 advanced placement courses as well as several college-credit courses linked to Syracuse University and local colleges. Ninety-three percent of this year's 341 graduates planned to go on to college. SAT scores this year were 530 for both the verbal and math parts of the test.</p>
        <p>Youth sports teams are organized by the Carmel Parks and Recreation Department through the Mahopac Sports Association. The department recently opened an inline skating rink in Mahopac.</p>
        <p>Mahopac lacks a public swimming pool, but residents may swim at Long Pond beach at Sycamore Park, a 32-acre recreation area equipped with tennis courts, ball fields and playgrounds. Seasonal park passes for Mahopac residents are $4 a person. The Country Club at Lake MacGregor also welcomes children to its semiprivate 18-hole golf course. Club dues range from $1,750 to $3,000; children's memberships are $350. Nonmembers pay greens fees of $35 to $65.</p>
        <p>The Putnam Arts Council offers a variety of classes for both children and adults at the Belle Levine Art Center in Mahopac. In addition to two art galleries, the center has  a pottery studio and darkroom.</p>
        <p>A wide variety of local restaurants serve everything from deli food to contemporary American cuisine. Among the options are Flannagan's Tavern on Lake Mahopac, a favorite spot for a lakeside drink; Arturo's, an Italian restaurant known for its large portions; and Downey's, where boaters can dock long enough to dine on steaks and seafood.</p>
        <p>Residents don't even have to travel outside the town to see a movie since the recent opening of an eight-screen theater in Carmel. The original proposal called for almost twice as many screens, Mr. Catalano said, but the community couldn't stomach a project that large. ''That's just the way it is around here,'' he said with a chuckle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
