<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garages Make Supersized S.U.V.'s Even Bigger for Superrich M.V.P.'s</title>
    <meta content="27AUTO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siano, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDB1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garages Make Supersized S.U.V.'s Even Bigger for Superrich M.V.P.'s</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH SIANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siano, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New class of aftermarket super sports utility vehicles, some with as much as 485 horsepower, finds eager buyers among professional athletes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF luxury can be defined as lavishness beyond any pretense of necessity, what could be more of a luxury vehicle than a sport utility with the horsepower of a sports car but the handling of, well, a truck? But does the planet really need supercharged S.U.V.'s with as much as 485 horsepower?</p>
        <p>A new class of aftermarket super sport utilities -- with entries from such tuners as Roush Performance, Lingenfelter and Beverly Hills Motoring -- has found many eager buyers among professional athletes who can afford to burn money the way these muscle-bound trucks burn gasoline. Those who cannot hit .350 against Major League pitching or average 30 points a night in the National Basketball Association may wonder what they are missing. Recent test drives provided some answers, as well as a look at a more affordable alternative.</p>
        <p>Roush Expedition</p>
        <p>Jack Roush, who runs a multicar Nascar Winston Cup team, specializes in aftermarket enhancements for Ford production vehicles. Roush Performance, based in Livonia, Mich., sells juiced-up versions of the Mustang, Cougar, F-150 pickup and Expedition through selected Ford dealerships.</p>
        <p>The Roush Expedition announces itself to the world with Roush decals across the top of the front and rear windows, in case the five-spoke Argent aluminum alloy wheels leave any doubts. Other exterior touches include a chrome tip on the end of the high-performance exhaust system and a front bumper cover with integrated fog lamps.</p>
        <p>Inside, there is a wood steering wheel and walnut dash and door trim, with what Roush advertises as machined metal pedals. A closer look reveals that the pedals are metal plates screwed onto the regular rubber throttle and brake pedals. The dash and door trim, with wood grain that tries too hard to look authentic, has a similar tacked-on look.</p>
        <p>The small video screens in the back of each front-seat headrest are a much neater installation. The screens, linked to a VCR under one of the rear seats, produced a muddy image when a videotape of a black-and-white movie was played, but the color images were better. Although the system can also pick up broadcast TV signals, it is hit and miss. Passengers can also listen on headsets, the preferred mode given the exhaust noise in the rear seat. There are 10 cup holders -- 2 large enough for the biggest cup that 7-Eleven can throw at you.</p>
        <p>Fire up the engine, and the whine of the Paxton supercharger is immediately noticeable. It produces eight pounds of boost, which all seem to jump in at once with anything but the lightest prod of the pedal. As a result, the Expedition keeps kicking down into a lower gear in the four-speed automatic, a jolting phenomenon. Those who thrive on speed won't mind -- especially while they're passing most cars on the highway. But the Roush Expedition driver had better get far enough ahead before the next corner comes up.</p>
        <p>On two-wheel-drive models, Roush has lowered the car two inches and added a rear sway bar, new coil springs and Bilstein shocks and a modified air suspension at the rear (optional). But the suspension needs to be a good deal more taut; there's still an unsettling amount of body roll. The brakes, however, provided sure, steady stops.</p>
        <p>Brute force is the Expedition's forte. Three passengers and 160 pounds of peat moss, compost and topsoil couldn't get it to break a sweat. One caution: Time saved in the Roush Expedition is somewhat offset by time spent at the gas pump. I averaged 11 miles per gallon in 500 miles of driving, and I was at the pump so long, I checked to see if the tank was leaking.</p>
        <p>Roush sells the converted Expedition for $46,834. The company said the professional football players Deion Sanders and Nate Newton have been customers.</p>
        <p>Cigarette OnShore</p>
        <p>This souped-up Chevy Suburban is produced in Tuckahoe, N.Y., by A. I. Design, under a licensing agreement with Cigarette boats. The spotless floors of A.I.'s workshop (one couple had no qualms about allowing their toddler to crawl around the place while they discussed a purchase) are a clue to what the vehicle is like.</p>
        <p>Todd Brown, vice president of A. I. Design, said it took 60 man-hours to produce the custom console inside the Cigarette OnShore. A glimpse at the nickel-plated carbon-fiber interior trim (neatly folded into the cabin treatment, unlike the Roush wood trim), and you can believe numbers like that. Everything about this conversion has a seamless, factory-quality look to it, including the custom leather seats. The screen of the Alpine navigation system slides away into the dash when not in use, and is linked to a camera in the rear bumper that activates when the OnShore is in reverse. (The camera image is reversed to give the driver a true left-to-right image.)</p>
        <p>As with the Roush Expedition, the rear-seat passengers have two video screens to entertain them. In this case, they are connected to an Alpine DVD player and Sega Dreamcast game player -- the latter with wireless Internet access. The two screens can be operated independently.</p>
        <p>A Whipple supercharger brings the horsepower up to about 485, Mr. Brown says, along with a Gale Banks Engineering exhaust system. Larger sway bars and firmer bushings at the front and rear are the main suspension enhancements.</p>
        <p>In a short test drive, the OnShore demonstrated poised and refined behavior. Its 7.5 pounds of boost came in smoothly, bringing the vehicle up to speed rapidly. Mr. Brown estimates a 14-second quarter mile. The suspension is much more taut than that in the Roush Expedition, allowing the OnShore to maintain a greater degree of equilibrium. (Just don't enter any slaloms with it.) Of the three trucks tested, the OnShore had the best ride quality.</p>
        <p>The upgraded brakes include Brembo cross-drilled rotors and calipers. The system worked well at stopping something that combines this much mass and velocity, but the pedal feel was relatively numb.</p>
        <p>The OnShore beats the Roush Expedition in all areas -- exactly what it should do, of course, since it costs almost four times as much as a full Roush conversion: $185,000 (or $155,000 for the Crew Cab Dualie) fully equipped. Too steep? There's an entry-level version for $135,000 with less-snazzy electronics and Brembo brakes only at the front. If you need any more incentive, the OnShore comes with a 3-year, 36,000-mile warranty. Only 200 are going to be built.</p>
        <p>Ford SVT F-150 Lightning</p>
        <p>This 360-horsepower pickup was developed by Ford's in-house Special Vehicle Team, which also created the SVT Mustang Cobra and SVT Contour. The main exterior enhancements, beside the Lightning badges on each flank, are a front bumper cover with integrated driving lights and twin ceramic-coated three-inch exhaust tips that both exit on the right side, just behind the cab.</p>
        <p>Inside, the touches are understated enough that your gun rack wouldn't be out of place. The seating is a combination bench-style, with the driver and outside passenger getting extra lateral bolsters on the seatback and bottom. Trim is a combination of cloth and leather. The basic comforts are there: power mirrors, six-way power driver's seat, a CD player, air-conditioning, automatic transmission and cruise control.</p>
        <p>What the SVT Lightning offers is performance at a reasonable price ($31,400, with destination and delivery charges included).</p>
        <p>An Eaton supercharger provides eight pounds of boost that arrive steadily and forcefully with some firm prodding on the gas pedal. Ford says the truck can cover a quarter mile in 14.6 seconds, and that number may improve with the 2001 model, which is scheduled for a slight horsepower increase. It is due out around the first of the year.</p>
        <p>Although the Lightning will never be mistaken for a sports car, its lighter weight and shorter wheelbase compared with the Roush and Cigarette make it the choice for someone seeking an enhanced truck that is fun to drive, once you get comfortable with it. In a week of mixed driving, the Lightning got 15 miles to a gallon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF luxury can be defined as lavishness beyond any pretense of necessity, what could be more of a luxury vehicle than a sport utility with the horsepower of a sports car but the handling of, well, a truck? But does the planet really need supercharged S.U.V.'s with as much as 485 horsepower?</p>
        <p>A new class of aftermarket super sport utilities -- with entries from such tuners as Roush Performance, Lingenfelter and Beverly Hills Motoring -- has found many eager buyers among professional athletes who can afford to burn money the way these muscle-bound trucks burn gasoline. Those who cannot hit .350 against Major League pitching or average 30 points a night in the National Basketball Association may wonder what they are missing. Recent test drives provided some answers, as well as a look at a more affordable alternative.</p>
        <p>Roush Expedition</p>
        <p>Jack Roush, who runs a multicar Nascar Winston Cup team, specializes in aftermarket enhancements for Ford production vehicles. Roush Performance, based in Livonia, Mich., sells juiced-up versions of the Mustang, Cougar, F-150 pickup and Expedition through selected Ford dealerships.</p>
        <p>The Roush Expedition announces itself to the world with Roush decals across the top of the front and rear windows, in case the five-spoke Argent aluminum alloy wheels leave any doubts. Other exterior touches include a chrome tip on the end of the high-performance exhaust system and a front bumper cover with integrated fog lamps.</p>
        <p>Inside, there is a wood steering wheel and walnut dash and door trim, with what Roush advertises as machined metal pedals. A closer look reveals that the pedals are metal plates screwed onto the regular rubber throttle and brake pedals. The dash and door trim, with wood grain that tries too hard to look authentic, has a similar tacked-on look.</p>
        <p>The small video screens in the back of each front-seat headrest are a much neater installation. The screens, linked to a VCR under one of the rear seats, produced a muddy image when a videotape of a black-and-white movie was played, but the color images were better. Although the system can also pick up broadcast TV signals, it is hit and miss. Passengers can also listen on headsets, the preferred mode given the exhaust noise in the rear seat. There are 10 cup holders -- 2 large enough for the biggest cup that 7-Eleven can throw at you.</p>
        <p>Fire up the engine, and the whine of the Paxton supercharger is immediately noticeable. It produces eight pounds of boost, which all seem to jump in at once with anything but the lightest prod of the pedal. As a result, the Expedition keeps kicking down into a lower gear in the four-speed automatic, a jolting phenomenon. Those who thrive on speed won't mind -- especially while they're passing most cars on the highway. But the Roush Expedition driver had better get far enough ahead before the next corner comes up.</p>
        <p>On two-wheel-drive models, Roush has lowered the car two inches and added a rear sway bar, new coil springs and Bilstein shocks and a modified air suspension at the rear (optional). But the suspension needs to be a good deal more taut; there's still an unsettling amount of body roll. The brakes, however, provided sure, steady stops.</p>
        <p>Brute force is the Expedition's forte. Three passengers and 160 pounds of peat moss, compost and topsoil couldn't get it to break a sweat. One caution: Time saved in the Roush Expedition is somewhat offset by time spent at the gas pump. I averaged 11 miles per gallon in 500 miles of driving, and I was at the pump so long, I checked to see if the tank was leaking.</p>
        <p>Roush sells the converted Expedition for $46,834. The company said the professional football players Deion Sanders and Nate Newton have been customers.</p>
        <p>Cigarette OnShore</p>
        <p>This souped-up Chevy Suburban is produced in Tuckahoe, N.Y., by A. I. Design, under a licensing agreement with Cigarette boats. The spotless floors of A.I.'s workshop (one couple had no qualms about allowing their toddler to crawl around the place while they discussed a purchase) are a clue to what the vehicle is like.</p>
        <p>Todd Brown, vice president of A. I. Design, said it took 60 man-hours to produce the custom console inside the Cigarette OnShore. A glimpse at the nickel-plated carbon-fiber interior trim (neatly folded into the cabin treatment, unlike the Roush wood trim), and you can believe numbers like that. Everything about this conversion has a seamless, factory-quality look to it, including the custom leather seats. The screen of the Alpine navigation system slides away into the dash when not in use, and is linked to a camera in the rear bumper that activates when the OnShore is in reverse. (The camera image is reversed to give the driver a true left-to-right image.)</p>
        <p>As with the Roush Expedition, the rear-seat passengers have two video screens to entertain them. In this case, they are connected to an Alpine DVD player and Sega Dreamcast game player -- the latter with wireless Internet access. The two screens can be operated independently.</p>
        <p>A Whipple supercharger brings the horsepower up to about 485, Mr. Brown says, along with a Gale Banks Engineering exhaust system. Larger sway bars and firmer bushings at the front and rear are the main suspension enhancements.</p>
        <p>In a short test drive, the OnShore demonstrated poised and refined behavior. Its 7.5 pounds of boost came in smoothly, bringing the vehicle up to speed rapidly. Mr. Brown estimates a 14-second quarter mile. The suspension is much more taut than that in the Roush Expedition, allowing the OnShore to maintain a greater degree of equilibrium. (Just don't enter any slaloms with it.) Of the three trucks tested, the OnShore had the best ride quality.</p>
        <p>The upgraded brakes include Brembo cross-drilled rotors and calipers. The system worked well at stopping something that combines this much mass and velocity, but the pedal feel was relatively numb.</p>
        <p>The OnShore beats the Roush Expedition in all areas -- exactly what it should do, of course, since it costs almost four times as much as a full Roush conversion: $185,000 (or $155,000 for the Crew Cab Dualie) fully equipped. Too steep? There's an entry-level version for $135,000 with less-snazzy electronics and Brembo brakes only at the front. If you need any more incentive, the OnShore comes with a 3-year, 36,000-mile warranty. Only 200 are going to be built.</p>
        <p>Ford SVT F-150 Lightning</p>
        <p>This 360-horsepower pickup was developed by Ford's in-house Special Vehicle Team, which also created the SVT Mustang Cobra and SVT Contour. The main exterior enhancements, beside the Lightning badges on each flank, are a front bumper cover with integrated driving lights and twin ceramic-coated three-inch exhaust tips that both exit on the right side, just behind the cab.</p>
        <p>Inside, the touches are understated enough that your gun rack wouldn't be out of place. The seating is a combination bench-style, with the driver and outside passenger getting extra lateral bolsters on the seatback and bottom. Trim is a combination of cloth and leather. The basic comforts are there: power mirrors, six-way power driver's seat, a CD player, air-conditioning, automatic transmission and cruise control.</p>
        <p>What the SVT Lightning offers is performance at a reasonable price ($31,400, with destination and delivery charges included).</p>
        <p>An Eaton supercharger provides eight pounds of boost that arrive steadily and forcefully with some firm prodding on the gas pedal. Ford says the truck can cover a quarter mile in 14.6 seconds, and that number may improve with the 2001 model, which is scheduled for a slight horsepower increase. It is due out around the first of the year.</p>
        <p>Although the Lightning will never be mistaken for a sports car, its lighter weight and shorter wheelbase compared with the Roush and Cigarette make it the choice for someone seeking an enhanced truck that is fun to drive, once you get comfortable with it. In a week of mixed driving, the Lightning got 15 miles to a gallon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
