<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Putting The Best Through Qualifying</title>
    <meta content="Y27TIG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicklaus, Jack</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD81331F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Putting The Best Through Qualifying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column discusses successful career of golfer Jack Nicklaus and his positive impact on sport (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN one great figure in sports more or less sanctifies the  supposed heir apparent that  immediately follows in his or her sneakers or cleats, it has become known as passing the baton. But what we hear is not always what is truly meant, deep down.</p>
        <p>Last week, after Jack Nicklaus finished playing the first two rounds of the Professional Golfers' Association tournament with Tiger Woods, he paid Woods a gracious and lavish compliment. It reminded this reporter of the line of praise bestowed by Bobby Jones -- a golfing icon if ever there was one -- after Nicklaus had won his third Masters, at 26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN one great figure in sports more or less sanctifies the  supposed heir apparent that  immediately follows in his or her sneakers or cleats, it has become known as passing the baton. But what we hear is not always what is truly meant, deep down.</p>
        <p>Last week, after Jack Nicklaus finished playing the first two rounds of the Professional Golfers' Association tournament with Tiger Woods, he paid Woods a gracious and lavish compliment. It reminded this reporter of the line of praise bestowed by Bobby Jones -- a golfing icon if ever there was one -- after Nicklaus had won his third Masters, at 26.</p>
        <p>''Young man,'' Jones said, ''you play a game that I am totally unfamiliar with.'' A few years later, I had an opportunity to speak with Jones -- the model of what was often considered a Southern gentleman -- and asked him about that  moment. ''Well,'' Jones said, in his easy drawl, ''I laid on a compliment. You know how you do those things.''</p>
        <p>The implication was clear. Jones, then the only man to have won the Grand Slam of Golf, in 1930, was not about to to give Nicklaus a perch above him in the pitch-and-putt pantheon.</p>
        <p>If there has ever been a finer champion than Nicklaus, both on or off the course, he doesn't come readily to mind, though Woods is certainly a splendid candidate.</p>
        <p>What Nicklaus said, after having played with Woods last week, was: ''What Tiger is doing right now, I think he is a better player than I ever was.'' But ''right now'' is an interesting phrase. Tiger, who has won 5 major titles at 24, is ahead of Nicklaus's 3 major victories at a comparable age. But Nicklaus added 15 more majors in his career. Nicklaus might well have been saying, ''Let's not jump the gun. Let's just wait and see.''</p>
        <p>And recall what the Golden Bear added about the advancement in equipment: ''I'm not sure you can do that'' -- Woods's use of clubs -- ''with the golf ball we used to play with because it had so much spin on it. Today you can tailor a golf ball to your game more than you could then.''</p>
        <p>What makes a champion is the feeling that when he goes to compete, he can't lose. This feeling lasts for a long time, like forever. Recall the conversation Muhammad Ali had with Joe Louis. Ali said that he in his prime could have beaten Louis in his prime. Louis said to him, ''You know I had a Bum-of-the-Month club.'' Ali said, ''I know.'' And Louis said, ''You'da been one of the bums.''</p>
        <p>To many, the best all-around basketball player ever was Oscar Robertson. Until Michael Jordan came along. To some, Robertson remains the best. Several years ago I asked Robertson -- who averaged nearly a triple-double for 10 straight years -- his opinion. ''Jordan's a great player,'' Robertson said, ''but we had fewer teams, and the talent wasn't as diluted. So I think Jordan would have scored about 20 points a game.''</p>
        <p>''Twenty a game?'' I said. ''But you scored 30 a game in that era.''</p>
        <p>''Well,'' Robertson said with a shrug, ''I handled the ball more than he does.''</p>
        <p>Damon Runyon once described Red Grange, the spectacular running back of the 1920's, this way: ''He is three or four men and a horse rolled into one. He is Jack Dempsey, Babe Ruth, Al Jolson, Paavo Nurmi and Man o' War.'' Grange told me several years ago that ''Gale Sayers and O. J. Simpson are the greatest running backs I've seen in football in the last 10 years.'' That took care of 10 years, and left the rest of the century -- which told me something about Grange's competitiveness. ''And over all?'' I asked. ''They're bigger today,'' Grange said, ''not better.''</p>
        <p>The wonderful Shirley Povich, who for more than half a century wrote a sports column for The Washington Post, told me about the time he took Walter Johnson, who was as famous for his modesty as he was for being the fastest pitcher of his time, to a baseball game to watch the new fireballing sensation Bob Feller.</p>
        <p>All around them, fans were whistling and exclaiming. Shirley said that Walter seemed equally impressed.</p>
        <p>''I asked a question which had long concerned me,'' Shirley said. ''I turned to Walter and asked, 'Is he as fast as you were, Walter?' ''</p>
        <p>''No,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Casey Stengel, too, was impressed with the modern player, but not to the extent that they were better than the older guys. Shortly before Stengel died, in 1975, I asked him to compare the two greatest home-run hitters in history.</p>
        <p>''Now this fellow in Atlanta is  amazin','' Casey said. ''He hits the ball the best for a man his size. But I can't say he hits the ball better than Ruth. Ruth could hit the ball so far nobody could field it. And that's even with the medicinal improvements today.</p>
        <p>''They come along now with the  aluminum cup and it improves players who only used to wear a belt and it's better for catching ground balls.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
