<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wide World of Tennis Calls to Yonkers Ace</title>
    <meta content="27TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scharf, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scharf, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markowitz, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DE1731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wide World of Tennis Calls to Yonkers Ace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MARKOWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markowitz, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of young tennis ace Erik Scharf, top player at St John's University in Queens, who still practices with his twin brother, Brian, at Andrus Park in Yonkers, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE tennis courts at Andrus Park here on Central Avenue look a little like the surface of the moon. They are full of craters, and the asphalt has a slope to it. But from 1996 to 1998 they were home to the best high school player in the state, Erik Scharf of Roosevelt High School right down the road.</p>
        <p>Scharf is now the No. 1 player at St. John's University in Queens, but he still practices with his twin brother, Brian, at Andrus Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE tennis courts at Andrus Park here on Central Avenue look a little like the surface of the moon. They are full of craters, and the asphalt has a slope to it. But from 1996 to 1998 they were home to the best high school player in the state, Erik Scharf of Roosevelt High School right down the road.</p>
        <p>Scharf is now the No. 1 player at St. John's University in Queens, but he still practices with his twin brother, Brian, at Andrus Park.</p>
        <p>Last year, he continued his dominance at the Division I college level, registering a 33-3 record and earning the No. 2 ranking in the Eastern Conference. This enabled him to play, for the first time, in the N.C.A.A. National Championships in Athens, Ga., where he lost in the first round to the No. 1 seed, Jeff Morrison of the University of Florida.</p>
        <p>Scharf, 21, has spent this summer playing in lower-level professional events in Armonk, Binghamton and the Bronx, and at an event on Long Island, the Hamlet Cup, on the highest professional level.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago at the qualifying tournament for the GHI Challenger in Crotona Park in the Bronx, Scharf lost to Matt Breen, an Australian pro ranked in the 200's internationally.</p>
        <p>''I was up 2-love in the second set and 40-5 on my serve, but couldn't win the game,'' said Scharf, who lost the match 6-2, 6-2. ''But I haven't played against a lot of strong players like him.''</p>
        <p>That's because there are no other players of his ability in Westchester now. Just as Scharf has shown an allegiance to the courts at Andrus Park, he has shown a similar devotion to his home county. His mother, Ase, said that as an adolescent Scharf never wanted to leave the county and his tennis clinics at Concordia College in neighboring Bronxville to travel with the family to Norway, her homeland.</p>
        <p>Scharf, who commutes to St. John's, never attended a Florida tennis academy, and unlike many college players of his stature, he has never traveled outside New York State to play pro tournaments in the summer.</p>
        <p>Last year, he practiced with Rob Givone of Katonah, but Givone retired as a pro player late last year, and Scharf said Givone is no longer available for practice sessions.</p>
        <p>''It's not how much you practice,'' said Scharf, who plays at least two hours a day six days a week in addition to running both long distance and sprints and jumping rope. ''It's who you practice with.''</p>
        <p>Right now, Brian, his brother, is Scharf's daily practice partner. Brian, who plays either the No. 3, 4 or 5 singles position at St. John's, ''helps me out a lot,'' Scharf said.</p>
        <p>''It's important to have someone to go out with every day who's on my level,'' the 6-foot-1, 165-pound Erik said. ''We're brothers, but we're both very competitive. We motivate each other, and it gives us a lot of confidence that we're both playing on the same team.''</p>
        <p>Next year, Scharf will need a new practice partner, though, as he plans to set out on a pro career that will surely take him far outside Westchester. Except for the Challengers in Armonk, Binghamton and the Bronx, New York is not the host of any lower-level professional tournaments.</p>
        <p>Scharf will have to play plenty of these tournaments before he can fulfill his dream of one day playing in the U.S. Open, which will begin tomorrow in Flushing Meadow, just down the road from the St. John's campus.</p>
        <p>''Rob Givone told me that the more exposure you get in those tournaments the better,'' Scharf said. ''You really need to see what it's like out there before you can know how far you can go.''</p>
        <p>Givone said he thinks Scharf can be a very solid pro. ''He fights for every point,'' he said. ''If he keeps that same attitude during the down times, he'll develop weapons and get the experience he needs to be a solid pro.''</p>
        <p>Scharf does not foresee being a flash in the pan.</p>
        <p>''I know I might have to play the Satellite and Challenger tournaments for three or four years before I can play on the A.T.P. Tour,'' he said, referring to the Association of Tennis Professionals. ''If you don't give yourself that long, you don't know if you can make it or not.''</p>
        <p>Satellite tournaments are the lowest level in professional tennis, Challenger is the next level up and Association of Tennis Professionals is the top level.</p>
        <p>Givone, who had a world ranking in 1995 of No. 347, played on the pro tour for five years before retiring. Phil Williamson of Mount Vernon, whose top ranking was No. 297 in 1992, had a longer pro career, and Larry Davidson of New Rochelle, who had a ranking of No. 284 in 1979, played on the pro tour for a shorter period than Givone.</p>
        <p>Scharf says he hopes to surpass them all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
