<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Personality</title>
    <meta content="27GAILEYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gailey, Phil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenstein, Fred I</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Presidential Difference, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1D9153EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Personality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phil Gailey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gailey, Phil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phil Gailey reviews book The Presidential Difference: Leadership Style From FDR to Clinton by Fred I Greenstein (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE PRESIDENTIAL DIFFERENCE</p>
        <p>Leadership Style</p>
        <p>From FDR to Clinton.</p>
        <p>By Fred I. Greenstein.</p>
        <p>282 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Martin Kessler Books/</p>
        <p>The Free Press. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE PRESIDENTIAL DIFFERENCE</p>
        <p>Leadership Style</p>
        <p>From FDR to Clinton.</p>
        <p>By Fred I. Greenstein.</p>
        <p>282 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Martin Kessler Books/</p>
        <p>The Free Press. $25.</p>
        <p>The modern presidency, perhaps more than any other institution, magnifies the personal strengths and weaknesses of the office's occupant. Some human imperfections are more disabling than others, and in a president they can have major consequences. Consider Bill Clinton, whose recklessness plunged him into a scandal that depleted much of the White House's moral authority, or Richard Nixon, whose insecurities and emotional dark side helped bring down his presidency.</p>
        <p>In ''The Presidential Difference: Leadership Style From FDR to Clinton,'' Fred I. Greenstein, a professor of politics at Princeton, offers new insights into the successes and failures of 11 American presidents. His work provides a useful yardstick for considering this year's two presidential contenders, George W. Bush and Al Gore, an unsatisfying choice for many voters who are troubled by Bush's lack of gravitas and Gore's lack of candor. There are some surprises in his assessments that are at odds with popular perceptions of the nation's chief executives, and even serious students of presidential history may find parts of Greenstein's work illuminating.</p>
        <p>Greenstein rates modern presidents on six qualities that bear on their effectiveness as leaders: communication, organization, political skill, vision, cognitive style and emotional intelligence. No single president scores high on all of these attributes, but our most successful chief executives have possessed the right combination of the ones that matter most.</p>
        <p>Greenstein believes that the key presidential quality is emotional intelligence, which he defines as ''the president's ability to manage his emotions and turn them to constructive purposes, rather than being dominated by them and allowing them to diminish his leadership.''</p>
        <p>Greenstein says that only three of the 11 presidents he studied ''stand out as fundamentally free of distracting emotional perturbations'' -- Eisenhower, Ford and Bush, none of whom was considered a particularly strong president, although each had virtues that Greenstein maintains are not fully recognized or appreciated. Four others -- Roosevelt, Truman, Kennedy and Reagan -- were marked by emotional undercurrents that did not significantly impair their leadership.'' These four presidents -- except for Truman, all great communicators -- would make most people's lists of the 20th century's dominant chief executives, even though Kennedy's brief presidency was defined more by style than by lasting achievements.</p>
        <p>It's no surprise that Greenstein finds Johnson, Carter, Nixon and Clinton to have been the most emotionally handicapped presidents of the lot. ''Clinton's foibles made him an underachiever and national embarrassment,'' he writes. ''Carter's defective temperament contributed to making his time in office a period of lost opportunity. Johnson and Nixon presided over major policy breakthroughs, but also over two of the most unhappy episodes of the 20th century,'' Vietnam and Watergate.</p>
        <p>Franklin Delano Roosevelt, according to Greenstein, presents the most complex balance sheet of presidential strengths and weaknesses. While F.D.R. was a towering figure who defined the modern presidency, a superb communicator and an inspiring leader, Greenstein contends that his ''chaotic organizational methods,'' his lack of vision and his intuitive approach to decision making were major defects. F.D.R worshipers will find that assessment blasphemous. Whatever his flaws, he is revered for pulling the nation through the Great Depression and leading it to victory in World War II.</p>
        <p>Mercifully, Greenstein spares us most of the pyschobabble we have come to expect from authors probing the emotional makeup of our presidents. Instead, he provides us with a perceptive view of the leadership qualities and the events that shaped the triumphs and tragedies of the modern presidency. At the very least, it makes for a challenging parlor quiz.</p>
        <p>Phil Gailey is editorial page editor and vice president of The St. Petersburg Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Phil Gailey is editorial page editor and vice president of The St. Petersburg Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
