<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stumbling Out of the Gate</title>
    <meta content="27BLYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blythe, Will</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bausch, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hole In the Earth, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFD9153EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stumbling Out of the Gate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Will Blythe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blythe, Will</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Will Blythe reviews book A Hole in the Earth by Robert Bausch; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A HOLE IN THE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Robert Bausch.</p>
        <p>358 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A HOLE IN THE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Robert Bausch.</p>
        <p>358 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $24.</p>
        <p>SOME novels are like quietly amiable guests at a party. Neither glamorous nor provocative nor loud nor funny, they wouldn't, at first glance, seem capable of carving out much visibility for themselves, and yet by the end of the evening their self-possession and ease have made intimates of everyone. Robert Bausch's fourth novel, ''A Hole in the Earth,'' is such a book. While it won't win any prizes for stylistic innovation, it is a splendid novel, original in the best sense -- establishing characters so fresh yet familiar that they might be helping themselves to what's in your refrigerator even as you read about them.</p>
        <p>The protagonist, Henry Porter, is the sole screw-up in a family of successes. At 39, he has already failed at marriage, fatherhood and the real estate business. Although not misogynistic, Henry is bewildered by the female sex. ''No matter what you do, you can't win where women are concerned,'' he declares. Now he's a middle-school teacher living alone in a Virginia suburb of Washington, and all he really wants to do is spend his summer vacation betting on the horses at local tracks.</p>
        <p>He remains frozen in a kind of late-stage adolescence (a much-derided state of which we American guys are rumored to be masters). He craves the approval of his stern Roman Catholic father, who has achieved renown as a war hero and federal judge. For Henry, his dad's stature is nearly unbearable -- it's as if the son must approach the bench for sentencing any time he's around his father. ''Do your duty,'' his father advises him. And he would -- if he could figure out what that duty was. With its searing portrayal of a character jangled by alternating currents of hate and love for his father, Bausch's novel stalks the same psychic ground as Saul Bellow's ''Seize the Day.''</p>
        <p>Advancing by way of the most mundane of domestic exchanges (''You got any orange juice?''), ''A Hole in the Earth'' is, in fact, a thriller of American dysfunction, generating an agonizing suspense not through gunplay (though there is a bit) but by raising the kind of question that families are always asking about their own: will Henry ever grow up?</p>
        <p>It doesn't look likely. On the very June day his 18-year-old daughter, Nicole -- whom he hasn't seen in almost six years -- shows up unexpectedly from California, Henry makes his apologies and bolts off to the track to play the daily double. ''Mom said I'd hear those very words,'' Nicole tells him, ''not just daily double but I've got to make the daily double before the end of the first day.'' After he spends the afternoon successfully wagering on the horses, Henry takes his girlfriend, Elizabeth, out to a fancy meal, only to discover that she is pregnant with his child.</p>
        <p>No matter where he turns, Henry can find no refuge from the Fates, whom he imagines as a bunch of overweight guys sitting around smoking cigars. Back home, Nicole occupies her old room; her friend Sam, who has accompanied her from California, takes over the master bedroom, leaving poor old dad the couch. Father and daughter squabble constantly about vegetarianism, animal rights and boys while Sam mopes nearby, not so secretly in love with Nicole. God bless this happy home! It's an open and rather comic question as to who exactly is the adult in the house. So much for Henry's blissful solitary summer handicapping the ponies.</p>
        <p>From this point, the humiliations pile up faster than the laundry. In a lather of anxiety, Henry proposes marriage to Elizabeth, backs out, deliberates, proposes again, driving his girlfriend away with his indecision. In what surely must be one of the all-time embarrassing scenes of unrequited love, he eventually corners her in an elevator that gets stuck between floors. An accident ensues: Elizabeth slips through Henry's arms and falls down the shaft to the basement. She ends up in a hospital, comatose, while Henry retreats to a Burger King, where he sips soda and waits to be picked up by his teenage houseguest. More ignominy follows, and then, perhaps, a last, urgent chance at grace.</p>
        <p>Is there anything that lifts ''A Hole in the Earth'' above the rather crowded realm of the male-midlife-crisis novel? Well, for one thing, all the principals, regardless of their age or sex, are suffering through their respective cris de coeur. It's not just the middle-aged white guy who gets to have all the terrifying fun of falling to pieces. For another, Bausch, who is the twin brother of the writer Richard Bausch, displays a rare kindheartedness to his characters -- or, better, let's just say that the tortures he puts them through are not in vain. Written with compassion and insight, ''A Hole in the Earth'' definitely hits the daily double.</p>
        <p>Will Blythe is the literary editor of Men's Journal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Will Blythe is the literary editor of Men's Journal.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
