<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Man With a Knife Is Shot in Leg By the Police</title>
    <meta content="27SHOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Michael (Shooting Victim)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1D81031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Man With a Knife Is Shot in Leg By the Police</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police in Bronx shoot Michael Jones in the leg, allegedly after he brandishes a butcher's knife at another man and two officers; small crowd shouts anti-police remarks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 51-year-old Bronx man was shot by the police early yesterday morning when, the authorities said, he brandished a butcher's knife at another man and two officers.</p>
        <p>The man, Michael Jones, was not seriously injured, but the shooting, in Soundview -- a neighborhood made tense by the police shootings of two unarmed black men since early 1999 -- led to an encounter between the officers and a small crowd that gathered and shouted anti-police remarks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 51-year-old Bronx man was shot by the police early yesterday morning when, the authorities said, he brandished a butcher's knife at another man and two officers.</p>
        <p>The man, Michael Jones, was not seriously injured, but the shooting, in Soundview -- a neighborhood made tense by the police shootings of two unarmed black men since early 1999 -- led to an encounter between the officers and a small crowd that gathered and shouted anti-police remarks.</p>
        <p>The police said the violence began shortly before midnight Friday in a sixth-floor apartment on Lacombe Avenue, where Mr. Jones lives with Denise Evans and her children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones punched Ms. Evans and fractured her nose, the police and residents of the building said. He then ran from the apartment with a large knife, the police said, and was pursued by Ms. Evans's son Leshan Evans, 23, who caught him in a parking lot behind a row of stores on Randall Avenue.</p>
        <p>Two officers on patrol duty in the 43rd Precinct saw the men arguing about 12:30 a.m., the police said, and ordered them to separate. Mr. Jones refused to comply and one of the officers sprayed him with pepper spray as he lunged forward with the knife, the police said.</p>
        <p>''The officers used the spray first, but he did not drop the knife,' said Lt. Stephen W. Biegel, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>The police said Officer Jose D. Casiano, 35, fired twice at Mr. Jones, grazing him once in the right leg.</p>
        <p>The shooting occurred near the area where four plainclothes officers killed Amadou Diallo in a barrage of 41 shots in February 1999, and near the site where a narcotics officer killed Malcolm Ferguson last March.</p>
        <p>As more officers arrived, a small crowd converged on the parking lot and began to heckle the officers, neighbors said.</p>
        <p>Tasha Tillery, 17, who arrived at the parking lot just moments after hearing the two gunshots, said she saw Mr. Jones handcuffed and lying on the ground, asking for an ambulance. She said he had worked for years as a maintenance man at a movie theater and was well liked by his neighbors. The small crowd began to jeer the officers.</p>
        <p>''We were screaming, 'Why are you guys always trying to kill people?' '' she said.</p>
        <p>The police arrested Ms. Tillery  and held her on a charge of disorderly conduct until late yesterday morning, when she was released pending a court appearance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones, who was treated at a local hospital and released, was being held yesterday on charges of attempted assault, menacing and criminal possession of a weapon. The police said they were considering other charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans was charged with disorderly conduct and held on two outstanding warrants.</p>
        <p>As is customary in police shootings, Officer Casiano was reassigned from patrol duties pending an investigation of his use of his weapon, Lieutenant Biegel said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
