<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding A Name To a Lease</title>
    <meta content="27QAQA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DF1E3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding A Name To a Lease</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: I have been living in a rent-stabilized apartment for several years.  For the last two years my girlfriend has been living with me. We are committed to each other but fear marriage. Since we both realize our relationship is for the long term, will it be possible to have my girlfriend's name added to my lease? . . . Jerry Omanoff, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A: ''The letter writer does not have the right to add his girlfriend to the existing lease as an additional tenant,'' said Paul M. Gulielmetti, a Manhattan real estate lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: I have been living in a rent-stabilized apartment for several years.  For the last two years my girlfriend has been living with me. We are committed to each other but fear marriage. Since we both realize our relationship is for the long term, will it be possible to have my girlfriend's name added to my lease? . . . Jerry Omanoff, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A: ''The letter writer does not have the right to add his girlfriend to the existing lease as an additional tenant,'' said Paul M. Gulielmetti, a Manhattan real estate lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulielmetti explained that the Rent Stabilization Code gives a tenant the right to add to the lease only a spouse who is also using the apartment as a primary residence. In fact, he said, if the letter writer declines to renew his current lease in the hope that the landlord will offer a new lease to him and his girlfriend, the landlord could take the position that the new lease is a vacancy lease entitling him to a vacancy increase of as much as 20 percent.</p>
        <p>However, Mr. Gulielmetti said, the letter writer's girlfriend could obtain succession rights to the apartment if she has used the apartment as her primary residence for at least two years before his death provided she qualifies as a ''nontraditional family member'' under the code.</p>
        <p>''In order for the girlfriend to be recognized as a nontraditional family member she would have to demonstrate an emotional and financial commitment and interdependence with Mr. Omanoff,'' Mr. Gulielmetti said, adding that the required residency period would be only one year if the girlfriend is disabled or at least 62 years old.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulielmetti said that while no single factor determines nontraditional-family-member status, the Rent Stabilization Code sets forth several factors that may be considered. Among them are the longevity of the relationship, shared payment of household expenses, intermingling of finances, maintaining joint accounts or credit cards, engaging in family-type activities and functions, naming each other in wills, and holding themselves out as family members in a manner that evidences the intention of creating a long-term, emotionally committed relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulielmetti said that it would be wise for the letter-writer to complete and send to the landlord a form published by the State Division of Housing and Community Renewal entitled ''Notice to Owner of Family Members Residing With the Named Tenant in the Apartment Who May Be Entitled to Succession Rights/ Protection From Eviction.''</p>
        <p>''Although Mr. Omanoff is not required to submit this form, doing so could make it easier for his girlfriend to establish succession rights at a later date,'' Mr. Gulielmetti said.</p>
        <p>Getting Names of Other Shareholders</p>
        <p>Q: As a shareholder in a co-op, do I have the right to request the names and apartment numbers of the other shareholders so I can campaign for votes? Also, do I have the right to attend meetings of the board or request a copy of the minutes of those meetings? . . . Harry Brownstein, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A: Morton H. Rosen, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that under Section 607 of the state's Business Corporation Law, a shareholder is entitled to a list of other shareholders, their apartment numbers and the number of shares they own.</p>
        <p>With respect to the second question, Mr. Rosen said, unless the co-op's proprietary lease or bylaws state otherwise, a board is free to conduct its meetings in private and refuse a shareholder's request to attend.</p>
        <p>''It may also refuse a shareholder's request for a copy of the minutes of board meetings,'' Mr. Rosen said, adding that such a refusal would be relatively uncommon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
