<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Usual Suspects Are Expected to Emerge From Regional Battles</title>
    <meta content="Y27CON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL PREVIEW 2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DD1031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Usual Suspects Are Expected to Emerge From Regional Battles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Atlantic Coast</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Florida State, a potential national champion now and forever. It needs receivers for Chris Weinke, its 28-year-old quarterback, but it has always found them. Clemson will challenge if its offense jells and its rebuilt secondary comes together.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT North Carolina, with an offense retooled after last season's 3-8 aberration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Atlantic Coast</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Florida State, a potential national champion now and forever. It needs receivers for Chris Weinke, its 28-year-old quarterback, but it has always found them. Clemson will challenge if its offense jells and its rebuilt secondary comes together.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT North Carolina, with an offense retooled after last season's 3-8 aberration.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS QB Chris Weinke and CB Tay Cody, Florida State; OLB Keith Adams and FS Robert Carswell, Clemson; TE Alge Crumpler, North Carolina; RB LaMont Jordan, Maryland.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Georgia Tech at Clemson Oct. 28, Clemson at Florida State Nov. 4, Florida at Florida State Nov. 18.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Georgia Tech replace quarterback Joe Hamilton and remain competitive?</p>
        <p>Atlantic 10</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Massachusetts, the Division I-AA national champion in 1998, will be a power again behind the running of tailback Marcel Shipp. Delaware and James Madison, both with sound defenses, may be nationally ranked, too.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT Villanova, because Brian Westbrook, a combination running back and wide receiver, is back after missing last season with an injured knee. In 1998, he became the first college player to gain 1,000 yards rushing and 1,000 yards receiving in one season.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS MLB Kole Ayi, Massachusetts; DE Chris Morant, James Madison; RB Butter Pressey, Delaware; QB Mike Scipione, Villanova.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Villanova at James Madison Oct. 7, Delaware at Massachusetts Nov. 11, Villanova at Delaware Nov. 18.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can any visitor beat Massachusetts, which has lost only one home game the last two years?</p>
        <p>Big East</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Miami, once the best team in the nation, and Virginia Tech, which made a run for the national title last season, are powers again. Miami, with 14 starters back from its Gator Bowl-winning team, gets the edge, but beware of Tech and its wizard at quarterback, Michael Vick.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOTS Pitt, 5-6 last season, has a dangerous passing game, and Boston College can run.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS QB Michael Vick and OT Dave Kadela, Virginia Tech; WR Santana Moss and ILB Dan Morgan, Miami; WR Latef Grim, Pitt; CB Will Allen, Syracuse.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Virginia Tech at Boston College Sept. 30, Florida State at Miami Oct. 7, Virginia Tech at Miami Nov. 4.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Syracuse, for years a national power, turn around from last season's 3-4 conference debacle?</p>
        <p>Big Ten</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS A powerhouse conference that sent seven teams to bowl games last season and has seven in a consensus preseason Top 25. The best may be Wisconsin, with sound running depite Ron Dayne's graduation, and Michigan, if quarterback Drew Henson recovers quickly from preseason foot surgery.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT Illinois, which beat Michigan and Ohio State on the road last season and has most of that offense back.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS QB Drew Brees, Purdue; CB Jamar Fletcher, Wisconsin; WR David Terrell and OG Steve Hutchinson, Michigan; C Ben Hamilton and DE Karon Riley, Minnesota.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Penn State at Ohio State Sept. 23, Wisconsin at Michigan Sept. 30, Michigan at Purdue Oct. 7.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Penn State, with a new defensive coordinator and nine new defensive starters and with quarterback Rashard Casey facing legal problems, be a national challenger again?</p>
        <p>Big 12</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Nebraska, with a brutal but partly rebuilding defense, and an offense almost as good, may be the best team in the nation. Kansas State, with question marks on offense, benefits from a soft schedule. Texas has a secure defense and talented quarterbacks in Major Applewhite and Chris Simms.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT Colorado, despite a tough early schedule, a new quarterback and an offense that lacks the power of recent years.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS QB Eric Crouch, OG Russ Hochstein and ILB Carlos Polk, Nebraska; OT Leonard Davis and DT Casey Hampton, Texas; S Jarrod Cooper, Kansas State; DE Justin Smith, Missouri.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Texas-Oklahoma at Dallas Oct. 7, Nebraska at Oklahoma Oct. 28, Nebraska at Kansas State Nov. 11.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION If quarterback Eric Crouch is hurt, will Nebraska hold up with inexperienced replacements?</p>
        <p>Conference USA</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Southern Mississippi, with a solid defense, should roll after season-opening road games against Tennessee and Alabama. East Carolina's many-splendored offense should win games, too.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOTS Houston, Louisville, Cincinnati and Memphis are clustered on the next tier. None seem a title threat.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS DE Cedric Scott and SS Leo Barnes, Southern Mississippi; QB David Garrard and LB Pernell Griffin, East Carolina; OG Josh Lovelady, Houston; C Doug Rosfeld, Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Virginia Tech at East Carolina Sept. 7, Southern Mississippi-Alabama at Birmingham, Ala., Sept. 16, East Carolina at Southern Mississippi Nov. 25.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Will Southern Mississippi, with so many new offensive assistants, play cohesively?</p>
        <p>Ivy</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Cornell, which averaged 40 points a game last season, returns 10 offensive starters to its pro-type offense. Yale, another passing team, needs the inexperienced Peter Lee to measure up to the graduated Joe Walland at quarterback.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT Penn, with its big offense, although graduation took three starting defensive linemen.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS CB Todd Tomich and SS Than Merrill, Yale; QB Gavin Hoffman and TB Kris Ryan, Penn; QB Ricky Rahne and WR Joe Splendorio, Cornell; WR Stephen Campbell, Brown.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Yale at Cornell Sept. 23, Penn at Cornell Nov. 18, Yale at Harvard Nov. 18.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Cornell's defense hold up in a league in which every team averaged at least 30 points a game last year?</p>
        <p>Pacific 10</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Washington's productive option offense features quarterback Marques Tuiasosopo, who passed for 302 yards and ran for 207 against Stanford last season. Southern California should win behind a veteran defense. Alas, the Big 2 do not meet.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOTS U.C.L.A., if it finds depth. Oregon, if it finds runners.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS OT Chad Ward and SS Hakim Akbar, Washington; RB Ken Simonton, Oregon State; TE Todd Heap, Arizona State; DE Kenyon Coleman, U.C.L.A.; DT Ennis Davis, Southern California.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Oregon at Southern California Oct. 14, U.C.L.A. at Washington Nov. 11, Southern California at U.C.L.A. Nov. 18.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Washington's new linebackers and cornerbacks help to put the Huskies into the national championship picture?</p>
        <p>Patriot</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Colgate and Lehigh, who tied for the title last year, are again the best, although graduation hit both offenses hard.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOT Towson, especially if it finds a worthy successor to quarterback Joe Lee.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS RB Randall Joseph and CB Brandon Tinson, Colgate; WR Jamal White, DE Andrew Hollingsworth and FS Ricky Crestwell, Towson.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Colgate at Towson Sept. 30, Lehigh at Towson Oct. 7, Colgate at Lehigh Nov. 4.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Colgate replace Ryan Vena and can Lehigh replace Phil Stambaugh, the best quarterbacks in this high-powered passing league last year?</p>
        <p>Southeastern</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS With 19 returning starters, Alabama, the surprising conference champion last season, looks good again. So do Florida, with a veteran defense, and Georgia, with a big offense led by quarterback Quincy Carter.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOTS Many candidates, but not Lou Holtz's South Carolina Gamecocks, who were 0-11 last season in his first season with the team.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS WR Freddie Milons, C Paul Hogan and OLB Saleem Rasheed, Alabama; DE Alex Brown, Florida; ILB Jamie Winborn, Vanderbilt; CB Fred Smoot, Mississippi State.</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Florida at Tennessee Sept. 16, Alabama at Tennessee Oct. 21, Auburn at Alabama Nov. 18.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can quarterback Jesse Palmer, in his senior year, do justice leading Florida's pass-happy offense?</p>
        <p>Others</p>
        <p>CONTENDERS Notre Dame is the best of a weak group of independents, and its running game has improved, but the Irish could be 0-4 before the end of September. Texas Christian, with a soft schedule, is favored in the Western Athletic Conference; Colorado State in the Mountain West, Marshall in the Mid-American, Boise State in the Big West and Duquesne in the Metro Atlantic Athletic.</p>
        <p>LONG SHOTS Utah and Brigham Young in the Mountain West, Fresno State in the W.A.C., Miami of Ohio in the Mid-American, New Mexico State in the Big West and Iona, which won no games two years ago, in the Metro Atlantic Athletic.</p>
        <p>KEY PLAYERS FS Tony Driver, Notre Dame, and FS Chris Lepore, Navy (independents); WR-KR Steve Smith, Utah, and OLB Kautai Olevao, Utah (Mountain West); RB LaDainian Tomlinson and DE Aaron Schobel, Texas Christian (W.A.C.); CB Daninelle Derricott, Marshall (Mid-American); QB Bart Hendricks, Boise State, and OT Rick DeMulling, Idaho (Big West); QB Tony Zimmerman, Duquesne, and TB Ralph Saldiveri, Iona (Metro Atlantic Athletic).</p>
        <p>PIVOTAL GAMES Nebraska at Notre Dame Sept. 9, Marshall at Michigan State Sept. 9, Fairfield at Duquesne Sept. 16, Colorado State at Utah Oct. 21, Boise State at New Mexico State Oct. 28, Fresno State at Texas Christian Nov. 11.</p>
        <p>KEY QUESTION Can Notre Dame, which lost its last four games last year and finished at 5-7 and out of a bowl, become a winner again and save Coach Bob Davie's job?</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL PREVIEW 2000</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
