<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paterno Takes Quest and Critics in Stride</title>
    <meta content="Y27PAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL PREVIEW 2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paterno, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DF1031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paterno Takes Quest and Critics in Stride</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Penn State and coach Joe Paterno preparing for 2000 college football season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Paterno once called Alabama Coach Bear Bryant ''the nearest thing we had to a god of football.'' And when Paterno met Bryant for a national championship, Paterno made some mortal mistakes.</p>
        <p>After Paterno's conservative play calling helped Alabama preserve a 14-7 lead over Penn State with a goal-line stand late in the 1979 Sugar Bowl, the Nittany Lions squandered another chance when they were penalized for having too many men on the field during an Alabama punt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Paterno once called Alabama Coach Bear Bryant ''the nearest thing we had to a god of football.'' And when Paterno met Bryant for a national championship, Paterno made some mortal mistakes.</p>
        <p>After Paterno's conservative play calling helped Alabama preserve a 14-7 lead over Penn State with a goal-line stand late in the 1979 Sugar Bowl, the Nittany Lions squandered another chance when they were penalized for having too many men on the field during an Alabama punt.</p>
        <p>''When I stood toe to toe with Bear Bryant,'' Paterno once wrote, ''he outcoached me.''</p>
        <p>Bryant retired in 1982 and died in 1983. In their four meetings as head coaches, Paterno never defeated Bryant and recalled last week that Bryant was ''an epic figure.'' But this season, which begins for Penn State today with the Kickoff Classic against Southern California. at Giants Stadium, Paterno can eclipse Bryant and become No. 1 on a prestigious list.</p>
        <p>Should the Nittany Lions win seven games, Paterno would have 324 victories, one more than Bryant's 323, the most for a coach in Division I-A. Eddie Robinson won 408 games at Grambling State, a Division I-AA school. At age 73, as Paterno begins his 51st season at Penn State and his 35th as head coach, his pursuit of Bryant's record will put him in the national spotlight and help write the narrative of the 2000 season.</p>
        <p>''I really don't give it a lot of thought,'' Paterno said recently, when asked about Bryant's record. ''I suppose when it happens -- if it happens -- I'll be, you know, I'll probably choke up again.'' He was referring to the emotion he showed on the field after his 300th victory, in 1998.</p>
        <p>But the attention paid to Paterno this season may not be all flattering. There are renewed questions about Paterno's coaching touch, the kind that have circulated before -- and have always been disproved -- after low points in his career. Perhaps more serious is skepticism about his use of his starting quarterback, Rashard Casey, who has been charged with beating an off-duty police officer. To some, playing Casey seems to contradict much of the ethical approach that Paterno has stood for throughout his illustrious career.</p>
        <p>In 1999, despite a 10-3 record, the Nittany Lions ended their season in disappointment. Expected to contend for the national championship and rated No. 2 in all the polls with a 9-0 record in November, they lost their final three Big Ten games -- by a total of 12 points -- and fell from contention.</p>
        <p>The first of those defeats, 24-23 at home against Minnesota, came on a last-second Minnesota field goal after a Penn State punt. Had the Nittany Lions attempted and converted a 50-yard field goal, instead of punting from the Minnesota 33-yard line, the Gophers would have needed a touchdown to win. Penn State's kicker, Travis Forney, had hit the left upright from the same spot earlier and was successful twice from 44 yards. ''That's a mistake I made,'' Paterno said after that game.</p>
        <p>The skid that began that day continued a trend of poor finishes. Paterno's teams used to get stronger late in the season. But in the last three years, the Nittany Lions are 4-7 in November, and they have emphasized conditioning in recent months to eliminate fourth-quarter sags.</p>
        <p>The more specific focus of debate this season will be the presence of Casey, a senior charged with aggravated assault for a fight with the officer, Patrick Fitzsimmons, outside a bar in Casey's hometown, Hoboken, N.J., on May 14. Fitzsimmons has also filed a civil suit against Casey and two other men who were with Casey, although only one of the other men was charged with assault in the criminal case.</p>
        <p>The Civil Rights Division of the Justice Department, at the request of the police chief, is investigating allegations that the officer was the victim of a racially based attack. The police said that the white officer was with a black woman when they encountered Casey and his friends, all of whom are black. Before the fight, Casey told the woman she should be with black men, the police chief said.</p>
        <p>The situation is awkward for Paterno. And although the coach has stressed his support for Casey, he has not publicly explained his rationale at any length. Some critics want more from an individual who has, in the past, talked and written extensively about educational standards for athletes and is currently crusading against betting on college sports in Nevada.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to play Rashard Casey until something convinces me I shouldn't,'' Paterno said. When told that some observers are perplexed by the situation, Paterno said: ''You don't expect me to do anything just because something is alleged. If some people out there are perplexed, I'm probably perplexed about their perplexions.''</p>
        <p>With a grand jury in New Jersey expected to weigh the severity of charges against Casey this autumn, would an indictment of his quarterback persuade Paterno to change his thinking? ''If it was a question of indictment, I think I would probably want to talk that over with university officials,'' Paterno said. ''But that's different than if he's guilty. I'd have to decide.''</p>
        <p>He has made big decisions before. After graduating from Brown in 1950, Paterno was headed for law school but accepted what he thought would be a temporary position as an assistant coach at Penn State. His coach at Brown, Rip Engle, was moving and he needed Paterno's help in installing the T-formation with the Nittany Lions. As Paterno grew comfortable in coaching, he began to crave a head-coaching position and discussed it with Vince Lombardi, a friend from Brooklyn who was also learning the craft as an assistant.</p>
        <p>Lombardi had coached a New Jersey high school team against Paterno's Brooklyn Prep team when Paterno was a player. Lombardi told Paterno that they would face discrimination in their careers because they were Italian and Catholic. Paterno had already felt the snubs of some wealthy and privileged fellow students at Brown. His experiences, he has said, sharpened his sensitivity regarding discrimination.</p>
        <p>Since replacing Engle in 1966, Paterno has won two national championships and 20 of 30 bowl games and has had five undefeated seasons while compiling a record of 317-83-3. He has befriended prominent politicians, including Republican presidents. He and his wife, Sue, have donated $3.5 million to Penn State for nonsports use. He has sent dozens of players to the National Football League, including Courtney Brown and LaVar Arrington, defenders who were the first two players chosen in the draft last spring. He has motivated and related to several generations of athletes.</p>
        <p>''It means the world to me, him believing in me that much,'' Casey said, when asked about playing for Paterno. ''I can look back at all the times I met with him and spoke to him. He knows me as a person. He knows how I carry myself.''</p>
        <p>Casey said people frequently ask him about Paterno's intensity and Casey tells them: ''You've got to get used to him. He can intimidate you early. When he yells at me, I laugh at his voice.''</p>
        <p>It is a voice from Flatbush, which rises in pitch and intensity when Paterno is angry. Omar Easy, a tailback, said Paterno's voice ''is kind of different.''</p>
        <p>''You can stay a mile away and hear him screaming,'' Easy said.</p>
        <p>Justin Kurpeikis, a defensive end, discussed Paterno's energy and how he runs after players up and down the field at practice. ''It's somewhat comical,'' he said. ''It's amazing. You don't realize he's as old as he is because he doesn't act his age.''</p>
        <p>Linebacker Ron Graham also marvels at Paterno's energy. ''You see him out on the practice field, running around and being involved the way he is, you wouldn't think he's 70-some years old,'' Graham said.</p>
        <p>Wide receiver Rod Perry said: ''It's not real hard to relate to good people. Good people kind of cross generation gaps.''</p>
        <p>Consistent in appearance for decades, Paterno retains a full head of dark hair, flecked with gray. He still wears tinted glasses and rolled-up pants above white socks and black athletic shoes. He will turn 74 right before Christmas but will probably not retire, even if he surpasses Bryant, who coached almost until he died. In 1998, Paterno said, ''I have programmed myself that I want to go through 2001,'' but last summer he signed a five-year extension through 2004. He has frequently said he would not know what to do without coaching.</p>
        <p>Paterno chuckled when he recalled a comment by 70-year-old Bobby Bowden of Florida State, whose 304 victories are second among active coaches. ''When you retire, there is just one more big event,'' Bowden said. ''And I ain't ready for that.''</p>
        <p>In a light moment last year, Paterno suggested he would remain head coach for 50 years. That would take him to 2015, when the man some call St. Joe would be 88 years old. ''That should get me into heaven,'' Paterno said. ''It will be my penance.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL PREVIEW 2000</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
