<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Make 200 Million Flip-Flops</title>
    <meta content="27BRAD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DB1331F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Make 200 Million Flip-Flops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on recycling the 6.5 million tires being recalled by Bridgestone Corp (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE deaths and injuries attributed to failed Firestone tires are horrific, but recalling 6.5 million tires poses another problem: what to do with them once they are taken off Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles and other light trucks.</p>
        <p>If someone figured out a way to stack the tires in a column at a landfill, they would form a pile 949 miles high. The last thing anyone wants is a high-rise breeding ground for mosquitoes, particularly those carrying the West Nile virus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE deaths and injuries attributed to failed Firestone tires are horrific, but recalling 6.5 million tires poses another problem: what to do with them once they are taken off Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles and other light trucks.</p>
        <p>If someone figured out a way to stack the tires in a column at a landfill, they would form a pile 949 miles high. The last thing anyone wants is a high-rise breeding ground for mosquitoes, particularly those carrying the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>Some Americans simply abandon their worn-out tires by night at the edge of the nearest stream, river or park. This is not only illegal but impractical for Bridgestone/Firestone, which is recalling enough tires to form a wall 50 feet high, 50 feet thick and a half mile long -- big enough to clog most rivers in the United States.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone and the Ford Motor Company said on Friday that they were looking for ways to use the scrap tires more productively, something the industry has been doing for years. They are focusing on ways to increase demand for scrap rubber, since tire-scrapping factories already have huge stockpiles of tires waiting to be torn apart whenever someone is willing to pay enough to cover the shredding costs. Proposals include mixing them with asphalt for paving roads, recycling them as auto parts, chopping them up for furnace fuel and grinding them up to use as garden hoses or playground mats.</p>
        <p>One of Ford's ideas, not surprisingly, is to turn the tires into auto parts for yet more sport utility vehicles. The immense Ford Excursion, which weighs as much as three small cars and is so big that it allows tall drivers to look in the windows of school buses, already uses a rubber air deflector, located below and behind the front bumper, that is made from scrap tires.</p>
        <p>Chop up the tires, separate out the steel bands that fly apart when the tires fail at high speed, and you would have 67 million pounds of rubber. That would be enough to make more than 100 million pairs of flip-flops. Or they could be used for huaraches, the flat Mexican sandals with soles made from tires that were de rigueur in the 1960's for hippies rebelling against their parents' leather shoes.</p>
        <p>The only problem is that the shoe industry is unenthusiastic about using old tires for the same reason that motorists are: the rubber tends to come apart after a while. The technology for various composite materials has improved so much that even in Mexico, huaraches are seldom made from tires now, said Fawn Evenson, the president of the American Apparel and Footwear Association.</p>
        <p>The recalled tires could also end up being sliced apart and shoveled into power plant furnaces as fuel -- a small step toward offsetting the poor energy efficiency of the Ford Explorer, which gets 15 miles to the gallon in the city and 19 on the highway. A typical tire on a family vehicle has the energy content of seven gallons of oil, partly because of the extensive use these days of synthetic rubber, an oil-based substance.</p>
        <p>Of the 270 million tires scrapped each year in the United States, about 114 million are mixed with coal and used as fuel, says the Scrap Tire Management Council, which is run by tire makers. But burning tires is unpopular with environmentalists.</p>
        <p>The green crowd prefers using tires to make garden hoses. Black ''soaker'' hoses, with many small holes in them for slow irrigation, not only use water much more efficiently than sprinklers but are made mainly from recycled tires. A million tires a year are used to make Moisture Master soaker hoses, said Paul Schneider, the product's marketing manager. The Firestone recall will make more scrap rubber available, he said.</p>
        <p>With a small subsidy, Ford and Firestone could actually prevent some injuries. Rubber playground mats made from recycled tires are very safe, and making them available more widely would prevent some of the 200,000 injuries and more than a dozen deaths that occur each year on the nation's playgrounds, said Donna Thompson, the director of the nonprofit National Program for Playground Safety, which is financed by the Centers for Disease Control.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thompson said that while she had not heard from Ford or Bridgestone, all of the recalled tires could be turned into 350 very large, thick playground mats for as little as $2 million, and then be given away to schools and cities that could not otherwise afford such mats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
