<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discovering Little Mysteries in the Yard</title>
    <meta content="LIGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDE1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discovering Little Mysteries in the Yard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR several weeks, there has been a mystery in my garden. It took quite a few days of sleuthing to solve, but I did get the best of it.</p>
        <p>The episode began one cool morning when I was weeding underneath some cotoneaster plants. These are very sprawly woody evergreens quite flat on the ground. While moving from one plant to the next on my hands and knees, I discovered a rather large mound of soil underneath one of the cotoneasters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR several weeks, there has been a mystery in my garden. It took quite a few days of sleuthing to solve, but I did get the best of it.</p>
        <p>The episode began one cool morning when I was weeding underneath some cotoneaster plants. These are very sprawly woody evergreens quite flat on the ground. While moving from one plant to the next on my hands and knees, I discovered a rather large mound of soil underneath one of the cotoneasters.</p>
        <p>Next to the mound, about a trowelful of soil, was a hole that was easily an inch across. My first thought was to cover it up, but on second thought, I decided that whatever lived there went to a lot of work to dig the hole and it did not seem fair to cover it up.</p>
        <p>Then I forgot about the incident  until the next day. There, along the edge of the slate walk, was another mound and its hole, about about the same size. Someone had definitely  taken up residence.</p>
        <p>There were many squirrels in the neighborhood, but they live in trees. So they were immediately ruled out. Also, I knew there many mice around. I had seen them but they were secretive and do not dig such big holes.</p>
        <p>Then early one morning, the mystery was solved: I opened the front  door to retrieve the morning paper and heard the telltale alarm call of a  chipmunk. Sure enough, down he plopped into the hole.</p>
        <p>Since then, I have seen these saucy little animals quite frequently around the premises. In fact, one seems to relish sitting on one of my troughs. Sometimes this chipmunk just takes in the sunshine. Other times he holds his paws, squirrel-like and nibbles on some seeds.</p>
        <p>The handsome chipmunks have prominent black stripes down their backs that stand out against their tawny brown fur. Underneath their eyes are clear white stripes, which make them look quite perky. The whole length of the animal, including the somewhat bushy-tipped tail, is usually about eight inches.</p>
        <p>By this time my curiosity was aroused to learn more about chipmunks. So off to the library to check out the encyclopedias. I learned that chipmunks do indeed belong to the squirrel clan and many of their habits are similar. The chipmunk's diet seems to be rather harmless as far as a gardener is concerned. They relish seeds, nuts and berries although they have been known to nibble on buds of flowers and low-growing shrubs.</p>
        <p>These little creatures are great family members. One of the encyclopedias had a drawing of their underground den. It appeared quite cozy with a large central room in the burrow where they sleep off the winter months and also raise their families. The mother chipmunk could  have as many as eight babies so there is potential for a large local population.</p>
        <p>One of the naturalists who studied chipmunks took a measurement of these underground burrows and found that they can be as long as 12 feet. Of course, there are always two entrances, in case one gets blocked, I suppose.</p>
        <p>During the early fall months it is possible to note the fat cheeks of chipmunks. They stuff their cheeks with all kinds of food, then they store it underground for the long haul through winter. The winter storage cache could be as large as a half bushel, depending on the size of the burrow and the family. Although chipmunks do not truly hibernate as do bears, they do enjoy sleeping during the winter months. But if a winter's day proves to be warm and sunny, these beguiling creatures will pop up out of their dens just to have a look around.</p>
        <p>The chipmunks are welcome to have around, so far. Some gardeners complain that they make a nuisance of themselves with their large holes. And of course, the local cats and dogs  have great fun trying to catch them.</p>
        <p>The North American continent has two species of chipmunks, one in the western states and the eastern species. One curious point: The genus name for the chipmunk is Tamias. which roughly translated means ''a steward.'' This is a tribute, no doubt, to their ability to carry so much food for storage in the fat little cheeks.</p>
        <p>This is but one of the many types of creatures that can be a part of the gardening experience if time is taken to look around and observe, to listen for the bird songs and to see who lives where. Some of the loveliest creatures don't even make a sound, such as butterflies. Yet they afford endless fascination with their graceful darting about from flower to flower.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
