<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tradition in Rye: Hanging Out at the Wall</title>
    <meta content="27WALL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEXT GENERATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rye (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D71731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tradition in Rye: Hanging Out at the Wall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>RYE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Wall, dead end in Rye, NY, which, for decades, has been unofficial teenage hangout, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A RED BMW came to a stop near the stone wall. Here's Armen. The gold Lexus pulling up, that's Scott. Then a shiny blue Volkswagen convertible. Amy.</p>
        <p>As each car pulled up to the stone wall along Rye Town Park last Monday, several teenagers hopped out and greeted one another with hugs, loose, slappy handshakes and the same question: Where's the party tonight?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A RED BMW came to a stop near the stone wall. Here's Armen. The gold Lexus pulling up, that's Scott. Then a shiny blue Volkswagen convertible. Amy.</p>
        <p>As each car pulled up to the stone wall along Rye Town Park last Monday, several teenagers hopped out and greeted one another with hugs, loose, slappy handshakes and the same question: Where's the party tonight?</p>
        <p>That's the perennial question at the Wall, the spacious dead end formed by Rye Beach Road and Old Rye Beach Road. It overlooks the park's rolling lawn and beach, Long Island Sound and Rye Playland. But the teenagers who hang out here face the other way, toward the road to monitor the cars that cruise by. They name the passengers and usually add their current opinion of them.</p>
        <p>Everyone in Rye knows the Wall. For decades it has been the unofficial meeting place, and kids here today have parents who hung out here in high school.</p>
        <p>Other ages visit, but the Wall basically belongs to the seniors at Rye High School, who mostly go on to expensive colleges, live in expensive homes and, after their 16th birthday, usually drive expensive cars.</p>
        <p>''If you come back here once you're in college, you basically stick out like a sore thumb,'' said Ed Lamanna, 19, who will be attending Temple University.</p>
        <p>''You're kind of seen as a loser,'' Richard Suarino, 18, added. He is the only one in the group staying local, at Westchester Community College, he said, ''so if I come by next year, I'm the loser.''</p>
        <p>A Jeep Cherokee careened around the block. Its passengers perused the crowd and kept going. Sophomores.</p>
        <p>''The day you get your license, it's ritualistic to drive by the Wall,'' said Samir Ahmed, who is heading to Middlebury College in Vermont.</p>
        <p>''Freshmen are afraid to come here,'' explained Stephan Bill, who is off to SUNY Potsdam. ''Sometimes you'll get junior high school kids walking here, but they're not too welcome.''</p>
        <p>Neither are the Rye police, but they come anyway. One officer was pulling up now.</p>
        <p>Parking is prohibited and the police often disperse the teenagers and stop Frisbee games on the park lawns. This evening, the officer was cool. He gave the group a few minutes. Other officers, the teenagers say, seem to enjoy checking for licenses, beer bottles and the smell of marijuana.</p>
        <p>No one from Rye ever actually goes to Playland, but the teenagers often gather in the bird sanctuary in back of it or in the parking lots of nearby yacht clubs.</p>
        <p>Last year, the high school tried to start a teen center, but the teenagers got disgusted because security guards would be hired to prevent drinking.</p>
        <p>There is little to do in Rye at this age but drink, the teenagers say. They can't get into the bars here, so some go drinking in Greenwich Village. Most get fake I.D.'s and go to a New Rochelle bar that accepts them. The fake I.D.'s don't work at the stores in Rye, so they buy beer at delis in Port Chester.</p>
        <p>The goal each day is to find out who is having a party while their parents are away. Often there's a keg and a $5 cup charge, all you can drink. The parties always end around 11, when the police inevitably find them and break them up.</p>
        <p>The biggest party of the summer, the teenagers said, was a five-kegger given by a teenager whose mother had a four-kegger during her own senior summer. He had to top that before going off to college.</p>
        <p>The biggest party of the school year, the teenagers said, was given as a low-key gathering by a freshman girl whose parents were overseas. It turned chaotic and lasted three days. Teenagers raided the freezer and caused thousands of dollars worth of damage. A door was ripped off the hinges. Walls were bashed in.</p>
        <p>Police Commissioner Joseph Verille said such occurrences are not uncommon. ''The parents go away, the kid invites a few close friends over and the next thing you know, a lot of people show up whether you want them there or not,'' he said. ''Things get out of control, and the parents' house gets trashed.''</p>
        <p>Mike Stevens, who is also headed to Middlebury, said: ''I think there's a lot of drinking here because of the stress and the boredom. A lot of kids around here get so much pressure from their parents about the future. They're like, 'Where am I going to school? What am I going to do?' During the winter, when college applications were due, I saw kids drinking a lot.''</p>
        <p>But now they're leaving for college and saying goodbye to one another, and to the Wall.</p>
        <p>Last week, a group of friends gathered around Liza Knowles, who was leaving for Colgate the next morning. While they took group photographs, Liza hugged her boyfriend Stephan next to his Mitsubishi Montero. Playland's ferris wheel twinkled in the dusk. He and Liza were breaking up, he said, because ''we're young still and we'll be so far apart.''</p>
        <p>Someone turned on a car radio. Britney Spears. Some of the girls did a dance step or two. Everyone kept saying they were leaving, but no one would go. Soon they would all be leaving, and you can't go back to the Wall.</p>
        <p>But now the police car was coming back, and everyone headed for their cars and that evening's party.</p>
        <p>NEXT GENERATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
