<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South's Football Fans Still Stand Up and Pray</title>
    <meta content="27PRAY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0D81031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South's Football Fans Still Stand Up and Pray</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>HATTIESBURG, Miss., Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Students and fans are praying before high school football games around South, trend likely to grow as word catches on; school officials, responding to Supreme Court ban on officially-sanctioned student-led prayer, carefully stay out of way of grass-roots efforts to restore prayer to its traditional position before kickoff; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It started slowly at first, a few students holding hands in the bleachers and saying ''Our Father who art in Heaven'' while football players gathered on the North Forrest High School field Friday night. But by the time they got to ''deliver us from evil,'' most of the crowd of 4,500 was standing, proudly reciting the Lord's Prayer, insisting that God cannot be removed even from a Class 4-A high school football game.</p>
        <p>School officials carefully stayed out of the way, in order not to violate a June decision of the United States Supreme Court prohibiting student-led prayer at games and assemblies if it is officially sanctioned by the school. Handbills had been distributed by a Christian ministry active in southern Mississippi urging people to pray just before the game, but no loudspeaker was used, and there was no official leader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It started slowly at first, a few students holding hands in the bleachers and saying ''Our Father who art in Heaven'' while football players gathered on the North Forrest High School field Friday night. But by the time they got to ''deliver us from evil,'' most of the crowd of 4,500 was standing, proudly reciting the Lord's Prayer, insisting that God cannot be removed even from a Class 4-A high school football game.</p>
        <p>School officials carefully stayed out of the way, in order not to violate a June decision of the United States Supreme Court prohibiting student-led prayer at games and assemblies if it is officially sanctioned by the school. Handbills had been distributed by a Christian ministry active in southern Mississippi urging people to pray just before the game, but no loudspeaker was used, and there was no official leader.</p>
        <p>''Just because the government shut down the prayers on the intercom doesn't mean they can stop us from praying silently or just starting a prayer, just by leading it by someone anonymously,'' said Savannah Spencer, an eighth-grade clarinet player who prayed with most of the school band. ''Our band teachers and drum majors said we can stand up if we wanted to.''</p>
        <p>The scene was repeated, with various levels of participation, at scores of high school football games around the South on Friday, and is likely to grow as word catches on. Throughout the region, where the line between religion and high school football has never been particularly well marked, grass-roots efforts are underway to restore prayer to its traditional position just before the kickoff.</p>
        <p>The court's decision, in a case involving the Santa Fe, Tex., school board, was denounced in many Christian pulpits around the South as the last straw in the court's recent decisions on religion in public life. All summer, a loosely knit coalition of conservative organizations and religious denominations have worked on ways to legally maintain prayer at student gatherings, and the solution was on display Friday night: a planned recitation of the Lord's Prayer, immediately after the National Anthem, by students and parents who have not sought permission from the school to do so.</p>
        <p>''As long as the school isn't involved, the students and the fans can get up and say whatever they want,'' said Paul Ott, a popular outdoor-sports broadcaster in southern Mississippi who has been using his radio show to spread the word about the prayer. ''We are not going to let them take God any further away from our country. People all over are standing up and saying the Lord's Prayer to protect their religious liberty.''</p>
        <p>The movement is catching on  from Texas to the Carolinas. In Asheville, N.C., last week, more than 25,000 people gathered at a high school football stadium for a rally sponsored by a new group called We Still Pray, which is promoting the recitation of the Lord's Prayer. Scattered groups of people said the prayer at dozens of games in western North Carolina on Friday night.</p>
        <p>An organization called ''No Pray, No Play'' is advocating the same idea in Texas, and has been supported by pastors around the state who are organizing prayers for next week's games. In Forest City, N.C., a radio station is allowing a pastor to say a prayer at the beginning of high school football broadcasts, and is urging fans at the game to turn up their radios during the prayer. The American Family Association, a conservative Christian organization led by the Rev. Donald Wildmon, is promoting the prayer at football games on its widely heard radio shows.</p>
        <p>In most cases, church organizers are trying to stay within the court ruling by bypassing the school administration. In its 6-to-3 decision, the court said that impermissible school involvement included the use of the stadium public address system, a speaker representing students, any direct supervision or approval by the faculty, or any  policy that explicitly or implicitly encourages prayer.</p>
        <p>But some districts are going further. In Batesburg-Leesville, S.C., Friday, the student body president said a prayer over the public address system before a football game. The school board in Searcy, Ark., voted to let a Christian group hold prayers around a school flagpole before games.</p>
        <p>The American Civil Liberties Union branch in South Carolina says it will go to court to stop the practice in Batesburg-Leesville. But Steven Shapiro, the national legal director of the A.C.L.U. in New York, said he was not sure what to make of the students who are saying the Lord's Prayer on their own. If the school is genuinely uninvolved, it might constitute protected free speech, he said, though he is concerned about its presence at a school event.</p>
        <p>''It's a complicated legal question, but one of the things we have learned over the years is that school officials are rarely uninvolved at their own events, rarely passive observers,'' he said. ''School officials don't like to relinquish control.'' The organization's response will depend on the facts of a district's involvement, he said.</p>
        <p>Walter Dellinger, a constitutional scholar at Duke University Law School and former solicitor general of the United States, said prayer could pass muster only if it was truly private and independent of school authority, at which point it would be considered protected free speech.</p>
        <p>''It strikes me as unfortunate that football games can be used as occasions for prayer, the effect of which is to make some students feel like religious strangers at their own public schools,'' he said. ''But as long as it is a product of private decisions by individuals or groups, it doesn't violate the Constitution.''</p>
        <p>At two high schools in Hattiesburg, the school principals said organizers had told them the prayer would be said, but they took no action. At a game not far from North Forrest at Hattiesburg High School, just a few students and parents rose to pray.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take a while to catch on, like anything else, but I think it's going to grow pretty big,'' said John Simpson, the principal of Hattiesburg High School, who prayed. ''Most of the students and parents support this -- they think the Supreme Court went too far. I would love to be in the middle of it, but I'm not going to violate the law. So I'm glad the kids are doing it.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone was pleased by the precise nature of the prayer, however. Matthew Krell, who is Jewish and is a drum major in the band at Hattiesburg High, said he wished the organizers had not chosen such a well-known Christian prayer.</p>
        <p>''I'm not against prayer, but it shouldn't be one specific to a single religion,'' he said. ''If they ever really got organized, I guess I'd just have to say the Sabbath prayer -- it's Friday night, you know.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
