<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Trickle, Not a Rush, In Tourism to Vietnam</title>
    <meta content="27REP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vietnam-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vietnam</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shenon, Philip</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D6113EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Trickle, Not a Rush, In Tourism to Vietnam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shenon, Philip</byline>
      <dateline>HANOI, Vietnam</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article explores reasons for lag in American tourism to Vietnam 25 years after end of Vietnam War in light of recently signed US-Vietnamese trade agreement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years after the end of the Vietnam War and a month after the United States completed an historic trade agreement with its former enemy, tour organizers in both countries hope that American travelers will finally start to make their way to Vietnam in large numbers.</p>
        <p>The trade pact, which was signed on July 13, is not expected to have an immediate, direct impact on tourism. It is mainly intended to expand trade in goods between the two countries, and to open Vietnam's backward economy to American investment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years after the end of the Vietnam War and a month after the United States completed an historic trade agreement with its former enemy, tour organizers in both countries hope that American travelers will finally start to make their way to Vietnam in large numbers.</p>
        <p>The trade pact, which was signed on July 13, is not expected to have an immediate, direct impact on tourism. It is mainly intended to expand trade in goods between the two countries, and to open Vietnam's backward economy to American investment.</p>
        <p>But among Vietnamese tourism officials, the hope is that the agreement will inspire new confidence in this country among Americans planning to travel to Asia. Although the country boasts 5,000 years of history, cities and countryside of exceptional beauty, unspoiled palm-fringed beaches and some of the best food in Asia, many Americans apparently still see Vietnam as a difficult, even hostile destination.</p>
        <p>''They think Vietnam is like North Korea,'' said Doug Reese, the Washington-based representative for Vietnamtourism, a government agency. ''People keep thinking about the war. They think Vietnam is dangerous, that they won't be welcome.''</p>
        <p>In fact, as most recent visitors to Vietnam will attest, the country is eager to welcome foreign travelers, Americans in particular, and the friendliness of the reception can be overwhelming to any American who remembers the torment of the war.</p>
        <p>During the recent nationwide celebration to mark the 25th anniversary of the country's reunification -- and the defeat of the American-backed government of South Vietnam -- the Communist government offered little of the anti-American propaganda that was once was its daily fare.</p>
        <p>Most of the current Vietnamese population was born after the war, and Vietnamese youngsters avidly enjoy American music and fashion.</p>
        <p>Since she began organizing tours to Vietnam three years ago, Lesley Gonzalez of Asian Pacific Adventures in Northridge, Calif., said her clients have yet to report a bad experience. ''All of their expectations,'' she said, ''are surpassed: the hotels, the food, the hospitality of the people.''</p>
        <p>Vietnamese officials have been disappointed by the sluggish growth in tourism from the United States. Of the 64,400 visas reported issued to Americans last year by the Vietnamese Embassy in Washington, almost 46,100 of them went to Vietnamese-Americans, many going to see their families, not to spend money at tourist sites or in hotels or restaurants.</p>
        <p>Over all, foreign tourism to Vietnam continues to set records. The country's tourism authority recorded almost 1.06 million visitors in the first six months of the year, a jump of 18 percent from the same period of 1999. China, France, Taiwan, Britain and Japan sent the largest numbers of tourists last year, in that order.</p>
        <p>But the Vietnamese had hoped for -- and planned for -- more dramatic growth. A building boom in the early 1990's has resulted in a glut of hotel rooms, notably in Hanoi, the nation's capital, and Ho Chi Minh City, formerly Saigon. According to government figures, the country's hotel occupancy rate last year was 43 percent.</p>
        <p>One result, for visitors, is that Vietnam can be a bargain. Comfortable, newly renovated hotel rooms can be had for under $20 a night in major cities. And world-class luxury is a relative bargain as well.</p>
        <p>The newly opened five-star Hilton Hanoi Opera -- not to be confused with the prison down the street that was known to jailed American pilots as the Hanoi Hilton -- offers rooms for $94 a night plus 15 percent tax, a rate that includes breakfast, evening cocktails, butler service and a full gym.</p>
        <p>Across the street is the fabled Metropole Hotel, a lovingly restored French colonial gem that is now run by Sofitel, the French hotel chain. A five-course meal in its Vietnamese restaurant costs less than $20 with wine, and features a floor show of Vietnamese dance. Rooms begin at $100, plus tax.</p>
        <p>The lag in United States tourism may be due less to memories of the war and more to a practical fact: There are no direct flights between the United States and Vietnam. Tourism officials in both countries say that an American tourist influx will begin in earnest only when the two countries establish direct air connections.</p>
        <p>Currently Americans are usually required to connect elsewhere in Asia with flights of Vietnam Airlines or one of several Asian or European airlines that fly to Hanoi and Ho Chi Minh City.</p>
        <p>Although Vietnam Airlines has junked most of its old Russian fleet and replaced it with new Boeing and Airbus jets, tour operators say American travelers are wary of flying Vietnam's national carrier. ''It's important for the U.S. carriers to go,'' Mr. Reese said. ''The arrival of the American carriers is like the U.S. government seal of approval for travel to Vietnam.''</p>
        <p>United Airlines, Northwest and other American carriers have said they are eager to obtain landing rights in Vietnam. But negotiations on an air-rights agreement have repeatedly bogged down. There is optimism in Washington and Hanoi that the trade agreement signed last month has established an atmosphere of cooperation that will extend to the landing-rights talks, which are resuming this summer.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
