<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hanging On for Dear Life Beyond 100 M.P.H.</title>
    <meta content="27BOAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lilly, Art</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D71031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hanging On for Dear Life Beyond 100 M.P.H.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Jeff Harris and Art Lilly setting offshore powerboat world record of 140.120 miles an hour; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is difficult to describe the feeling of disorder, but it's something like taking the wheel of a high-performance automobile barreling down the freeway at speeds well beyond the legal limit. The car is weaving through traffic, but the responsibility for maintaining control is being shared with the passenger beside you, who has sole command of the accelerator.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, he is laughing and hooting, and his friends and colleagues have confided to you that he's a brilliant maniac.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is difficult to describe the feeling of disorder, but it's something like taking the wheel of a high-performance automobile barreling down the freeway at speeds well beyond the legal limit. The car is weaving through traffic, but the responsibility for maintaining control is being shared with the passenger beside you, who has sole command of the accelerator.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, he is laughing and hooting, and his friends and colleagues have confided to you that he's a brilliant maniac.</p>
        <p>All you can do is steer, react and hope for the best. And that, in essence, describes my first 100-plus-mile-an-hour experience last Thursday on the Chesapeake Bay at the helm of a Super Vee Light twin-engine rocket called Pier 57. The man at my side was Art Lilly, who holds numerous powerboating records in the sport and was named the 1999 American Power Boat Association throttleman of the year.</p>
        <p>The four-boat, Tennessee-based Pier 57 team arrived in Baltimore the previous evening for this weekend's 15th annual Chesapeake Challenge Offshore Powerboat Race. The action continues this afternoon on the Patapsco River, where dozens of boats in numerous classes are competing in a lead-in event to the association's national championships in Washington, N.C., in October.</p>
        <p>In last year's Chesapeake stop, Lilly and his driver, Jeff Harris, narrowly averted tragedy when the driver of another boat lost control on a turn and spun out across their deck. ''He was upside down and his props ran right down the side of our boat and missed our canopy by about 20 inches, which was pretty scary,'' Lilly said.</p>
        <p>Unfazed, Harris and Lilly went out the next day and took the checkered flag for their class.</p>
        <p>The relationship between driver and throttleman clearly has its Butch and Sundance moments.</p>
        <p>''The throttle guys usually have different attitudes than the drivers,'' said David Woods, the Pier 57 owner, who is also a throttleman for one of the Fountain-built Super Vee racers. ''It's a known fact. If you're on the throttle, you're the one pushing it.''</p>
        <p>Not one to miss a setup line, Woods's driving partner, Fred Tull, agreed. ''The driver does tend to be more level-headed,'' he said. ''You always need to calm the throttle guy down a bit. Right there you've got your responsible individual, and your irresponsible individual.''</p>
        <p>Joking aside, the teamwork between a driver and a throttleman as they negotiate tight turns over the course of a typical 100-mile Super Vee race is intricate and exhausting. In addition to governing the speed of the 39-foot boat, the throttleman also controls the attitude of the trim tabs and the outdrives for the 850 horsepower engines, which must be constantly adjusted depending on the water conditions.</p>
        <p>With no small measure of trepidation -- my last voyage under power had been on a leaky inflatable dinghy with a cranky five-horsepower outboard -- I accepted an offer for a spin with Lilly aboard one of the two Pier 57 Super Vee Lights. After donning a helmet and a life jacket, fastening my seat belt and shoulder harness, and taking note of the oxygen regulator in the event we flipped over, we got underway with a last question from Woods: ''Anybody you want me to call?''</p>
        <p>Jogging at about 10 m.p.h. out of the marina, it was with a huge sigh of relief that I saw before us a long, glassy expanse of calm water. Lilly, who relishes racing in big seas, seemed exasperated by the lack of bumpy chop and liquid moguls.</p>
        <p>Speaking into a helmet headset, his voice was as flat as the seaway. ''It's never like this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But his mood picked up when the throttle went down, and in an instant we were doing 60 m.p.h. and climbing fast. We bolted past a schooner full of tourists and I caught a glimpse of them along the starboard rail: their heads snapped in unison, from left to right, like a row of midcourt spectators at a tennis match taking in Pete Sampras's first serve.</p>
        <p>To my left, a Global Positioning System navigation set could barely keep up with our progress. Though too intent on my clammy hands at the wheel to give it a fixed gaze, I saw we were at 80 m.p.h., and a nanosecond later we were over 95. When Lilly asked for an update, we had topped off at 106, which earned a chuckle and a satisfied ''all right'' over the walkie-talkie. In the rearview mirror, the Key Bridge was rapidly shrinking.</p>
        <p>Soon, Lilly eased the throttle back for the return trip to the marina and said, ''I could do this all day, but we've got to save those engines for the weekend.''</p>
        <p>As the responsible one, I couldn't disagree.</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
