<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Not Easy on the Greens</title>
    <meta content="27MINI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miniature Golf</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E1DC1731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Not Easy on the Greens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article offers sampling of miniature golf courses in Westchester County, NY; list of toughest holes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOLFERS are often reminded that Westchester has some of the world's most difficult golf holes.</p>
        <p>There's the 18th at Winged Foot in Mamaroneck, a 448-yard par 4 where, during the 1984 U.S. Open, Fuzzy Zoeller waved a white towel in mock surrender after Greg Norman made a 40-foot putt to force a playoff. There's the 11th at Westchester Country Club, a par 4 where Sergio Garcia made a double bogey and gave up a comfortable lead in the final round of last year's Buick Classic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOLFERS are often reminded that Westchester has some of the world's most difficult golf holes.</p>
        <p>There's the 18th at Winged Foot in Mamaroneck, a 448-yard par 4 where, during the 1984 U.S. Open, Fuzzy Zoeller waved a white towel in mock surrender after Greg Norman made a 40-foot putt to force a playoff. There's the 11th at Westchester Country Club, a par 4 where Sergio Garcia made a double bogey and gave up a comfortable lead in the final round of last year's Buick Classic.</p>
        <p>But how many golf legends who have conquered those courses have ever had to putt under a waterfall at Rye Playland while a roller coaster full of screaming children rattled by?</p>
        <p>And when was Tiger Woods, who just won his third major championship this year, last seen trying to tame the Seal Hole at 9W Golf in Palisades?</p>
        <p>No one should underestimate the difficulty of Westchester's miniature golf holes. A recent sampling of some killer courses found that the toughest holes could giveeven the most seasoned touring pro a chronic case of the yips on the putting green.</p>
        <p>The course at Saxon Woods Park on Mamaroneck Avenue in White Plains, next to the park's large public pool, has several challenging stretches. The course is laid out around a large fountain, and several creeks splash through the tropical garden setting, lulling golfers into a false sense of comfort. But don't be seduced: a monster awaits.</p>
        <p>The holes are long (which by miniature golf standards means ''too far to long jump'') and are often guarded by rocks and tricky undulations in the fairways. Each hole has an explanatory diagram plaque, but most fall far short of conveying the treachery of the hazards.</p>
        <p>The first hole, for example, is a straightaway par 3 that looks easy on paper. But just try hitting a tee shot that avoids the  fairway's gentle hills, which knock most putts off line. The second hole pitches up a sloping fairway to a cup nestled between two boulders.</p>
        <p>The third hole is a true test of nerves for golfers of any skill level. The fairway is essentially a two-sided ramp with a gap in the middle, like an opening drawbridge.</p>
        <p>To negotiate this stretch, the tee shot must behave like a car in a chase scene. Shots hit hard enough hurtle safely over the chasm, but weaker ones plunge toward the stream below, to be saved only by a mercifully placed safety grating.</p>
        <p>On the seventh hole, one's fate is up to the gods of golf, since off the tee you must putt through one of three hollow logs that deposit the ball on the green. And on the ninth, a par 2, the five bunkers that sit smugly in the middle of the fairway make it almost impossible to get a tee shot through.</p>
        <p>The 10th, also a par 2, is the closest you can get to a blind tee shot in miniature golf. The L-shaped dogleg has a boulder in the middle of the fairway, and the hole is well guarded by two more stones on either side.</p>
        <p>The three finishing holes at Saxon Woods are also well protected. The 17th cup is on top of a plateau, and the 18th is smack behind a large rock.</p>
        <p>The 19th is a bonus hole. There is no liquor served, but maybe there should be. It is an unnerving par 2, a long dogleg to the right, which presents a classic gamble: you can take a shortcut by trying to hit the ball into a skinny hollow log running over the lake, or you can lay up by hitting left, around the dogleg and taking a chance with a long  second putt.</p>
        <p>Speaking of difficult finishing holes, you can't get a more challenging one than the 18th at the Family Golf Center, which last month opened a miniature golf course (along with a pro shop and a driving range) in Yorktown Heights.</p>
        <p>The center, at 2710 Lexington Avenue in Mohegan Lake, looks like an industrial park but opens in the back to a landscaped area where the holes wind among lush foliage.</p>
        <p>There is a small practice green, and you'll need it. The layout is tough and actually seems less suited to golfers than mountain goats.</p>
        <p>The 18th hole, for example, has an undulating fairway, which slopes sharply downhill. Tee shots are struck under a walk-through waterfall, and like on most holes here, the fairways are obstructed by landscaped garden beds.</p>
        <p>The Golden Bear Golf Center in Elmsford offers some of the most challenging miniature golf holes in Westchester, but the first challenge is finding the course. It is part of a large golf center tucked away in the Fairview Corporate Park on Route 9A, just north of Interstate 287.</p>
        <p>Golfers should consider bringing along a driver. This is miniature golf on steroids, with some holes bordering on pitch-and-putt length.</p>
        <p>There are two 18-hole layouts. The Masters course, to the south, is slightly more difficult than the Legends course to the north.</p>
        <p>Many holes have island bunkers mid-fairway, forcing golfers to choose between the safer, longer way around or risking it all with a tight squeeze to shave off some distance.</p>
        <p>On the Masters course, the 11th hole is 50 feet long and runs so steeply uphill that you'd like to trade in your putter for an 8-iron. The 12th is a dogleg right, and the tee shot must scoot along the very left side of the fairway to avoid a gaping basin that swallows imperfect tee shots like a black hole.</p>
        <p>The 13th hole, another dogleg right, heads down the steepest slope one can encounter in mini-golf onto a green with more bumps than an elephant burial ground.</p>
        <p>On the Legends course, the fairway takes a hairpin turn on the second hole. The third hole circles around a boulder the size of a large shed, and the fourth is a long S-shaped hole.</p>
        <p>Across the Tappan Zee bridge, in Rockland County, there is 9W Golf in Palisades. It is part of George Kopac's Driving Range, which Mr. Kopac said dates back at least to the 1930's. The miniature golf course was originally built in the 50's and retains some of its original charm.</p>
        <p>Here there are faux churches to hit under. The 11th hole runs under a toy lighthouse.</p>
        <p>The course looks more like a theme park, but the structures serve as mental distractions. And there are some downright tough holes, as Richard F. Jones of Dobbs Ferry found out. Mr. Jones, a social worker in Yonkers, used to play minigolf on Long Island and said he found Hudson Valley courses not as challenging. But then he ran into 9W and could only muster a round low enough to tie his partner, Michele Marcondes from Hartsdale, a minigolf neophyte.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones's trouble came at the seventh hole, putting under an oversized slot machine with flashing lights. His concentration broken, he was sent into a tailspin, putting under a trained seal statue, then a locomotive, then a rocket ship.</p>
        <p>The tee shot at the 11th hole, under a tall lighthouse and into one of two tubes that deposit the ball onto the green, caused more consternation . And by the time he got to the suspension bridge with three lanes for tee shots, he was ready to hang up his spikes.</p>
        <p>The mini-golf course at Rye Playland is just inside the main park entrance, near the boardwalk on the edge of the Long Island Sound. .</p>
        <p>The Playland course, concrete holes in an expanse of red gravel, must technically be considered a links-style layoutk.</p>
        <p>Most of the holes are fairly simple straightaway designs, but the 12th is a bit tricky, with a tee shot under a waterfall. But the Playland course has other charms. Where else can you get cotton candy, saltwater taffy and candy apples afterward?</p>
        <p>Playland is where Steven Pappas, 46, a piano mover from Manhattan, took his roommate's children out for some mini golf, but he wasn't about to lose to them.</p>
        <p>''Get legs, baby,'' he yelled at his tee shot on the eighth hole, a short straightaway with a tricky green. When he crowed about beating his opponent, one of the children said, ''Yeah, against an 11-year-old.''</p>
        <p>''So?'' Mr. Pappas retorted, narrowly missing a three-foot knee-knocker. ''He's closer to the ground.''</p>
        <p>Where Luck Would Help</p>
        <p>Here are some of the toughest miniature golf holes in the region:</p>
        <p>*The Drawbridge Hole, No. 3 at Saxon Woods Park in Scarsdale. Clear the chasm or drop toward the water below.</p>
        <p>*The 18th at the Family Golf Center course in Yorktown Heights. A tee shot under a waterfall, and down a sloping fairway to a bumpy green.</p>
        <p>*The 11th hole on the Masters course at the Golden Bear Golf Center in Elmsford. A 50-foot-long hole straight uphill. Hmm, putter or 8-iron?</p>
        <p>*The 18th at 9W Golf in Palisades. Just to make the green, the tee shot  must clear a narrow slot under a tall weather vane.</p>
        <p>*The 19th at Saxon Woods. Long dogleg right that entices the gambling  golfer to putt through a narrow hollow log over water.</p>
        <p>*The 13th hole at the Masters course at the Golden Bear. A dogleg right that has the steepest slope in mini-golf onto a bumpy green.</p>
        <p>*The second hole on the Legends course at the Golden Bear. A long, U-shaped hole with a hairpin turn in the fairway.</p>
        <p>*The 16th at Rye Playland. The tee shot is under a waterfall, and next to a roller coaster. Good luck.</p>
        <p>*The Seal Hole at 9W Golf in Palisades. Actually, a fairly simple hole, if you're used to putting with a seal staring you down.</p>
        <p>COREY KILGANNON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
