<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Englewood: A Case Study and a Work in Progress</title>
    <meta content="27ENGL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Englewood (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D81031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Englewood: A Case Study and a Work in Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two-decade effort to revive western flank of Palisade Avenue in Englewood, NJ, is often cited as a case study in the challenge of suburban redevelopment; many of steps the city took were small in scale; business vacancy rate was 16 percent in 1994, and today only one storefront is vacant (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For two decades, officials in Englewood, N.J., have been working to revive the western flank of Palisade Avenue, the city's main commercial street. Their painstaking efforts are often cited as a case study in the challenge of suburban redevelopment.</p>
        <p>Even today, says Peter Beronio, the city's director of economic development, ''we're still a work in progress.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For two decades, officials in Englewood, N.J., have been working to revive the western flank of Palisade Avenue, the city's main commercial street. Their painstaking efforts are often cited as a case study in the challenge of suburban redevelopment.</p>
        <p>Even today, says Peter Beronio, the city's director of economic development, ''we're still a work in progress.''</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, Englewood officials came to realize that before they could make people want to shop on West Palisade Avenue, they needed to improve the neighborhood around it. The city bought property on blighted Armory Street (which intersects with West Palisade) that had been abandoned by absentee landlords; it helped residents -- mostly blacks and Hispanics -- rehabilitate their homes; it shut down an auto body shop suspected of being a drug marketplace; and it cleaned up a park that was also notorious for criminal activity.</p>
        <p>Many of the steps the city took were small in scale, like improving the sidewalks, facades, streets and lighting. Officials also rid storefronts of solid iron gates, which attracted graffiti, and prohibited anyone under 18 from buying spray paint without a note from a teacher or parent, Mr. Beronio said.</p>
        <p>The first sign that perceptions of West Palisade had changed came in 1998, when ground was broken for a two-story retail building developed by Group USA, a national discount women's clothing chain. The $2.5 million building opened in November, replacing seven vacant, dilapidated buildings. Other tenants include Mikasa, a china and flatware store, and the Children's Place.</p>
        <p>In June, the city Planning Board approved a second building, which will include stores, offices and three floors of condominiums. ''We're big advocates of providing more downtown housing,'' said N. David Milder, a consultant who helped Englewood with its revitalization strategy. Residents not only become customers of nearby stores, but they are also likely to take an interest in keeping up the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Mr. Beronio said, downtown Englewood had a 16 percent business vacancy rate, with most of the empty spaces on the west side. Today, only one storefront on West Palisade Avenue is vacant.</p>
        <p>''They were very methodical, but with a vision,'' said Jef R. Buehler, the acting state coordinator of Main Street New Jersey, a state program that provides assistance for downtown revitalization. ''Their long-term plan was very comprehensive. They didn't just invest money in a brick-and-mortar project. Those are fine, but alone, that's not the answer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
