<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Season of the Bounce</title>
    <meta content="27SUN1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/opinion/27SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3D71331F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Season of the Bounce</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial assess bounce in polls Vice Pres Al Gore has received after selecting Sen Joseph Lieberman as his running mate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2000 presidential campaign has produced an unusually intense post-convention period. The tradition that the nominees spend a few sleepy weeks resting before Labor Day seems a thing of the distant past, thanks to an unusual volatility in the polls and increasingly heated exchanges between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush. Even Mr. Gore has got to be a little surprised at the way he has been lifted in voter surveys since the Democrats adjourned their convention. After a smooth run-up to the Republican convention, Mr. Bush has been looking defensive and has even been publicly self-critical about his problems in making the case for his huge tax cuts. The candidates are mischievously making feints into each other's friendly territory -- Mr. Gore in Florida and Mr. Bush in several states carried by the Democrats in recent elections. All told, the voters have reason to believe both men's predictions that this will wind up as a tough, tight race.</p>
        <p>The candidates' fortunes and the lead in the polls are likely to change several times before the election. But the most striking feature of the past 10 days has been the ''bounce'' experienced by Mr. Gore after his selection of Senator Joseph Lieberman as a running mate and after a spirited convention in Los Angeles. Many polls show him slightly ahead of Mr. Bush for the first time. Some independent voters have swung to his side, and Mr. Gore increased his support among Democrats to levels that are traditional, suggesting that the party faithful may have come home. He has also strengthened his ratings as a convincing leader, whereas before voters rated Mr. Bush more highly on leadership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 2000 presidential campaign has produced an unusually intense post-convention period. The tradition that the nominees spend a few sleepy weeks resting before Labor Day seems a thing of the distant past, thanks to an unusual volatility in the polls and increasingly heated exchanges between Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush. Even Mr. Gore has got to be a little surprised at the way he has been lifted in voter surveys since the Democrats adjourned their convention. After a smooth run-up to the Republican convention, Mr. Bush has been looking defensive and has even been publicly self-critical about his problems in making the case for his huge tax cuts. The candidates are mischievously making feints into each other's friendly territory -- Mr. Gore in Florida and Mr. Bush in several states carried by the Democrats in recent elections. All told, the voters have reason to believe both men's predictions that this will wind up as a tough, tight race.</p>
        <p>The candidates' fortunes and the lead in the polls are likely to change several times before the election. But the most striking feature of the past 10 days has been the ''bounce'' experienced by Mr. Gore after his selection of Senator Joseph Lieberman as a running mate and after a spirited convention in Los Angeles. Many polls show him slightly ahead of Mr. Bush for the first time. Some independent voters have swung to his side, and Mr. Gore increased his support among Democrats to levels that are traditional, suggesting that the party faithful may have come home. He has also strengthened his ratings as a convincing leader, whereas before voters rated Mr. Bush more highly on leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has also had some success in switching the campaign focus to budget issues and away from the personality terrain that favors Mr. Bush.  The vice president has done an effective job in attacking the Bush tax cut as a giveaway to the wealthy. Last week, Mr. Bush trotted out some low- to middle-income taxpayers whose federal tax bills would be cut by as much as three-quarters. But these individual cases do not erase Mr. Gore's basic point that the overall distribution of the Bush plan is toward the most wealthy taxpayers. Mr. Bush's case was not helped by his difficulty in getting his numbers straight.</p>
        <p>The vice president's stands on health, schools and the environment are also more favored by voters. But the Texas governor may still do damage with his charge that under the Democrats, the military has deteriorated -- an echo of the chimerical ''missile gap'' raised by John F. Kennedy in 1960. He also sought to show a statesmanlike side by meeting on Friday with Vicente Fox Quesada, the president-elect of Mexico, and calling for improved ties with Latin America. Mr. Gore had a good response on the military issue, however, noting that military spending had begun declining when Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's running mate, was defense secretary. Wearing his veteran's cap, Mr. Gore noted that he (by implication, unlike Mr. Bush) had volunteered for Vietnam, and he condemned the governor's talk of American weakness as sending a dangerous signal to the world.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign's challenge remains to escape the shadow of President Clinton and the scandals of the last several years. Knowing this, Mr. Bush's strategists are sorting out their options as to how to attack on the character issue. On Mr. Bush's order, the Republicans withdrew a television ad tying Mr. Gore directly to Mr. Clinton's problem with telling the truth. They apparently feared the ad might create a backlash. But Mr. Bush will continue to argue that most Americans want to restore ''honor and dignity'' to the White House by a total change of administration.</p>
        <p>Bush aides also indicate that the governor plans to attack Mr. Gore over the 1996 Democratic fund-raising scandals. That issue came into the news last week when Attorney General Janet Reno decided not to seek appointment of a special prosecutor to investigate Mr. Gore's denials that he had been aware of fund-raising irregularities in that campaign. Ms. Reno's repeated refusal to bring in an independent prosecutor on the fund-raising issue has amounted to a disgraceful dereliction of duty. But as this page said two months ago, installing a special prosecutor at the height of the campaign would disrupt the electoral process. Since Mr. Gore has released all his deposition statements on this matter, voters can decide how to judge him, and Mr. Bush is fully entitled to raise this issue throughout the fall.</p>
        <p>Any presidential election comes down to a complex mix of issues, performance records and personality. But it is still the issues that offer the biggest contrast between these two men. A race decided on what to do with the surplus, how to manage American military strength and on social concerns like the environment, abortion rights, guns, schools and poverty could lay the groundwork for progress, no matter who wins.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
