<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Symphony Helps Its Players Get Work</title>
    <meta content="27VALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greater Bridgeport Symphony</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Musicians to Go (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelly, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DE1731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Symphony Helps Its Players Get Work</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Musicians to Go, founded in 1996 by Greater Bridgeport Symphony flutist Jane Shelly as means to familiarize community with orchestra's musicians and help members earn extra money (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN medieval times, one could always count on a troubadour to stop by the chateau and provide a little music. There were also trouveres, minstrels, and if one were lucky enough to have a kingdom, most likely an in-house ensemble of court musicians.</p>
        <p>But in the 21st century, where does a princess bride go to find music for her nuptials? Where can a king (read: C.E.O.) find up-scale entertainment for his subjects' (read: employees) annual holiday fete?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN medieval times, one could always count on a troubadour to stop by the chateau and provide a little music. There were also trouveres, minstrels, and if one were lucky enough to have a kingdom, most likely an in-house ensemble of court musicians.</p>
        <p>But in the 21st century, where does a princess bride go to find music for her nuptials? Where can a king (read: C.E.O.) find up-scale entertainment for his subjects' (read: employees) annual holiday fete?</p>
        <p>One answer is Musicians to Go, started four years ago by Jane Shelly, principal flutist of the Greater Bridgeport Symphony.</p>
        <p>In 1996, at the time of the orchestra's 50th anniversary, Ms. Shelly said, ''It became apparent that the time had passed when an orchestra could sit in symphony hall, announce a program and the public would show up. We needed to get out in the community and let people know who we are and what we're about.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shelly raised $1,000 in seed money, and in three days' time, she and several other musicians from the orchestra performed in nine venues in and around Bridgeport to get the word out. They also each earned around $100 per day.</p>
        <p>Now anyone who calls the symphony office looking for a chamber group is put in touch with her and she makes all the arrangements. Prices for up to eight musicians range from $75 to $175 per hour per musician. The Greater Bridgeport Symphony takes a small commission.</p>
        <p>''The purpose,'' Ms. Shelley said, ''is to give the musicians ancillary work. It increases the loyalty of the musicians to the symphony. And every time we go out we ask that the name of the symphony be displayed, mentioned or published in a program.''</p>
        <p>A bride-to-be in search of a Baroque trumpet for the processional and recessional, for example, could turn to Musicians to Go.</p>
        <p>''If you don't know somebody or your church organist doesn't, then it's difficult to find music of a high caliber,'' Ms. Shelly said. ''The client is comfortable because the musician is of a certain caliber.''</p>
        <p>Weddings now account for 80 percent of Musicians to Go bookings. In many cases, the brides know they want music but nothing else.</p>
        <p>''I perceive part of my job as guiding a bride or client to appropriate combinations for their event,'' Ms. Shelly said.</p>
        <p>One bride wanted trumpet, violin and cello, ''not your average ensemble,'' she added, and Ms. Shelly convinced the bride to add flute for balance and use the trumpet for going to and from the altar.</p>
        <p>There was one event -- not a wedding -- where the musicians had to pretend they were on a boat: the Titanic. ''A restaurant in Captain's Cove was having a Titanic party,'' Ms. Shelly said. ''They requested the music that was played in the movie as the ship was going down. And they asked that they wear life preservers. I sent a string quintet. Despite trepidations they had a good time.''</p>
        <p>Getting wet is a no-no delineated in the contract. ''I spell out very clearly that our instruments are priceless,'' Ms. Shelly said. ''Many violinists and cellists have to make a choice between owning an instrument and owning a home. Therefore, when we're asked to play outside, they have to protect the instruments from direct sunlight and even one drop of rain or else they have to have us inside.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shelly recalled an event in which she and a harpist were playing outside and it started to rain. ''Mid note, she put the cover over the harp and took it inside. You can't risk ruining a $60,000 instrument.''</p>
        <p>The musicians, who always wear formal attire, are popular at corporate events, having performed at General Electric, Peoples Bank and Chase Manhattan. They are regulars at university and college graduations and special events, as well as performing for elementary and middle school assemblies.</p>
        <p>Mary Elliot Drake, principal bassoonist, has been with the Greater Bridgeport Symphony since the early 1970's. As a musician living in Norwalk, she said she enjoys playing a variety of music, and that the Musicians to Go bookings offer a chance to play chamber music in woodwind trios and quintets. ''I've opened up a bunch of banks,'' she said. Most of her gigs are receptions and parties. At civic events, she said, ''we tend to be background music before the official arrives to cut the ribbon.''</p>
        <p>While she enjoys the extra opportunity to play, Ms. Drake said the money is nice. ''Musicians around here need about 8 or 10 jobs just to keep going,'' she said. ''Most of us don't have the time to do that organization.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shelly said she has never turned down a request. The classically trained musicians play jazz, Dixieland and Broadway show tunes as well as Bach, Beethoven and Brahms.</p>
        <p>''They can have whatever they want, but it's my job to guide them to something that will make them happy,'' Ms. Shelley said.  MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
