<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shut-Out Nigerians Talk Of Leaders With Scorn</title>
    <meta content="27NIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nigeria-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nigeria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDA1031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shut-Out Nigerians Talk Of Leaders With Scorn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>ABUJA, Nigeria, Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>shut-out</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among those standing outside the gates of the hotel where the world's most powerful man had just checked in, anger simmered beneath the hope his visit inspired. President Clinton, soon after his plane had touched down here in the capital of Africa's most populous nation, had been brought to the Nicon Hilton and would soon visit President Olusegun Obasanjo.</p>
        <p>Despite the Nigerian authorities' efforts to clear people from the street outside the hotel's main entrance, a crowd of perhaps a hundred had built up -- out-of-state visitors, displaced street hawkers, the jobless, all ordinary Nigerians struggling to be heard. Even under normal circumstances, few of them would have made it through the gates of the Nicon Hilton, Nigeria's most prestigious hotel, whose rate for a single night would equal many Nigerians' annual earnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among those standing outside the gates of the hotel where the world's most powerful man had just checked in, anger simmered beneath the hope his visit inspired. President Clinton, soon after his plane had touched down here in the capital of Africa's most populous nation, had been brought to the Nicon Hilton and would soon visit President Olusegun Obasanjo.</p>
        <p>Despite the Nigerian authorities' efforts to clear people from the street outside the hotel's main entrance, a crowd of perhaps a hundred had built up -- out-of-state visitors, displaced street hawkers, the jobless, all ordinary Nigerians struggling to be heard. Even under normal circumstances, few of them would have made it through the gates of the Nicon Hilton, Nigeria's most prestigious hotel, whose rate for a single night would equal many Nigerians' annual earnings.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Clinton's visit had turned the hotel into a fortress.</p>
        <p>''We can't go inside -- in my own fatherland!'' said Prince Inyang, a jobless 31-year-old. ''There are Nigerians inside who are having a bash and enjoying themselves. But other Nigerians are suffering. If you see all the Nigerians standing here, you see suffering written on their faces.''</p>
        <p>On a continent seldom visited by American presidents, in a country where the last visit by a sitting American president, Jimmy Carter, is considered a historic event, the hope was that Mr. Clinton would erase all their suffering. The anger was directed at Nigeria's leaders, who the people believed were trying to prevent Mr. Clinton from witnessing their suffering.</p>
        <p>Okoi Bassey, 25, who sells newspapers in street traffic, said he was one of the many peddlers the authorities had tried to chase away from the area in recent days. The police had confiscated about $70 worth of his newspapers, he said angrily.</p>
        <p>''The politicians are the criminals,'' he said. ''We are the ones working with our sweat under the sun all day. We are suffering. Let President Clinton see me.''</p>
        <p>As in most poor corners of the world, there is an exaggerated belief here of what an American president can accomplish. And perhaps the expectations were higher with Mr. Clinton, who is widely loved in Africa.</p>
        <p>Nigerians interviewed said they hoped his visit would help rebuild the country's educational system, rein in the military for good and create business opportunities. Asked what she expected from Mr. Clinton's visit, Fatima Sule said simply: ''He will uphold our young democracy and not let it die. We have been suffering for so long under military regimes. We don't ever want to go back.''</p>
        <p>Of all the wishes, though, one theme united most of them: Nigeria's leaders had ruined the potential of a country that is one of the world's top oil producers and President Clinton would point them in the right direction.</p>
        <p>''All my body is full of joy to see President Clinton come to this Nigeria,'' said Benjamin Akpa, 41, a tailor. ''I want President Clinton to put order in our government. We have had three Senate presidents in one year because they were corrupt. I want President Clinton to tell our legislators that they must be serious about democracy.''</p>
        <p>Emanuel Uzoechi, 44, wanted to warn Mr. Clinton not to trust Nigeria's leaders. ''Nigeria's name is a bad one in the world,'' he said. ''Is it poor people like me who have made it bad? No, it's the people who don't sweat and who steal by signing with their pens. And so he should be careful about canceling our debt.''</p>
        <p>Ema Ayikoye, 23, echoed the sentiment about debt cancellation. Since coming to office 15 months ago, Mr. Obasanjo has made forgiveness of Nigeria's $30 billion debt one of his priorities.</p>
        <p>''How is debt cancellation going to help the poor people?'' Mr. Ayikoye asked. ''Will we see any benefit from it? Or will it simply benefit the people who have already stolen our money?''</p>
        <p>Christopher Odenigbo, 45, had another suggestion: ''President Clinton should tell all the big men in Nigeria to bring 1.1 million naira each,'' he said, mentioning a figure of about $11,000. ''We can take that money and open a small-scale industry.''</p>
        <p>Shortly before noon, police officers came over to clear the crowd in front of the Nicon Hilton's entrance.</p>
        <p>''What a disgrace!'' one man from the crowd shouted.</p>
        <p>''You can see it,'' said Adamu Ibrahim, 30. ''We are the poor. They don't want us to be heard.''</p>
        <p>But the police could only push the crowd a few feet away. A black limousine in a motorcade came out of the entrance, carrying President Clinton to his meeting with President Obasanjo.</p>
        <p>''He waved at us!'' said Sule Alhaji, 54, a man in the crowd. ''He was happy to see us!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
