<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Foot in Two Countries</title>
    <meta content="CHANNE$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Channel Islands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toth, Susan Allen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4D6113EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Foot in Two Countries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN ALLEN TOTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toth, Susan Allen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Allen Toth travel article describes visit to Channel Islands; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT looked like a huge tomb rising from the beach. A gray-brown monolith with a shadowy entrance, it had concrete slopes and a flat roof that had been weathered into smoothness. As my husband, James, and I walked along the peaceful four-mile stretch of sands on St. Ouen's Bay on the island of Jersey, we could not keep our eyes from this monumental bunker or the immense stone-and-concrete wall, curving for miles, to which it was connected.</p>
        <p>On a bright mid-September afternoon, the sun was so warm that it felt like summer. The long, empty beach was alluring. But the monolith and its defensive wall -- part of the vast Nazi fortifications that survive in the Channel Islands -- were chilling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT looked like a huge tomb rising from the beach. A gray-brown monolith with a shadowy entrance, it had concrete slopes and a flat roof that had been weathered into smoothness. As my husband, James, and I walked along the peaceful four-mile stretch of sands on St. Ouen's Bay on the island of Jersey, we could not keep our eyes from this monumental bunker or the immense stone-and-concrete wall, curving for miles, to which it was connected.</p>
        <p>On a bright mid-September afternoon, the sun was so warm that it felt like summer. The long, empty beach was alluring. But the monolith and its defensive wall -- part of the vast Nazi fortifications that survive in the Channel Islands -- were chilling.</p>
        <p>After that first afternoon on the beach, our 10 days in the Channel Islands continued to startle us with contrasts. The islands -- Jersey, Guernsey, Alderney, the semifeudal seignory of Sark, Herm and a few private ones -- are part of two worlds. Lying just off the coast of France, they have been dependencies of the British crown since the Norman Conquest in 1066. So although many of the place names are French, English is spoken everywhere. The islands' famously sunny weather is decidedly un-English; their food tempered with French flavors.</p>
        <p>The relationship with Britain is uniquely complex: although subject to certain of its policies, the Channel Islands impose many of their own laws. While Britain has a double-digit value added tax, Jersey and Guernsey have prospered as tax-free shopping zones and tax havens. These two biggest islands are best known by name for their prized purebred cows, which can be seen grazing in fields here and there, and for flowers and produce. But highly populated Jersey (86,000) and Guernsey (59,000) now attract more financiers than farmers.</p>
        <p>Aware of many of these contradictions before arriving, I still sometimes felt a little disoriented, both in time and space, during our 10 days in the islands -- three days on  Jersey and a week on Guernsey. Time seemed eerily fluid. It was often easy to forget that World War II was almost half a century past.</p>
        <p>Early in the war the British decided that it would be prohibitively expensive in both manpower and equipment to defend the islands, and in 1940 Hitler sent in occupying troops and a land army of enslaved workers. The Nazis fortified Jersey and Guernsey with an armor plate of concrete; Alderney became an infamous concentration camp. For five years the islanders who had chosen not to evacuate lived under an increasingly grim occupation.</p>
        <p>Now, although the Channel Islands contain many examples of historic architecture, including neolithic tombs, medieval through Napoleonic forts, castles and manors from many centuries, the Nazi heritage dominates the coastline. Concrete-and-stone seawalls, deserted bunkers, ominous gun emplacements, slit-eyed observation towers and other fortifications often look so intact that it seems soldiers could man them once again. But, somewhat disconcertingly, they have become tourist attractions.</p>
        <p>In Guernsey's German Occupation Museum, we had a glimpse of those harsh years. Yellowing notices dictated orders for commandeered transport and executions of alleged traitors and spies. Showcases displayed not only German weapons, military equipment and incongruous band instruments but also relics of civilian life, such as the substitute foods, like carrageen moss used for making jelly, scraped together by the increasingly hard-pressed islanders.</p>
        <p>A short walk from our rented cottage in Guernsey along quiet wooded lanes took us to the almost hidden German Underground Hospital, carved out of the island's rock in a series of deep tunnels. Peering through the grilled entrance one early evening, I could see what looked like peeling whitewashed walls, stretching into a receding darkness. Tending to claustrophobia, I did not return. Visiting friends did tour the Guernsey hospital (Jersey has one too) and reported oozing mildew and a sense of desolation.</p>
        <p>If concrete bunkers lurk in the background, however, they do not unduly darken Jersey and Guernsey. After our walk on the beach at St. Ouen, we spent the rest of our few days on Jersey among greenery, flowers and tranquil ocean scenery, including a languid beach walk near Orgeuil Castle in Gorey. Like most visitors, we headed to the island's best-known attraction, Gerald Durrell's Jersey Zoo, whose parklike setting is home to about 100 species of rare and endangered animals -- among them the Madagascar aye-aye, the Andean bear and the Sumatran orangutan. Durrell, who died in 1995, began the zoo as a breeding center, and it now functions also as an international training school. But despite its serious purpose, the place has a delightful holiday air.</p>
        <p>The zoo's luxuriant gardens made us want to visit the Jersey Flower Center, home of Flying Flowers, one of the largest mail-order floral companies in the world. This was not a simple expedition. Driving anywhere on either Jersey or Guernsey, we quickly found, was not easy. Detailed maps are almost impossible to find. Granite-walled narrow roads, mostly poorly marked, twine and intersect, and almost all of them are filled with whizzing traffic. Pulling over is out of the question. Despite years of practice on Britain's most challenging roads, we found our hours behind the wheel in the Channel Islands often unnerving.</p>
        <p>After several false turns, we did end up at the Flower Center, which was having a quiet day. We strolled past a huge gift shop and cafe, through greenhouses filled with budding carnations, and around the topiary-studded outdoor gardens. In the midst of this commercial complex was a wall hung with photographs and somber information about the many young men who had tried to escape from Jersey during World War II. Few survived. This moving display, created in 1995 for the 50th anniversary of the liberation, did not seem at all out of place; here, as elsewhere, the war is part of living memory.</p>
        <p>Braving the roads again, we spun off to the Eric Young Orchid Foundation, hidden among country lanes. The collection was the generous public bequest of its founder, a passionate breeder of orchids. Its indoor enclosures were landscaped with waterfall, ponds, moss-covered tree trunks, vines and ferns, all a vibrant backdrop for dazzling multicolored orchids hanging almost in front of our noses. (The foundation closed for renovation just after Easter, and is scheduled to reopen early next year.)</p>
        <p>Even at the end of the day, we were surrounded by flowers. Our country-house hotel, Greenhills, nestled among gardens glowing with pink, coral and scarlet begonias, impatiens, geraniums and roses. Taking a dip in the outdoor pool, I felt as if I were dabbling in a paradisaical tropical lagoon. Our smallish bedroom, alas, was less appealing: dark, stuffy, and noisy from a farm road that ran three feet from our ground-floor window.</p>
        <p>Our 15-minute flight to Guernsey the next morning was a mini-adventure of its own. Aurigny Airlines, based on Alderney, is known for its distinctive cigar-shaped planes, with interiors so narrow that they have no aisles. Instead, 13 passengers climb aboard through several exterior flaps as each is called, one by one, presumably so that the plane will not become unbalanced and tip over. Once seated, I enjoyed the bird's-eye view of ocean and islands, but I did not breathe too heavily nor did I lean unduly to the right or left.</p>
        <p>Settling into our airy country apartment on Guernsey, we found ourselves back among flowers. Our sitting room opened onto a sunny private patio, sunk into a hilly lawn and edged by orange geraniums, nasturtiums and blue lobelia. La Cachette, our tastefully decorated two-bedroom unit, was one of three carved out of a 17th-century granite farmhouse; it was a welcome haven during our busy week.</p>
        <p>Since Guernsey's roads were as crammed with traffic as Jersey's, we experimented with using the public buses. La Cachette was only a short walk from a bus stop into the main town, St. Peter Port. Sometimes, however, the minisized buses were too full to stop, which meant a long wait for the next one.</p>
        <p>This combination of rural peace and urban congestion seemed characteristic of both islands. Handsome houses, many of them grand villas, lined the roads, protected from traffic (and public view) by high stone walls. Sometimes a gap between houses revealed an open field, often with a few Jersey or Guernsey cows or horses. Greenhouses gave way  to more houses, perhaps a hotel,  then another small field, and more houses. It was hard to know where town ended and country began.</p>
        <p>One bus excursion remains joltingly clear in my mind. Having read about a ''sightseeing coastal tour'' of Guernsey, we eagerly lined up one afternoon to board an ancient rickety-looking double-decker. For an hour and a half, with no informative commentary, we rumbled around the island's main circular road, often scenic but sometimes inland, reaching a top speed of perhaps 15 miles an hour. When we finally stopped for refreshments, the driver announced that because the rest of the road was so narrow, we were going to turn around and retrace our journey. It was a long afternoon.</p>
        <p>So we returned to our rental car. But we soon discovered that once we parked somewhere, and began to walk, Guernsey unfolded in a series of wonderful panoramas. One excursion took us through St. Peter Port, up and down steep terraced streets, through spacious Candie Gardens, into the medieval town church, and past the bustling stalls of the Market Halls. From the top of the town, we could look over well-kept Regency and Georgian houses down into the harbor, where uncountable brightly painted boats and yachts swung at anchor.</p>
        <p>OUR favorite walks were by the sea. At Jerbourg Point we took a coastal path that began on a cliff, almost dived into the water near a lighthouse, and then meandered among trees along the water. On that sunny Sunday  morning, other walkers sometimes passed, but Guernsey's footpaths were never crowded. A walk from Icart Point took us to a view of the Pea Stacks, a group of rocks that Renoir lovingly painted.</p>
        <p>Refreshments were never hard to find. After our walk at Jerbourg, we stopped for Sunday lunch at the clifftop Idle Rocks Hotel. There, seated on an outdoor terrace with miles of sunlit ocean in front of us, we basked and dined. James managed an English roast-beef dinner with two kinds of potatoes, rutabaga puree, buttered cabbage, watercress and Yorkshire pudding; I decided on a vaguely Gallic ''roast vegetable stack,'' topped with broiled goat cheese. Both plates, we agreed, were far better prepared and presented than the usual English pub fare. After sharing an apple strudel with custard for dessert, we regarded our bill of about $27, which included drinks, with some amazement.</p>
        <p>Seafood too, we found, was fresh, plentiful, and not expensive. To eat like this, we needed to keep walking. Besides the up-and-down coastal paths, we relished the long flat stretches of empty beach that fringe the western side of Guernsey. At Rocquaine Bay, we crossed a stone causeway at low tide to visit the tiny island of Lihou, where the ruins of a medieval Benedictine priory are being excavated. The firm white sands of Vazon Bay and Cobo Bay lay next to the coastal road; we could park and be striding along the beaches in minutes.</p>
        <p>By mid-September, except for buses, we ran into few crowds anywhere. At Victor Hugo's home, Hauteville House -- where he lived for 14 years during his exile from France, a result of vociferous and eloquent attacks on Louis Napoleon -- I joined a tour of its bravura interiors with only six others. In Saumarez Park, the well-planned Folk Museum, filled with mementoes and reconstructions of earlier days on the islands, was ours alone for an hour. Visiting the 13th-century Sausmarez Manor (one branch of the family dropped the second ''s''), we wandered undisturbed through its Exotic Woodland Garden, an acre and a half of subtropical and temperate plants, along a fascinating sculpture trail. Opened in 1998, it displays nearly 200 contemporary works, all for sale, each set with quirky imagination among foliage and trees, and even in water.</p>
        <p>On our last day, we took the half-hour ferry to Herm, a thinly populated island (60 year-round residents), half a mile wide and a mile and a half long. Carefully developed to preserve its natural beauty, the island has a few clustered restaurants, one small hotel, and a meticulously maintained network of footpaths that lead from one glorious beach to another.</p>
        <p>On Shell Beach, far from any sound of people, I dabbled my feet in the surprisingly warm water while James stretched out in the sun. Later, at lunch, we pondered Herm oysters (a mere $5 for six) and settled on poached salmon salad ($10). Afterward we walked the circuit of the island and tried to fix in our minds the wildflowers along the path and the aquamarine sparkle of the water below. Looking across the sea, I forgot busy roads and packed buses. I did not brood about the German occupation. Instead, as I studied the nearby outlines of Sark and farther away the low rise of Alderney (next time), I thought of lush gardens, long walks, endless beaches and a dining table on a sunlit terrace.</p>
        <p>Amid cows and flowers, echoes of darker days</p>
        <p>Information</p>
        <p>The Channel Islands have excellent tourist information centers.</p>
        <p>JERSEY : Jersey Tourism, Liberation Square, St. Helier, Jersey JE1 1BB; (44-1534) 500-777, fax (44-1534) 500-899; www.jersey.com.</p>
        <p>GUERNSEY : States of Guernsey Tourist Board, Post Office Box 23, St. Peter Port, Guernsey GY1 3AN; (44-1481) 723-552; fax (44-1481) 714-951; www.tourism.guernsey.net.</p>
        <p>Ferries run every hour between 8:30 a.m. and 5:30 p.m. in high season from St. Peter Port to Herm Island. The journey is 20 to 30 minutes, the round-trip fare about $11. Prices are reckoned at 66 pence to the dollar. Further information about Herm is available from the Guernsey Tourist Board or from the family that owns the island, Adrian and Pennie Heyworth, at (44-1481) 722-377.</p>
        <p>Lodging</p>
        <p>JERSEY : Jersey has a free brochure listing accommodations, from modest bed-and-breakfasts to self-catering to luxury hotels. We stayed at the Greenhills Country Hotel, St. Peter's Valley, Jersey JE3 7EL, (44-1534) 481-042; fax (44-1534) 485-322. Bed and breakfast for two, $186; half-board for two, $238. (Rooms vary widely; be sure to ask about light, size and a quiet location.)</p>
        <p>GUERNSEY : Our self-catering apartment, like a private cottage, was one of three at a house called La Pompe, on the Ruette de la Pompe in the hamlet of Les Mouilpieds, St. Martin, Guernsey GY4 6TJ; (44-1481) 239-096, fax (44-1481) 237-079. Our immaculate, brightly furnished two-bedroom, two-bath apartment costs $882 a week for four, $614 for two in mid-September, including linen, towels and a welcome food pack.</p>
        <p>The Idle Rocks Hotel at Jerbourg Point, St. Martin, open from Jan. 1 to Dec. 23, offers rooms with breakfast from about $30 a person (standard room, in winter) to about $126 a person (balcony and sea view, in summer); (44-1481) 237-711; fax (44-1481) 235-592.</p>
        <p>Restaurants</p>
        <p>JERSEY : We liked the simple Beach Cafe on Bonne Nuit Bay, where we ate fresh lobster salad ($10) at an outdoor picnic table.</p>
        <p>For fancier cooking, try the charming Village Bistro in Gorey. A typical set lunch at $21 might include, among several choices, smoked salmon salad with herb creme fraiche; escalope of pork with woodland mushroom risotto; roasted hazelnut and cocoa pavlova with apricot compote and vanilla ice cream. Reservations essential: (44-1534) 853-429. Open for dinner Tuesday through Sunday and lunch Wednesday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>GUERNSEY : The Absolute End Seafood Restaurant, the Longstore, St. Peter Port, (44-1481) 723-822, offers a three-course set lunch for about $18. Our meal included a delicious lobster bisque, baked plaice and Chef's Meringue, a towering confection of ice cream, cream and chocolate sauce.</p>
        <p>Sunday lunch at the Idle Rocks Hotel (see above) offers a special menu for as little as $8 a person.</p>
        <p>We had well-cooked fish, but very poor service, at the well-known and expensive Le Nautique, (44-1481) 721-714, Quay Steps, in the heart of St. Peter Port: light lunch for two, with wine, about $75.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>JERSEY : The Jersey Zoo at Les Augres Manor, Trinity, (44-1534) 860-000 is open all year. from 9:30 a.m. to 6 p.m., or until dusk in winter. Admission $12 adults, $9.75 seniors, $8 children.</p>
        <p>The Eric Young Orchid Foundation, Victoria Village, Trinity, (44-1534 861-963, is undergoing renovations, and is scheduled to reopen early next year. When it does, it will be open all year but only on Thursday, Friday and Saturday from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Admission for adults is about $4; seniors $2.25.</p>
        <p>The Jersey Flower Center, Retreat Farm, St. Lawrence, is open daily from March 29 to Oct. 29, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., with free admission; (44-1534) 865-665.</p>
        <p>GUERNSEY : The German Occupation Museum, (44-1481) 238-205, near the airport behind the Forest Church, is open daily between April and October from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., November through March, Tuesday to Sunday 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. Admission about $4; children about $2.</p>
        <p>The Folk Museum at Saumarez Park, Castel, (44-1481) 255-384, is open from mid-March through October, from 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission, $3.75; children and students $1.50.</p>
        <p>Sausmarez Manor Exotic Woodland Garden, with its sculpture park, is part of the grounds of Sausmarez Manor, St. Martin; (44-1481) 235-571. and is open daily from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. The house is open for limited tours from April to October. Admission to the grounds is free, $2.50 for the garden and sculpture park.</p>
        <p>SUSAN ALLEN TOTH</p>
        <p>SUSAN ALLEN TOTH's most recent book is ''England for All Seasons'' (Ballantine).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SUSAN ALLEN TOTH's most recent book is ''England for All Seasons'' (Ballantine).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
