<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even in Hawaii, Talk Turns to the Failed Ewing Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y27NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD71031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even in Hawaii, Talk Turns to the Failed Ewing Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LAHAINA, Hawaii, Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses reaction of NBA players to failed trade of Patrick Ewing to Seattle SuperSonics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vin Baker and Allan Houston checked into their hotel rooms tonight, hours before the United States Olympic basketball team met for its first practice in paradise.</p>
        <p>''Our rooms are directly across the hallway from each other,'' Baker said. ''And I kind of looked back at him like: 'This is weird. We might have been doing this the whole season.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vin Baker and Allan Houston checked into their hotel rooms tonight, hours before the United States Olympic basketball team met for its first practice in paradise.</p>
        <p>''Our rooms are directly across the hallway from each other,'' Baker said. ''And I kind of looked back at him like: 'This is weird. We might have been doing this the whole season.' ''</p>
        <p>Houston shrugged and nodded at Baker, the Seattle SuperSonics forward who was minutes away from becoming his teammate earlier this week when a four-team, 13-player trade collapsed. Patrick Ewing stayed with the Knicks, and Baker waited hopelessly for the telephone to ring. The call never came.</p>
        <p>Thousands of miles away, they are still talking about the blockbuster that fizzled.</p>
        <p>The United States team opened its weeklong training camp in Hawaii, and few of the players wanted to talk about their monthlong road to certain Olympic gold in Sydney, Australia. Most of them wanted to talk about Ewing, Baker and what happened to the proposed swap.</p>
        <p>''Weird is the word,'' said Baker, who twisted his left ankle on the first day of practice. ''I don't know how to feel. I really haven't talked to anyone from Seattle or New York. There's no telling what's going on right now. I just feel different. It was the most traumatic week of my life.''</p>
        <p>He was not alone. Houston, who was mentioned as trade bait in a deal that would have also brought Glen Rice to the Knicks, was backing Ewing.</p>
        <p>Paying homage to his teammate by wearing No. 6 -- the number Ewing wore as part of the 1984 and 1992 Olympic teams, Houston wondered aloud why Ewing's detractors could actually believe that the Knicks would be better off without their 38-year-old center.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it was so much in the locker room as being appreciated outside the locker room,'' Houston said. ''A lot of people would have been eating their words if it happened. They would have been like: 'Man, we don't have Patrick. What are the Knicks without Patrick?'</p>
        <p>''Let's be realistic: in New York, if you look at Patrick and what he means to New York, on the court you would see something different than how people view Patrick. It shouldn't be like that. They should appreciate what he's done, where he's brought the Knicks. The Garden has been selling out. They go to the championship series almost every year. And he has been the biggest reason since he's been there. That's what should really matter.</p>
        <p>''Am I surprised he's looking to go? No.''</p>
        <p>Alonzo Mourning liberally took shots at all the non-Ewing believers.</p>
        <p>''New York is a very malicious town,'' said Mourning, Ewing's best friend and on-court nemesis. ''Especially the media. And it's all about, 'What have you done for me lately?' Unfortunately, there hasn't been a lot of loyalty toward Patrick at all. It's disappointing to think that they wouldn't give that man his due. He's carried that organization for 15 years.''</p>
        <p>Mourning, the star center for the Miami Heat, added: ''I was happy they were getting rid of him. It would have given us an edge.''</p>
        <p>Beyond wounding Ewing's and Baker's egos, the trade talk hurt other players' psyches as well. Gary Payton, Baker's teammate in Seattle and on the Olympic team, was hurt that the Sonics did not tell him of the deal until minutes before it was about to be consummated.</p>
        <p>''At least try to tell me you're trading my best friend,'' Payton said. ''You try to call me 10 minutes before you make an announcement. I'm just like: 'I'm just working for you now. There's no loyalty. This is a business.' It wasn't like: 'Gary, we're going to try to let him know. We consider this his team.' ''</p>
        <p>Payton said he believes that trading for Ewing would not have helped the Sonics as much as keeping the 28-year-old Baker does.</p>
        <p>''It would have been a great trade for the Knicks,'' Payton said. ''Getting Glen Rice and Vin Baker and adding them to Sprewell, Houston and Camby, what can you say? They would play like a playground squad. They would be running and gunning and playing with each other.''</p>
        <p>The team assembled in Hawaii, of course, is an even better group. Vince Carter dunked on one end, while Houston, Jason Kidd and Shareef Abdur-Rahim took short pull-up jump shots on the other end under the watchful eye of the assistant coach Larry Brown. As the players left the Lahaina Civic Center, they were greeted by a small number of fans and an unfamiliar backdrop: swaying palms, the cresting Pacific Ocean and an air-conditioned charter bus.</p>
        <p>''You can take your mind off of it out here,'' Baker said. ''You can just relax and hang out with the best players in the world.''</p>
        <p>Houston added: ''The bottom line is, it didn't happen. Patrick is a Knick. That's really all that matters right now.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
