<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Best, and the Worst, of Times</title>
    <meta content="27THEA$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yellen, Sherman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harper, Wally</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Say Yes! (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3D91431F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Best, and the Worst, of Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Sherman Yellen-Wally Harper musical Say Yes! at Berkshire Theater Festival in Stockbridge, Mass; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT stood, and how mightily it stood, for the best of times (the New York World's Fair, 1939/40) right after the worst of times (the Depression, still unfathomably called the Great Depression). Or so some people, mostly wide-eyed children, thought, not knowing that the worst of times were yet to come. In the second year of the Fair, a bomb went off at the British Empire Exhibition. Two police officers were killed. Then the Japanese Pavilion was set afire. The arsonists remembered Pearl Harbor.</p>
        <p>What a daunting notion it is to make an upbeat musical about that World's Fair, the theme park of yesteryear at Flushing Meadow in Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT stood, and how mightily it stood, for the best of times (the New York World's Fair, 1939/40) right after the worst of times (the Depression, still unfathomably called the Great Depression). Or so some people, mostly wide-eyed children, thought, not knowing that the worst of times were yet to come. In the second year of the Fair, a bomb went off at the British Empire Exhibition. Two police officers were killed. Then the Japanese Pavilion was set afire. The arsonists remembered Pearl Harbor.</p>
        <p>What a daunting notion it is to make an upbeat musical about that World's Fair, the theme park of yesteryear at Flushing Meadow in Queens.</p>
        <p>And the title of the new show by Sherman Yellen (all the words, spoken and sung) and Wally Harper (the music), developed at the O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford and now at the Berkshire Theater Festival in Stockbridge, Mass., says it all. Or so they think.</p>
        <p>That title is ''Say Yes!'' and that says it about the myth, now the legend, the family fun, the good times. The 1,200-acre fair had no less than 36 amusement areas, from Billy Rose's Aquacade, in an amphitheater of its own, to an enchanted forest and, yes, a military encampment.</p>
        <p>And there was one site named Living Magazine Covers. Presumably with that in mind, Mr. Yellen -- who has written about his obsession with collectibles and memorabilia that bring back the Fair -- frames the musical with the cover of Life, which covered New York at work and at play, in the words of one of Mr. Yellen's lyrics. Life appears as an intended metaphor for life. The concept, for whatever it may have been worth is, well, forgotten.</p>
        <p>It's not that the show's creators are obliged to dwell on the dark side or to create a ''Grand Hotel'' or ''Cabaret'' musical of the ominous. If the cockeyed optimistic is their vision, how nice. And how nice it would be to welcome a glittering musical evocative of the Starlight Roof (one of the show's purported settings) and Fred and Ginger. Or at least of the gargantuan World's Fair itself, a financial disaster though it represented the beginning and the end of an era (if an era can be said to last two years).</p>
        <p>But a discombobulated musical with a dopey, desperate plot and routine songs is all there is, and just what it has to do with the World's Fair, except for a reference here (the Kodak Pavilion) and a song there (''This World's Fair'') many people might like to know.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yellen has concocted a standard-issue rich boy falls for working-class girl tall tale and fattened it with complications, complications, complications.</p>
        <p>The rich boy, for a time, is Barnaby. He will be disinherited if he doesn't marry a debutante. The Baroness, who is penniless -- the Depression hit her very late -- sets her airhead daughter, Gloria, out to nab Barnaby. But Gloria loves Hurricane Murphy, a penniless lug. And Barnaby, who has a penchant for philanthropy, loves a Life reporter, Lenore, who makes statements of social significance. Then there is her very charitable father, the neighborhood druggist, and her wiseacre brother, and it's time to yell, Stop!</p>
        <p>Except there is Linda Thorson as the bad manipulative Baroness, who takes a stranglehold on crushing  dumbness and orchestrates it her way. This show doesn't begin until the bad lady says so. When the elegant Ms. Thorson chooses to play the forlorn mother who thought she raised her daughter properly by sending her to all the best stores, you will see a grasping diva ready for the kill, in a killer performance.</p>
        <p>Christianne Tisdale (Lenore) and J. Robert Spencer (Barnaby) are affable as the honest sweethearts, with integrity intact, as well as a real sense of screwball comedy, in a ludicrously staged duet, ''The Future Is You.'' But stylish performers cannot fix a toneless musical. You have seen it all before, only not advertised as ''The World's Fair Musical.''</p>
        <p>''Say Yes!'' Berkshire Theater Festival, Stockbridge, Mass. (413) 298-5576. Performances through Saturday.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
