<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Water (and Save Room for Dessert)</title>
    <meta content="27DINE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beacon Stamford (Stamford, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD61631F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Water (and Save Room for Dessert)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Beacon Stamford restaurant in Stamford, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT a difference two weeks can make in a restaurant's development, as we discovered at Beacon Stamford, a new restaurant on the water in Stamford. Our first visit was not encouraging. Exhausting waits between courses, dishes that didn't match menu descriptions, a tray of water glasses spilled over one guest, and other missteps led us to conclude that this new venture wasn't ready for prime time.</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, a knowledgeable waiter got everything right, and the food was almost flawless. Obviously it takes time to iron out the wrinkles, even for an experienced chef-restaurateur like Waldy Malouf (formerly at the Rainbow Room).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT a difference two weeks can make in a restaurant's development, as we discovered at Beacon Stamford, a new restaurant on the water in Stamford. Our first visit was not encouraging. Exhausting waits between courses, dishes that didn't match menu descriptions, a tray of water glasses spilled over one guest, and other missteps led us to conclude that this new venture wasn't ready for prime time.</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, a knowledgeable waiter got everything right, and the food was almost flawless. Obviously it takes time to iron out the wrinkles, even for an experienced chef-restaurateur like Waldy Malouf (formerly at the Rainbow Room).</p>
        <p>We began with three types of bread (best: grilled sourdough, slightly charred, painted with olive oil), followed by wood-roasted oysters (plump and barely cooked, as we prefer them) in their shells in a heavenly shallot broth, and risotto of shrimp and herbs (creamy, succulent, piqued by fresh basil, mint, parsley and tarragon). A sizzling casserole of creamy baked penne with three cheeses (Gruyere, Roquefort, Parmesan) was nursery food with herbed sophistication.</p>
        <p>Our parade of delicious entrees was led by herb-grilled salmon in a horseradish bread sauce, the best, most delicate salmon we have had in ages, enlivened by its parsley-mint-tarragon-chervil crusting. Other stand-outs were grilled calf's liver (pink as requested) with apple-smoked bacon, vermouth and onions; suckling pig (extraordinarily tender meat and ribs, rubbed with a tangy bitter chocolate-and-spice mix) with grilled apple; and spit-roasted Long Island duck (crisp mahogany skin, moist, smoky meat) with grilled scallions and an arugula-orange salad.</p>
        <p>Our entrees came with a blistering hot casserole of delicious grilled and roasted vegetables (carrots, yellow tomatoes, eggplant, zucchini). Extra sides that dazzled were Beacon gratin potatoes (tickled by Gruyere, Parmesan, thyme, shallots and mint) and simple roasted asparagus.</p>
        <p>Beacon's few misses were mostly from menu misnomers leading to unrealized expectations.</p>
        <p>Shiitake mushroom and crabmeat salad was really crabmeat salad (sparklingly fresh) with just a few mushroom slivers. Grilled seafood open ravioli consisted of sheets of wide pasta floating in a broth with scallops and a few fish shards. Why call it ravioli and raise false expectations? Wood-roasted peaches and blueberries, with a sub-head ''vanilla cake and pan juices'' turned out to be a cake with blueberry filling and a solitary peach slice on top.</p>
        <p>A more serious mishap was the wood-roasted trout, which was scorched ebony outside. The white flesh inside was so dry even a sauce couldn't have helped.</p>
        <p>A truly memorable dessert was toasted almond honey souffle with caramel-cognac ice cream and caramel-cognac sauce. When the oven-hot souffle arrived, the ice cream and sauce were poked into its center. The alternating hot and cold taste sensations were tantalizing.</p>
        <p>Nothing could top that, but several other desserts came close: chocolate chocolate chip souffle with dark chocolate ice cream and sauce; caramelized apple pancake with cognac ice cream; a trio of house-made sorbets (the plum was especially intense); and chocolate angel food cake with fresh blackberries and whipped mascarpone.</p>
        <p>The mother dessert of all, super Beacon Blondie, was a  3/4-liter glass globe filled with two scoops of vanilla ice cream, thick hot fudge sauce, whipped cream, pecan brittle and wavy white chocolate strips, a $14 number intended for two.</p>
        <p>Dinner for two, three courses each, came to $88, before tax, tip or drinks. A medium-size, well-chosen, eclectic wine list begins at $22 a bottle.</p>
        <p>In a prime location overlooking a marina, Beacon Stamford has created a sleek new environment featuring sizzling-from-the-grill cuisine. And it only gets better.</p>
        <p>Beacon Stamford  183 Harbor Drive, Stamford  (203) 327-4600</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Lively tri-level dining room. Noisy at peak hours.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Friendly, but inconsistent.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Roasted oysters, filet mignon steak tartare, lobster soup, arugula salad, penne with three cheeses, risotto of shrimp and herbs, herb-grilled salmon, duck, suckling pig, grilled lamb chops, roasted veal chop, grilled calf's liver, Beacon gratin potatoes, toasted almond-honey souffle.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $12-$18, dinner entrees $16-$29.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Noon-2:30 p.m. Friday only, 5:30-10 p.m. Monday-Thursday, 5:30-11 p.m. Friday-Saturday, 5-9 p.m. Sunday.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.</p>
        <p>ACCESS -- Elevator accessed from parking lot, seven steps at entrance.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
