<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Invitation to a Beheading</title>
    <meta content="27WEBERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Eugen (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayer, Arno J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Furies, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0D9153EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Invitation to a Beheading</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eugen Weber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Eugen (Prof)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eugen Weber reviews book The Furies: Violence and Terror in the French and Russian Revolutions by Arno J Mayer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE FURIES</p>
        <p>Violence and Terror in the</p>
        <p>French and Russian Revolutions.</p>
        <p>By Arno J. Mayer.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 716 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE FURIES</p>
        <p>Violence and Terror in the</p>
        <p>French and Russian Revolutions.</p>
        <p>By Arno J. Mayer.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 716 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $35.</p>
        <p>All history is contemporary history, reflecting current questions, engaged in topical debates. Arno J. Mayer's hefty opus, ''The Furies,'' addresses chapters of a past still very much a part of our present and convulsions that continue to polarize and stir emotions -- not least the author's own. In his preface, Mayer refers disdainfully to ''ex-Communist renegades'' and ''ultraconservative historians'' who fault the French and Russian Revolutions for ''all the purgatorial fires of the 20th century.'' Revolution, Clemenceau once said, ''is all of one piece.'' You have to take the good with the bad. Mayer agrees. His revolutionary glass is half full or better. Still, he feels the need to explain how easily, how naturally, revolutions skid from hope to horror.</p>
        <p>Mayer traces the road from reform to rage and terror, one of menace and fear, vengeance and countervengeance, exhilaration, self-delusion and mutual carnage. He has wise things to say about the blending of traditional enmities and new war cries, about the clash between urban imperialism and rural distrust, about the satisfaction of butchering familiar enemies rather than complete strangers, about the rise of informing as a civic virtue. He points out the link between revolution and foreign war. He reminds us that both France and Russia were more than four-fifths rural on the eve of their revolutions, fair warning to those who attribute the French Revolution to Voltaire and Rousseau, or the Russian to Marx.</p>
        <p>There are many ways to read this long, rich and idiosyncratic book. As Mayer warns, objective and value-free study of the subject is impossible. So, throwing objectivity to the winds, I find it hard not to conclude that in both France and Russia movements for reform as well as revolts against hard times and unbearable conditions were hijacked by small groups of true believers determined to precipitate a radically new social and political order. Revolting against orthodoxy and oppression, both revolutions introduced orthodoxies and oppressions far worse than those that they rejected. Both attempted to build liberty upon heaps of corpses, stability on intimidation and fear, fraternity on systematic terror.</p>
        <p>In Mayer's view, the furies of revolution are ''fueled above all by the resistance of the forces and ideas opposed to it'' -- just as, presumably, the wrath of a mugger is kindled by his intended victim. Mayer, of course, is more discriminating than that. He is more disposed to empathy than to excoriation: that's the historian's way. The trouble with his empathy is that it sometimes turns his explanations into exculpations, by presenting aggression as defensive -- which it sometimes was -- and by treating victimizers as victims of circumstance.</p>
        <p>This becomes striking when he deals with Stalin's Soviet Union. ''It is difficult if not impossible,'' Mayer tells us, to ''equate Stalin and Hitler,'' and he quite sensibly points out that demonization of the Soviet leader hinders critical study. But critical study need not entail rationalization of monstrous policies. Soviet pots were as black as Nazi kettles. Indeed, the millions dehumanized and murdered by Stalin were more numerous than Hitler's victims. ''Leaving aside the human costs,'' Mayer writes, ''the economic achievements of the first five-year plan were astonishing.'' But the human costs were astonishing, too. How could they be left aside?</p>
        <p>It is in this spirit that ex-Communists become ''renegades'' -- a term that may simply denote rejection of party and principles they found unsatisfactory, but that is more commonly used in the pejorative sense of deserter or turncoat. ''People's democracies,'' meanwhile, are referred to without qualification. What democracies? Which people's? And while it's true that ''counterrevolution was not innocent,'' it is far from clear that ''without it there would have been no Furies.'' In Mayer's den of fear, however, there are many mansions; and the pressures said to drive revolution toward terror extend liberally to foreign threat, refusal to knuckle under to unreasonable demands, even failure to show enthusiasm at the right moment.</p>
        <p>More generally, the grand sweep of Mayer's argument glides over particulars and shortchanges crucial details. Personalities, for example, were central to both the French and Russian Revolutions, since those who presided over terror navigated in narrow circles where ideological debate often masked more personal antipathies and ambitions. We know too little about such matters; but the least we can do is indicate that they count. Inexperience in public affairs, which Mayer mentions once in passing, was another key ingredient, especially in France. The best-known representatives of the Terror were too young not to be ham-handed. Robespierre died at 36, Danton at 35, Saint-Just at 27, not a moment too soon.</p>
        <p>In his preface, Mayer suggests an analogy between the revolutionary furies of the modern age and those of Aeschylus' Greece, which leads a wonderfully expressive title into untenable territory. Mayer's ''Furies'' are the raging Erinyes, who emerge from darkest hell with snakes in their hair, whips and torches in their hands, to spur retribution. They are, he writes, ''entwined with an endless cycle of spiraling violence . . . characteristic of moments of rupture and (re)foundation.'' But, Mayer goes on, the Furies can also be Eumenides, the ''Kindly Ones'' as the Athenians called them, who represent the ''difficult transition from a crescendo to a diminuendo of violence.'' In fact, ''Eumenides'' was an antonym intended to flatter the wrathful Erinyes and thus avoid their ire. Be that as it may, Mayer's metaphor better fits the French experience, which laid the grounds for a secular democracy, than it does the feudal kleptocracy of post-Communist Russia.</p>
        <p>Both revolutions were driven by demons or deities that surged from the lower depths of hell or society to torture their victims and to drive them mad. But Aeschylus' Eumenides as much as the Erinyes were there to protect family, society and the world at large against anarchy, to punish crimes that disturbed social order and to hold in check the hubris that in making men forget that they were mortal, encouraged them to challenge order and the gods. Hubris was much in evidence after 1789 and after 1917. But the Erinyes were tamed in the former case; in the latter, murder remains unpunished, crime unavenged. Perhaps the revolutionaries were right, and old deities really have run out of steam. The demons, meanwhile, rage on.</p>
        <p>Eugen Weber is a professor of history at the University of California, Los Angeles. His latest book is ''Apocalypses, Prophecies, Cults and Millennial Beliefs Through the Ages.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eugen Weber is a professor of history at the University of California, Los Angeles. His latest book is ''Apocalypses, Prophecies, Cults and Millennial Beliefs Through the Ages.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
