<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Times Roll Along At Hotels And Casinos</title>
    <meta content="27INSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salomon Smith Barney Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rietbrock, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDB1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Times Roll Along At Hotels And Casinos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenneth N Gilpin Market Insight column contains interview with Salomon Smith Barney lodging and gaming research analyst, Michael Rietbrock, regarding economic future of hotel and casino industries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE great advantage of a hotel,'' George Bernard Shaw once observed, ''is that it's a refuge from home life.''</p>
        <p>With the economy booming, hoteliers are entertaining lots of refugees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE great advantage of a hotel,'' George Bernard Shaw once observed, ''is that it's a refuge from home life.''</p>
        <p>With the economy booming, hoteliers are entertaining lots of refugees.</p>
        <p>Wall Street has noticed. For the first seven months of the year, an index of 20 hotel operators compiled by Salomon Smith Barney was up 18.5 percent, drubbing the Standard &amp; Poor's 500, which was down 2.6 percent in the same period.</p>
        <p>And it looks as if the good times will keep rolling, because business travel picks up in early fall.</p>
        <p>Michael Rietbrock, head of lodging and gaming research at Salomon Smith Barney, took time last week to discussed the conditions in his segment of the travel industry. Following are excerpts from the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. Retailing stocks have been weak recently, largely on fears that the economy will slow. Do you see any signs of a slowdown coming to gambling and lodging stocks?</p>
        <p>A. The stocks have been strong performers this year, but off of very depressed levels. Most of these stocks, for example, are well below their 1999 highs.</p>
        <p>And the outlook remains extremely strong. The fundamentals are better than they were last year, and earnings are 25 percent higher, on average.</p>
        <p>Q. How does assessing the lodging industry compare with forecasting the overall economy?</p>
        <p>A. This is the easiest business in the world to look at.</p>
        <p>Supply of new hotels grows with new construction, and new construction, which has been high for three years, is showing signs of slowing down. But it is still pretty high.</p>
        <p>And demand for hotel room space is very highly correlated with growth in the gross domestic product.</p>
        <p>Q. This is very much a ''people'' business. How is this labor-intensive industry adapting to the Internet age?</p>
        <p>A. The hotel industry is way behind other travel industries, most notably the airlines, in cutting travel agency fees.</p>
        <p>Everybody is working hard to develop online booking services, and in most cases,  right now online bookings are less than 2 percent of total bookings. Within five years, we could see that percentage rise to 10 percent to 15 percent. That will save the hotel companies a lot of money, and put a lot of pressure on travel agent fees.</p>
        <p>But I don't think it will go much further than that, because the inherent problem with direct booking is that when most people travel they want to book their airline, rental car and hotel together.</p>
        <p>Now, there is a lot of talk about a joint booking portal for the hotel industry, but so far the coordination hasn't been there. The big hotel companies, the Marriotts of the world, don't have a lot of incentive to give smaller brands equal shelf space.</p>
        <p>Q. Is the strong economy helping gambling companies, too?</p>
        <p>A. Business is healthy coast to coast, and that is a function of the economy's strength.</p>
        <p>Still, Las Vegas has surprised everyone. A lot of new casinos were built out there last year, and all that construction has not only been absorbed, but the companies continue to grow their earnings against tough year-over-year comparisons.</p>
        <p>The thing that has been great is Las Vegas's ability to transform itself. It used to be all about gambling. But now it is gambling, entertainment, shopping, great restaurants, golf. It is more like Orlando. That, in turn, has made it a much more acceptable place to hold large conventions.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, Atlantic City continues to grow moderately but steadily, and the riverboat casinos are doing great, mainly because several of those markets have liberalized their boarding policies.</p>
        <p>Q. Which gambling stocks do you like?</p>
        <p>A. We are recommending Park Place Entertainment, which is the old Hilton gaming business. In the last year they bought Caesar's from Starwood and have dominant positions in Las Vegas and Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>We also like Harrah's Entertainment. They have a lot of big properties and have developed the first frequent-gambler card, which tracks gambling patterns and gives management a much better understanding of what gamblers like and don't like.</p>
        <p>And MGM Grand is a neat company, although we recently downgraded it because the stock has gone up a lot. The management team is very shareholder-oriented.</p>
        <p>Q. Any picks among hotel operators?</p>
        <p>A. Our key recommendations are Starwood, Four Seasons and Marriott International.</p>
        <p>Starwood has a lot of exposure to the big urban markets in the United States and has become a pretty successful turnaround.</p>
        <p>We like Four Seasons because of the strength of the upscale market in big cities, and because of its growth internationally.</p>
        <p>The key to Marriott is the brand: it is something like McDonald's.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
