<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show Heralds the Rugged Beauty of Maine</title>
    <meta content="27ART.$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Katonah Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFD91731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show Heralds the Rugged Beauty of Maine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <dateline>KATONAH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D Dominick Lombardi reviews Maine and the Modern spirit exhibit at Katonah Museum of Art; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE current exhibition at the Katonah Museum of Art here, titled ''Maine and the Modern Spirit,'' presents both the familiar and the unexpected. Familiar because there are many expected images that conjure up Maine's harsh and beautiful environment, and unexpected because there are more than a few works that, aside from the sense of contemplation and isolation, have a more universal approach to content.</p>
        <p>Visitors are first greeted by two whimsical sculptures by Bernard Langlais. These works, part of his acrobat dogs series (1977), serve as an excellent introduction to the exhibition's theme. The variety of raw, splintery wood he uses to fabricate his works is similar to the type used by the makers of lobster traps. The subject, acrobatic dogs that balance one atop the other, elicits a sort of absurd and dangerous fun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE current exhibition at the Katonah Museum of Art here, titled ''Maine and the Modern Spirit,'' presents both the familiar and the unexpected. Familiar because there are many expected images that conjure up Maine's harsh and beautiful environment, and unexpected because there are more than a few works that, aside from the sense of contemplation and isolation, have a more universal approach to content.</p>
        <p>Visitors are first greeted by two whimsical sculptures by Bernard Langlais. These works, part of his acrobat dogs series (1977), serve as an excellent introduction to the exhibition's theme. The variety of raw, splintery wood he uses to fabricate his works is similar to the type used by the makers of lobster traps. The subject, acrobatic dogs that balance one atop the other, elicits a sort of absurd and dangerous fun.</p>
        <p>From this introductory point, the exhibition is divided into two groups. The room to the left of the main hall contains works that, for the most part, are from the first half of the 20th century. Here, familiar names like Edward Hopper, George Bellows, Marsden Hartley and Louise Nevelson grace the walls.</p>
        <p>Nevelson's ''Maine Meadows: Old Country Road'' (1931) is the exhibition's most noteworthy work, because it is so different from her formidable, monochromatic sculptures. In ''Maine Meadows,'' Nevelson employs a variety of muddied reds, greens, grays and whites with fanciful lines and a spiraling composition. At close range, the painting appears unevenly thought out, while at the same time, an elusive depth keeps one drawn to it. It's only when you step back as far as the room will allow that a harmony of elements comes to the fore -- houses sway, hilltops pulsate and a road and the landscape heave and recede as stars shine in the daytime sky.</p>
        <p>Hartley's ''Summer-Sea Window No. 1'' (1937) is like a poem. Its forceful scratch lines and delicate brush strokes gently define the objects, while the palette soothes the mind. The odd composition, which is both playful and precise, subtly suggests a face, while inconsistent perspective expands the viewer's thoughts.</p>
        <p>''In a Rowboat'' (1916) by Bellows is the exhibition's most dramatic narrative. Here the painter depicts an actual experience in which he and three others were caught in a storm while in a rowboat. He shows himself rowing, aching for land, as a sudden coastal storm engulfs a nearby mountain. Bellows indicates the formidable wind in his painting with whips of hair, bending trees and unforgiving waves. It is the way the artist creates the sudden change in temperature with heavy cold color and blocked-out sunlight, however, that brings the chill of the experience to the viewer.</p>
        <p>A much quieter time is immortalized in Hopper's ''Rocks and Houses, Ogunquit'' (1914). Here we see what  Hopper is best known for. He is unparalleled when it comes to capturing natural sunlight and atmosphere, and his ability to capture a quiet moment reminds us of the peaceful side of life.</p>
        <p>The other half of the exhibition, focused on the second half of the 20th century, also has big names like Alex Katz and Robert Indiana, but it is the lesser-knowns who more directly define a recent concern for the environment.</p>
        <p>Janice Kasper, who can be loosely described as Georgia O'Keeffe with a cause, makes a very specific reference to her concerns for the clear cutting of trees in Maine's great forests. Two paintings, titled ''Now You See Them'' and ''Now You Don't'' (both 1989), illustrate her concerns. In ''Now You See Them,'' Ms. Kasper paints a stand of leafless, ghost-white trees that make long blue shadows over barren land. In the second canvas, ''Now You Don't,'' the trees are reduced to lifeless stumps. To emphasize the cruelty of this act, she paints the tops of the remaining trunks to look like meat, complete with a central bone and rings of darkening red. The clouds that hover above twist and agonize as if to say there is no point in raining here.</p>
        <p>A pair of paintings by Dennis Pinette take a more general view of the loss of natural landscape. The works depict a fictitious forest fire, which devastates a large expanse of trees and underbrush. In the artist's mind, this symbolizes society's tendency to consume and destroy everything in its path. Mr. Pinette's technique of employing thick, choppy brush strokes and lively color transmits the sounds and textures of a crackling fire, while the sheer energy of the work adds an unexpected beauty.</p>
        <p>Paul Plante helps us see nature's beasts in a new light through his numerous, small-scale oil pastels. In ''Northern Cardinal'' (2000), each image in the painting focuses at close range on the eyes of a different bird, revealing a marked diversity among the same species. There are subtle differences among the dozens of cardinals: the color, the distinct gaze, the tilt of the head. Perhaps he does this so we might understand and appreciate these animals as individual, integral beings and not as occasional sightings.</p>
        <p>''Maine and the Modern Spirit'' will remain at the Katonah Museum of Art through Sept. 24. The number to call for information is (914) 232-9555.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
