<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; The Real Thing</title>
    <meta content="27FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="57" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tomatoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD9113EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; The Real Thing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Reynolds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reynolds, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Reynolds extols virtues of fresh summer tomatoes; recipes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's summer, and our long national tomatomare is over! In the dank, dark 9 1/2 to 10 months when you can't get a decent wolf peach in this town, tomato deprivation leads to a depression of almost Scandinavian proportions. Oh, you can find things called ''vine ripened,'' but that only means that this here bad tomato has been on a vine longer than that there bad tomato.</p>
        <p>The canned kind works for sauces, but science, after years of meddling with the fresh ones, has come up miserably short. I don't care what kind of bathing suit she's wearing, I wouldn't look at an uncanned tomato in months that don't have a July, August or September in them, much less hit on one. Occasionally my lycopene satyriasis weakens during those off months, and a grape or cherry love apple worth downing on the way to the subway materializes, but most wouldn't meet the standards of even the most ravenous hornworm. The ridiculously high prices these antisucculents command at virtually all our ''important'' produce palaces are usurious; sometimes I get so mad wandering the aisles I want to bring in my bat and hit fungoes with it. Those few not rejected as too hard for batting practice -- skins tough as horsehide, meat bland and rubbery, cores the texture of tree bark, juice tasteless and insulting -- are also useless as shot puts: even though you think they'll never die, they do rot after a couple of weeks. I tell you, I'd rather eat a pound of unrinsed leek than a tomato sold in New York between October and July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's summer, and our long national tomatomare is over! In the dank, dark 9 1/2 to 10 months when you can't get a decent wolf peach in this town, tomato deprivation leads to a depression of almost Scandinavian proportions. Oh, you can find things called ''vine ripened,'' but that only means that this here bad tomato has been on a vine longer than that there bad tomato.</p>
        <p>The canned kind works for sauces, but science, after years of meddling with the fresh ones, has come up miserably short. I don't care what kind of bathing suit she's wearing, I wouldn't look at an uncanned tomato in months that don't have a July, August or September in them, much less hit on one. Occasionally my lycopene satyriasis weakens during those off months, and a grape or cherry love apple worth downing on the way to the subway materializes, but most wouldn't meet the standards of even the most ravenous hornworm. The ridiculously high prices these antisucculents command at virtually all our ''important'' produce palaces are usurious; sometimes I get so mad wandering the aisles I want to bring in my bat and hit fungoes with it. Those few not rejected as too hard for batting practice -- skins tough as horsehide, meat bland and rubbery, cores the texture of tree bark, juice tasteless and insulting -- are also useless as shot puts: even though you think they'll never die, they do rot after a couple of weeks. I tell you, I'd rather eat a pound of unrinsed leek than a tomato sold in New York between October and July.</p>
        <p>Producers slip into the frequent American trap of style over substance -- or in this case, shippability over taste. Geneticists and purveyors miss the point when they tart tomatoes up to look ''perfect,'' like too-red Christmas tree ornaments; tomatoes are supposed to look as though they've been in the ring with Evander Holyfield (the best ones have been) -- ridged, misshapen, part ripe and part not yet ready, wounded with skin-cracking so savage it looks like dirt-filled stretch marks.</p>
        <p>But now these beautiful beat-up ragtags are here: heirloom tomatoes cultivated before the introduction of the hybrids in the 1940's. The luscious German Johnsons, the Hugh'ses, Green Zebras, three kinds of Brandywine, all the Stripers, the Yellow Taxis, the orange Tangerines and the tiny sweet Wild Mex, the Cherokees Purple and Chocolate -- a two-and-a-half-month feast!</p>
        <p>Though there are many tomato entrepreneurs during these summer months, none could be as passionate as an ingratiating, self-effacing Ivy Leaguer (''I must be the only Princeton alum who sells tomatoes'') named Tim Stark, who with his wife, Jill, their baby daughters, Gwendolyn and Charlotte, and about 10,000 tomato plants compose Eckerton Hill Farm in Lenhartsville, Pa., not far from where the Amish cavort.</p>
        <p>In 1995, Stark worked as a harried management consultant in New York and spent weekends tending what was then a hobby. ''I'd drive into the city with that Toyota loaded with tomatoes,'' he laughs, pointing at a small, dilapidated truck, ''and go from restaurant to restaurant, saying, 'Here's what I got.' Now they pretty much know who I am.''</p>
        <p>Pretty much? Not only does Stark sell to such heavily starred restaurants as Daniel, Payard, Bouley and Gramercy Tavern, he also is pursued by serious retailers like the Vinegar Factory and Agata &amp; Valentina (Brrring! Wake up, Balducci's) and regularly sells out at the Union Square Green Market (get there early Mondays and Wednesdays before the chefs clean him out).</p>
        <p>''I'm not much of a farmer,'' Stark scolds himself quietly. ''I don't get good volume, except in '96 before the baby was born, when it just rained and rained. I should go for volume, but I don't.'' This is not the bogus confessional of, say, a Barbra Streisand protecting herself from further criticism by insisting that her only flaw is ''I'm a perfectionist'' when in fact her defects run considerably deeper and are far more wide-ranging. No, by corporate-farm standards, Tim Stark does not do well. ''The problem is,'' he says, ''I'm always experimenting. I'll probably lose one or two thousand tomato plants this year.''</p>
        <p>When pressed for the reasons his fruits are in such demand, he shrugs and says: ''I don't know. My soil's clay, and maybe they grow better in clay than in sand. But they're not supposed to. Maybe it's because I've got good drainage. Maybe it's because I use compost -- horse and chicken manure, straw, corncobs -- I get from a nearby mushroom house. See, most farmers use a water-soluble fertilizer. The nitrogen in it pumps up the fruits with water so they look good but taste lousy.''</p>
        <p>Stark is also the first tomato Calvinist I've ever encountered. ''I think tomatoes should suffer,'' he says seriously. ''Most farmers baby their plants. They see a little blight, they rush right over and dump nitrogen or phosphorous on it. I don't. I think tomatoes need to struggle a little to get their roots in.'' Just what this portends for Gwendolyn and Charlotte is unclear, but it sure works for his tomatoes. Or something does. ''I started as a gardener and I'm still a gardener at heart,'' he says. ''But my garden got kind of big.''</p>
        <p>Big for a garden, small for a farm. Some tomato farmers in California and Florida plant as many as 400 acres at a time. Stark's 10, half of which are planted with tomatoes, abut his mother's house, where he grew up and where she still lives. And as Tim shows you around his tomato plants, he might remind you of a slightly older James Dean lovingly diving among his lettuces in ''East of Eden.'' When he sees a plant not doing well, blight near the soil, ''I just can't stand to look at them when they're like that,'' he says dolefully.</p>
        <p>Tim is not exactly organic, but he's not exactly not. He's stricter. ''Organic farmers had very high standards. But when the Department of Agriculture tried to write federal guildelines, they were so influenced by agribusiness, which tried to allow genetically modified seeds and sludge'' -- which includes human waste -- they got about 350,000 letters of protest. It's better now, but they still allow you to use copper-based spraying. I won't touch it. Every year I get set to fill out the applications needed to be certified organic, and every year I just never get around to it.'' It's easy to understand why. Since abandoning his consulting business, he and Jill, a lawyer, work longer hours than ever. He plants, tends and harvests all seedlings by hand. She did, too, until the kids arrived. And his success with tomatoes brought requests from restaurants and retailers to grow microveggies (mostly used for overly precious garnish), which are difficult and time-consuming.</p>
        <p>June and early July, Stark frets, is his period of fear: ''I just don't know what I'm going to get. We had two weeks of wet and overcast weather this spring, then two solid weeks of rain in summer. A lot of blight set in. I didn't know what was going to happen. We usually put out the seedlings in early May, but when the second baby came at the end of April, I had to plant later.'' He wipes a tired eye. ''Yeah, I'll probably burn out,'' he says with a quiet laugh, and he's very convincing.</p>
        <p>Although Stark believes there are good hybrids (When questioned, he took several seconds to answer: ''Well, there's the Carmello. That's pretty good''), I've never had one nearly as good as my own favorite, the heirloom German Johnson out of North Carolina. Philippe Bertineau, the chef at Payard Patisserie and Bistro, who turned me on to Stark, makes a deliciously simple salad with heirlooms -- and a deliciously complex paella-stuffed heirloom for those who crave a midsummer challenge. Lycopenophiles agree on three things: first, if you've got a Really Great tomato, the best way to eat it is to go simple; second, if you put one of these Really Great tomatoes in the refrigerator, there are no indulgences you can earn or buy that will keep you out of hell; and third, if you do it again, it will be worse.</p>
        <p>Tim Stark's Favorite Tomato Recipe  1 Cherokee Purple tomato  1 Aunt Ruby's German Green tomato (''I love the contrasting colors'')  1 slice Cabot's cheddar cheese  1 thin spreading of your favorite mayonnaise (his is Hellman's)  2 slices of undistinguished toast.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the tomatoes thickly. (''I put a lot of tomato in my sandwich.'')</p>
        <p>2. Spread the mayo on the toast</p>
        <p>3. Insert the tomatoes and the cheese between the slices of toast.</p>
        <p>4. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 sandwich.</p>
        <p>My Favorite Tomato Recipe  1 fat, fabulous German Johnson, Brandywine or other Heirloom, ideally one of those noted above*  1 plate.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the tomato.</p>
        <p>2. Put it on a plate.</p>
        <p>3. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>*If the tomato is Great but not Really Great, you might sprinkle a little salt on it or a couple of basil leaves and a thin stream of olive oil.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 serving.</p>
        <p>Philippe Bertineau's Heirloom Tomato Salad With Farm Goat Cheese  1 Cherokee tomato  1 Green Zebra tomato  1 Striped tomato  1 Aunt Ruby's German Green tomato  1 pint mixed baby heirloom tomatoes: cherry, pear and currant  2 shallots, minced  3 tablespoons Spanish extra-virgin olive oil  2 tablespoons sherry vinegar  1 tablespoon balsamic vinegar  Salt and freshly ground white pepper to taste  4 ounces fresh goat cheese, at room temperature  1 bunch basil, leaves washed, stemmed, stacked and finely diced (do not chop roughly or the basil will bruise and turn brown) or 1 bunch chives, minced  Brittany gray sea salt to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Slice each large tomato crosswise into  1/4-inch slices. Arrange each variety of tomato in alternating colors in a circle around a serving platter, then place the baby tomatoes in the center.</p>
        <p>2. Sprinkle the tomatoes with the minced shallots, oil, vinegars, salt and pepper. Marinate the tomatoes 2 minutes, turn over and marinate 2 minutes on the other side.</p>
        <p>3. Crumble the goat cheese on top of the tomatoes and sprinkle the chopped basil. Season with gray sea salt. Wait 10 minutes before serving. (Do not refrigerate.)</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
