<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Pipeline</title>
    <meta content="27COV.$17" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D71431F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Pipeline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MANSNERUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dispute between builders and environmental groups over New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection's proposed Water Quality and Watershed Management Rules, which will, by governing waste water and sewer lines, shape state's housing development over next two decades; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE after another, speakers from local environmental groups, a few of them near tears, told a hearing here this month that the Whitman administration was delivering much of the New Jersey's vulnerable open space to developers.</p>
        <p>Ben Forest of the Monmouth County Friends of Clear Water, describing a county ''ravaged by development pressures,'' said, ''I rarely spend a day on the road without seeing another bank of trees developed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE after another, speakers from local environmental groups, a few of them near tears, told a hearing here this month that the Whitman administration was delivering much of the New Jersey's vulnerable open space to developers.</p>
        <p>Ben Forest of the Monmouth County Friends of Clear Water, describing a county ''ravaged by development pressures,'' said, ''I rarely spend a day on the road without seeing another bank of trees developed.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, state officials faced a room full of builders, who  told them the administration was all but shutting down the housing industry. After the meeting, Bradley N. Haber, the president of the New Jersey Builders Association, said, ''You heard people crying for their lives, the lives of their employees.''</p>
        <p>The subject -- or at least the immediate subject -- of this agonizing is a 400-page document called the Water Quality and Watershed Management Rules. The rules, now in the form of a proposal by the Department of Environmental Protection, regulate sewer and septic service and waste-water discharge; their vocabulary runs to terms like Water Quality Management Plans and Total Maximum Daily Loads.</p>
        <p>But the dispute playing out is mostly about how to distribute the  million new residents that New Jersey is expecting over the next 20 years. Like so many environmental issues in this state, this one evokes a threat that all New Jerseyans recognize and most of them hate: new houses. People can only go where the water goes -- or, more specifically, where the wells, sewer lines and septic tanks go. And with the new rules, the Whitman Administration proposes to contain the centrifugal force of development.</p>
        <p>Even the most disinterested observers, though there are not many, say the water rules will do much to determine the state's landscape. Some of the passion is about drinking water and the rivers, streams and lakes that the state has been obligated to clean up since 1978. But the proposed constraints on where a new Wawa or a row of vacation villas could go lead to fights over other things: the tax structure, property rights, education financing, low-income housing, immigration, socioeconomic segregation. The new scheme is supposed to make development follow the design of the State Development and Redevelopment Plan, which carves the state into  population centers, farming areas, pristine zones and buffers. The idea is to promote development in places already designated for sewer service and choke it off in outlying areas.</p>
        <p>The Whitman administration says the new water rules leave roughly 300,000 acres open to development while responding to clean-water mandates and growing anti-sprawl sentiment. But, as the jarring disconnect between the environmentalists' and the developers' predictions suggests, the rules are open to different readings.</p>
        <p>Under the rules, which apply to all projects approved by local  authorities after July 3, a developer seeking to extend sewer service or install septic systems over a certain size would have to conduct a set of environmental analyses.</p>
        <p>The second level of review is based on the lines drawn in the state plan. In areas designated for development, called Planning Areas 1 and 2, and in smaller ''centers'' around the state, the applicant would only have to meet requirements for the usual environmental permits. But in Areas 3, 4 and 5, which are supposed to have much lower densities, a project would have to satisfy more specific policies set out in the state plan.</p>
        <p>The building and real estate industry says the department would be inclined to deny most applications, sealing off undeveloped land, crowding people into cities they do not want to live in, inflating housing costs and ruining many small builders and property owners. They also contend that of the 300,000 acres that the department says can be developed, most are in fact off-limits because of local zoning, lack of sewage-treatment capacity and other environmental problems.</p>
        <p>Most environmental advocates say that the rules would not apply to most development proposals after the exemptions and grandfather clauses, and that the department would be inclined to approve the others anyway. The result, they argue, would be continued sprawl, huge public expenditures for new infrastructure and an increase in the discharge of polluted water by hundreds of millions of gallons a day.</p>
        <p>Many others say they are perplexed that the face of the state is being mapped out in rules that hardly anyone understands, if they have read them at all.</p>
        <p>Even though the rules emerged from four years of negotiations with interested groups, and even though the Department of Environmental Protection has extended the public comment period by a month, to Oct. 2, the department is still receiving pleas for more time.</p>
        <p>''This will establish limits to the growth of the state of New  Jersey,'' said Jim Sinclair, vice president of the New Jersey Business and Industry Association. ''There are winners and losers in this process. We haven't figured out yet who they are, or whether it's good public policy. We haven't had a public discussion.</p>
        <p>''This governor has done brave things to push forward the whole  question of the state plan and has turned it into a much more action-oriented document than a philosophical discussion. But I think we  should be very much concerned about what the detail is and what we get in the end.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the Legislature could send the proposed rules back for rewriting. More than 70 of the Legislature's 120 members signed a letter to Governor Whitman urging her to strengthen the rules.</p>
        <p>The builders and environmentalists can agree on one point: the  rules accord great discretion to the Department of Environmental Protection. While each side contends that the department will use that discretion to the other's benefit, both complain that the rules lack standards and predictability.</p>
        <p>For the most part, the analyses required for new development are not hydrological studies but assessments of factors like probable population and employment growth in the area, neighboring land uses and estimated water consumption.</p>
        <p>''You can spin it however you want,'' said Nancy Wittenberg, director of environmental affairs for the builders association. ''There's no way to tell from the rule what's approvable and what's not. It makes us nervous.''</p>
        <p>Bill Neil, the director of conservation for the New Jersey Audubon Society, does not disagree. His written comments to the department quote the assertion in a public administration treatise that when regulators are left to carry out vague directives, the result is ''at best a hell of administrative boredom'' and at worst ''a tightly woven fabric of legitimized privilege.''</p>
        <p>While the Audubon Society clearly favors maximum preservation of open space, Mr. Neil said the current proposal ''seems to rely on the threat of expensive and burdensome studies loaded on developers' backs to drive them away'' while allowing the savviest to dodge them.</p>
        <p>And those who worry most about such burdens are small builders. ''My father's been building in New Jersey since the 1950's,'' said Stuart Kramer, who builds about 10 houses a year in Morris County. ''We're a family business. We're not on the New York Stock Exchange. We don't have millions and millions of dollars behind us to go to court every time we go to a subdivision.''</p>
        <p>At the moment, Mr. Kramer's problem is that he bought a 120-acre farm that is zoned for residential development but is in Planning Area 4, designated rural by the state plan. ''I could put 400 cattle on it,'' he said. ''Is that what they want? Can I put a golf course on it? I don't know. Can I wait it out? I hope so.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kramer added that the potential effect on local businesses -- suppliers, lumber yards, delis that serve truck drivers and construction crews -- ''is an interesting thing nobody seems to care about.''</p>
        <p>Many municipal officials do care, although many want to turn away new housing and all of them would like to deflect the heat for saying no to developers. The League of Municipalities opposes the measure because local officials ''are still concerned about the heavy hand of the state,'' said William Dressel, the league's director.</p>
        <p>Moreover, said Lewis Goldshore, a lawyer who is advising the league, ''If they want, for example, an office building or another good ratable where the state says thou shalt not sewer, that's where the rubber meets the road.''</p>
        <p>All complaints are directed, of course, at the governor -- though a spokeswoman, Steffanie Bell, said the apparent impossibility of satisfying everyone ''suggests that this is a good rule.''</p>
        <p>David Pringle of the New Jersey Environmental Federation, a leader in the campaign to tighten the rules, said, ''It's ironic that the governor says we don't want growth anywhere, and now the developers say the governor doesn't want growth anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Everyone agrees that some growth is inevitable, and that each new resident will increase demand for housing -- and thus the cost -- in a state that is already the most densely populated in the nation.  But the cost of that housing, and the cost of minimizing the  environmental damage it does, can be distributed in different ways.</p>
        <p>The builders call for big infusions of public money: $200 million a year for redevelopment in cities and older suburbs, $150 million to correct existing pollution and increased state funds for infrastructure improvements.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates certainly do not oppose state aid, but they argue that if housing and infrastructure costs in countryside settings are pushed up by building constraints, they should not be subsidized by taxpayer-financed investments. As Jeff Tittel, the president of the New Jersey chapter of the Sierra Club, put it, ''Am I going to pay for it, or is the guy in the McMansion going to pay for it?''</p>
        <p>While the builders association protests that the administration would crowd one million additional people into Planning Areas 1 and 2, which make up 27 percent of the state, many others contend that housing them all need not require vast acreage or directing everybody to Newark and Camden.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lawrence of New Jersey Future said her organization had looked at many alternatives to large-lot exurban zoning and building. ''Everybody likes Princeton Borough, right?'' she said. ''If you built other Princeton Boroughs, building at Princeton densities, you could put all of the state's population on 16.5 percent of the land. We could do the same thing at Montclair densities.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lawrence also said that most of the states newcomers are immigrants, who settle in older areas, and that an aging population can be expected to shift from many-bedroomed houses to smaller quarters in more urban places.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Wittenberg of the builders association said she saw no such demand in the cities. 'Theyre talking about building in places where people with children dont go,' she said. 'And then nobody wants poor people,' she added, 'but nobody will talk about it either.'</p>
        <p>Mr. Tittel said builders might run out of demand before they run out of land, given the number of housing units now in the pipeline --- that is, given preliminary approval but yet built. Except for the few that might have received approvals after July 3, none of them are subject to the new water rules.</p>
        <p>Local approvals are not tracked by any state agency [checking; possibly planning commission has a guesstimate], and officials of the builders association say they cannot hazard a guess.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tittel said that just in Hunterdon County, he had counted about 1,500 subdivisions and 500 commercial projects that had been approved since 1992, at least three-quarters of them not yet built.</p>
        <p>John W. Kellogg, the Hunterdon County planning director in Hunterdon County, said the county was already under pressure from continuing commercial development along Route 78 and the new Merrill Lynch complex in Hopewell, Mercer County, just to the south.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellogg said local officials were nervous about water supplies, enough so that at least 10 of the countys 16 had changed their zoning recently to require larger lots. He predicted that states new rules were 'clearly going to put brakes on things, but as to his opinion on them, he said, 'I dont even know what I think.'</p>
        <p>At the environmental protection department in Trenton, the authors and advocates of the rules say they are constantly battling misinformation, although they concede that they lack some important data, like the exact acreage and locations that could be developed under their proposal.</p>
        <p>Robert Tudor, the deputy commissioner who faced the builders along with Lance R. Miller, the director of the watershed program, disputed their assertion that they would be left with little to build on. Mr. Tudor said that to reach its estimate of 300,000 to 400,000 acres, the department took all sewer service areas and subtracted the acres with lines already in place and 'all environmentally sensitive areas, especially wetlands.'</p>
        <p>Department officials also take issue with the claim by some environmental groups that the rule would permit the discharge of an additional 300 million gallons a day of polluted water. The state has less than 200 million gallons a day of unused wastewater-treatment capacity, they say, and even a population increase of 1 million would not require that much.</p>
        <p>The disputes get much more technical than that, but these might be lost amid a political clamor. And even if the new rules survive, they will assure continued local flareups: They provide for public hearings at various stages of the approval process, even before a builders initial conference with planning officials. And, as the attorney for the builders association, Michael Gross, told his audience, ''The public doesnt want development.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
