<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Norman Set for Silent Treatment in Final With Enqvist</title>
    <meta content="27HAML$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hamlet Cup (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norman, Magnus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Enqvist, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DF1131F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Norman Set for Silent Treatment in Final With Enqvist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <dateline>COMMACK, N.Y., Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Magnus Norman and Thomas Enqvist advance to final of Hamlet Cup tennis tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forget the booming serve, the wicked forehand and the brilliant shot selection. For Magnus Norman, one of the toughest parts about defending his Hamlet Cup title Sunday against his good friend and fellow Swede Thomas Enqvist will come during the crossovers.</p>
        <p>''Because he's a friend, sometimes you want to talk at that point, but it's the final, so you can't,'' said Norman, who advanced tonight with a 4-6, 6-4, 7-6 (0) victory over Richard Krajicek of the Netherlands. ''It's always very difficult to play a very good friend.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forget the booming serve, the wicked forehand and the brilliant shot selection. For Magnus Norman, one of the toughest parts about defending his Hamlet Cup title Sunday against his good friend and fellow Swede Thomas Enqvist will come during the crossovers.</p>
        <p>''Because he's a friend, sometimes you want to talk at that point, but it's the final, so you can't,'' said Norman, who advanced tonight with a 4-6, 6-4, 7-6 (0) victory over Richard Krajicek of the Netherlands. ''It's always very difficult to play a very good friend.''</p>
        <p>Laughing, he added, ''Of course, I've never beaten him, so he's got a tremendous advantage.''</p>
        <p>Enqvist, who is seeded third in this preamble to the United States Open and is 4-0 against Norman, has not dropped a set en route to Sunday's final, eliminating Arnaud Clement of France, 7-6 (2), 6-1, earlier today. It will be the third all-Swedish final on the men's tour this year, with Andreas Vinciguerra defeating Magnus Larson in Copenhagen and Norman beating Vinciguerra in Bastad for one of his three ATP titles.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to a tough match,'' said Norman, who beat Alex Corretja in last year's final. ''In my opinion, when Thomas is playing good, he's the best player in the world.''</p>
        <p>Enqvist said of Norman, ''He's had an unbelievable year.''</p>
        <p>While Enqvist made short work of the 22-year-old Clement, Norman struggled early against Krajicek, who used his powerful serve-and-volley game to near perfection as he stormed through the first set. But Norman began turning it around in the second set, catching the 6-foot-5-inch Krajicek flat-footed at the baseline with his powerful forehand several times and coming into the net himself often enough to disrupt Krajicek's rhythm.</p>
        <p>Krajicek did not help himself, either, as his service game began tailing off early in the second set. Norman was quick to take advantage, moving in on Krajicek's second serve and getting a break in the fifth game on a great forehand return.</p>
        <p>Norman then went up in the third set, 3-1, and was serving for the match at 5-4 when Krajicek fought back. He got to break point with a halfcourt volley and broke back for the first time since the last game of the first set when Norman sent a backhand sailing wide.</p>
        <p>Both held serve to force the tie breaker, but after Krajicek opened by blowing an overhead, it was all Norman. Krajicek compounded that with a forehand error, was unable to handle a serve down the middle and double-faulted to fall behind by 0-4.</p>
        <p>''I was feeling I was getting a second chance when I mis-hit the overhead, and it was downhill from there,'' Krajicek said. ''From 2-all in the second set to 3-1 in the third, I was just hanging in there. I'm not unhappy, but I am a little bit disappointed.''</p>
        <p>Enqvist, who had 13 of his 14 aces in the first set against Clement, rallied from 0-3 for the victory, his 41st in singles matches this year against 16 losses.</p>
        <p>''Today's match started a little like yesterday's,'' said Enqvist, who also trailed, 0-3, against Fabrice Santoro on Friday. ''It was a tough first set. But I am confident in the way I am playing, especially with my serve.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
