<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word: Inspiring Speeches; Appeals for Support by Susan, Rudy, Richard, Kelly, Al and George W.</title>
    <meta content="27WORD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bader, Jenny Lyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hawk, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boesch, Rudy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wigglesworth, Kelly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hatch, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4DA1331F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word: Inspiring Speeches; Appeals for Support by Susan, Rudy, Richard, Kelly, Al and George W.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY LYN BADER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bader, Jenny Lyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pleas offered by Susan Hawk, Rudy Boesch, Kelly Wigglesworth and Richard Hatch to stay on the island in the Survivor television show are compared with speeches made by Vice Pres Al Gore. Gov George W Bush, John McCain and Ralph Nader; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE two candidates surveyed their voters and saw a group evenly divided -- loyal stalwarts on each side, swing voters in the middle. Pundits and fans who had followed the race closely had no idea who would win. Even casual observers said it would be neck and neck. The venue was the nerve-racking finale of the CBS hit show ''Survivor,'' in which 16 castaways endured trials, forged alliances and ate bugs in their quest to win a million dollars.</p>
        <p>The evening began with four finalists vying for the prize: Susan Hawk, the truck driver; Rudy Boesch, the ex-Navy Seal; Kelly Wiglesworth, the river guide; Richard Hatch, the corporate trainer. First they had to answer trivia questions about castaways eliminated in earlier episodes. Kelly triumphed, displaying impressive social skills; she knew even the middle names of the children of former cast mates. Susan was ousted, and the remaining islanders had to hold a totem pole for hours until their patience ran out. Kelly won again, showing quiet fortitude and an iron will.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE two candidates surveyed their voters and saw a group evenly divided -- loyal stalwarts on each side, swing voters in the middle. Pundits and fans who had followed the race closely had no idea who would win. Even casual observers said it would be neck and neck. The venue was the nerve-racking finale of the CBS hit show ''Survivor,'' in which 16 castaways endured trials, forged alliances and ate bugs in their quest to win a million dollars.</p>
        <p>The evening began with four finalists vying for the prize: Susan Hawk, the truck driver; Rudy Boesch, the ex-Navy Seal; Kelly Wiglesworth, the river guide; Richard Hatch, the corporate trainer. First they had to answer trivia questions about castaways eliminated in earlier episodes. Kelly triumphed, displaying impressive social skills; she knew even the middle names of the children of former cast mates. Susan was ousted, and the remaining islanders had to hold a totem pole for hours until their patience ran out. Kelly won again, showing quiet fortitude and an iron will.</p>
        <p>But the crucial moment came when the last two, Kelly and Richard, had to present their cases to a jury of their ex-peers. One hopes that the presidential candidates, Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore, were watching and taking notes. Kelly learned that to win an election, dazzling social skills -- or quiet fortitude and an iron will -- are not enough. The winner needs a speech that inspires and empowers the undecided.</p>
        <p>Richard, who won, excelled at defining his candidacy. This year's presidential candidates tried to make similarly effective speeches at their televised conventions, with the added problem of having a larger electorate to persuade -- and many fewer people watching than the CBS audience of 50 million, eclipsed only by the Super Bowl. Comparisons between the candidates and survivors proved irresistible.</p>
        <p>JENNY LYN BADER</p>
        <p>George W. Bush, the Republican candidate, defined himself as an outsider:</p>
        <p>I come from a different place, and it has made me a different leader. In Midland, Tex., where I grew up, the town motto was ''the sky's the limit.'' And we believed it. . . . Neighbors helped each other. . . . This background leaves more than an accent, it leaves an outlook. . . .</p>
        <p>That background may lack the polish of Washington. Then again, I don't have a lot of things that come with Washington. I don't have enemies to fight. I have no stake in the bitter arguments of the last few years. I want to change the tone of Washington to one of civility and respect.</p>
        <p>Kelly said she was no politician. She hoped she had made no enemies and asked her tribe to judge her not on what she had done on the island, but on who she is and how much fun she is to have around.</p>
        <p>Um, I'm not a politician. I didn't come here to campaign for myself. I think we're all adults here. I think we all know that, you know, this is a game and I hope nobody has taken anything personally . . . I hope we're not going to be judged here on how we chose to play the game. I'm hoping what we're going to be judged on -- or I personally will be judged on -- is the person that I am, the conversations that we had, the time we spent together, the things we talked about. You know, with that game we played the other night -- how well did you get to know people . . . I didn't have the conversations I had with you and want to know things about you and share my life with you because I thought I was going to be quizzed on it or it was part of my strategy. It was because we were all here together and I cared to know all of you. . . . [If] we were voting for the sweetest or the nicest or things like that maybe neither of us would be up here. I don't know that the best person is sitting up here. But hopefully, you know, the better person will win.</p>
        <p>Al Gore, concerned that the national election was starting to resemble a high school one, asked constituents to vote not for the more popular guy, but for the one who works the hardest and even makes unpopular decisions.</p>
        <p>I know my own imperfections. I know that sometimes people say I'm too serious, that I talk too much substance and policy. Maybe I've done that tonight.</p>
        <p>But the presidency is more than a popularity contest. It's a day-by-day fight for people. Sometimes, you have to choose to do what's difficult or unpopular. Sometimes, you have to be willing to spend your popularity in order to pick the hard right over the easy wrong. . . .</p>
        <p>I know I won't always be the most exciting politician. But I pledge to you tonight: I will work for you every day and I will never let you down.</p>
        <p>Richard took an even blunter vote-for-me-even-if-you-don't-like-me approach. And he hoped his achievements would be respected, if not beloved.</p>
        <p>I take a little bit of a different approach to it. For me, it's not about you deciding who the best person is. I don't think you really know who I am and probably don't know who Kelly is. My approach to the game was one of strategy from the beginning. Before I even got here, I started to think about what it might take to get through 14 ejections, and it got really complicated. And I couldn't really plan it as well as I thought -- and it certainly didn't turn out to go according to plan. But I certainly had a strategy, and I came to play a game, and I was playing a game. There were a lot of sincere interactions, but no matter how sincere they were I don't think anybody really knows who we are in only 39 days. I think the starts of friendships are certainly things that have happened, but for me instead of who's the better person it is about who played the game better. And I'm hoping you just respect my having approached the game from that perspective from early, early, early on.</p>
        <p>John McCain, an early favorite, endorsed Mr. Bush, honoring a campaign promise. In a letter to his supporters in May, he wrote:</p>
        <p>From the first day of my campaign, I said repeatedly that if I did not win the Republican nomination for president, I would support whoever did. This was a pledge I made when I was at 3 percent in the polls and repeated  again throughout the primaries. And like all the promises I made along the campaign trail, this was one I intended to keep.</p>
        <p>Rudy, a military hero with a reputation for straight talk, was an early favorite in the game. Although he had called Richard names in the past, he voted for him, simply because the two forged an alliance. He explained his vote to Bryant Gumbel in the post-finale reunion.</p>
        <p>We set up an alliance and I gave him my word, and my word is good.</p>
        <p>Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, said he joined the race to critique both the Democrats and Republicans. Announcing his candidacy, he said:</p>
        <p>This is the foundation of our campaign, to focus on active citizenship, to  create fresh political movements that will displace the control of the Democratic and Republican parties, two apparently distinct political entities that feed at the same corporate trough. They are in fact simply the two heads of one political duopoly, the DemRep Party. This duopoly does everything it can to obstruct the beginnings of new parties including raising ballot access barriers, entrenching winner-take-all voting systems, and thwarting participation in debates at election times.</p>
        <p>Susan, the unlikely Ralph Nader of Pulau Tiga, expressed her disdain for both front-runners, with a special animosity reserved for the one with whom she had been closest in the past.</p>
        <p>I plead to the jury tonight to think a little bit about the island that we have been on. This island is pretty much full of only two things, snakes and rats. And in the end, with Mother Nature, we have Richard, the snake, who  knowingly went after prey, and Kelly, who turned into the rat, that ran around like the rats do on this island, trying to run from the snakes. I feel we owe it to the island's spirits that we have learned to come to know to let it be in the end the way Mother Nature intended it to be: for the snake to eat the rat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
