<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Connecticut; Norwalk Is No Longer 'the Hole in the Doughnut'</title>
    <meta content="27WCZO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norwalk (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Eleanor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DC1F3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Connecticut; Norwalk Is No Longer 'the Hole in the Doughnut'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charles, Eleanor</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citywide surge of new construction and conversions of older buildings in Norwalk, Conn, has given city vibrancy it has not experienced in decades; photo; map (In the Region/Connecticut) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A CITYWIDE surge of new construction and conversions of older buildings in Norwalk has given the city a vibrancy it has not experienced in decades. Long overshadowed by fashionable towns around it like Darien, New Canaan, Wilton and Westport, Norwalk chafed under the characterization of ''hole in the doughnut.''</p>
        <p>But today, buoyed by a healthy economy and profiting as an alternative to Stamford's tight real estate market, its buildable land and reusable buildings are at last in development. ''It's great what's happening here,'' said the city's seven-term mayor, Frank J. Esposito. ''Now we are the doughnut, not the hole.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A CITYWIDE surge of new construction and conversions of older buildings in Norwalk has given the city a vibrancy it has not experienced in decades. Long overshadowed by fashionable towns around it like Darien, New Canaan, Wilton and Westport, Norwalk chafed under the characterization of ''hole in the doughnut.''</p>
        <p>But today, buoyed by a healthy economy and profiting as an alternative to Stamford's tight real estate market, its buildable land and reusable buildings are at last in development. ''It's great what's happening here,'' said the city's seven-term mayor, Frank J. Esposito. ''Now we are the doughnut, not the hole.''</p>
        <p>One major project is a new office building  at Merritt 7, the glittering glass-walled complex of five buildings containing 1.2 million square feet of offices at the junction of Route 7 and the Merritt Parkway. Ground is to be broken next month for the 250,000-square-foot building at the south of the complex, with occupancy scheduled for 2002.</p>
        <p>Merritt 7, with the Norwalk River winding through it, was regarded as Albert D. Phelps's folly when he began building it 21 years ago in what was then Norwalk's hinterland. To compensate tenants for the remote location, Mr. Phelps built a small railroad station behind the buildings where Metro-North agreed to make stops. He also showered his tenants with amenities that still include banking, laundry, dry-cleaning and jewelry repair services, limousine and car rentals, a barbershop, a travel agency, a newsstand and a clothing store.</p>
        <p>Over the years Merritt 7 has maintained an occupancy rate of around 90 percent and become a magnet for satellite businesses. Facing it across Route 7 is a string of shops, restaurants and three hotels: a Homestead Guest Studios, a Four Points Sheraton and a Marriott Courtyard. Less than a mile up Route 7 a 170-room, $15 million Hilton Garden Inn is under construction and scheduled for a November opening, said Lowell Beebe-Center, general manager of the inn for its builders, New Castle Hotels of Shelton and Widewaters Group of DeWitt, New York, franchisees of the Hilton Hotels Corporation.</p>
        <p>The three-story 120,000-square-foot hotel on five acres will focus on the corporate market generated by Merritt 7 and Merritt View, a fully occupied 250,000-square-foot office building just south of Merritt 7 that  W&amp;M Properties of Stamford bought and redeveloped in 1994.</p>
        <p>At Merritt 7's rear, across Glover Avenue, Hewitt Associates, a global management consulting firm based in Lincolnshire, Ill., is putting up a 250,000-square-foot office building at an estimated cost of $20 million. When completed in September of next year  it will house 500 Hewitt employees now  occupying two buildings in Norwalk plus 300 newly hired workers.</p>
        <p>MERRITT on the River, a new development, is taking shape at the southern end of Merritt 7: a 236,000-square-foot former Caldor headquarters has been gutted and is being rehabilitated as a state-of-the-art office building and next to it construction has begun on a new 229-unit luxury apartment building and garage topped with a swimming pool. One-  and two-bedroom apartments will be available to corporate and individual tenants on its completion next spring. Carl R. Kuehner III, president of Building and Land Technologies in Wilton, and John P. Crosby, chairman of Albert G. Phelps Inc. (Merritt 7) are partners in the project.</p>
        <p>According to Kathleen Williams, the leasing agent for Merritt on the River, the office building is already 90 percent leased. Peppers and Rogers, a marketing company relocating from Stamford, took 83,000 square feet, and Centerchem, a beauty products company also moving out of Stamford,  took 8,500. Other tenants include State Farm Mutual, VSI Communications, HealthMarket Inc. and Adelphia Business Solutions.</p>
        <p>Commerce Packaging is building a 46,000-square-foot headquarters on Wilson Avenue in Norwalk. The company provides highly specialized packaging of goods for military and industrial purposes, packaging the Hubble Telescope for Perkin-Elmer, for instance.</p>
        <p>''Stamford was not very accepting of us when we wanted to expand there,'' said Mickey Alexander, the company president. ''We've been in Stamford since 1954 and we wanted to build where we could combine our Stamford and Norwalk locations. Stamford would not do anything for us. In my opinion they don't want any manufacturing -- not even light manufacturing like ours.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, said Mr. Alexander, referring to the director of marketing and development for the Norwalk Redevelopment Agency, ''Jim Banks could not have been more helpful in finding property for us.''</p>
        <p>The site Mr. Banks found is in one of the state's enterprise zones. In return for locating in economically stagnant neighborhoods the state offers businesses up to 80 percent in real estate and personal property tax abatements for five years, provided the company hires a specific number of local employees.</p>
        <p>Priceline started in Norwalk, moved to the High Ridge Office Park in Stamford and has now moved back to Norwalk, leasing the 130,000-square-foot Oxford Health Plans building on Route 1 from Oxford, which has consolidated at its headquarters in Trumbull.</p>
        <p>ACCORDING to Jeffrey Dunne, a senior vice-president at CB Commercial in Stamford, the cost of building in Norwalk is somewhat lower than in Stamford and continues to be an attraction. ''Typically you have the high cost of 100 percent structured rather than surface parking in Stamford,'' he said, ''and high-rise construction is more expensive than low-rise by 15 to 20 percent.'' He noted that annual office rents at Merritt 7 were in the low $30's per square foot, comparable to those in downtown Stamford, but rents elsewhere in Norwalk were in the high $20's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Banks finds that retailers come to Norwalk without his help, enticed by a 15-mile radius of customers in neighboring upscale towns. ''When I was a little boy this was a great shopping town,'' Mayor Esposito recalled. ''That's coming back, but in the way of the times.''</p>
        <p>Instead of a Thom McAn's shoe store, a five-and-ten, dress shops and mom and pop stores, Norwalk's new retailers include Circuit City, Sports Authority, Super Stop &amp; Shop, Home Depot, Frank's Garden Center, Barnes &amp; Noble and Toys ''R'' Us. An ABC Carpet store will soon break ground and a Walmart will occupy a former Caldor store  on Route 7, one of four such conversions in Connecticut. Sixteen Walmarts are up and running in the state.</p>
        <p>''Route 1 is filling up fast,'' said Stanley M. Seligson, chairman of Seligson Properties, a local developer. He expects his own $30 million retail project on 13 acres at 777 Connecticut Avenue (Route 1) to be completed by Christmas. Costco is building a 135,000-square-foot store on the property and providing space for 660 cars in a two-level structure. On the same site Mr. Seligson's Olympia Construction Company is putting up a 20,000-square-foot building to be occupied by Pier 1, Kinko's and an AT&amp;T wireless store, served by surface parking for 75 cars.</p>
        <p>In the historic waterfront district of South Norwalk, Clay Fowler, a partner in Spinnaker, a Stamford development company, has begun selective demolition of excess parts  of the Lock Building on Marshall and Water  Streets opposite the Maritime Aquarium. Bought by Spinnaker in April for $3.3 million, the defunct lock factory, built in stages from the mid-1800's to the 1940's, has had numerous small businesses, artists and assorted transient tenants while controversy over its future swirled.</p>
        <p>Disputes over turning it exclusively into artists' studios ended when the city designated Spinnaker as the redeveloper and settled on a plan. ''It will be used primarily for offices in the open space loft-y style,''  Mr. Fowler said. ''It will appeal to creative types focused on art, technology and media.''</p>
        <p>The building's 130,000 square feet will be reduced to 104,000 square feet, with interior spaces ranging from 2,000 square feet to more than 20,000, governed by existing interior brick walls. ''Every office will have some exposed brick and original wood beams,'' Mr. Fowler said. The brick exterior will be washed and repointed, preserving a 60-foot-wide sign, reading Norwalk Lock Company, painted directly on the brick. Renamed the Lock Art and Technology Center, the $14 million project is expected to open early next year.</p>
        <p>Norwalk's housing market has also had a renaissance. Prices rose more than 30 percent between June of 1998 and June of this year, bringing the cost of an average house from $305,399 to $397,018, according to Ellen Balazs, a broker at Coldwell Banker. And along Shorehaven Road near the Westport border a dozen waterfront homes in two subdivisions are being custom built on one-acre lots, priced in the $3 million to $4 million range. ''There hasn't been anything like this available in Norwalk for decades,'' said Patsy Brescia, a broker at William Pitt Real Estate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
