<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Duncan W. Richardson and Jacob Rees-Mogg; Eaton Vance Information Age Fund</title>
    <meta content="27INVO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/27/business/27INVO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eaton Vance Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Legomsky, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Duncan W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rees-Mogg, Jacob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D81231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Duncan W. Richardson and Jacob Rees-Mogg; Eaton Vance Information Age Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE LEGOMSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Legomsky, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investing With column reports on Eaton Vance Information Age Fund and its co-managers, Duncan W Richardson and Jacob Rees-Mogg; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO Duncan W. Richardson and Jacob Rees-Mogg, co-managers of the $322 million Eaton Vance Information Age fund, risk is clearly not a measure of financial virility. Investing in the technology, media and telecommunications sector ''does not have to be an extreme sport,'' Mr. Richardson said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, avoiding unnecessary risk is the pair's guiding principle. When buying and selling stocks in this fast-paced, highly volatile sector, the managers adhere to a philosophy of growth at a reasonable price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO Duncan W. Richardson and Jacob Rees-Mogg, co-managers of the $322 million Eaton Vance Information Age fund, risk is clearly not a measure of financial virility. Investing in the technology, media and telecommunications sector ''does not have to be an extreme sport,'' Mr. Richardson said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, avoiding unnecessary risk is the pair's guiding principle. When buying and selling stocks in this fast-paced, highly volatile sector, the managers adhere to a philosophy of growth at a reasonable price.</p>
        <p>One result of the approach is that both Mr. Richardson, who oversees the fund's assets in the United States,  the majority of the portfolio, and Mr. Rees-Mogg, who is based in London and selects the non-American holdings, have largely sidestepped pure Internet plays like e-tailers or content-oriented Web sites, which have been among the most expensive  stocks in the category.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rees-Mogg is openly leery of many of the measures, like price-to-sales ratios, that analysts and investors use to value fledgling technology, media and telecommunications companies that have yet to earn money. He relies on more traditional yardsticks. One is the peg ratio, which compares the price-to-earnings multiple to the long-term earnings growth rate of a company; another is the ratio of enterprise value (the market value of a company's debt and equity, less cash) to cash flow.</p>
        <p>He concedes, however, that this approach can mean lost opportunities. Two years ago, he said, he  passed on a chance to buy shares in an Australian Internet game maker, Uproar.com, at the initial public offering, citing what he called the company's ''hopelessly boring'' games, very expensive valuation and low quality. ''The stock did phenomenally well for a while,'' he said, but added, ''We are comfortable making that kind of mistake.''</p>
        <p>The tempered approach to growth investing has not compromised returns. For the three years ended Aug. 22, the fund returned 29.16 percent, annualized, compared with 14.73 percent for all world stock funds tracked by Morningstar Inc. and 19.12 percent for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>Eaton Vance Information Age was created in 1995 to capture what both managers viewed as powerful long-term opportunities resulting from rapid technological change and industry deregulation in markets outside the United States. ''We view the three sectors as an interlocking trinity,'' Mr. Rees-Mogg explained, meaning that growth in one industry necessitates growth in the others.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Richardson, 42, and Mr. Rees-Mogg, 31, have media-flavored family backgrounds. Mr. Richardson's father worked in advertising and public relations for Burson Marsteller, now part of Young &amp; Rubicam, the big advertising and public relations company that is to be acquired by WPP. Mr. Rees-Mogg's father, Lord Rees-Mogg, was vice chairman of the Board of Governors of the British Broadcasting Company from 1981 to 1986 and was editor of The Times of London from 1967 to 1981; he is still a columnist for the newspaper.</p>
        <p>THE fund now contains 108 stocks, with the American and foreign weightings generally conforming to those of the Morgan Stanley Capital International index; the managers, however, have considerable latitude to adjust the percentages. Typically, about 60 percent of the fund is invested in American stocks; but at the end of July, the figure was almost 70 percent, with an additional 14.6 percent in Japan and 15.8 percent in Europe. Eighty-eight percent of the assets were in stocks, with the balance in cash.</p>
        <p>No stock in the portfolio accounts for more than 5 percent of assets, and the top 10 names make up just 22 percent of assets. Although the fund has generally been skewed toward larger companies -- the median market capitalization is $11.8 billion -- Mr. Richardson says the inclusion of some smaller companies provides extra diversification.</p>
        <p>The emphasis on stability is evident in the fund's Sharpe ratio, a measure of risk-adjusted return. The fund's ratio is 0.9. A ratio of 1.0 would be average.</p>
        <p>The global fallout from the recent gyrations in the Nasdaq market has reinforced the managers' aversion to risk. ''This is no time to be complacent,'' Mr. Richardson said. ''Valuation risk is very high in this market.''</p>
        <p>The Azlan Group of Britain has been one of the fund's successful smaller holdings. The company, with $653.8 million in revenue last year, makes computer systems and peripherals and provides related training. Mr. Rees-Mogg said the company was well positioned to take advantage of the growth in the network communications sector.</p>
        <p>''Its partnerships with some of the leading technology companies should permit the company to grow organically and through acquisitions'' that create added value for shareholders, he said. The share price has more than doubled, to 183.5 pence, or $1.25, since he bought the shares two years ago at an average price of 67 pence.</p>
        <p>MR. RICHARDSON is bullish on McGraw-Hill, the publisher that also owns the S.&amp; P. index franchise and debt rating agency. Although the company has reported double-digit earnings increases for several years, the stock has not received much attention on Wall Street, he said.</p>
        <p>''The company is becoming more of a global operator,'' succeeding in adapting its basic businesses worldwide, he said. He expects the share price to be driven by strong results in textbook publishing and financial services -- especially the bond rating business. Most states are running budget surpluses and making education a top priority -- trends that should accelerate the drive to upgrade school textbooks, he added. He said that the company could beat the Wall Street earnings forecast of $2.35 a share for this year and that its earnings growth percentage could be in the mid-teens for the next few years. At $59.94, the stock sells at 25.11 times earnings, versus a P/E of 29.95 for the S.&amp; P. 500. Mr. Richardson first bought shares in 1997 at an average price of $53.14.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rees-Mogg likes the Nippon Broadcasting System, a radio broadcasting group and publisher of audiovisual materials; the company went public in Japan in 1996. In part, the investment, started in March 1999 was a play on strength in advertising revenues. He bought the shares at the equivalent of $30.85; they closed Friday in Tokyo at 6,500 yen, or $60.72.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
