<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chilies and Citrus Juice Can Spark Up Fish and Vegetables</title>
    <meta content="LIFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chili Peppers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Citrus Fruits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Juices</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DE1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chilies and Citrus Juice Can Spark Up Fish and Vegetables</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florence Fabricant Food column offers fish recipes sparked by chilies and citrus juices; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the cuisines of sultry climates demonstrate, sharp seasonings played against a touch of acidity can be hot weather appetite whetters. Chilies and citrus juices are what do the trick.</p>
        <p>But you do not need to be in Mexico, India or Thailand to follow this example. It's a formula that works just as well in summer here, using fresh fish and vegetables as the candidates for such seasonings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the cuisines of sultry climates demonstrate, sharp seasonings played against a touch of acidity can be hot weather appetite whetters. Chilies and citrus juices are what do the trick.</p>
        <p>But you do not need to be in Mexico, India or Thailand to follow this example. It's a formula that works just as well in summer here, using fresh fish and vegetables as the candidates for such seasonings.</p>
        <p>The following dishes, which could make a menu, use herbs and chilies with potatoes, corn, eggplants and striped bass.</p>
        <p>Potato and Corn Salad With Thai Seasonings  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>1 1/2 pounds medium-size Yukon gold potatoes, peeled  Salt  Kernels stripped from 4 ears corn  2 tablespoons Thai fish sauce (nam pla), see note  1 tablespoon light brown sugar  4 tablespoons mayonnaise  3 tablespoons fresh lime juice  Pinch chili powder  Freshly ground black pepper to taste  4 scallions, trimmed and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1/4 cup chopped cilantro leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Put potatoes in saucepan with salted water to cover, bring to a boil, lower heat to medium and cook until tender, about 20 minutes. Remove with slotted spoon. Add corn kernels to pan and cook two minutes. Drain. Allow vegetables to cool about 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, combine fish sauce and sugar in small saucepan and heat just until sugar dissolves. Set aside until cool. Beat in mayonnaise, lime juice and chili powder.</p>
        <p>3. Slice potatoes and put in bowl. Season with salt and pepper and toss with corn, scallions and cilantro. Pour dressing over and toss lightly again, then serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: If Thai fish sauce is not available use two tablespoons Chinese oyster sauce mixed with a tablespoon of water, and omit sugar.</p>
        <p>Eggplants With Chilies and Lime  Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>4 long Japanese eggplants  3 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil  Salt  2 cloves garlic, minced  2 serrano chilies, minced  Juice and grated zest of 2 limes  Freshly ground black pepper to taste  2 tablespoons minced fresh mint leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Trim end from eggplants. Slice eggplants in half lengthwise, then on an angle in slices three-fourths of an inch thick.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the oil in a large, heavy nonstick skillet. Add the eggplant and stir-fry it over medium-high heat about 15 minutes, until it is lightly browned. At first, the eggplant will sop up all the oil, but gradually, as the eggplant softens and browns, it will release oil back into pan to enhance the browning.</p>
        <p>3. Season with salt and add garlic and chilies. Continue to saute a few minutes, until garlic and chilies are tender. Stir in lime juice and zest, season with salt and pepper to taste and transfer to serving dish. Sprinkle with mint and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Seared Striped Bass With Seasoned Lemon-Oil  Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>4 striped bass fillets, each about 6 ounces, with skin  Salt  6 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil  1 tablespoon coarsely ground black pepper  1 tablespoon ground cumin  2 teaspoons lightly crushed whole cumin seeds  1 tablespoon minced flat-leaf parsley  1 clove garlic, finely minced  Juice of 1 lemon.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 450 degrees. Season fish with salt and brush each on both sides with half a tablespoon of oil. Mix pepper and cumin together on a plate and lightly dust skin of the fillets with spice mixture.</p>
        <p>2. Heat a heavy oven-proof skillet, preferably cast iron, large enough to hold fish in a single layer. When very hot, add the fish, skin side down. Sear it until the skin no longer sticks to the pan, about three minutes. Turn the fish over and put the pan in the oven. Bake five to six minutes, until the fish is just cooked through.</p>
        <p>3. While fish is baking, mix remaining olive oil with crushed cumin, parsley, garlic and lemon juice.</p>
        <p>4. Transfer fish to a platter or individual dinner plates, drizzle with seasoned oil and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
