<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Life for East Lynne Company</title>
    <meta content="27THEA$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">East Lynne Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stahlhuth, Gayle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kliewer, Warren</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">O'Toole's Tonight, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DF1531F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Life for East Lynne Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on East Lynne Company, theater troupe in Cape May, NJ, which has been transformed by Gayle Stahlhuth since its founder, Warren Kliewer, died in July 1998; company's latest production is The O'Toole's Tonight; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN though the East Lynne Company often put on plays with sizeable casts, for 18 years it was known as a one-man show.</p>
        <p>The man was Warren Kliewer, the company's founder and life force. East Lynne was committed to esoteric early American plays that no other company produced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN though the East Lynne Company often put on plays with sizeable casts, for 18 years it was known as a one-man show.</p>
        <p>The man was Warren Kliewer, the company's founder and life force. East Lynne was committed to esoteric early American plays that no other company produced.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Kliewer died in July 1998, it was commonly believed that East Lynne would die, too.</p>
        <p>And it did. But only for one year.</p>
        <p>In her second season of struggling to keep a little theater alive, Gayle Stahlhuth is too busy to ask herself why she is doing it, even though the answer is simple. Frank Smith, the theater board president, asked her, and she did not say no.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stahlhuth was an East Lynne board member from 1987 to 1997, appearing in and adapting many of its productions. Her own version of the lives and times of Tim and Molly O'Toole, a song and dance team of the late 1800's, is playing at East Lynne's current home, the First Presbyterian Church in Cape May through next Saturday. And to partake of Cape May's customary Victorian Week festivities, she will return in her popular one-woman show, ''Lou: The Remarkable Miss Alcott,'' for three performances, Oct. 12 through 14.</p>
        <p>For East Lynne, Cape May has been an ideal home. But even in this historic town, the company has had such a nomadic existence that it was commonly thought to be on tour, even when it wasn't.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kliewer was known to make stages in unlikely spaces. Before he died, East Lynne set up residence at the Frankin Street School. He found refuge at the Cape May Institute for Continuing Education, where a deck was transformed into a stage. Then came the ballroom of Chalfonte Hotel. And there were tea-time ''porch readings'' at bed-and-breakfasts.</p>
        <p>The company's offices remain in Secaucus in Mr. Kliewer's home. And for 12 years, ''off and on,'' as Ms. Stahlhuth put it, the Williams Center in Rutherford was a first, a second and an alternative home for the company. That may happen again, she said, talking of negotiations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kliewer found stopovers for some productions in New Brunswick, Mount Holly, Trenton, Newark, Jersey City -- in colleges, in vocational schools, even in real theaters. He would call home anyplace he could hang his sets, or what he called ''pickup walls,'' for plays like ''Tortesa the Userer'' (1839) or ''A Politician Out-Witted'' (1788).</p>
        <p>Even though Ms. Stahlhuth is an actress, a producer and a playwright, she is ''a historian at heart,'' determined to keep Mr. Kliewer's vision alive. That includes her return to Cape May off-season to conduct oral history projects for seventh and eigth graders and elderly people.</p>
        <p>Because of the company's financial straits, somewhat alleviated by a recent $3,200 grant from Cape May County, the shows are small, but the new artistic director's dreams are big. This summer's season has been budgeted at $35,000.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Kleiwer was constantly trying to lure audiences to the uncharted plays of American history -- his era was the early 1800's but he went back to 1780 and forward to the 1920's -- how is Ms. Stahlhuth proposing to popularize the obscure, or at least make it accessible? ''Our audiences are building,'' she said. ''This is not run-of-the-mill fare. People find us. Quite a few follow us. Others who don't know what they've walked into are pleasantly surprised; these are good scripts, with wit. When some people hear 19th century, they jump on melodrama. But there's more.''</p>
        <p>She envisions a new old repertory. ''I'd love to do Richard Harding Davis's 'The Dictator' of 1910,'' she said. ''He was a prominent newspaperman; he's mentioned in 'The Front Page' but he's more than a footnote. He wrote this funny Marx Brothers kind of play, but I'd need a minimum of 10 actors -- and they'd all be doubling.</p>
        <p>''And I found plays by Theodore Dreiser. Does anybody know he wrote plays? I'm still digging.''</p>
        <p>THE O'TOOLES TONIGHT  The East Lynne Company.  The First Presbyterian Church in Cape May, 500 Hughes Street, Cape May.  Through Sept. 2. Wednesday through Sunday, 8 p.m.  (609) 884-5898.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
