<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clearing the Decks for a Trade Pact's Riches</title>
    <meta content="27VIET$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shipbuilding, Conversion and Repair</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vietnam</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Caterpillar Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salzman, Anthony D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D61231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clearing the Decks for a Trade Pact's Riches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>VUNG TAU, Vietnam</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New trade pact between US and Vietnam rescinds US embargo that blocked trade for 19 years; lower American tariffs on Vietnamese goods will increase demand for them and, consequently, production; article focuses on impact of new paradigm on Vietnam's fishing and shipbuilding industries and on Anthony D Salzman, American expatriate who imports Caterpillar industrial engines into Vietnam; photos; charts; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO explain why he is so excited about the new trade agreement with the United States, Pham Van Tuat clambered aboard the Xin Thu, his new 89-foot wooden fishing trawler, and gestured into its spacious holds. Lower American tariffs for Vietnamese seafood products in the United States, he explained, will mean more demand for tuna and squid. And that is where this $125,000 trawler comes in.</p>
        <p>The Xin Thu, the largest of his nine boats, can travel 400 miles out to sea and bring back 200 tons of fish, Mr. Tuat said. To demonstrate how, he bundled his visitors down into the engine room. There, still bearing its maker's signature yellow paint, was something that makes many American executives here as excited as Mr. Tuat: a brand-new, $32,000, 480-horsepower Caterpillar engine.</p>
        <p>''We'll be exporting to America soon,'' Mr. Tuat said triumphantly, hurrying his guests onto a skiff to beat the ebb tide back to shore. ''I'm planning to build another boat like this one. But even bigger.''</p>
        <p>To a large extent, Mr. Tuat's plans are the fruits of seven years of toil by Anthony D. Salzman, an entrepreneur from New York. Mr. Salzman came to Hanoi from Japan in 1993, hoping to capitalize on that country's swelling investment in Vietnam. He wound up opening a dealership for Caterpillar, which was among the most vocal companies in urging the Clinton administration to lift the United States embargo that blocked trade for 19 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman, 49, is now one of Vietnam's most prominent American residents, well known for his outspoken, unrelenting style. And he is just one of many American executives here who say a trade pact will unleash a tide of exports -- and lift his fortunes with it. After five years of talks, the United States and Vietnam signed the agreement on July 13, and it is expected to be ratified by Congress, though probably not this year.</p>
        <p>Since President Clinton ended the embargo in 1994, the American commercial adventure in Vietnam has resembled its earlier military one, with optimism quickly bogged down in a quagmire of red tape, corruption and Communist recalcitrance. To skeptics, the new agreement is yet another capitulation: tariffs on Vietnamese goods would drop immediately, while Vietnamese tariffs and quotas on American products would fall only gradually, in some cases enduring as long as seven years.</p>
        <p>But supporters here say the agreement represents a new, irrevocable commitment by Vietnam to open the country to global markets and to play by internationally accepted trade rules.</p>
        <p>MOREOVER, as Vietnamese exports rise and foreign investment returns, executives like Mr. Salzman say, demand will also rise for American products, whether toothpaste or trucks and bulldozers.</p>
        <p>''The impact is indirect,'' Mr. Salzman said. With rising export revenue, he predicted, ''my electric business is going to grow, my marine-engine business is going to grow.''</p>
        <p>''And as everything else grows,'' he added, ''the infrastructure business should grow, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman foresees $1 billion in sales for his venture, V-Trac -- for Vietnam Tractor -- over the next 10 years if Vietnam carries through on its commitments. But he and other veterans of business here warn that change should not be expected overnight. With or without the trade accord, Vietnam is still a poor, Communist country, with an absence of legal, social and physical infrastructure that sent foreign investment inflows plummeting to about $1.5 billion a year in 1999 from roughly $3.3 billion in 1997.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Vietnam is no longer a hostile, war-ravaged country. More than half the population is too young to have ever seen an American G.I. And Vietnam's other former adversaries, meanwhile, have moved back in. France was the top investor in the country last year, and Japan the top trading partner. The United States is still only Vietnam's seventh-largest foreign investor and trading partner.</p>
        <p>''It can be a challenging market, but I think the potential is definitely here,'' said Michael R. Frisby, counselor for commercial affairs at the American Embassy in Hanoi and a Vietnam war veteran. ''Companies should come and investigate this market, because with ratification of the treaty the potential in Vietnam will increase exponentially.''</p>
        <p>Vietnam is already rich in resources. It is the largest producer of black pepper and robusta coffee, which is used for instant blends. And it is the second-largest exporter of rice, after Thailand, and a key source of seafood, cashews and bauxite. Its workers earn high marks from foreign employers -- and not just for the low pay.</p>
        <p>The country also has much potential as a consumer market. More than one-third of its 78 million people live in poverty, but some of its roughly 18 million urbanites are sitting on what bankers and economists estimate are billions of dollars in gold and other hidden savings, with perhaps $1 billion to $2 billion more coming in from relatives overseas every year. Many Vietnamese hoard their money to avoid income taxes, and because they do not trust banks.</p>
        <p>Although American companies lack much market share here, their brands are easily recognized. When Coca-Cola returned in 1994, it found people still familiar with its logo. Offices in Vietnam at that time were still using old I.B.M. computers and keeping cool with rusting Carrier air-conditioners, all left behind when the United States pulled out nearly 20 years earlier.</p>
        <p>THE first Caterpillar equipment arrived here before World War II, when Vietnam was still a French colony. More Cats, of course, came during the American military involvement.</p>
        <p>Old Caterpillar tractors and bulldozers were still rumbling across the landscape in 1990, when Bruce St.  John, then Caterpillar's representative in Bangkok, traveled to Vietnam to assess the prospects.</p>
        <p>He learned that Vietnamese mechanics still knew how to service Caterpillar equipment. Given Vietnam's infrastructure needs, Mr. St. John, who served in the Army in Vietnam in 1970 and 1971, predicted a lucrative market for Caterpillar.</p>
        <p>''It looked like a very attractive opportunity,'' said Mr. St. John, who now works at the same factory, in Mossville, Ill., where Mr. Tuat's engine was built.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. St. John testified before Congress about the embargo. Caterpillar's stance set off protests from groups that had been urging the United States to pressure Hanoi to find missing American soldiers.</p>
        <p>Caterpillar executives argued that Vietnamese markets were falling to Japanese and European competitors and that more influence on the M.I.A. issue could be gained by trading with Vietnam. In 1993, Caterpillar opened its office in Hanoi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman took an unlikely road to Vietnam -- and to bulldozers. His father, Herbert, secured the family fortune in 1967 when he sold the company his own father founded, Standard Bag, to Boise Cascade. Herbert Salzman went on to serve four presidents in various positions at the State Department and started the agency that would become the Overseas Private Investment Corporation, which guarantees American investments in third-world countries.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Salzman studied at Yale University and the Duke University law school. After stints at American Express and Lehman Brothers, he chose to explore his entrepreneurial roots, a decision that took him to Portugal and Spain. Then he tried Asia, starting in 1992 with Japan, where his wife was born.</p>
        <p>When his effort to crack Japan's closed markets did not succeed, Mr. Salzman and his wife moved to Vietnam. ''Yen were pouring in,'' he recalled. ''It meant that Vietnam was going to be an important Asian economy.''</p>
        <p>Hanoi was a long way from the Salzmans' apartment on Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. When he and his wife called an exterminator to rid their new home of rats, Mr. Salzman said, a man showed up with a snake in a bag.</p>
        <p>Efforts by the Communist government to keep tabs on the new capitalist arrivals were equally rustic. Mr. Salzman learned that his phones were tapped when he heard officials breathing over the line. Fax machines were illegal -- they were too hard to decipher.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Salzman said he never felt any animosity as a citizen of Vietnam's former enemy. He set up the first American Chamber of Commerce in Hanoi and began prospecting for business ideas that would capitalize on Vietnam's obvious need for new infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman had just abandoned hopes of investing in a cellular telephone operator when he met Caterpillar's Hanoi representative, James Ferrara. Caterpillar was already fielding offers from its big distributors in Hong Kong, Indonesia, France and Canada to expand to Vietnam, Mr. Salzman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman prevailed over the other bidders, he said, by appealing to the company's traditional preference for family-owned dealerships. In mid-1994, he set up V-Trac. A Caterpillar spokesman, Jeffrey S. Hawkinson, said Mr. Ferrara was not available to confirm Mr. Salzman's account.</p>
        <p>While many Vietnamese knew the Caterpillar name, Mr. Salzman needed to spread the word that Cat was back. In 1995, he advertised a contest offering a $1,000 prize for the oldest working Caterpillar equipment in the country. The winning entry was a 1939 generator serving on a tugboat. The overwhelmed winner carried off his prize in two shopping bags filled with Vietnamese currency.</p>
        <p>SELLING new equipment, however, was still difficult. The same year, V-Trac lost a $7 million contract to supply bulldozers and other heavy equipment to one of Vietnam's cement companies. Mr. Salzman blamed the Jackson-Vanik law, a cold-war statute aimed at Communist countries not allowing free emigration. The law prohibited trade financing to such countries by the Export-Import Bank or by OPIC, the agency started by Mr. Salzman's father. The Vietnamese cement contract went instead to Komatsu of Japan.</p>
        <p>In 1998, President Clinton waived the Jackson-Vanik restrictions against Vietnam, and last year V-Trac won $2.3 million in financing from OPIC, the first deal the agency had made in Vietnam since the war. V-Trac now employs 140 people in seven offices around the country.</p>
        <p>But financing is still difficult to obtain from risk-averse government agencies, Mr. Salzman complained. The Ex-Im Bank, for one, started operations in Vietnam in December, but has yet to finance a deal.</p>
        <p>In fact, the trade accord may be a bigger boon to other companies from other countries as they invest in Vietnam. Textile companies from Taiwan, for example, poured millions of dollars into Vietnam on the prospect of exporting to the United States with reduced tariffs. Now, a Taiwan trade official said, they are counting the minutes until the agreement is ratified by Congress.</p>
        <p>BUT what is good for Taiwan textile companies in Vietnam may also be good for Caterpillar. Just north of Vung Tau, the Hualon Corporation of Taiwan has a factory that makes cloth and polyester yarn. When the plant opened in 1997, there was no electricity, so Hualon paid $15 million for three Caterpillar generators. Now it is planning to build a second plant next door, more than doubling its power needs.</p>
        <p>Power is now available from the local utility, but Hualon's generators remain cheaper -- and more reliable. Back in Vung Tau at the Technical Raw Material Trading &amp; Supplying Company, Phan Doan Hung showed off a new, $400 million shoe factory left dormant for a day by a power failure; its 2,200 employees had to stay at home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hung and the companies in Europe, Korea and Taiwan that buy his shoes said the trade agreement would mean more business for his factory. ''We'd like to export our product directly to America,'' he added. ''That way we can earn a bigger profit.''</p>
        <p>To ensure that he has the power he needs to meet his contract deadlines, Mr. Hung is buying a $61,000 Caterpillar generator. ''Please come soon,'' he said to a visiting V-Trac executive. ''You see what it's like today. I worry, worry, worry.''</p>
        <p>Ford Vietnam, a joint venture between Ford Motor and a Vietnamese partner, also uses Caterpillar generators to power its $102 million factory near Hanoi. Business is slow: Ford makes only 100 of the 14,000 cars that the factory could produce each month. Company executives are optimistic that the trade agreement will change that.</p>
        <p>''The agreement makes me feel even more confident because of the way it makes other businesses grow,'' said Deborah Aronson, general director of Ford Vietnam. ''There's a significant retail population that is looking to demonstrate its success.''</p>
        <p>Chronic power failures, however, underscore Vietnam's limitations as a market and investment. Though the economy is regaining speed, unprofitable state-owned businesses drain government coffers, while banks, like so many elsewhere in Asia, are paralyzed by bad loans. Income tax rates are so high that it is sometimes cheaper for foreign companies to hire expatriates than to pay Vietnamese a competitive after-tax wage.</p>
        <p>The agreement also leaves unresolved a litany of structural problems, executives say. Vietnam is only beginning to experiment with capital markets; it recently opened a stock market, but regulations still hobble businesses' ability to raise money. Vietnam is trying to overhaul these rules, but its bureaucracy is still Byzantine, its licensing rules unclear, and its foreclosure and bankruptcy laws inadequate. Courts are not independent; they answer to the Communist Party.</p>
        <p>And some executives here do not share Mr. Salzman's faith that the trade pact will permeate the economy. Ronald R. Kiel, 3M's managing director in Vietnam, agrees that the accord is essential for Vietnam's future but says the country's goods are too poor and its infrastructure too decrepit. ''I don't think you're going to see an explosion of industrial output because the country isn't geared up for it,'' Mr. Kiel said.</p>
        <p>Others have more faith. ''I think that Vietnam does have the potential for explosive economic growth, more so than most countries in Asia,'' said Wesley Grove, the chief representative of Chase Manhattan Bank in Ho Chi Minh City.</p>
        <p>Gerard Letellier is another believer. Mr. Letellier is chief executive of Morning Star Cement, a $400 million joint venture of the Swiss cement giant Holderbank Financiere Glarus and Vietnam National Cement.</p>
        <p>Booming demand for cement to build homes has sent Morning Star's production soaring from 400,000 tons in 1998 to one million tons last year. The trade agreement, Mr. Letellier predicted, ''will open the Vietnamese market to U.S. investors, and this means new infrastucture.''</p>
        <p>''And this is good,'' he added, ''for the cement business.'' (There is no need to guess whose equipment Morning Star uses to excavate the limestone to make that cement.)</p>
        <p>CATERPILLAR'S dividend doesn't end at the quarry. Increased shipping traffic is also helping the Bien Dong Shipyard south of Ho Chi Minh City. Bien Dong's workers are putting finishing touches on a new $70,000 ferry; inside it is a $30,000 Caterpillar engine. ''After this one's done, we're building another for the same purpose but with a 400-horsepower Caterpillar engine,'' said Phan Ngoc Chuc, Bien Dong's director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chuc is investing $200,000 and hiring 20 new workers to double the shipyard's production and to take advantage of what he thinks will be a boom in demand for another kind of vessel. Dwindling catches and environmental concerns have prompted Vietnam to push its fishing fleet farther out to sea, requiring larger, more powerful boats. Such big boats are more economical when they remain at sea, so Mr. Chuc foresees building other boats to transport their catch to shore.</p>
        <p>Back in Vung Tau, Mr. Tuat remembers that when he was a boy in the 1950's, he had to go only about a mile out to catch all the fish he needed. Bigger boats won't be enough to compete in the American market now, he realizes. He and other fishermen will need to improve the quality of their product, he says, investing in more ice and freezers that will burn more fuel.</p>
        <p>That may help Caterpillar sell bigger engines in Vienam. But it could help Mr. Tuat, too. One of his sons, it so happens, sells ice. The other sells fuel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO explain why he is so excited about the new trade agreement with the United States, Pham Van Tuat clambered aboard the Xin Thu, his new 89-foot wooden fishing trawler, and gestured into its spacious holds. Lower American tariffs for Vietnamese seafood products in the United States, he explained, will mean more demand for tuna and squid. And that is where this $125,000 trawler comes in.</p>
        <p>The Xin Thu, the largest of his nine boats, can travel 400 miles out to sea and bring back 200 tons of fish, Mr. Tuat said. To demonstrate how, he bundled his visitors down into the engine room. There, still bearing its maker's signature yellow paint, was something that makes many American executives here as excited as Mr. Tuat: a brand-new, $32,000, 480-horsepower Caterpillar engine.</p>
        <p>''We'll be exporting to America soon,'' Mr. Tuat said triumphantly, hurrying his guests onto a skiff to beat the ebb tide back to shore. ''I'm planning to build another boat like this one. But even bigger.''</p>
        <p>To a large extent, Mr. Tuat's plans are the fruits of seven years of toil by Anthony D. Salzman, an entrepreneur from New York. Mr. Salzman came to Hanoi from Japan in 1993, hoping to capitalize on that country's swelling investment in Vietnam. He wound up opening a dealership for Caterpillar, which was among the most vocal companies in urging the Clinton administration to lift the United States embargo that blocked trade for 19 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman, 49, is now one of Vietnam's most prominent American residents, well known for his outspoken, unrelenting style. And he is just one of many American executives here who say a trade pact will unleash a tide of exports -- and lift his fortunes with it. After five years of talks, the United States and Vietnam signed the agreement on July 13, and it is expected to be ratified by Congress, though probably not this year.</p>
        <p>Since President Clinton ended the embargo in 1994, the American commercial adventure in Vietnam has resembled its earlier military one, with optimism quickly bogged down in a quagmire of red tape, corruption and Communist recalcitrance. To skeptics, the new agreement is yet another capitulation: tariffs on Vietnamese goods would drop immediately, while Vietnamese tariffs and quotas on American products would fall only gradually, in some cases enduring as long as seven years.</p>
        <p>But supporters here say the agreement represents a new, irrevocable commitment by Vietnam to open the country to global markets and to play by internationally accepted trade rules.</p>
        <p>MOREOVER, as Vietnamese exports rise and foreign investment returns, executives like Mr. Salzman say, demand will also rise for American products, whether toothpaste or trucks and bulldozers.</p>
        <p>''The impact is indirect,'' Mr. Salzman said. With rising export revenue, he predicted, ''my electric business is going to grow, my marine-engine business is going to grow.''</p>
        <p>''And as everything else grows,'' he added, ''the infrastructure business should grow, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman foresees $1 billion in sales for his venture, V-Trac -- for Vietnam Tractor -- over the next 10 years if Vietnam carries through on its commitments. But he and other veterans of business here warn that change should not be expected overnight. With or without the trade accord, Vietnam is still a poor, Communist country, with an absence of legal, social and physical infrastructure that sent foreign investment inflows plummeting to about $1.5 billion a year in 1999 from roughly $3.3 billion in 1997.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Vietnam is no longer a hostile, war-ravaged country. More than half the population is too young to have ever seen an American G.I. And Vietnam's other former adversaries, meanwhile, have moved back in. France was the top investor in the country last year, and Japan the top trading partner. The United States is still only Vietnam's seventh-largest foreign investor and trading partner.</p>
        <p>''It can be a challenging market, but I think the potential is definitely here,'' said Michael R. Frisby, counselor for commercial affairs at the American Embassy in Hanoi and a Vietnam war veteran. ''Companies should come and investigate this market, because with ratification of the treaty the potential in Vietnam will increase exponentially.''</p>
        <p>Vietnam is already rich in resources. It is the largest producer of black pepper and robusta coffee, which is used for instant blends. And it is the second-largest exporter of rice, after Thailand, and a key source of seafood, cashews and bauxite. Its workers earn high marks from foreign employers -- and not just for the low pay.</p>
        <p>The country also has much potential as a consumer market. More than one-third of its 78 million people live in poverty, but some of its roughly 18 million urbanites are sitting on what bankers and economists estimate are billions of dollars in gold and other hidden savings, with perhaps $1 billion to $2 billion more coming in from relatives overseas every year. Many Vietnamese hoard their money to avoid income taxes, and because they do not trust banks.</p>
        <p>Although American companies lack much market share here, their brands are easily recognized. When Coca-Cola returned in 1994, it found people still familiar with its logo. Offices in Vietnam at that time were still using old I.B.M. computers and keeping cool with rusting Carrier air-conditioners, all left behind when the United States pulled out nearly 20 years earlier.</p>
        <p>THE first Caterpillar equipment arrived here before World War II, when Vietnam was still a French colony. More Cats, of course, came during the American military involvement.</p>
        <p>Old Caterpillar tractors and bulldozers were still rumbling across the landscape in 1990, when Bruce St.  John, then Caterpillar's representative in Bangkok, traveled to Vietnam to assess the prospects.</p>
        <p>He learned that Vietnamese mechanics still knew how to service Caterpillar equipment. Given Vietnam's infrastructure needs, Mr. St. John, who served in the Army in Vietnam in 1970 and 1971, predicted a lucrative market for Caterpillar.</p>
        <p>''It looked like a very attractive opportunity,'' said Mr. St. John, who now works at the same factory, in Mossville, Ill., where Mr. Tuat's engine was built.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. St. John testified before Congress about the embargo. Caterpillar's stance set off protests from groups that had been urging the United States to pressure Hanoi to find missing American soldiers.</p>
        <p>Caterpillar executives argued that Vietnamese markets were falling to Japanese and European competitors and that more influence on the M.I.A. issue could be gained by trading with Vietnam. In 1993, Caterpillar opened its office in Hanoi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman took an unlikely road to Vietnam -- and to bulldozers. His father, Herbert, secured the family fortune in 1967 when he sold the company his own father founded, Standard Bag, to Boise Cascade. Herbert Salzman went on to serve four presidents in various positions at the State Department and started the agency that would become the Overseas Private Investment Corporation, which guarantees American investments in third-world countries.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Salzman studied at Yale University and the Duke University law school. After stints at American Express and Lehman Brothers, he chose to explore his entrepreneurial roots, a decision that took him to Portugal and Spain. Then he tried Asia, starting in 1992 with Japan, where his wife was born.</p>
        <p>When his effort to crack Japan's closed markets did not succeed, Mr. Salzman and his wife moved to Vietnam. ''Yen were pouring in,'' he recalled. ''It meant that Vietnam was going to be an important Asian economy.''</p>
        <p>Hanoi was a long way from the Salzmans' apartment on Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. When he and his wife called an exterminator to rid their new home of rats, Mr. Salzman said, a man showed up with a snake in a bag.</p>
        <p>Efforts by the Communist government to keep tabs on the new capitalist arrivals were equally rustic. Mr. Salzman learned that his phones were tapped when he heard officials breathing over the line. Fax machines were illegal -- they were too hard to decipher.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Salzman said he never felt any animosity as a citizen of Vietnam's former enemy. He set up the first American Chamber of Commerce in Hanoi and began prospecting for business ideas that would capitalize on Vietnam's obvious need for new infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman had just abandoned hopes of investing in a cellular telephone operator when he met Caterpillar's Hanoi representative, James Ferrara. Caterpillar was already fielding offers from its big distributors in Hong Kong, Indonesia, France and Canada to expand to Vietnam, Mr. Salzman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salzman prevailed over the other bidders, he said, by appealing to the company's traditional preference for family-owned dealerships. In mid-1994, he set up V-Trac. A Caterpillar spokesman, Jeffrey S. Hawkinson, said Mr. Ferrara was not available to confirm Mr. Salzman's account.</p>
        <p>While many Vietnamese knew the Caterpillar name, Mr. Salzman needed to spread the word that Cat was back. In 1995, he advertised a contest offering a $1,000 prize for the oldest working Caterpillar equipment in the country. The winning entry was a 1939 generator serving on a tugboat. The overwhelmed winner carried off his prize in two shopping bags filled with Vietnamese currency.</p>
        <p>SELLING new equipment, however, was still difficult. The same year, V-Trac lost a $7 million contract to supply bulldozers and other heavy equipment to one of Vietnam's cement companies. Mr. Salzman blamed the Jackson-Vanik law, a cold-war statute aimed at Communist countries not allowing free emigration. The law prohibited trade financing to such countries by the Export-Import Bank or by OPIC, the agency started by Mr. Salzman's father. The Vietnamese cement contract went instead to Komatsu of Japan.</p>
        <p>In 1998, President Clinton waived the Jackson-Vanik restrictions against Vietnam, and last year V-Trac won $2.3 million in financing from OPIC, the first deal the agency had made in Vietnam since the war. V-Trac now employs 140 people in seven offices around the country.</p>
        <p>But financing is still difficult to obtain from risk-averse government agencies, Mr. Salzman complained. The Ex-Im Bank, for one, started operations in Vietnam in December, but has yet to finance a deal.</p>
        <p>In fact, the trade accord may be a bigger boon to other companies from other countries as they invest in Vietnam. Textile companies from Taiwan, for example, poured millions of dollars into Vietnam on the prospect of exporting to the United States with reduced tariffs. Now, a Taiwan trade official said, they are counting the minutes until the agreement is ratified by Congress.</p>
        <p>BUT what is good for Taiwan textile companies in Vietnam may also be good for Caterpillar. Just north of Vung Tau, the Hualon Corporation of Taiwan has a factory that makes cloth and polyester yarn. When the plant opened in 1997, there was no electricity, so Hualon paid $15 million for three Caterpillar generators. Now it is planning to build a second plant next door, more than doubling its power needs.</p>
        <p>Power is now available from the local utility, but Hualon's generators remain cheaper -- and more reliable. Back in Vung Tau at the Technical Raw Material Trading &amp; Supplying Company, Phan Doan Hung showed off a new, $400 million shoe factory left dormant for a day by a power failure; its 2,200 employees had to stay at home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hung and the companies in Europe, Korea and Taiwan that buy his shoes said the trade agreement would mean more business for his factory. ''We'd like to export our product directly to America,'' he added. ''That way we can earn a bigger profit.''</p>
        <p>To ensure that he has the power he needs to meet his contract deadlines, Mr. Hung is buying a $61,000 Caterpillar generator. ''Please come soon,'' he said to a visiting V-Trac executive. ''You see what it's like today. I worry, worry, worry.''</p>
        <p>Ford Vietnam, a joint venture between Ford Motor and a Vietnamese partner, also uses Caterpillar generators to power its $102 million factory near Hanoi. Business is slow: Ford makes only 100 of the 14,000 cars that the factory could produce each month. Company executives are optimistic that the trade agreement will change that.</p>
        <p>''The agreement makes me feel even more confident because of the way it makes other businesses grow,'' said Deborah Aronson, general director of Ford Vietnam. ''There's a significant retail population that is looking to demonstrate its success.''</p>
        <p>Chronic power failures, however, underscore Vietnam's limitations as a market and investment. Though the economy is regaining speed, unprofitable state-owned businesses drain government coffers, while banks, like so many elsewhere in Asia, are paralyzed by bad loans. Income tax rates are so high that it is sometimes cheaper for foreign companies to hire expatriates than to pay Vietnamese a competitive after-tax wage.</p>
        <p>The agreement also leaves unresolved a litany of structural problems, executives say. Vietnam is only beginning to experiment with capital markets; it recently opened a stock market, but regulations still hobble businesses' ability to raise money. Vietnam is trying to overhaul these rules, but its bureaucracy is still Byzantine, its licensing rules unclear, and its foreclosure and bankruptcy laws inadequate. Courts are not independent; they answer to the Communist Party.</p>
        <p>And some executives here do not share Mr. Salzman's faith that the trade pact will permeate the economy. Ronald R. Kiel, 3M's managing director in Vietnam, agrees that the accord is essential for Vietnam's future but says the country's goods are too poor and its infrastructure too decrepit. ''I don't think you're going to see an explosion of industrial output because the country isn't geared up for it,'' Mr. Kiel said.</p>
        <p>Others have more faith. ''I think that Vietnam does have the potential for explosive economic growth, more so than most countries in Asia,'' said Wesley Grove, the chief representative of Chase Manhattan Bank in Ho Chi Minh City.</p>
        <p>Gerard Letellier is another believer. Mr. Letellier is chief executive of Morning Star Cement, a $400 million joint venture of the Swiss cement giant Holderbank Financiere Glarus and Vietnam National Cement.</p>
        <p>Booming demand for cement to build homes has sent Morning Star's production soaring from 400,000 tons in 1998 to one million tons last year. The trade agreement, Mr. Letellier predicted, ''will open the Vietnamese market to U.S. investors, and this means new infrastucture.''</p>
        <p>''And this is good,'' he added, ''for the cement business.'' (There is no need to guess whose equipment Morning Star uses to excavate the limestone to make that cement.)</p>
        <p>CATERPILLAR'S dividend doesn't end at the quarry. Increased shipping traffic is also helping the Bien Dong Shipyard south of Ho Chi Minh City. Bien Dong's workers are putting finishing touches on a new $70,000 ferry; inside it is a $30,000 Caterpillar engine. ''After this one's done, we're building another for the same purpose but with a 400-horsepower Caterpillar engine,'' said Phan Ngoc Chuc, Bien Dong's director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chuc is investing $200,000 and hiring 20 new workers to double the shipyard's production and to take advantage of what he thinks will be a boom in demand for another kind of vessel. Dwindling catches and environmental concerns have prompted Vietnam to push its fishing fleet farther out to sea, requiring larger, more powerful boats. Such big boats are more economical when they remain at sea, so Mr. Chuc foresees building other boats to transport their catch to shore.</p>
        <p>Back in Vung Tau, Mr. Tuat remembers that when he was a boy in the 1950's, he had to go only about a mile out to catch all the fish he needed. Bigger boats won't be enough to compete in the American market now, he realizes. He and other fishermen will need to improve the quality of their product, he says, investing in more ice and freezers that will burn more fuel.</p>
        <p>That may help Caterpillar sell bigger engines in Vienam. But it could help Mr. Tuat, too. One of his sons, it so happens, sells ice. The other sells fuel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
