<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treating Fish With Respect in Huntington</title>
    <meta content="27DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Legal Sea Foods (Huntington Station, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0D71631F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treating Fish With Respect in Huntington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Legal Sea Foods restaurant in Huntington Station, Long Island (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEGAL SEA FOODS is making waves at the Walt Whitman Mall in Huntington Station. From the minute it opened, lines have been snaking out the door. Displaced New Englanders and frequent visitors to Boston have been in the forefront. They know that Legal Sea Foods, the 50-year-old chain that began as a fish market in Cambridge, Mass., is the place for reliable, moderately priced fish and shellfish. For many Long Islanders, no trip to Boston is complete without at least one meal at Legal Sea Foods.</p>
        <p>It is only in the last five years that the growing chain has ventured outside Massachusetts. Today, these restaurants dot the East Coast, with outposts as far away as Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEGAL SEA FOODS is making waves at the Walt Whitman Mall in Huntington Station. From the minute it opened, lines have been snaking out the door. Displaced New Englanders and frequent visitors to Boston have been in the forefront. They know that Legal Sea Foods, the 50-year-old chain that began as a fish market in Cambridge, Mass., is the place for reliable, moderately priced fish and shellfish. For many Long Islanders, no trip to Boston is complete without at least one meal at Legal Sea Foods.</p>
        <p>It is only in the last five years that the growing chain has ventured outside Massachusetts. Today, these restaurants dot the East Coast, with outposts as far away as Florida.</p>
        <p>The Long Island venture, on the south end of the mall, next to the movie theater, is a large, sprawling, sleek spot. The dining rooms are sectioned into more intimate areas by nautical room dividers and stunning wood walls. The aquatic look is everywhere: outlines of monster-size fish etched on the windows, a faux waterfall backdrop to a fish sculpture and wavy blue wall treatments.</p>
        <p>The room is more elegant than the crowd. Sports attire is the norm. Diners who wouldn't dream of wearing shorts and T-shirts on a Saturday night to an Italian restaurant in the same price bracket go the casual route here.</p>
        <p>Prices vary widely, with half the entrees $20 and over and half under: not astronomical but not inexpensive.</p>
        <p>A month after the opening, the service staff was still a bit shaky. One evening we had a super waitress who was attentive, knew the menu and recited specials complete with prices. But our experience another night was probably more typical. The waiter kept asking if everything were all right but never noticed that the bread basket was empty. At all times, runners delivering dishes hadn't a clue where to place them.</p>
        <p>But food, especially the legendary chowders and the sweet lobsters, is the draw here. Do not miss the creamy, rich, deservedly famous clam chowder. A similar creamy fish chowder is its equal. We also liked the peppy Rhode Island red chowder, a k a Manhattan in these parts.</p>
        <p>Other recommended openers are the firm, appealing popcorn shrimp with two dipping sauces; the super crab cake containing large shards of crab meat; the blue cheese salad with pears, walnuts, endive and frisee; and a light seafood antipasto of grilled shrimp and calamari over salad. Fried smelts were lightly breaded but far from crisp.</p>
        <p>That same criticism can be made about a few of the fried entrees: three jumbo soft-shell crabs and six plump oysters. The fried clams, though, were as crisp as one could hope for.</p>
        <p>The dish I always head for at Legal Sea Foods is the steamed lobster ($26 to $40 depending on size, one and a quarter to two and a half pounds). Each sampled was a sweet success. Also making a splash were grilled shrimp Cajun style, which were slightly spicy; grilled swordfish topped with a cold cucumber sauce; and a flavor-packed cioppino brimming with perfectly cooked lobster, scallops, shrimp, squid, clams and mussels in the shell plus chunks of whitefish. An Arctic char special was also cooked correctly, but its asparagus-wild mushroom risotto was dry.</p>
        <p>Most entrees arrive with a couple of side dishes. Waiters are happy to make substitutions. Best choices are the crisp French fries, the thin onion strings, the crisp-tender green beans, the skins-on mashed potatoes and the tasty snap peas with oyster sauce.</p>
        <p>For the record, there are steaks, chicken, pork chops and a vegetarian casserole on the menu.</p>
        <p>The only dessert that didn't deliver was the homemade chocolate ice cream. Ours was marred by big ice crystals. The tangy Key lime pie makes a terrific finale, as does the bananas Foster, a big bowl of vanilla ice cream and a sauce boat of sauteed bananas, caramel and rum that are combined by the diner at the table. We were happy, too, with the warm chocolate pudding cake, the layered white and dark chocolate mousse sparked by a chunky raspberry compote and an unorthodox but nevertheless delicious Boston cream pie.</p>
        <p>Legal Sea Foods  Walt Whitman Mall, 160 Walt Whitman Road (Route 110), Huntington Station (631) 271-9777.</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Bustling New England-style fish house.  SERVICE -- Hit and miss.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- All chowders, crab cake, popcorn shrimp, blue cheese salad, seafood antipasto, lobsters, cioppino, swordfish, Cajun shrimp, fried clams, Key lime pie, Boston cream pie, bananas Foster, chocolate mousse, chocolate pudding cake.  WINE LIST -- Reads like a list of a much more expensive and formal restaurant, with 130-plus choices, including 28 half bottles, 15 selections by the glass and 3 samplers. Bottle prices: $15 to $45.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch, entrees $6 to $17 (lobster roll). At dinner, appetizers $3.50 to $15; entrees $10 to $46; desserts $3.25 to $5.75.  CREDIT CARDS -- All the majors.  HOURS -- 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. Monday through Thursday, till 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday; noon to 9 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS -- None taken. There is preferred seating, which means if you call ahead, the wait on a Saturday night will be 15 to 20 minutes rather than the up-to-an-hour wait for walk-ins.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Fully accessible.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
