<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00; Bring the Noise</title>
    <meta content="WLN092351" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eminem (Rapper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leland, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EEDF1F3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00; Bring the Noise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By By John Leland</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leland, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Leland explores renewed debate, sparked by Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation's opposition to rapper Eminem's lyrics and violence at New York's National Puerto Rican Day Parade, over whether music can contribute to climate of immorality and its new subtext, that just hearing songs can push unlawful crowd into mayhem; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten years back, I found myself on a witness stand in Alexander City, Ala., talking to a jury about rap music. The owner of a local record store had been charged with violating the city's obscenity ordinance for selling a cassette of 2 Live Crew's ''Move Somethin''' to a police officer. As a music critic, I was supposed to provide something of an art-historical framework for the group's raunchy rhymes and the music's roots in the South Bronx. The city prosecutor leaned in. But the music didn't stay in the ghetto, did it? he asked. He let the implications of his question hang in the air: once the lyrics started spilling out of the grooves and into the real world, there was no telling where they'd take us.</p>
        <p>A decade later, the debate is once again live. The Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation has led the charge against Eminem, whose raps include lines like, ''You faggots keep egging me on till I have you at knifepoint.'' In a taut statement, the group stated that his lyrics ''encourage violence against gay men and lesbians.'' More recently, in response to the sexual mayhem that followed this year's National Puerto Rican Day Parade, the event's board announced that in the future they might bar some rap acts. A member of the board, Federico Perez, who was careful not to blame the rappers directly, told The Times, ''If we can prevent music that is conducive to these acts that are outside the norm, well, we'll have to do that.'' And with that, the debate moved beyond the Parents Music Resource Center, beyond vague, theoretical claims about how music can contribute to a climate of immorality. The new subtext is that just hearing the songs can push a lawful crowd into mayhem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten years back, I found myself on a witness stand in Alexander City, Ala., talking to a jury about rap music. The owner of a local record store had been charged with violating the city's obscenity ordinance for selling a cassette of 2 Live Crew's ''Move Somethin''' to a police officer. As a music critic, I was supposed to provide something of an art-historical framework for the group's raunchy rhymes and the music's roots in the South Bronx. The city prosecutor leaned in. But the music didn't stay in the ghetto, did it? he asked. He let the implications of his question hang in the air: once the lyrics started spilling out of the grooves and into the real world, there was no telling where they'd take us.</p>
        <p>A decade later, the debate is once again live. The Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation has led the charge against Eminem, whose raps include lines like, ''You faggots keep egging me on till I have you at knifepoint.'' In a taut statement, the group stated that his lyrics ''encourage violence against gay men and lesbians.'' More recently, in response to the sexual mayhem that followed this year's National Puerto Rican Day Parade, the event's board announced that in the future they might bar some rap acts. A member of the board, Federico Perez, who was careful not to blame the rappers directly, told The Times, ''If we can prevent music that is conducive to these acts that are outside the norm, well, we'll have to do that.'' And with that, the debate moved beyond the Parents Music Resource Center, beyond vague, theoretical claims about how music can contribute to a climate of immorality. The new subtext is that just hearing the songs can push a lawful crowd into mayhem.</p>
        <p>Though such battles usually play best on Republican turf, this season the Democratic ticket is ready to rumble. As Joseph Lieberman, a point man on this issue, told the Los Angeles convention, ''No parent in America should be forced to compete with popular culture to raise their children.'' Al Gore seconded the sentiment, and his wife, Tipper, is, of course, a founder of the P.M.R.C.</p>
        <p>The promise of mass popular culture, whether a parade or a hit album, has always been that there is redemptive meaning in numbers. Early in the recently rereleased ''Gimme Shelter'' -- the documentary film about the Rolling Stones' 1969 concert at Altamont, where members of the Hell's Angels stabbed a man to death -- Mick Jagger touts this promise. He tells reporters that the free concert will create ''a microcosmic society which sets an example to the rest of America as to how one can behave in large gatherings.'' But this particular gathering is extraordinarily large -- 300,000 people -- and things quickly get out of control. The hippies are hurting themselves even before the Angels take to the job in earnest. When a few start to have bad trips, the organizers, reluctant to lay a bummer on the crowd, decline to issue a warning about the acid. Over the course of the movie, the late-60's ideal of togetherness turns into a dystopia of violence, revulsion and finally death. Some of the most searing music of the era becomes a soundtrack to a horror film.</p>
        <p>''Gimme Shelter'' and the Puerto Rican Day Parade aftermath show pop music's promise carried to one hormonal extreme. The lonely found strength in numbers; the numbers found expression in violence. But it's limiting to pose the debate in terms of whether the music spawned the violence. The music and the violence were both outgrowths of the very loneliness that draws people together into these mass experiences in the first place.</p>
        <p>I saw ''Gimme Shelter'' when I was a kid, and I was enthralled; I felt the same way when I first heard hip-hop in the late 70's, and I've been listening to it ever since. I haven't always liked what I heard, but even at its most offensive, it's still more unpredictable and creative than the other junk on the radio. And I can't quite give up on its possibilities: that this disturbing music could give voice to urgent loneliness, that by coming together to hear it, fans can find a respite. With some mixed feelings I recently introduced my 12-year-old son to the music of Eminem -- better he heard it from me, etc. By listening to it together, I hoped to provide a context in which he could make sense of it. He heard it, and he liked it. He thought the violence was just play-acting, but he thought the sadness in the songs was real.</p>
        <p>As strident as it may be, the anger in popular music is only a faint reflection of larger forces -- isolation, dislocation, fear -- and fighting it, instead of them, won't solve much. Better for MTV to surround Eminem with its usual gay-friendly programming, and the parade to bring rap into its family fold. Not because the messages are harmless, but because isolating them from civic life only lets them fester, unchecked and self-justifying, in the dark shadows beyond the spotlight's watchful gaze. For all their showy posturing, the Rolling Stones, like the rappers at the parade, were themselves at the mercy of the very real violence in the culture at large. In a new memoir, ''Hell's Angel: The Life and Times of Sonny Barger and the Hell's Angels Motorcycle Club'' (Morrow), the biker leader reveals just how captive the band was. As the carnage escalated, Keith Richards threatened to leave the stage. Barger ''stuck my pistol into his side and told him to start playing his guitar or he was dead.'' Richards obliged. He had met the real street fighting men. Debates about pop music worry about the man preaching sympathy for the Devil, but they often miss the real menace. It's standing just offstage, and sometimes it's dressed like an Angel.</p>
        <p>John Leland is a reporter at The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Leland is a reporter at The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
