<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pruning Season</title>
    <meta content="27HARRIST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Kretser, Michelle</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rose Grower, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1D9153EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pruning Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joanne Harris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harris, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Harris reviews novel The Rose Grower by Michelle de Kretser (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ROSE GROWER</p>
        <p>By Michelle de Kretser.</p>
        <p>299 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ROSE GROWER</p>
        <p>By Michelle de Kretser.</p>
        <p>299 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers. $25.</p>
        <p>The date is July 14, 1789, and the world is in flux. The first simmerings of unrest are barely perceptible in the small Gascon town of Castelnau, where Jean-Baptiste de Saint-Pierre, a provincial magistrate, and his three daughters, Claire, Sophie and Mathilde, lead lives of genteel poverty in their ancestral home, Montsignac. But there are omens in the sky -- thunder, fire, then a man falling earthward. The revolution has begun.</p>
        <p>For Stephen Fletcher, a young American balloonist who dreams of ''boundless possibility,'' it is a revolution of the heart. For Claire -- lovely, superficial and married -- his descent from the heavens brings a promise of excitement and romance. For Mathilde, the delightfully cynical 8-year-old (''Oh no -- another Rousseauist!''), he provides tales of adventure and distant lands. For Sophie, Saint-Pierre's quiet, unconventional second daughter, he embodies an impossible fantasy, a love she dare not articulate. Blinded by her infatuation with Stephen -- who, in his turn, has eyes only for Claire -- Sophie fails to notice the admiration of Joseph Morel, a tormented young physician who yearns above all things to ''ease the suffering with which this world is so rich endowed.'' But as both Stephen and Joseph are drawn inexorably into the revolutionary cause, we see how the good intentions of dreamers and enthusiasts can bring an entire world to chaos.</p>
        <p>''The Rose Grower'' is a lovely, meticulously researched first novel that evokes the beginnings of the Terror in crisp, elegant, compassionate prose. The revolution according to Michelle de Kretser is a powerfully human affair, a collection of personal histories, betrayals and tragedies. Like the citizens of Oran in ''The Plague,'' the people of Castelnau have little sense of the magnitude of what is happening around them; their concerns are more immediate. A letter to Sophie takes up a whole chapter. Against a backdrop of carnage and upheaval, old Saint-Pierre finds solace in the preparation of his grandmother's recipe for cruchade. To the magistrate and his family, the manipulative local butcher, Ricard, is more of a villain than any Paris politician. And, as in Camus's novel, true heroism is shown not by artists, ideologues or makers of history but by humble doctors and sanitary engineers.</p>
        <p>However, it is in Sophie, the rose grower of the title, that the true spirit of the novel resides. Her dream is the impossible rose, a crimson hybrid as yet undiscovered in the 18th century. Her influence -- quiet, reasonable, practical -- pervades every chapter like the scent from her garden. And the book is itself an extravagance of roses: damask roses and China roses; decorous roses and lascivious roses; blooms with names like Maiden's Blush and Robert le Diable. Through Sophie, we come to experience roses in every way: the taste of their petals, their colors and habits of growth, the shape of their leaves.</p>
        <p>Our appreciation of scent, Sophie insists, is instinctive -- like love, like hope. And her roses are not only an expression of her instincts, they are a means of honoring the memory of her dead mother, of gaining her father's approval. They are a release for her sexual yearnings, an outlet for her creativity and, finally, a symbol of the promise of a new future. Her crossbreeding of roses -- as radical in its way as any of the revolution's ideals -- represents ''an inarticulate longing for perfection.''</p>
        <p>This ambition, as Stephen puts it, to ''conjure the world differently'' exists here on many levels. From his balloon, Stephen sees vistas hitherto unknown. Throughout the country, the Jacobins lose sight of their original intentions. In the village, Joseph Morel wallows in filth and disease to bring hope to the people. Ironically, it is the romantic Stephen who eventually lapses into domesticated mediocrity, while the revolutionaries fall on one another in mounting greed and paranoia. Even Joseph becomes disillusioned. Only gentle Sophie does not waver. Braving violence, illness and thwarted love, she continues her pursuit of the crimson rose.</p>
        <p>In spite of its sly asides on Rousseau, ''The Rose Grower'' remains a profoundly optimistic book. Sophie's long-sought blossom symbolizes the triumph of the imagination, the instinctive -- and often disastrous -- search for perfection that accompanies some of the most horrific years of France's history. As one of de Kretser's characters observes, the revolution is like the ''course traced by a star as it wheels through the heavens.'' And yet, he adds, ''wheels, by their very nature, continue turning.''</p>
        <p>Joanne Harris is the author of the novels ''Chocolat'' and ''Blackberry Wine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joanne Harris is the author of the novels ''Chocolat'' and ''Blackberry Wine.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
