<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No-Name Defense Deserves Its Obscurity, Anand Shows</title>
    <meta content="27CHES$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DD1031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No-Name Defense Deserves Its Obscurity, Anand Shows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Viswanathan Anand of India and Vladimir Kramnik of Russia have been running neck and neck behind Garry Kasparov for the last seven years. Most of this time Anand has been second and Kramnik third, but lately it's Kramnik who has performed marginally better.</p>
        <p>Anand lost his championship match with Kasparov by 10 1/2-7 1/2 in 1995. Now it's Kramnik's turn. He will challenge Kasparov in London in October.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Viswanathan Anand of India and Vladimir Kramnik of Russia have been running neck and neck behind Garry Kasparov for the last seven years. Most of this time Anand has been second and Kramnik third, but lately it's Kramnik who has performed marginally better.</p>
        <p>Anand lost his championship match with Kasparov by 10 1/2-7 1/2 in 1995. Now it's Kramnik's turn. He will challenge Kasparov in London in October.</p>
        <p>In the most recent event in which the two met each other, the Dortmund Supertournament in mid-July, Anand showed just how close they were by tying with Kramnik for first place.</p>
        <p>How incisively Anand plays can be seen in his victory over the Dutch grandmaster Jeroen Piket in round three.</p>
        <p>The variation with 5 . . . b5 and 6 . . . Bc5 was always considered so weak that it has never acquired a name. Yet the long-recommended refutation, 7 Ne5 Ne5 8 d4 Bd4 9 Qd4, is scoffed at nowadays in view of 9 . . . d6 10 c3 O-O 11 f3 c5 12 Qd1 h6 13 a4 Bb7 14 ab ab 15 Ra8 Ba8 16 Na3 Bc6 17 Bf4 Qe7.</p>
        <p>After those moves, a draw resulted in Malakhov-Shchekachev in last year's Russian Championship. So far, White has not found a way to exploit his two bishops in this semi open formation.</p>
        <p>After 11 Na3, it seems that no one likes to defend the b5 pawn by 11 . . . b4. It is true that 12 Nc4 bc 13 de cb 14 Bb2 Ne5 15 Nfe5 de 16 Qd8 Kd8 17 Ne5 looks poor for Black.</p>
        <p>So, Piket, who is a connoisseur of this defense, chose to follow the majority opinion and sacrifice a pawn with 11 O-O.</p>
        <p>Anand's 14 Ra4!? was a more flexible integration of his position than 14 Be3. Piket could have taken a pawn with 14 . . . Ne4, but then 15 Bd5 Qe8 16 Qc2 Ne7 17 Be4 Qb5 18 Bh7 Kh8 19 Bd3 Qh5 20 Be2 leaves Black a pawn down without any counterchances.</p>
        <p>With 15 . . . h6, Piket deviates from 15 . . . Qd7 16 Bc2 d5 17 e5 Ne4 18 Nc3 as played in a Bologan-Tkachiev game in Enghien-les-Bains, France, last year.</p>
        <p>That game could have continued with 18 . . . Ne5 19 de Bf3 20 Qf3 Bf2 21 Kh1 Be1 22 Ne4 de 23 Qe4 Bd2! 24 Qh7 Kf8 25 Qh8 Ke7 26 Qh4 with a draw by perpetual check. What did Anand have in mind against that?</p>
        <p>Also, 15 . . . Ba5!? 16 Nc3 Bc3 17 bc Re4 18 Be3 Bf3 19 gf Re8, with White's bishop pair and his broken kingside minimizing each other, was worth exploration.</p>
        <p>After 16 Bc2, Piket's pressure against the white center was not succeeding. So he tried to break through with 16 . . . d5 17 e5 Ne4 18 Nc3 Re5, but after 19 Ne4 Re4 20 Be4 de, 21 d5!, his counterattack was dead.</p>
        <p>Piket's desperate counter with 21 . . . Bf3 22 gf Qh4 was coldbloodedly repulsed by Anand's 23 Rae4 Qf2 24 Kh1. After 24 . . . f5 25 Rc4! Na5 26 Rf1 Nc4 27 Rf2 Bf2 28 Qe2, Piket, seeing that he had to lose a piece, gave up.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
