<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Patient Life of Sacrifice, Touching Many</title>
    <meta content="27COLM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chow and Lam Laundry (Nyc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chow, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chow, Mimi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DB1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Patient Life of Sacrifice, Touching Many</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Jacobs Coping column on death of Peter Chow, Hong Kong immigrant who, with his wife, Mimi, ran Chow and Lam Laundry on Manhattan's East 10th Street; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I COULD have taken my dirty clothes to a half-dozen closer laundries, but Chow and Lam Laundry was worth the extra two-block schlep. The other places folded with careless abandon, leaving a tangle of unmatched socks at the bottom of your laundry bag.</p>
        <p>Not Mimi and Peter Chow. Sheets were folded so crisply, like linen origami, it felt shameful to use them. My laundry bag, dropped off as an unwieldy blob, came back a perfect square.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I COULD have taken my dirty clothes to a half-dozen closer laundries, but Chow and Lam Laundry was worth the extra two-block schlep. The other places folded with careless abandon, leaving a tangle of unmatched socks at the bottom of your laundry bag.</p>
        <p>Not Mimi and Peter Chow. Sheets were folded so crisply, like linen origami, it felt shameful to use them. My laundry bag, dropped off as an unwieldy blob, came back a perfect square.</p>
        <p>But it wasn't just fragrant, well-folded clothes that drew me to their cramped, overheated storefront on East 10th Street and Second Avenue. Peter and Mimi dispensed good cheer, as if they actually enjoyed washing other people's garments.</p>
        <p>After a recent vacation, I arrived to find Mimi alone, her usual smile weak, her eyes weighted by gray bags. The Chows were always together, so I knew something was wrong. ''Where's your husband?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>Peter had died a week before, she said, killed by the asthma that had grown steadily worse over the last decade. He was 53. A doctor had warned him about the laundry's dust and lint, but there were three children in college, debts to repay and dignity to maintain.</p>
        <p>I never knew Peter, just that he was helpful, chatty and seemingly intelligent. He was one of the many human cogs we encounter each day that make city life more palatable. But I learned that he was much more. He had been a teacher in Hong Kong, but like many immigrants with limited English, felt too old to reinvent himself in America.</p>
        <p>I also discovered that despite the brusque anonymity that defines New York, some people actually care about the folks who clean their wardrobes. Nearly two dozen customers showed up for the funeral in Queens. Cards, flowers and food overwhelmed the nook where the couple exchanged dirty clothes for beige tickets.</p>
        <p>With a brother in New York and a few thousand dollars in savings, Peter moved his family here in 1984. Life in Hong Kong was good, but Peter thought the schools emphasized rote memorization over literature, art and free thinking. And with two universities in a city of six million people, he feared the competition would turn his children into frazzled automatons.</p>
        <p>In New York the family scraped by. Mimi, once a teacher, took on housekeeping and cooking jobs. Peter hawked cheap toys in the subway, ironed shirts and worked in a jewelry factory.</p>
        <p>One day Peter noticed an empty storefront on 10th Street. Inspired by other Chinese immigrants who did well in the laundry business, he borrowed money from friends and signed a 10-year lease. The first few years they worked seven days, often sleeping at the back of the shop. In 12 years, they never took a vacation. ''We've never even seen the Empire State Building,'' Mimi said.</p>
        <p>Even until the end, when business was good, five hours of sleep was a luxury. Peter's asthma worsened, and his hands became so cracked from the damp heat that customers would avert their eyes.</p>
        <p>On her 51st birthday last weekend, Mimi sat on a stool behind the counter recalling their life together. Peter's worn coat was still hanging next to a pair of toothbrushes, two washcloths and two mugs.</p>
        <p>She had come back to work a few days after burying her husband. ''Peter would have wanted it that way,'' she said in Mandarin, her eyes welling up.</p>
        <p>She worries about her halting English and carrying on alone but says she has no choice. Her daughter, Lisa, 20, has two more years at Barnard. David, 23, is in his second year at Columbia Medical School, and Antony, 25, just graduated from law school.</p>
        <p>Mimi tries to stifle her anger, the sense that Peter worked himself to death. If only they had had health insurance, she said.</p>
        <p>Her son David told me that despite the years of thankless work, his parents were content. ''People might think he had no joy in his life,'' he said. ''But he was happy just hanging out with my mom. That's why he didn't mind working so hard.''</p>
        <p>He could also see the fruits of his toil in his children. Other Chinese-born parents pressured their children to study math or computer science, to drive hard for the Ivy League, but not Peter. ''His motto,'' Lisa said, ''was do whatever makes you happy.''</p>
        <p>Mimi says she feels Peter at her side, reminding her to take breaks, to eat well and to be patient with fussy customers. She always wears a smile, even if it's frail. ''Peter used to do all the ironing,'' she said with a laugh, glancing at the waiting pile of rumpled shirts. ''I hate to iron.''</p>
        <p>A man drops off his bag, asks for the usual (Woolite, no bleach, no creases) and lays a hand on her shoulder. ''How are you, Mimi?'' he asks.</p>
        <p>''Fine,'' she says unconvincingly.</p>
        <p>But she won't stay a laundress forever, perhaps a few more years until her children start working. ''I want to enjoy my grandchildren,'' she says. ''At least one of us should be there for that.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
