<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00: On Language; Lookism</title>
    <meta content="WLN092601" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDF1F3EF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 8-27-00: On Language; Lookism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column explores meaning and use of relatively new word lookism, meaning prejudice or discrimination based on appearance, and media's oversensitivity in calling Vice Presidential candidate Joe Lieberman a Jewish person rather than a Jew (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Communism is all but dead, and socialism is passe. Capitalism is doing fine, but as an attack word it has been replaced by market economy. Has the suffix -ism lost its sting?</p>
        <p>In politics, ism-itis is receding, but in reference to forms of discrimination, the beatism goes on. On the analogy of racism, a term that began as racialism in 1907 but dropped the second syllable in 1935, we have sexism (1968) and ageism (1969). And now a relatively new entry:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Communism is all but dead, and socialism is passe. Capitalism is doing fine, but as an attack word it has been replaced by market economy. Has the suffix -ism lost its sting?</p>
        <p>In politics, ism-itis is receding, but in reference to forms of discrimination, the beatism goes on. On the analogy of racism, a term that began as racialism in 1907 but dropped the second syllable in 1935, we have sexism (1968) and ageism (1969). And now a relatively new entry:</p>
        <p>''We face a world,'' says Nancy Etcoff, a psychologist at Massachusetts General Hospital, ''where lookism is one of the most pervasive but denied prejudices.'' She is author of ''Survival of the Prettiest''; though her title is Darwinian, her message bewails the evolution of the power of beauty.</p>
        <p>Oxford's 1999 ''20th Century Words,'' by John Ayto, defines lookism as ''prejudice or discrimination on the grounds of appearance (i.e., uglies are done down and the beautiful people get all the breaks).'' The lexicographer's earliest citation was in The Washington Post Magazine in 1978, which reported that fat people coined a defensive word: ''lookism -- discrimination based on looks.''</p>
        <p>When the G.O.P. candidate George W. Bush flashed a half-smile that struck some as a smirk, he was widely derided for this facial expression. ''Bush isn't the only presidential candidate to suffer from this elaborately sanctioned lookism,'' wrote Julia Keller in The Chicago Tribune. ''Former Republican hopeful Steve Forbes endured numerous remarks about his blinkless stare . . . while Al Gore has been called 'wooden' so often that he probably measures himself by the board foot.''</p>
        <p>The word's usage is transatlantic. ''Lookism is a crime,'' a writer in London's Daily Telegraph observed in 1991, ''on the same level as racism, sexism, ageism, heterosexism, classism, etc.'' In Barre, Me., last year, a workshop was held on the topic ''Today's Pressures: Drugs, Alcohol, Sex and Lookism.''</p>
        <p>A Reuters reviewer of the new Oxford Compact English Dictionary had a bright lead: ''So there you are, all decked out in chuddies, carpenters and a shrug with a brand-new buzz cut, and for some reason your best friend refuses to talk to you. It is probably a serious case of lookism.''</p>
        <p>O.K.: chuddies are underpants, carpenters are pants with loops for tools, a shrug is a tight-fitting cardigan and a buzz cut is a close crewcut. I'll also pass along the O.C.E.D.'s screenager, ''Internet- or computer-addicted teenager.''</p>
        <p>The extension of lookism is already in circulation: if you call out to someone you consider in any way attractive, ''Hey, good-lookin','' you are a lookist.</p>
        <p>Gentile-American Person's Guide</p>
        <p>''What disturbs me,'' writes Jack Tucker from somewhere in cyberspace, ''is the politically correct way that Senator Joseph Lieberman has to be referred to on television: 'a Jewish person.' The media don't want to say he is a 'Jew' because the word sounds so harsh.''</p>
        <p>Not only is Mr. Tucker correct in construing media as plural, he is also sensitive to the oversensitivity of some newscasters. He was not the only one to notice the lengthy terminology: in a related vein, a call came from Gerald Rafshoon, the documentary producer who was a Carter White House aide, to ask, ''How come I never hear 'Episcopalian-American'?''</p>
        <p>The use of the word Jew is not a problem in print journalism; both The New York Times and The Washington Post headlined ''First Jew on Major U.S. Ticket.'' One reason is to save space, a consideration of all headline writers; another is that speaking -- even in quick news flashes -- differs from writing. Speaking is more personal. That's why many in broadcast and cable news preferred first Jewish person or first Jewish-American or even first person of the Hebrew faith to be so named. They had the vague feeling that the monosyllabic word might be taken as offensive -- as it is when delivered with a curled lip -- and went out of their way not to offend.</p>
        <p>No Jew would say, ''I am a Jewish person'' or, except in the most formal circumstances, ''Mine is the Hebrew faith.'' Jews are comfortable with the adjective, ''I'm Jewish,'' or the noun, ''I'm a Jew.'' The reluctance of non-Jews to use the ''harsh'' word is well intentioned, but such overly sensitive shying-away from the J-noun draws a sardonic smile from some Jews.</p>
        <p>When many whites referred to blacks in their speech, they hesitated to apply the noun to a person; instead of saying, ''He's a black,'' they would say, ''He's a black guy,'' as if the use of black as an adjective to modify guy somehow removed it from any interpretation as derogation. This awkwardness was removed by the adoption of African-American; that compound noun is not as stark as black.</p>
        <p>Nouns often sound harsher than the adjectives on which they are based; thus Jew is felt to be stronger than Jewish, which could also be taken to mean ''like a Jew.'' Take blond/blonde: ''She's blond'' is acceptable as a description of hair color, but she's a blonde, using the noun form to impute fun-loving characteristics, could be taken by some to be the newly dread lookism.</p>
        <p>What about Jewish-American; is it any different from American Jew? Yes; the difference is context. When I am in a voting booth, I can fairly be counted by demographers to be Jewish-American, and when I am in a synagogue, I can be identified as an American Jew.</p>
        <p>Back to Senator Lieberman. He is undeniably a person and a member of a religious faith, but the quick identification is best: Joe's a Jew. So is his wife, Hadassah, whose name is the Hebrew equivalent of Esther. The feminine form Jewess, popularized in Sir Walter Scott's ''Ivanhoe'' (1820), has long been considered sexist, like actress.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
