<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spa Is Out to Change Image Of an Underpampered Area</title>
    <meta content="27SPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cynergy New York Spa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grace, Cynthia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5D71431F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spa Is Out to Change Image Of an Underpampered Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cynthia Grace, clinical psychologist, has opened Cynergy New York Spa and Wellness Cenrer with her husband on 135th Street in Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harlem is not known as an oasis of peace and tranquillity. But Cynthia Grace hopes her new spa will help  change that.</p>
        <p>''It's time,'' she said. ''People in Harlem really need this type of service. The interest is there and the income diversity supports it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harlem is not known as an oasis of peace and tranquillity. But Cynthia Grace hopes her new spa will help  change that.</p>
        <p>''It's time,'' she said. ''People in Harlem really need this type of service. The interest is there and the income diversity supports it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Grace, a clinical psychologist and 20-year spa user, opened Cynergy New York Spa and Wellness Center with her husband last month on 135th Street between Frederick Douglass and Adam Clayton Powell Boulevards. They say the day spa is the first ever to operate in Harlem. For many people, the venture and others like it are evidence that the area's demographics are changing and that the second Harlem renaissance is under way.</p>
        <p>Cynergy is earthy, scented with lavender, grapefruit and eucalyptus, and decorated with African masks, African-American-inspired paintings and fresh floral arrangements. Dr. Grace said the decor was meant to create a womblike atmosphere. The spa's staff of 10, all of African descent, offer services like Rain Forest Mini Facials, Harlem's Heaven Reflexology and Ancestral Aromatherapy Massage.</p>
        <p>''It's wonderful to have this kind of service in our community,'' Elsie Simmons said as she waited for her mauve nail polish to dry. ''It's just kind of nice to have black people taking care of me. It's kind of a comforting feeling.'' Ms. Simmons owns the EMC Business Institute, a computer training school in Harlem, and used to go to Elizabeth Arden downtown.</p>
        <p>The spa is just a few blocks from Striver's Row, on 138th and 139th Streets. In the 1920's, during the Harlem renaissance, that area flourished as professional blacks moved into 19th-century town houses and helped make it the commercial center of Harlem. Beginning in the 1950's, the neighborhood went into decline, and many black-owned businesses moved to 125th Street.</p>
        <p>Since the 1990's, there has been tremendous growth in this part of Harlem, said Karen Phillips, president of the Abyssinian Development Corporation, which is run by the Abyssinian Baptist Church.</p>
        <p>Today the neighborhood has a custom shoemaker, a bakery, boutiques, restaurants and significantly more housing than it did just a few years ago. Ms. Phillips said several franchises, including the International House of Pancakes and Papa John's Pizza, were also scheduled to move into the area.</p>
        <p>''What we're trying to do,'' she said, ''is educate the residents and let them know that there are a lot of goods and services that they can get in their neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
