<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>32-Story Hotel Is Rising on Baltimore's Harborfront</title>
    <meta content="27AFOC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baltimore (Md)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Marriott Waterfront Hotel</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belfoure, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DB1731F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>32-Story Hotel Is Rising on Baltimore's Harborfront</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES BELFOURE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belfoure, Charles</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inner Harbor East is considered linchpin in $500 million redevelopment of 32-block industrial area that connects Baltimore's Inner Harbor with residential neighborhoods of Fells Point and Canton; 32-story Baltimore Marriott Waterfront Hotel will be city's largest hotel and is nearing completion as part of redevelopment; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 32-STORY hotel that will be the city's largest is nearing completion as part of a $500 million redevelopment of a gritty industrial area that links the original Inner Harbor project with two gentrified historic neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Inner Harbor East, with three million square feet of space on 18 acres, is considered the linchpin in the redevelopment of  the 32-block industrial area that connects  the Inner Harbor with the residential neighborhoods of Fells Point and Canton. With several other pending projects, it will help create a continuous path of development along two miles of the harbor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 32-STORY hotel that will be the city's largest is nearing completion as part of a $500 million redevelopment of a gritty industrial area that links the original Inner Harbor project with two gentrified historic neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Inner Harbor East, with three million square feet of space on 18 acres, is considered the linchpin in the redevelopment of  the 32-block industrial area that connects  the Inner Harbor with the residential neighborhoods of Fells Point and Canton. With several other pending projects, it will help create a continuous path of development along two miles of the harbor.</p>
        <p>Developed by H&amp;S Properties Development Corporation of Baltimore, Inner Harbor East will eventually be nine contiguous blocks of residential, retail, office and entertainment space. The current construction is actually the second phase of the development. It began in 1995 with the construction of the 130,000-square-foot headquarters for  Sylvan Learning Systems and the Promenade, a 113-unit rental building, at a total cost of $33 million.</p>
        <p>When finished next February, the 750-room Baltimore Marriott Waterfront will be the first hotel to be built here in 15 years. Aside from providing guest rooms for business travelers and tourists, the $135 million  concrete tower will provide critically needed space for convention visitors.</p>
        <p>The hotel has a separate entry and lobby for busloads of conventioneers. Two levels are specifically for convention activities, including column-free ballrooms of 20,000 and 17,000 square feet that can be divided into smaller meeting spaces. Rooms with hospitality suites for seminars surround the ballrooms, and there is a space designed as a command post for meeting planners. A large freight elevator can bring displays and equipment, including automobiles, directly from the street to the ballrooms for meetings.</p>
        <p>The new hotel has already had an effect on convention business, according to Michael S. Beatty, a vice president of H&amp;S. ''The Shriners convention is booked for 2005,'' he said. ''That's 30,000 visitors.''</p>
        <p>Regular guests will arrive under a porte-cochere about 20 yards from the edge of the harbor and enter a vaulted lobby. The penthouse level contains rooms of usual size as well as luxury suites with views for five miles in all directions.</p>
        <p>Next to the hotel tower is a 50,000-square-foot office-retail complex, with 600 parking spaces, being built for $20 million. A 210,000-square-foot office building, already fully leased, that shares a two-story retail base with an adjacent hotel is under construction  on the block bounded by Fleet Street, Central Avenue, Exeter Street and Aliceanna Street four blocks away. The 207-room hotel will fly the Marriott Courtyard flag, and be intended for business travelers. The $22 million complex, to be completed in November, will have a Fresh Fields supermarket on the first floor and a 370-space parking garage above it.</p>
        <p>BEGINNING in early 2001 and across from the Marriot Courtyard on Exeter Street, construction will start on a 90,000-square-foot entertainment complex that will include an 18-screen movie theater and 40,000 square feet of retail stores on the street level.</p>
        <p>A 450,000-square-foot office and retail building with 1,200 spaces of underground parking is due to begin early next year in the adjacent block. The residential part of the project along Lancaster Street will begin as well, with the construction of a 225-unit long-term-stay hotel and two luxury apartment buildings with 225 and 90 units. A 300,000-square-foot office building by the edge of the water is also being considered.</p>
        <p>H&amp;S was not the original developer of the project. The first developer assembled the parcels in the 1980's, but got into financial difficulties and came close to foreclosure. When the bank was about to call its loan, city officials asked John Paterakis Sr., who owns H&amp;S Bakeries, a major supplier to regional food stores, a few blocks to the east, to buy the loan. He did, expecting the city to acquire the property from him at the same price he paid for it.</p>
        <p>When it did not, Mr. Paterakis, with no development experience to speak of, reluctantly started the project himself. He brought in a co-developer to obtain approvals and create a master plan. In 1995, frustrated by delays, Mr. Paterakis became an active one, Mr. Beatty said, constructing the Sylvan building and the Promenade.</p>
        <p>For all its early reticence about development, H&amp;S is now diving headlong into two more large projects directly south of Inner Harbor East. It has formed a joint venture with a major Baltimore developer, Streuver Brothers Eccles &amp; Rouse, and is completing the acquisition of the vacant Allied Signal site from Honeywell Corporation. About $300 million is expected to be spent to turn the 27-acre parcel into a mixed-use development to be called Harbor Point, with 1.8 million square feet.</p>
        <p>Near the southeastern edge of the Allied Signal site is a six-acre parcel along Thames Street, on which Streuver Brothers Eccles &amp; Rouse and H&amp;S will build 141 residential units and 330,000 square feet of office space. That project will cost $90 million and be completed in 2003.</p>
        <p>Other pending projects, a few blocks away, include an 80,000-square-foot four-story building for Whitman Requardt &amp; Associates, one of the oldest engineering firms in the city. The Living Classroom Foundation will build the nation's first museum dedicated to black seamen and shipbuilders a few blocks east of the Allied site.</p>
        <p>H&amp;S Bakeries, which started in a row house in East Baltimore 60 years ago, owns several blocks and buildings east of the project, but has no plans to relocate or to  redevelop that property.</p>
        <p>Inner Harbor East's tower was criticized as out of scale with the adjacent neighborhood of Little Italy, criticism that was rejected by its developers, who cited zoning that would have allowed them to build a taller structure. ''We could have built a 430-foot hotel, but we kept it at 330 feet and reduced the bulk of the other buildings so they wouldn't overwhelm the streets,'' Mr. Beatty said.</p>
        <p>Critics still complain about the scale of the Inner Harbor East project, but accept  its economic value for Baltimore's waterfront. ''Our project will be a huge driver for people who want to live down here,'' Mr. Beatty said. ''We've tried to create a 24-hour environment with a mix of residences, offices, retail and entertainment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
