<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Ignores the Pain And Pushes His Lead to 9</title>
    <meta content="27GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nec Invitational (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D71031F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Ignores the Pain And Pushes His Lead to 9</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>AKRON, Ohio, Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tiger Woods leads after 3 rounds of NEC Invitational golf tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An insect stung Tiger Woods today, but the final two holes bit Phil Mickelson.</p>
        <p>After cutting Woods's lead from 11 strokes to 6 during today's third round of the NEC Invitational, Mickelson made crucial blunders: a bogey at No. 17, followed by a three-putt double-bogey at No. 18. Meanwhile, despite being stung on his left ring finger on the 15th green, Woods shot his third consecutive round in the 60's (67) and he will enter the final round at Firestone Country Club with a comfortable nine-stroke lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An insect stung Tiger Woods today, but the final two holes bit Phil Mickelson.</p>
        <p>After cutting Woods's lead from 11 strokes to 6 during today's third round of the NEC Invitational, Mickelson made crucial blunders: a bogey at No. 17, followed by a three-putt double-bogey at No. 18. Meanwhile, despite being stung on his left ring finger on the 15th green, Woods shot his third consecutive round in the 60's (67) and he will enter the final round at Firestone Country Club with a comfortable nine-stroke lead.</p>
        <p>Setting a tournament scoring record for 54 holes (192, 64-61-67) and extending the seven-stroke lead he began the day with, Woods was cruising at 18 under par heading into Sunday's final round. Hal Sutton, Mickelson and Phillip Price were tied for second place at nine under par, but does anyone really expect the world's No. 1 player to lose a nine-stroke lead with 18 holes to play?</p>
        <p>Officially, the tournament ends Sunday. Realistically, Woods has secured his eighth victory this season, and if he captures the $1 million first-place check in this World Golf Championships event, it will raise his earnings this year to more than $7.6 million.</p>
        <p>Woods's three-round total of 192 broke the previous Firestone 54-hole tournament record set by Jose Maria Olazabal (195) in 1994. But more than records, Woods wants victories. And after three sparkling rounds, including a nine-under-par 61 on Friday that tied the course record, he was in position to coast home on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''If I can just make pars on Sunday, somebody is going to have to shoot really low to beat me,'' said Woods, who is trying to become the first back-to-back winner at Firestone since Jack Nicklaus in 1962 and '63. ''I had a big lead, and with a big lead, all you need to do is make a bunch of pars. That's what I did today. You don't need to put a lot of pressure on yourself with an 11-stroke lead. They have to come and get you.''</p>
        <p>The most precarious part of Woods's day came on the 15th green, when he was stung on the left ring finger by an insect that was walking across his putting line. Woods was uncertain whether it was a bee or a wasp. But he was certain that it was painful.</p>
        <p>''I had my glove on, I tried to pick him up and throw him away, and he whipped his tail around and got me,'' Woods said. ''I got stung. It doesn't feel very good. The stinger is still in me. It hurt quite a bit.''</p>
        <p>But it did not deter Woods from his mission, as he ended his day making par on the final 14 holes after a torrid start to his round. He built his 11-stroke lead with a birdie-eagle-birdie barrage that thrilled his huge gallery and immediately put the rest of the field on notice. Apparently, Woods had enough drama last weekend, when he won the P.G.A. Championship in a thrilling three-hole playoff against Bob May.</p>
        <p>This weekend, a playoff should not be necessary. Instead of easing into his round, Woods crammed most of his best shots into the first three holes. He birdied No. 1 with a 10-foot putt. He made eagle at the par-5, 497-yard No. 2, using a driver and a 6-iron to reach the fringe in two shots, then making a 15-foot putt. Woods then birdied No. 3 with a gorgeous pitching wedge approach shot from 127 yards that he hit within 2 feet of the hole, setting up an easy tap-in for birdie.</p>
        <p>Before Mickelson could break a sweat, Woods had gone from 15 under par to 19 under, increasing his lead to 11 strokes over Mickelson, who was still at eight under. Give Mickelson credit for playing solid golf from that point through No. 16. He chipped in from 22 feet for birdie at No. 15, then at the par-5, 620-yard No. 16, Mickelson hit a huge drive, hit his second shot over the green, then got up and down for birdie to reach 12 under par, while Woods was still at 18 under.</p>
        <p>If Mickelson could have made par at No. 17 and No. 18, he would have entered the final round down by six strokes, with a much more realistic chance to win. Instead, he hit his second shot at the par-4 No. 17 over the green into deep rough, left his chip short, then missed a 12-foot par attempt. And at the par-4 No. 18, after a poor drive into the rough, followed by an approach shot that landed short of the green, Mickelson gave away crucial strokes. His chip shot landed 6 feet from the hole. Then he missed the 6-footer for par and shocked everyone by missing his 3-foot putt for bogey.</p>
        <p>Mickelson left the green with a stunned look on his face. Meanwhile, Woods appeared well on his way to adding another runaway victory, perhaps similar in size to his 15-stroke triumph at this year's United States Open.</p>
        <p>''It may be more drama for the people watching to have a finish like we did last week,'' Woods said. ''But I would have much rather have it where it's a lot like the U.S. Open.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>HAL SUTTON, who shot Saturday's low round of 65, made a hole in one at No. 12, using a 5-iron from 188 yards.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
