<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="27CRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5DE133AF934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAX VON SYDOW is so remarkably vulnerable in Bille August's PELLE THE CONQUEROR (1987) that watching him is almost painful at times. It's like seeing an aged fighter, obviously defeated, stagger back for round after round, with a courage dredged up from heaven knows where. Mr. von Sydow plays a destitute Swedish widower who goes to Denmark to make a new life for himself and his little boy, Pelle (Pelle Hvenegaard). But father and son end up as little more than indentured servants on a cruel man's farm, where life is a soap opera of seduction, emotional need, romantic tragedy and revenge - and a little cognac helps everybody get through the day. A drama about dashed hopes and dreams that don't come true, ''Pelle'' won the best foreign language film Oscar - Sunday at 1:30 p.m. on Bravo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAX VON SYDOW is so remarkably vulnerable in Bille August's PELLE THE CONQUEROR (1987) that watching him is almost painful at times. It's like seeing an aged fighter, obviously defeated, stagger back for round after round, with a courage dredged up from heaven knows where. Mr. von Sydow plays a destitute Swedish widower who goes to Denmark to make a new life for himself and his little boy, Pelle (Pelle Hvenegaard). But father and son end up as little more than indentured servants on a cruel man's farm, where life is a soap opera of seduction, emotional need, romantic tragedy and revenge - and a little cognac helps everybody get through the day. A drama about dashed hopes and dreams that don't come true, ''Pelle'' won the best foreign language film Oscar - Sunday at 1:30 p.m. on Bravo.</p>
        <p>They've been talking for years now about a remake of THE WOMEN (1939), which was never even nominated for an Oscar, but the original is sacred to many movie fans. Norma Shearer, Joan Crawford and Rosalind Russell are glorious as the noble wife, the other woman and the village gossip in Clare Boothe's savage all-woman comedy about marriage, divorce and rampant cattiness among the Park Avenue set. How can you not love a movie with lines like ''Can the sob stuff, Mrs. Haines'' and ''I've had two years to grow claws, Mother - jungle red''? George Cukor directed - Thursday at 11:30 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Billy Wilder directed an all-male cast (unless you count the female extras who appear as Russian prisoners) in STALAG 17 (1953), the intense, fascinating comic drama about American soldiers in a World War II German prisoner-of-war camp. William Holden won the best actor Oscar for his role as Sefton, the unlikable wheeler-dealer whose barracks-mates suspect of being an informer. Otto Preminger does an acting turn as Von Scherbach, Peter Graves is the security officer with a secret, Robert Strauss is Animal (who has an almost pathological crush on Betty Grable), and Harvey Lembeck is his fun-loving pal Harry (who looks lovely in a makeshift wig) - Sunday at 5:30 p.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>When Edward Burns made THE BROTHERS MCMULLEN (1995) for a repoted $25,000 or so (before post-production costs), it won the top prize at the Sundance Film Festival and he was hailed as the hot young filmmaker of the moment. Mr. Burns, now 32, has gone on to other, more expensive films, but the charm of his first work holds up nicely. He plays one of three brothers temporarily living together in their parents' Long Island house. All have assorted problems with women and what has been described as a strongly Irish-Catholic sense of sin - Saturday at 8 p.m., Saturday/Early Sunday 1:15 a.m. on IFC.</p>
        <p>Some things remain true from generation to generation. When a teenager's parents leave town, he or she must immediately give a party. Reginald Hudlin managed to make that story fresh in HOUSE PARTY (1990), a musical of sorts that's also a comedy of teenage manners, strong on exuberance and authenticity. The stars are Robin Harris and Christopher Reid, the rappers knowns as Kid 'n' Play. Mr. Harris plays the event's young host; Mr. Reid is an invited guest who will do anything to get to the party, even though he's grounded. You see, there's this girl he likes - Saturday at 3 p.m. on Channel 11.</p>
        <p>- Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
