<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tamara Hardesty, Howard Hsu</title>
    <meta content="27HARD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARDESTY, TAMARA GAVRIELLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HSU, HOWARD PITT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DA1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tamara Hardesty, Howard Hsu</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tamara Gavrielle Hardesty, a classical singer, and Howard Pitt Hsu, a music teacher, were married yesterday by the Rev. Paul Gilbert at St. John's of Lattingtown Episcopal Church in Locust Valley, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hardesty, 29, is keeping her name. She is a lyric soprano and has performed with L'Opera Francais de New York and the Dicapo Opera Theater. She graduated from the Manhattan School of Music and received a master's degree in opera performance from the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tamara Gavrielle Hardesty, a classical singer, and Howard Pitt Hsu, a music teacher, were married yesterday by the Rev. Paul Gilbert at St. John's of Lattingtown Episcopal Church in Locust Valley, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hardesty, 29, is keeping her name. She is a lyric soprano and has performed with L'Opera Francais de New York and the Dicapo Opera Theater. She graduated from the Manhattan School of Music and received a master's degree in opera performance from the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The bride is a daughter of Chava Telem Hardesty of Augusta, W.Va., and Thomas Jefferson Hardesty of Sigourney, Iowa. Her mother is a medical indexer with the National Library of Medicine in Bethesda, Md. The bride's father retired as a staff writer for The Oskaloosa Herald in Oskaloosa, Iowa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hsu, 30, teaches music at the Harlem School of the Arts in New York, a community arts school. He is also a conductor and has led the Bronx Arts Ensemble, a chamber group, and the orchestra of the Lake George, N.Y., Opera Festival. He graduated from the University of Pennsylvania and received a master's degree in music from the San Francisco Conservatory of Music.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is a son of Chun-chin and Tse-chi Hsu of Pittsburgh. His mother retired as a manager of Asian Express, a restaurant in Pittsburgh. His father is an emeritus professor of education at the University of Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>It is good that first impressions are not always lasting impressions. When Ms. Hardesty laid eyes on Mr. Hsu in 1991, he had just fled from his roach-infested apartment in New York and was seeking refuge at a friend's apartment nearby, where Ms. Hardesty was living as a roommate. When Mr. Hsu entered, he was dragging his possessions jammed into two pieces of luggage wrapped in garbage bags (to keep the roaches out).</p>
        <p>''I thought, 'Who is that guy with trash bags for luggage?' '' Ms. Hardesty remembered. It was a brief moment and the only time they met during Mr. Hsu's two-day stay at the apartment.</p>
        <p>When they met three years later, in San Francisco, she did not remember that he was ''the garbage bag man.'' In fact, she did not remember him at all. His phone number had been given to her by their mutual friend from the Manhattan apartment. She had just arrived to join the apprentice program of the San Francisco Opera and was feeling alone. (''Had I remembered our first encounter,'' she now says, ''I wouldn't have called him in the first place.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Hsu, for his part, did not remember it either. They had dinner together.</p>
        <p>''I thought she was way out of my league,'' he recalled. But as a conductor he had known singers before and found them, he said, ''very self-centered and extroverted,'' so he did not care.</p>
        <p>She said, ''He is nerdier than I was used to, but I went home thinking, 'What a perfect husband he would make.' '' She felt, however, that at 22 she was too young to marry. A friend changed her mind.</p>
        <p>''My friend said, 'If he is everything you are looking for, then you just have to go for it,' '' Ms. Hardesty remembered.</p>
        <p>They began dating in 1994. One day that summer, they were in Mr. Hsu's apartment when he said, ''I have something for you.'' Strains of ''Der Rosenkavalier'' by Richard Strauss wafted through the room as he presented to her a glass rose, an allusion to the silver rose in the opera, a symbol of engagement. The opera is one of Mr. Hsu's favorites, one of the few in which a pair of lovers live happily every after.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
