<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watching the World, Never Mind the Cars, Go By</title>
    <meta content="27MEDI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DC1231F934A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watching the World, Never Mind the Cars, Go By</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dozens of older people who have become fixtures on benches along Broadway Mall, median that stretches from Columbus Circle to Washington Heights; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After five days of rain and clouds, the sun decided to shine over West 80th Street and Broadway one recent afternoon. Shoppers were giddy with the weather, swishing their bags and grinning as they darted in and out of stores. Everyone seemed to have somewhere to be and something to do, and so most overlooked Ethel Berg in the median.</p>
        <p>She was the woman in the blue corduroys and the rainbow plaid blouse, her slim, veiny hands clutching a vinyl handbag and her dyed auburn hair sprouting up like the actress Mary Martin's once did in ''Peter Pan.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After five days of rain and clouds, the sun decided to shine over West 80th Street and Broadway one recent afternoon. Shoppers were giddy with the weather, swishing their bags and grinning as they darted in and out of stores. Everyone seemed to have somewhere to be and something to do, and so most overlooked Ethel Berg in the median.</p>
        <p>She was the woman in the blue corduroys and the rainbow plaid blouse, her slim, veiny hands clutching a vinyl handbag and her dyed auburn hair sprouting up like the actress Mary Martin's once did in ''Peter Pan.''</p>
        <p>She was only one of dozens of people in their 70's and 80's who spent their day at the 240 benches along the Broadway Mall, which stretches from Columbus Circle to Washington Heights. These men and women often dress in their Sunday best -- fedoras and bow ties, gloves and heels -- and they rarely venture beyond their favorite bench. They are fixtures of their intersections.</p>
        <p>A median is a curious hangout, though. Wind and eye-watering exhaust whip by with the passing cars and drown out any quiet. A median is not beautiful, either, when compared with the lush views offered by nearby Riverside Park and Central Park. But Ms. Berg, 85, would never choose a peaceful park over her noisy perch.</p>
        <p>So, what's the attraction?</p>
        <p>''The mall is the poor man's oasis on the Upper West Side,'' said Alan Moss of the Department of Parks. ''You are just in the middle of everything, and seniors, especially, like to sit and watch the world go by.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Berg knows there is more to it. ''In the park, you find young women and babies,'' she said. ''Here, we find each other.''</p>
        <p>To appreciate the allure of the mall, which was created in 1904 to cover construction work on the Seventh Avenue subway line, is to understand Ms. Berg's daily routine. At 8 a.m., Ms. Berg, a former secretary for Young &amp; Rubicam, awakes to an empty apartment on West 79th Street. Her husband and her sister died a few years ago, and her busy daughter lives nearby. She watches television until after lunch, and then she heads to her bench. A couple of retired Cuban hairdressers have claimed the block north of her, but she has not met them because she does not stray from her own.</p>
        <p>''I live on this block, so why should I go further?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>Unlike some median regulars, she never brings anything to read because it makes her dizzy. Instead, she chats with those who stop to rest weary feet or catch their breath. At 5 p.m., she goes home and falls asleep listening to talk radio.</p>
        <p>But before she leaves, Ms. Berg will usually see her friend. It is this friendship that keeps her coming back.</p>
        <p>''I have a friend that I met on the bench, and I see her every day,'' she said. ''She remembers this neighborhood when it was fancy, so she doesn't like it now. But I think it's O.K.''</p>
        <p>And sure enough, a few minutes later a prim woman with a careful blonde coiffure and orange lipstick came strolling toward Ms. Berg's bench. And there they sat for hours, chatting in the sunshine.</p>
        <p>KELLY CROW</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
