<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Wades Into the Details of Mideast Negotiations</title>
    <meta content="Y25MID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3DD103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Wades Into the Details of Mideast Negotiations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>THURMONT, Md., July 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton plunges into nitty-gritty of issue-by-issue deliberations at Camp David summit between Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat; Israeli and Palestinian officials say negotiators, under Clinton's direct supervision, are engaged in forging working agreement in effort to establish concrete points of accord and highlight gaps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton plunged into the nitty-gritty of issue-by-issue deliberations at Camp David today. After meeting almost until dawn with Israeli and Palestinian negotiators, he oversaw a day and night of what officials said quietly was the exercise of drafting the skeleton of an agreement.</p>
        <p>The White House would not confirm that a document was being drafted. But Israeli and Palestinian officials said the negotiators, under the direct supervision of President Clinton, were engaged in forging a working agreement in an effort to establish concrete points of accord and highlight the gaps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton plunged into the nitty-gritty of issue-by-issue deliberations at Camp David today. After meeting almost until dawn with Israeli and Palestinian negotiators, he oversaw a day and night of what officials said quietly was the exercise of drafting the skeleton of an agreement.</p>
        <p>The White House would not confirm that a document was being drafted. But Israeli and Palestinian officials said the negotiators, under the direct supervision of President Clinton, were engaged in forging a working agreement in an effort to establish concrete points of accord and highlight the gaps.</p>
        <p>Unofficially imposing another informal deadline on the process, the White House announced that Mr. Clinton, whose departure for Japan last Wednesday almost collapsed the talks, would leave Camp David at noon on Tuesday to attend the funeral of a longtime family friend in Arkansas. He is to return at midnight.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Israeli and Palestinian officials said they expected it to become clearer on Tuesday ''whether we are moving forward or at a standstill,'' as Amnon Lipkin-Shahak, a senior Israeli negotiator inside Camp David, told Israel's Channel 2 television tonight.</p>
        <p>At midday Joe Lockhart, the president's spokesman, offered his least guarded assessment of the 14 days of talks, saying the pace and intensity of the president's schedule suggested that five days after talks had nearly collapsed, Mr. Clinton believed that there was a prospect for success.</p>
        <p>''I hesitate to use a phrase like hopeful, because these issues are so difficult,'' Mr. Lockhart said at a briefing at a press center several miles from Camp David. ''But obviously the last time I stood here it was an hour or so removed from the collapse of discussions. The fact that it's continuing is a positive thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockhart said the president, who held up crossed fingers as he boarded his helicopter to return to his Catoctin Mountains retreat on Sunday, was engaged in a ''rolling assessment'' of the probability of success. He said a final deadline would not be ''calendar-driven.''</p>
        <p>''While the president believes the discussions are substantive, he will remain here and keep the parties here,'' Mr. Lockhart said. ''The fact that he was up to 5 a.m. working through issues in a very personal hands-on way and back at it this morning should lead you to believe that he thinks staying here for the time being is worthwhile.''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview played on Israeli television, a reporter asked Mr. Lipkin-Shahak, Israel's transportation minister, to estimate, by percentage, the chances of an agreement. ''It's either zero or 100,'' he responded. ''There is no middle ground.''</p>
        <p>That remark and a similar one made on Sunday by a senior Palestinian negotiator, Mahmoud Abbas, also known as Abu Mazen, indicate that the Israelis and the Palestinians are for now discounting the possibility of a partial agreement that would leave aside the potentially deal-breaking issue of Jerusalem's status.</p>
        <p>But other officials say that the draft agreement has not yet touched Jerusalem and that the Americans may still try to persuade the parties to reach an accord without resolving the city's contested status.</p>
        <p>Under the ground rules at Camp David, nothing is agreed until everything is agreed, and a senior Palestinian official said tonight that the dispute over Jerusalem had caused the parties to retreat from offers that were on the table last week.</p>
        <p>The official said the Palestinians' mood had soured after Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel asserted that he would not feel bound by compromise positions reached at the summit if it ended in failure.</p>
        <p>After returning early from Japan, where he attended a meeting of leading industrial nations, Mr. Clinton met on Sunday night with Mr. Barak and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat. Some 30 American, Israeli and Palestinian delegates shared a dinner in which Mr. Clinton sat between the two leaders.</p>
        <p>Afterward, around midnight, Mr. Clinton convened the senior negotiators from each side, leaving aside the two leaders. After breaking near dawn for a nap, he cut short a White House staff meeting to rush back into the talks with the negotiators.</p>
        <p>Over a total of nine hours, he worked with various teams specializing in different issues, recessing before an expected evening meeting.</p>
        <p>An official photograph from inside Camp David showed Mr. Clinton with two Israeli negotiators on one side and two Palestinian negotiators on the other.</p>
        <p>All are taking furious notes, and Dennis B. Ross, the American Middle East peace envoy, holds a thick loose-leaf binder in his lap.</p>
        <p>Uri Savir, an Israeli lawmaker who served as a senior negotiator of the Oslo interim peace agreement of 1993, said he viewed the photograph as an illustration of document drafting.</p>
        <p>''Judging from my experience in these things,'' he said, ''there would be no reason for Clinton to spend this amount of time with the negotiators themselves for any other reason. And that's a very good sign. Generally when you finish writing, you discover the gaps are wider than you thought. But in a very real sense, you are launched in the dynamic of an agreement.''</p>
        <p>In the Middle East, those whose fate rests on the deliberations seize each day's limited news from Camp David with a mixture of anxiety and excitement.</p>
        <p>Everyone there who has lived through the ups and downs of the conflict awaits the end in a protective zone of skepticism for what would be the amazing news -- exhilarating for some, gut-wrenching for others -- that the 52-year, blood-soaked conflict was to be resolved.</p>
        <p>In Israel a poll published this morning showed that 59 percent of the Israelis surveyed hoped that the summit meeting would end in agreement, even knowing full well the ''painful compromises'' that would be entailed.</p>
        <p>That reflects what Mr. Barak has been arguing: that despite the defection of rightist parties that left him with a minority government this month, the public supports his peacemaking and would endorse an agreement.</p>
        <p>''If he should sign an agreement,'' said Dalia Itzik, the environment minister, ''he will present it as, 'ladies and gentlemen, the agreement you always dreamed of: the end of the conflict in return for a few Arab neighborhoods that you personally have never visited and have no interest in.' ''</p>
        <p>No Israeli leader had ever broached the idea of sharing sovereignty in East Jerusalem with the Palestinians until last week, when word leaked out of the talks that Mr. Barak was considering it. The official formula always called for a united, undivided Jerusalem under Israeli sovereignty, even though most Israelis know that on the ground, Jerusalem is a segregated city.</p>
        <p>But some analysts say that as the morning's polls indicate, Israelis may be prepared to absorb a changed outlook relatively quickly.</p>
        <p>''I have a feeling that we are at a turning point in public opinion'' toward Jerusalem, said Dr. Tamar Hermann, director of the Tami Steinmetz Center for Peace Research at Tel Aviv University. ''The moment the taboo was removed on even discussing the issue of dividing Jerusalem, it created an opening.''</p>
        <p>Gearing up to fight against any agreement, dozens of rightist Israeli politicians met today on the Mount of Olives in East Jerusalem, where they broadcast a video clip of Mr. Barak's campaign pledge to keep Jerusalem undivided. ''Israel is united around a united Jerusalem,'' Mr. Barak said in the video, which was spliced to play and replay the remark.</p>
        <p>But a senior Palestinian official said the idea of sharing sovereignty in East Jerusalem is now off the table, having been rejected by both sides.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
