<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="25TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DA103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Baseball Hall of Fame  BASEBALL HALL OF FAME -- Named Jane Forbes Clark chairman and Joe Morgan vice chairman of the board at the National Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>American League  SEATTLE MARINERS -- Activated SS Alex Rodriguez from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned OF Charles Gipson to Tacoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Named Dave Stewart pitching coach. Reassigned former pitching coach Rick Langford to Syracuse of the International League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Baseball Hall of Fame  BASEBALL HALL OF FAME -- Named Jane Forbes Clark chairman and Joe Morgan vice chairman of the board at the National Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>American League  SEATTLE MARINERS -- Activated SS Alex Rodriguez from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned OF Charles Gipson to Tacoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Named Dave Stewart pitching coach. Reassigned former pitching coach Rick Langford to Syracuse of the International League.</p>
        <p>National League  CINCINNATI REDS -- Named DeJon Watson major league scout.  Frontier League  CHILLICOTHE PAINTS -- Announced that OF Joe Calamenco has signed a minor-league contract with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  DETROIT SHOCK -- Activated F Olympia Scott-Richardson from the injured list. Waived G Madinah Slaise.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  GIANTS -- Waived FB Brian Aikins.  ATLANTA FALCONS -- Signed G Everett McIver. Waived G Alex Bernstein.  CAROLINA PANTHERS -- Agreed to terms with DT Eric Swann on a one-year contract.  GREEN BAY PACKERS -- Agreed to terms with OT Chad Clifton on a four-year contract.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS -- Signed RB Mark Kacmarynski. Announced the retirement of RB Dan Kendra.  PITTSBURGH STEELERS -- Signed OL Ryan Thomassie. Released LB Mike Sands.  MIAMI DOLPHINS -- Signed OT Todd Wade and CB Ben Kelly to multiyear contracts.  MINNESOTA VIKINGS -- Signed DL Chris Hovan.  ST. LOUIS RAMS -- Signed DE Vince Amey. Released DL Samson Sherrod.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS -- Signed LB Steve Tovar. Released CB Damen Wheeler.  TAMPA BAY BUCCANEERS -- Waived FB Jim Kitts.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  RANGERS -- Agreed to terms with G Johan Holmqvist and G Vitali Yeremeyev.  CAROLINA HURRICANES -- Agreed to terms with D Sandis Ozolinsh on a five-year contract.  MINNESOTA WILD -- Named Mike Ramsey and Mario Tremblay assistant coaches. Signed D J.J. Daigneault.  PHOENIX COYOTES -- Signed LW Ramzi Abid to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
        <p>ATP TOUR -- Promoted David Higdon to vice president, corporate communications and Greg Sharko director of communications, Americas.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BIG EAST CONFERENCE -- Promoted director of sport administration James Siedliski to assistant commissioner for sport administration.  NORTHEAST CONFERENCE -- Accepted St. John's, N.Y. as an associate member in football for the 2000 season.  AKRON -- Named Chad Flanders men's assistant soccer coach.  ASSUMPTION -- Named Jim Vail tight ends coach, Randy Homa inside linebackers coach, Greg Crum defensive line coach, and Isaiah Taulbee running backs coach. Named Katie Kerr women's assistant basketball coach and Al Pettway and Franz Steiner men's assistant basketball coaches.  BOSTON COLLEGE -- Named Rob Miller men's tennis coach.  CURRY -- Named John Ritucci men's tennis coach.  FURMAN -- Named Julie Glasser assistant softball coach.  GEORGIA SOUTHWESTERN -- Named Barry Davis baseball coach.  GREENSBORO -- Promoted Mike Lackemacher to full-time women's lacrosse coach and named him women's assistant soccer coach.  IOWA -- Announced resignation of Kristen Holmes, assistant field hockey coach.  LORAS -- Named Matt Kalb assistant football coach and Travis Senters and Adam Verble graduate assistant football coaches.  LSU -- Announced the resignation of Herb Vincent, sports information director.  MAINE -- Named Michael Burden men's assistant basketball coach.  OKLAHOMA CITY -- Announced the retirement of Joseph Sahmaunt, athletic director, effective August, 2000.  PENN STATE -- Named Sarah Duttera women's assistant swimming coach.  PEPPERDINE -- Named Nick Rodionoff women's swimming and diving coach.  RHODE ISLAND COLLEGE -- Announced the resignation of Scott Perry, baseball coach.  ST. JOHN'S, N.Y. -- Named Greg Bolitsky men's tennis coach.  SOUTHERN MISSISSIPPI -- Named Cindy Willie assistant softball coach.  TULSA -- Named Sammy Lawanson linebackers coach.  UC IRVINE -- Named Cory Hillis men's and women's assistant swimming coach.  VANDERBILT -- Promoted director of basketball operations Brad Frederick to men's assistant basketball coach. Named Dan Muller administrative assistant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
