<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Quiet Wood, a Pathologist Under Siege</title>
    <meta content="25PROF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Ward B. Stone</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stone, Ward B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5D7133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Quiet Wood, a Pathologist Under Siege</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <dateline>DELMAR, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles Ward B Stone, New York State's chief wildlife pathologist; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE, in the dappled woods of upstate New York on a kiss-perfect summer day, Ward B. Stone is downstairs in the laboratory, showing off his freezer collection.</p>
        <p>The walk-in model. Then the chest unit, stocked with neatly labeled jars -- bits of brains, livers, spleens mostly. Next, a stainless steel beauty with shelves, on wheels. ''This is the mobile mort,'' explains Mr. Stone, 61, whose flannel shirt-sleeves are rolled up, jeans faded, eyebrows tufted, white hair long, unruly. ''It's for dead people, but we use it for turtles.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE, in the dappled woods of upstate New York on a kiss-perfect summer day, Ward B. Stone is downstairs in the laboratory, showing off his freezer collection.</p>
        <p>The walk-in model. Then the chest unit, stocked with neatly labeled jars -- bits of brains, livers, spleens mostly. Next, a stainless steel beauty with shelves, on wheels. ''This is the mobile mort,'' explains Mr. Stone, 61, whose flannel shirt-sleeves are rolled up, jeans faded, eyebrows tufted, white hair long, unruly. ''It's for dead people, but we use it for turtles.''</p>
        <p>In this, Mr. Stone's 32nd year as chief and only wildlife pathologist for New York State, his freezers are crammed with animals whose deaths will have to wait to be investigated -- victims of illegal hunts, poisonings and pesticide ingestions among them. It's triage time.</p>
        <p>This summer Mr. Stone, who works a seven-day week in normal years, has a corpse crisis: everybody's nervous, so everybody's shipping him their dead crows, sparrows and blue jays, about 300 a day, to be checked for West Nile virus. He estimates finding about 50 cases so far.</p>
        <p>He looks over the latest delivery. ''What's this chicken doing here?'' grumbles Mr. Stone. ''We're not doing some veterinarian's work for free! Next thing, everybody will be sending us their pet parakeets.''</p>
        <p>The ''we'' means Mr. Stone, two assistants, a secretary and a couple of summer interns. Now consider that in addition to the West Nile candidates -- which, depending on a host of factors, his team may slice, dice, type and pickle, sending tissue to a nearby lab for testing -- the daily haul for necropsies can include bear, moose, beaver, swans, hawks, bats and deer, deer, deer.</p>
        <p>Also consider that he is always running a study on pesticides; writing scientific articles (in today's mail, acceptance letters for two); inveighing against human-made threats to wildlife; lumbering off to inoculate infested ducks, which cause swimmer's itch in local lakes; testifying in court; nursing wounded animals; and swabbing down his crematory. Mr. Stone, whose last raise lifted his salary to $59,908, may be a touch overwhelmed. But now, for a change, no one is trying to fire him.</p>
        <p>''We're all getting along,'' remarks Mr. Stone, with a dramatic eye roll. ''At the moment.''</p>
        <p>He has a file of dire letters from the many superiors he's outlasted. (And they have plenty from him.) A darling of environmentalists, who praise his pioneering work in detecting pollutants like polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, in wildlife, and who rally when his job is in jeopardy, Mr. Stone turns out to be a loud, throbbing administrative pain.</p>
        <p>HE has leaked data to reporters, sampled landfills and incinerator ash -- far afield from pathology, sniff specialists who call him untrained, a meddler -- attacked popular fishing practices like lead sinkers and embarrassed  bosses at the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation by finding traces of DDT on the grounds of a regional office.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stone, whose ancestors landed at Plymouth Colony, has a sturdy sense of self-importance, a taskmaster's bite, a truculent shoulder shrug and a lifelong sense of wonder about wild critters. In wildlife pathology, Mr. Stone, who has a master's degree in zoology, is influential, regarded as innovative but precise. So he apologizes not.</p>
        <p>On the contrary. ''There's always so much going on that I have a nagging feeling I'm not doing enough,'' says Mr. Stone, leaning back in his office chair and using his belly as an arm rest.</p>
        <p>Last year, with a nagging feeling about those dying crows, Mr. Stone was one of the early investigators to  send samples around the country persistently, until the deadly, mosquito-borne virus was identified.</p>
        <p>About the recent public response, he has mixed emotions. The spraying may threaten monarch butterflies and some fish, he says. Yet West Nile threatens not only humans, he notes, but large mammals and birds like the bald eagle and the peregrine falcon, which have scant populations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stone, who grew up in rural Columbia County, tries to live within the means dictated by his convictions and his bank account. He has been driving the same gas-efficient car since 1992. His lawn is green, free of pesticides, lush with weeds. With his partner, Mary Bayham, an ecologist, he has four children under 7 (he also has an adult daughter from a past marriage); he and the kids built their swing set from road scraps. He teaches them to whittle toys, garden, fish and stroll through streams.</p>
        <p>Nature, as Mr. Stone knows too well, can also be savage. Last month he and Ms. Bayham buried their fifth child, a newborn. His grief is raw and tear-drenched. ''I was the scientist but I had the most faith that something could be done,'' he whispers.</p>
        <p>So he steeps himself in the work -- today's birds from New York City have just arrived -- walks in the woods and attends to the life-affirming demands of his brood.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Ward Stone, age 6, bursts into the office, announcing that he wants to look for frogs along the trails surrounding the Wildlife Pathology Unit. Ask him what he wants to be when he grows up, prods his beaming father.</p>
        <p>Jonathan?</p>
        <p>He is already running down the hall toward the perfect summer day. ''A wildlife pathologist!'' echoes the reply. ''You got a problem with that?''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
