<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Governor to Replace Georgia Senator</title>
    <meta content="Y25MILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Roy  (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Zell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coverdell, Paul (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DF103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Governor to Replace Georgia Senator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Georgia Gov Roy Barnes appoints popular predecessor, Zell Miller, to succeed late Paul Coverdell as US senator, instantly changing partisan political calculus both in Georgia and in Washington; 68-0year-old Democrat will serve on interim basis then run in nonpartisan special election in November to fill remainder of Coverdell's term, which expires in January 2005; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Roy Barnes today appointed his popular predecessor, Zell Miller, to succeed the late Paul Coverdell as United States senator, a choice that instantly changed the partisan political calculus both in Georgia and in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, a 68-year-old Democrat who left office in early 1999 after two terms, will serve as senator on an interim basis and then run in a nonpartisan special election in November to fill the remainder of Mr. Coverdell's term, which extends until January 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Roy Barnes today appointed his popular predecessor, Zell Miller, to succeed the late Paul Coverdell as United States senator, a choice that instantly changed the partisan political calculus both in Georgia and in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, a 68-year-old Democrat who left office in early 1999 after two terms, will serve as senator on an interim basis and then run in a nonpartisan special election in November to fill the remainder of Mr. Coverdell's term, which extends until January 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller's acceptance of the offer to succeed Mr. Coverdell, a Republican who died last week, was a huge relief to Mr. Barnes, a Democrat, and to party leaders around the country, including President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore. Several officials close to Mr. Barnes said the governor was convinced that Mr. Miller was the only Georgia Democrat who could hold on to the seat in November, particularly given the scarcity of time to raise money and organize a campaign.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in his Capitol office this evening, Mr. Barnes made it clear that Mr. Miller, who rebuffed pleas from President Clinton to run against Mr. Coverdell in 1998, was not easily persuaded to abandon his position as a college professor in the north Georgia mountains.</p>
        <p>''In the end,'' said Mr. Barnes, who was lobbied by Democratic aspirants virtually from the moment that Mr. Coverdell died on Tuesday after a stroke, ''the one who didn't want it was the one who had to take it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, a career politician who left office with approval ratings that hovered near 80 percent, said ''the fires of political ambition that had burned so long and so strong within me had finally cooled.'' But he said he ultimately accepted the job because of his devotion to his state and the sense of obligation he developed as a marine.</p>
        <p>''I accept this mission,'' he said, ''with a heavy heart and a profound sense of duty.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coverdell was secretary of the Senate Republican conference. Mr. Miller's appointment narrows the Republican margin in the Senate to 54 to 46, and provides an unanticipated boost to Democratic hopes of winning control in either this November's general election or in 2002.</p>
        <p>Throughout this year's campaign, Democrats had been given a far greater chance of taking control of the House than the Senate. But Mr. Coverdell's death and Mr. Miller's appointment, coupled with close Senate races in several states with either open seats or Republican incumbents, have given the Democrats renewed hope.</p>
        <p>While the Republicans remain favored to retain control of the Senate, Mr. Miller's appointment means the Democrats could take over by picking up a net of five seats in the event of a Republican presidential victory, or by picking up four seats if Mr. Gore wins the presidency in November. That is because a four-seat gain would result in a partisan deadlock in the Senate that could be broken by Mr. Gore's Democratic vice president.</p>
        <p>The Miller appointment also could help Mr. Gore in his quest to win Georgia in the presidential election. The state, which has become a partisan battleground in recent years, is considered to be leaning toward Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the presumptive Republican nominee, but not by enough to keep Mr. Gore from contesting it aggressively. Mr. Gore will presumably benefit from get-out-the-vote efforts by Mr. Miller and Mr. Barnes.</p>
        <p>''Governor Bush will have to spend more time in Georgia if he expects to carry the state,'' said Merle Black, a political scientist at Emory University.</p>
        <p>Mr. Black said that Mr. Miller was ''the strongest possible candidate that Governor Barnes could have chosen'' and that he would easily unite Georgia's various Democratic factions.</p>
        <p>''Right now,'' he said, ''it's really hard to see how anybody could beat him.''</p>
        <p>Q. Whitfield Ayres, a Republican pollster based in Atlanta, agreed that Mr. Miller was the strongest Democratic choice but minimized his potential influence on the presidential race.</p>
        <p>''Zell Miller is popular in part because independent and Republican-leaning voters have supported him in the past,'' Mr. Ayres said, ''but those same voters are more likely to prefer George Bush than Al Gore. And I don't know that Zell Miller on the ticket generates any substantial increase in turnout.''</p>
        <p>The selection leaves Georgia's Republicans in a quandary. Before today's announcement, several of Georgia's eight Republican congressmen had been considering entering the race to succeed Mr. Coverdell. But Mr. Miller's seeming strength is likely to chill the ambitions of many, particularly since the congressmen would have to resign their relatively safe seats to run for the Senate. Aides to several of the Republican House members said they planned to meet on Tuesday afternoon to discuss their options.</p>
        <p>''Coming off of eight years of service, he's obviously a formidable candidate,'' said Representative Johnny Isakson, one of several Georgia Republicans considering the race.</p>
        <p>Chuck Clay, the state Republican chairman, said it was vital for his party to unite quickly around a candidate. There is no limit to the number of candidates who can compete in the nonpartisan special election, meaning the Republicans might split the conservative vote if more than one runs.</p>
        <p>''What we cannot do is shred our vote between two or three candidates and let a Democrat walk into Paul Coverdell's office,'' Mr. Clay said. ''What a travesty that would be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clay criticized Mr. Barnes for not appointing a caretaker senator who would be faithful to Mr. Coverdell's philosophy.</p>
        <p>''They've gone back to what they know best, which is power politics,'' he said of the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes, who lost a gubernatorial primary to Mr. Miller in 1990, countered that Mr. Miller was clearly the most qualified candidate of either party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller wasted little time in appealing today to independents and Republicans, pledging to adopt the ''spirit of dignity, integrity and bipartisan cooperation that were the hallmarks of Paul Coverdell's career.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, who has run for statewide office seven times, is best known for bringing the lottery to Georgia and devoting the proceeds to college scholarships and universal prekindergarten programs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
