<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jakarta Lawmakers Press Leader on Ousters</title>
    <meta content="Y25IND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahid, Abdurrahman (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD8133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jakarta Lawmakers Press Leader on Ousters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, July 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Surly standoff between Indonesian Parliament and its first democratically elected leader drags on as more than 200 members reject President Abdurrahman Wahid's explanation for why he ousted two popular cabinet ministers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A surly standoff between Parliament and its first democratically elected leader dragged on today as more than 200 members rejected President Abdurrahman Wahid's explanation for why he had ousted two popular cabinet ministers.</p>
        <p>The members signed a petition demanding that Mr. Wahid go before the House of Representatives again to explain his actions. Mr. Wahid outraged the lawmakers in an appearance on Thursday, when he refused to give an account of the dismissals, saying the House had no right to interrogate him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A surly standoff between Parliament and its first democratically elected leader dragged on today as more than 200 members rejected President Abdurrahman Wahid's explanation for why he had ousted two popular cabinet ministers.</p>
        <p>The members signed a petition demanding that Mr. Wahid go before the House of Representatives again to explain his actions. Mr. Wahid outraged the lawmakers in an appearance on Thursday, when he refused to give an account of the dismissals, saying the House had no right to interrogate him.</p>
        <p>The action today raises the heat in what has been a long summer of discontent. The president is scheduled to face a pivotal meeting of the People's Consultative Assembly on Aug. 7, in which he is quite likely to face sharp questions about his often turbulent nine months in office.</p>
        <p>As the supreme legislative body, the People's Consultative Assembly could remove the president from office. Five hundred of its 700 members are from the House.</p>
        <p>Yet, experts said, the lack of viable alternatives makes it highly unlikely that the assembly would oust Mr. Wahid -- at least for now.</p>
        <p>But the deeply poisoned atmosphere has stirred fears that violence could mar the meeting next month. The government plans to deploy 29,000 army troops and police officers in this capital.</p>
        <p>The tension has also hobbled the economic recovery. The currency, the rupiah, has tumbled 25 percent since January and now trades at levels reminiscent of the Asian economic crisis. Economic policy is paralyzed, as investors wait for Mr. Wahid to reshuffle his economic ministers after the Assembly session.</p>
        <p>''Unless Wahid fixes the economy, he can't fix all these other things, because they flow out of people's sense of well-being or lack of well-being,'' said Gustav F. Papanek, a professor emeritus of economics at Boston University who is advising the government on economic policy.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Mr. Wahid apologized to the House for his remarks and pleaded with lawmakers to lay the matter to rest. But in a sign that his quirky charm is wearing thin, 252 members rejected the overture and mounted a scalding attack on his leadership. ''The president should not issue any more baseless or controversial statements, because it could negatively affect the stock market, cause recklessness or confusion or trigger disputes among the public,'' the legislators said in their petition, which went to Speaker Akbar Tandjung.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tandjung said the House would debate the petition after the Assembly had ended its session in the middle of next month. That all but guarantees that Mr. Wahid will remain under siege for the rest of the summer, though few political experts here say they believe that he is in danger of being ousted.</p>
        <p>To some extent, the sparks between the legislature and the president are a symbol of how far Indonesia has come. Under the country's longtime leader, Suharto, the House was a rubber-stamp institution that did the president's bidding. Since Mr. Wahid was elected, the lawmakers and the Indonesian people have begun to demand openness and accountability from their politicians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wahid, a Muslim leader with frail health but a whip-sharp sense of humor, began his term with a wide-open style that suggested a break from the past. But in the last several months, his administration has been sullied by charges of corruption and arbitrary rule.</p>
        <p>In April, Mr. Wahid abruptly dismissed two respected ministers, Laksamana Sukardi and Jusuf Kalla.  In meetings with political leaders, Mr. Wahid has said the cabinet ministers had been tainted by allegations of graft. But he has not produced evidence to support those assertions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
