<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jones Elevates His Opponent</title>
    <meta content="25FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Roy Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harding, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicker, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D7133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jones Elevates His Opponent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON DICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dicker, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roy Jones Jr to defend his world light-heavyweight championship against Eric Harding (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best Roy Jones Jr. could come up with yesterday in hyping his next opponent, Eric Harding, was Harding's ability to avoid being knocked to the canvas.</p>
        <p>''There has to be something good about him; he's never been down,'' Jones said. ''He's fought some pretty good people in that time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The best Roy Jones Jr. could come up with yesterday in hyping his next opponent, Eric Harding, was Harding's ability to avoid being knocked to the canvas.</p>
        <p>''There has to be something good about him; he's never been down,'' Jones said. ''He's fought some pretty good people in that time.''</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old Jones (42-1, 34 knockouts) will defend his undisputed light-heavyweight title against the 27-year-old Harding (19-0-1, 6 knockouts) on Sept. 9 in New Orleans. Jones, who will receive no money up front, will split the $34.95 pay-per-view fees with Muhammad Ali's children's charity. Harding will reportedly earn a guaranteed $500,000 to $700,000, by far his biggest payday.</p>
        <p>The two fighters entered the Nike showroom in Lower Manhattan escorted by women in skimpy Mardi Gras costumes as zydeco music blared. Jones wore a blue floral print shirt, shorts, sneakers and a crown, which made him look like the winner of a sand-castle contest at the beach.</p>
        <p>Jones, considered by many to be the best boxer in any division, is still pondering a move up to heavyweight. And he is still hunting for the great fight that will elevate him into a household name.</p>
        <p>Harding, a left-handed counterpuncher, is probably not the man to push Jones there. He will, however, make good human-interest fodder.</p>
        <p>Harding estimated he had been arrested 15 to 20 times on charges ranging from drug dealing to assault. He said he changed his criminal path when he was shot on a Philadelphia street at age 22 after a dispute with two men. The bullet ricocheted off his beeper, he said, and pieces of the beeper lodged in his right thigh and had to be removed.</p>
        <p>Harding lives with his wife and three children in East Hartford, Conn. An affable fellow, the corn-rowed, bespectacled Harding was clearly enjoying his big break but said he was not intimidated by Jones.</p>
        <p>Harding showed uncustomary ferocity in his last fight. He broke Antonio Tarver's jaw and ribs in earning a unanimous decision in a title elimination bout on June 23.</p>
        <p>''You never know what you get with me,'' said Harding, the International Boxing Federation's top-ranked contender. ''It might be the slick boxer you can't hit, or it might be the guy who goes in to bang it out.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
