<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anorexia Can Strike Boys, Too</title>
    <meta content="25CASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cholesterol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markel, Howard (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cholesterol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cholesterol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5DD1E3BF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anorexia Can Strike Boys, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD MARKEL, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markel, Howard (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Howard Markel column says that while teenage girls in search of perfect body still make up majority of cases of anorexia nervosa, disorder is being reported across wide socioeconomic range; cites case of boy who died from self-starvation brought on by fear of effects of fats and cholesterol (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An emaciated boy named Michael sits in a hospital bed, intently playing a video game. Only 15, he looks like a wizened old man: the color of his skin gray, his hair falling out and the his arm and leg muscles all but melted away.</p>
        <p>He was referred for a possible diagnosis of anorexia nervosa. Michael has a much simpler explanation: ''Really, doc, I'm fine. I just don't want to eat anything that will corrode my arteries and give me a heart attack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An emaciated boy named Michael sits in a hospital bed, intently playing a video game. Only 15, he looks like a wizened old man: the color of his skin gray, his hair falling out and the his arm and leg muscles all but melted away.</p>
        <p>He was referred for a possible diagnosis of anorexia nervosa. Michael has a much simpler explanation: ''Really, doc, I'm fine. I just don't want to eat anything that will corrode my arteries and give me a heart attack.''</p>
        <p>A most vexing eating disorder, anorexia results from self-imposed starvation to the point it seriously harms one's physical and mental health. Often linked to the powerful images of impossibly thin women shown in the mass media, the problem was long thought to be almost exclusive to affluent teenage girls.</p>
        <p>Recently, physicians have begun to appreciate that anorexia has many faces and is hardly restricted to one socioeconomic class or gender.</p>
        <p>Teenage girls in search of the perfect body still make up the majority of cases. But cases have also been reported among teenagers from the rural South, African-Americans from poor urban centers, and even American Indians on reservations.</p>
        <p>And, of course, it is not only girls who are at risk. Many boys stop eating for a variety of reasons, including participating in sports that require intense attention to weight, like wrestling and track. Each year, about a million American teenagers develop anorexia, and anywhere from 1,000 to 10,000 die from its long-term ravages.</p>
        <p>Recently, I have been seeing boys and girls who do not want to eat because of a fear of the effects of fat and cholesterol on their bodies. Michael's ''lipophobia'' (fear of fat) began six months before we met when his beloved grandfather, an overweight man who liked his steaks rare and his vegetables deep-fried, dropped dead of a heart attack while the two were playing checkers.</p>
        <p>Since then, Michael had studiously  avoided all foods containing fat. His diet now consisted entirely of water, slices of fat-free turkey luncheon meat and -- his favorite -- pita bread.</p>
        <p>In the months before he was admitted to the hospital, Michael lost over 45 pounds and stopped his pubertal development. He suffered many other symptoms, including physical exhaustion, cold, clammy skin, a slowed heart rate, low blood pressure causing dizziness whenever he got up and severe constipation.</p>
        <p>During Michael's hospital stay a team of pediatricians, psychiatrists, nutritionists and gastroenterologists worked to fatten him up to prevent even more serious illnesses from setting in. We managed to put some weight on Michael with high-caloric milk shakes that we convinced him were cholesterol-free.</p>
        <p>Soon enough, however, we had to discharge him. After giving his parents a menu of high-calorie foods for Michael to eat, I asked him to keep a detailed diary of his daily diet. Within a few weeks he produced an almost obsessively detailed and beautifully printed document, showing a return to the pita bread. His parents said they did not know what to do.  ''After all,'' his mother noted, ''you can't force a 15-year-old to eat, can you?''</p>
        <p>Each subsequent week Michael continued to lose weight. Advice from eating disorder counselors, psychiatrists, and even antidepressant medications did little to arrest the process.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to comprehend the complex dynamics that lead to self-inflicted starvation, the vicious cycle begun by limiting food intake to the point that the brain no longer senses hunger, followed by the inexorable damage to the muscles, heart, kidneys and other organs.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a better understanding of anorexia and other eating disorders, early recognition and concerted efforts by physicians, mental health professionals and -- most important -- family members, this deadly disorder can be conquered. But some either come to diagnosis too late or do not respond to treatment.</p>
        <p>Several months after Michael was discharged, a physician from his hospital called and told me that the boy died that  morning of a cardiac arrest. Despite the boy's fears, an autopsy later revealed clean and open arteries, with no cholesterol blockages. But the heart was wasted and shrunken in appearance.</p>
        <p>I grieved for the loss of a young man no one could reach. Neither medical knowledge nor pleading were powerful enough to get him to perform the simple act of eating three meals a day.</p>
        <p>CASES Dr. Markel is an associate professor at the University of Michigan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dr. Markel is an associate professor at the University of Michigan.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
