<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tyrannical Boss Meets More Than His Match</title>
    <meta content="25TABL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Working Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ackerman, Rob</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grappo, Connie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tabletop (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DB133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tyrannical Boss Meets More Than His Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. J. R. BRUCKNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruckner, D J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D J R Bruckner reviews Working Theater production of Rob Ackerman's play Tabletop, directed by Connie Grappo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 14 years the Working Theater has sponsored plays about people at their jobs. Its beginning was auspicious, since right about then Americans began greatly expanding their time at work. Given its purpose, the company must be very pleased with Rob Ackerman's ''Tabletop,'' which inaugurates the 15th season and which makes the work we do, despite all the laughter this production provokes, downright spooky at times.</p>
        <p>Dean Taucher, the set designer, who has made a lot of television commercials with the playwright, turns the performance space of the Bessie Schonberg Theater in Chelsea into a photographic studio so filled with authentic tools and equipment that it practically drags you into it. And the six people working in it put so much pressure on one another in pursuit of the perfect commercial that after 100 minutes you feel like slouching home to a friendly gin bottle where you can smile in tranquillity without feeling your nerves are going to fray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For 14 years the Working Theater has sponsored plays about people at their jobs. Its beginning was auspicious, since right about then Americans began greatly expanding their time at work. Given its purpose, the company must be very pleased with Rob Ackerman's ''Tabletop,'' which inaugurates the 15th season and which makes the work we do, despite all the laughter this production provokes, downright spooky at times.</p>
        <p>Dean Taucher, the set designer, who has made a lot of television commercials with the playwright, turns the performance space of the Bessie Schonberg Theater in Chelsea into a photographic studio so filled with authentic tools and equipment that it practically drags you into it. And the six people working in it put so much pressure on one another in pursuit of the perfect commercial that after 100 minutes you feel like slouching home to a friendly gin bottle where you can smile in tranquillity without feeling your nerves are going to fray.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ackerman has long been a property master for films, television commercials and shows, and he has acute eyes and ears for telling details. His story, like most good stories, is a kind of fairy tale, this one about a village idiot who faces down an implacable tyrant and makes him say ''please.'' But the story is far less important than the relationships among these characters. Everything here depends on the acting and directing.</p>
        <p>The studio belongs to Marcus Gordon, one of the country's most successful producers of close-in action shots for commercials (''tabletop'' in the trade), a perfectionist whose chief management tool is intimidation, much of it magnified and put to good purpose by his icy assistant, Andrea. Her tools are the three union technicians manning all the equipment -- Jeffrey, Oscar and Dave. And then there is a nonunion gofer, Ron, nominally assigned to help Jeffrey set up the shots of elaborately arranged fruit, ice cream concoctions, whatever, but who is likely to stumble into everyone else's domain with ideas they don't want to hear.</p>
        <p>Casting Rob Bartlett, the writer, parodist and all-purpose performer for ''Imus in the Morning,'' as Marcus is inspired. His Marcus is a bully whose vulnerability keeps peeping out every time he relaxes his guard, which isn't often. His contempt for everyone else in the advertising game is corrosive, vividly imaginative and unprintable. His explosions when things go wrong leave debris, some of it quite messy, all over the place. When with his head almost inside a camera, he roars, ''Ready . . . action . . . and cut,'' you have to laugh but feel you might be watching a high priest offering a sacrifice. He can purr ''Fear is our friend, boys,'' and make your flesh crawl. And when he intones about television, ''The shows are a lie, commercials are the truth,'' he leaves no doubt he means it.</p>
        <p>Harvy Blanks makes Oscar, who handles sound and the tapes, one of those men whose pride in his competence often blinds him to conflicts around him but not so effectively that he doesn't see he might be happier if he could start a business of his own. Dave, the lighting man, played by Jack Koenig, has the guts to defy Marcus by refusing to work extra days so he can live a life of his own. And Dean Nolen as Jeffrey, an assistant director who sets up every shot for Marcus, gets the fear and mean-spiritedness of this character just right. He loathes talk about higher purposes or alternative ways of doing things because the shop's work is craft, requiring tunnel vision. Besides, he is perfectly ready to steal other people's credit, labor and even their equipment if he needs any of those things.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Hanly Rice, without so much as a flicker of the eye, can let you feel Andrea's pleasure in recognizing a weakness in someone or a slight opening in an argument that she can exploit. Andrea is in the game solely for money, and Ms. Rice can let you know when Andrea is thinking about it even when she's silent.</p>
        <p>Then there is Ron, the innocent gofer. This is the most complex character of the lot, and Jeremy Webb lets the layers of it unfold so naturally that the depths Ron can plumb in a crisis come as the one real surprise in this comedy. Needless to say, his strength comes as a terrific shock to everyone else in the studio as well. This is where Mr. Ackerman's writing is at its best. For the audience notices early on that, for all his dreamy philosophizing about art in the work at the studio, Ron is one person who doesn't flatter Marcus because he genuinely agrees with him, and he is the only one who realizes when Marcus demands perfection he is not puffing his ego; he really has a vision of perfection. When Ron says at the outset that ''a 30-second commercial on television is the single most important statement of our time,'' he is laughed off. But it is that belief that makes him triumphant at the end.</p>
        <p>There is a lot of good material here about the ambiguity most people feel about their work -- not only about the struggle between pride and cynicism but also about whether you are most effective, and satisfied, if you are made to want to do the right thing for the wrong reasons. Casual remarks reflecting these puzzlements can bring out conflicted feelings that give depth to all the characters, and that counts since you either love or hate these characters or you leave. Those underlying differences of motive and vision also supply the framework for the series of minor irritating disasters that bring the plot to its climax.</p>
        <p>And that, all in the last few minutes, is where the play falls apart -- that ''please'' doesn't, not at all. Letting junior save the day is a device proven in a lot of successful old films and sitcoms. But to pull it off here Mr. Ackerman has to have the key characters totally forget, if only for the moment, what they have really learned about themselves and one another in this place. In other words, it is contrived.</p>
        <p>Even Connie Grappo, whose astute direction covers up some awkward transitions and tones down occasionally intrusive dialogue, cannot rescue this ending. The speed she brings to the chaotic collapse of the little world of the studio is impressive. But it doesn't hide the fact that some of these people have stepped out of character for the last laugh. The play has been so enjoyable that the disappointment is not a sharp one. But it is a bit sad. Mr. Ackerman came so close.</p>
        <p>TABLETOP</p>
        <p>By Rob Ackerman; directed by Connie Grappo; sets by Dean Taucher; costumes by Ilona Somogyi; lighting by Jack Mehler; production manager, Allan Kerr; stage manager, Neveen Mahmond; assistant stage manager, Janine L. Pangburn. Presented by the Working Theater, Robert Arcaro, artistic director; Mark Plesent, producing director. At Dance Theater Workshop's Bessie Schonberg Theater, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea.</p>
        <p>WITH: Harvy Blanks (Oscar), Jeremy Webb (Ron), Dean Nolen (Jeffrey), Jack Koenig (Dave), Elizabeth Hanly Rice (Andrea) and Rob Bartlett (Marcus).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
