<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convicted Killer Is Ordered Extradited to U.S.</title>
    <meta content="Y25PHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Einhorn, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maddux, Holly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jospin, Lionel (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDE103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convicted Killer Is Ordered Extradited to U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French Prime Min Lionel Jospin orders that Ira S Einhorn, once charismatic leader of Philadelphia's counterculture who was convicted in absentia of murdering girlfriend Holly Maddux 22 years ago, be extradited to US; Einhorn jumped $40,000 bail and disappeared shortly before trial in 1977; police found Maddux's body in steamer trunk in Einhorn's apartment 18 months after she disappeared; he has been free since arrest three years ago, and has been required to report weekly to authorities (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prime minister of France has ordered that Ira S. Einhorn, once a charismatic leader of Philadelphia's counterculture who was convicted in absentia of murdering his girlfriend 22 years ago, be extradited to the United States, legal authorities announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Given his track record, I am still concerned that he is going to flee,'' the Philadelphia district attorney, Lynne Abraham, said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The prime minister of France has ordered that Ira S. Einhorn, once a charismatic leader of Philadelphia's counterculture who was convicted in absentia of murdering his girlfriend 22 years ago, be extradited to the United States, legal authorities announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Given his track record, I am still concerned that he is going to flee,'' the Philadelphia district attorney, Lynne Abraham, said.</p>
        <p>With a final legal challenge still possible, Ms. Abraham noted that Mr. Einhorn had been a fugitive for 20 years and had vowed never to return to his home city, where he had been celebrated as a leading hippie advocate of peace, mysticism and environmentalism.</p>
        <p>The extradition was ordered by Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, said Ms. Abraham, who had no estimate on when American authorities hoped to regain custody of Mr. Einhorn, now 60. He has been fighting extradition since, after an extensive search across Europe, he was discovered three years ago living under an alias in Champagne-Mouton, in the Bordeaux region of France.</p>
        <p>Mr. Einhorn jumped $40,000 bail and disappeared as he was about to go on trial in the 1977 killing of Holly Maddux, who had been his lover. The police found Ms. Maddux's body in a steamer trunk in Mr. Einhorn's apartment 18 months after she disappeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Einhorn's transition from counterculture guru to accused murderer caused a sensation in Philadelphia. He denied committing the killing, saying the Central Intelligence Agency, KGB or other ''large intelligence agencies'' sought to frame him because he had uncovered classified mind-control experiments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Einhorn has 60 days to appeal to France's highest administrative tribunal, the Council of State.</p>
        <p>Last year, after lengthy legal maneuvering, the French Court of Appeals ruled that Mr. Einhorn could be extradited provided he would be granted a new trial and would not face the death penalty. The court decided to reverse its earlier order protecting Mr. Einhorn after Pennsylvania enacted a law in 1998 granting people convicted in absentia the right to a new trial if they returned and demanded one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Einhorn's lawyer, Theodore Simon, said yesterday that there was no way to guarantee a retrial. The 1998 law, Mr. Simon said, was clearly unconstitutional because it would violate the separation of powers in having a state legislature try to force a retrial on the court system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Einhorn has been free since he was arrested three years ago. He was required to report weekly to the authorities in France, where he lived in a remote millhouse with his wife.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
