<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>King E-Novel Short of Expected Demand</title>
    <meta content="Y25KIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Plant, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DC103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>King E-Novel Short of Expected Demand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Demand for Stephen King's new electronic book, The Plant, falls short of expectations, in closely watched test of King's attempt to transform book sales over Internet; fans download 41,000 copies of first chapter of novel by afternoon of July 24 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Demand for horror writer Stephen King's new electronic book fell short of expectations yesterday, in a closely watched test of the author's attempt to transform book sales over the Internet.</p>
        <p>The demand for the book fell short of his last novella in March, which seemed to foretell a revolution in publishing when more than 400,000 fans jammed computer servers trying to download it in the first two days after it appeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Demand for horror writer Stephen King's new electronic book fell short of expectations yesterday, in a closely watched test of the author's attempt to transform book sales over the Internet.</p>
        <p>The demand for the book fell short of his last novella in March, which seemed to foretell a revolution in publishing when more than 400,000 fans jammed computer servers trying to download it in the first two days after it appeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. King's Web site operators planned to handle a similar demand this time. But as of yesterday afternoon, fans had downloaded 41,000 copies of the first chapter of ''The Plant,'' an epistolary novel about the predations of a vicious vine that Mr. King plans to publish in monthly installments.</p>
        <p>The difference between the two experiments may be that this time Mr. King elected to publish the book without the support of a publisher, relying entirely on the Internet and word-of-mouth to attract readers. ''We didn't have the marketing and sales promotion that Simon &amp; Schuster put behind 'Riding the Bullet,' and that obviously accounted for some of the difference,'' said Marsha DeFilippo, an assistant to Mr. King.</p>
        <p>''Riding the Bullet'' is the novella that Mr. King published in electronic form.</p>
        <p>Mr. King's promotion of ''The Plant'' consisted of two advertisements, a morning television appearance and a few newspaper interviews.</p>
        <p>Mr. King was ''very pleased'' with sales so far, Ms. DeFilippo said.</p>
        <p>Bill Curry, a spokesman for Amazon.com, said 40,000 downloads was impressive. He said it was comparable to first-day sales for ''Riding the Bullet,'' when technical flaws limited access.</p>
        <p>Mr. King added another turn of the screw that may have thrown off some readers by trying out a novel honor-system payment plan. Mr. King asked readers to pay him a dollar for each chapter they downloaded, and warned that he would not post new installments unless he received payments for at least 75 percent of the downloads.</p>
        <p>Amazon.com agreed to handle the payments, and said that by late yesterday afternoon the company had received about 25,000 credit card payments for the first chapter, and another 7,000 customers promised to send a check or cash. Amazon.com, which accounted for 70 percent of sales, distributed ''Riding the Bullet'' free of charge and in one installment.</p>
        <p>Mr. King was particularly pleased to see that the number of payments so far seemed to meet his 75 percent figure, Ms. DeFilippo said.</p>
        <p>William Thornton, president of Radiant Ideas, which maintains www.stephenking.com, said that some visitors to the Web site objected to the installment plan. He said that about a quarter of visitors to the Web site declined to download the chapter.</p>
        <p>Jeff Bezos, the chief executive of Amazon.com, said he hoped that the honor-system model might inspire others to try distributing books like ''shareware,'' software circulated on the Internet with payment expected later. ''If you can make it easy for people, people are going to be willing to pay,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a hint perhaps of battles to come, some other booksellers questioned Mr. King's decision to favor Amazon.com as the exclusive bill collector. ''It is a shame,'' said Ed Morrow, owner of the Northshire Bookstore in Manchester Center, Vt., and the former president of the American Booksellers Association. He noted that Mr. King could have elected to send customers to the association's Booksense Web site or to another store, including his own.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
