<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hunk of Starry Dynamite Burns in Cygnus</title>
    <meta content="25NOVA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supernovas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Southampton</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hunk of Starry Dynamite Burns in Cygnus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Southampton astronomers say star in constellation Cygnus is destined to collide with unseen companion, burnt-out core of Sun-like star, and explode in supernova in about 200 million years; star is distant enough not to pose any danger to Earth but close enough for explosion to be easily visible (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The future appears to be very bright, though brief, for a star known as KPD1930+2752, in the constellation Cygnus. According to astronomers at the University of Southampton in England, the peculiar star is destined to explode in a supernova.</p>
        <p>Located within the Milky Way galaxy about 2,000 light-years away, KPD1930+2752 is distant enough not to pose any danger to Earth but close enough that it would provide a dazzling display.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The future appears to be very bright, though brief, for a star known as KPD1930+2752, in the constellation Cygnus. According to astronomers at the University of Southampton in England, the peculiar star is destined to explode in a supernova.</p>
        <p>Located within the Milky Way galaxy about 2,000 light-years away, KPD1930+2752 is distant enough not to pose any danger to Earth but close enough that it would provide a dazzling display.</p>
        <p>''If it went off now, it would be easily visible in the daylight sky,'' said Dr. Pierre F. L. Maxted, a postdoctoral research assistant at University of Southampton and one of the researchers whose report on the doomed star will be published in Monthly Notices of The Royal Astronomical Society.</p>
        <p>KPD1930+2752 is an unusual star that consists almost entirely of helium, not hydrogen, the most common element in the cosmos.</p>
        <p>The observations of the University of Southampton astronomers turned up another oddity: telltale wobbles in the frequency of light that are caused by the gravitational pull of an unseen companion, the burnt-out core of a Sun-like star known as a white dwarf.</p>
        <p>From the quickness of the wobbles -- one full orbit lasts only 137 minutes -- the astronomers calculated that the two stars are less than a million miles apart and will eventually crash into each other in about 200 million years. On cosmic time scales, that is the very near future. The Sun, by comparison, is expected to live about four billion years.</p>
        <p>Because the combined mass is too great for a stable star, astronomers say, a supernova will be the result.</p>
        <p>The collapse of this double-star system could result in an explosion known as a type Ia supernova. Type Ia supernovae have been immensely useful to cosmologists as cosmic candlesticks, because they all burst at roughly the same brightness. Just as one can calculate how far away a 60-watt light bulb is by how bright it appears, astronomers use type Ia supernovae to calibrate cosmic distances.</p>
        <p>But no one is sure exactly what is exploding in a type Ia supernova. The spectrum of light emitted is devoid of signs of hydrogen, which is odd since stars are generally made almost entirely of hydrogen.</p>
        <p>For that reason, astronomers hypothesize a type 1a supernova might be the explosion of a white dwarf that has exhausted its hydrogen fuel. But a white dwarf cannot explode by itself.</p>
        <p>''It's like a hunk of dynamite,'' said Dr. Robert P. Kirshner, an astronomer at the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics in Cambridge, Mass. ''It's perfectly O.K. as long as you don't detonate it.''</p>
        <p>One idea for how the white dwarf detonates is that it siphons off gas from a Sun-like companion until it becomes gravitationally unstable.</p>
        <p>Another idea is that the white dwarf collides with another star -- which is the fate of KPD1930+2752 -- and then blows up.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kirshner, for one, is not convinced that a supernova is inevitable. The collision could eject some of the mass, leaving behind a stable star.</p>
        <p>''The logic there is not perfect,'' Dr. Kirshner said. ''On the other hand, it's a very intriguing system.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
