<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Wings, No Worry, 'Cause She Sings a Lot in a Hurry</title>
    <meta content="23ANGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/arts/23ANGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7DE1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Wings, No Worry, 'Cause She Sings a Lot in a Hurry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews concert revival of 1938 musical I Maggie and Angel, at 14th Street Y; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Beauty's truth; truth is beauty./ Gabriel, blow your rooty-tooty!''</p>
        <p>This bit of celestial invocation, from the 1938 musical ''I Married an Angel,'' suggests what the Bible might sound like had it been written by Lorenz Hart. Actually, to get the full effect you need to hear the words sung, with honeyed harmony and swinging rhythms, to Richard Rodgers's music, preferably by a chorus of cherub-faced sopranos with Pre-Raphaelite hair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Beauty's truth; truth is beauty./ Gabriel, blow your rooty-tooty!''</p>
        <p>This bit of celestial invocation, from the 1938 musical ''I Married an Angel,'' suggests what the Bible might sound like had it been written by Lorenz Hart. Actually, to get the full effect you need to hear the words sung, with honeyed harmony and swinging rhythms, to Richard Rodgers's music, preferably by a chorus of cherub-faced sopranos with Pre-Raphaelite hair.</p>
        <p>As it happens, such a choir is on call through this weekend at the 14th Street Y, where ''I Married an Angel'' has been given an infectiously loving concert production by Musicals Tonight! Overseen by its tireless producer, Mel Miller, Musicals Tonight! is an admirable shoestring variation on the formula behind the beloved Encores series of American musicals in concert.</p>
        <p>With only a piano in lieu of an orchestra, and an ensemble of varying experience and polish, this production nonetheless offers vivid glimpses into the heaven that is Rodgers and Hart, which of course has room for an earthy spirit of whimsy. It says much about the show's tone that when the angel of the title marries a human, she loses her wings on her wedding night.</p>
        <p>The charms of the original production, which ran for nearly a year on Broadway, can only be partly realized in a concert staging. Instead of an angel who learns to dance when she can no longer fly, famously created by Vera Zorina, this version offers one who sings. She is played by Nanne Puritz, who is sweet-sounding indeed (in interpolated vocal parts) as the creature who descends to answer the prayers of a love-weary Budapest banker (Brad Little).</p>
        <p>But the evening, efficiently staged by Thomas Mills with musical direction by Mark Hartman, really belongs to the worldly. That category notably includes Mr. Little's converted cynic, who radiantly delivers the title song, and the invaluable Kathy Fitzgerald (of the Broadway revue ''Swingin' on a Star'') as a man-savvy countess who teaches the angel how to survive on earth.</p>
        <p>''Are all women bad?'' asks the angel. ''Only the good ones,'' answers the countess, who proceeds to explain that truth is not necessarily beautiful in a wicked hymn to deception called ''A Twinkle in Your Eye.'' Ms. Fitzgerald's knowing rendition alone makes the $15 ticket to the show a heaven-sent bargain.</p>
        <p>''I Married an Angel'' is at the 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street, Manhattan, through tomorrow. Performances are today at 8 p.m. and tomorrow at 2 and 7 p.m. Tickets are $15. Information: (212) 362-5620.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
