<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; In Sports, Dysfunction Has Its Uses</title>
    <meta content="23FREE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/sports/23FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chrebet, Wayne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Mike Freeman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DF163AF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; In Sports, Dysfunction Has Its Uses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Freeman Sports of The Times column discusses enmity between teammates and holds that it does not always negatively affect performance of team; cites New York Jets receivers Keyshawn Johnson (now of Tampa Bay Buccaneers) and Wayne Chrebet, who have publicly denigrated each other; Johnson and Chrebet played major roles in success of Jets in recent years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not long after his autobiography had been published that Keyshawn Johnson, the author, had one of his first run-ins with Wayne Chrebet, the target. The incident happened outside a dormitory, where Jets players were staying at training camp. Chrebet, according to a number of Jets players, was so angry at Johnson's calling him the ''team mascot'' in his book that he wanted to physically confront his teammate.</p>
        <p>Chrebet approached Johnson, edging close to the lanky receiver, saying that if Johnson had something to say, he should say it to his face. Johnson told Chrebet that he had better take a few steps back. It seemed that a fight was inevitable until a teammate arrived to calm things down. The Rumble in the Gang Green Jungle was avoided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not long after his autobiography had been published that Keyshawn Johnson, the author, had one of his first run-ins with Wayne Chrebet, the target. The incident happened outside a dormitory, where Jets players were staying at training camp. Chrebet, according to a number of Jets players, was so angry at Johnson's calling him the ''team mascot'' in his book that he wanted to physically confront his teammate.</p>
        <p>Chrebet approached Johnson, edging close to the lanky receiver, saying that if Johnson had something to say, he should say it to his face. Johnson told Chrebet that he had better take a few steps back. It seemed that a fight was inevitable until a teammate arrived to calm things down. The Rumble in the Gang Green Jungle was avoided.</p>
        <p>Chrebet, who is six inches shorter and nearly 25 pounds lighter, and who declined repeated requests for interviews this week, showed guts in confronting Johnson that day nearly four years ago, but he also must have had rocks in his head. Johnson could fold Chrebet up and stash him in a carry-on.</p>
        <p>The dislike between these two flowed like venom through a snakebite. Still, for four seasons on the field, they co-existed well, Johnson providing offensive explosion while Chrebet played best supporting actor, a mighty mite who dominated the underneath passing lanes.</p>
        <p>Now Johnson expresses his dislike of Chrebet from afar, lobbing grenades from sunny Tampa, where the 3-0 Jets travel this week to play the 3-0 Buccaneers. Maybe Johnson and Chrebet will go on a fishing trip together before the game to patch things up.</p>
        <p>Or maybe not.</p>
        <p>The fact that the two never shared a cup of coffee but still enjoyed individual and team success is not unusual in sports. Two teammates can hate each other and still win. A coach and player may not be able to sit in the same room without staring poison darts in each other's direction, but the team rolls once the games begin. A general manager thinks the coaching staff isn't playing his players out of spite, but the franchise prospers.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in sports it is sometimes fine to be dysfunctional. Billy Martin and Reggie Jackson argued daily, except when Martin was fighting George Steinbrenner. Late in his career, San Francisco quarterback Joe Montana despised his backup, Steve Young. They both won titles. Montana is in the Hall of Fame and Young is on his way.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Bulls often wanted to wring the neck of that great sports thespian Dennis Rodman during their more recent championship runs. Center Patrick Ewing, who is old school, never jelled with his teammate Latrell Sprewell, who is hip-hop; the Knicks still made the postseason dance. The Houston Comets of the Women's National Basketball Association just won their fourth championship, even though their two best players, Sheryl Swoopes and Cynthia Cooper, barely speak.</p>
        <p>Dislike, spite, lack of trust -- teams won't admit it but those wonderful emotions can sometimes propel them as much as unity and harmony. Johnson is a classic self-motivator, so he would probably argue this point, but a small part of him was in competition with Chrebet, always wanting to outdo him, and that made Johnson even better than he already was. And Chrebet wanted to top Johnson, which gave Chrebet his edge on the field.</p>
        <p>They competed and the Jets prospered.</p>
        <p>Johnson has been portrayed as a bad guy because he has spoken out -- and out -- against Chrebet. Johnson owns a restaurant and is one of the hardest-working players in football, and his name has never shown up on a police blotter. What's not to like about that resume?</p>
        <p>The news media complain that Johnson talks a lot. Sure, his mouth sometimes needs a stop sign, but if he didn't do interviews, he would be ripped for being surly. Talk too much, athletes are told to pipe down; talk too little, they're uncooperative.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, to many, Chrebet is the good guy, the anti-Keyshawn. And there are many things to like about Chrebet. Yet Chrebet has not always been an angel when it comes to his nemesis. During Johnson's rookie season, before a team meeting, Johnson sat in a chair that Chrebet, who had been with the Jets for one year, commonly used. Chrebet told Johnson to move. Johnson took the high road and did. It was all part of the competition.</p>
        <p>Johnson said that after the Buccaneers play the Jets, he would not shake the hand of Coach Al Groh, whom Johnson blames for trading him to Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Johnson and Chrebet probably won't exchange pleasantries either.</p>
        <p>Or, thankfully, punches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
