<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sideshow Is Over; Let the Feature Begin</title>
    <meta content="23JETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/sports/23JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: JETS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DC1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sideshow Is Over; Let the Feature Begin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets prepare for game against Tampa Bay Buccaneers, where former Jets receiver Keyshawn Johnson plays (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jets Coach Al Groh looked relieved when he walked into a nearly deserted news media room today, after encountering a packed house all week overflowing with reporters who peppered him with questions about Keyshawn Johnson. Groh spoke to the team early in the week about trying to avoid becoming entangled in the Johnson sideshow; the players were told to be careful what they said about Johnson. Still, Groh said he did not dread weeks like this.</p>
        <p>''You have that type of thing when you're in playoff games,'' he said. ''There's a lot of hype that surrounds a lot of games during the season. What teams that are successful learn to do is keep their eye on the target. Players have to learn how to do that. If you can cut the fat off and deal with a nice lean cut, that's what good teams have to be able to do. If there were nobody coming to the game, I would still think it's important that the targets are clearly seen by the team.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jets Coach Al Groh looked relieved when he walked into a nearly deserted news media room today, after encountering a packed house all week overflowing with reporters who peppered him with questions about Keyshawn Johnson. Groh spoke to the team early in the week about trying to avoid becoming entangled in the Johnson sideshow; the players were told to be careful what they said about Johnson. Still, Groh said he did not dread weeks like this.</p>
        <p>''You have that type of thing when you're in playoff games,'' he said. ''There's a lot of hype that surrounds a lot of games during the season. What teams that are successful learn to do is keep their eye on the target. Players have to learn how to do that. If you can cut the fat off and deal with a nice lean cut, that's what good teams have to be able to do. If there were nobody coming to the game, I would still think it's important that the targets are clearly seen by the team.''</p>
        <p>Groh, in explaining what he meant, cited Tiger Woods as an example of an athlete able to block out all distractions. Groh noted that Woods had skipped a memorial service for the late golfer Payne Stewart just before the start of the United States Open this year, which Woods won in a runaway. Groh said he did not mention Woods to the Jets, but whatever he did say apparently worked.</p>
        <p>''He does a great job telling us what he expects from us,'' said center Kevin Mawae, who was the only Jet to speak out about Johnson this week. ''The guys in the locker room do a good job of not buying into the hype. The last thing you want to do is be a locker-room poster boy for the other team. Which I heard I may have made anyway.''</p>
        <p>Cornerback Aaron Glenn said there would be some sense of relief in the Jets' locker room when this week is over. The Jets have had two heavily hyped games in their first four weeks: the game in the second week of the season against Bill Belichick's Patriots and now Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Wayne Chrebet did not show up in the locker room again today when reporters were permitted in, but he did manage to dance around the subject of Johnson when he made a prescheduled appearance on WFAN radio. Chrebet said that he had left the Jets' locker room to watch television whenever reporters came in this week. ''Some players, that's part of their routine,'' Chrebet said of Johnson's comments. ''My routine is just to go do the necessary things and not let any distractions get in the way.''</p>
        <p>Jets Must Stop the Run</p>
        <p>Lost this week while the focus was on Keyshawn Johnson is that the heart of the Bucs' offense is their running game. The passing game has accounted for four touchdowns, as many as fullback Mike Alstott has alone. Alstott, a locomotive of a fullback at 6 feet 1 inch, 248 pounds, pairs with Warrick Dunn, the whippet running back at 5-8, 180. Alstott has 193 yards on 52 rushes. Dunn has 143 yards on 40 runs.</p>
        <p>''Both have a style that's fairly unique,'' Groh said. ''Alstott is a big back with finesse. He's really light on his feet. When he gets cornered, then he takes advantage of his great size and becomes a tackle breaker.''</p>
        <p>Said Aaron Glenn: ''They say Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne are thunder and lightning, right? Well, this is another thunder and lightning right here. You have a guy who comes in and he's real quick when they do those one-back sets in Dunn. Then you have the big bruiser back there in Alstott. It's going to be a challenge for us to tackle that guy.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: JETS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
