<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journal; No Business Like Show Business</title>
    <meta content="23RICH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/opinion/23RICH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Live With Regis (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DC1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journal; No Business Like Show Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Rich Op-Ed column on George W Bush's awkward appearance on television program Live With Regis, illustrating that male candidates desperately seeking undecided female voters will do desperate things; also takes issue with Al Gore's often self-contradictory posturing about Hollywood as 'creepy' preview of what his administration might be like at its pandering worst (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not since Richard Nixon tried to prove his 60's hip bona fides by delivering a ''Sock it to me'' gag on ''Laugh-In'' has there been a shotgun marriage of show biz and politics more awkward than George W. Bush's Thursday appearance on ''Live With Regis.'' But male candidates desperately seeking undecided female voters will do desperate things. In this case, Mr. Bush -- whose co-stars on the show were a man who breaks boards over his head and the singer Sarah Brightman -- donned a dark shirt and matching tie from the ''Regis collection'' and suffered gladly the morning's Kathie Lee wannabe, the persistently dim Susan Hawk of ''Survivor.'' He at least knew better than to give her a smooch, as he had Oprah two days before in his continuing if doomed quest to make up the ground he lost after Al's Excellent Kiss.</p>
        <p>You almost have to feel for Mr. Bush. A man who by his own admission loved ''Cats'' and hasn't been to a movie theater in years, he is not exactly a slick show-biz hand. John Mellencamp and Tom Petty have even forbidden him to play their songs at rallies. But swamped by Al Gore's latest manic chat-show tour (Oprah, Letterman, Leno in 10 days) and Joe Lieberman's (Imus, Conan, Jon Stewart in 24 hours), the poor guy has no choice but to play, even if he doesn't quite get the game. How long will it be before Dick Cheney starts quipping big time with Gilbert Gottfried on ''Hollywood Squares''?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not since Richard Nixon tried to prove his 60's hip bona fides by delivering a ''Sock it to me'' gag on ''Laugh-In'' has there been a shotgun marriage of show biz and politics more awkward than George W. Bush's Thursday appearance on ''Live With Regis.'' But male candidates desperately seeking undecided female voters will do desperate things. In this case, Mr. Bush -- whose co-stars on the show were a man who breaks boards over his head and the singer Sarah Brightman -- donned a dark shirt and matching tie from the ''Regis collection'' and suffered gladly the morning's Kathie Lee wannabe, the persistently dim Susan Hawk of ''Survivor.'' He at least knew better than to give her a smooch, as he had Oprah two days before in his continuing if doomed quest to make up the ground he lost after Al's Excellent Kiss.</p>
        <p>You almost have to feel for Mr. Bush. A man who by his own admission loved ''Cats'' and hasn't been to a movie theater in years, he is not exactly a slick show-biz hand. John Mellencamp and Tom Petty have even forbidden him to play their songs at rallies. But swamped by Al Gore's latest manic chat-show tour (Oprah, Letterman, Leno in 10 days) and Joe Lieberman's (Imus, Conan, Jon Stewart in 24 hours), the poor guy has no choice but to play, even if he doesn't quite get the game. How long will it be before Dick Cheney starts quipping big time with Gilbert Gottfried on ''Hollywood Squares''?</p>
        <p>Pity Mr. Bush. He's so out of it that he may be the only politician in America, regardless of party, who has not hypocritically grandstanded about the Federal Trade Commission's ''shocking'' report that entertainment companies market violence and sex to kids. Instead of offering a glib governmental panacea to curb Hollywood excesses, Mr. Bush warned that Washington schemes to govern cultural content, ''no matter how well intended or well funded, are simply no match'' for parental supervision.</p>
        <p>Such is the fallen estate of the Bush campaign, however, that his rational stance was easily drowned out by his opponents' shameless barrage of TV clowning (take the Manischewitz shtick, please, Mr. Lieberman), moralistic sermonizing and over-the-top Radio City and Beverly Hills fund-raising. Mr. Bush was also sabotaged by his own self-immolating strategists, who sent their personal Dr. Laura stand-in, Lynne Cheney, as the ticket's anti-Hollywood emissary to Congress and political talk shows. With characteristic shrillness and selective indignation, Ms. Cheney condemned Eminem (though, curiously, without any reference to his homophobic lyrics) and a five-year-old Miramax movie seen only in art houses (''Kids'') while scrupulously avoiding mention of more recent violent (''Fight Club'') and lubricious (''There's Something About Mary'') fare marketed to kids by the conservative fat cat Rupert Murdoch.</p>
        <p>This whole culture war, of course, is for public consumption only until Election Day. As Ernest Hollings, the South Carolina Democrat, observed in last week's Senate Commerce Committee hearing, there have been 20 hearings by the same committee on kids and media -- and what do taxpayers have to show for it? The V-chip! Mr. Gore proudly takes credit for that gizmo, but it's no Internet. Ninety-seven percent of American parents don't use it, according to a study that another Democrat, John Breaux, cited in the hearing. The vice president's new placebo for worried moms -- his ultimatum that Hollywood ''shape up in six months'' or face punitive legislation -- is just as feeble. Such legislation is more likely a full-employment program for First Amendment lawyers than an impediment to any teenager's access to Dr. Dre.</p>
        <p>Which is not to say that Mr. Gore's frenzied and often self-contradictory posturing about Hollywood has been without meaning. It's a creepy, if G-rated, preview of coming attractions depicting what his administration may be like at its opportunistic and pandering worst.</p>
        <p>On the matter of culture and children, Mr. Gore is repeating his familiar pattern. It was not until years after his sister died of lung cancer that he stopped taking tobacco money and boasting of his tobacco farming so that he could tardily declare Joe Camel Public Enemy No. 1. According to The Los Angeles Times, the vice president's embrace of the F.T.C. report is just as sudden a conversion: a year ago he was reassuring Hollywood executives that he had nothing to do with President Clinton's post-Columbine decision to commission it in the first place. Mr. Gore pulled a similar stunt in 1987 when he and Tipper Gore, on the eve of his first presidential run, groveled behind closed doors before Hollywood donors to disown as a ''mistake'' Mrs. Gore's 1985 anti-rock-smut crusade, which had led to another high-dudgeon Congressional hearing.</p>
        <p>Yet even were Mr. Gore consistent on this issue, it would still be a smoke screen to deflect public attention from what's really going on in the fast-consolidating entertainment industry right now -- and its potentially deleterious effect on children and parents alike. The most important matter before the F.T.C. -- and the F.C.C. -- is hardly the report Mr. Gore and Mrs. Cheney are hawking but the approval of pending media mergers like the AOL purchase of Time Warner. These momentous deliberations are happening off-camera and receive far less attention from politicians and press.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates here and in Europe believe that an unchecked AOL Time Warner may have enough technological and economic clout to dictate how Americans use the coming cable TV-Internet box (and what content they get at what price). Part of that clout could well determine what movies and music are pushed to future generations of children and under what rules. The time is fast arriving when most kids will rent or purchase their media in the privacy of their own homes by cable pay-per-view or Internet downloads rather than by going to multiplexes, Blockbuster or record stores. (Multiplexes are already a dwindling source of movie distribution -- witness the recent theater-chain bankruptcies.)</p>
        <p>But even as Mr. Gore proposes government intervention in movie-and-music marketing, he offers nothing but dead silence about AOL Time Warner and other entertainment industry regulatory issues -- all of which will have a far more lasting effect on the child culture he purports to hold so close to his heart as a potential Parent in Chief.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign can't call Mr. Gore on this. While the vice president often goes Hollywood -- the Gores even had Disney supply costly ''Beauty and the Beast'' costumes and a makeup artist for their 1995 Halloween party -- Mr. Bush has actually worked for Hollywood. As a board member of Silver Screen, which financed R-rated Disney Touchstone movies, he pocketed $100,000 over a decade.</p>
        <p>In this regard, the political contributions that are most worth tracking are not those high-profile sums that Mr. Gore collected from movie stars and directors last week. Steven Spielberg, Rob Reiner and Tom Hanks aren't giving so that Mr. Gore will help them let 15-year-olds sneak into ''Saving Private Ryan'' -- they're giving because they support his traditionally liberal stands on social issues.</p>
        <p>Media corporations, by contrast, are seeking favors -- big regulatory favors that increase their hold on our culture, airwaves and wallets. According to the Center for Responsive Politics, the two top contributors, Seagram (home of Eminem) and Time Warner, give extravagantly to both parties. Everyone's in the tank. A new investigation by the Center for Public Integrity (read it at  www.publicintegrity.org) reveals that some 118 members of Congress, as well as F.C.C. employees, have traveled as far as Taiwan on media-corporation junkets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush isn't going to challenge these corporations any more than Mr. Gore or Mr. Lieberman are, but at least he doesn't condescend to us by pretending he will. The ingenious trick of Mr. Gore's strategy is that he exploits the vast reach of the entertainment industry to get out his message of phony threats against the entertainment industry. And he doesn't risk being grilled about this contradiction since he has held no press conference with actual journalists, as opposed to entertainers, since mid-July.</p>
        <p>Poor Mr. Bush can't even begin to compete in this racket. He is so clueless about show biz that he hoped he might book into Letterman during his New York visit this week, when the show was in reruns. Ricki Lake awaits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
