<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art Auction Houses Agree to Pay $512 Million in Price-Fixing Case</title>
    <meta content="23AUCT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/business/23AUCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000929T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubman, A Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davidge, Christopher M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Diana D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DE163AF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art Auction Houses Agree to Pay $512 Million in Price-Fixing Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL and RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol; Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sotheby's and Christie's agree to pay $512 million to settle charges that they cheated buyers and sellers in price-fixing scheme dating back to 1992; reported civil settlement comes as Justice Department steps up three-year criminal probe on collusion that stifled competition; settlement is equivalent of 3-4 years of annual pretax profits, but trial judgment could have reached $1.3 billion; civil case arose from federal antitrust probe of years of secret meetings involving Christopher M Davidge of Christie's and Diana D Brooks of Sotheby's, as well as longtime Sotheby's chairman A Alfred Taubman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world's largest auction houses, Sotheby's and Christie's, agreed yesterday to pay $512 million to settle claims that they cheated buyers and sellers in a price-fixing scheme dating back to 1992.</p>
        <p>The civil settlement, reported by lawyers but not officially announced, comes as prosecutors for the Justice Department are stepping up efforts to conclude a three-year criminal investigation focusing on evidence that the two auction giants stifled competition by colluding on a host of business practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world's largest auction houses, Sotheby's and Christie's, agreed yesterday to pay $512 million to settle claims that they cheated buyers and sellers in a price-fixing scheme dating back to 1992.</p>
        <p>The civil settlement, reported by lawyers but not officially announced, comes as prosecutors for the Justice Department are stepping up efforts to conclude a three-year criminal investigation focusing on evidence that the two auction giants stifled competition by colluding on a host of business practices.</p>
        <p>The lawyers said that the auction houses are each responsible for $256 million of the settlement.</p>
        <p>The settlement is equivalent to about three or four years of annual pretax profits for each firm. If the case had gone to trial, however, and the auction houses lost, they could have been liable for triple damages, a judgment that could have reached $1.3 billion, one lawyer connected with the case said.</p>
        <p>Lawyers familiar with the negotiations said yesterday that the agreement was reached late Thursday night at the offices of Weil Gotshal &amp; Manges, the law firm representing Sotheby's, and included Christie's counsel, Skadden Arps Slate Meagher &amp; Flom, as well as the lead counsel representing the buyers and sellers in the class-action suit, Boies, Schiller &amp; Flexner of Armonk, N.Y., and Hanover, N.H.</p>
        <p>The civil case grew out of the federal antitrust investigation that focuses on documents that court papers say record years of secret meetings by top officials of the two houses aimed at colluding on fees paid by buyers and sellers as well as a host of other business practices.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have been investigating actions dating back as early as 1992 to see whether the two houses cooperated to set identical commission charges for buyers in 1992 and for sellers in 1995. This would have made it more difficult for sellers to play the houses off against each other in the hope of extracting better deals. It would have also made it impossible for buyers to choose between them solely on the basis of commission costs.</p>
        <p>The documents also established that the companies exchanged confidential lists of superrich collectors who were not to be charged commissions at all. The auction house officials are also said to have shaken hands on a host of other policies such as charging identical interest rates to sellers and not poaching each other's staffs.</p>
        <p>The settlement was based on everything from auction house employee diaries and expense accounts to travel records and notes that put Sotheby's and Christie's officials together at times and places where the strong inference pointed to conspiracy, people close to the case said.</p>
        <p>Michael L. Weiner of Skadden Arps declined to comment, referring calls to a public relations spokesman for Christie's, who did not return a call. A spokesman for Sotheby's, Matthew Weigman, also declined to comment as did David Boies and Richard B. Drubel of the Boies firm. There was no response to a message left for a Sotheby's lawyer, Greg Danilow at Weil Gotshal.</p>
        <p>The agreement will not be formally announced until Judge Lewis A. Kaplan rules on whether to approve the settlement preliminarily and give notice to the buyers and sellers, a decision that is expected soon. Under the agreement, the boards of both auction houses are required to vote on the settlement by Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, half of the $256 million would be due within 30 days of the judge's preliminary approval and the remainder after final court approval. Each auction house has the option of making up to $50 million of its payment in certificates to sellers, which would be transferable and could be used toward reducing commission costs on future consignments.</p>
        <p>In addition to the $256 million that the houses are required to pay, they also have to split the costs of notifying the 120,000 buyers and sellers as well as such administrative expenses as processing and distributing the claims, which could cost an additional $1 million, people close to the case said.</p>
        <p>On May 26, Judge Kaplan selected Mr. Boies and Mr. Drubel of the Boies firm to lead the civil case after an unusual bidding process intended, the judge said, to maximize the recovery for clients while keeping legal fees down. The judge had law firms submit sealed bids offering the highest settlement figure they would be willing to accept in negotiations and turn over entirely to their clients, without taking a fee. The firms also proposed a second figure for a settlement beyond this, from which they would receive a quarter and their clients the rest.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in an opinion that made no reference to the settlement, Judge Kaplan discussed the bidding process and noted one potential problem: if the case could not be settled for more than the winning bidder's maximum figure, the firm would have no incentive to pursue the case and would ''make a hasty exit.'' But the judge said that in such an eventuality he retained the authority to reject an inadequate settlement. There was no suggestion that the judge was referring specifically to yesterday's agreement.</p>
        <p>The federal investigation began more than three years ago but it was thought to have been dormant until January when the Justice Department's antitrust office in New York received more than 100 pages of documents -- memorandums and notes of secret meetings that took place between Christopher M. Davidge, a former Christie's chief executive, and Diana D. Brooks, his counterpart at Sotheby's. (Mr. Davidge resigned from his job on Dec. 24.) The documents also contain reports on these meetings written by Mr. Davidge and sent to his boss, Anthony Tennant, chairman of Christie's from 1993 to 1996.</p>
        <p>Along with providing the documents, Christie's agreed to cooperate with the federal inquiry and, in exchange for its help, the company was granted a form of leniency called conditional amnesty, with the provision that its cooperation be complete and truthful. Christie's general counsel, Jo Backer Laird, disclosed the cooperation on Jan. 28.</p>
        <p>The settlement also includes some of Sotheby's longtime executives including A. Alfred Taubman, the former chairman who is still its majority shareholder, and Ms. Brooks. Both abruptly resigned from their posts in February and are under investigation by federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>By some accounts, documents gathered for this case show that the collusion began with Mr. Taubman and Sir Anthony who, as early as 1992, instructed Mr. Davidge and Ms. Brooks to carry out the scheme.  Since the case began, Mr. Taubman through his lawyers, has denied any wrongdoing. Sir Anthony, when reached by telephone at his London home, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>To wind up their investigation, prosecutors under John J. Greene, head of the Justice Department antitrust office in New York, have been intensively negotiating with counsel for Ms. Brooks, seeking a deal that would secure her testimony against her former boss, Mr. Taubman, in exchange for leniency, according to people close to the talks.</p>
        <p>The settlement came after negotiations in which each auction house tried to be the first to strike an agreement in the hope that the other would be forced to accept a worse deal or to fight it out in the courts with the buyers and sellers.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 29, 2000, Friday  An article on Saturday about an agreement by Sotheby's and Christie's to pay $512 million to settle a civil antitrust lawsuit by auction buyers and sellers who contend that they were cheated by collusion on fees referred incorrectly to John J. Greene, the federal prosecutor who is leading a separate criminal antitrust investigation in New York. He is not the head of the Justice Department's New York antitrust office; the head is Ralph T. Giordano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 29, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about an agreement by Sotheby's and Christie's to pay $512 million to settle a civil antitrust lawsuit by auction buyers and sellers who contend that they were cheated by collusion on fees referred incorrectly to John J. Greene, the federal prosecutor who is leading a separate criminal antitrust investigation in New York. He is not the head of the Justice Department's New York antitrust office; the head is Ralph T. Giordano.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
