<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drawn to the Faces Others Avoid; For Some, Foster Care System Fulfills a Longing to Adopt</title>
    <meta content="23ADOP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/nyregion/23ADOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFD71F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drawn to the Faces Others Avoid; For Some, Foster Care System Fulfills a Longing to Adopt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on famously hard-to-adopt foster children in New York City's custody, many of them older, some of them with physical or emotional problems, all of them severed from their birth parents but lacking adoptive homes of their own; although many wealthier childless New Yorkers increasingly turn to costly private adoptions, often circling globe for an orphan to bring home, there are some New Yorkers willing to adopt city children that few seem to want; some of these prospective parents are driven by economics, others by their consciences; examples cited (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a windowless room on the eighth floor of a Lower Manhattan office building, a pair of photo albums are passed around one recent evening. On page after page, artful portraits of boys and girls stare up, some smiling solo at the camera, some draping their arms around a brother, a sister.</p>
        <p>The faces are achingly familiar, for they are the famously hard-to-adopt foster children in the city's custody, many of them older, some of them with physical or emotional problems, all of them legally severed from their birth parents but lacking adoptive homes of their own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a windowless room on the eighth floor of a Lower Manhattan office building, a pair of photo albums are passed around one recent evening. On page after page, artful portraits of boys and girls stare up, some smiling solo at the camera, some draping their arms around a brother, a sister.</p>
        <p>The faces are achingly familiar, for they are the famously hard-to-adopt foster children in the city's custody, many of them older, some of them with physical or emotional problems, all of them legally severed from their birth parents but lacking adoptive homes of their own.</p>
        <p>Lesser known are the faces assembled around the table, wordlessly poring over the pages of these so-called family albums.</p>
        <p>As wealthier childless New Yorkers turn increasingly to costly private adoptions, often circling the globe for an orphan to bring home, these are the New Yorkers willing to adopt the city children that few seem to want: the Queens schoolteacher itching to be a mother for the first time; the childless couple waiting for something to call out from one of these pages; the upstate Orange County parents who no longer want to take in foster children, only to have to return them some years later.</p>
        <p>Economics has something to do with their choices. None of them can afford private adoption, which can easily run up to $20,000. Adoptions from the foster care system are subsidized, offering $500 to $1,200 a month per child, depending on medical needs.</p>
        <p>But money is only part of it, they say. Like Ada Jurado, 48, who has taken in several foster children over the years, many would-be adoptive parents say they are driven by their consciences and determined to act on those consciences locally.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Jurado, a school safety monitor in Middletown, says she was driven in part by the memory of her own mother, who raised seven children and took in a stranger's child as well. The mother of her husband, Juan, also raised children other than her own. So now, with two teenage daughters moving out of the family's sprawling suburban home in a few years, Mrs. Jurado said she felt a sense of obligation to a child without a home. ''I have room now,'' she said. ''It's like wanting to give back.''</p>
        <p>In many ways, Mrs. Jurado is emblematic of those who adopt the city's foster children: mostly middle-aged women who used to be foster parents, according to a study of city adoptions by Trudy B. Festinger, a social work professor at New York University.</p>
        <p>In 1998, 3,820 foster children were adopted in New York City, and two-thirds of the people who adopted them were single parents, mostly mothers. Their median age was 51; fathers had a median age of 52. Half of the adoptive parents were the very foster parents -- including relatives -- who took the children into their care early on.</p>
        <p>There is no readily available data on the racial or class backgrounds of the people adopting city children. But Ms. Festinger says most of them are working people or those on public assistance. Although there are exceptions -- the actress Isabella Rosselini has an adoptive son from the city foster care system, as the child welfare commissioner, Nicholas Scoppetta, is fond of noting -- the parents are often from the same communities as the foster children.</p>
        <p>Whoever these prospective parents are, city officials and others say it feels as if there are never enough of them, especially in the aftermath of recent legislation aimed at speeding up adoptions. The 1997 Adoption and Safe Families Act, a federal law intended to accelerate and increase foster care adoptions, requires child welfare officials to consider ending parental rights if a child has been in foster care for 15 of the last 22 months.</p>
        <p>''I think the message is, we will need more adoptive parents if children are freed for adoption and parents' rights are terminated under A.S.F.A.,'' Mr. Scoppetta said.</p>
        <p>At the moment, there are about 1,000 children in the city's custody who have been freed for adoption but not yet placed with an adoptive family. They are the ones the city is pushing most aggressively.</p>
        <p>There are orientation sessions for interested parents like the one last week, sponsored by the Council on Adoptable Children. And there is the city's annual adoption fair scheduled for tomorrow afternoon in the East Meadow of Central Park. In addition, 14,000 children -- close to half of the total foster care caseload of 32,000 -- are in the custody of foster parents who are interested in adopting them.</p>
        <p>The city has had some success in adoptions in recent years, with the number of completed adoptions climbing from 1,130 in the 1990 fiscal year to a peak of 4,000 in 1997 and then dipping to 3,100 in 2000.</p>
        <p>Nationally, pressed by the new adoption law and financial incentives offered by the Clinton administration, adoptions have increased noticeably. According to figures released by the Department of Health and Human Services this week, adoptions rose nationwide to 46,000 in the 1999 fiscal year, from 28,000 in 1996. The federal agency has granted financial rewards to states that have increased their adoption numbers; New York was not among the recipients this year.</p>
        <p>The waits for the city's children are still typically quite long. According to Ms. Festinger's analysis, New York City children who were adopted in 1998 came into foster care at a median age of 4.4 months, were freed for adoption at 5.6 years old, and were not adopted until a median age of 8.4 years.</p>
        <p>Such waits in turn can make public adoptions virtually impossible for those who want to take in a baby. That is what Patricia, a Queens school aide, hoped for at first, a baby that she and her husband of 19 years could raise from the beginning.</p>
        <p>She does not know anyone who has gone through the private or international adoption networks, but heard only that they are prohibitively expensive. She has heard, too, about the sad, troubled lives of foster children, and seen them firsthand in the public school system.</p>
        <p>But at 44, having all but given up hopes to bear a child, she has turned to that system anyway. She says that she would now be happy to have a toddler, the younger the better. ''My husband and I don't have any children of our own,'' said Patricia, who agreed to reveal the details of her search for a child on the condition that her last name be withheld. ''We wanted a family.''</p>
        <p>Her reasons seem about as selfish and selfless as those of anyone who wants children. ''I would like to take that responsibility,'' she added, ''try to train children to be able to contribute to society, to God. I'd really love that. Aside from the love and sharing and all that, I'd really love that.''</p>
        <p>Katherine and Larry, the only white couple in the room that night, had driven in from Highland Falls, in upstate Orange County, to look through the family album. They, too, had unsuccessfully tried for years to have their own child. They, too, had heard that private adoptions would be beyond their financial reach.</p>
        <p>On this evening, Katherine, who works at a bookstore, and Larry, an architect, sat at one end of the table, long after everyone else had left, carefully looking at each picture, reading the short narratives of the children's lives and waiting for something special to leap off a page. Katherine, 45, said she was not sure what she was looking for. And she wondered aloud what would happen to all those ones she skipped: the sweet-looking boy named Clyde, the brother and sister who were at risk of being separated.</p>
        <p>''Oh my God, how do I turn the page so fast?'' she murmured. And then she turned the page.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
