<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Township Bristles as Whitman Chooses Site for Sex Offenders</title>
    <meta content="23PRIS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/nyregion/23PRIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Woodbridge (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DD163AF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Township Bristles as Whitman Chooses Site for Sex Offenders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>WOODBRIDGE, N.J., Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Gov Christine Todd Whitman decides to locate both a temporary and permanent treatment center for violent sex offenders near two state prisons in Woodbridge, prompting charges from local officials and residents that state was insincere in promising two years ago to search for other locations; Whitman also nullifies court order requiring state to relocate 115 violent sex offenders housed at Kearny jail by today, invoking state's Disaster Control Act and declaring state of emergency in housing of sex offenders; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Christine Todd Whitman decided today to locate both a temporary and a permanent treatment center for violent sex offenders near two state prisons here, prompting charges from local officials and residents that the state was insincere in promising two years ago to search for other locations.</p>
        <p>The governor also nullified a court order requiring the state to relocate 115 violent sex offenders housed at a Kearny jail by today, invoking the state's Disaster Control Act and declaring a state of emergency in the housing of sex offenders. Her action, which also angered Kearny officials, extended the state's use of the Kearny center at least until the temporary quarters in Woodbridge are ready in the next few weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Christine Todd Whitman decided today to locate both a temporary and a permanent treatment center for violent sex offenders near two state prisons here, prompting charges from local officials and residents that the state was insincere in promising two years ago to search for other locations.</p>
        <p>The governor also nullified a court order requiring the state to relocate 115 violent sex offenders housed at a Kearny jail by today, invoking the state's Disaster Control Act and declaring a state of emergency in the housing of sex offenders. Her action, which also angered Kearny officials, extended the state's use of the Kearny center at least until the temporary quarters in Woodbridge are ready in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>The Woodbridge mayor, James E. McGreevey, angrily accused the governor -- whom he nearly defeated in the last election for governor -- of creating the emergency by failing to act sooner to find a place for the sex offenders. He said the township would continue to fight in court.</p>
        <p>''This is a crisis of their own design, and they did not do this rationally,'' said Mr. McGreevey, who is running for governor in the next election, in 2001. ''One would hope that this was done for objective reasons and is not a political vendetta.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the Whitman administration proposed building the center in Woodbridge Township, which is already home to two maximum-security prisons: East Jersey State Prison and the Adult Diagnostic and Treatment Center, the state's only prison for sex offenders.. The new center would house sex offenders who have served their sentences but have been committed for further treatment by a civil court judge who has deemed them too violent to be released.</p>
        <p>When Woodbridge sued to block the center, state officials said they would seek alternatives, and later  reached a tentative agreement with officials in Maurice River Township, in South Jersey, to build the center there. But Maurice River officials reversed themselves this month after a public outcry, and on Wednesday, a State Superior Court judge denied Woodbridge's request to halt construction of the temporary center. State officials then said they would have to house the sex offenders in one of the two townships.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the governor said Woodbridge was the best site, for environmental, public safety and treatment reasons, for the proposed 300-bed, $43 million unit, to be built  on the 100-acre prison complex.</p>
        <p>She conceded that there were already about 3,000 convicts at the maximum-security prisons, but vowed that the new center would not result in any net increase in the prisons' inmate population.</p>
        <p>In the residential, industrial and warehousing areas around the proposed site of the detention center, the reaction to the governor's decision ranged from indifference to anger.</p>
        <p>One woman who works at an educational center for troubled youths in Middlesex County said that the East Jersey prison, which looms behind fencing, razor wire and high walls, was ''just a building in our midst'' and that school employees never hear or see what goes on inside.</p>
        <p>''But I just work here,'' said the woman, who would not give her name. ''I don't live here, and therein lies the difference.''</p>
        <p>Veronica Menchan, who lives barely half a mile from the entrance to the prison complex, was furious with Mrs. Whitman for putting even more of a burden on a community she said had already borne so much.</p>
        <p>''We're concerned that they are sex offenders because we hear that they are never really rehabilitated,'' said Mrs. Menchan, whose family has lived in her house for 37 years. ''We were never really terrified before, but now I am. We have enough of these places here already, but now they are going to just dump another one in our lap.''</p>
        <p>The choice of a permanent location caps a process that began two years ago, when Governor Whitman signed into law a measure allowing the state to seek civil commitment for violent sex offenders who have completed their prison terms but are considered too dangerous to release. The law requires that these offenders be segregated from inmates in the state prison system, and as a result they were initially put in space leased by the state in the Hudson County Correction Center in Kearny.</p>
        <p>But Hudson County said Mrs. Whitman's decision to keep the sex offenders there was a violation of the state's lease, and it moved in court to evict the treatment and housing unit.</p>
        <p>Mark Fleming, an assistant attorney general, said today that the governor had nullified the court's deadline to move the sex offenders out of Kearny by declaring a state of emergency in the providing of secure housing and treatment settings for the former inmates. The declaration is similar to the emergency declarations the governor makes to suspend certain laws after hurricanes and floods.</p>
        <p>The use of such powers in regard to prisons, Mr. Fleming said, was first invoked, and upheld by state courts, in the 1980's when there was a shortage of state prison beds, and county centers were pressed into service, often in the face of local opposition.</p>
        <p>The new center will be built and staffed by the Corrections Department and the state Department of Health and Senior Services. The corrections commissioner, Jack Terhune, said that under the emergency declarations, the state would continue to use the Kearny location for the next few weeks while it erects fencing, razor wire and other security equipment around the unused dormitory-style buildings on the Woodbridge site that serve as temporary housing.</p>
        <p>He said bids for the permanent unit would go out soon and completion was expected within two years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
