<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ISRAEL IS STUDYING NEGOTIATING IDEAS ONCE UNTHINKABLE</title>
    <meta content="23ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/world/23ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temple Mount (Jerusalem)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ben Ami, Shlomo (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED81F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ISRAEL IS STUDYING NEGOTIATING IDEAS ONCE UNTHINKABLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel addresses possible endgame in peace effort with Palestinians by allowing full buffet of formerly unthinkable ideas to be spread on negotiating table; most recent idea is US proposal to give UN Security Council control over Temple Mount as way to break deadlock over Judaism's holiest site; Israelis confirm that Min Shlomo Ben Ami has discussed with French and Egyptian leaders idea that international control could rise above major obstacle, but note that Yasir Arafat has not shown any interest (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would have been unthinkable just several years ago for Israel to contemplate entrusting anything to the United Nations, much less control of the most holy site in Judaism.</p>
        <p>But in the endgame of the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort, Israel is allowing a full buffet of formerly unthinkable ideas to be spread on the negotiating table as food for thought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would have been unthinkable just several years ago for Israel to contemplate entrusting anything to the United Nations, much less control of the most holy site in Judaism.</p>
        <p>But in the endgame of the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort, Israel is allowing a full buffet of formerly unthinkable ideas to be spread on the negotiating table as food for thought.</p>
        <p>Most recently, Israel has been deliberating on an American proposal that would grant the United Nations Security Council control over the Temple Mount as a way to break the Israeli-Palestinian deadlock over the sacred site. That deadlock emerged at the Camp David talks in July as the major obstacle to a comprehensive settlement.</p>
        <p>According to today's issue of the Israeli newspaper Haaretz, in fact, Israeli diplomats are working assiduously to promote the idea that only international control of the 35-acre holy zone would resolve competing Israeli and Palestinians claims on the site -- by rising above them.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials confirmed only that Foreign Minister Shlomo Ben Ami had discussed the idea with French and Egyptian leaders this week.</p>
        <p>They noted, however, that the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, had not shown any interest in the proposal; he is seeking full Palestinian sovereignty over what is known in Arabic as Haram al Sharif, the Noble Sanctuary, which is the third holiest site in Islam.</p>
        <p>''Until Arafat is willing to consider this or any other alternative, we can't really consider any idea seriously ourselves,'' said Gadi Baltiansky, a spokesman for Prime Minister Ehud Barak.</p>
        <p>While meetings between Israeli and Palestinian negotiators did take place here this week -- despite Israeli flip-flopping about whether to proceed -- the talks appear to be at a fruitless juncture.</p>
        <p>Israel's Channel 2, however, reported tonight that efforts were under way to arrange a meeting between Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat for Saturday night. There was no official confirmation.</p>
        <p>Both parties are looking for the United States to try to break the stalemate by as early as next week, either by issuing a draft treaty with bridging proposals or by convening another summit meeting or both.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Mr. Barak are trying to impart a sense of urgency -- Mr. Clinton because his months in office are numbered and Mr. Barak because he is likely to face a call for new elections when Parliament reconvenes at the end of October.</p>
        <p>But the Palestinians say they are not willing to be rushed. ''In spite of the wish to reach an agreement before the American elections, this need is not absolute,'' Nabil Shaath, the Palestinian minister of planning and international cooperation, said early this week in a speech in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Negotiations are going to continue with whoever is elected, Gore or Bush,'' he said. ''Secondly, lame duck presidents have managed in the past to accomplish great things in the Middle East.''</p>
        <p>United Nations control of the Temple Mount is the latest in a series of proposals for resolving the status of the site, which more than any other issue, stands in the way of a final peace accord that would formally end the 52-year-old Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</p>
        <p>Since the Old City was occupied by Israel in the aftermath of the 1967 Middle East war, Israel has claimed sovereignty over the entire huge stone structure, but permitted the Islamic authorities to exercise control over the two ancient mosques and great stone plaza on top.</p>
        <p>The Western Wall beneath, guarded by Israeli soldiers, is the most sacred site of worship for Jews.</p>
        <p>Gershom Gorenberg, an expert on the mount, said the site had predictably ended up as the core of the conflict not only because of its religious importance to both sides but also because of its ''mythic value'' in their historical narratives.</p>
        <p>For secular Israelis, capturing the mount was a pinnacle of Zionism, which made the Jewish homeland more solid by reclaiming the sacred center of Judaism after two millenniums. Religious Jews saw it as the first step toward redemption. For the Palestinians, in contrast, losing the mount became emblematic of all the other losses; regaining it became a driving goal of their nationalist movement.</p>
        <p>The myths, though, never squared with the reality on the ground. The Israelis never really took over the mount, and the Palestinians never really lost it. The Israelis claimed the Western Wall and an adjacent Arab neighborhood that they razed to created the wall's plaza.</p>
        <p>But they have allowed the Muslim authorities continued control over Al Aksa mosque and the Dome of the Rock to this day, backed up the country's chief rabbis.</p>
        <p>There has been what Mr. Gorenberg -- whose book, ''The End of Days: Fundamentalism and the Struggle for the Temple Mount,'' will be published by The Free Press in December -- calls ''a de facto division of holy space'' that has prevented a holy war.</p>
        <p>But the Camp David talks, which for the first time in seven years of peace talks dealt with the previously taboo subject of contested Jerusalem, forced decades of ambiguity into the open. It provoked some Israelis to admit aloud, as a Haaretz editorial did last week, ''The Temple Mount is not really in our hands.''</p>
        <p>The editorial called on Mr. Barak ''to enshrine'' the existing arrangement in a permanent agreement, saying it is ''not in Israel's interest to impose its sovereignty over a Muslim place of worship.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barak and his associates insisted on such sovereignty, which even many secular, moderate Israelis consider important.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians, however, refused to enter into a long-term lease arrangement for their holy space. They also questioned Israeli historical claims that the site was home to the First and Second Temple as well as Jewish traditional beliefs that Adam was created there and that Abraham nearly sacrificed Isaac there.</p>
        <p>No Arab leader, Mr. Arafat said, could give away the rock from which Muhammad is said to have leapt to heaven. No Jewish leader, Mr. Barak said, could give away the rock that more or less marks where the temple once stood.</p>
        <p>''If an agreement is reached, then in religious and national terms, the two sides will have agreed to the idea of more than one truth existing in Jerusalem -- that there's more than one way up God's mountain,'' Mr. Gorenberg said. ''But that's a big if.''</p>
        <p>Under the latest proposal, the Security Council would assume sovereignty, granting control over the Islamic sites to the Palestinians while the Israelis kept the Western Wall.</p>
        <p>The seeming Israeli willingness to seek Security Council guarantees for such an arrangement is seen here as a sign of how Israel's relations with the United Nations have improved since it withdrew from southern Lebanon and advertised a new willingness to surrender much of East Jerusalem in a peace pact with the Palestinians. For more than three decades, Israel has been the target of regular condemnation by the United Nations for its occupation of lands seized in war.</p>
        <p>Previously, Mr. Arafat had proposed assigning control of the site to an Islamic committee, which Israel rejected. Academic experts suggested recognizing divine sovereignty.</p>
        <p>And the Americans proposed split-level sovereignty: The Palestinians would control the upper level and the Israelis the subterranean space, where the remains of the temple are believed to be. That prompted the Palestinians to say this week that if they would promise to prevent excavations under the site if they got  sovereignty.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
