<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Correcting A Mistake</title>
    <meta content="23LEWI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/opinion/23LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DF163AF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Correcting A Mistake</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column praises House for correcting legislative mistake in 1996 immigration law which has led to retroactive deportation of aliens for minor offenses that may have occured years ago (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hardly anyone noticed, but the House of Representatives did something rare and admirable the other day. It voted to correct a legislative mistake that has had cruel consequences for thousands of legally admitted aliens: the retroactive deportation feature of the 1996 Immigration Act.</p>
        <p>The 1996 law defined as ''aggravated felonies'' requiring deportation a large number of offenses, including minor misdemeanors. And it applied the new definition retroactively, so that people who had been convicted before 1996 were subject to deportation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hardly anyone noticed, but the House of Representatives did something rare and admirable the other day. It voted to correct a legislative mistake that has had cruel consequences for thousands of legally admitted aliens: the retroactive deportation feature of the 1996 Immigration Act.</p>
        <p>The 1996 law defined as ''aggravated felonies'' requiring deportation a large number of offenses, including minor misdemeanors. And it applied the new definition retroactively, so that people who had been convicted before 1996 were subject to deportation.</p>
        <p>I have described, in columns, some harsh human results of the 1996 law. Mary Anne Gehris, who was brought to this country from Germany as an infant 33 years ago, pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor in 1988 for pulling another woman's hair in a quarrel. She avoided deportation only when her home state pardoned her. Others were not so lucky.</p>
        <p>The bill just passed by the House provides that an alien who was convicted of an ''aggravated felony'' before passage of the 1996 act could avoid deportation. Moreover, the bill allows those who have already been deported under the retroactive clause to apply for readmission. The bill now goes to the Senate.</p>
        <p>Aliens have little or no political influence. How, then, did this bill get through the House -- without a dissenting voice, as it happens?</p>
        <p>Horror stories about the wrenching of people from their families for deportation troubled Americans. People asked me why retroactive deportations did not violate the clause of the Constitution barring ex post facto laws. (The answer is that the bar applies only to criminal laws, and deportation has always been treated by the courts as non-criminal.)</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress urged broad changes in the 1996 act, such as reducing the number of ''aggravated felonies'' and restoring judicial review. Republicans resisted those changes. But Lamar Smith, a principal author of the 1996 act and chairman of the House immigration subcommittee, was ready to support a limited reform. He worked with liberal Democrats, notably Representative Barney Frank of Massachusetts, to produce the bill that passed.</p>
        <p>On the floor such ideological opposites as Mr. Frank and Henry Hyde, Republican of Illinois and chairman of the House Judiciary Committee, spoke for the bill. When a crime was committed long ago, Mr. Hyde said, and aliens ''have clearly rehabilitated themselves,'' deportation ''seems an extreme remedy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frank made the point that the House vote contradicted the idea ''that only big money dominates politics.'' The bill ''will mean a great deal to many people,'' he said, ''and to my knowledge there are not a lot of campaign contributors among them.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Hyde and Mr. Frank said that without the new bill the Immigration and Naturalization Service  should have used its discretion not to pursue deportations where, in Mr. Hyde's words, ''the facts called out for forbearance.'' But there is too little wise forbearance in the I.N.S., as a new horror story this week showed.</p>
        <p>Claudia Young is the German wife of an American, Rick Young, who brought her to Portland, Ore. As described in an article by Richard Read in The Oregonian, she was nursing her year-old daughter on July 18 when I.N.S. officers arrested her. She was handcuffed and chained, twice strip-searched, then deported and barred from returning to the United States for 10 years.</p>
        <p>Why? Because she did not have the proper visa. An I.N.S. official in Portland said the law gave him no choice. So much for discretion -- or common sense.</p>
        <p>Officials at I.N.S. headquarters in Washington were distressed at the story. A spokesman said to me, ''It won't happen again.'' And, he said, ''We're ready to help Claudia Young come back.''</p>
        <p>What that story tells us is that amending unjust immigration law is necessary -- but it is also necessary to remove a harsh rigidity that persists in I.N.S. ranks.</p>
        <p>One way to accomplish that human change is to lay down guidelines explaining to I.N.S. agents that they have discretion to use what Henry Hyde called ''forbearance,'' and then to train them in its use. The I.N.S. has promised for many months to issue just such guidelines. Officials now say that the guidelines and training should come soon. It cannot be soon enough.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
