<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; What Will Women Want? Two Peeks</title>
    <meta content="23DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/living/23DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ghesquiere, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lang, Helmut</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerrigan, Daryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DC1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; What Will Women Want? Two Peeks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of spring collections of Nicolas Ghesquiere, French designer, Helmut Lang, Austrian, and Daryl Kerrigan, who is Irish, presented on runways of New York City; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicolas Ghesquiere did a Peter Pan yesterday after his season-defining Callaghan show, flying from the kisses of editors before they could tell him what is already old news. That he is changing fashion.</p>
        <p>Between Mr. Ghesquiere and Helmut Lang, who showed a first-rate collection on Thursday, lies the direction of fashion for next spring and perhaps beyond. It remains to be seen, of course, what the Europeans will dish out when they begin their collections next week in London. But here in New York, where the runways have been ruled for years by self-made legends from the Bronx and small towns of the Midwest, the day now belongs to Mr. Ghesquiere, who is French; Mr. Lang, who is Austrian; and, emphatically, Daryl Kerrigan, who is Irish and in her way is also influencing fashion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicolas Ghesquiere did a Peter Pan yesterday after his season-defining Callaghan show, flying from the kisses of editors before they could tell him what is already old news. That he is changing fashion.</p>
        <p>Between Mr. Ghesquiere and Helmut Lang, who showed a first-rate collection on Thursday, lies the direction of fashion for next spring and perhaps beyond. It remains to be seen, of course, what the Europeans will dish out when they begin their collections next week in London. But here in New York, where the runways have been ruled for years by self-made legends from the Bronx and small towns of the Midwest, the day now belongs to Mr. Ghesquiere, who is French; Mr. Lang, who is Austrian; and, emphatically, Daryl Kerrigan, who is Irish and in her way is also influencing fashion.</p>
        <p>It's true that both Mr. Ghesquiere and Mr. Lang showed clothes that brought to mind, respectively, the styles of the late Giorgio di Sant'Angelo and Azzedine Alaia. And yet they convincingly moved beyond those references, so that when you looked at Mr. Ghesquiere's gathered jersey dresses wound with grommeted belts or Mr. Lang's bandagelike harnesses over T-shirts or with gladiator skirts, your brain recognized the fretwork, but the heart still raced on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ghesquiere, who also designs for the prestige house Balenciaga, opened with draped cotton T-shirts over elastic-gathered briefs, and advanced to jersey dresses and skirts that fell in drapes and folds around the body, ending often in asymmetrical points just above the knee. Though soft, the clothes had a tough, modern edge, and the lightning bolts of red, blue and silver sequins that streaked improbably across the front of some of the evening looks evoked the valor of decoration ribbons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lang, in an interview the day after his show, said that while it was possible to see a connection between his clothes and those of Mr. Alaia, the inspiration for his crisscrossed harnesses was microscopic drawings of fish and insects he had found in some 17th-century books. ''They're completely amazing,'' he said. No doubt. But what one noticed about his presentation, especially as the show progressed, was how immaculate every detail was -- from the flawless hair and makeup to the soundtrack of obscure love songs and the rigorous way Mr. Lang abstained from sending out anything that didn't convey a message of female strength.</p>
        <p>That meant pleated skirts and tight bodices with Roman sandals, and strict-looking coats and jackets over bra tops that, for once, looked right. Black leather was scaled with tiny perforations, giving pants a twinkling effect, as if covered in sequins. The detail was another idea, Mr. Lang said, inspired by his biology books. He has always been loath to give the source of his more fetishistic styles, such as trousers with a half-moon opening just above the rear that could easily accommodate a roving hand. He is too discreet or too coy for such conjecture. But think of it as a Freudian slit. Mr. Lang is not Viennese for nothing.</p>
        <p>Far more meaningful is the almost couture finish that Mr. Lang has given his clothes for several years, and that came through clearest with this collection. Which may explain why he plans to open a workroom in New York next year for made-to-measure clothes for both men and women. ''But we'll do it in a modern way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So those were the high points. Elsewhere on the runways, it was a mixed bag. What was Victor Alfaro up to? Hard to tell. His blousey and fan-pleated tops with matching satin trousers in frosted lipstick hues of peach and taupe seemed to combine louche glamour with the worst elements of bridge sportswear. Under a lattice of dangling bird cages, Cynthia Rowley on Thursday presented a less-than-thrilling collection of cream cotton eyelet in snug trousers and flounced dresses, vintage-looking lingerie silk and dresses that looked as if the models had been attacked with neon Silly String. But there were good moments of urban dishabille, notably a camisole of washed pink silk gathered at the waist over lacquered white jeans scattered with tiny painted flowers around the pockets.</p>
        <p>The key word on Richard Tyler's invitation for his show Thursday was ''Dolls,'' making one think that his expert tailoring might be squandered on cradle cutie-pies. In fact, he meant store mannequins, eerie resin ladies, which, when gathered in a menage or posed seductively, seemed to be enjoying a much more active fantasy life than the people who went to Mr. Tyler's Gramercy Park mansion to inspect them. It was a marvelous way to show off his clothes -- the expert embroidery on hip-hugging leather pants, the cut of a jacket composed of geometric pieces of gray wool, the derriere draping of a low-backed minidress. At their best, Mr. Tyler's clothes suggest an interior life, a knowingness about sex and sin that is hidden, like some V.I.P. room of the senses, behind a wall of perfect tailoring.</p>
        <p>At Gavin Brown's art gallery on West 15th Street, Sonja Rubin and Kip Chapelle staged a tableau vivant on Wednesday night, with powdered models in rustic leather and linen mixed with earthy knits, including a loosely braided halter that looked like a snarl of brown roots. Though a bit on the dour side, their clothes have a poetic sensuality, and they have a following. As a bleached-blond pianist belted out a somber ''Marseillaise'' to signal the start of the presentation, in rushed the young onlookers in their own nomadic Chelsea weeds. The temperature in the room rose by 20 degrees.</p>
        <p>The sexual taunt of John Bartlett's collection, at the Bryant Park tents on Thursday night, was not the 50 or so buff men standing in Jockey shorts on an escalated platform, though they helped. It was the use of rope -- a lariat around the neck, a twisted knot at the waist of beautifully plain jersey dresses. But as a theme it was a noose: clever as a tiny whip coiled on the shoulder of a white leather sheath, but ultimately irrelevant.</p>
        <p>Cunning little frocks for romance against the downy pillows? Sounds like Tuleh, the line designed by Bryan Bradley and Josh Patner, who showed a featherweight collection of playful prints and sequined candy stripes on Friday at Sotheby's. Their show was an ode to the late fashion illustrator Antonio Lopez, with lots of halter numbers and trailing sashes, but without the sense of real abandon that Mr. Lopez captured, and that makes the fashion heart beat faster.</p>
        <p>Looking at clothes by designers who see connections between seams and, say, modern sculpture generally leaves you with a headache. Ralph Rucci is an exception. His show on Friday elegantly played structure against volume, and made fine use of harder materials, like stingray, with classic fabrics like jersey and gazar. Paintings by Cy Twombly and Antonio Tapies inspired prints on organza, but not at the expense of craft, which is Mr. Rucci's main obsession.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
