<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If It's Goodbye Books, Then Hello . . . What?</title>
    <meta content="23TANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/technology/23TANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THINK TANK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zipperstein, Steven J (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Think Tank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If It's Goodbye Books, Then Hello . . . What?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>E1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has reading become old-fashioned? Are computers dragging literacy down? Are Americans going to cultural hell in a technological handbasket? Ruminations on these and related questions appeared in the summer 2000 issue of Dissent magazine in an article titled ''Goodbye to All That?: Elegies for the Book.'' The author is Steven J. Zipperstein, the David E. Koshland Professor in Jewish Culture and History at Stanford University. Excerpts follow.</p>
        <p>I write these words in a building on the Stanford campus carved out of limestone, designed by Frederick Law Olmstead at the turn of the century, when he helped John Stanford transform his massive horse farm into a university. Mine was among the first buildings; the humanities here remain housed mostly in these older, sedate, dusty buildings, with the sciences, the law school and the business school in far more plush, up-to-date quarters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Has reading become old-fashioned? Are computers dragging literacy down? Are Americans going to cultural hell in a technological handbasket? Ruminations on these and related questions appeared in the summer 2000 issue of Dissent magazine in an article titled ''Goodbye to All That?: Elegies for the Book.'' The author is Steven J. Zipperstein, the David E. Koshland Professor in Jewish Culture and History at Stanford University. Excerpts follow.</p>
        <p>I write these words in a building on the Stanford campus carved out of limestone, designed by Frederick Law Olmstead at the turn of the century, when he helped John Stanford transform his massive horse farm into a university. Mine was among the first buildings; the humanities here remain housed mostly in these older, sedate, dusty buildings, with the sciences, the law school and the business school in far more plush, up-to-date quarters.</p>
        <p>Here I sit in a book-lined study, with shelves of wood (and also, admittedly, a new Dell computer), where I spend my days reading, writing and speaking with students and colleagues. It is much the same routine as has existed for faculty in the better-endowed universities for much of the century. Outside my window, just across the street, is the business school, which now prepares its students primarily for work in high-tech jobs. Its basement lunchroom has the most aggressive feel on campus. On the streets of my morning commute, I pass company after company at the forefront of the technological transformation. . . .</p>
        <p>When I consider their impact, I conflate it with the fact that both my favorite bookstores here -- one for new books and the other for used books -- shut down in the last three months. This is, of course, a direct result of the popularity of Web-based book buying and the impact of megabookstores. A few blocks from the now-closed secondhand bookstore, a sleek, very, very fashionable shop with wide aisles displaying, it seems, fabulously expensive design books and magazines has opened, and is doing brisk business. These tomes -- gorgeous, seductive nonbooks -- are mostly oversize, packed with pictures, and the people who crowd into the shop peruse their pages in ways altogether different, it seems, from ''true'' readers. They inhale them with their eyes; they move across their pages without the tense, alert attention demanded by books. On their faces one sees obvious, casual pleasure, but not learning. I refuse, on principle, to walk in.</p>
        <p>Am I a Luddite smarting in the wake of inescapable change? The analogy feels, at times, all too apt, and I bristle at it. Especially since I, too, cannot resist being deeply impressed by the technological discoveries around me, including electronic books the size of paperbacks containing full libraries. Who can fail to be impressed by the prospect of tiny chips the size of one's shirt buttons that claim to hold all human knowledge acquired since Rousseau?</p>
        <p>Wrestling, then, with my darker fears regarding computers and their impact on reading, I'm reminded that . . . there is considerable evidence of widespread, very serious, innovative reading today. Informal, associative book clubs are flourishing where, as often as not, writers' writers (Paul Auster, for example) are showcased. Or look at the way in which books are celebrated in the remarkable Harry Potter series, best sellers throughout the world whose impact on American reading habits has been dramatic. Their spectacular popularity is all the more striking since the books' young protagonists solve their mysteries in the school library. This is the source in every one of the books in the series of great, deep wisdom. They valorize book learning much more, it seems to me, than they glamorize witchcraft, which remains in the books a distant, dazzling fantasy. Books here are the real, potent sources of magic.</p>
        <p>It's even impossible to savage television as a prime source of today's onslaught on books. Some of television's patron saints have emerged as unlikely, highly influential hawkers of cultural literacy. Turn on television and you find Oprah is, of course, the devotee of new, sometimes obscure, and sometimes truly worthy, significant books. It is easy to poke fun at her, but, arguably, this saccharine talk-show host's impact on the reading habits of the English-speaking world of the early 21st century rivals that of the conversationalist Samuel Johnson centuries earlier. It's even impossible to know whether to bemoan or celebrate the impact on contemporary reading habits of Barnes &amp; Noble or Borders. True, like deadly, relentless armies of ants they've eaten up small independent stores. But their stores are packed with good books and avid readers. The perky protagonist of the film ''You've Got Mail'' made peace, in the end, with the future, and fell, happily, into the waiting arms of a benign, sweet megabookstore owner. A sound decision, or merely a Quisling-like capitulation? It seems impossible to say. . . .</p>
        <p>For as long as many of us can remember -- if we're serious about reading, that is -- we've sat with paper in hand, staring at symbols to which we, more frequently than not, credit far more than mere abiding pleasure. We owe these pages whatever ability we have to see the world with clarity. We credit them, and justly so, with whatever ability we have to see ourselves with generosity and empathy. To imagine these as gone, or truly obscure, to imagine that otherwise intelligent, eager, inquisitive people around us might well feel in 10 or 20 years that picking up a book is something quaint is to imagine a postmodern hell. . . .</p>
        <p>I recall standing a few months ago at the information booth at our local Borders and asking where to find the latest issue of The New York Review of Books. The clerk looked at me vacuously and asked what that was. I remember thinking that right here, in the midst of mountains of books, was proof of a decline so fundamental that it felt, simply, irreversible. Later, I passed by that same clerk, and I strained to hear him talking. I assumed, of course, he would sound utterly stupid. Instead, I listened to him expound for a while on the popularity of Ricky Martin, what it meant for popular music, for ethnic culture, even sexual politics. His sentences were well formed, his thinking reasonably sophisticated: he seemed ironic, bright and intellectually alive. I felt chastened, confounded as to what to think. I looked now at the man with more fascination than loathing as I walked by him, clutching my new books close to my heart.</p>
        <p>THINK TANK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
