<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Raises Recommended Tire Pressure</title>
    <meta content="Y23TIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/business/23TIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D61F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Raises Recommended Tire Pressure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co recommends that owners of Explorer sport utility vehicles inflate their tires to 30 pounds per square inch, replacing former 26 pounds pressure; Bridgestone/Firestone publicly urged Ford to raise its recommendation for Explorers equipped with Firestone tires; higher tire pressure allows vehicles to operate safely both carrying more weight and at greater speeds (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company recommended tonight that owners of Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles inflate their tires to 30 pounds per square inch, instead of the 26 pounds that the automaker has recommended for the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., the manufacturer of the Firestone light truck tires blamed for 101 deaths, mostly in Explorers, publicly urged Ford on Thursday to raise the recommended pressure. Ford agreed to the change tonight, but pointed out that Goodyear tires on Explorers had performed with virtually no problems at a pressure of 26 pounds. Ford also noted that even Firestone executives had agreed until the last few weeks that 26 pounds was an acceptable pressure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company recommended tonight that owners of Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles inflate their tires to 30 pounds per square inch, instead of the 26 pounds that the automaker has recommended for the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., the manufacturer of the Firestone light truck tires blamed for 101 deaths, mostly in Explorers, publicly urged Ford on Thursday to raise the recommended pressure. Ford agreed to the change tonight, but pointed out that Goodyear tires on Explorers had performed with virtually no problems at a pressure of 26 pounds. Ford also noted that even Firestone executives had agreed until the last few weeks that 26 pounds was an acceptable pressure.</p>
        <p>Higher pressure allows a tire to support more weight and go faster with less risk of failure. According to tire industry guidelines, the higher pressure should allow tires on the Ford Explorer to carry an additional 500 pounds. The higher pressure also raises the maximum speed at which the tires are certified to operate for at least 10 minutes, to 108 miles per hour from 106 miles per hour.</p>
        <p>The top speed of the Explorer, which is restricted by a computer chip in the engine, is 99 miles per hour. At 26 pounds, the tires also have the combined capacity to carry nearly 3,000 pounds in addition to the weight of the vehicle itself. But the weight of the Explorer is not evenly distributed, falling most heavily on the left rear tire, which has proved the most prone to failure.</p>
        <p>John Lampe, Firestone's executive vice president for sales and marketing, said in Congressional testimony on Thursday that the Explorer needed a larger margin of safety.</p>
        <p>An Explorer owner who allows the pressure to fall 7 pounds below Ford's recommended pressure, to 19 pounds per square inch, leaves the tires without the capacity to carry the weight of a moderately loaded Explorer, he said. He also pointed out that the recommended tire pressure for Chevrolet sport utility vehicles -- 35 pounds per square inch -- could fall by as much as 14 pounds before the tires became overloaded.</p>
        <p>Firestone, a unit of the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, announced on Aug. 9 that it was recalling 14.4 million tires, of which 6.5 million were still believed to be in use. The recall covers all ATX tires of the P235/75R15 size produced at various factories, plus Wilderness tires of the same size that were manufactured in Decatur, Ill. Wilderness tires of that size produced at other factories have not been recalled, although personal injury lawyers renewed their call today for these tires to be added to the recall.</p>
        <p>The tire maker said on Aug. 9 that 30 pounds was a better pressure than 26. Ford said then that while it believed that 26 pounds was a safe pressure, a range of 26 to 30 pounds was acceptable.</p>
        <p>But tonight, Ford urged Explorer owners to raise the pressure in their tires. In a letter addressed to Masatoshi Ono, the chairman and chief executive of Bridgestone/Firestone, and released to reporters, Ford said that, ''even recognizing that your non-recalled tires and the Goodyear tires have performed well at 26 p.s.i., we are advising our Explorer owners, based on your recommendation, that their Firestone P235/75R15 tires be inflated to 30 p.s.i., as this is within the 26-30 p.s.i. range jointly approved when the Firestone recall was announced and it should help to eliminate customer confusion.''</p>
        <p>The letter was from Carlos Mazzorin, who, as Ford's group vice president for global purchasing, has responsibility for the automaker's relationships with suppliers.</p>
        <p>A chart released by Ford on Wednesday showed that the tires provided the best stability and handling between 20 and 30 pounds, with the best at 30 pounds. Even with the tire-related deaths, Explorer occupants have a lower death rate in rollovers than those of most other midsize sport utility vehicles. But insurance industry figures show that Explorer drivers are still almost twice as likely to die in rollovers as drivers of Ford Taurus midsize sedans.</p>
        <p>Ford officials declined to elaborate on the letter to Mr. Ono.</p>
        <p>Ford's decision to raise the recommended pressure comes at a time of deepening mystery on two other issues in the Firestone tire recall. One mystery is whether the Firestone tires are failing because of a manufacturing problem in Decatur or because of a design problem that might affect tires made elsewhere. Another mystery is whether the Ford Explorer has a defective suspension.</p>
        <p>The big mystery at Firestone still lies in what went wrong with the tires. Mr. Lampe has admitted that the company made what he recently described as ''bad tires,'' while attributing this mainly to unspecified ''variations'' in the manufacturing process.</p>
        <p>But personal injury lawyers contend that some design defect -- they are not sure quite what -- must be responsible. They want Firestone to broaden its recall to 15-inch Wilderness tires manufactured at factories other than the one in Decatur, and they want Firestone to start recalling 16-inch Wilderness tires as well.</p>
        <p>Safetyforum.com, a research firm for personal injury lawyers, released today a review of all complaints to regulators about Firestone tires that can be mounted on Explorers. For those complaints in which the tire's size and place of manufacture could be identified, the majority involved tires that have not been recalled, the research firm said.</p>
        <p>''By selling the fiction that the problem is in Decatur, they get by with using non-Decatur tires as replacements,'' said Ralph Hoar, the founder of Safetyforum.com.</p>
        <p>But the research firm was only able to identify the tire sizes and places of manufacture for 12 percent of the complaints. While Ford declined to comment on SafetyForum.com's work, Firestone seized on the limited sample size, contending in a statement this evening, ''That is much too small a universe of tires on which to base such conclusions and such serious allegations.''</p>
        <p>The tire maker warned that ''consumers would be replacing good tires with good tires, delaying and adding confusion to the efforts to quickly replace the recalled tires.''</p>
        <p>On the suspension issue, Ford officials disclsoed on Wednesday that the automaker and regulators had received complaints about possible defects in the Explorer's front sway  bar.</p>
        <p>Ford and regulators say that they have not heard of any serious crashes related to the bar. But this is the suspension component that limits how much the vehicle tilts from side to side while going around curves, and it is one of the most important components in preventing rollovers.</p>
        <p>A computer analysis by The New York Times of a federal database of all fatal crashes across the country found that tire-related deaths in Explorers were somewhat more likely to involve rollovers than tire-related deaths in other sport utility vehicles. From 1994 through 1999, rollovers were a factor in 95 percent of the deaths that occurred in Explorers after a tire failed.</p>
        <p>During the same period, 80 percent of other sport utilities in fatal, tire-related crashes also rolled over, as did roughly 40 percent of cars. Since the overall rollover death rate for Explorers is low by sport utility vehicle standards -- although still high compared with cars -- the prevalence of rollovers in the Firestone tire cases is somewhat surprising.  But the type of failure occurring on Firestone tires happens mainly at high speeds, and rollovers are especially likely at high speeds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
