<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reno Orders Internal Inquiry Into Handling of Secrets Case</title>
    <meta content="Y23INQ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/national/23INQU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Security</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Wen Ho</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1D81F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reno Orders Internal Inquiry Into Handling of Secrets Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atty Gen Janet Reno tells Pres Clinton she has ordered internal review of prosecutors' handling of Wen Ho Lee national security case; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno told President Clinton today that she has ordered an internal review of prosecutors' handling of the case of Wen Ho Lee, the former Los Alamos nuclear scientist who was released from jail this month after the federal government's case against him largely collapsed, officials said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno, who met with the president at the White House for about 45 minutes at his request, said she had ordered a review of the case by the Justice Department's Office of Professional Responsibility after the judge handling the matter, James A. Parker of Federal District Court in Albuquerque, strongly condemned the prosecution's tactics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno told President Clinton today that she has ordered an internal review of prosecutors' handling of the case of Wen Ho Lee, the former Los Alamos nuclear scientist who was released from jail this month after the federal government's case against him largely collapsed, officials said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno, who met with the president at the White House for about 45 minutes at his request, said she had ordered a review of the case by the Justice Department's Office of Professional Responsibility after the judge handling the matter, James A. Parker of Federal District Court in Albuquerque, strongly condemned the prosecution's tactics.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno also said that she would seek to declassify some documents filed in connection with the case to explain the government's handling of Dr. Lee, officials said. Critics, particularly Asian-American groups, have said that Dr. Lee was the victim of racial profiling by overzealous prosecutors.</p>
        <p>In calling Ms. Reno to the White House, Mr. Clinton said he was ''quite troubled'' by the government's actions. Prosecutors charged Dr. Lee with 59 counts of putting at risk the nation's nuclear secrets. He was charged with downloading classified material to an unsecure computer with the intent of aiding a foreign government. Dr. Lee was kept in jail for nine months before his trial after prosecutors argued that he was a threat to national security. But the government dropped 58 of the charges as part of a deal in which Dr. Lee pleaded guilty to a single felony count of mishandling classified information.</p>
        <p>''I always had reservations about the claims that were being made denying him bail,'' the president told reporters last week.</p>
        <p>The issue of Dr. Lee's pretrial detention will be the focus of the Justice Department's review, aides to Ms. Reno said, but the review could grow beyond that.</p>
        <p>Despite the president's harsh words last week, it was clear today that the White House was trying to play down any disagreement between the president and the attorney general he appointed in 1993 -- perhaps to present a united front in advance of what is expected to be a contentious Congressional hearing on the issue next week.</p>
        <p>Senator Arlen Specter, Republican of Pennsylvania, who called the hearing, said today that an internal Justice Department review of the case was inadequate.</p>
        <p>''It's the attorney general's standard reply and then nothing happens,'' Mr. Specter said.</p>
        <p>White House aides explained that when the president said that the government's handling of Dr. Lee ''can't be justified,'' his scorn was more directed at the Federal Bureau of Investigation, an agency with which he has clashed, than with the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Joe Lockhart, the White House spokesman, said the president expressed his strong support for Ms. Reno at the meeting and agreed with her that ''the priority'' was to debrief Dr. Lee to determine what he did with the nuclear secrets that he improperly downloaded from federal government computers.</p>
        <p>''The attorney general gave the president a sense of where they are as far as looking at this,'' Mr. Lockhart said. ''I think they both agree the most important thing going on is the debriefing process and trying to find out just what happened to the computer tapes.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno, who spoke by telephone with the president on Wednesday for about 10 minutes, said before today's  meeting that she and the president were on the same page.</p>
        <p>''We had a chance to discuss it, and he was thoughtful and supportive,'' Ms. Reno said at her weekly media briefing this morning. ''I think anybody who looks at this case and doesn't know the circumstances of it is going to say, 'Why?' And I think that's what the president kind of naturally asked.''</p>
        <p>Next week, the Clinton administration is expected to come under heavy fire from Congressional Republicans who believe the case was bungled by the government. The Senate Judiciary Committee will question Louis J.  Freeh, the F.B.I. director; James Robinson, head of the Justice Department's criminal division; and Norman Bay, the United States attorney in New Mexico, who handled the prosecution of Dr. Lee.</p>
        <p>The Office of Professional Responsibility is led by H. Marshall Jarrett, a career prosecutor. The office handles accusations of criminal or ethical misconduct by Justice Department prosecutors. Its oversight includes the F.B.I., whose agents, critics say, treated Dr. Lee aggressively.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno was joined at today's meeting by her chief of staff, Ann M. Harkins. Beth Nolan, the White House counsel, and John D. Podesta, the president's chief of staff, also attended the session.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
