<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Post to Get New Publisher</title>
    <meta content="Y23POS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/business/23POST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Post</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Donald E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Boisfeuillet Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EED91F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Post to Get New Publisher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Donald E Graham will step down after 21 years as Washington Post publisher; his longtime associate, Boisfeuillet Jones Jr, will assume publisher's role; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donald E. Graham announced yesterday that he was stepping down after 21 years as publisher of The Washington Post to concentrate on steering its parent company, of which he is chairman and chief executive, as it continues to expand its new-media ventures.</p>
        <p>The publisher's job will be taken by his longtime associate, Boisfeuillet Jones Jr., the first publisher from outside the Meyer-Graham family in 30 years. Mr. Jones had been associate publisher and president of the newspaper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Donald E. Graham announced yesterday that he was stepping down after 21 years as publisher of The Washington Post to concentrate on steering its parent company, of which he is chairman and chief executive, as it continues to expand its new-media ventures.</p>
        <p>The publisher's job will be taken by his longtime associate, Boisfeuillet Jones Jr., the first publisher from outside the Meyer-Graham family in 30 years. Mr. Jones had been associate publisher and president of the newspaper.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Alan G. Spoon resigned as president and chief operating officer of the Washington Post Company to join a venture capital firm.</p>
        <p>The latest changing of the guard, while not expected to bring any change in direction for the newspaper, was still a symbolic moment: for 61 of the last 67 years, the publisher's job has been held by a member of Mr. Graham's family.</p>
        <p>Eugene Meyer, his grandfather, bought it in 1933. Since then, the only nonfamily publisher was James Sweeterman, who ran the newspaper for six years after Mr. Graham's father died in 1963.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham's mother, Katharine Graham, one of a tiny group of major newspaper publishers who have won  Pulitzer Prizes in their own right, took over in 1969 and presided over the newspaper's greatest modern triumph, the coverage of the Watergate scandal, which ended with the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. After 10 years, she turned the job over to her son in 1979.</p>
        <p>In his tenure as publisher, during which The Post's major competitor, The Washington Star, closed, Mr. Graham focused on broadening the newspaper's coverage and circulation in the ever-expanding suburbs, as well as building on The Post's reputation for enterprising national and international reporting.</p>
        <p>When Benjamin C. Bradlee, the flamboyant and hard-driving editor who oversaw the Watergate coverage, resigned, Mr. Graham replaced him with Leonard Downie Jr., who was equally hard-driving but less flamboyant -- a journalist who grew up at The Post, and was best known for his local investigative coverage and his stint as metropolitan editor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham's strategy of making the most of the newspaper's near-monopoly position in its region paid off for years; until three years ago, when it was supplanted by Newsday. The Post had the greatest household penetration of any large newspaper in the country. But like most other newspapers, it has suffered an erosion of daily circulation -- which was stemmed in the last year or so -- and a sharper drop in Sunday circulation.</p>
        <p>During that time, Mr. Jones -- who was two years behind Mr. Graham at school in Washington and worked with him on The Harvard Crimson -- served as the newspaper's lawyer and later as its president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham, in an interview, said: ''The point is to have a good publisher. Everyone here knows that Bo's basically running the paper the last few years. He's doing the job; he ought to have the title.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
