<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON APPROVES RELEASING SOME OIL FROM U.S. RESERVE</title>
    <meta content="23ENER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/politics/23ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strategic Petroleum Reserve</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Fuel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D61F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON APPROVES RELEASING SOME OIL FROM U.S. RESERVE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON with NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton orders release of 30 million barrels of oil from Strategic Petroleum Reserve over next month; announcement, day after Vice Pres Gore injects issue into his presidential campaign, helps drive down crude oil prices, suggesting action could in short run check or reverse surge in home heating and gasoline prices in weeks before Election Day; analysts see no guarantees that consumers will benefit, and warn decision does not address underlying issue of bringing energy supplies into line with demand; administration points to low inventories on East Coast as winter nears; Clinton made decision after talking with Gore, who suggestedreleasing smaller amount to start; opponent George W Bush says stockpile is for serious supply disruptions, as during war, and recalls that Gore himself opposed using reserve last winter; government is not selling oil outright, but will arrange with refiners to replace oil they are taking at later date; Sec Bill Richardson explains; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton ordered the release today of 30 million barrels of oil from the nation's emergency reserve over the next month, only a day after Vice President Al Gore injected the issue into the presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The announcement helped drive down crude oil prices, and analysts said the move could be effective, in the short run, in checking or even reversing the surge in home heating oil and gasoline prices in the run-up to Election Day. But analysts said there were no guarantees that consumers would benefit and that the decision did nothing to address the underlying issue of how to bring energy supply into line with demand over the long run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton ordered the release today of 30 million barrels of oil from the nation's emergency reserve over the next month, only a day after Vice President Al Gore injected the issue into the presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The announcement helped drive down crude oil prices, and analysts said the move could be effective, in the short run, in checking or even reversing the surge in home heating oil and gasoline prices in the run-up to Election Day. But analysts said there were no guarantees that consumers would benefit and that the decision did nothing to address the underlying issue of how to bring energy supply into line with demand over the long run.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they acted primarily because inventories of heating oil on the East Coast had fallen to worrisome levels, raising the risk of shortages should the winter be particularly cold or long.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made his decision after a sharp debate within the administration over whether releasing oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve was justified, and after talking by telephone on Tuesday with Mr. Gore, who told the president at that time that he intended to call for use of the reserve to stabilize oil prices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did that on Thursday but recommended starting with the release of a smaller amount, 5 million barrels, with the possibility of releasing more. Mr. Clinton committed himself today to a substantially larger 30-million-barrel release.</p>
        <p>The president's decision played neatly into Mr. Gore's campaign strategy of portraying himself as fighting for the people against powerful interests like big oil companies.</p>
        <p>It also allowed Mr. Gore to dominate the news again on an issue of his choosing, forcing his opponent, Gov. George W. Bush, into an argument about who could do more to help consumers. And it was clearly intended by Mr. Gore to minimize the chances that voters could be put in a sour mood before Election Day by high prices for gasoline or heating oil.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Mr. Bush said the stockpile was created as a backstop for times when the supply of oil has been seriously disrupted, such as a war. And he pointed out that as recently as last winter, Mr. Gore had opposed use of the reserve just to deal with rising prices.</p>
        <p>''I believe the vice president has made this decision, with the support of the president, for short-term political gain,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>At a stop in Pennsylvania a few hours before the administration announced its decision, Mr. Gore said it was time to stand up to what he called big oil and its apologists, of whom he implied Mr. Bush was one.</p>
        <p>''These prices are skyrocketing,'' Mr. Gore said. ''It's hurting small business. It's hurting those on fixed incomes. It's hurting young families. And the prospect for even higher prices ahead is going to cause even more trouble unless we act now.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they had been considering the issue for weeks, but came to a consensus on how to proceed only during a late-night conference call among the president's senior advisers on Thursday, a few hours after Mr. Gore gave a speech in which he laid out the case for drawing on the nation's oil reserves. Mr. Clinton then signed off on the strategy today.</p>
        <p>The decision was announced by Energy Secretary Bill Richardson,  who said the government would begin taking bids starting on Monday, with the expectation of releasing 30 million barrels over 30 days.</p>
        <p>Energy Department officials said they expected the oil to begin reaching buyers in Gulf Coast terminals by Nov. 1, and said the oil would go from there to refineries around the country over the next several weeks. The crude oil could be refined and on the market as heating oil by early December.</p>
        <p>Rather than selling the oil outright, the government intends to enter into deals with refiners under which the companies will agree to replace the oil it is taking, and then some, at a later date. In that way, Mr. Richardson said, the program would add to the nation's oil reserves rather than deplete them.</p>
        <p>The United States uses about 19 million barrels of oil a day, 10 million of them imported, according to the energy department. The 1 million barrels a day from the reserve, plus a modest increase in production promised several weeks ago by the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries means that crude oil supplies in the United States should  rise enough to lower prices of both crude oil and refined products in the short term, said Angela Antonelli, director for economic policy at the Heritage Foundation, a conservative research group.</p>
        <p>The price of crude oil for November delivery fell by $1.32 cents a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange today, closing at $32.68. Heating oil for delivery in October fell by 4.41 cents a gallon, to 95.48 cents. On Thursday, after Mr. Gore called for release of the reserves, prices dropped $1.24 a barrel for crude oil.</p>
        <p>Clinton officials acknowledged that there had been a split within the administration over how to proceed, with Treasury Secretary Lawrence H. Summers arguing against a big release of oil, and Mr. Richardson leading the charge in favor.</p>
        <p>But they said the differences narrowed in recent days as it became clear that stocks of home heating oil  were extremely low.</p>
        <p>Nationally, inventories of heating oil stood this week at 48.1 million barrels, down from 72.4 million barrels a year ago, according to the energy department. On the East Coast, inventories were at 24.4 million barrels, down from 48.5 million a year ago, and in New England they stood at 4.6 million barrels, down from 14 million a year ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson said the 30 million barrels of crude oil could put an additional 3 million to 5 million barrels of heating oil on the market. Because crude oil is refined into a number of products, supplies of gasoline and diesel are also likely to increase, he said.</p>
        <p>''Portland, Maine, will be in the 50's next week, so will Minneapolis, and it snowed in the Rockies yesterday,'' Mr. Richardson said at a news conference. ''We need to make sure the American families keep warm this winter and get their heating oil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson said that after 30 days the administration would evaluate whether the program was working and whether to continue.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that they had briefed OPEC members on the possibility of tapping the reserve, and that they were hopeful the organization would view the decision as a response to domestic concerns about the supply of heating fuel rather than as a challenge to OPEC's efforts to keep prices at a profitable level.</p>
        <p>The problem of heating oil inventories was driven in part by expectations among refiners that crude oil prices would decline in coming months, leading them to wait rather than build their inventories with expensive oil now, analysts said.</p>
        <p>If crude oil prices fall and stay down, refiners could prove more willing to increase their inventories, which could help lower heating oil prices. But refineries are already running close to capacity, limiting how much more heating oil they can produce. And crude oil prices are notoriously sensitive to other factors.</p>
        <p>Over the last two weeks, Iraq has also talked belligerently, accusing Kuwait of stealing its oil and intimating that it would reduce or cut its oil exports to pressure Kuwait's allies, particularly the United States.</p>
        <p>Iraq exports about 2.3 million barrels a day, or about 4 percent of the world's daily consumption, and any reductions on its part would destabilize a world market where supplies of oil are tight.</p>
        <p>''You can't put a finger on the outright price and where it's going to stop,'' said one New York oil trader. ''What will Iraq do or not do, will Saudi production hold; we'll have to see what new information is introduced into the market.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the move, especially in the Northeast, said it would be a substantial help in ensuring that consumers get through the winter without facing crippling heating bills.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that this is great news for the Northeast and the American economy,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat from New York.</p>
        <p>The strategic reserve was established in 1975, after the Arab oil embargo. It contains about 570 million barrels of oil, which is stored in salt domes along the Gulf Coast.</p>
        <p>It was first used in 1991, when President George Bush ordered that as much as 30 million barrels be released during the war against Iraq. In the end, only about 17 million barrels were actually sold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton then sold smaller amounts in 1996 as part of an effort to raise money to balance the budget. Small amounts have also been sold to pay some of the reserve's costs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
