<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.A.A. Says Delays Have Grown at La Guardia</title>
    <meta content="23FLIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/nyregion/23FLIG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Guardia Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D81F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.A.A. Says Delays Have Grown at La Guardia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FAA reports that delays at La Guardia Airport have grown so sharply that they contributed to increase in August in type of delays caused when too many planes are scheduled to take off at same time (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Aviation Administration reported yesterday that delays at La Guardia Airport had grown so sharply that they contributed to a 60 percent national increase in August in the type of delays caused when too many planes were scheduled to take off at the same time.</p>
        <p>The agency declined to release the number of delays broken down by individual airport, saying that airport control towers around the country were still checking the numbers and would probably release them next week. It is not known, therefore, how many more so-called volume delays there were at La Guardia Airport in August compared with August of last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Aviation Administration reported yesterday that delays at La Guardia Airport had grown so sharply that they contributed to a 60 percent national increase in August in the type of delays caused when too many planes were scheduled to take off at the same time.</p>
        <p>The agency declined to release the number of delays broken down by individual airport, saying that airport control towers around the country were still checking the numbers and would probably release them next week. It is not known, therefore, how many more so-called volume delays there were at La Guardia Airport in August compared with August of last year.</p>
        <p>But in a report of national numbers, F.A.A. officials said that ''the growth in volume delays reflects the increase in traffic at the busiest airports,'' and added, ''One reason is the significant increase in flights at New York La Guardia.''</p>
        <p>The information was released during the same week that officials of the Port Authority, the agency that manages La Guardia, announced that airlines could not add any flights during the airport's peak hours in the morning and evening because traffic has reached near-gridlock conditions at those times.</p>
        <p>The quick rise in flights at La Guardia is the result of a federal law passed in March that partly lifted flight restrictions on the busy airport, creating more slots for smaller regional jets that fly to underserved cities.</p>
        <p>Since the change, airlines have added about 200 flights a day at the airport and some airport officials expected that as many as 400 more would be scheduled soon. Before the new flights began coming in, the airport would handle about 1,200 flights, counting both takeoffs and landings, on a very busy day.</p>
        <p>With the increase in traffic, lines of planes waiting on the taxiways sometimes grow to more than 25 at La Guardia even on a day with fine weather. This long line means that planes may have to wait more than an hour to take off after leaving the gate.</p>
        <p>At all the nation's airports, the types of delays recorded by the F.A.A. -- those caused mostly by weather, excess flight volume, runway problems or equipment problems -- increased to 47,893 in August from 37,189 a year earlier. Weather is the biggest cause of delays. But while weather delays increased somewhat this year, volume delays rose significantly, to 5,397 from 3,376 last August.</p>
        <p>In its report, the F.A.A., clearly referring to the conditions that have developed at La Guardia, said that ''when an airport that is scheduled over its capacity for portions of the day receives even a small amount of additional flights, it will usually experience a dramatic increase both in delays and their duration.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference yesterday at La Guardia, four members of the New York Congressional delegation praised the Port Authority's action to try to prevent delays from becoming longer during peak times as airlines schedule more flights. ''The airlines want to make money, but they have a responsibility to ensure customer satisfaction,'' said Representative Nita M. Lowey, whose district extends into Queens.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
