<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 in Buffalo Teachers' Union Admit Contempt of Court</title>
    <meta content="23BUFF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/nyregion/23BUFF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buffalo (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Buffalo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D81F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 in Buffalo Teachers' Union Admit Contempt of Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVER PETERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three leaders of Buffalo teachers' union plead guilty to contempt of court, second day of their trial on charges they had ignored court order to stay on job; later in day, teachers in Buffalo school district vote to accept five-year contract worked out earlier in week with state mediator (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three leaders of the Buffalo teachers' union pleaded guilty to contempt of court yesterday, the second day of their trial on charges that they had ignored a court order to stay on the job.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, teachers in the Buffalo school district, the state's second largest, voted to accept a five-year contract worked out earlier in the week with a state mediator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three leaders of the Buffalo teachers' union pleaded guilty to contempt of court yesterday, the second day of their trial on charges that they had ignored a court order to stay on the job.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, teachers in the Buffalo school district, the state's second largest, voted to accept a five-year contract worked out earlier in the week with a state mediator.</p>
        <p>''We had decided weeks ago, or at least I had, that we would plead guilty,'' said Philip Rumore, president of the Buffalo Teachers Federation, which defied a state law banning teacher walkouts and called  strikes on Sept. 7 and 14 to pressure the Board of Education on wage, hiring and retirement benefits demands. ''I had never felt comfortable pleading not guilty.''</p>
        <p>The union still faces disciplinary hearings before the Public Employment Relations Board, the state agency that enforces New York's ban on strikes by public employees.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's vote by the union's 3,000 members followed Wednesday's vote by the Board of Education to accept the new agreement. The contract will restore teaching positions in the arts and physical education, but will also increase co-payments for prescription drugs, a first for a public employees' union in the Buffalo area, school officials said.  The contract provides no raises in its first year and a raise of up to 2 percent every six months after that for the next four years.</p>
        <p>At their arraignment in State Supreme Court in Buffalo on Monday, Mr. Rumore; Edith LeWin, the union's vice president; and Barbara Bielecki, its secretary, pleaded not guilty to violating Justice Kevin M. Dillon's back-to-work order, issued Sept. 12. But yesterday, they changed their pleas to guilty. Each faces up to 30 days in jail and $1,000 in fines.</p>
        <p>Paul G. Buchanan, president of the school board, said yesterday that the light penalties -- small fines and no jail time -- imposed on striking teachers in Yonkers last year had evidently not been enough to deter  Buffalo teachers.</p>
        <p>''Whatever they did in Yonkers wasn't sufficient to keep Buffalo from going out,'' Mr. Buchanan said, ''so I just hope that whatever the penalty turns out to be will be strong enough to stop other unions from going out.''</p>
        <p>He said he was particularly pleased that the new contract would allow Buffalo schools to join an experiment in contracting with the local United Way to provide service workers to schools, so that a troubled child's family -- not just the student -- could be included in social therapy. Two suburban Buffalo school districts are testing the use of outside social workers, he said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Buchanan said the union's reluctant agreement to give up some health benefits was a first for the area. Current and retired teachers covered by the contract now pay $1 for each prescription; under the new contract, they will pay $5 for generic medications and $10 for brand-name drugs.</p>
        <p>''According to City Hall,'' Mr. Buchanan said, ''this is the first time a major public service union in the Buffalo area, not only in schools, but police and fire and sanitation too, agreed to givebacks on benefits.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumore said the union was victorious in getting the school board to restore teaching positions in music, arts and physical education for Grades 1 through 3, positions that had been cut for budget reasons. Those classes are already taught in higher grades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
