<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President of Princeton To Step Down Next Year</title>
    <meta content="23PRIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/nyregion/23PRIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shapiro, Harold T (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6D71F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President of Princeton To Step Down Next Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Harold T Shapiro, president of Princeton University for 13 years, says he will step down next summer; Princeton has completed $1.1 billion fund-raising campaign and a plan to expand undergraduate enrollment by 10 percent; he is third Ivy League president to announce his resignation this year, which could complicate searches for successors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the completion of a $1.1 billion fund-raising campaign and a plan to expand undergraduate enrollment by 10 percent, Dr. Harold T. Shapiro, the president of Princeton University for 13 years, said yesterday that he would step down next summer.</p>
        <p>He is the third Ivy League president to announce his resignation this year, which could complicate the searches for successors. In May, Neil L. Rudenstine, the president of Harvard University, said he planned to step down next spring after 10 years. And in February, E. Gordon Gee said he would leave Brown University for Vanderbilt University after only two years in Providence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the completion of a $1.1 billion fund-raising campaign and a plan to expand undergraduate enrollment by 10 percent, Dr. Harold T. Shapiro, the president of Princeton University for 13 years, said yesterday that he would step down next summer.</p>
        <p>He is the third Ivy League president to announce his resignation this year, which could complicate the searches for successors. In May, Neil L. Rudenstine, the president of Harvard University, said he planned to step down next spring after 10 years. And in February, E. Gordon Gee said he would leave Brown University for Vanderbilt University after only two years in Providence.</p>
        <p>For Dr. Shapiro, 65, who will stay at Princeton to teach and conduct research in bioethics policy, the resignation will bring to an end more than two decades at the helm of two of the nation's most prominent research universities: he spent eight years as president of the University of Michigan before coming to Princeton.</p>
        <p>Under Dr. Shapiro, Princeton led the way in increasing financial aid for low- and middle-income students in recent years. Princeton replaced loans with grants for poorer students and removed the value of a student's home from its calculations for financial aid; other Ivy League universities quickly moved in similar directions.</p>
        <p>The 1980's and early 1990's were a tough time to be a college president, as federal and state support failed to keep up with soaring higher education costs. Recent years, however, have been almost ideal. The stock market has soared, generating huge gifts and rising endowments.</p>
        <p>Princeton now has more than $8 billion in the bank, four times what it had when Dr. Shapiro arrived.</p>
        <p>The growing hunger to attend big-name universities has sent applications soaring. Princeton last year admitted only 1,697 students from among 13,654 applicants.</p>
        <p>Many students, faculty and administrators yesterday said Dr. Shapiro was leaving a much-improved campus.</p>
        <p>Jin H. Kim, who is president of the undergraduate student government, said he was sorry to see Dr. Shapiro step down.</p>
        <p>''He has left Princeton in the best shape it's ever been in its entire history,'' said Mr. Kim, who is studying at the Woodrow Wilson School of Government and International Affairs.</p>
        <p>One of the nation's richest universities, Princeton was already in solid shape when Dr. Shapiro arrived in January 1988 but his early tenure was rocky.</p>
        <p>As the stock market plunged in 1987, alumni giving fell, creating budget deficits. And although Dr. Shapiro was applauded for inviting the entire college community -- from campus police officers to trustees -- to an inaugural lunch of lox and beef tenderloin, students, faculty and alumni complained that he was remote.</p>
        <p>To familiarize himself with Princeton, he began to read a book by a Princeton professor every week and to attend his or her lectures -- habits he has continued. ''You can learn a lot about someone by looking not just at who they are and what they are like, but by looking at their work and the things they have spent time on,'' Dr. Shapiro said yesterday. ''You learn things that are very hard to get out of a conversation.''</p>
        <p>He hired faculty, created new academic initiatives, refurbished old dormitories and added new buildings. A campus center opened this month, the first time the university has had a central meeting place for students and faculty to eat, relax and watch cultural events.</p>
        <p>Recent financial aid changes  helped Princeton attract a more diverse student body. In 1987, 83 percent of Princeton's students were white and 65 percent male. Today, half of the students are women and 30 percent are black, Hispanic or Asian.</p>
        <p>Nancy Weiss Malkiel, dean of the college, said the president -- who teaches one course each year -- has also reinvigorated undergraduate education, creating new academic centers and expanding the faculty by about 1 percent a year. Princeton's student-faculty ratio is now 6 to 1, she said, one reason the university decided it could add students.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shapiro proved especially skilled at bringing in large gifts from wealthy alumni, like $100 million from the builder Gordon Y. S. Wu, primarily for engineering, and $55 million from the insurance company executive Peter B. Lewis, mostly for a new genomics institute and research center.</p>
        <p>As a manager, Dr. Shapiro said he believed in taking risks, although he added that one recent decision -- the hiring of Peter Singer, a bioethics professor -- turned out to be more contentious than he and other faculty members expected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer, appointed in 1998,  supports euthanasia for some severely disabled infants and his views have been widely attacked by protesters on campus, editorial writers, and many in the field of ethics. Steve Forbes, who is a Princeton trustee and a large donor, said he would stop making gifts to the university.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
