<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Only Progress Comes Off of the Field</title>
    <meta content="23YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/sports/23YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DD163AF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Only Progress Comes Off of the Field</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Detroit Tigers defeat New York Yankees, 9-6; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The result from Toronto flashed intermittently on the scoreboard in the later innings at Yankee Stadium last night. By game's end in the Bronx, most of the Yankees realized that lowly Tampa Bay had beaten the Blue Jays and reduced the Yankees' number for clinching the American League East to six.</p>
        <p>But that had hardly eased the stress that is building around the Yankees, who lost again -- that's six straight defeats, and eight in nine games -- and played badly again, falling to Detroit, 9-6.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The result from Toronto flashed intermittently on the scoreboard in the later innings at Yankee Stadium last night. By game's end in the Bronx, most of the Yankees realized that lowly Tampa Bay had beaten the Blue Jays and reduced the Yankees' number for clinching the American League East to six.</p>
        <p>But that had hardly eased the stress that is building around the Yankees, who lost again -- that's six straight defeats, and eight in nine games -- and played badly again, falling to Detroit, 9-6.</p>
        <p>The regular season is scheduled to end in nine days, the playoffs will start in 11 days and the Yankees look as if they need a defibrillator. That might come in the form of a well-pitched game by Roger Clemens today, or a late-inning comeback, or a big day from Bernie Williams or Paul O'Neill. But something is needed to snap them out of their collective trance, which seems to get deeper by the day.</p>
        <p>They have been outscored, 69-24, over the last nine games, and they have not even held a lead in the last week. The Yankees' offense finally stirred last night to tie the game at 2-2 in the bottom of the fifth inning. But the left-hander Denny Neagle crumbled like feta cheese in the top of the sixth, initiating a low rumbling of boos that grew in the ninth inning. That's when Yankees pitchers failed to cover bases -- shades of Hideki Irabu -- on three consecutive plays.</p>
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre works to defuse pressure from his players and tries to focus on the good things that happen; Chuck Knoblauch and Derek Jeter, the Nos. 1 and  2 hitters in his lineup, combined to reach base eight times. Paul O'Neill rejoined the lineup after missing a week with a hip injury, although he struck out four times.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees' losing streak is its longest in more than three years, and it is not a matter of getting better pitching, or shoring up the defense, or getting a few more hits. The Yankees are awful right now, in almost everything they are doing.</p>
        <p>Neagle feels no undue tension in the Yankees' clubhouse. ''They're not going to worry and press because they're thinking, 'Jeez, it's close to the postseason and we're not playing the type of ball we're supposed to be playing right now,' '' Neagle said. ''Trust me, I'm not saying, 'We'll be there when the bell rings.' I'm not a big believer in that, either.</p>
        <p>''But we're all human and sometimes you press too hard, and it has nothing to do with the fact that we're not playing the kind of ball we're used to down the stretch.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees had just 24 hits in the five games leading up to last night, hitting just .156; Cleveland's Bartolo Colon threw a one-hitter against them Monday, and Toronto's David Wells allowed just five hits Thursday. So Torre made changes in his lineup, dropping the sluggers Glenallen Hill and Jose Canseco, benching third baseman Scott Brosius, who has not driven in a run in his last 10 games, and moving catcher Jorge Posada to sixth. He switched the struggling first baseman Tino Martinez to seventh.</p>
        <p>Torre also inserted a couple of contact hitters into the lineup, Luis Sojo at third base and Jose Vizcaino at second, and shifted Knoblauch from second base to designated hitter. ''Right now we need hits,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>But slumps manifest themselves universally. Even with a batting order stocked with contact hitters, Detroit's Hideo Nomo struck out eight in the first three innings, throwing lots of fastballs in counts when the Yankees hitters seemed to be expecting him to throw his forkball.</p>
        <p>Neagle shut out the Tigers early, as well. But after walking Billy McMillon to lead off the fifth, he hung a changeup to Deivi Cruz, and Cruz, the Tigers' shortstop, ripped a two-run homer. David Justice tied the game with a two-run single, and his hit, coming with two outs, seemed like a lift for a team needing a jolt.</p>
        <p>But Neagle (7-6) tried to make an adjustment on his mechanics, drawing back his right shoulder a little bit more as he turned to throw the ball, and he fell apart. ''I made a stupid mental mistake,'' Neagle said.</p>
        <p>Torre said: ''I really don't know; it looked like he lost his command all of a sudden.''</p>
        <p>Damion Easley bunted a ball back to the third-base side of the mound, and Neagle failed to make the play on Easley's infield hit. Bobby Higginson singled with one out, Easley taking third. Neagle walked the slugger Dean Palmer, in what might have been an attempt to work around Palmer to get to the left-handed-hitting McMillon.</p>
        <p>But with his mechanics fouled up, Neagle threw a wild pitch that allowed Easley to score the go-ahead run and the other runners to advance, and walked McMillon to reload the bases. Torre replaced Neagle with Jason Grimsley, and Cruz blooped a single into short center field to score one run. Another run came home on a ground ball and Hal Morris poked a pop-fly double down the left-field line; two more runs. Neagle was charged with six runs in five and a third innings, and Detroit led, 7-2.</p>
        <p>The Yankees picked away for some more runs, but in the top of the ninth, reliever Jeff Nelson covered first too late on an infield hit. Then the rookie Ted Lilly, focused on the runner at first, forgot there was a runner at third and failed to cover home when he threw a wild pitch. Frazzled by his own mistake, Lilly broke late on a grounder to the right side, and the boos resounded.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Yankees officials met with the agent for pitcher DENNY NEAGLE to discuss a contract extension. ''It was phase one,'' said BRIAN CASHMAN, the Yankees' general manager. Neagle will be eligible for free agency after this season. . . . DAVID CONE threw about 15 minutes in the bullpen this afternoon, and will talk with Manager JOE TORRE about his status today. It figures that Cone will make his last two starts -- first Monday, and then Sept. 30 in Tampa Bay -- simply because the Yankees have nothing to lose by allowing him to try.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
