<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Rattled By Bad News From Intel</title>
    <meta content="Y23STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/technology/23STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EEDB1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Rattled By Bad News From Intel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones Industrial Average rises 81.85, to 10,847.37; S&amp;P 500 index falls 0.33, closing at 1,448.72; Nasdaq composite is down 25.11, to 3,803.76; 10-year Treasury note falls 12/32, to 99 8/32, yielding 5.85 percent; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A steep tumble in shares of Intel dragged the stock market lower yesterday, after the company's warning late on Thursday that its sales in the third quarter would grow much less than had been expected. Trading in Intel set a daily record of more than 300 million shares.</p>
        <p>But investors proved to be resilient, seeming to see more buying opportunities than problems in the Intel news, and the market shed nearly all its losses by the closing bell. Indeed, the Dow Jones industrial average rebounded to climb more than 80 points. Coordinated intervention in the currency markets by the United States and its allies to support the weak euro also bolstered investors' confidence, some analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A steep tumble in shares of Intel dragged the stock market lower yesterday, after the company's warning late on Thursday that its sales in the third quarter would grow much less than had been expected. Trading in Intel set a daily record of more than 300 million shares.</p>
        <p>But investors proved to be resilient, seeming to see more buying opportunities than problems in the Intel news, and the market shed nearly all its losses by the closing bell. Indeed, the Dow Jones industrial average rebounded to climb more than 80 points. Coordinated intervention in the currency markets by the United States and its allies to support the weak euro also bolstered investors' confidence, some analysts said.</p>
        <p>The technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index opened sharply lower, falling 214 points, or 5.6 percent, in anticipation of a big sell-off in a market where investors were already worried about the performance of the technology sector and the prospect of weaker earnings growth over all as the American economy slows down. In early trading, the Dow fell 143 points, or 1.3 percent, and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 27 points, or 1.9 percent, both pulled lower by their technology components.</p>
        <p>Investors reduced the damage in part by buying consumer staples and health care stocks like Coca-Cola and Merck and biotechnology stocks like Amgen, as technology issues were sold. Then some of the technology stocks that were hit hard because of Intel's announcement rallied, as investors apparently took the opportunity to pick them up at lower prices. Dell Computer, which was down as much as $5.19, finished the day at $35.94, down $2.</p>
        <p>Hewlet-Packard also helped the rebound, announcing that it would buy back $1 billion of its stock. Its shares were down $3.25 early in the day but turned quickly and finished the day up $5, at $104.25.</p>
        <p>Even Intel contributed a bit to the rebound, as its stock bounced from a $46.50 low for the day to finish at $47.94. But it was still down $13.55, or 22 percent.</p>
        <p>''I think we hit a little bit of an air pocket here but that's all,'' said Jeffrey M. Applegate, chief United States strategist at Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>He said the surprise intervention on behalf of the euro by the central banks might help market sentiment some. Many companies, including Gillette, Procter &amp; Gamble and McDonald's, have been saying that the weak euro was trimming their earnings when translated back into dollars. And if this intervention leads to a turn for the euro, that could help the outlook, at the least.</p>
        <p>But Douglas R. Cliggott, United States equity strategist at J. P. Morgan Securities, said ''there is no way we are out of the woods yet.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Intel is not going to be alone in being a high-profile tech company that disappoints on the downside'' on sales and earnings.</p>
        <p>At the end of the day, the Nasdaq was down 25.11 points, or 0.7 percent, at 3,803.76 and is now down 6.5 percent for the year. The Dow was up 81.85 points, or 0.8 percent, to 10,847.37 and is down 5.7 percent for the year. The S.&amp; P. 500 fell 0.33 point, or 0.02 percent, to 1,448.72 and is off 1.4 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>The impact of Intel was reflected in its contribution to the declines of the indexes. In the Dow, Intel contributed about 80 negative points, while it added about 10 negative points to the S.&amp; P. 500. In the Nasdaq 100, an index of the biggest stocks in the Nasdaq composite, Intel accounted for about 54 negative points. The Nasdaq 100 finished the day down 16.97 points, at 3,701.18.</p>
        <p>Intel's volume on the day, 308 million shares, shattered the Nasdaq record set in July by JDS Uniphase, which traded 200.4 million shares. Intel broke that record before lunch was over. Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was 1.17 billion shares.</p>
        <p>Intel reported after the close of the market on Thursday that third-quarter revenue would rise just 3 to 5 percent over the $8.3 billion in the second quarter. Analysts had been predicting growth of 12 to 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The reason for the slowdown in revenue, Intel said, was weaker demand in Europe for its microprocessing chips. Some of that slump in sales, Mr. Applegate said, was because of the sharp decline this year in the euro, which is down over 12 percent.</p>
        <p>Intel did not mention what the impact of the sales shortfall would be on its earnings in the third quarter. But the announcement had a quick impact on analysts' estimates. According to First Call/Thomson Financial, analysts reduced Intel's earnings forecast 3 cents a share, to 38 cents a share, for the third quarter and 43 cents a share for the fourth quarter. The forecast for 2001 was trimmed to $1.74 from $1.86.</p>
        <p>Chuck Hill, director of research at First Call, also said that the fall in Intel's earnings forecast had pulled down the overall estimates for earnings growth in the third quarter for the companies in the S.&amp; P. 500. Analysts surveyed by First Call now expect earnings to grow 16.7 percent this quarter, compared with the similar quarter of 1999. This is down from 23.6 percent growth in the first quarter and 21.6 percent growth in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>General Motors fell early in the day, dropping as much as $1.94 after it was reported that Carl C. Icahn had sold his stake in the company Mr. Icahn told G.M. in August that he might buy as much as 15 percent of its stock. It was not clear yesterday if Mr. Icahn had permanently dropped his plans to invest in the automaker; the announcement of his plans in August sparked a rally. But G.M. joined in the market rally at the end of the day, finishing at $68.25, down just 6 cents.</p>
        <p>In the Treasury market yesterday, interest rates rose slightly. Thomas Connor, head government trader at J. P. Morgan Securities, said that the small sell-off came as the stock market rallied from its opening lows. He said that bonds had rallied, sending interest rates lower, late on Thursday after the Intel announcement.</p>
        <p>At the time, bond traders expected Intel to spark a sharp sell-off in stocks yesterday, sending investors into bonds. But that did not happen.</p>
        <p>The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note climbed to 5.85 percent, from 5.83 percent on Thursday, while the price, which moves in the opposite direction, fell 5/32, to 99 8/32.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
