<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.E.C. Files Fraud Complaint Against a Financier</title>
    <meta content="Y23FRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/23/business/23FRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conspiracy, Criminal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frankel, Martin R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5DC1F3BF930A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.E.C. Files Fraud Complaint Against a Financier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission files fraud complaint against Martin R Frankel, who bilked insurance companies and investors out of at least $200 million; he fled to Germany, where he is jailed on other charges while extradition procedures continue; numerous co-conspirators face deep legal troubles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission said yesterday that it had filed a fraud complaint against Martin R. Frankel, the financier who is already facing federal criminal charges in a huge insurance scandal.</p>
        <p>The agency also filed a complaint against John A. Hackney, accusing him of receiving more than $8 million for helping Mr. Frankel loot the assets of 10 insurance companies. And the United States attorney's office in Connecticut said that Mr. Hackney had pleaded guilty to involvement in a racketeering conspiracy and money laundering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission said yesterday that it had filed a fraud complaint against Martin R. Frankel, the financier who is already facing federal criminal charges in a huge insurance scandal.</p>
        <p>The agency also filed a complaint against John A. Hackney, accusing him of receiving more than $8 million for helping Mr. Frankel loot the assets of 10 insurance companies. And the United States attorney's office in Connecticut said that Mr. Hackney had pleaded guilty to involvement in a racketeering conspiracy and money laundering.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. did not specify how much money it wanted Mr. Frankel to return or what financial penalties it was seeking in yesterday's complaint, but previous estimates of the amount Mr. Frankel siphoned from insurance companies and investors start at a minimum of $200 million. Insurance commissioners in Arkansas, Mississippi, Missouri, Oklahoma and Tennessee have filed a federal lawsuit asking for more than $600 million in damages from Mr. Frankel for the money he is accused of stealing from companies in their jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel, a 45-year-old Ohio native who fled the United States in May 1999 and was captured four months later in Germany after an international manhunt, is currently in a German jail fighting efforts to extradite him. He is serving a three-year German prison term after pleading guilty in June to failing to pay German customs taxes on diamonds he smuggled into the country and to carrying false passports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel is accused in this country of diverting insurance premiums of companies he controlled to a Swiss bank account and spending some of that money on expensive luxuries.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's filings were the finale in a week of stepped up public activity in the case.</p>
        <p>Robert Todd Bennett, 44, of Mahopac, N.Y., pleaded guilty Wednesday in Federal District Court in New Haven to pocketing at least $35,000 from the sale of a Cadillac and Mercedes belonging to Mr. Frankel, as well as racketeering, conspiracy, wire fraud and money laundering.</p>
        <p>More important, federal officials say, Robert J. Guyer, 62, of Dundee, Mich., admitted in court Monday that he told the S.E.C. in 1994 that he was president of Liberty National Securities when in fact Mr. Frankel operated the brokerage firm. S.E.C. officials said that Mr. Guyer's willingness to serve as a front helped Mr. Frankel carry out his financial maneuvering in violation of a 1992 injunction barring him from any involvement in such activities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackney is seen as another crucial player. He was chief executive of the Franklin American Corporation, a public company in Tennessee that Mr. Frankel used secretly to acquire control of insurance companies.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people have wondered how Frankel could pull this off,'' said Wayne Carlin, who oversees enforcement for the S.E.C.'s regional office in New York City. ''A big part of the answer is the people who were willing to be fronts for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guyer said, ''There's a million things I'd like to say, but my attorney has told me not to make any comment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackney, Mr. Frankel and their lawyers could not be reached for comment. Mr. Carlin said that the investigation was continuing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
