<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bowler Briefed in Torts, Not Retorts</title>
    <meta content="07SALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/arts/07SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001014T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cavanagh, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ed (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DD153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bowler Briefed in Torts, Not Retorts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews new NBC comedy series Ed, with Tom Cavanagh; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On NBC's ''Providence,'' Tom Cavanagh played a recurring character called Dog Boy, a man who identifies with dogs. Maybe it's coincidental, but on NBC's new romantic comedy series, ''Ed,'' Mr. Cavanagh gets doggy again, playing a man with many canine qualities: his puppyish Ed Stevens is loyal, affectionate and eager to be loved.</p>
        <p>All that palpable eagerness could be sloppy and annoying, but Mr. Cavanagh makes it so engaging and likable that his show's loopy premise becomes believable enough. In his cute, capable hands, Ed does seem like the kind of fellow who would name the freckles on his wife's face after the Three Stooges and then, upon finding this wife in bed with another man, would flee rather than confront. He even seems like the kind of guy who, after he has been fired from his corporate law job in New York, would buy a bowling alley in his Ohio hometown -- after he finally kisses the girl he had a crush on in high school a dozen years before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On NBC's ''Providence,'' Tom Cavanagh played a recurring character called Dog Boy, a man who identifies with dogs. Maybe it's coincidental, but on NBC's new romantic comedy series, ''Ed,'' Mr. Cavanagh gets doggy again, playing a man with many canine qualities: his puppyish Ed Stevens is loyal, affectionate and eager to be loved.</p>
        <p>All that palpable eagerness could be sloppy and annoying, but Mr. Cavanagh makes it so engaging and likable that his show's loopy premise becomes believable enough. In his cute, capable hands, Ed does seem like the kind of fellow who would name the freckles on his wife's face after the Three Stooges and then, upon finding this wife in bed with another man, would flee rather than confront. He even seems like the kind of guy who, after he has been fired from his corporate law job in New York, would buy a bowling alley in his Ohio hometown -- after he finally kisses the girl he had a crush on in high school a dozen years before.</p>
        <p>Ed is a throwback, a hopeful, pixilated Capra character who wants to believe that things will work out as they should and is genuinely baffled and disappointed when they don't. Yet ''Ed'' the show doesn't seem creaky because Ed the character has also been endowed with ironic self-awareness, as might be expected on a series created by the men behind ''The Late Show With David Letterman.'' He does wonders for both lawyers and bowling.</p>
        <p>In keeping with Hollywood tradition, Ed's quaint hometown, Stuckeyville, is populated with more eccentrics than you could find wandering around Greenwich Village these gentrified days. The Midwestern folks in Stuckeyville aren't warm and fuzzy, but neurotic and spiky, like the old country doc who can't be sarcastic enough to his young partner, Ed's best friend, Mike (Josh Randall).</p>
        <p>There's also Mike's wife, Nancy (Jana Marie Hupp), and their new baby, for domestic humor, and Molly, friend to both Ed and Carol, played by Lesley Boone, who brings likable good humor to the thankless part of go-between.</p>
        <p>Ed's main neurosis is his determined niceness. ''You are very, very nice,'' says Carol, the cheerleader he pined for as a teenager and finally gets to kiss as a grown-up. But Ed is also funny and maybe even a little dark, in a nice sort of way, and that's why Carol finds herself wanting to kiss him even though she has been dating a more selfish, roguish type for many years.</p>
        <p>Carol, who has matured from a cool, pretty cheerleader into a cool, pretty high school English teacher, is still fending off schoolboy crushes -- from both grown men and high school students. She could be hard to like, but the actress, Julie Bowen, has a sweet nervous intelligence that manages to overcome Carol's obvious advantages and make the character's problems with relationships sympathetic.</p>
        <p>Certainly the series can't survive only on the back-and-forthing between Ed and Carol, though they do carry the first two episodes nicely. So Ed has been given a complicated professional situation to generate stories outside the budding romance. He sets up a law practice inside the bowling alley -- sort of like a Starbucks inside a bookstore, he explains. He compares the three peculiar people who make up his staff to the irregulars rack at a department store.</p>
        <p>This promising start makes you want to pat Mr. Cavanagh on the head. And if you're a lawyer or a bowler, you might feel like scratching him behind the ears, too.</p>
        <p>ED  NBC, tomorrow night at 8  (Channel 4 in New York)</p>
        <p>Created by Rob Burnett and Jon Beckerman; Richard Davis, pilot producer; Andrea Newman, series producer; James Frawley, pilot director; Kathleen McGill, line producer; Michele Fazekas and Tara Butters, story editors; Patricia Goldstein, production designer; Rob Draper, director of photography; Marc Buckland, co-executive producer. Produced by Viacom Productions in association with Worldwide Pants and NBC Studios. Mr. Burnett, Mr. Beckerman and David Letterman, executive producers.</p>
        <p>WITH: Tom Cavanagh (Ed Stevens), Josh Randall (Dr. Mike Burton), Jana Marie Hupp (Nancy Burton), Julie Bowen (Carol Vessey) and Lesley Boone (Molly Hudson).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW  Correction:  October 14, 2000, Saturday  A listing of credits last Saturday  with a television review of the new romantic comedy series ''Ed,'' on NBC, included an erroneous identification from the network. The production designer is Chris Shriver, not Patricia Goldstein.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 14, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A listing of credits last Saturday  with a television review of the new romantic comedy series ''Ed,'' on NBC, included an erroneous identification from the network. The production designer is Chris Shriver, not Patricia Goldstein.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
