<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sure Thing: El Duque in October</title>
    <meta content="07YANK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/sports/07YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1DD123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sure Thing: El Duque in October</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Oakland Athletics, 4-2; Yankees lead American League division series 2-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez was in slacks and a leather jacket when he bumped into Yankees Manager Joe Torre in the basement hallway of Yankee Stadium a few minutes before midnight last night. Hernandez extended his hand. ''Todo bien,'' he said. All is well.</p>
        <p>''Todo bien,'' Torre responded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez was in slacks and a leather jacket when he bumped into Yankees Manager Joe Torre in the basement hallway of Yankee Stadium a few minutes before midnight last night. Hernandez extended his hand. ''Todo bien,'' he said. All is well.</p>
        <p>''Todo bien,'' Torre responded.</p>
        <p>All is well with the Yankees after Hernandez pitched seven innings and Mariano Rivera relieved in the eighth and ninth to beat Oakland and their ace, Tim Hudson, 4-2. It gave the Yankees a two-games-to-one advantage in the three-of-five-game division series, which they can wrap up here tonight when Roger Clemens opposes Oakland's Barry Zito.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' dominance in this era appeared to be coming to an end only a few days ago, yet they can clinch this series in Game 4 and move on to face Seattle in the American League Championship Series, which would start Tuesday in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>There was some irony in Hernandez's words to Torre, for Hernandez had appeared on the verge of unraveling like a threaded spool in the middle innings. He could not control his changeup, his pitch count was astronomical, and he was completely frustrated, griping to teammates about his performance.</p>
        <p>Oakland's Art Howe managed as if the Athletics were going to eventually nail Hernandez, and it was hard to argue with his logic.</p>
        <p>And yet, in the end, Hernandez extended his record of postseason perfection to 6-0 -- the Yankees have never lost in any of the seven games he has started in October.</p>
        <p>''He's made of special insides,'' said Billy Connors, the Yankees' interim pitching coach. ''Some guys are.''</p>
        <p>The Athletics have never beaten Hernandez, who has a 4-0 record against them, but El Duque changed his style of pitching substantially since he last faced Oakland in August. He now uses his fastball more, elevating it when he gets ahead in the count, then mixes in changeups low and away.</p>
        <p>He got ahead of the Oakland leadoff batter Terrence Long in the first inning and catcher Jorge Posada gestured with an upward jerk of his glove as he signaled for fastballs high in the strike zone. Fourteen of the 16 pitches Hernandez threw in the first inning were fastballs.</p>
        <p>But the Athletics succeeded in foiling the other part of Hernandez's apparent plan, ignoring his changeup. Deprived of this weapon in the first four innings, Hernandez labored, and the number on the pitch counter Connors holds in his hands rose quickly. There were 28 pitches in the second inning, 21 in the third, a staggering 108 in the first five innings.</p>
        <p>''He was complaining the whole game,'' said Luis Sojo, the second basemen who is quickly becoming a postseason cult hero. ''He was telling us he didn't have his good stuff.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees had a lead, however, most of it courtesy of the Athletics. Trailing by 1-0 in the second inning, the Yankees had runners at first and third and Glenallen Hill bounced a high chopper off the plate. Hudson waited on the mound for it to come down, like a punt returner, as Bernie Williams raced home.</p>
        <p>Hudson had no chance to throw out Williams but tried anyway, and instead of getting Hill out at first, Hudson extended the inning one more batter; Derek Jeter drove home a second run with a two-out infield single.</p>
        <p>Sojo walked to lead off the fourth and Scott Brosius dropped a bunt in front of the plate. Catcher Ramon Hernandez rushed out to retrieve the ball and fired to second, where the shortstop Miguel Tejada stretched for the throw like a first baseman -- and let it tip off the webbing of his glove. Sojo got up and scrambled to third.</p>
        <p>There was nobody out and even though the Yankees led, 2-1, Howe played his infield back, feeling good about the Athletics' chances of scoring runs against Hernandez. Sojo scored on a ground ball to short, but it seemed like no big deal to Oakland; El Duque was in trouble.</p>
        <p>Long led off the fifth inning for Oakland with a blistering home run, reducing the Yankees' edge to 3-2. After Hernandez walked Jason Giambi with one out, Jeter cut off a ground ball headed for the middle and flipped to Sojo at second to begin a nifty 6-4-3 double play. Yankee Stadium exploded.</p>
        <p>But Hernandez was disconsolate, discouraged, moving slowly off the field. Torre summoned him into the narrow runway that leads to the clubhouse, the two standing close together.</p>
        <p>''Remember who you are,'' Torre said. ''Don't worry, just be who you are.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez said later, ''Mr. Torre told me to stop battling myself.''</p>
        <p>The sixth inning went much more smoothly, Hernandez suddenly finding control of his changeup, making an adjustment, keeping his front shoulder tucked in longer. He retired the Athletics with 10 pitches, pushing his pitch count to 118. But at the very least, El Duque had pitched deep into the game.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Mike Stanton and the right-hander Jeff Nelson were throwing as the seventh inning began, but Torre and Connors really didn't talk much about relieving Hernandez at the start of the seventh. ''That's all based on his history,'' Torre said. ''If you based it on the first five innings, you wouldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez struck out Jeremy Giambi, using his changeup, but Hernandez, the one batter El Duque had really dominated in the first five innings, pulled a single to left. Now the left-handed hitting Long was coming to bat, two hits in three at-bats, including a home run. Stanton was ready in the bullpen and Hernandez's pitch count was over 125.</p>
        <p>''I gave it a lot of thought and I just decided to leave him in there,'' Torre said. ''It's just a trust factor at that point in time.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez turned and looked at Sojo and told him the ball would be coming his way; he was going to throw a changeup to Long. Hernandez  flipped his 130th pitch of the game, low, and Long smacked a hard grounder to Sojo's left.</p>
        <p>Sojo dived, gloved the ball, turned while on his back and threw to second, where Jeter crossed the bag, kicked the base and threw to first. Double play.</p>
        <p>The place was bedlam, and Hernandez moved crisply off the field after allowing four hits and five walks over seven innings, his night over. Rivera pitched the last two innings, the Yankees added an insurance run and now appear in control of this series.</p>
        <p>Todo bien.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
