<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y07CAM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/politics/07CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5D7153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HOUSE</p>
        <p>SILENCE, AGAIN, IN NEW MEXICO  Representative Joe Skeen, a Republican from New Mexico's Second District, will probably win his 11th term this fall, in part by maintaining his eight-year policy of not debating his opponent. But this time, Mr. Skeen's Democratic challenger, Michael Montoya, the state treasurer, is not letting him off the hook easily. Mr. Montoya suggests that one reason Mr. Skeen will not debate is because he has Parkinson's disease and does not want voters to see him. In a news release, Mr. Montoya said that efforts by Mr. Skeen to conceal his illness were ''tantamount to dereliction of duty to the voters who put him in office.'' Mr. Skeen, 73, disclosed he had the disease in 1997, just after it was diagnosed. He says he does not debate challengers because his Congressional record is public and he has no interest in providing an opponent easy publicity.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HOUSE</p>
        <p>SILENCE, AGAIN, IN NEW MEXICO  Representative Joe Skeen, a Republican from New Mexico's Second District, will probably win his 11th term this fall, in part by maintaining his eight-year policy of not debating his opponent. But this time, Mr. Skeen's Democratic challenger, Michael Montoya, the state treasurer, is not letting him off the hook easily. Mr. Montoya suggests that one reason Mr. Skeen will not debate is because he has Parkinson's disease and does not want voters to see him. In a news release, Mr. Montoya said that efforts by Mr. Skeen to conceal his illness were ''tantamount to dereliction of duty to the voters who put him in office.'' Mr. Skeen, 73, disclosed he had the disease in 1997, just after it was diagnosed. He says he does not debate challengers because his Congressional record is public and he has no interest in providing an opponent easy publicity.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>GORE UPSTAGED  Vice President Al Gore learned something about scene-stealing last night in New York. As he talked to an audience of his in-laws' friends in Greenwich Village, his grandson, Wyatt, toddled across the stage, rolled over on his back, clapped his hands and otherwise made complete hay of the evening.</p>
        <p>''I'm melting,'' the vice president said. laughing, as the boy, who is 15 months old, rolled over at Mr. Gore's feet.</p>
        <p>The evening began with the private reception by David and Lisa Schiff, the parents of Drew Schiff, Mr. Gore's son-in-law, at the Village home of Jennifer Bartlett, an artist and longtime Schiff family friend. Also on hand was Mr. Gore's mother, Pauline, visiting from Tennessee. She was celebrating her 88th birthday but was unable to descend the stairs where the 80 people were sitting in chairs. So her son carried her a cake, ablaze with candles, up the winding staircase.</p>
        <p>Katharine Q. Seelye (NYT)</p>
        <p>UNION LEADERS TAKE TO THE ROAD  The A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s president, John J. Sweeney, and more than a dozen other union leaders are planning a series of bus tours around the Midwest and Northwest to whip up support for Vice President Al Gore. When the buses carrying Mr. Sweeney, Richard Trumka, the secretary treasurer of the labor federation, and Linda Chavez-Thompson, its executive secretary, arrive in towns there will be rallies, worksite leafleting, phone banks and town meetings.  The tours will go to Illinois, Kentucky, Michigan, Missouri, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Washington, West Virginia and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRAVEL LOG -- The stats for Friday:</p>
        <p>Length of the Official Day: Gore, 18 hours; Bush 11 hours  States Visited: Gore, 3; Bush, 3  Towns and Cities Visited: Gore, 3; Bush, 3  Events: Gore, 2; Bush, 3  Interviews : Gore, 10; Bush, 10  Diners visited/unscheduled drop-bys: Gore, 0; Bush, 0  Main message: Gore, middle-class tax cuts to help families save for retirement; Bush, empowering parents, ''tools for parents'' and renewing the fight against drug abuse.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
