<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Financial and Technology Stocks Send Markets Lower</title>
    <meta content="Y07STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/business/07STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DB153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Financial and Technology Stocks Send Markets Lower</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composite index falls 3.2 percent, or 111.09 points, to 3,361.01, and is off 17.4 percent for year; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index drops 1.9 percent, or 27.29 points, to 1,408.99, and is off 4.1 percent for year; Dow Jones industrial average falls 1.2 percent, or 128.38 points, to 10,596.54, and is down 7.83 percent for year; US bond prices are higher; yield on Treasury's 10-year note falls to 5.82 percent, from 5.85 percent, while price rises 7/32, to 99 16/32; graphs in intraday fluctuations in Dow Jones industrial average and Nasdaq composite index since August; charts on large price percentage gains and losses for Oct 6 and key US interest rates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks plunged yesterday, led by declines in financial and technology stocks, as investors worried about corporate earnings disappointments and dismissed what was generally a positive employment report for September.</p>
        <p>Despite a small rally at the end of the day, the Nasdaq composite index fell 3.2 percent, or 111.09 points, to 3,361.01, and is off 17.4 percent for the year. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 1.9 percent, or 27.29 points, to 1,408.99, and is off 4.1 percent for the year. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 1.2 percent, or 128.38 points, to 10,596.54, and is down 7.83 percent for the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks plunged yesterday, led by declines in financial and technology stocks, as investors worried about corporate earnings disappointments and dismissed what was generally a positive employment report for September.</p>
        <p>Despite a small rally at the end of the day, the Nasdaq composite index fell 3.2 percent, or 111.09 points, to 3,361.01, and is off 17.4 percent for the year. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 1.9 percent, or 27.29 points, to 1,408.99, and is off 4.1 percent for the year. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 1.2 percent, or 128.38 points, to 10,596.54, and is down 7.83 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>A rumor that one of Wall Street's big brokerage firms had suffered large losses in the junk bond market sent its stock and the stocks of other brokerage firms sharply lower. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, the object of the rumor, would not comment in detail, except to say that reports it had suffered big losses in the third quarter were ''greatly exaggerated.'' Its stock plunged 8.4 percent.</p>
        <p>Some market analysts said that the response to the rumors was a sign of the depth of the negative sentiment in the stock market right now. Other analysts, however, pointed out that there has been a major sell-off in the high-yield market for telecommunications bonds recently, which means that some firm must be suffering losses, even if they are small. The Lehman Brothers index of high-yield telecommunications bonds plunged 3.3 percent in September and the sell-off has continued.</p>
        <p>The stream of warnings about revenue and earnings shortfalls from companies has been relentless, including Dell Computer, Pitney Bowes, Xerox and Caterpillar this week; Apple Computer and Eastman Kodak the week before; and Intel earlier.</p>
        <p>The brunt of the selling in the face of these earnings disappointments has fallen upon technology stocks. The technology-heavy Nasdaq has now declined five consecutive weeks, falling 20.6 percent in that period, and it is now about 200 points away from its May low of 3,164.55. But the September employment report was a reminder that the nation's economy is still moving ahead nicely. The Labor Department reported that the unemployment rate in September fell to 3.9 percent, matching a 30-year low, while there were 252,000 new nonfarm payroll jobs created, including about 75,000 strikers from Verizon who returned to work. At the same time, data for average hourly earnings and hours worked all point to benign wage pressures and continued productivity gains, which should be a plus for earnings going forward.</p>
        <p>So why didn't the jobs report help market sentiment? Robert Barbera, chief economist at Hoenig &amp; Company in Rye Brook, N.Y., said that the Federal Reserve was trying to slow economic growth to a pace of 3 percent to 4 percent and curb inflationary pressures. While the jobs report reflected progress toward that goal, this pace of growth, he said, is ''incapable of delivering the growth in revenues and the growth in earnings that the market had become accustomed to and is still expecting.''</p>
        <p>Stan Jonas, managing director at Fimat U.S.A. in New York, suggested another problem. He said that some investors had been expecting the economy to slow down even more and prompt the Fed to cut interest rates early next year. But the Fed, when it decided to leave its interest rate benchmark unchanged at 6.5 percent after its policy meeting Tuesday, said it was still worried about inflationary pressures. Combined with a jobs report that did not hint at a sharp slowdown in growth, Mr. Jonas said hopes for a rate cut had been dashed.</p>
        <p>This disappointment is also hurting corporate bonds, he said, adding to the recent sell-off that helped fan yesterday's rumor. Kirk D. Hartman, executive vice president at Banc of America Capital Management, said the selloff in telecommunications bonds was a response to both the huge amount of bonds being issued and fears that these companies could be announcing soon that the slowdown in economic growth would hurt earnings and revenues, which would send the price of both their stocks and bonds lower.</p>
        <p>Raymond O'Rourke, a spokesman for Morgan Stanley, pointed to an article in The Wall Street Journal yesterday as a possible source of the rumor. The Journal reported that Morgan Stanley said that market talk that it had suffered big junk bond trading losses was ''greatly exaggerated.'' Mr. O'Rourke repeated that comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>Other brokerage firm stocks that seemed to be hit by the rumor included Merrill Lynch, down $5.13, to $61.19, and the Goldman Sachs Group, down $6, to $108.88. Among the technology stocks that led the market lower were Hewlett-Packard, Cisco Systems, Intel, JDS Uniphase and Qualcomm.</p>
        <p>Joseph Liro, an economist who follows the equity market at Stone &amp; McCarthy Research Associates in Princeton, N.J., said that once the actual third-quarter reports for all the companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 index were tallied the earnings growth would be strong, meaning the current pessimism is off base and that ''the stock market has overshot on the downside.''</p>
        <p>In the bond market, the stock selloff appeared to help push prices higher as investors switched from stocks to bonds. The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note fell to 5.82 percent, from 5.85 percent Thursday, while the price, which moves in the opposite direction, rose 7/32 , to 9916/32 .  The containment of inflationary pressures reflected in the September employment report also helped.</p>
        <p>But Ethan S. Harris, senior economist at Lehman Brothers, said that the Fed probably gave the bond market a new concern after its policy meeting Tuesday by saying specifically that the recent rise in oil prices was a cause of concern. In its statement, the Fed said: ''The increase in energy prices, though having limited effect on core measures of prices to date, poses a risk of raising inflation expectations.''</p>
        <p>It was not until September that oil prices seemed to worry bond investors much at all and now this, Mr. Harris said, ''raises the profile of oil prices for the fixed-income market.''</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
