<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Rulings Curb Efforts To Rein In Judicial Races</title>
    <meta content="Y07JUD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/national/07JUDG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDD153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Rulings Curb Efforts To Rein In Judicial Races</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent court rulings say First Amendment prohibits many of new ethics rules and campaign finance restrictions some states have imposed in effort to limit aggressive judicial politicking; judges are elected in 42 states; in many of them, formerly bland judicial campaigns have come to resemble other races, complete with attack advertising and multimillion-dollar war chests; recent rulings suggest that some of new rough-and-tumble could not be prevented (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As campaigns for state judgeships have become nastier and more expensive in recent years, some states have tried to limit aggressive judicial politicking with new ethics rules, stricter enforcement and campaign finance restrictions.</p>
        <p>But several recent court rulings said that the First Amendment prohibited many of the new efforts because they curtailed political speech.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As campaigns for state judgeships have become nastier and more expensive in recent years, some states have tried to limit aggressive judicial politicking with new ethics rules, stricter enforcement and campaign finance restrictions.</p>
        <p>But several recent court rulings said that the First Amendment prohibited many of the new efforts because they curtailed political speech.</p>
        <p>The rulings by state and federal courts in Alabama, Georgia, Michigan, Ohio and other states have become a roadblock for efforts to curb the increasingly raucous nature of judicial politics.</p>
        <p>''These decisions are a big problem for the regulation of judicial candidates' conduct by official bodies,'' said Roy A. Schotland, an expert on judicial politics at Georgetown University Law Center in Washington.</p>
        <p>The rulings, all since March, have come during a political season widely described as one of the most contentious in judicial politics, with bitter races for the Supreme Courts of Idaho, Illinois, Ohio and other states.</p>
        <p>Judges are elected in 42 states. In many of them, what were once bland judicial campaigns have come to resemble other races, complete with attack advertising and multimillion-dollar war chests. In the recent rulings, the judges suggested that some of the new rough-and-tumble could not be prevented.</p>
        <p>''A rationale for judicial elections is that meaningful debate should periodically take place concerning the overall direction of the courts and the role of individual judges in contributing to that direction,'' said a Michigan Supreme Court decision in March.</p>
        <p>''Such debate is impossible, if judicial candidates are overly fearful of potential discipline for what they say,'' said the decision, written by Justice Maura D. Corrigan.</p>
        <p>United States Supreme Court rulings have said that judicial candidates have broad protections for campaign statements. But those precedents also held that states had a special interest in preserving their courts' integrity and could impose some restrictions on judicial candidates they could not impose on other candidates.</p>
        <p>Those precedents were handed down before the new trend of aggressive judicial campaigning, so the recent cases have been viewed as tests of whether the new efforts to police judicial campaigns violated the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>One of the important tests was among several challenges to Ohio limits on the amounts that judicial candidates could spend. The state argued that, even though such caps were not constitutional for other candidates, the unique nature of the courts meant the caps should be permitted in judicial races.</p>
        <p>Last month, Judge Solomon Oliver Jr. of Federal District Court disagreed, saying judicial spending caps are unconstitutional limits on ''the quantity of political speech.''</p>
        <p>Some critics of current judicial campaigning said the new rulings would increase what they saw as troubling momentum.</p>
        <p>''The issues that are being raised in these court cases are part of the trend to make judicial candidates more like other candidates,'' said Virginia E. Sloan, executive director of The Constitution Project, a bipartisan Washington group trying to make judicial races more dignified.</p>
        <p>Several of the recent cases involved efforts to control what candidates said, not what they spent. The Michigan case involved a challenge by a judge to disciplinary charges that he had waged a deceptive ''brass knuckles'' campaign in 1996 when he cast himself as ''one tough judge'' and described the incumbent as a ''bureaucrat'' who was responsible for the release of murderers.</p>
        <p>A 1995 Michigan ethics rule said judicial candidates could not make statements that were misleading. But the Michigan court said that a rule preventing misleading statements was too broad, and it directed disciplinary officials to review the case to see if the judge was guilty of intentional falsehoods. Courts have said states can bar judicial candidates from intentional false statements.</p>
        <p>This month, a federal judge in Atlanta made a similar ruling, striking down a Georgia ethics rule because it prohibited misleading statements and omissions, not just intentional falsehoods.</p>
        <p>And this summer a federal judge in Alabama issued a temporary injunction barring disciplinary officials from removing from office a State Supreme Court justice, Harold F. See Jr. The officials had filed charges against Justice See because of accusations he made about a challenger in a primary last spring in a race for chief justice.</p>
        <p>The federal judge in Alabama, Ira DeMent, said Justice See was likely to prevail at a trial in arguing that the Alabama ethics rule was too broad. The rule said judicial candidates were barred from making statements that a ''reasonable person'' would deem misleading.</p>
        <p>Even as they made the recent rulings, some of the judges made it plain that they were worried that First Amendment protections might create more of a free-for-all in judicial campaigns.</p>
        <p>But, they said, the Constitution left them no choice.</p>
        <p>''Abuses are no longer potential or theoretical, they have arrived,'' said Willis B. Hunt Jr., the federal judge in the Georgia case. ''The people of Georgia have chosen to elect their judges. That decision, like all decisions, has consequences, one of which is that contested elections, with all their baggage, will occur.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
