<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When to Ruff Partner's Ace (First, Be Sure You're Right)</title>
    <meta content="07CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D7143CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When to Ruff Partner's Ace (First, Be Sure You're Right)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column discusses player solving partner's problem in high level of play; offers elegant example; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most defenders have enough to do in attempting to solve their own problems. On a higher plane altogether are those who foresee that partner is about to have a problem, and solve it for him by taking charge of the defense. The diagramed deal, an elegant example, was played in a league match in Sweden, long a power on the international bridge scene.</p>
        <p>East and West were two brothers, Terje and Roger Lie, who were employing a strong club system. The two-club opening suggested a hand with six clubs, but a five-card club suit, in conjunction with a four-card major, was allowable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most defenders have enough to do in attempting to solve their own problems. On a higher plane altogether are those who foresee that partner is about to have a problem, and solve it for him by taking charge of the defense. The diagramed deal, an elegant example, was played in a league match in Sweden, long a power on the international bridge scene.</p>
        <p>East and West were two brothers, Terje and Roger Lie, who were employing a strong club system. The two-club opening suggested a hand with six clubs, but a five-card club suit, in conjunction with a four-card major, was allowable.</p>
        <p>In view of the spade misfit, North should perhaps have passed the two-spade overcall. His three-heart bid, made in the hope of finding a fit in that suit, was optimistic, and landed his partner in a shaky three-spade contract. This would have been doomed if East, as was likely, had held the diamond ace. As it was, South had a chance of making seven trumps and a trick in each red suit.</p>
        <p>A likely defense was for the defense to play three rounds of clubs, since East could hope that this would promote a trump trick for his partner. This would have failed, for South would have been able to ruff high, draw trumps, and lead a heart. This would set up a heart trick in dummy with the diamond king remaining as an entry.</p>
        <p>The singleton club was indeed led to the queen, and East continued with the ace. But when South followed suit, West thought matters over carefully. He now knew that his partner had begun with exactly five clubs, and therefore must have four hearts. It followed that South must have six or seven strong spades, and three or four weak diamonds.</p>
        <p>West could see a road to a successful defense, and was doubtful whether his partner, with less information, would know what to do. He therefore ruffed his partner's ace and led a small diamond, sealing the declarer's fate.</p>
        <p>Declarer was forced to put up the king, losing his entry for the potential heart trick. He could lead a diamond, hoping for a ruff, but that could be prevented easily by a trump shift.</p>
        <p>South lost the first two tricks and eventually three tricks in the red suits, for down one. And the Lie brothers won the International Bridge Press Association's Carey Limousine Award for the best defense of the year.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
