<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Union, Congratulating the Serbs, Will Begin Lifting the Sanctions on Yugoslavia</title>
    <meta content="Y07EUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/world/07EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE EUROPEANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5D7153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Union, Congratulating the Serbs, Will Begin Lifting the Sanctions on Yugoslavia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union says its foreign ministers will meet to begin lifting sanctions imposed on Yugloslavia in 1999, moving quickly to show support for opposition leader Vojislav Kostunica and making good on September promise to reward Serbs if they oust Pres Slobodan Milosevic; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving quickly to show support for the opposition leader Vojislav Kostunica, the European Union announced today that its foreign ministers would meet on Monday to begin lifting sanctions imposed on Yugoslavia in 1999.</p>
        <p>The decision, coming much sooner than many had expected, will begin to make good on a September promise to reward the Serbs if they ousted President Slobodan Milosevic in the Sept. 24 elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving quickly to show support for the opposition leader Vojislav Kostunica, the European Union announced today that its foreign ministers would meet on Monday to begin lifting sanctions imposed on Yugoslavia in 1999.</p>
        <p>The decision, coming much sooner than many had expected, will begin to make good on a September promise to reward the Serbs if they ousted President Slobodan Milosevic in the Sept. 24 elections.</p>
        <p>In a brief statement that echoed those from leaders across Western Europe, President Jacques Chirac of France, which holds the current rotating presidency of the 15-nation Union, congratulated the people of Serbia on liberating themselves first with a vote ''and then in the street'' when it seemed their victory ''might be stolen from them.''</p>
        <p>As president of France and the leader of the Union, Mr. Chirac officially recognized Mr. Kostunica as the new president of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>''Today I salute President Kostunica,'' he said, ''and I confirm that sanctions will be lifted with the return of democracy.'' Sealing the ready approval with which the new leader of Yugoslavia is being welcomed by a world weary of Mr. Milosevic's brutality, Mr. Chirac also invited Mr. Kostunica to attend a European Union summit meeting late next week in Biarritz, France.</p>
        <p>In Germany, a spokesman for Chancellor Gerhard Schroder said he had canceled all his engagements today to follow developments in Yugoslavia -- an indication of the gravity with which events are viewed across a continent on which Mr. Milosevic's reign represented the last scourge of Communist rule.</p>
        <p>European Union officials said that barring any sudden changes in Yugoslavia, the foreign ministers would probably lift an oil embargo and a flight ban immediately. But lifting the other two sanctions -- financial restrictions that have affected the most of the country's large companies and a ban on visas for Mr. Milosevic, his family and close associates -- might take more time.</p>
        <p>It is not clear what the future holds for Mr. Milosevic, who tonight appeared on Serbian television and congratulated Mr. Kostunica on winning the elections, but seemed to envision a future for himself in Yugoslavia's politics. In the light of Mr. Milosevic's indictment on charges of war crimes, that would be difficult for the West to tolerate, and would probably complicate Mr. Kostunica's efforts to introduce real democracy to Serbia.</p>
        <p>''Nobody would want to fetch up in a situation in which some of those who were most guilty for what has happened in the last few years, who were most guilty for cheating the Serbian people, were able to disappear with their loot to some warm clime,'' said Chris Patten, external relations commissioner for the European Union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patten said the Union would move swiftly to bolster the relief assistance it has already provided in small quantities, and with difficulty, to isolated Serbian cities governed by the opposition to Mr. Milosevic. Serbia is coping with hundreds of thousands of Serbian refugees from the wars Mr. Milosevic lost in Croatia, Bosnia and Kosovo, and the general standard of living in Serbia has plummeted in recent years.</p>
        <p>The European Commission, working with opposition economists, has estimated that Yugoslavia, which consists of Serbia and the small republic of Montenegro, needs about $4 billion to rebuild itself over seven years. The European Union is considering contributing about half that.</p>
        <p>The apparent downfall of Mr. Milosevic could either speed the integration of the Balkan peninsula with the rest of Europe, or emphasize the Continent's division into two Europes, with the southeastern part a region of unstable and impoverished countries lagging far behind wealthier Central and Western Europe.</p>
        <p>Many questions remain about whether the European Union will come up with the support it has talked of for the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Already, Western Europe is struggling with just how and when it will integrate nearly a dozen countries that appear to have the economic credentials to join the Union within the decade.</p>
        <p>Speaking in Poland today, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain took his turn at tackling the subject of the future of Europe, saying the ''hand of partnership'' had to be held out to the Serbian people.</p>
        <p>Enlargement, he said, has to come soon. Without it, ''Western Europe will always be faced with the threat of instability, conflict and mass migration on its borders,'' he said, adding, ''Without enlargement the political consensus behind economic and political reform in the weaker transition countries may splinter. ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair offered yet another model of what shape the European Union should take. In May, Germany's foreign minister, Joschka Fischer, suggested that a European federation with a directly elected president and a parliament sharing real executive and legislative powers was needed. A month later, Mr. Chirac suggested a far looser structure, a ''united Europe of states rather than a United States of Europe'' where some countries could cooperate on matters that other countries were not interested in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair today called for a ''statement of principles'' agreed to by all members, which would define what should be governed at a European level and what would be decided nationally. He also suggested a second chamber of the European Parliament, comprising representatives of national parliaments, to oversee foreign and security policy.</p>
        <p>''The most important challenge is for Europe is to wake up to the new reality,'' he said. ''Europe is widening and deepening simultaneously. There will be more of us in the future, trying to do more.''</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE EUROPEANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
