<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bell to Miss Rest of Year, but Help Is Here</title>
    <meta content="07SHEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/sports/07SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Derek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DE123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bell to Miss Rest of Year, but Help Is Here</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets outfielder Derek Bell will miss remainder of year due to injury (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Game 2, the Mets benefited from the continuing emergence of Timo Perez and the clutch contribution of Darryl Hamilton in the 10th inning. As the division series with the Giants continues, those contributions may be needed again because the Mets learned yesterday that right fielder Derek Bell would be lost for the postseason.</p>
        <p>Bell, who came up lame in Game 1 while trying to run down a hit by Barry Bonds, underwent a magnetic resonance imaging exam yesterday and was found to have a sprained ligament in his upper right ankle. At Shea Stadium yesterday, Manager Bobby Valentine said that Bell would have to keep weight off the ankle for three to six weeks and had no chance of returning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Game 2, the Mets benefited from the continuing emergence of Timo Perez and the clutch contribution of Darryl Hamilton in the 10th inning. As the division series with the Giants continues, those contributions may be needed again because the Mets learned yesterday that right fielder Derek Bell would be lost for the postseason.</p>
        <p>Bell, who came up lame in Game 1 while trying to run down a hit by Barry Bonds, underwent a magnetic resonance imaging exam yesterday and was found to have a sprained ligament in his upper right ankle. At Shea Stadium yesterday, Manager Bobby Valentine said that Bell would have to keep weight off the ankle for three to six weeks and had no chance of returning.</p>
        <p>Bell may have made his last appearance in a Mets uniform, too, because he is a free agent at season's end. Bell began the season by collecting a club-record 40 hits in April. But he slumped badly, hitting .187 after the All-Star Game break and finishing the season with a .266 average. With Perez, Jay Payton and Benny Agbayani providing the Mets with young, inexpensive talent in the outfield, it is unlikely the Mets will want to re-sign Bell, who is making $5 million this season.</p>
        <p>In Game 1, Bell was replaced by Hamilton. In Game 2, Perez got the start and responded with three hits and two runs batted in. The Mets are not allowed to replace Bell on the roster for this series, but will be able to if they advance to the next round.</p>
        <p>Perez, who provided a spark from the leadoff spot in Game 2, gained the start even though the Mets were facing a tough left-hander.</p>
        <p>He will be hard to displace in this series.</p>
        <p>''I think his emergence is even more important now,'' Mets General Manager Steve Phillips said. ''I think he was going to contribute whether Derek was here or not.</p>
        <p>''If you stop and were to consider the situation without having Timo in the mix right now, I would be a little more concerned than I really am with Derek being out.''</p>
        <p>Reed's Record vs. Giants Poor</p>
        <p>The Mets are faced with a tough matchup in Game 3 today. Rick Reed, the Mets' starter, has struggled against San Francisco, while his counterpart, Russ Ortiz, has compiled a 4-0 career mark against the Mets. Reed was 0-2 with a 6.07 earned run averaged against the Giants this year and is 2-5 in his career.</p>
        <p>''Rick has been one of our best pitchers,'' Bobby Valentine said. ''He's been there. He'll be there again. And I'm very confident in his abilities.''</p>
        <p>Ortiz pitched seven innings of one-hit ball this season in an 11-1 victory over the Mets, a game in which Reed was on the losing end.</p>
        <p>Valentine has not yet committed to a Game 4 starter, but he said yesterday that he was leaning toward Bobby J. Jones, the right-hander.</p>
        <p>''Bobby Jones is the leading candidate,'' Valentine said.</p>
        <p>Giants Manager Dusty Baker said Mark Gardner would start Game 4.</p>
        <p>There has been speculation that Valentine would bring back Mike Hampton, the Game 1 loser, on three days' rest, especially if the Mets lose Game 3 and are facing elimination.</p>
        <p>In Praise of Franco</p>
        <p>John Franco, the closer who agreed to become a setup man, was a star of Game 2, striking out Barry Bonds to end the game on a 3-2 changeup. At Shea yesterday, Steve Phillips singled him out for praise.</p>
        <p>''You know, John, when he first came to the Mets, was very talented, very successful, and somewhat, not immature, but, you know, he was a prankster,'' Phillips said. ''I think that over time, from when he first became a Met until now, he has matured and grown into a leader on the team and a real professional.</p>
        <p>''The way he has handled the transition, the shots of him in the dugout when Benitez is on the mound and he is cheering and yelling, 'You're the man,' and the way he handled yesterday's game, not accepting the accolades and reminding people that Benitez is still the guy, I give John Franco a tremendous amount of credit.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton Having Fun</p>
        <p>Darryl Hamilton was one of the Mets players at Shea yesterday, still basking in his two-out, 10th-inning double that led to the Mets' winning run in Game 2. ''It feels very good,'' he said. ''I think this is the reason why I worked so hard in rehab to come back, because I felt we had a good chance to win on this team.''</p>
        <p>Starting Time Announced</p>
        <p>The starting time for Game 3 at Shea Stadium today was finally determined yesterday when Seattle completed its first-round sweep of the Chicago White Sox. Today's Mets-Giants game will start at 4:18 p.m. Game 4 tomorrow will start at 8 p.m. if the Yankees-A's series ends tonight; it will start at 4:07 p.m. if the Yankees and A's have to play a Game 5 tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
