<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/world/07BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D6143CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: ANOTHER SYNAGOGUE ATTACK  In the second attack of its kind this week, stones were thrown at a synagogue in the Kreuzberg district of Berlin, breaking several windows. ''The broken windows are a mirror image on German society,'' said Andreas Nachama, head of Berlin's Jewish community. According to government figures, 817 anti-Semitic crimes were reported last year. Several politicians, including Foreign Minister Joschka Fischer, attended Sabbath services in Berlin to show solidarity with Jews.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: ANOTHER SYNAGOGUE ATTACK  In the second attack of its kind this week, stones were thrown at a synagogue in the Kreuzberg district of Berlin, breaking several windows. ''The broken windows are a mirror image on German society,'' said Andreas Nachama, head of Berlin's Jewish community. According to government figures, 817 anti-Semitic crimes were reported last year. Several politicians, including Foreign Minister Joschka Fischer, attended Sabbath services in Berlin to show solidarity with Jews.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: REPORTER CONVICTED  Andrei Babitsky, a Radio Liberty reporter who set off a furor over press freedom after Russian troops detained him in Chechnya, was convicted of using false identity documents. The court gave him amnesty, but he said he would appeal. Mr. Babitsky surfaced in Dagestan last winter with a false passport after Russian soldiers turned him over to a group of Chechens, supposedly in a trade for Russian captives. Mr. Babitsky has said the Chechens gave him the passport.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: HEARINGS ON AMERICAN  A Moscow court will begin hearings Oct. 18 into whether a former American naval officer accused of espionage, Edmond Pope, is healthy enough to stand trial, his lawyer said. Mr. Pope suffers from bone and blood cancer, which was in remission before his April arrest on charges that he tried to buy plans for a high-speed torpedo. The lawyer said Mr. Pope would plead not guilty.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: BLAIR AND AHERN TO MEET  Prime Minister Tony Blair and his Irish counterpart, Bertie Ahern, will meet in London next week to review the growing infighting among Protestant politicians in Northern Ireland and the threat it poses to the continuation of Belfast's new power-sharing government. David Trimble, first minister of the Northern Ireland Assembly, faces a threatened challenge to his leadership of the Ulster Unionist Party and pressure to withdraw from government with Sinn Fein.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: EX-BASQUE LEADER SENTENCED  The Madrid high court sentenced Francisco Mujica Garmendia, a former chief of the armed Basque separatist group E.T.A., to 109 years in jail for the 1987 bombing of the Civil Guard headquarters in which a woman died. He had already received a 12-year sentence for another bomb attack on the same day. Under Spanish law he will serve a maximum of 30 years.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: CONSERVATIVE PLATFORM  Preparing to face elections next month, Canada's new conservative party unveiled its platform, stressing tax cuts, tougher measures on crime and more spending on health, defense and debt reduction. Backing away from an earlier call for a flat 17 percent federal income tax, the Canadian Alliance proposed scaled reductions, moving to two rates: 17 percent up to $67,000 and 25 percent beyond that. Prime Minister Jean Chretien is expected to call an election for Nov. 27.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: DRIVE ON REBELS  With elections scheduled Tuesday, President Chandrika Kumaratunga vowed to step up the military campaign against the separatist Tamil Tigers. She said a major drive against the rebels was already under way.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: POLIO CEASE-FIRE  The ruling Taliban and the rival forces of the United Front have again agreed to a three-day cease-fire, from next Tuesday to Thursday, to allow United Nations workers to immunize children against polio. Similar halts to the fighting took place in May and June.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: REBELS SAID TO SEEK SURRENDER  Members of a Muslim rebel group holding five hostages, including an American, are seeking to surrender after evading troops for three weeks, military officials said. Some 5,000 troops swept onto southern Jolo island on Sept. 16 but have been unable to find the American, three Malaysians and a Filipino held by the Abu Sayyaf rebels. A sizable group of rebels has sent surrender feelers, Gen. Manuel Teodosio said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>LEBANON: FLYING TO IRAQ  A plane carrying medical supplies will fly to Baghdad next week, as Lebanon joins the growing number of countries defying the international air embargo against Iraq, an organizer of the flight said. Hani Soleiman, a member of the Support Committee for the Iraqi People, said Prime Minister Salim Hoss had given permission for the fight. The committee will meet Monday with the doctors' and pharmacists' unions to decide who will be on the flight and what supplies will be taken.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SIERRA LEONE: U.N. GROUP ON WAY  An 11-member delegation from the Security Council, led by Sir Jeremy Greenstock, Britain's ambassador to the United Nations, leaves today on a mission to Sierra Leone, with stops in Guinea, Liberia, Mali and Nigeria. Sir Jeremy, left, said extensive meetings would be held with a wide range of Sierra Leoneans, international military officers and relief workers. The Security Council is planning to field a force of more than 20,000 peacekeepers in Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>IVORY COAST: OPPOSITION CANDIDATE BARRED  The supreme court barred former Prime Minister Alassane Ouattara from running in the Oct. 22 presidential election to return the country to civilian rule. Court President Tia Kone said Mr. Ouattara did not meet nationality conditions required of candidates under a new Constitution approved overwhelmingly in a July referendum.  The court earlier approved the candidacy of the military ruler, Gen. Robert Guei. Immigrants from neighboring countries and Muslims from northern Ivory Coast are Mr. Ouattara's primary supporters.</p>
        <p>(Reuters, AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
