<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At a Crucial Moment, Hudson Shows His Age</title>
    <meta content="07OAKK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/sports/07OAKK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hudson, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DD123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At a Crucial Moment, Hudson Shows His Age</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Oakland Athletics pitcher Tim Hudson's throwing mistake in Game 3 of American League division playoff series against New York Yankees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oakland starter Tim Hudson, the team's 20-game winner in his first full major league season, will think about his second-inning misplay and want to rewind it in his mind.</p>
        <p>Hudson was the one pitcher the A's thought could swing the series last night and send Oakland closer toward an improbable American League pennant. Then Hudson, battling nerves and rejuvenated Yankee hopes in their raucous stadium, did the improbable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oakland starter Tim Hudson, the team's 20-game winner in his first full major league season, will think about his second-inning misplay and want to rewind it in his mind.</p>
        <p>Hudson was the one pitcher the A's thought could swing the series last night and send Oakland closer toward an improbable American League pennant. Then Hudson, battling nerves and rejuvenated Yankee hopes in their raucous stadium, did the improbable.</p>
        <p>He threw home for an out that was not there.</p>
        <p>Armed with a 1-0 lead, the 25-year-old Hudson retired the Yankees in order in the first inning, then allowed a double to Bernie Williams to lead off the second. After striking out Tino Martinez, Hudson allowed Paul O'Neill to reach first on a infield chopper before facing slugger Glenallen Hill with one out.</p>
        <p>Hill chopped a grounder back to Hudson, and when Hudson saw Williams running home, he figured he would try to throw him out. The sure out was to first base, as Hudson would keep saying for 30 minutes after the A's 4-2 loss.</p>
        <p>Hudson was not in time to get Williams and catcher Ramon Hernandez held the ball in resignation. ''It was a brain cramp,'' Hudson said. ''If I had to do it all over again, I would thrown home Nobody called for me to throw it home. It was bad choice on my part, I had no chance of getting him.</p>
        <p>''Even if I was going to first, it may not have been an out. But I was thinking to get any run I could cut down against the Yankees.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he knew what he should have been thinking: ''With this team, you have to take every out when you can get it,'' he said with a sigh.</p>
        <p>After the Yankees tied it at 1-1, Hudson retired Luis Sojo on a fly ball to center field and walked Scott Brosius. Derek Jeter, 0 for 9 in the series, cracked a grounder to shortstop. Miguel Tejada got his glove on it but bobbled it; Jeter reached first on what was ruled a single and O'Neill scored for the 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>''We definitely had our miscues tonight and they took advantage,'' Hudson said. ''It definitely cost us a run or two. We're young, we're going to make mistakes.''</p>
        <p>Hudson battled for eight innings, though, giving up six hits, a few in the infield, for three earned runs. He struck out five and walked four. His teammates -- neither in the field nor at the plate -- helped him.</p>
        <p>The A's defense was shoddy, too, making two errors and some hasty decisions borne of inexperience and eagerness.</p>
        <p>''We let him down,'' said third baseman Eric Chavez, who went 0 for 4 in his first time as the cleanup hitter. ''He was a little nervous even if he didn't show it. We just didn't make the plays we had to make. We were just a bit too excited. I know I was swinging too hard.''</p>
        <p>But if the Yankees' Orlando Hernandez held the A's in check, so did the A's defense.</p>
        <p>''We just didn't execute, it's as simple as that,'' A's Manager Art Howe said. ''I don't think it was because of the stage we were on. We just didn't play well tonight.''</p>
        <p>In the fourth inning, A's catcher Hernandez, also a playing his first full major league season, decided he would field a dribbling bunt by Brosius and try to get Sojo at second instead.</p>
        <p>Instead, Hernandez overthrew second baseman Randy Velarde, and Sojo rambled to third. Again, Jeter's grounder was good for a run batted in, and what turned out to be the winning run.</p>
        <p>In the eighth inning, gave up an R.B.I. single to Sojo and the A's could not make up the deficit. ''This series is not over yet; we're still confident we can win,'' Ramon Hernandez said.</p>
        <p>Tonight the A's hand the ball to the youngest player on the roster, the 22-year-old left-hander Barry Zito, for the most important game in his life. It is also his first postseason start. ''I know what's at stake,'' Zito said.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's going to get to me. I just stay in my routine and work pitch for pitch.'' And hope his defense does the job.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
