<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOUSE PASSES BILL TO TOUGHEN LAWS ON FORCED LABOR</title>
    <meta content="07TRAF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/politics/07TRAF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweatshops</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4DE123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOUSE PASSES BILL TO TOUGHEN LAWS ON FORCED LABOR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT and JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel; Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House overwhelmingly approves wide-ranging measure that toughens laws against trafficking of women and children for prostitution and sweatshop labor and helps states and localities fight domestic violence; Senate is expected to approve measure and send it for Pres Clinton's signature; bill establishes specific laws against trafficking; Central Intelligence Agency estimates that up to 50,000 women and children are brought to US each year under false pretenses, and forced to work as prostitutes, abused laborers or servants; another major component of bill would reauthorize Violence Against Women Act for five years, allocating $3.3 billion to increase financing for shelters for victims of domestic violence and for law enforcement officials who investigate domestic abuse (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The House overwhelmingly approved a wide-ranging measure today that toughens laws against the trafficking of women and children for prostitution and sweatshop labor and helps states and localities fight domestic violence.</p>
        <p>The Senate is expected to approve the measure, which is a House-Senate conference report, on Wednesday and quickly send it to the White House for President Clinton's signature. The House vote today was 371 to 1, with only Representative Mark Sanford, Republican of South Carolina, voting no because it increased federal spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The House overwhelmingly approved a wide-ranging measure today that toughens laws against the trafficking of women and children for prostitution and sweatshop labor and helps states and localities fight domestic violence.</p>
        <p>The Senate is expected to approve the measure, which is a House-Senate conference report, on Wednesday and quickly send it to the White House for President Clinton's signature. The House vote today was 371 to 1, with only Representative Mark Sanford, Republican of South Carolina, voting no because it increased federal spending.</p>
        <p>The bill establishes specific laws against trafficking; violators can be sentenced to prison for 20 years to life, depending on the severity of the crime. They can also be forced to make full restitution to their victims, paying them the salary they would have been due for their months or years of involuntary service.</p>
        <p>In a recent report, the Central Intelligence Agency estimated that between 45,000 and 50,000 women and children are brought to the United States each year under false pretenses, and forced to work as prostitutes, abused laborers or servants.</p>
        <p>Few state or federal laws are aimed directly at people who deliver or control woman or children for the purpose of involuntary servitude or slavery in sweatshops or brothels. So prosecutors often assemble cases using related laws, like document fraud or illegal interstate commerce, and accept penalties that they believe are too light for the offense.</p>
        <p>Another major component of the bill would reauthorize the Violence Against Women Act for five years. That provision would allocate $3.3 billion to increase financing for shelters for victims of domestic violence and for law enforcement officials who investigate domestic abuse.</p>
        <p>The bill also includes strong protection and aid for the women or children who are brought to the United States and held in bondage. Often, they are arrested and deported when discovered, since they are not legal residents of the United States.</p>
        <p>''We punish the person for the act of being trafficked,'' said Senator Sam Brownback, a Kansas Republican and one of the bill's sponsors.</p>
        <p>Under the new bill, victims of ''severe forms of trafficking'' -- defined as people who are held against their will ''for labor or services through the use of force, fraud or coercion for the purpose of subjection to involuntary servitude, peonage, debt bondage or slavery'' -- would be eligible for a special visa letting them stay in the country at least through the duration of their captors' prosecution and perhaps permanently.</p>
        <p>They would also be eligible for various forms of personal aid -- even if they were not legal residents of the United States. Only 5,000 of these new visas could be granted in a year.</p>
        <p>If financing is provided in separate appropriations bills, the trafficking bill would authorize the Justice Department to help private groups build shelters and provide additional assistance to trafficking victims. The department already provides funds to a few private groups providing these services.</p>
        <p>The bill would also establish an interagency Office to Monitor and Combat Trafficking, to be based in the State Department, to direct and coordinate federal efforts in this area. This codifies an interagency task force that the Clinton administration set up in 1998.</p>
        <p>The measure would also require the State Department to report each year on the efforts other nations make to stop trafficking and gives the government the authority, starting in 2003, to withhold some foreign aid to countries found not to be making reasonable efforts.</p>
        <p>The State Department first opposed this provision, but the language was changed so that application of sanctions was not automatic.  In a statement today, the department praised the bill's passage: ''This legislation will help us track down and prosecute traffickers as well as aid and protect their victims.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department was similarly pleased. William Yeomans, chief of staff of the Civil Rights Division, said: ''I think we pretty much got what we need.''</p>
        <p>The provision that reauthorizes the 1994 Violence Against Women Act also allocates additional aid to state and local governments to pay for domestic abuse specialists in rural areas, as well as for new financing for training, education and security on college campuses. Included in the program is continued financing for the national domestic violence hot line, which supporters say receives 13,000 a calls a month.</p>
        <p>''This bill is the strongest commitment that Congress has ever made to fighting domestic violence and sexual assault,'' Representative Constance A. Morella, Republican of Maryland, said.</p>
        <p>In tradeoffs that allowed these popular provisions to advance without delay, House and Senate negotiators approved several unrelated, contentious issues. One permits the enforcement of state liquor laws in federal court. Critics call it an effort  to use the federal courts in a dispute between wine and beer wholesalers and small independent wineries and breweries that seek to sell their wares over the Internet.</p>
        <p>Another measure would help American victims of terrorism who win federal lawsuits against so-called rogue states to collect their judgments from those countries.</p>
        <p>Finally, the package included a measure that would penalize states that release a convicted murderer or rapist who later commits a similar crime in another state. Critics say that this provision would cost states federal law enforcement financing and create unneeded bureaucracies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
