<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charge in Stadium Case Dropped Against Father in Baby Death</title>
    <meta content="07ROCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/nyregion/07ROCK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maniaci, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grossberg, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raciti, Robert (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDE123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charge in Stadium Case Dropped Against Father in Baby Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Supreme Court Judge Robert Raciti agrees to dismiss resisting arrest charge against Brian Peterson, who was arrested along with Raymond Maniaci in connection with incident during New York Mets baseball game; Peterson is currently on probation for manslaughter in death of newborn son in Newark, Del, motel in 1996 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens judge agreed yesterday to dismiss the most serious charge from a Shea Stadium bottle-throwing incident involving Brian C. Peterson, who pleaded guilty in 1998 to manslaughter in the death of his newborn son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson, 22, was arrested Sept. 26 after, the police said, he tried to interfere with the arrest of his friend, Raymond Maniaci. The authorities said Mr. Maniaci threw a plastic bottle that landed on the field within 10 feet of John Rocker, the Atlanta Braves pitcher who gained notoriety for his comments assailing Mets fans and other groups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Queens judge agreed yesterday to dismiss the most serious charge from a Shea Stadium bottle-throwing incident involving Brian C. Peterson, who pleaded guilty in 1998 to manslaughter in the death of his newborn son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson, 22, was arrested Sept. 26 after, the police said, he tried to interfere with the arrest of his friend, Raymond Maniaci. The authorities said Mr. Maniaci threw a plastic bottle that landed on the field within 10 feet of John Rocker, the Atlanta Braves pitcher who gained notoriety for his comments assailing Mets fans and other groups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson was charged with resisting arrest, a misdemeanor that carries a penalty of up to one year in jail. He was also charged with harassment and disorderly conduct, both violations.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, Justice Robert Raciti of State Supreme Court granted a request by prosecutors to dismiss the resisting arrest charge. He said the other charges would also be dismissed if Mr. Peterson stayed out of trouble for the next six months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maniaci, 21, who was charged with reckless endangerment, attempted assault in the third degree and other misdemeanors, pleaded guilty to disorderly conduct and was ordered yesterday to pay a $250 fine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson, of Wyckoff, N.J., was released from prison in January after serving 18 months of a two-year prison term and was placed on probation for two years.</p>
        <p>In a highly publicized case, Mr. Peterson and his high school sweetheart, Amy S. Grossberg, then a freshman at the University of Delaware, pleaded guilty to negligent manslaughter for discarding their infant in a motel trash bin in 1996.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Delaware Department of Correction said yesterday that it was still unclear how the stadium incident would affect Mr. Peterson's probation. The spokeswoman, Beth Welch, said information about the Queens case and other details about Mr. Peterson's conduct since he was released from prison would be included in progress reports being prepared in Delaware and in New Jersey, where his probation is being supervised.</p>
        <p>The reports will be submitted to a Delaware judge, probably within the next month, Ms. Welch said.</p>
        <p>''It's possible we may determine that this action violated a term or terms of his probation,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But, she added, ''Ultimately it's up to the judge.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson declined to comment yesterday. But his lawyer, Jack T. Litman, said the judge's decision to drop the most serious charge and essentially dismiss the other charges proved that Mr. Peterson ''had no role in the events at Shea Stadium that was of any significance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman acknowledged that Mr. Peterson had tried to persuade police officers not to arrest his friend, whom he had driven to the baseball game, and may have raised his voice.</p>
        <p>The police said that Mr. Peterson had screamed obscenities at them and flailed his arms, ignoring three warnings from the officers to leave the area.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Litman said that although Mr. Peterson may have acted ''perhaps immaturely or perhaps foolishly'' in asking the police to let his friend go, ''it was not, so far as Brian is concerned, in any way a criminal incident.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
