<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slimline Stallone, With a Bruising Touch and a Gentle Mutter</title>
    <meta content="07CART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/arts/07CART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kay, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McKenna, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stallone, Sylvester</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Miranda</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Get Carter (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DE153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slimline Stallone, With a Bruising Touch and a Gentle Mutter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Get Carter, directed by Stephen Kay, written by David McKenna; Sylvester Stallone and Miranda Richardson star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its first few moments ''Get Carter'' worms its way into the small but select sub-phylum of vacuous and overdirected minor classics like ''Kalifornia'' and others that inhabit the recesses of the Movie Channel in the predawn hours on a weeknight. It's so minimally plotted that not only does it lack subtext or context, but it also may be the world's first movie without even a text.</p>
        <p>Sylvester Stallone, dragged into the 1990's by the dazzling and incoherent hand of the director, Stephen Kay, is Jack Carter. Though he comes from Las Vegas, he's not Jack Carter the motormouth stand-up comedian, but rather a man with an even more lethal specialty: he's an enforcer for the Vegas mob. He is shown applying his bruising touch to a customer and muttering a last-resort retort: ''This is going to another level.'' If the picture bothered to do this, the audience members filing out barely half an hour into the movie might have been enticed to stay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In its first few moments ''Get Carter'' worms its way into the small but select sub-phylum of vacuous and overdirected minor classics like ''Kalifornia'' and others that inhabit the recesses of the Movie Channel in the predawn hours on a weeknight. It's so minimally plotted that not only does it lack subtext or context, but it also may be the world's first movie without even a text.</p>
        <p>Sylvester Stallone, dragged into the 1990's by the dazzling and incoherent hand of the director, Stephen Kay, is Jack Carter. Though he comes from Las Vegas, he's not Jack Carter the motormouth stand-up comedian, but rather a man with an even more lethal specialty: he's an enforcer for the Vegas mob. He is shown applying his bruising touch to a customer and muttering a last-resort retort: ''This is going to another level.'' If the picture bothered to do this, the audience members filing out barely half an hour into the movie might have been enticed to stay.</p>
        <p>Carter wears what must be some new kind of miracle fabric version of shantung silk impervious to bloodstains and tears despite his strenuous forays into beatdowns. He spends much of his time storming from one seamy room shot from too many showoff angles to the next, trying to get to the heart of his brother's murder. Carter flies to Seattle, even though the strong-arm business in Vegas suffers so much from his absence that he's warned by his brother-in-punishment (John C. McGinley) that if he leaves it's going to cause him trouble. (McGinley is even more hyperactive than usual; perhaps he was afraid he couldn't be seen in all the 40-watt-bulb darkness. The film is lighted like the lobby of an Ian Schrager-Philippe Starck hotel, with so much shadow that it deserves an above-the-title credit.)</p>
        <p>That doesn't stop Carter, because he has to make up for having disappeared from his brother's life for five years. He feels a debt of honor, and although no one ever says it, the B-picture motto -- ''somebody's got to pay'' -- reverberates through what passes for a plot. This includes Carter threatening sotto voce and a number of actors doing some of their most baroque work. The group includes Mickey Rourke as a computer sleaze merchant and Alan Cumming as a computer ''gazillionaire,'' in a turn so fey and peculiar that his work as the Great Gazoo in ''The Flintstones Viva Rock Vegas'' was a note of subtle understatement by comparison.</p>
        <p>The movie credits the novel ''Jack's Return Home'' as its source, but it is an attempt to remake Mike Hodges's sleek 1971 British film noir ''Get Carter,'' in which Michael Caine was a post-mod, vengeance-minded gangster. (Mr. Caine appears here in a role that will increase regard for the original. Maybe that was his intention.) And like last year's ''Payback,'' which featured another marquee name essaying a seminal tough-guy vehicle -- Mel Gibson in what was a remake of ''Point Blank'' -- ''Carter'' is bloody and incoherent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stallone's new slimline ensemble makes him look like the guy at this week's hopelessly trendy new club who says, ''I don't think you're on the list'' without even bothering to check the clipboard. (That makes the scene when he beats up on just such a guy to gain admittance to a club unintentionally funnier than it should be.)</p>
        <p>Of course Mr. Caine's preening caginess made the outbreaks of violence in the original ''Get Carter'' all the more stunning, whereas with Mr. Stallone they're simply inevitable. The big difference is that Stallone doesn't shoot as many people, which may strike the filmmakers as revolutionary, given their star.</p>
        <p>There are many worse Stallone films, as anyone who caught the actor during the late 80's can attest. Obviously he wants to be different, which he does here by wearing a little beard and not raising his voice. The latter has the effect of making it seem that he gets into so many fights because no one can tell what it is he's saying. Had the movie played a bit more on his Man That Time Forgot discomfort, it might have been effective.</p>
        <p>The stylish murk seems to signal that everyone on the technical crew had his own agenda, each trying to outdo the others. When Mr. Stallone demands that Mr. Rourke peel off his sunglasses so he can see his eyes, the shot is so dark that the moment is pointless. That's O.K., though; so is the rest of the movie.</p>
        <p>''Get Carter'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes stylishly rendered scenes of standard B-movie ultraviolence, as well as drug use and a suggestion of rape.</p>
        <p>GET CARTER  Directed by Stephen Kay; written by David McKenna, based on novel ''Jack's Return Home'' by Ted Lewis; director of photography, Mauro Fiore; edited by Jerry Greenberg; music by Tyler Bates; production designer, Charles J. H. Wood; produced by Mark Canton, Elie Samaha and Neil Canton; released by Warner Brothers. Running time: 115 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Sylvester Stallone (Jack Carter), Miranda Richardson (Gloria), Rachael Leigh Cook (Doreen), Alan Cumming (Jeremy Kinnear), Mickey Rourke (Cyrus Paice) and Michael Caine (Cliff Brumby).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
