<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Fume After Fire Advances With Late Goal</title>
    <meta content="07SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/sports/07SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Fire</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trecker, Jamie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DE123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Fume After Fire Advances With Late Goal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE TRECKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trecker, Jamie</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Fire defeats MetroStars, 3-2, in third match of Major League Soccer semifinals to advance to finals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The third time was the charm for Chicago. The Fire edged the MetroStars, 3-2, in the third match of their Major League Soccer semifinal playoff series tonight, and clinched a berth in the M.L.S. Cup final on Oct. 15 in Washington.</p>
        <p>Ante Razov was the hero with a tie-breaking goal in the 88th minute of a game that ended a season of impressive comebacks for the MetroStars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The third time was the charm for Chicago. The Fire edged the MetroStars, 3-2, in the third match of their Major League Soccer semifinal playoff series tonight, and clinched a berth in the M.L.S. Cup final on Oct. 15 in Washington.</p>
        <p>Ante Razov was the hero with a tie-breaking goal in the 88th minute of a game that ended a season of impressive comebacks for the MetroStars.</p>
        <p>The Fire will meet the Kansas City Wizards, who defeated the Los Angeles Galaxy in the other semifinal.</p>
        <p>Chicago's victory preserved its chances to win both of United States soccer's major honors; the Fire will face the Miami Fusion here on Oct. 21 for the U.S. Open Cup.</p>
        <p>Razov's goal tonight came in the traditional Chicago way: on a breakaway. Chris Armas collected the ball about 30 yards from the net and loped it over the defenders to give Razov a clear one-on-one chance.</p>
        <p>''We created a lot of chances in the second half and we were finally able to get a goal,'' Razov said.</p>
        <p>But for the MetroStars, this game wasn't so much a loss as a theft. Goalkeeper Mike Ammann was cursing the officiating after the match and Tab Ramos was complaining. ''We had a clear goal taken away from us,'' Ramos said, ''and the refereeing was awful. To lose like this was a shame.''</p>
        <p>Added Lothar Matthaus: ''This is a huge problem, not just for us now, but for M.L.S. This is supposed to be a FIFA referee, and everyone can see that he stole from us tonight.''</p>
        <p>The call that burned the MetroStars the deepest came with the score tied at 2-2 in the 63rd minute, when Adolfo Valencia had a clear goal called back for offsides. Valencia, who not only appeared to be  onside, but had also seen the Fire's Jesse Marsch play the ball first, was  livid at the call, made by the junior referee Jorge Reyes.</p>
        <p>''All of these calls are very close, but if a call or two would have gone our way, it would have been a different story,'' MetroStars Coach Octavio Zambrano said.</p>
        <p>The Fire got off to a fast start.  Defender C. J. Brown slipped a ball off a Hristo Stoichkov corner kick past the startled Ammann in the fourth minute to open the scoring.</p>
        <p>Brown, who was unmarked in the area, flicked the ball with his left heel on the cross, sending it into the lower right side of the net.</p>
        <p>Chicago scored again when Stoichkov delivered a world-class strike in the 31st minute. After collecting a seemingly innocuous cross from Razov, Stoichkov launched a shot from 20 yards that whipped past Ammann, ricocheted off the crossbar and fell into the net.</p>
        <p>On the ensuing sequence, the MetroStars covered the length of the field to score. Alex Comas slotted a ball across the goalmouth to Mike Petke, who in turn found Valencia near the penalty spot.</p>
        <p>Despite being tied up by Brown, Valencia got the shot off, and even goalkeeper Zach Thornton's big hands could not keep the ball from crossing the line.</p>
        <p>Four minutes later, in the 36th minute, Valencia collected his own rebound off Thornton and scored with a coolly taken volley. Suddenly, the game was tied.</p>
        <p>''We let them get back in the game,'' Razov said. ''That was a wake-up call for us.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars avoided a penalty  at the 60-minute mark when Petke got away with clearly tackling Stoichkov in the penalty box.</p>
        <p>Stoichkov, vehement after a pattern of such take-downs, was subsequently carded by Tim Weyland, who was escorted from the field by security guards after the game.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
