<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Remarks by Milosevic, Clinton and Key Serbs</title>
    <meta content="Y07TEX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/world/07TEXT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0DF123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Remarks by Milosevic, Clinton and Key Serbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Text of statement by Pres Slobodan Milosevic accepting election of Vojislav Kostunica to succeed him, and statement of Pres Clinton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is the statement by President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia accepting the election of Vojislav Kostunica to succeed him, as broadcast by CNN:</p>
        <p>I've just received official information that Vojislav Kostunica won the elections. This decision was made by the body that was authorized to do so under the Constitution, and I consider that it has to be respected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is the statement by President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia accepting the election of Vojislav Kostunica to succeed him, as broadcast by CNN:</p>
        <p>I've just received official information that Vojislav Kostunica won the elections. This decision was made by the body that was authorized to do so under the Constitution, and I consider that it has to be respected.</p>
        <p>I want to thank all those who voted for me, and at the same time those who didn't, because they lifted from my soul a heavy burden I have borne for 10 years.</p>
        <p>Concerning my party, it is going to provide very strong opposition. I have always said no party can ever demonstrate all its strengths and qualities if it isn't in opposition for a time, because the time spent in opposition allows a party to expel those who got in to feed some personal interest. I'm sure the coming times will be a great help to the Socialist Party of Serbia and to you, and sure of the party's victory in the next election.</p>
        <p>For me personally, because my burden has been lifted, I plan to spend some time with my family, especially my grandson, Marko, and after that to continue to strengthen my party and to increase its contributions to the society and further development of this country -- like the contributions it has already made to the defense and renewal of our country.</p>
        <p>I congratulate Mr. Kostunica on his electoral victory and wish for all citizens of Yugoslavia great success during the new presidency.</p>
        <p>As President Milosevic acknowledged the election of Mr. Kostunica to succeed him, Belgrade was aswarm with official statements of congratulations and concern. Here is a sampling:</p>
        <p>PATRIARCH PAVLE -- of the Serbian Orthodox Church, addressing the army chief of staff, Gen. Nebojsa Pavkovic:</p>
        <p>I appeal to you and our people's army to publicly accept what our people and the democratic world accept -- Vojislav Kostunica as the president of Yugoslavia. . . . (Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>GENERAL PAVKOVIC</p>
        <p>Honored Mr. Kostunica, in the name of all the members of the Yugoslav Army and on my own behalf, I want to congratulate you on your victory in the Yugoslav presidential election.</p>
        <p>In the turbulent events which took place in recent days, our citizens demonstrated their political and national maturity and put an end to another great crisis. Members of the Yugoslav Army, strictly respecting constitutional rulings, did not take part in the political struggle and are ready to accept the people's will and all the legitimate decisions of the electoral institutions.</p>
        <p>Addressing Mr. Milosevic's desire to stay active in politics, General Pavkovic said:</p>
        <p>We are sure that in this new function, you will do everything to have all problems solved in a civilized manner and return the country to normal political and economic life. (Reuters)</p>
        <p>In Washington, President Clinton's remarks at a news conference reflected those of leaders around the world. The transcript was prepared by Federal News Service, a private company.</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT CLINTON</p>
        <p>I'd like to say a few words about the historic developments in Serbia.</p>
        <p>First and foremost, this is an extraordinary victory for the people of the former Yugoslavia, who endured oppression and deprivation, who saw through the propaganda, who took their country back with nothing but courage, principle and patriotism.</p>
        <p>They will now define the shape of their future. They have said they want to live in a normal country, at peace with its neighbors and a part of the world. The rest of us will welcome them.</p>
        <p>This is a victory for newly elected President Kostunica, for his integrity and leadership in bringing this new day. As Yugoslavia's new leaders work to build a truly democratic society, we will move with our European allies to lift sanctions and bring them out of isolation. This is a victory for all southeast Europe.</p>
        <p>As long as Mr. Milosevic was in power, the danger of more violence in Bosnia, Kosovo, Montenegro, Macedonia remained high. A dark cloud has lifted, and though tensions and challenges clearly remain, prospects for enduring stability in the Balkans have greatly improved.</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
