<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beliefs; A Vatican office attacks pluralistic relativism, and the resulting fallout is spread far and wide.</title>
    <meta content="07BELI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/national/07BELI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinfels, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">John Paul II (Pope)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratzinger, Joseph (Cardinal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6DA153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beliefs; A Vatican office attacks pluralistic relativism, and the resulting fallout is spread far and wide.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Steinfels</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinfels, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Steinfels Beliefs column discusses document issued by Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger, who heads Vatican's Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, that condemns certain theories of religious pluralism; some Christian theologians find this approach insufficiently respectful of other religions; many Christian leaders expressed distress at change of climate in Vatican; some interfaith dialogues are canceled in protest although Pope reaffirms commitment to ecumenism (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Sept. 5, Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger, who heads the Vatican's Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, issued a document titled ''Dominus Iesus'' (''The Lord Jesus'') that condemned certain ''relativistic theories'' of religious pluralism. A month later, the dust has still not settled.</p>
        <p>In some eyes, Cardinal Ratzinger was only saying the obvious and doing his job. Haven't Christians always believed that it is through Jesus Christ and the church of the Gospel that salvation has been mediated to all humankind? If grace and holiness seemed manifest within other religions or among those who had never heard the Gospel, this, too, was attributable, in ways not always to be understood, to Jesus' redemptive acts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Sept. 5, Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger, who heads the Vatican's Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, issued a document titled ''Dominus Iesus'' (''The Lord Jesus'') that condemned certain ''relativistic theories'' of religious pluralism. A month later, the dust has still not settled.</p>
        <p>In some eyes, Cardinal Ratzinger was only saying the obvious and doing his job. Haven't Christians always believed that it is through Jesus Christ and the church of the Gospel that salvation has been mediated to all humankind? If grace and holiness seemed manifest within other religions or among those who had never heard the Gospel, this, too, was attributable, in ways not always to be understood, to Jesus' redemptive acts.</p>
        <p>Some Christian theologians have found this traditional approach insufficiently respectful of other faiths.  They have devised theories of Christs in other religions, or they have emphasized the saving action of the Second Person of the Trinity (the Word, or Logos) or of the Third Person (the Spirit), quite apart from the historically specific figure of Jesus of Nazareth. Christians might find salvation in Jesus, but the Logos or the Spirit could work as well through Buddha or Muhammad.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Ratzinger's reply, beneath the highly technical theological language of ''Dominus Iesus,'' was to display a formidable array of Christian affirmations of the central redemptive role of Jesus.</p>
        <p>Those affirmations begin with the fourth-century Nicene Creed, Christianity's most uniting statement of faith, which, it should be noted, the cardinal's document quotes in its original form, without the added language that Eastern Orthodox churches reject. The affirmations continue right through the documents of the Second Vatican Council, considered the seedbed of modern Roman Catholic ecumenism and interfaith dialogue.</p>
        <p>So why, in other eyes, was the Vatican declaration something like a theological equivalent of Ariel Sharon's striding into the area of Al Aksa Mosque?</p>
        <p>Many Christian leaders, including the archbishop of Canterbury, expressed their distress at what seemed a sharp change of climate in the Vatican. Italian Jewish leaders withdrew their participation from a Vatican-sponsored Day of Jewish-Christian Dialogue, and the event had to be canceled.</p>
        <p>The World Alliance of Reformed Churches, similarly scheduled to participate in an official dialogue with Catholics in Rome, considered calling off that session as well. The alliance, based in Geneva, went ahead with the meeting, but only after expressing its dismay at the Vatican declaration ''in the strongest terms possible.'' The pope himself felt compelled to address the group with the message that ''the commitment of the Catholic Church to ecumenical dialogue is irrevocable.''</p>
        <p>But these high-level disruptions of ecumenical and interreligious relations scarcely compared to the unsettling of Catholics in the pews. Was  the church teaching that their non-Christian spouses, parents or grandchildren could not be saved? Wasn't this document a gratuitous insult to their partners in interfaith efforts?  Reactions ranged from puzzlement to bitterness, and pastors have been fielding questions and calming the waters in sermons.</p>
        <p>Some church leaders were quick to hold the news media responsible for this confusion. They could point to misleading headlines or articles suggesting that only Catholics could go to heaven. They could equally have blamed lazy thinking that takes the maxim ''All religions are pretty much the same, and one's as good as another'' as the gold standard in tolerance, when in fact it trivializes the serious claims most faiths make.</p>
        <p>But media shortcomings and lazy thinking are more or less permanent facts of life that the Vatican might have considered in wording and presenting its declaration. And they don't explain the reservations voiced by a number of Catholic bishops and scholars, who otherwise sympathized with the declaration's intent.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Edward Cassidy, president of the Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity, was quoted by an Italian paper as calling the declaration inopportune.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Roger Mahony of Los Angeles said, ''The tone of 'Dominus Iesus' may not fully reflect the deeper understanding that has been achieved through ecumenical and interreligious dialogues over these last 30 years or more.''</p>
        <p>Archbishop Alexander Brunett of Seattle, reviewing his own years in church-sponsored dialogues with other religious groups, said, ''This declaration does not add much to the process; nor does it further the cause of mutual understanding and respect.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Robert P. Imbelli, a theologian teaching at Boston College, makes a strong case for ''Dominus Iesus'' in a coming issue of Commonweal magazine. Yet he notes in passing that ''the tone of the document is peremptory'' and that its theological claims about the church raise ''legitimate questions'' -- not small points, coming from a defender.</p>
        <p>Distress over ''Dominus Iesus'' may arise less from what it says than from what it doesn't say. There is a use of words like ''fully,'' ''completely,'' ''exclusive'' and ''definitive'' that cry out for further explanation. There are few expressions of humility or openness, even of the sort that Cardinal Bernard Law of Boston managed to make clearly in a statement that welcomed the declaration enthusiastically.</p>
        <p>''Dominus Iesus,'' he wrote, ''is not a proclamation of some human superiority in contrast to any other person or institution'' but instead ''a reaffirmation of what the church believes and lives with an ever abiding sense of her own unworthiness.''</p>
        <p>A number of Catholic leaders have suggested that Cardinal Ratzinger's Vatican office sees itself as theologians writing for theologians. It is up to local bishops to handle the pastoral consequences: the distress felt by Catholics and their partners in ecumenical and interreligious activities.</p>
        <p>Is this a realistic division of labor?  Can one say the declaration accomplished its goals? Are Catholics less inclined today than a month ago to relativize ancient teachings about Jesus, or equate all religions? Are they possibly even more inclined to do so? And when the American bishops gather at their fall meeting next month, will anyone ask these questions?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
