<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Version Of My Job, Made for TV</title>
    <meta content="07NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/nyregion/07NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Platt, Oliver</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Deadline (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DD123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Version Of My Job, Made for TV</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Column contends television show Deadline, starring Oliver Platt, about big city tabloid newspaper columnist, is filled with fantasy; says programs about journalists rarely get it right, adding glamour where none exists (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OLIVER PLATT, an engaging and intelligent actor, dropped by the newsroom a few months ago. He was preparing for his starring role as a newspaper columnist in ''Deadline,'' a new NBC series that got rolling the other night.</p>
        <p>His character writes for a tabloid newspaper modeled on The New York Post. But Mr. Platt was also curious about life at a newspaper famous for its many sections that fall to the floor when you turn the pages while trying to keep your balance on a lurching IRT train.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OLIVER PLATT, an engaging and intelligent actor, dropped by the newsroom a few months ago. He was preparing for his starring role as a newspaper columnist in ''Deadline,'' a new NBC series that got rolling the other night.</p>
        <p>His character writes for a tabloid newspaper modeled on The New York Post. But Mr. Platt was also curious about life at a newspaper famous for its many sections that fall to the floor when you turn the pages while trying to keep your balance on a lurching IRT train.</p>
        <p>At one point, he asked about the routine of a big-city columnist. Naturally, we were flattered, and wanted to help him out.</p>
        <p>Let him know what it is like to race into a burning house and rescue terrified tots. (We hard-bitten newspaper types never talk about children, only tots.) Let him sense the thrill of solving crimes and feel the adrenaline rush that comes with pulling a wounded cop out of the line of fire. Maybe share the memory of lunch with the debauched contessa, a glorious afternoon in Rome that was ruined when the Red Brigades shot up the restaurant, killing no one but spilling what was left of a fine Brunello di Montalcino.</p>
        <p>We worried, however, that these exploits were so thrilling, Mr. Platt might not entirely believe them. Instead, we played it safe and told a bunch of lies.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, we said, a columnist's day is really boring. Sometimes, it means spending hours plowing through tedious reports, or placing countless phone calls and waiting forever for people to call back, or staring at the wall while wondering what to write. Some days, the high point is the arrival of the 5 o'clock coffee wagon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Platt saw right through the charade, as did the clever ''Deadline'' writers. They didn't buy this boredom nonsense. Their script for the first episode told it like it is.</p>
        <p>The columnist, Wallace Benton, informs the police that he is going with them when they raid the apartment of two mass murderers. ''Look, I'm a reporter -- I need details for my story,'' he says, strapping on a helmet worthy of Michael Dukakis. He even waves the officers into action with a shout of ''Go, go, go!''</p>
        <p>Later, at the station house, detectives interrogate one of the perps. Sure enough,  Benton is there. ''You guys mind if I talk to this gent alone?'' he asks. No problem. The detectives immediately leave, saying, ''Knock yourself out.''</p>
        <p>How true, how true. Stuff like that happens to a columnist all the time. Only yesterday, the right leg was throbbing from an old bullet wound suffered on a raid in Queens.</p>
        <p>SPEAKING of legs, you might feel yours being pulled. The reality is that television shows rarely get journalism right, and this one is no exception. There is a simple reason.</p>
        <p>Most people in the news trade lead unexciting, not-ready-for-prime-time lives. That is why they became journalists in the first place, so they could hang around, and write about, people infinitely more fascinating than themselves. (Then again, lawyers as a group are not electrifying, either, yet that hasn't ended the parade of lawyer shows.)</p>
        <p>On the rare occasion that television accurately captures newsroom life, it almost hates to admit it.</p>
        <p>Remember ''Lou Grant,'' the 70's series about a city newspaper with rolled-up sleeves? Its writers borrowed liberally (read: stole) from real events. One segment had a subplot about a part-time college correspondent who showed promise but was also a bit of a smart aleck. He was fired when, as a prank, he slipped phony information into an article.</p>
        <p>We know someone just like that. In fact, you are reading him right now. His long-ago firing for a misguided joke was public knowledge at the time, written about in articles and a book. Yet when he called, out of curiosity, to ask if he was indeed the model, the ''Lou Grant'' producers went into total denial. Never read about you, they said. Pure coincidence.</p>
        <p>''Ripped from the headlines,'' you see, was not yet a bragging point.</p>
        <p>''Deadline'' is no ''Lou Grant.'' But it may yet make a pass at reality, assuming that it isn't canceled first. Then we could give the Benton character some real newspaper advice. What better tip than this from an old colleague: Never do your expense account when you're in a good mood. You only err in the boss's favor.</p>
        <p>Not that we really have much to teach on this score to a swashbuckler like Benton, who lives in a New York duplex, wears expensive suits, makes $300,000 a year and has a corner table at Pastis.</p>
        <p>Besides, the 5 o'clock coffee wagon just arrived. Got to go.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
