<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Take the Home-Field Advantage, and Giants' Momentum</title>
    <meta content="07CHAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/sports/07CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D9153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Take the Home-Field Advantage, and Giants' Momentum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass On Baseball column discusses home-field advantage in playoffs and how it can effect players (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before the Mets play their first home playoff game of the new millennium, one thing should be made perfectly clear: The Mets and the San Francisco Giants did not share the best home record in the major leagues this year.</p>
        <p>That canard has been rampant the past few days as the merits of the teams have been debated. Indeed, both teams have played very well in their own parks, but the Mets finished the regular season with a better home record than the Giants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before the Mets play their first home playoff game of the new millennium, one thing should be made perfectly clear: The Mets and the San Francisco Giants did not share the best home record in the major leagues this year.</p>
        <p>That canard has been rampant the past few days as the merits of the teams have been debated. Indeed, both teams have played very well in their own parks, but the Mets finished the regular season with a better home record than the Giants.</p>
        <p>The Giants won 55 games and lost 26 at home, the brand spanking new Pacific Bell Park. Those figures are incontrovertible. The popular misconception is that the Mets' home record was the same. It was not. The Mets won 55 games and lost 25 at home. That's a one-loss difference, enough to give them the distinction of having had the best home record.</p>
        <p>Why is there a difference in the number of home games each team played? Ay, there's the rub. The Mets opened the season in Japan, and the first game with the Chicago Cubs there was considered a Mets home game. But a game half a world from Shea Stadium cannot be lumped with games played at Shea. The decision therefore is final: best home record, Mets.</p>
        <p>Now that that matter is settled, what bearing could Shea Stadium have on the division series that will resume there today? The Giants learned Thursday night that a good home record during the season does not add any runs to the home team's score. If the home team doesn't have as many players cross the plate as the visiting team, the home team still loses.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the more relevant question is what bearing could the Mets' mercurial 10-inning, 5-4 victory in San Francisco on Thursday night have on the series?</p>
        <p>Trying to answer that question, Al Leiter said: ''Hopefully, this is a good momentum for us to really feel good about ourselves going back to New York, 1-1. The way we came back to win that game, with such an emotional high, hopefully we all feel good about ourselves going back to New York.''</p>
        <p>Leiter was as instrumental as anyone in bringing the Mets home tied in the three-of-five game series. He berated himself for throwing the pitch that Barry Bonds rapped for a leadoff double in the ninth inning, a hit that knocked Leiter out of the game. But Leiter left with a 4-1 lead and had every reason to think that Armando Benitez would preserve that lead, or some semblance of it.</p>
        <p>But Benitez did not, and his failure led to the drama that made the Mets' victory so emotionally charged. J. T. Snow's pinch-hit, three-run home run tied the game and ignited a frenzy among the Giants fans that threatened to transport the home team to victory not only in that game but also in the first one in New York. A loss could have been demoralizing to the Mets.</p>
        <p>But just as unexpectedly, because they had two out and no one on base, the Mets scored the tie-breaking run in the 10th and won the game, shocking those same frenzied fans into a stunned silence that may last from now until opening day 2001.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the more relevant issue will be whether the double turn of events will have any effect on the way the teams play subsequent games. The next two of those games will be played at Shea.</p>
        <p>''We have just as good a record at home as they do,'' John Franco said, ignoring the subtle difference established above. ''Giants fans are unbelievable, they're loud, very supportive. But the way I know New York fans, it'll be just as loud and even louder. If last year in the Atlanta series was any indication, they're going to be very loud and supportive.''</p>
        <p>Leiter, too, expected input from the fans, saying they ''will be pretty brutal'' on the Giants and ''make it tough on them.'' ''But look,'' he added, ''you're not here in the playoffs if you're not able to handle that kind of distraction and adversity.''</p>
        <p>Yet fans can affect a player. John Rocker, Exhibit A, hasn't been the same since he tangled with Mets fans last season. The fans' treatment of the Braves' relief pitcher prompted a post postseason tirade that got him suspended and undermined his early-season effectiveness.</p>
        <p>As for the boost the come-from-ahead victory may give the wild-card Mets, recall that last year they split the first two games of the division series in Arizona, then returned home and knocked off the favored Diamondbacks in the two games here. The Diamondbacks had won 100 games during the season.</p>
        <p>The Giants didn't win 100, but they led the major leagues in victories in a parity-producing season. Momentum is a debatable and often ephemeral intangible. Earl Weaver, a manager of some repute, believed momentum was a three-run home run. Mike Piazza said recently that momentum doesn't carry from game to game.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Mets split the games in Arizona by winning the first game. This time they won the second. They will soon learn if the effect is the same.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to get a split out of here,'' Darryl Hamilton said after scoring the winning run. ''We did that. Now we have home-field advantage and hope we can take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
