<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Affluent Nassau Faces Debt Troubles, All Sides Ask Why</title>
    <meta content="07NASS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/nyregion/07NASS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Himmelfarb, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gulotta, Thomas S (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D8153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Affluent Nassau Faces Debt Troubles, All Sides Ask Why</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article speculates about how affluent Nassau County landed in financial crisis, with bond rating one notch above junk; Richard Himmelfarb, associate professor of political science at Hofstra University, holds it's unfair to entirely blame county executive Thomas Gulotta, that voters keep re-electing him and bear some responsibility; while most municipal failures are caused by external factors, Nassau's problems are internal and include deficit spending, inadequate tax increases and political complacency; State Comptroller H Carl McCall criticizes inefficient and unfair tax system supported with borrowed money and says situation calls for 'chastisement'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nassau County is attracting rubberneckers, and not just those crawling past accidents on the Long Island Expressway. Like a suicide in high society, the county, in its current fallen financial state, brings out a morbid curiosity among finance experts, academics, politicians and, closest to home, residents themselves.</p>
        <p>What could have gone so terribly wrong, they wonder? How could a rich county in an economic boom end up with a bond rating one notch above junk, flirting with bankruptcy and in the same predicament as some hapless upstate industrial cities or</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nassau County is attracting rubberneckers, and not just those crawling past accidents on the Long Island Expressway. Like a suicide in high society, the county, in its current fallen financial state, brings out a morbid curiosity among finance experts, academics, politicians and, closest to home, residents themselves.</p>
        <p>What could have gone so terribly wrong, they wonder? How could a rich county in an economic boom end up with a bond rating one notch above junk, flirting with bankruptcy and in the same predicament as some hapless upstate industrial cities or</p>
        <p>New York City during the darkest moments of its fiscal crisis?</p>
        <p>Experts on municipal finance and commuters at bus stops all have their thoughts, touching on points that often have as much to do with psychology as money matters.</p>
        <p>''It's unfair to blame the county executive for the entire mess,'' said Richard Himelfarb, an associate professor of political science at Hofstra University, in response to the frequently voiced view that Thomas S. Gulotta, who has led the county for the last 13 years, is, along with county legislators,  responsible for the county's predicament. ''The fact is, ultimately these people were being re-elected time after time by the people. To the extent that anyone has fallen asleep at the switch, it's the people.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The most baffling question to me as a political scientist is why this affluent and well-educated group of people is willing to tolerate a degree of corruption and a degree of mismanagement you really don't see in the United States. In many cases, that's reserved for the third world.''</p>
        <p>Most municipal financial disasters are  caused by external factors: recessions, a disintegrating tax base or an investment adviser run amok. But the litany of Nassau's scapegoats is long and keeps growing from within, like a tumor: deficit spending, inadequate tax increases, expensive union contracts, imperfect politicians, the political complacency that can come with privilege, and, surprisingly, a healthy economy that for years kept the problems from erupting.</p>
        <p>The county faces an $81.7 million budget deficit this year and a shortfall of up to $379.6 million by 2004, according to Frank Zarb, head of the Nassau Interim Finance Authority. The state-appointed group will take over the county's financial operations if, by the end of the month, Nassau fails to balance its 2001 budget and fails to produce a plan to reduce its deficits in future years.</p>
        <p>A survey of 400 Nassau County voters at the beginning of September found that they thought that budget problems and government mismanagement were the county's biggest problems.</p>
        <p>The survey of Nassau voters, by the Kitchens Group of Maitland, Fla., found that a ''staggering'' 71 percent of Nassau voters would prefer a tax increase to eliminating family service programs, which are at risk of being cut. And 62 percent said an income tax would be the fairest tax, because more money is paid by the people who make the most.</p>
        <p>But in interviews, residents of Nassau County, where the average home sells for $254,500, have varied views on the way out of the mess.</p>
        <p>At the Long Island Bus station in Hempstead, Georgina Willie, a retiree who lives in Hempstead, said today: ''They need to do something that would not hit on the homeowners. We're the ones who work every day. Gulotta needs to do something. He's the one at the top that we blame.''</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Ruffin, a grocery store cashier from Roosevelt, was also waiting for a bus. ''If it were for a better, safe neighborhood, I could see paying an extra $100 in taxes,'' said Ms. Ruffin, who leaves at 5:30 a.m. to get to work. But does she believe new taxes would be spent that way? ''No, definitely not,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At Pennsylvania Station on Wednesday, commuters waiting for the Long Island Rail Road voiced a similar cynicism about the county's ability to use a tax increase responsibly. But some found it hard not to place blame on the county's fabled Republican political machine, now under assault after decades of one-party rule.</p>
        <p>''They've been living on next year's revenue; I really think that's the biggest problem,'' said Jerry Mantell, a bridal designer from Cedarhurst. ''I think it's bad management. You've had one party in there too long, and it leads to all those things. And I'm a Republican.''</p>
        <p>Nearby, Berry Coles, a social worker from North Merrick, said it was time for Mr. Gulotta to move on. ''I just don't see where he's made any dramatic changes,'' he said. ''I don't think he's putting money in the right places.''</p>
        <p>Bill Morrogh, an information systems director from Wantagh, said, ''The financial control board should take over, because the politicians are incapable of cutting the patronage and waste.'' As for any tax increases, he added, ''They're not going to kill me, but the waste will.''</p>
        <p>Jude Alexis, a computer programmer from Old Westbury, said he could support a targeted tax increase to save the county. ''It would preferably be for people who can afford it,'' he said, adding that he would pay a tax increase to support the upcoming police contracts.</p>
        <p>Ray Horton, who was executive director of the Temporary Commission on New York City Finances during the city's financial crisis in the mid-1970's, suggested some strategies for reducing the county's labor costs.</p>
        <p>''You can either reduce the number of employees or figure out some way to avoid cockamamie contract increases,'' he said, referring to a proposed raise for Nassau County police, already among the nation's highest paid. ''You can give the union its choice: if they want a five-year, 22 percent increase, fine, but you're going to fund it by firing whatever percentage of the police force you're required to fire to break even on labor costs. It's hard politically, but it's manageable where there's a will.''</p>
        <p>Eleanor D. Craig, associate chairwoman of the department of economics at the University of Delaware and an expert in municipal finance, said that frequently when municipalities, counties, cities or states were in crisis, they were trying to spend their way into more terms. ''They've taken on programs and built things they wouldn't have built if hadn't been trying to buy the votes,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Phoebe Goodman, executive director of the Nassau Citizens Budget Committee, said many of the current problems were caused by county politicians who had been reluctant to take the difficult but necessary step of reassessing property, cutting down on costly tax rebates, because they feared ''that they wouldn't be loved anymore and might lose office.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''We do have a very effective machine here, and its sole purpose to the naked eye seems to be to keep re-electing themselves, to be in power in order to stay in power. I don't think anybody understood just how bad it was. When the rating services a year and a half ago dropped the credit rating, that's what finally woke everybody up."</p>
        <p>H. Carl McCall, the state comptroller, served on the oversight boards that brought Troy and Yonkers out of financial crises. He recalled how Nassau and Suffolk Counties were in similar fiscal distress in 1992, seeking help from the state.</p>
        <p>''Suffolk County went forward to do the right kinds of things, the right financial practices, and now they're in good shape, and Nassau County had a very ruinous approach to fiscal management,'' he said. ''I think this can all rest squarely on the shoulders of the county executive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall saw parallels between Nassau's situation and the biblical story of the man who gave his various servants sums of money, which some invested profitably, but which one buried in the earth, angering the master.</p>
        <p>He chastised the servant and sent him away amid weeping and the gnashing of teeth, Mr. McCall said.</p>
        <p>''I think there needs to be some chastisement in Nassau before we forgive them,'' Mr. McCall said.</p>
        <p>''They used more financial gimmicks than we have seen anywhere else in the country, they have an inefficient and unfair taxation system, and they supported that with borrowed money. Everybody simply brushed aside the criticisms and continued to say, 'Look, everything's fine.' ''</p>
        <p>In Nassau County, Mr. McCall said, ''If the public was aware of how bad things were, they would've reacted sooner; a lot of this was disguised.''</p>
        <p>But even after the strongest wake-up call, at least one academic had trouble believing the extent of the fiscal emergency. Professor Himelfarb remembers when he first heard that the county's bonds had been downgraded to a step above a junk rating.</p>
        <p>''I was driving on the road, through Great Neck, and there were all of these people in Mercedeses and Corvettes,'' he said. ''I remember thinking, 'How the heck could this happen here?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
