<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republican's Unusual Gift: A Vote on the House Floor</title>
    <meta content="Y07HOU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/politics/07HOUS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE HOUSE RACES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armenian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hastert, J Dennis (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rogan, James E (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DA153CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republican's Unusual Gift: A Vote on the House Floor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Speaker J Dennis Hastert clears way for House vote on contentious resolution to condemn mass killings of Armenians in Turkey 85 years ago, even though Clinton administration says measure would damage relations with Turkey, important ally in NATO; measure is priority in Southern California district of Rep James E Rogan, which has largest Armenian-American constituency in country; Rogan, a Republican, is in tough re-election bid; Hastert defies critics who say he is putting party interests ahead of foreign policy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, a measure to condemn the mass killings of Armenians in Turkey 85 years ago as genocide languished in Congress. That was before James E. Rogan's seat was in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Now that Mr. Rogan, a House impeachment manager and perhaps his party's most vulnerable incumbent, is fighting for his political life in next month's elections, the Republican leadership in the House is coming to his rescue in an unusual way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, a measure to condemn the mass killings of Armenians in Turkey 85 years ago as genocide languished in Congress. That was before James E. Rogan's seat was in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Now that Mr. Rogan, a House impeachment manager and perhaps his party's most vulnerable incumbent, is fighting for his political life in next month's elections, the Republican leadership in the House is coming to his rescue in an unusual way.</p>
        <p>It is common for party leaders to help embattled incumbents bring home political prizes -- often in the form of bridges, dams and highways. But Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois is clearing the way for the House to vote next week on the contentious Armenia resolution, a priority in Mr. Rogan's Southern California district, which has the largest Armenian-American constituency in the country. Prospects for passage are unclear.</p>
        <p>By fulfilling a promise to bring up the measure, Mr. Hastert was defying critics who said he was putting party interests ahead of foreign policy.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration said the measure would damage relations with Turkey, an important ally in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization.</p>
        <p>Backers argued that the resolution had bipartisan support, which included the two top Democrats in the House, Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the minority leader, and David E. Bonior of Michigan, the minority whip. But Republican aides acknowledged that Mr. Rogan's lobbying and his re-election battle pushed the measure to a vote.</p>
        <p>''If it weren't for Jim Rogan, this wouldn't be coming to the floor,'' said John P. Feehery, Mr. Hastert's spokesman.</p>
        <p>The resolution has been the talk of the three Armenian-language television stations and five newspapers in Mr. Rogan's district around Pasadena, Calif.</p>
        <p>Rogan aides estimated that more than 20,000 registered voters of Armenian descent live in the district.</p>
        <p>Armenians have maintained that thousands of their people were killed from 1915 to 1923 as part of a campaign by the Ottoman Empire to force Armenians out of eastern Turkey. The Turks have acknowledged that some 300,000 people were killed, but have said the deaths occurred when the Ottoman Empire tried to quell civil unrest. The Ottoman Empire became Turkey in 1923.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogan's stature has been slipping with Armenian-Americans because they think he has not paid enough attention to issues they care about. The influential Armenian National Committee had endorsed Mr. Rogan in the past, but this year was backing his Democratic rival, Adam Schiff, who also supported the resolution. House Republican leaders hope Mr. Rogan reaps enough credit for the measure to help sway undecided voters.</p>
        <p>''The fact this is of interest to Rogan's constituents is not lost on the leadership,'' said Representative Thomas M. Davis III of Virginia, head of the House Republican re-election campaign. ''This resolution will be a very tangible debating point for him.''</p>
        <p>Opponents are fighting back. Turkey has hired, for $1.8 million, two former chairmen of the House Appropriations Committee, Robert L. Livingston of Louisiana and Gerald B.H. Solomon of New York, both Republicans, along with Stephen J. Solarz, a former Democratic representative from New York, to lobby against the bill.</p>
        <p>Armenia's supporters have mustered a counterattack, hiring former New York congresswoman, Susan Molinari, a Republican.</p>
        <p>The measure, approved this week by the House International Relations Committee, 24 to 11, has split the Republican leadership. Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the majority leader, is leaning against the measure, his aides say, although he supports allowing a floor vote. Mr. Hastert and Representative Tom DeLay of Texas, the majority whip, would not say how they would vote.</p>
        <p>The resolution has stirred bipartisan concern, particularly among the Texas delegation because Turkey has threatened to cancel a $4.5 billion deal to buy 145 attack helicopters made by Bell Helicopter Textron in Fort Worth, a division of Textron Inc.</p>
        <p>Even though the resolution is nonbinding and does not go to the Senate or to President Clinton for approval, it has ignited opposition. On Monday, the president of Turkey, Ahmet Necdet Sezer, called Mr. Clinton to complain, just days after the Turkish foreign minister, Ismail Cem, warned that if the resolution passed, ''serious effects of it should be expected on Turkish-U.S. relations.''</p>
        <p>Turkey, officials said, could ground American warplanes that fly out of Turkish air bases to patrol northern Iraq. Mr. Clinton expressed his concerns directly to Mr. Hastert on Thursday, aides said.</p>
        <p>''I don't think this would be a good time to be rocking the boat unnecessarily,'' said Representative Porter J. Goss, the Florida Republican who heads the House Intelligence Committee.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Rogan is trying to play down his role and dismisses talk that the Republican leaders are doing him a favor, noting the support from Mr. Gephardt and Mr. Bonior.</p>
        <p>''It's time for the House to answer the question who remembers the Armenians?'' Mr. Rogan said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE HOUSE RACES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
