<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President Plays Coach in First Lady's Campaign</title>
    <meta content="07CLIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/07/politics/07CLIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DE123CF934A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President Plays Coach in First Lady's Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY and RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L; Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton has taken intense and consuming interest in wife Hillary Clinton's campaign for Senate in New York, interposing himself on matters ranging from far-reaching strategy to custodial details that would seem to fall below presidential duties; no other race in nation--including one by Vice Pres Al Gore to succeed him--has commanded as much of his attention, and drawn as much of his time and concern; aides to Hillary Clinton say intensity of Clinton's involvement varies from day to day, but his influence is felt as much as anyone's at her headquarters, save that of candidate herself; Clinton and his aides play down what he is doing in New York, concerned partly that his involvement would suggest that Hillary Clinton's political skills are not up to demands of race; Clinton has attended dozens of fund-raisers, raising more than $5 million for wife's campaign; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The announcement came crackling over the office intercom in the din of Hillary Clinton's campaign headquarters: ''The president of the United States is on Line 5 for Bill.''</p>
        <p>Bill is Mrs. Clinton's campaign manager, Bill de Blasio. The president of the United States is, of course, married to the Democratic candidate for Senate in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The announcement came crackling over the office intercom in the din of Hillary Clinton's campaign headquarters: ''The president of the United States is on Line 5 for Bill.''</p>
        <p>Bill is Mrs. Clinton's campaign manager, Bill de Blasio. The president of the United States is, of course, married to the Democratic candidate for Senate in New York.</p>
        <p>News of who was holding on Line 5 set off a rustle of excitement in the campaign headquarters near Madison Square Garden. But it was hardly a rare occurrence.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has taken an intense and consuming interest in the campaign for Senate in New York, friends and advisers said, interposing himself on matters ranging from far-reaching strategy to custodial details that would seem to fall below the presidential pay grade.</p>
        <p>In the twilight of his presidency, Mr. Clinton has found time to offer his counsel on where Mrs. Clinton should campaign (upstate, his aides say) and how heavily she should advertise on television (too much a few months ago, not enough last month).</p>
        <p>He has advised her on fund-raising strategy (raise more hard money), and how to come across at her debate tomorrow (speak in compact sentences). And he has offered up his very strong views on what he thinks she should be talking about on the trail (it's the economy, Mrs. Clinton).</p>
        <p>When Mr. Clinton called Venus Williams, the tennis star, to congratulate her for winning the United States Open last month, she asked him why she felt bombarded with commercials for Representative Rick A. Lazio, and had seen none for Mrs. Clinton. An irritated Mr. Clinton promptly called the first lady's advisers to demand why they were not buying more television time, campaign aides said.</p>
        <p>No other race in the nation -- including the one by Al Gore to succeed him -- has commanded as much of Mr. Clinton's attention, and drawn as much of his time and concern, the president's friends say. While aides to Mrs. Clinton say the intensity of Mr. Clinton's involvement varies from day to day, depending on the pull of his other duties, his influence is felt as much as anyone's at her headquarters, save for that of the candidate herself.</p>
        <p>There are times that Mr. Clinton, who is feeling the discomfort of playing the spectator as he begins his exit from elected life, seems so invested in his wife's campaign that it is as if he were running against Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Mr. Clinton has, at times, pressed Mrs. Clinton to do things that seem more suited to his political style. White House officials said Mr. Clinton urged her aides to inject more policy minutiae into her speeches. While that may work for the president, who can be arresting on the stump, Mrs. Clinton sometimes comes off as a plodding speaker.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Mrs. Clinton both declined requests for an interview for this article.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and his aides have gone to some lengths to play down what he is doing in New York, concerned partly that his involvement would suggest that Mrs. Clinton's political skills were not up to the demands of this race.</p>
        <p>''I've seen it when he was the candidate and she was the spouse, and now when she is the candidate and he is the spouse, and their roles have totally flipped,'' said Mark Penn, the longtime Clinton pollster who Mrs. Clinton installed in a senior role in her campaign at the strong urging of Mr. Clinton. ''But make no mistake about it: she has learned about New York, she makes the decisions, and she runs the show.''</p>
        <p>Still, reports of his intervention are plentiful.</p>
        <p>For example, upon learning that Mr. Lazio's wife, Patricia, was attacking Mrs. Clinton for attacking Mr. Lazio on his record on health care in Congress, President Clinton immediately called campaign officials in New York and urged them to make a rebuttal. They did.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has also chastised campaign officials for cramming Mrs. Clinton's calendar with too many events, warning that fatigue can lead to mistakes -- all the while sounding very much the way Mrs. Clinton did in 1992 when he was the candidate. ''He's actually into a spouse role -- 'You're working her too hard, she really needs a day off,' -- the same things that she used to say about him,'' said one adviser to both Clintons.</p>
        <p>Because he is president, and is viewed by Democrats and Republicans as unrivaled in his political skills, Mr. Clinton helps his wife in ways that no other spouse conceivably could, giving her an enormous advantage over Mr. Lazio, the Suffolk County Republican.</p>
        <p>The most public manifestation of that has been in fund-raising. For months, aides said, Mr. Clinton had reassured his wife that she would have enough money to be competitive. And in the face of fund-raising reports that now suggest that Mrs. Clinton has good reason to be worried, the president has gone to considerable lengths in public and private to back up his assurances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has attended two dozen fund-raisers for his wife across the country this year, raising more than $5 million. On Wednesday night, he was the star attraction at a fund-raiser for Mrs. Clinton at the home of Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts. Earlier in the week, Mr. Clinton appeared at three events in Florida, leaving Mrs. Clinton free to travel in New York while he was raising money for a campaign that he fears is underfinanced.</p>
        <p>Last month, as Mr. Clinton was preparing to travel to Philadelphia for a groundbreaking of the National Constitutional Center on Independence Mall, he called Edward G. Rendell, the general chairman of the Democratic National Committee and the former mayor of Philadelphia, and asked him to put together a quick fund-raiser. Mr. Rendell said the president specifically said he wanted to collect hard money -- the strictly regulated contributions that are the most difficult to raise and the kind Mrs. Clinton most needs.</p>
        <p>''He called me four or five days before,'' Mr. Rendell recalled. ''He said, 'If I come in an hour early, can you get people to come and do something for Hillary, because we need hard money?' So I sold it by saying, 'Come help Hillary, but this will probably be the last chance in Philadelphia to see the president in a small group.' ''</p>
        <p>The take? ''Fifty-five thousand dollars in hard money,'' Mr. Rendell said. ''For five days' notice, I was stunned. People wanted to say one last goodbye to the president.''</p>
        <p>At the White House, cabinet members and lawmakers describe Mr. Clinton as almost distracted by what is happening in New York, saying that he frequently drifts away from the official agenda to report some new bit of news out of the race, or describe a new poll by Mr. Penn. Not one day goes by, Mr. Clinton's friends say, when he does not talk about the race.</p>
        <p>Last month, Bill Richardson, the secretary of energy, walked into the Cabinet Room at the White House in preparation for bilateral negotiations with the prime minister of India. But Mr. Clinton's mind was far from the Indian subcontinent. This was a few days after Mrs. Clinton had debated Mr. Lazio, and the president had a new poll from Mr. Penn.</p>
        <p>''He was ecstatic about the debate results,'' Mr. Richardson said. ''He was exulting. His words were, 'The numbers on Hillary's debate are great.' ''</p>
        <p>At the White House, the president, Mrs. Clinton and her campaign team can often be found in the Map Room or the Family Theater, drilling for her debates, or fine-tuning lines in some speech. The president was instrumental in helping to come up with a crucial line in Mrs. Clinton's acceptance speech, which was intended to address concerns about her campaigning for office in a state where she had never lived: ''I may be new to the neighborhood, but I'm not new to your concerns.''</p>
        <p>One adviser recalls the Clintons practicing the line. ''It was like an inflection thing,'' the adviser said. ''He would say, 'Try to deliver it this way and pause here in the sentence.' She'd listen and go back and do it her way and try to pick up from his advice.''</p>
        <p>Several aides said that although the president is not dictatorial in suggesting what she should say and how she should say it, his views usually prevail.</p>
        <p>''He's very deferential,'' said one White House official. ''He'll say, 'Here's how I would answer that question, but you're the candidate, so make up your own mind.' ''</p>
        <p>Another White House official said that when Mrs. Clinton is in her office there, she often tells her staff, '' 'Check with Bill on that.' Or, 'This goes by the president.' She's extremely reliant on him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has gone to some lengths to obscure his role in his wife's campaign in the months since he called The Daily News to defend the first lady against charges that she made an anti-Semitic slur in Arkansas 26 years ago. Mr. Clinton's call served to rocket the story into major newspapers, and he has described it to friends as one of his greatest mistakes of the year.</p>
        <p>That probably explains why Mr. Clinton has yet to visit Mrs. Clinton's campaign headquarters. His appearances with her have been infrequent and are the subject of elaborate discussions over where he should sit and whether he should speak. In fact, when he does appear, as at Mrs. Clinton's nomination at the Democratic State Convention, the president often says little or even nothing.</p>
        <p>But even when asserting that he is not playing much of a role in the campaign, Mr. Clinton has startled aides by reciting word-for-word some daily attack Mr. Lazio has made against the first lady. ''If you spend any time with him, you know he knows everything that's going on,'' a senior White House aide said.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles B. Rangel of Manhattan recalled that while he was flying on Air Force One with the Clintons, the president ''appeared to be working over her speech'' that she was to give accepting her party's nomination. But days later, when Mr. Rangel was at the president's table at a state dinner, he recalled: ''I jokingly said he had written her acceptance speech. He violently disagreed. The fact is, he wanted everyone to know how completely independent she was. And that he was only reviewing it.''</p>
        <p>Like everything to do with the first couple, this latest chapter in their public lives is an intricate and exceedingly complicated involvement. Friends of the Clintons, for the most part, will not discuss the president's role in the campaign, and much of it is played out either in private conversations between the Clintons or through intermediaries. The first couple do not use e-mail.</p>
        <p>Some of Mrs. Clinton's aides say that at this point, with her campaign going well, the president's guidance is not as critical it was when Mrs. Clinton entered the race more than a year ago, and they would be just as happy if he stayed in Washington. That, though, seems unlikely.</p>
        <p>''Even if we didn't want him, we couldn't get rid of him,'' Mr. Rangel said, ''because he's committed to this race. We're dealing with a team effort.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
