<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debt Offerings For This Week</title>
    <meta content="19EQUI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debt Offerings For This Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>7-Eleven Inc., Dallas, 10 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>7-Eleven Inc., Dallas, 10 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Accelerated Networks Inc., Moorpark, Calif., an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>ASCO P.L.C., Aberdeen, Scotland, an initial public offering of 12.5 million American depositary shares, each share represents 5 ordinary shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Basic Energy Services Inc., Midland, Tex., an initial public offering of 3.7 million shares. Prudential Securities.</p>
        <p>Charles River Laboratories, Wilmington, Mass., an initial public offering of 12.5 million shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Cepheid, Sunnyvale, Calif., an initial public offering of 5 million shares. UBS Warburg.</p>
        <p>ClickSoftware Ltd., Tel Aviv, an initial public offering of 5 million ordinary shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Cox Radio Inc., Atlanta, 8 million shares. Credit Suisse First Boston and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom A.G., Bonn, 200 million American depositary shares, each shre represents 1 ordinary share. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown, Dresdner &amp; Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Handspring.com Inc., Mountain View, Calif., an initial public offering of 10 million shares. Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers' Services Ltd., Concord, Mass., an initial public offering of 11 million shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Parlex Corp., Methuen, Mass., 1.4 million shares. Harkness.</p>
        <p>Plantronics Inc., Santa Cruz, Calif., 1 million shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Pohang Iron &amp; Steel Co. Ltd., Seoul, South Korea, 23.2 million american depositary shares, each ads represents 1/4 of 1 share. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Silverline Technologies Ltd., Bombay, an initial public offering of 5.2 million American depositary shares, each share represents 2 equity shares, 3.64 million in the United States and Canada. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Telefonos de Mexico S.A., Mexico, 27.6 million American depositary shares, each share represents 20 Series L shares, 19 million in the United States and Canada. Salomon Smith Barney and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Valero Energy Corp., San Antonio, 5 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Vitech America Inc., Miami, 4.2 million shares. Joe Charles.</p>
        <p>(Source: MCM EquityWatch.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
