<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The patent office is fighting once again to hold onto its own revenue in the budget battle.</title>
    <meta content="19PATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5D81431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The patent office is fighting once again to hold onto its own revenue in the budget battle.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patent and Trademark Office battles House subcommittee proposal to keep its budget flat and divert any office revenue above $905 million to other agencies; warns of increased delays in patent processing and approval; proposal comes as office gears up to accept patent applications via Internet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG considered a small, backwater agency, the Patent and Trademark Office has found itself in recent years at the forefront of the new, high-technology economy. Its leaders are happy with the recognition, but they say to hold that place and improve their performance, they need only one thing from the rest of the federal government: to keep all the money the office earns.</p>
        <p>In a letter this month to Congress, the White House made the case for dozens of programs it wants financed in this year's appropriations bill, among them the patents office. But last week, the House Appropriations Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, State and the Judiciary proposed appropriating $905 million for the patent office, a raise that the subcommittee says includes only an adjustment for inflation, and diverting any patent office revenue above the new level to other agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG considered a small, backwater agency, the Patent and Trademark Office has found itself in recent years at the forefront of the new, high-technology economy. Its leaders are happy with the recognition, but they say to hold that place and improve their performance, they need only one thing from the rest of the federal government: to keep all the money the office earns.</p>
        <p>In a letter this month to Congress, the White House made the case for dozens of programs it wants financed in this year's appropriations bill, among them the patents office. But last week, the House Appropriations Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, State and the Judiciary proposed appropriating $905 million for the patent office, a raise that the subcommittee says includes only an adjustment for inflation, and diverting any patent office revenue above the new level to other agencies.</p>
        <p>The director of the patent office has responded that diverting that money would deny his agency 25 percent of its self-projected revenue, or $295 million, causing hiring freezes and increased delays in patent processing and approval.</p>
        <p>The Patent and Trademark Office believes it should be exempt from such budget battles since it earns enough money to pay its own keep. Yet since 1992, Congress has appropriated some of those earnings for other, unrelated agencies. And so the fight is on.</p>
        <p>The battle is taking place as the patent office fields criticism that it has been slow and clumsy in adapting its policies, hiring practices and training efforts to keep up with the  high-technology economy. The boom in software-related inventions, Internet business patents, and human genome and biotechnology patents has frequently caught the agency off guard and led to controversy, court cases and even patent cancellations.</p>
        <p>Intellectual property has emerged as the centerpiece of many entrepreneurial ventures, since it is an asset suddenly necessary to secure investors and financing. As a result, patent officials say they have more work.</p>
        <p>Trademark registrations are up 40 percent this year, and patent applications have increased 12 percent. Many business method inventions and other technology related innovations are charting new courses in patenting practices that may be challenged in courts. So any hint that the quality of examinations may suffer even as it starts taking longer to award patents gets attention.</p>
        <p>The flat budget proposal also comes just as the patent office is finally gearing up to take its own plunge into the Internet. The office announced this month that it would now accept credit card payments for the basic filing fee for a patent application, patent maintenance fees, and fees for trademark applications for registration or renewal.</p>
        <p>And it has plans to allow inventors to file electronic patent applications. Now the patent office's director says those innovations may be threatened if the office cannot pay for them with money it collects in user fees.</p>
        <p>''All of our revenues, projected to be $1.2 billion in fiscal year 2001, are paid as fees by the knowledge-based high-tech leaders and individual entrepreneurs who rely on us to help them flourish in this economy,'' Q. Todd Dickinson wrote to the subcommittee on intellectual property. ''We are no burden on the American taxpayer.''</p>
        <p>Members of the Appropriations Subcommittee have said that the patent office has overestimated how much money it will earn in 2001, and how much work it will have next year. So the skimming of the patent revenues that the subcommittee is proposing will be less than 25 percent, they say. In fact, the subcommittee predicts that its appropriation would divert only $167 million from the patent office. But even that would be more than the $116 million diverted in 2000 -- and that amount was a record.</p>
        <p>So far, the patent office is not considering raising user fees.</p>
        <p>The patent office is not alone in relying on user fees, or in having Congress appropriate some of them. The Immigration and Naturalization Service also earns income from customer fees, for example, and some of those are also diverted.</p>
        <p>And patent fees are substantial. Applying for and maintaining a patent can cost thousands of dollars when all is said and done, an amount that many inventors think is too high. In 1999, the patent office issued 265,000 patents and trademarks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dickinson, naturally, says the subcommittee's proposed appropriation is not enough. He told Congress that such financing lead to the following:</p>
        <p>*A freeze on hiring and overtime for current staff, which in turn might tempt patent examiners, trademark lawyers and others to leave the patent office.</p>
        <p>*The imposition of restrictions on training for examiners and administrators.</p>
        <p>*An increase in the time it takes the agency to take its first action on each patent application from 11 months to 15, and on trademark applications from 4.5 months to 8.</p>
        <p>*A situation in which 150,000 patents are rejected for an initial examination, not allowed or not issued at all.</p>
        <p>*An increase in the time it takes to appeal agency decisions.</p>
        <p>*A Reduction or elimination of the planned electronic filing of patent applications, online searching and upgrades of examiner computer equipment.</p>
        <p>*A risk to the financing of 87 patent and trademark libraries around the country.</p>
        <p>Others apparently agree. Representative Howard Coble, Republican of North Carolina and chairman of the subcommittee on courts and intellectual property, recently introduced legislation that would allow the patent office to keep all of its fees, and Representative Jim Moran, Democrat of Virginia, introduced an amendment to the appropriations bill that would restore the agency's funding to the amount requested by the White House.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Office of Management and Budget has recommended that President Clinton veto the bill if financing appropriated by the appropriations subcommittee is less than the administration's request. The White House also wants part of the patent office's revenues -- just not as much as Congress.</p>
        <p>All of that is a long way off. It may be months before the appropriations bill winds its way through the House  and Senate to the president's desk, and it is unlikely to get there bearing the same figures hammered out in last week's subcommittee meeting.</p>
        <p>But patent office officials and outside supporters like the Intellectual Property Owners Association and the American Intellectual Property Law Association know that budget appropriations are inevitable.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line for fee payers is that their money is not going to be used for the P.T.O.,'' said Brigid Quinn, a public affairs officer. ''But we will remain hopeful until the final stamp.''</p>
        <p>PATENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
