<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hitching Stars to His Wagon; A Talent Agent Moved, and the Talent Tagged Along</title>
    <meta content="19AGEN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agents (Business)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morris, William, Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Creative Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiatt, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/William Morris Agency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/International Creative Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Professions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D81431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hitching Stars to His Wagon; A Talent Agent Moved, and the Talent Tagged Along</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>President and co-chief executive Jim Wiatt has moved to revive William Morris, talent agency that once dominated Hollywood; has shaken up talent agency business with relentless effort to lure stars from his former agency, International Creative Management; has lured seven talent agents from ICM who brought stars with them; table; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its heyday, the venerable William Morris agency dominated Hollywood, representing legends like Marilyn Monroe, Elvis Presley, Frank Sinatra, Charlie Chaplin, Will Rogers, Fannie Brice, Al Jolson and Mae West. But by the late 1980's, the agency had stumbled and was hemorrhaging clients and agents, the result of its board's apathy and old-guard ways coupled with the death of its top Hollywood agent, Stan Kamen, in 1986.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, William Morris was dwarfed by two agencies, Creative Artists and International Creative Management, which represented a sizable chunk of movie and television stars and directors. ''The movie division needed some fixing,'' said Jim Wiatt, the former co-chairman of International Creative Management and now president and co-chief executive of William Morris.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In its heyday, the venerable William Morris agency dominated Hollywood, representing legends like Marilyn Monroe, Elvis Presley, Frank Sinatra, Charlie Chaplin, Will Rogers, Fannie Brice, Al Jolson and Mae West. But by the late 1980's, the agency had stumbled and was hemorrhaging clients and agents, the result of its board's apathy and old-guard ways coupled with the death of its top Hollywood agent, Stan Kamen, in 1986.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, William Morris was dwarfed by two agencies, Creative Artists and International Creative Management, which represented a sizable chunk of movie and television stars and directors. ''The movie division needed some fixing,'' said Jim Wiatt, the former co-chairman of International Creative Management and now president and co-chief executive of William Morris.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiatt spoke with considerable understatement. Since taking the job at the Beverly Hills headquarters of William Morris last August, the 53-year-old agent has not just sought to fix William Morris but has shaken up the talent agency business with a relentless effort to lure stars from his old employer, only two miles away. Even by the brass-knuckle standards of two former William Morris agents, Michael Ovitz and Ron Meyer, who used similar tactics 20 years ago to turn Creative Artists into the town's dominant agency, Mr. Wiatt's efforts have been surprising, dramatic and fast-moving.</p>
        <p>The agency business itself is in the grip of change in Hollywood. Facing a studio system relying mostly on star vehicles, television networks nervous about declining audiences, competition from talent managers and even lawyers, agents are involving themselves -- and their clients -- in the world of the Internet and high technology as they seek ways to expand their financial base. But success and failure in the agency business hinges on a question that has remained the same since the 1920's: how many high-priced clients does an agency represent?</p>
        <p>In the last year, seven talent agents have joined Mr. Wiatt from I.C.M. The most recent arrival, Steve Dontanville, one of I.C.M.'s top agents, brings with him, among others, Meg Ryan, Sigourney Weaver, Julianne Margulies, Courtney Love, Alfre Woodard and Patrick Stewart. Other former I.C.M. agents have brought to William Morris clients like Russell Crowe, Catherine Zeta-Jones, Emily Watson and Spike Lee. Mr. Wiatt himself has signed up Michael Douglas from Creative Artists. And former clients of his at I.C.M. like Eddie Murphy, Sylvester Stallone, Tim Allen, Nora Ephron and Penny Marshall have joined him at William Morris.</p>
        <p>The reason so many agents have moved out of I.C.M., which remains very powerful despite the losses, is, to some degree, loyalty to Mr. Wiatt, who was a mentor and friend to them. But, more important, money was a driving factor. Agents are well paid. A veteran and second-tier talent agent could earn $750,000 to $1 million a year, perhaps more with bonuses. By all accounts, William Morris increased the ante to lure the agents. An I.C.M. agent said that a former colleague, who earned $550,000, was being paid nearly double that figure at William Morris.</p>
        <p>Privately, agents at I.C.M. are outraged at Mr. Wiatt, who worked in top jobs there for 23 years and seems intent, they said, on hurting the agency. (Mr. Wiatt personally tried to lure a British film director away from one of his old friends at William Morris.) Publicly, executives at I.C.M. -- an agency with clients like Mel Gibson, Julia Roberts, Denzel Washington, Jodie Foster, Cameron Diaz, Michelle Pfeiffer, Chris Rock and Rosie O'Donnell -- said the exodus of agents and stars to join Mr. Wiatt was, essentially, the nature of the game.</p>
        <p>''You win some, you lose some,'' said Ed Limato, co-president of I.C.M., who represents numerous movie stars. ''We're cushioned against such things. We have a great bench, we have reserves. Jim's an old friend. I'm sorry he's gone. So we start a new era. Just look at our client list.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Berg, chairman of the agency, said he had expected some agents to follow Mr. Wiatt. Although partners with Mr. Berg, Mr. Wiatt was known to have had a distant, chilly relationship with him and to have been eager to leave, especially after William Morris offered him a contract far more lucrative than his $1.5 million pay package at I.C.M.</p>
        <p>''We had a senior leader, after 23 years, who left and became a competitor,'' Mr. Berg said, adding that Mr. Wiatt's departure would have no financial impact.</p>
        <p>''Our business for the last 10 years has been on a growth trajectory,'' he said, and he added that he was certain that would continue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiatt, a well-liked figure in Hollywood who is known for his friendliness and approachability, has surprised his close friends with the tough tactics. He has overhauled the New York office of William Morris, and trimmed the London unit. About 18 agents have departed. In the process, William Morris has also lost important clients, mostly to Creative Artists. These include performers like George Clooney, Brendan Fraser, Joseph Fiennes, Gillian Anderson and Matthew Perry, and directors like Anthony Minghella (''The English Patient'') and John Madden (''Shakespeare in Love'').</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiatt, seated in an office at William Morris with his former colleague at I.C.M., David Wirtschafter, who is head of worldwide motion pictures, said: ''The priority was the movie division. It needed some new blood. And I think from a morale standpoint it probably wasn't operating as well as it should have been.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Wirtschafter, who represents mostly writers and directors, said he had joined Mr. Wiatt out of ''enormous personal and professional loyalty to him.'' A somewhat distant and intense figure, Mr. Wirtschafter has, according to one agent, unnerved some of the veteran William Morris agents working for him with his biting comments. ''What's happened here in terms of the change in profile, and the absolutely extraordinary agent and client migration, is, in large part, due to Jim,'' Mr. Wirtschafter said.</p>
        <p>The last time such an exodus of clients occurred -- and it took place over several years -- began in 1986 when Stan Kamen, who ran the movie division of William Morris and was Hollywood's top agent, died. Mr. Kamen's client list was a Who's Who of Hollywood stars of the 1970's: Goldie Hawn, Barbra Streisand, Jane Fonda, Robert Redford and Warren Beatty.</p>
        <p>What followed over the next few years was an exodus of agents and their clients to Creative Artists and I.C.M. and a steady decline in the film unit of an agency that had been founded in 1898 by a German immigrant, William Morris, and had its start placing singers and comics on the vaudeville circuit.</p>
        <p>Decades later, the company's mailroom employed aspiring agents like Barry Diller, David Geffen and Michael Ovitz. The company's wealth was based not only on its client base, but substantial real estate holdings in Beverly Hills and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Today, the company's leadership is dominated as it always was by businessmen representing few, if any, clients. The result was an agency -- and an 11-member board -- that was, until recently, the most buttoned-up in town, rooted in tradition and conservative by nature.</p>
        <p>Walt Zifkin, chief executive at William Morris, said Mr. Wiatt's performance so far had been ''beyond expectations.''</p>
        <p>''It's considerable and it's strengthened us,'' Mr. Zifkin said. ''He's brought over some very good people with very good clients. He's bought over good people who are very compatible with our culture.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiatt replaced Arnold Rifkin, who represented Bruce Willis and others and who struggled in the mid-1990's to put William Morris on a par with Creative Artists and I.C.M. But Mr. Rifkin damaged his career at William Morris when he negotiating secretly for a top movie job at Sony in 1996: by all accounts the William Morris board never forgave him once the news was leaked. Top William Morris executives said they were also unhappy over Mr. Rifkin's inability to sign up high-priced stars.</p>
        <p>The agency shifts are taking place against a backdrop of unusually intense turmoil, even for a business where turmoil is the norm.</p>
        <p>''For years, the agency business was basically like a high school club -- you were judged how cool and important you were depending on what club had you as a member,'' said Jim Berkus, chairman of the United Talent Agency, a significant player now in the agency business. ''During the Stan Kamen era at William Morris, it was cool to be in the Morris club. During the height of Mike Ovitz's power, it was cool to be in the C.A.A. club.</p>
        <p>''But now there are four or five different agencies in town, and clients are less concerned about the name of the agency and the number of times the agents get their picture in Vanity Fair,'' he said. ''Clients are asking, 'What level of service am I getting for my commission?' '' (Clients generally pay 10 percent of their earnings to agents.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Berkus's United Talent Agency, once a secondary player, now has such high-priced clients as Jim Carrey, Harrison Ford, Kevin Costner, Madonna and Drew Carey and the television writer-producers David Chase (''The Sopranos'') and Dick Wolf (''Law and Order'').</p>
        <p>Other agents agree with Mr. Berkus.</p>
        <p>Although Creative Artists lost some clients after Mr. Ovitz abruptly quit in 1995 to briefly become president of the Walt Disney Company -- and there were predictions in newspapers that the agency would splinter -- it remains the No. 1 agency in Hollywood, representing stars like Tom Cruise, Will Smith, Meryl  Streep and Tom Hanks, and directors such as Steven Spielberg, Robert Zemeckis and Michael Mann.</p>
        <p>''We're the most stable game in town,'' said Bryan Lourd, one of the managing partners of Creative Artists. ''Five years ago, everyone said we were going down. Look at us.''</p>
        <p>Richard Lovett, the agency's president, echoed the view that the current warfare between William Morris and I.C.M. helps Creative Artists, which has deliberately sought to soften its image as the town's bully.</p>
        <p>''It was a company that people were afraid of,'' he said. ''It was a fear-based company. We don't believe in that kind of company. Maybe with the change of image it appears that we're not the fearsome machine we were. But we would argue that the results are better.''</p>
        <p>There are a number of factors behind the shifts in the agency business. Agencies are competitively struggling to gain a foothold in the Internet world, to satisfy cable television's hunger for material, to arrange film financing deals for clients' movies. The result is that smaller agencies like Endeavor and Broder-Kurland-Webb-Uffner are substantial players in the Hollywood arena, alongside the bigger ones.</p>
        <p>''The agency business has not changed so much over the years, but everything around us has changed,'' said Bob Broder, one of the founders of the respected agency with a heavy clientele of writers and directors.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Zimmer, a top agent at the United Talent Agency, was more blunt.</p>
        <p>''In a weird way, all of the major agencies are spending a lot of time coping with the same problems as opposed to each other as the problem,'' Mr. Zimmer said. Except in the case of the William Morris agency and International Creative Management.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
