<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Get New Offense As New Season Nears</title>
    <meta content="Y19ROU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFD61431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Get New Offense As New Season Nears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants players discuss their preparations for upcoming season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instead of draft picks and free-agent signings, much of the news of professional football this off-season has involved prosecutors, indictments and trials.</p>
        <p>With training camps to open next month, five members of the Giants -- Tiki Barber, Greg Comella, Howard Cross, Sam Garnes and Amani Toomer -- participated in a round-table discussion at The New York Times last week with Thomas George, who covers pro football, and other sports reporters and editors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Instead of draft picks and free-agent signings, much of the news of professional football this off-season has involved prosecutors, indictments and trials.</p>
        <p>With training camps to open next month, five members of the Giants -- Tiki Barber, Greg Comella, Howard Cross, Sam Garnes and Amani Toomer -- participated in a round-table discussion at The New York Times last week with Thomas George, who covers pro football, and other sports reporters and editors.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in the first of two articles, the Giants spoke at length about off-field violence, the public's perceptions of pro football players and related issues. Today, they discuss trends in offensive and defensive strategies and the Giants' plans for the coming season. Here are excerpts from their remarks.</p>
        <p>Q. What changes can we expect to see in teams' strategies this season?</p>
        <p>SAM GARNES -- You'll see more of a wide-open approach. Offense is going to try to get the ball in the end zone as many times as they can. In the old days, you'd try to shorten the game by running the ball and just playing defense. Nowadays, teams like St. Louis and Minnesota, that is the way things are going.</p>
        <p>AMANI TOOMER -- Yeah, you're going to see a lot more big-play offenses. This year 10-play drives aren't good; you've got to put the ball in the end zone quick and often.</p>
        <p>HOWARD CROSS -- Teams like St. Louis, Minnesota, Indianapolis and Washington, all the movement is basically stemming from what the defense did, where they have zone blitzes, they're dropping guys out, they're shuffling guys around. When you're in the middle of your snap count, they move people. Well, they just started moving the offense around to make them stop moving the defense around.</p>
        <p>GREG COMELLA -- The defenses have become so complex nowadays that it's not good enough just to line up and run what you're going to run, because of all different types of blitzes.</p>
        <p>Q. Is it harder for a team like the Giants to make this transition, because you have to play outdoors in November and December? --</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- I don't think weather has as much to do with the game as people have said in the past. The only thing that really would make a big impact on our game is the wind, where you couldn't really be able to throw the ball accurately.</p>
        <p>Q. Have the Giants adopted the plays that the top draft pick, Ron Dayne, ran at Wisconsin?</p>
        <p>TIKI BARBER -- I don't know if that's necessarily true. Ron Dayne was good at running between the tackles and breaking long runs. We've had plays like that in our system. I think it's more Ron Dayne will get those plays in our offense.</p>
        <p>But if we have a play where a running back needs to come out of the backfield and make a linebacker miss and run an out-route, he's not going to do it. Someone like me is going to do it. Offenses in general in the league are geared toward player-specific plays.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- You know, Ron's coming in at the perfect time, because we're evolving our offense. So we're running plays with men more upfield, more between the tackles. We were headed in that direction and Ron just happened to be perfect for it.</p>
        <p>We're evolving from more of a possession offense to a downfield, quick-strike offense. That's what everybody's doing. Since we play Dallas and Washington, and these teams will have success with a certain type of defense, we develop a certain type of offense to beat that.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- The reason why we've tailored it a little bit to Ron's style is if you look at St. Louis, if you look at Washington, if you look at any high-powered offense, they've had a balance, despite their complex schemes with the shifts and the motions, you know, they've had great running games.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- Nowadays they use the pass to open up their running game, and the passers used to use the running game to open the pass. So that's the difference right now.</p>
        <p>Q. You talk about a vertical game or quick strike. How do you attack the corner blitz?</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- You've got to show week after week that if a team does corner blitz, you can beat that corner blitz and that'll scare the defensive coordinators away from it.</p>
        <p>GARNES -- The N.F.L. goes through different periods. We started off in the earlier days, you know, defense was winning. Then you find a couple of offensive coordinators who know how to beat that same defense, then you go to that style of playing ball. And then after a while you find a defensive coordinator who can stop that. And it goes back and forth.</p>
        <p>Q. How will defenses respond?</p>
        <p>CROSS -- They'll be bringing a lot more secondary people. And it's not so much to stop a quarterback or to even hit him, it's to shorten the time of the throw. They're bringing guys to give quarterbacks less time. That's what the challenge is going to be: just to give yourself enough time to throw.</p>
        <p>Q. It sounds like offenses need excellent play callers to counteract what the defenses are trying to do.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- As important as that is, it's important to have a very knowledgeable quarterback, because if you have a quarterback who knows what he's doing, he can get you out of any bad play, based on what the defense is doing, and get you to a good play.</p>
        <p>One of the reasons why the secondary blitzes are getting so complex is because they break all the rules for the offense. Because if they bring a corner blitz, they're still dropping the same amount of guys -- except instead of it being a cornerback, it's a defensive end. It ends up being unnecessary for us to react the way we do, with those quick, quick passes.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Our guys are noticing that you have to be a lot smarter to play. You got to not just know your plays, you got to know your adjustments. There's a lot more study involved than there used to be.</p>
        <p>Q. With St. Louis and Tennessee getting to the Super Bowl and St. Louis winning it, does that give hope to other teams that they, too, can transform themselves quickly from losers to winners? --</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- Oh, yeah. Every coach around the league is using their example, that you can come from anywhere and be in the Super Bowl. So every team knows that when they go into their camp, if they do everything right, if they get their whole team believing in the system, they can go to the Super Bowl and win it. That's our hope.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- As you reach the professional level, the physical talent level per man, I would say, is pretty close to being similar. And the difference, I really believe, has to do with each athlete's mind. A team like St. Louis, they knew when they walked on the field last year that they were going to win. There wasn't doubt. They had the mind of a champion. And that's what propelled them to such success. And that's not to say that there aren't some guys that are just physically more gifted than others, because that's true, too. Deion Sanders -- I think everyone recognizes that he has some skills that few, if any, have. But for the most part it has more to do with guys' attitudes and guys' hearts.</p>
        <p>Q. What did St. Louis and Tennessee do last year that you admire?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- They won.</p>
        <p>TOOMER -- I liked that they were aggressive. They were aggressive on offense; they were aggressive on defense. They didn't change their style for any team. They just went through the whole league and kind of said: ''Look, this is what we're going to do. Can you guys stop it?'</p>
        <p>Q. The Redskins in particular appear to have been loading up for this season. As you watched them put their team together, were you envious?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- They're trying to make the Super Bowl next year, period. They're not building for the future; they're building for next year. And you respect that as a player, because everyone wants a ring. I don't do off-season conditioning for five hours a day just to go out there and play and say, ''Hey, I'm playing football.'' People want to win. They want to win the Super Bowl so they're remembered. That's what you play the game for.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- We got one thing we're playing for, that's the Super Bowl. That's it. We don't have any other objectives. That's why guys love to play so much. Because this is the only time we'll have in our lives where we'll get to have something so close with a group of people that we're all striving for one major goal. It happens once a year. Super Bowl. One game, it's all or nothing.</p>
        <p>Q. How real was the apparent divisiveness in the Giants' locker room last year, when some defensive players criticized the offense?</p>
        <p>BARBER -- You know, we weren't doing our job, and they had a right to say we weren't doing it. But it wasn't like we hated each other. I mean, we're a team. We were working toward the same goal, they just wanted us to work better.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you head into the new season thinking that the offense will finally come alive? Or is that an illusion?</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- I'm really excited about the offense.</p>
        <p>BARBER -- It's brand new. It's not the same thing.</p>
        <p>CROSS -- Put it like this, it's new to everybody. We're all learning and everything's new and this is going to take some study, but it's going to work out. I believe it's going to be a really big thing.</p>
        <p>COMELLA -- It gets back to what I was saying earlier -- it's important what comes from inside of each one of us. You can implement the most complex offense or defense in the world, but if you can't get a hungry bunch of athletes out there on the field who are willing to bust their butt every play and lay it all on the line, then it's not going to matter what you install. You got to have guys that are hungry, ambitious and willing to work and pay the price for success.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
