<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Pragmatism in South Africa's Foreign Policy Disappoints Some Old Supporters</title>
    <meta content="Y19ZIM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">South Africa-International Relations-Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mbeki, Thabo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mandela, Nelson R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFD61431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Pragmatism in South Africa's Foreign Policy Disappoints Some Old Supporters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>HARARE, Zimbabwe, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South African Pres Thabo Mbeki, year after succeeding Nelson Mandela, is increasingly embracing pragmatic foreign policy seemingly driven as much by national interest as by humanitarian principle; relations with Zimbabwe cited; as Zimbabwe lurches toward parliamentary elections and growing number of opposition party supporters are killed, beaten and intimidated, Mbeki government has been strangely silent; has failed to condemn Pres Robert Mugabe who is widely blamed for instigating and condoning worst spate of political violence in decade; Mbeki has praised Mugabe in public while prodding him in private--treading carefully with significant trading partner and ally and ignoring protests from domestic and international human rights activists; analysts expect to see more behind-the-scenes negotiating and and less tongue-lashing from continent's biggest economic and military force; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As waves of political violence and lawlessness wash across this country, the people here look south for hope. There, at the foot of the continent, sits South Africa, the beacon of democracy and the uncontested power of sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
        <p>The former South African president, Nelson Mandela, cast his moral mantle over the continent. His successor, Thabo Mbeki, seemed to continue that policy, proclaiming the dawning of an ''African renaissance'' in which leaders would no longer tolerate despots or ignore the cries of the weak and oppressed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As waves of political violence and lawlessness wash across this country, the people here look south for hope. There, at the foot of the continent, sits South Africa, the beacon of democracy and the uncontested power of sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
        <p>The former South African president, Nelson Mandela, cast his moral mantle over the continent. His successor, Thabo Mbeki, seemed to continue that policy, proclaiming the dawning of an ''African renaissance'' in which leaders would no longer tolerate despots or ignore the cries of the weak and oppressed.</p>
        <p>Yet, as Zimbabwe lurches toward  parliamentary elections next weekend and growing numbers of opposition party supporters have been beaten, killed and intimidated, South Africa remains remarkably silent.</p>
        <p>It has not condemned President Robert Mugabe, 76, who is widely blamed for condoning or instigating the worst political clashes here in more than a decade. Instead, Mr. Mbeki praises Mr. Mugabe in public and prods him in private, treading carefully with a significant trading partner and ally and ignoring protests from human rights activists here and abroad.</p>
        <p>One year after he inherited the reins of power from Nelson Mandela, Mr. Mbeki is increasingly embracing a pragmatic foreign policy seemingly driven as much by national interest as by humanitarian principle.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, he has pledged soldiers to keep peace in Congo, sent helicopters to rescue Mozambicans from the floods and traveled to the West as a champion of debt relief, foreign investment and poverty reduction for his struggling continent.</p>
        <p>But in December, Mr. Mbeki declined to meet one-on-one with the Dalai Lama, in part because some  officials feared that a meeting might endanger South Africa's budding economic relations with China. And this month, the Mbeki government drew sharp criticism from Amnesty International, the human rights group, for considering arms sales to the Chinese despite that country's spotty human rights record.</p>
        <p>As South Africa's post-apartheid democracy flexes its diplomatic muscles in a world that looks more and more toward Africa for solutions to African problems, analysts say they expect to see more behind-the-scenes negotiating and less tongue-lashing from the continent's biggest economic and military force.</p>
        <p>''Mandela really used his presidency as a bully pulpit,'' said Chris Landsberg, a lecturer in international relations at the University of the Witswatersrand in Johannesburg. ''Thabo will articulate the importance of those same norms, democracy, good governance, the rule of law. What he will not do is mention names.</p>
        <p>''He won't go to Washington and single out Mugabe publicly. And in the future, I think we're going to see more instead of less of this quiet diplomacy.''</p>
        <p>It is a strategy pursued by many powerful nations as they strive to influence, rather than alienate, ideologically wayward but strategically important leaders and countries.</p>
        <p>While opposition party leaders here have condemned Mr. Mbeki for negotiating quietly with Mr. Mugabe and American, British and other European officials to resolve the crisis, Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott praised Mr. Mbeki's handling of the situation during a visit to South Africa last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mbeki's strategy is not very popular among ordinary people here in Zimbabwe's capital. These days, Mr. Mugabe's support is waning in cities like this one, and his campaign rally on Saturday drew an appreciably smaller crowd than the one held by the opposition today.</p>
        <p>But South African officials say they have little choice. Mr. Mugabe is widely viewed as a proud and mercurial leader who responds poorly to public criticism. They say they cannot afford to lose leverage with such an important neighbor.</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe is South Africa's largest regional trading partner, although exports to Zimbabwe account for only about 3.5 percent of its total trade. And Mr. Mugabe, a staunch supporter of the South African anti-apartheid struggle, remains a key player in southern Africa. Alienating him, officials say, could threaten regional trade agreements and peace efforts in Congo.</p>
        <p>So in April, Mr. Mbeki told Mr. Mugabe privately to tone down the heated rhetoric, end the violence, hold free and fair elections and obey the rule of law, South African officials say. In return, Mr. Mbeki promised to negotiate with the West to free funds for land redistribution and to argue Zimbabwe's case with officials from the International Monetary Fund, which is withholding financial support.</p>
        <p>The strategy has had some success. Mr. Mugabe did agree to allow international observers to monitor the parliamentary elections, scheduled for Saturday and Sunday. Donors have agreed in principle to finance land reform. But the violence has only gotten worse, leaving the opposition here feeling betrayed.</p>
        <p>Since March, at least 26 people have been killed and 150 injured, most of them black supporters of the new opposition party, the Movement for Democratic Change. But during a visit to Zimbabwe last month, Mr. Mbeki did not mention the attacks. Instead, he praised Mr. Mugabe for his past support.</p>
        <p>''I am pleased to take this opportunity publicly to salute President Mugabe, the rest of the leadership and the people of Zimbabwe for what they did to ensure our liberation from apartheid tyranny,'' Mr. Mbeki said in a speech at the opening of the Zimbabwe Trade Show in Bulawayo, while members of the opposition shook their heads in disbelief.</p>
        <p>''South Africa provided moral leadership to the region under President Nelson Mandela,'' said Welshman Ncube, the secretary general of the Movement for Democratic Change. ''We looked to South Africa in admiration and hope. It is a grave disservice to the people of Zimbabwe and the region that they align themselves with despots.''</p>
        <p>South African officials, acknowledging that Mr. Mugabe has not responded as Zimbabwe's opposition had hoped, contend that there would have been no progress at all if he had publicly rebuked Mr. Mugabe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandela, on the other hand, has spoken out about Zimbabwe. But even Mr. Mandela, who is celebrated as one of the world's pre-eminent moral voices, had to juggle humanitarian principle and national interest.</p>
        <p>In 1997, for instance, Mr. Mandela decided to close South Africa's embassy in Taiwan, a country considered supportive of the anti-apartheid struggle, a prelude to establishing full diplomatic ties with the China. Another longtime supporter with a poor human rights record, Fidel Castro, kept Mr. Mandela's friendship.</p>
        <p>For similar reasons, Mr. Mbeki's government quietly allowed the former Ethiopian dictator, Mengistu Haile Mariam, to get medical treatment in South Africa last year while rights activists angrily clamored for his extradition. Mr. Mengistu, another supporter of the battle against apartheid, is wanted in Ethiopia on genocide charges. The South African government said it received no formal extradition request.</p>
        <p>South Africa is still feeling its way in foreign policy as it reaches beyond its borders after decades of apartheid-era isolation.</p>
        <p>''We may be wrong,'' said Mr. Mbeki, reflecting on his government's Zimbabwe strategy in an interview with foreign journalists last month. ''I mean, somebody may say that perhaps we'd produce results by shouting, denouncing. I don't know.</p>
        <p>''But this is our neighbor,'' he said.  ''We have to live with the Zimbabweans forever here. So let's end this violence. But let's look for a cooperative approach.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
