<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="19DIAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D61431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I was at a Midtown florist shop, waiting for my wife's birthday bouquet to be completed, when a New York City firefighter in full dress uniform asked if his arrangement of a dozen red roses could take precedence. He explained that he was running late for a date to meet his girlfriend on the observation deck of the Empire State Building.</p>
        <p>He said they were fans of the 1994 Warren Beatty and Annette Bening movie, ''Love Affair,'' in which a key event was a meeting at the Empire State. That day was his girlfriend's birthday and he was going to pop the question -- the engagement ring was in his pocket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>I was at a Midtown florist shop, waiting for my wife's birthday bouquet to be completed, when a New York City firefighter in full dress uniform asked if his arrangement of a dozen red roses could take precedence. He explained that he was running late for a date to meet his girlfriend on the observation deck of the Empire State Building.</p>
        <p>He said they were fans of the 1994 Warren Beatty and Annette Bening movie, ''Love Affair,'' in which a key event was a meeting at the Empire State. That day was his girlfriend's birthday and he was going to pop the question -- the engagement ring was in his pocket.</p>
        <p>I got a lump in my throat. I explained that the original 1957 movie ''An Affair to Remember,'' with Cary Grant and Deborah Kerr, played an integral part in the romance and engagement of myself and my wife over 42 years ago. I wished him luck and off he went. An incurable romantic, I wonder if she said yes.</p>
        <p>PETER MORRONE</p>
        <p>THE URBAN RITE</p>
        <p>Each man worships at a temple of his own</p>
        <p>You see him at the corner of the street</p>
        <p>His back toward the crowd for privacy</p>
        <p>No bell, candle or chorus beckons him</p>
        <p>Mere greed or need is his summons</p>
        <p>To the ritual of diminishing the Principal</p>
        <p>In the ceremony at the feet of the Great A.T.M.</p>
        <p>DORIS L. MEYER</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>May 21, 2000. The first baseball game of my son, Marcus, almost 3 -- and my birthday. A great combination to start, but hold on, this really gets going. We begin at the ticket line at Shea Stadium. A lovely couple in their mid-40's walk up to us. ''Would you like these box seats?'' they ask. ''We have a few extra.'' Happy day! Upon entrance to the ballpark, we are handed Mets jerseys because  it's Mets Jersey Day. Happy, happy day! We go get a hot dog. A fellow asks if we want to sign up for a credit card and get a free mitt. Thank you. Happier day! We go back to our seats and my son laments, ''How come they're not hitting me the ball, Daddy?''</p>
        <p>''You have to have patience,'' I say. ''You just be ready.'' Fifth inning. Mets tie the score. Edgardo Alfonzo steps up to the plate, hits a pop fly down the first-base line and -- you guessed it -- we got it. Marcus in my lap and we caught the ball! The crowd went wild. Happiest birthday ever!</p>
        <p>P.S. Oh, yeah, Mets get the winning run, bottom of the ninth.</p>
        <p>DAVID KENER</p>
        <p>Ron Tomme always liked the story told to him by an actress on one of the major soap operas at that time. Her role on the soap was that of a Broadway star. One day, shopping in Bloomingdale's, she was approached by a fan. ''Tell me,'' the fan said, ''are you an actress in real life?''</p>
        <p>Looking out the window of his Upper West Side apartment one recent morning, Harold S. Spitzer noticed a man on the other side of the street pulling a handcart loaded with new telephone directories. The man passed an oversized carton on its side, the rags and paper around it signifying that it was the abode of a homeless person. The man stopped, looked back and then took a telephone directory from the top of the pile, placed it gently in front of the open carton and continued on his way.</p>
        <p>Still another problem for the M.T.A. to solve: Sara Landis was on a bus crossing 23rd Street during a rush hour. The bus hit every red light and traffic was at a standstill. As she got up for her stop, she said sympathetically to the driver, ''You caught all the stops, didn't you?''</p>
        <p>''No problem,'' he replied, and then added, ''it's all the people getting on and off that slows me down.'' She got off -- fast!</p>
        <p>DREAMING UP A DINNER</p>
        <p>I'd like to give a dinner</p>
        <p>for the next generation</p>
        <p>and serve them large helpings</p>
        <p>of food for thought,</p>
        <p>and some soul food, too.</p>
        <p>Balanced portions of</p>
        <p>pride and humility,</p>
        <p>passion and restraint,</p>
        <p>daring and caution</p>
        <p>would be ladled onto their plates.</p>
        <p>I would pass large bowls</p>
        <p>of compassion, thoughtfulness</p>
        <p>and generosity,</p>
        <p>insisting that everyone partake.</p>
        <p>I would urge them to sample</p>
        <p>new approaches to old problems</p>
        <p>and to try appreciation</p>
        <p>for everything they take for granted.</p>
        <p>And I would pack a doggy bag if all of this</p>
        <p>is too heavy to digest at one meal.</p>
        <p>MARY ANN GAUGER</p>
        <p>The recent news article about boys' superior knowledge of geography reminded Susan Jacobs of a conversation she overheard while working out at a health club. One of the young trainers, obviously not a native New Yorker, asked his client for suggestions on where he should take his parents when they visited. The client ran through the usual tourist sites, evoking little interest, and finally he mentioned a cruise on the Circle Line.</p>
        <p>''What's that?'' the trainer asked. The client replied that it was a tour boat that circled Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''That's a great idea,'' the trainer exclaimed. ''I love boat rides. Will we be sailing on the Atlantic Ocean or the Pacific?''</p>
        <p>Not all boys know geography!</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>When I was 18, I got my first job, at the Woolworth Building at 233 Broadway at Park Place. My salary was $10 a week and I worked as a file clerk on the 10th floor. I lived with my parents and eight brothers and sisters in a tenement in Brooklyn and we had just the bare necessities of life. Each day as I entered the Woolworth Building I stood in amazement, admiring the mosaic ceiling and the beautiful woodwork.</p>
        <p>Recently, at the age of 88, I again came to the Woolworth Building, this time with a different reaction -- much pride and a full heart. My eldest son, Bruce Clark, a lawyer, occupies the entire 36th floor!</p>
        <p>ROSALIND CLARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
