<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jackson Lasts in League of Youth</title>
    <meta content="19PACE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DC1531F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jackson Lasts in League of Youth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>EL SEGUNDO, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Basketball column discusses career of Indiana Pacers guard Mark Jackson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Jackson attended the Oscar De La Hoya-Shane Mosley fight on Saturday night, trying to blow off steam with teammates before Game 6 of the N.B.A. finals. Among those accompanying the 35-year-old point guard to the Staples Center were Jonathan Bender, a willowy 19-year-old, who last June was attending his senior prom, and Al Harrington, 20, two years from high school.</p>
        <p>''I got them popcorn and those cinnamon churros, or whatever you call them,'' Jackson said. ''They were excited. But no Coke. Water instead. I didn't want them to have too much sugar.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Jackson attended the Oscar De La Hoya-Shane Mosley fight on Saturday night, trying to blow off steam with teammates before Game 6 of the N.B.A. finals. Among those accompanying the 35-year-old point guard to the Staples Center were Jonathan Bender, a willowy 19-year-old, who last June was attending his senior prom, and Al Harrington, 20, two years from high school.</p>
        <p>''I got them popcorn and those cinnamon churros, or whatever you call them,'' Jackson said. ''They were excited. But no Coke. Water instead. I didn't want them to have too much sugar.''</p>
        <p>The responsible patriarch of the Indiana Pacers roster spoke on Father's Day, slightly more than a year after his own father died. Someone asked Jackson if the Pacers' attempt to come back from a three-games-to-one deficit in the National Basketball Association finals was the hardest thing he ever had to do on a court.</p>
        <p>''Playing after losing my father,'' he said. ''That was simply the hardest. If I look back and think how I did it, it had nothing to do with me. It was all God. There were times when I wanted to roll over and put my head under the pillow.''</p>
        <p>But Jackson gathered himself and forged on. As he has been doing for much of the last four or five seasons, he lived on instincts, skill and smarts to keep up with the N.B.A.'s kids and compensate for his lack of athleticism. Today, one of the few pass-first point guards left in the league is two victories from a championship, blemishes in his game and all.</p>
        <p>Thirteen years after he was drafted out of St. John's, you wonder which odds should have been longer: on Jackson playing this long or the Pacers becoming the first team in finals history to erase a 3-1 deficit and win in seven.</p>
        <p>''If you leave it to the critics, probably about the same,'' he said through a half-smile.</p>
        <p>Some people have referred to him as a slow-footed point guard. ''Some people even say a very slow-footed point guard,'' Jackson said. ''When you look around and guys are on vacation now that don't have half as many question marks as I have -- and to know that God has put me in a position to have a Game 6 and to be the maestro of a championship-caliber team, a guy that's as limited as me, I can't help but thank him.''</p>
        <p>Jackson is a free agent after this season, and there is no guarantee he will return to the Pacers -- although putting the floor-leader duties exclusively in Travis Best's hands does not seem like the wisest move Indiana could make in the off-season.</p>
        <p>Even with his physical limitations, Jackson knows how to find the open man, whether it is Reggie Miller materializing on the perimeter from the morass in the paint or Jalen Rose sneaking along the baseline. A prospective coaching career -- Rick Pitino recently said he thought Jackson would become the next great young coach -- will most likely be put on hold for at least two seasons.</p>
        <p>The competition and the kids still enrapture Jackson.</p>
        <p>''For the state of basketball in general, it's a tremendous lesson,'' he said. ''Rather than working on some things that can get you endorsements and praise, work on some things that can get you here in June. Work on some things that's going to get you a ring. Work on some things that can separate you from the pack as a winner. Be students of the game. I learned that going to college and watching Chris Mullin every single day.</p>
        <p>''Now I watch guys run around like chickens without heads and I realize that was me once.''</p>
        <p>The day before Game 6, Jackson recalled draft day in 1987, when he was picked in the first round by the Knicks. ''You're thinking, 'I made it,' '' he said. ''I didn't put a timetable on myself because a lot of people didn't think I would make it. I didn't think about playing 13 years. I was just tickled I actually arrived. I wanted to prolong it as long as I actually could.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''It's been a great ride. To know there's still some gas left in the tank makes it more enjoyable.''</p>
        <p>Jackson says the Pacers ''rebuked the demons'' in Game 5, in which the Pacers annihilated the Lakers, 120-87. He likes his team's resilience, its ability to fight back.</p>
        <p>''For a few years now, when our back is against the wall, we've responded,'' he said. ''And we've been a lot of places. So this isn't anything that stands out right now. This isn't nothing new to me or this basketball team. And if I have to go down swinging with a bunch of guys, this is the group I want to go down with.''</p>
        <p>His three children were back in Indiana and could speak to their father yesterday only by telephone. He would have to make do with Bender and Harrington, the Pacers kids he took to the fight on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>''It reminded me of what it's going to take in this series,'' Jackson said of Mosley's thrilling victory by split decision. ''If you want it, rather than sitting back, dancing and jabbing, you got to take it.''</p>
        <p>It would be some finish, watching the Pacers move the ball for two more games and blend together seamlessly, five as one. Knocking off the heavily favored Lakers of Shaq and Kobe would be an amazing story, almost as amazing as a very slow-footed point guard playing 13 years.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
