<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bad Weather Means Monday At Pocono 500</title>
    <meta content="Y19AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pocono 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2D71431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bad Weather Means Monday At Pocono 500</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>LONG POND, Pa., June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rain causes one day delay in running of Pocono 500 auto race; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For only the second time in 27 years, a Nascar event was postponed here when the Pocono 500 Winston Cup race was called off today because of persistent rain and enveloping fog.</p>
        <p>The race was rescheduled for Monday at 10 a.m. by race teams eager to get to the circuit's next stop, in Sonoma, Calif., and before the crowd thins out because of the beginning of the work week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For only the second time in 27 years, a Nascar event was postponed here when the Pocono 500 Winston Cup race was called off today because of persistent rain and enveloping fog.</p>
        <p>The race was rescheduled for Monday at 10 a.m. by race teams eager to get to the circuit's next stop, in Sonoma, Calif., and before the crowd thins out because of the beginning of the work week.</p>
        <p>''I guess this just prolongs the agony,'' said Larry McReynolds, crew chief for the Lowe's Chevrolet team driven by Mike Skinner, which will start in the seventh position Monday morning. ''Somebody stuck another pin in the voodoo doll. You really don't change that much here for the weather conditions. I don't know what we'll do different tomorrow than we did today.''</p>
        <p>Nascar officials waited 2 hours 23 minutes past the 1 p.m. start time before deciding that a layer of fog obscuring parts of the two-and-a-half-mile speedway compounded the danger on an already slick racetrack.</p>
        <p>In July 1979, the early summer Pocono Winston Cup race was rescheduled for the following day because of rain and was won by Cale Yarborough in a memorable duel with Richard Petty.</p>
        <p>Winston Cup teams will now be pressed to get to the Save Mart/Kragen 350 next Sunday at Sears Point Raceway in Sonoma.</p>
        <p>Peter Jellen, who is charged with getting the cars and equipment to the West Coast for the Winston Cup points leader, Bobby Labonte, says the quick turnaround means a tense cross-country drive. ''You can't have a flat, you can't have scale trouble, can't have truck trouble,'' Jellen said.</p>
        <p>When the flag drops on the Pocono 500, Rusty Wallace will lead the 43-car field to the green flag. He turned a lap in 52.440 seconds, a record average speed of 171.625 miles an hour, to win his fifth pole of the season.</p>
        <p>Labonte's teammate, Tony Stewart, will start from the ninth position and try to win his third race in a row.</p>
        <p>John Andretti, a Lehigh Valley native, will start second in his homecoming race. His hopes are tempered, however, by the fact that last year in the two races here he was knocked out by accidents.</p>
        <p>''Why be too optimistic?'' he said. ''I think if we see the checkered flag, it will probably be a bonus.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
