<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Competition Influences Judgment</title>
    <meta content="19VIDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Post</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDA1431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Competition Influences Judgment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Failure of New York Post and five news programs to blur faces of women shown stripped by marauding group of men in Central Park, New York City, shows how competitive heat can overtake news organizations in 24-hour news cycle and how questionable ethical decision made by one outlet can influence others; decision to run identifiable images despite policies by most news organizations that greatly limit identification of sexual assault victims has led to debate in some newsrooms and angered women's rights groups; most television stations responded to complaints by pulling unaltered pictures and Post apologized; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scenes, in some form or another, appeared all over television and in the newspapers: lurid images from amateur videotape showing young women having water poured on them, being groped and having their shirts ripped off by a marauding group of men who sexually assaulted at least 50 women near the southern end of Central Park.</p>
        <p>Some news organizations blurred the faces of the victims. But on five news programs and in one newspaper, The New York Post, the women were clearly identifiable, several with their shirts taken off and others with no clothes at all during the attacks after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade on June 11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scenes, in some form or another, appeared all over television and in the newspapers: lurid images from amateur videotape showing young women having water poured on them, being groped and having their shirts ripped off by a marauding group of men who sexually assaulted at least 50 women near the southern end of Central Park.</p>
        <p>Some news organizations blurred the faces of the victims. But on five news programs and in one newspaper, The New York Post, the women were clearly identifiable, several with their shirts taken off and others with no clothes at all during the attacks after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade on June 11.</p>
        <p>Most news organizations have policies that greatly limit the identification of sexual assault victims because some view the crimes as having a stigma attached to them and because victims are less likely to come forward if they believe the crimes will be made public.</p>
        <p>But the coverage last week showed how competitive heat can overtake news organizations in a 24-hour news cycle and how questionable ethical decisions made by one outlet can influence others.</p>
        <p>The decision to run the identifiable images led to debate in some newsrooms and angered several women's rights groups, which complained that showing the women's faces only added to their humiliation.</p>
        <p>''It was a traumatic situation, and there is a stigma attached to sex crimes,'' said Nancy Millar, the president of the National Organization for Women's New York City chapter. ''Running their faces is just adding insult to injury.''</p>
        <p>After an onslaught of complaints, most television stations pulled the unaltered pictures and The Post apologized in a statement.</p>
        <p>The amateur videotape was bought by, or given to, at least five New York news stations last Monday afternoon, the day after the attacks, which had begun to capture international attention. That night, four stations -- WNBC, WABC, WCBS and the Fox affiliate, WNYW -- ran the tape.</p>
        <p>WABC and WNBC used clips that primarily showed the attackers. The faces of the women could not be seen. But WCBS and WNYW aired more graphic pictures in which the nudity was blurred but many of the women's faces were left unaltered.</p>
        <p>In one instance, WNYW played video in slow motion of a woman with no shirt on, crouched behind a wall, screaming and trying to hide.</p>
        <p>Paula Madison, WNBC's news director and vice president, said she had received the first tape about 4 p.m. last Monday, but decided to withhold many of the more graphic details until after the tapes could be properly edited.</p>
        <p>''I figured I could get beat, but that is O.K.,'' she said. She added that competition could not drive every decision or it would ''erode the public's confidence in your ability to tell the news in a comprehensive and responsible fashion.''</p>
        <p>But interest in the story continued to rise. Last Tuesday morning, the story appeared on the front pages of The New York Times, The Post and The Daily News. None of the newspapers used images in which the women could be identified.</p>
        <p>But WCBS, WNYW, the WB affiliate WPIX and the UPN affiliate WWOR continued to run the tape  without blurring the victims' faces. That morning, producers at New York 1, the city's 24-hour news channel, received a tape of the events -- more than 10 hours after it first appeared on other stations -- and quickly scanned it and placed it on the air, showing close-ups of two of the women's faces.</p>
        <p>Minutes later, a viewer wrote an e-mail message to New York 1 that read: ''These women had already been publicly humiliated once -- why humiliate them again by putting their faces on television, showing them sobbing and trying to cover themselves?''</p>
        <p>The video ran about three times that morning before Steve Paulus, New York 1's senior vice president and general manager, pulled it and ordered the women's faces blurred.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to be competitive with the other guys,'' said Peter Landis, the news director at New York 1. ''There was a bad judgment call to put it on the air before upper news management determined how to present it properly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulus sent out a memo in the afternoon reiterating the station's policy against identifying victims of sex crimes. It also said that what other stations were doing ''doesn't matter to us; we shouldn't have used it.''</p>
        <p>But the competitive pressure lingered and also influenced The Post, . That afternoon, hoping to beat out other print competition, The Post obtained images from its corporate cousin, British Sky Broadcasting. And on Wednesday morning, the newspaper published three pictures in which victims could clearly be identified, including the woman cowering behind the wall.</p>
        <p>''Since these images were played many times on television, we felt there was little to be gained by altering them,'' Xana Antunes, The Post's editor, said in an interview on Wednesday afternoon. Ms. Antunes added that the paper was careful not to print the names or addresses of the victims but spent little time worrying about the images.</p>
        <p>''On further reflection, we will take additional steps to protect the victims' identities,'' she said in a statement released later that afternoon.</p>
        <p>And TV stations' news programs had all taken the unaltered images off the air by Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In a brief conversation, Susan Sullivan, news director at WNYW, said that in the heat of competition her producers had not thought about editing the tape to protect the identities of the victims.</p>
        <p>''As soon I saw the tape run, I caught it, and we began obscuring the faces,'' Ms. Sullivan said.</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
