<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Complete Financial Picture on One Site</title>
    <meta content="19BANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Financial Services Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chase Manhattan Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yodlee.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5D91431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Complete Financial Picture on One Site</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Banks and brokerage firms are racing to offer single online sites where customers can find up-to-date data on all their accounts at range of institutions; big financial firms that once opposed account aggregation service as threat to customer privacy, are now embracing it as convenience for customers and powerful tool for building own business; Chase Manhattan Bank plans to team up with Yodlee.com to offer service free to its online customers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Banks and brokerage firms are racing to offer the newest new thing in online financial services: a single place where customers can find up-to-date information about all of their  accounts at a range of institutions.</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, big financial firms saw this innovation, known as account aggregation, as a threat to their customers' privacy and financial security. But now, fearing an onslaught of competition on the Internet, they are embracing it as a convenience for customers and a powerful tool for building their own business. Instead of warning against the service, banks are now telling their customers to be wary of obtaining such services from anyone but them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Banks and brokerage firms are racing to offer the newest new thing in online financial services: a single place where customers can find up-to-date information about all of their  accounts at a range of institutions.</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, big financial firms saw this innovation, known as account aggregation, as a threat to their customers' privacy and financial security. But now, fearing an onslaught of competition on the Internet, they are embracing it as a convenience for customers and a powerful tool for building their own business. Instead of warning against the service, banks are now telling their customers to be wary of obtaining such services from anyone but them.</p>
        <p>Chase Manhattan Bank, hoping to get a head start on its traditional competitors, is expected to announce today that it is teaming up with a year-old Internet-based company called Yodlee.com to introduce free account-aggregation services later this year for Chase's 30 million online customers. Other major banks and brokerage firms, including Merrill Lynch &amp; Company and the PaineWebber Group, are considering offering similar services through Yodlee or one of about a dozen other companies.</p>
        <p>Most of the new services are expected to be free to consumers, at least initially.</p>
        <p>These firms are reacting to the Internet-based businesses that are offering account aggregation with the hope of serving as a financial home page for consumers. Ameritrade Holdings, which operates a popular online brokerage, has been offering account aggregation at its Onmoney.com site on the Web, and earlier this month, America Online announced an alliance with Yodlee to provide a similar service for AOL's 22 million subscribers.</p>
        <p>So far, fewer than 300,000 people have registered for account aggregation, which compiles a variety of  information from different sources, from savings and checking balances at a bank to the value of stocks and bonds in brokerage accounts to the frequent-flier miles customers have accumulated with airlines. But financial industry executives predict that many more people will sign up for the service as major firms demonstrate their acceptance of the technology behind it.</p>
        <p>Using a process known as ''screen scraping,'' companies like Yodlee gain electronic access, usually overnight, to their customers' accounts at various financial institutions and download them into a central file. In the morning, a user can log in and get a current snapshot of her finances on one computer screen, or even on the screen of a hand-held device like a Palm Pilot or a wireless phone.</p>
        <p>The trade-off for that convenience is that customers must surrender the electronic passwords to all of their financial accounts. That is an exchange that some privacy advocates warn against. Even purveyors of the service acknowledge that most people are uneasy about disclosing that information, especially to a company they had never heard of a year ago.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing for someone to go to a start-up with an unusual name like Yodlee and ask them to keep all of their personal financial data,'' said Anil Arora, chief executive of Yodlee, based in Sunnyvale, Calif. ''It's another thing to go to a company like Chase that you already use as your primary financial company.''</p>
        <p>Bruce Zimmerman, a senior vice president of Chase, said that in a survey, about 45 percent of consumers said they would use an account-aggregation service if it were provided by a financial institution they trusted. ''We know that not everyone is going to use this tomorrow, but we think customers want this service and the time is right for us to take a leadership position in offering it,'' Mr. Zimmerman said.</p>
        <p>Account aggregation could prove very valuable to banks like Chase. Financial institutions want a complete picture of their customers' finances. They want to know what assets -- and debts -- their customers have elsewhere, both to protect themselves and to create opportunities to sell more products, like credit cards, loans and mutual funds.</p>
        <p>When its customers start using account aggregation, Chase will get a peek at their outside holdings, like a brokerage account at Merrill Lynch or use of an American Express card, and will be able to use that information to create solicitations to them. Chase will apply its own standards for privacy and security to the service, even though it will be operated by Yodlee, Mr. Zimmerman said.</p>
        <p>If customers do not want to receive pitches for credit cards or other products, he said, they can choose to be removed from mailing and calling lists. ''You have the right at any point to say, 'Do not call me, do not make me an offer,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Some financial industry executives say that using account aggregation as a tool for aggressive cross-selling could backfire. ''The firms that approach it that way are going to lose,'' said Marten Hoekstra, director of marketing at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>Instead, financial firms should treat account aggregation as a necessary convenience that all customers will soon demand and as a critical offering to cement relationships with customers, he said. Within a few years, brokerage firms will be using this innovation to offer to advise customers on the management of all of their assets, whether they are held in banks or at competing brokerages, Mr. Hoekstra said.</p>
        <p>PaineWebber is negotiating with Yodlee and several of its competitors, but it has not settled on a partner for the account aggregation services it plans to offer because the technology has not been perfected, Mr. Hoekstra said. ''It's a must-do as soon as it's reliable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch already offers an early version of account aggregation, for a monthly fee, to its wealthiest customers, those with at least $5 million invested at the firm, through Greentrak, a small, private company in New Rochelle, N.Y. The new management team for Merrill's brokerage operation is considering whether to offer a simpler form of account aggregation, through an Internet-based service like Yodlee's, to all of its customers, according to people at the firm.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who's in the financial services area wants to try to own the total financial relationship with clients,'' said Lon Massingil, executive vice president of Greentrak. ''That's the race that's going on now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
