<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shades of McCarthy! Antigay Bias in 50's Hollywood, Played for Laughs</title>
    <meta content="19JACK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Straight-Jacket (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4D91431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shades of McCarthy! Antigay Bias in 50's Hollywood, Played for Laughs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews play Straight-Jacket, written and directed by Richard Day, at Playhouse 91; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Straight-Jacket,'' a comedy by Richard Day, is set in Hollywood in the 1950's, a setting it uses to suggest a parallel between antigay bias and the House Un-American Activities Committee. The show, which opened yesterday at Playhouse 91 on the Upper East Side, concerns a gay matinee idol who, to keep up appearances, is coerced by the head of a movie studio into marrying a ditzy secretary; at the same time the McCarthyites are threatening to shut down the studio unless a big name star confesses to being a Communist.</p>
        <p>It's the kind of loopy, contrived setup that a Capraesque touch, sophisticated and warmhearted, might exploit to advantage. But Mr. Day, a first-time playwright, has created a dull-witted script that exhausts any sympathy one might feel for his characters long before they are declared to live happily ever after. Compounding the problem, Mr. Day, a television producer and writer by trade, has directed his own script here, employing an unwieldy, twin-turntable set by Ray Recht, and a pacing that emphasizes exit lines before each of the many scene changes, as if the show were about to cut to a commercial. Gail Brassard's vivid costumes stand out as anomalously bright.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Straight-Jacket,'' a comedy by Richard Day, is set in Hollywood in the 1950's, a setting it uses to suggest a parallel between antigay bias and the House Un-American Activities Committee. The show, which opened yesterday at Playhouse 91 on the Upper East Side, concerns a gay matinee idol who, to keep up appearances, is coerced by the head of a movie studio into marrying a ditzy secretary; at the same time the McCarthyites are threatening to shut down the studio unless a big name star confesses to being a Communist.</p>
        <p>It's the kind of loopy, contrived setup that a Capraesque touch, sophisticated and warmhearted, might exploit to advantage. But Mr. Day, a first-time playwright, has created a dull-witted script that exhausts any sympathy one might feel for his characters long before they are declared to live happily ever after. Compounding the problem, Mr. Day, a television producer and writer by trade, has directed his own script here, employing an unwieldy, twin-turntable set by Ray Recht, and a pacing that emphasizes exit lines before each of the many scene changes, as if the show were about to cut to a commercial. Gail Brassard's vivid costumes stand out as anomalously bright.</p>
        <p>The details of the plot do not warrant critical recounting. Suffice it to say that the intention is broad satire, which takes the form of mere exaggeration, and that a celebrity's vanity, an innocent girl's naivete, a mogul's corruption, an agent's cynicism and a love object's good heart are pounded to extremes.</p>
        <p>The protagonist, Guy Stone (played by John Littlefield, who was cast, evidently, for his resemblance to Rock Hudson), is the embodiment of sex-obsessed promiscuity, which is communicated with a parade of smutty double-entendres and bluntly suggestive embraces. His wife, Sally (Carrie Preston), believes Guy's sudden declaration of love even though he has ignored her entirely until then, and she's blind to his homosexuality until she finds dirty magazines and an obscene sex toy hidden in the bedroom armoire. Her every aesthetic -- in clothing, home design, movies and music -- is held up to ridicule for its conventional artlessness.</p>
        <p>The studio executive (Mal Z. Lawrence), a manipulative penny pincher, is a Jew in hiding; he's changed his name to Goldbergini (yuk yuk), which serves only to illustrate how ham-handed attempts to send up foolish bias end up reinforcing it instead. And Rick (Adam Greer), the writer (and Communist -- such complications!) whom Guy falls for with no perceivable provocation, is wont to say things like, ''If you told me two months ago that the person keeping my faith in humanity alive would be Guy Stone. . . .''</p>
        <p>You can't help feeling for the actors, who are hard pressed to charm. With the exception of Jackie Hoffman, a veteran of Second City, the Chicago improvisational troupe, whose practiced comic hyperbole surfaces in her role as the agent, the cast seems perilously close to suffocation by stereotype. At one point Rick is at work on a new script, and Guy, looking over his shoulder, counsels him not to use the word ''sex''; the studio censors won't allow it. But Rick is a reluctant screenwriter, anyway.</p>
        <p>''It's a play,'' he tells Guy. ''You can say whatever you want.''</p>
        <p>Alas, 'tis true.</p>
        <p>STRAIGHT-JACKET</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Richard Day; sets by Ray Recht; costumes by Gail Brassard; lighting by F. Mitchell Dana; sound by Peter J. Fitzgerald; composer, Stephen Edwards; production stage manager, Tamara K. Heeschen; general manager, Soloway/Levy. Presented by Mike Sullo. At Playhouse 91, 316 East 91st Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ron Mathews (Trick, Mike, Jeff, Josh, Salvation Army man, furniture delivery man, Ray Verrine and Ron), John Littlefield (Guy), Jackie Hoffman (Jerry), Carrie Preston (Sally), Mal Z. Lawrence (Saul), Adam Greer (Rick) and Stevie Ray Dallimore (Freddie).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
