<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Park Rampage Stirs Anguish On 2 Fronts</title>
    <meta content="19MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDD1531F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Park Rampage Stirs Anguish On 2 Fronts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick column holds Central Park, New York City, attacks on women who were doused with water, stripped and groped by mob of men are gender-based hate crimes; holds women were also victims of some police officers who allegedly ignored reports of park rampage; holds police are trained to passivity in such situations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S reaction time to the violence in Central Park, mostly from two aggrieved quarters. From women, who ask: When will it end? From police officers, who ask: What do you expect of us?</p>
        <p>The women are pained that in the year 2000, they are still victimized, still objectified. Because -- make no mistake -- the crimes in Central Park were sexual assaults. Young men in a mob decided to have a good time -- by terrifying women. They chased and cornered them, doused them with water, stripped them, groped them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S reaction time to the violence in Central Park, mostly from two aggrieved quarters. From women, who ask: When will it end? From police officers, who ask: What do you expect of us?</p>
        <p>The women are pained that in the year 2000, they are still victimized, still objectified. Because -- make no mistake -- the crimes in Central Park were sexual assaults. Young men in a mob decided to have a good time -- by terrifying women. They chased and cornered them, doused them with water, stripped them, groped them.</p>
        <p>Look at the videotapes (a blessing, those tapes). See the joy of these young men. See them leering, laughing, having a grand time terrorizing women. And look at the screaming, cowering women on those videotapes; see the face of abject fear.</p>
        <p>What accounts for this terrible regression? asked one e-mailer. Would that it had been regression.</p>
        <p>''It's just never stopped,'' said Kathy Rodgers, president of the NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund. ''For all the efforts we've been making, we haven't solved the problem. These guys decided they wanted to have fun.</p>
        <p>''What is their idea of fun? To target women. It is gender-based violence. It really is a hate crime.</p>
        <p>''It's still out there. It's so ingrained. I think for sexual assaults, which are anything other than rape, people still think it's no big deal: 'Nothing happened to you, right? You didn't get raped?' ''</p>
        <p>Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx borough president, was outraged, in part because the violence took place in the aftermath of the Puerto Rican Day Parade. He spoke out and has taken some heat from other Puerto Rican New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''It's shocking to me why everybody is so skittish,'' he said. ''Haven't we all got our brains on straight? A lot of people don't want to know the facts. We have a responsibility as husbands and fathers and brothers to say, 'Wait a minute, this is not acceptable behavior, this is criminal behavior.' Why aren't we calling it what it is? It's a crime. A hate crime.''</p>
        <p>Puerto Rican men ''are not brought up this way,'' Mr. Ferrer added, denouncing the attackers -- some apparently Puerto Rican, some not -- as ''thugs.''</p>
        <p>He needn't have been defensive. This crime crosses ethnic, racial and class lines. Think Tailhook, Glen Ridge, St. John's, Woodstock '99. ''It's generation to generation, and it is slow to change,'' said Harriet Lessel, director of the New York City Alliance Against Sexual Assault.</p>
        <p>Is there a remedy? Ms. Rodgers is working on renewing federal financing for the Violence Against Women Act. Ms. Lessel wants society to think about the role men and women play in objectifying women in ads, movies, rap lyrics.</p>
        <p>Maybe the Central Park videotapes should be required viewing for all adolescents in the metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>Women were the victims not only of violent thugs but also of some police officers who, people have charged, ignored reports of the park rampage and of threatening behavior before and during the parade.</p>
        <p>THOSE complaints, now under investigation, did not surprise one veteran police officer who called to talk about police passivity, first citing rules. Then, what is probably the real reason:  self-preservation.</p>
        <p>''There's a standing order -- don't take action in a demonstration situation unless directed by a supervisor, except in an emergency,'' said the officer, who insisted that his name be withheld.</p>
        <p>Deputy Chief Thomas P. Fahey, a Police Department spokesman, called that ''categorically and patently untrue.''</p>
        <p>But the officer explained that there is a lot of subjectivity in police work: ''There are certain things cops know, from a sense of cop memory.'' He said he understood why some officers wrote citations for public drinking while others apparently looked the other way or did not look at all. ''Right now, there is paralysis in the department,'' the officer said, citing the police killings of the unarmed Amadou Diallo and Patrick M. Dorismond. ''You're never going to get in trouble by not doing anything.''</p>
        <p>''Think about it,'' the officer continued, calling the parade ''contained chaos,'' complicated by ethnic sensitivities. ''You have a million people there. Are you going to set this off? Are you the one who is going to precipitate a riot? The political fallout would be a career-ender. You'd be doing midnights in the Bronx.''</p>
        <p>''We have expectations from TV of what cops can do; it's not realistic,'' he said. ''What do we want from these guys?''</p>
        <p>Don't look for a theme here. There's just hurt and resentment, enough to last until the next New York trauma.</p>
        <p>METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
