<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fox's Good-Guy Image Now Has an Edge to It</title>
    <meta content="19LAKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DD1531F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fox's Good-Guy Image Now Has an Edge to It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of Los Angeles Lakers forward Rick Fox in NBA championship series against Indiana Pacers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charismatic, intelligent and blessed with a movie star's good looks, Los Angeles Lakers forward Rick Fox thinks he is made for Hollywood, even saying on occasion that he would be a star on the silver screen if he was not playing basketball.</p>
        <p>But in watching Fox play against the Indiana Pacers, many observers feel he is already acting out a character role in these National Basketball Association finals. His looks, his marriage to the singer and actress Vanessa Williams and his history of nonconfrontation in the N.B.A. are hard to reconcile with the way he is suddenly pushing around and challenging the Pacers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charismatic, intelligent and blessed with a movie star's good looks, Los Angeles Lakers forward Rick Fox thinks he is made for Hollywood, even saying on occasion that he would be a star on the silver screen if he was not playing basketball.</p>
        <p>But in watching Fox play against the Indiana Pacers, many observers feel he is already acting out a character role in these National Basketball Association finals. His looks, his marriage to the singer and actress Vanessa Williams and his history of nonconfrontation in the N.B.A. are hard to reconcile with the way he is suddenly pushing around and challenging the Pacers.</p>
        <p>''I've had to answer some of those kinds of questions: 'Where is this coming from? You were a model citizen and a complete angel for 10 years,' '' Fox said today at the Lakers' practice facility. ''In a lot of cases, it's having enough respect to stand up for yourself and your teammates. When challenged, if you don't put your foot down, then guys are going to walk over your team. They are going to have less respect for you, and in the past that has been the case with us.''</p>
        <p>Fox's sentiments are a sign of the tension that has built between these clubs. Virtual strangers when this four-of-seven-game series began, the Lakers and the Pacers are developing a sincere dislike for one another. Fox got into an argument with Indiana's Jalen Rose in Game 3, and exchanged heated words with Rose, Mark Jackson and Reggie Miller in Game 5. And Jackson and Ron Harper had a confrontation that resulted in a double-technical foul in Game 3.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of bad blood,'' Lakers point guard Derek Fisher said. ''It's not just about them; it's about this time of year. This is now our sixth time playing this team in 12 days or so. That is where the bad blood comes from. They get tired of getting pushed around by Shaquille O'Neal just like we get tired of chasing their 3-point shooters around. It's not personal. It's just that we are competing.''</p>
        <p>But some of it may be personal. After Indiana's 120-87 victory in Game 5, Miller said the Lakers were not the laid-back team that many people associate with Los Angeles and the resurrection of Showtime.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the scuffles are coming from them, which is a shock,'' Miller said. ''Everyone thinks they're so nice and pretty, and you know, they're the glamour boys. It's Los Angeles, Evian, caffe latte, all that. They're doing all the pushing, the holding. Then they look at the refs like they're not doing anything.''</p>
        <p>Miller was almost certainly referring to what he perceived to be dirty play by Fox. He elbowed Fox in the back while Fox was arguing with Rose with 11 minutes remaining in Game 5. Fox, on the other hand, believed the Pacers were getting too celebratory and cocky near the end of their rout.</p>
        <p>''A lot of times in blowouts, teams take the liberty of celebrating, enjoying themselves, having an air of bravado,'' Fox said. ''That is something that I don't take too keenly to and I don't think our team does either. If you let it continue, it carries over to the next game.</p>
        <p>''Jalen and I had a great exchange. It wasn't a pleasant exchange but it was a competitive exchange. But Reggie wants to sneak in his exchange. He doesn't want to square up with you. I don't think that's very manly.''</p>
        <p>The verbal back-and-forth probably favors the Pacers, who like having hostile feelings toward their opponents. It is well documented that Miller feeds off controversy, and Fox realizes that he may be playing into the hands of the deadliest shooter in the series.</p>
        <p>''He needs to have a charge,'' Fox said. ''He needs to be the villain.''</p>
        <p>Even without the extra motivation, Miller and the Pacers returned to Los Angeles with confidence. They felt tremendous after manhandling the Lakers in Game 5 and, after averaging 119 points the last two games, they believed they could be the ones ahead in the series, three games to two. The Pacers attributed their Game 1 loss to nervousness about appearing in their first N.B.A. finals, thought they missed a prime opportunity to win Game 2 after Kobe Bryant sprained his ankle, and said that Game 4, which the Lakers won by 120-118 in overtime, could have gone either way.</p>
        <p>The aura of invincibility that the Lakers had the last time they played host to Indiana at the Staples Center is gone. ''The Lakers are not an impossible team to beat three times in a row, especially with the firepower we have as a team,'' said Travis Best, who is questionable for Monday's game with a bruised left shoulder. ''This is a closer series than people think.''</p>
        <p>Los Angeles, used to being viewed as superior all season, does not like the arrogance and sense of entitlement that was spawned in Indiana. The Lakers' plan is to return the Pacers to the cowering, uncertain team they handled easily in Games 1 and 2.</p>
        <p>''They have confidence because they have the chance to play another game,'' Fisher said defensively, when asked about Indiana's newfound brashness. ''But the fact is that we are still up, 3-2, and now we play on our court. It's easy to feel confident at home with your crowd. Let's see how much confidence they have tomorrow night.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. FINALS: LAKERS VS. PACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
