<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Help From the Mets, Reed Steers Clear of Trouble</title>
    <meta content="19METS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Milwaukee Brewers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Milwaukee Brewers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DC1531F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Help From the Mets, Reed Steers Clear of Trouble</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Milwaukee Brewers, 7-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first injury came in Japan, when the automatic door on a taxicab conked him on the knee.</p>
        <p>Then came a stiff neck against Los Angeles, a numb foot in Philadelphia, a bruised hand against Milwaukee and a pulled muscle in his side in St. Louis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first injury came in Japan, when the automatic door on a taxicab conked him on the knee.</p>
        <p>Then came a stiff neck against Los Angeles, a numb foot in Philadelphia, a bruised hand against Milwaukee and a pulled muscle in his side in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>''I just kept fighting, fighting and fighting,'' said the Mets right-hander Rick Reed, who escaped today's start without injury and with a 7-3 victory over the Brewers. ''Finally, my past two outings have been fine with me, right where I want to be. Each time out's getting better.''</p>
        <p>Reed (4-1) worked seven innings, allowing three runs on seven hits and a walk. He had no decision in each of his previous six starts -- ''That's unreal; I don't want to go through that again,'' he said -- but earned a victory today, his first since April 29.</p>
        <p>In the bottom of the first today, Ron Belliard smacked a leadoff home run. But the first hitter in Reed's last start against the Brewers inflicted more damage.</p>
        <p>In that game, at Shea Stadium on April 19, Marquis Grissom led off by smashing a liner off Reed's glove hand. Reed went on to pitch seven strong innings for a victory, but his wrist and palm were crushed.</p>
        <p>He could not make a fist or slide his hand into his glove for several days, and the pain disrupted his sleep.</p>
        <p>Reed missed a start and, as he struggled over the next month, he changed his mechanics to protect his hand when he got into fielding position.</p>
        <p>''I got into some bad habits with my front shoulder, and that started elevating the ball in the strike zone,'' Reed said.</p>
        <p>That was not a problem today for Reed, who trailed by 1-0 after Belliard's homer but pitched with a lead for most of the game, courtesy of the Mets' five-run fourth inning against Jason Bere.</p>
        <p>Matt Franco led off with a single and scored on Mike Piazza's double, and Jay Payton drove in another run with a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>After Benny Agbayani beat the throw to first base on what would have been an inning-ending double play, Kurt Abbott bashed an off-speed pitch for a three-run home run that traveled an estimated 405 feet.</p>
        <p>Abbott was starting at shortstop for the first time since Tuesday, when he made a throwing error that brought in the Chicago Cubs' winning run. Abbott admitted he wondered why he was not in Manager Bobby Valentine's lineup the next three games.</p>
        <p>''I think that's normal,'' he said. ''Of course. When you want to play and you're not in there, you have reason to ask, 'How come I'm not in there?' But he's the manager and he makes out the lineup every day.''</p>
        <p>But, Abbott said, he does not get upset when he is not playing. Valentine told Abbott and Melvin Mora they would share the playing time at short while Rey Ordonez was out with a broken forearm, but he never mentioned who would play when. ''Maybe the hot hand,'' Abbott said.</p>
        <p>Franco, whose second single helped the Mets score their sixth run, has a better idea of when he will start: every 10 or 11 days. He had not started since June 3, so he had a feeling he would today, at first base.</p>
        <p>He has 7 hits in 20 at-bats in his six starts, for a .350 average. When he does not start, he is 6 for 40, for .150.</p>
        <p>But Franco has felt comfortable with his swing all season and was a little embarrassed that a two-hit day would be notable.</p>
        <p>''I know how I feel and I know what I'm seeing, and I know I can hit what I'm seeing,'' Franco said. ''I've hit .280 many times and felt worse than I do now.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Outfielder DARRYL HAMILTON said he thought there was a ''good possibility'' he would be on a rehabilitation assignment by the end of this week, meaning he could be back with the Mets in the first few days of July. Hamilton, who has been out since early April with a toe injury, says he does not know if he will play regularly when he returns, but that is how he has prepared. ''The reason we've taken this much time is for me to get back playing like I was before, and that was every day,'' he said. ''We've been very conservative with the timetable.'' Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said he would have no plan on how to use Hamilton until he returned.</p>
        <p>Left fielder JASON TYNER reached on an infield single in the ninth inning and recorded his first major league stolen base, beating a throw from Milwaukee's HENRY BLANCO, one of baseball's best throwing catchers. . . . Pitching for Class AAA Norfolk, the right-hander BOBBY J. JONES allowed three runs on five hits in the first inning at Pawtucket on Sunday. But Jones followed with five scoreless innings, and he will return to the Mets and start on Friday. . . . MIKE HAMPTON, whose last start was pushed back because of a strained groin, worked on the side Sunday and will make his scheduled start on Tuesday. . . . Hamilton, who came up with the Brewers, is one player who will miss Milwaukee County Stadium, which is closing after this season. ''There's no other place to be when there's a packed house,'' Hamilton said. ''It's unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
