<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nortel Makes Inroads in Building Wireless World in Latin America</title>
    <meta content="19HEMI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico City (Mex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nortel Networks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Axtel (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unefon Sa De Cv</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Mexico City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDA1431F93AA25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nortel Makes Inroads in Building Wireless World in Latin America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nortel Networks of Canada seeks to capitalize on competition sweeping Latin America's telecommunications markets; has built fixed-wireless phone service in Mexico for Axtel that uses radio waves like cellular phone, but for use only in fixed site; is building fixed wireless system in Mexico City for Axtel's main competitor, Unefon, and is busy installing advanced communications systems throughout hemisphere; is also expanding in Asia and Europe; graph; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clearly, the history lay in the action, not the words. Before a mob of photographers, President Ernesto Zedillo placed the first telephone call on a new fixed-wireless network being installed in Mexico City.</p>
        <p>''De aqui pa'ya,'' he said in slangy Spanish that literally means ''From here to there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clearly, the history lay in the action, not the words. Before a mob of photographers, President Ernesto Zedillo placed the first telephone call on a new fixed-wireless network being installed in Mexico City.</p>
        <p>''De aqui pa'ya,'' he said in slangy Spanish that literally means ''From here to there.''</p>
        <p>Not as resonant perhaps as ''Mr. Watson, come here. I want to see you.'' But the May 11 call made history nonetheless because it marked another of Latin America's leap-frogging jumps into the future.</p>
        <p>And it represented yet another landmark in the effort by the system's creator, Nortel Networks of Canada, to become the next-generation Internet builder for the Americas. Perhaps more than any other technology player, Nortel -- already a power further north in North America -- is capitalizing on the changes sweeping Latin America as the company tries to make the entire hemisphere its home market.</p>
        <p>The fixed-wireless phone that Mr. Zedillo used works like any home telephone except that it was not connected by wire to the lines and poles run by Mexico's dominant telephone company, Telmex. Instead, the handset operates by radio wave, like a cellular phone, but one for use only in a fixed location. An outside antenna is all that needs to be installed -- a huge advantage in a country where it can take years to get a regular phone and where many rural areas have never been wired.</p>
        <p>President Zedillo's participation in the first call underscores the Mexican government's pride in the new system and in Axtel, the Mexican-controlled company that runs it. But development and construction of the system was the work of Nortel, a foreign company.</p>
        <p>Competition has come to Latin America's telecommunications, and Nortel has come with it. The company is building an essentially identical fixed wireless system in Mexico City for Axtel's main competitor, Unefon, and is busy installing advanced communications systems throughout South America, Central America and the Caribbean, with the exception of Cuba. Meanwhile, the company operates a wireless systems research center in Campinas, Brazil, and produces wireless communications equipment in an adjoining plant. Last week, Nortel announced a contract with GVT of Brazil, a local and long-distance telephone company, to install an advanced telecommunications system -- including the backbone of an optical network -- for the capital city of Brasilia and nine surrounding states.</p>
        <p>Until recently, Nortel employed 2,000 workers in northern Mexico to produce telephone equipment there. In a further attempt to focus on advanced systems, the company decided to sell the manufacturing operation to Solectron, the world's largest contract maker of electronics, for $900 million. But the two companies then promptly signed a four-year supply agreement worth more than $10 billion.</p>
        <p>Nortel also is expanding in Asia and Europe; on June 19 it is scheduled to announce a number of alliances with European companies that will collaborate with Nortel on the development of a new generation of Internet technology for Europe.</p>
        <p>In fact, Nortel is growing so rapidly outside Canada that doubts are being expressed at home about its corporate citizenship, and a Canadian magazine recently asked, only half joking, whether the company had surrendered its Canadian passport. Its headquarters remains in Brampton, Ontario, but more of its 75,000 employees live and work south of the Canada-United States border than north of it. Fewer than 10 percent of Nortel's executives still work in Canada, and just 8 percent of its $21 billion in revenues comes from there.</p>
        <p>''Our roots are definitely Canadian, but we're a global corporation,'' said Martha Helena Bejar, general manager of Nortel Networks Latin America. She spoke during an interview at Nortel's Mexican headquarters on the 30th floor of a downtown Mexico City building that bears the company's name. ''We're not focused on a specific market; we're focused on a segment, which is the telecommunications industry, including optical, Internet and wireless services.''</p>
        <p>Nortel is not the only corporation to cast its shadow across the hemisphere, of course. The American automobile companies have been doing it for decades, and both Nortel's fiercest competitors, Lucent Technologies and Cisco Systems, are trying to make inroads into Latin America. But Nortel is notable for the way it has expanded by exploiting the radical changes in the region's economic profile. As country after country has opened its market -- privatizing state-run enterprises, encouraging competition and liberalizing regulations to let technological change flourish -- Nortel has seized opportunities.</p>
        <p>And as the company rides the wave of change in Latin America's economies, it has been transforming itself from an old-line manufacturer -- mostly of telephone network switching equipment -- to one of the world's leading Internet and wireless communications equipment providers.</p>
        <p>The company had its start in 1895 as Northern Electric and Manufacturing and did not become a major player in the United States until the 1984 breakup of AT&amp;T's Bell System prompted many of the biggest American telephone companies to seek an alternative supplier to AT&amp;T for network equipment. Yet, by 1997 Nortel had grown to become second only to Lucent Technologies, the AT&amp;T spinoff, as the largest manufacturer of standard telecommunications gear in the world. The company is active in Europe and Asia as well as Latin America.</p>
        <p>That year, though, John A. Roth, Nortel's newly appointed chief executive, decided that the company had to make a ''right angle turn'' away from its customary business and into wireless communications, the Internet and what at the time was considered a daring combination of them both.</p>
        <p>Its strategy since then has been to acquire what it needs to get a toehold in the new market, then spend billions on research in an effort to outrun rivals like Cisco Systems and Lucent in the race toward a better Internet.</p>
        <p>Nortel has gone on a shopping spree and picked up many companies. But the biggest and most important so far has been Bay Networks, a data networking leader, based in Santa Clara, Calif. The purchase, in 1998, was for $9.1 billion in stock, roughly one quarter of Nortel's market capitalization at that time.</p>
        <p>The task of melding Bay's Silicon Valley mentality with the century-old telecommunications manufacturer made some analysts uneasy. And investors sneered at first.</p>
        <p>Today, the Bay acquisition is widely regarded as the key to Nortel's successful transformation, a makeover that has turned it into the biggest Canadian company ever by market capitalization and a global force to be reckoned with in advanced telecommunications and the Internet. Nortel has tried to position itself as the inventor of a bigger and faster Internet, a strategy featured in the company's television commercials, which put Nortel in the position of asking people all over the world, ''What do you want the Internet to be?''</p>
        <p>Since the Bay takeover, Nortel has made $12 billion of additional acquisitions, many of them companies in the United States that Nortel paid for with its own rapidly appreciating stock. Nortel shares reached an all-time high of $72 in March, and even after the stock market's downdraft it remains one of the better performing telecommunications stocks, traded in both New York and Canada. Its market value makes it the biggest blue-chip stock ever in Canada, accounting for more than 30 percent of the market value of the Toronto Stock Exchange 300 index.</p>
        <p>''The companies we bought are incubators, and they've each got a great idea,'' said Ms. Bejar, a United States citizen who was born in Colombia. ''Nortel Networks comes in and gives closure to those great ideas.''</p>
        <p>Innovations like the photonic switching technology developed for fiber optic networks by Xros Inc., the California company acquired for $3.25 billion in Nortel stock earlier this year, have broadened Nortel's technical arsenal. The company hires a quarter of all electrical engineering and computer science graduates in Canada and spends more on research -- $3 billion a year -- than the government of Canada or any Canadian company.</p>
        <p>More important, Nortel's growing technological prowess has helped the company expand across the hemisphere in a big way. Nortel first sold standard switching equipment in Latin America in the 1960's, but on a limited scale because it was competing with entrenched multinationals like Ericsson of Sweden and Alcatel of France that dominated traditional services in Latin America.</p>
        <p>The rapid development of wireless and optical networks gave Nortel the chance to break in because they required all new technology, not just an extension of existing service. Nortel has risen to No. 2, behind Ericsson in the region's wireless market.</p>
        <p>''We were able to get in with our wireless products in Brazil, Chile, Colombia and Central America, and capitalize on the liberalization of the markets,'' Ms. Bejar said. In some cases, as local regulations eased, Nortel's customers converted existing cellular phone licenses to fixed wireless and to wireless Internet access.</p>
        <p>Although Internet use in Latin America is comparatively small right now, advertisers, merchandisers and the telecommunications companies see great growth potential in the region. According to surveys, only about 1.5 percent of the region's 500 million people now use the Internet, compared with more than 24 percent in the United States. But Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company expects Internet access in the region to double the next three years, while rapidly developing economies like those of Brazil and Mexico could expand at a far quicker pace.</p>
        <p>Certainly the wireless market has demonstrated the region's growth potential. In 1995, there were 4 million wireless subscribers in Latin America; by the end of last year, that number had risen to 30 million, roughly the population of Canada. By 2003, the wireless market in Latin America is expected to be 70 million.</p>
        <p>Countries like Mexico enjoy something of an advantage when it comes to such advanced technology. Existing systems are so primitive that little is worth saving. Everything old can be replaced with the newest generation of technology.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of customers who take pride in leap-frogging over existing technologies and bragging, 'I have the same technology that MCI WorldCom has,' '' Ms. Bejar said.</p>
        <p>Jorge O. Mariscal, managing director of Latin America Equity Research for Goldman, Sachs said: ''What we've got now is an almost seamless Americas market. The combination of regulatory changes and market liberalization have worked toward creating a strong operating environment for not just international companies like Nortel but local companies, too.''</p>
        <p>He cited the example of Telmex, which after losing its monopoly on long-distance and local telephone service in Mexico, has been busy expanding into the United States and Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>In the end perhaps, the most obvious motivation for Nortel's transformation and push to expand is the limitation of its home base. Canada, the company's home for over a century, is already a well wired and mature market, whereas Latin America remains young and full of potential.</p>
        <p>''If you plot out the growth of wireless in Latin America it really looks like a hockey stick, fairly level and then zooming right up,'' Ms. Bejar said. A hockey stick seems a strange metaphor for a native of Colombia to use to describe a telecommunications market. But like Nortel itself, there's no question of where it had come from.</p>
        <p>''I guess that's Canadian, eh?'' she said.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
