<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up-to-Speed Artistry From a Three-Car Atelier</title>
    <meta content="03YORK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Artist Technicians (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shivnarain, Marvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D71230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up-to-Speed Artistry From a Three-Car Atelier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marvin Shivnarain, graphics director of Long Island silk-screen printing company, is also owner of operator of Artist Technicians, garage in Richmond Hill, Queens, where he paints murals and intricate graphics on exteriors of cars, motorcycles and bicycles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the still of the night, Marvin Shivnarain paints pictures on automobiles.</p>
        <p>His work is not the latest in illegal late-night graffiti. He gets paid to create what he calls rolling works of art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the still of the night, Marvin Shivnarain paints pictures on automobiles.</p>
        <p>His work is not the latest in illegal late-night graffiti. He gets paid to create what he calls rolling works of art.</p>
        <p>By day, Mr. Shivnarain is the graphics director of a silk-screen printing company on Long Island. But at night, he paints murals and intricate graphics on the exteriors of cars, motorcycles and bicycles, and also sandblasts permanent designs in windshields and car windows. As the owner and operator of Artist Technicians, a custom graphics studio in a nondescript three-car garage in Richmond Hill, Queens, Mr. Shivnarain is capitalizing on a growing trend -- the incredibly stylized car.</p>
        <p>''Eight years ago, someone would get a brand new car and they would just buy some chrome rims and put a stereo in,'' he said. ''Now that's not enough. Just a stock paint job doesn't work anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shivnarain's work is part of a trend that began in the 1950's, when Mexican-Americans in California created the low rider, which then was most likely to be a car like a Thunderbird or a Cadillac with adjusted suspensions so that its body sat only a few inches from the road.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, the proliferation of magazines devoted to these ground-hugging cars, and the added exposure they received from being in hip-hop music videos, increased the cars' popularity nationwide. Meanwhile, a competition circuit arose as people competed to create the most spectacular custom cars.</p>
        <p>Today, the low-rider craze has grown into a $1 billion a year business, according to Lonnie Lopez, editor of Low Rider magazine, and includes ''slammers,'' imported vehicles like Honda Civics and Toyota Camrys that are personalized by individual owners. Some of the most garishly decorated slammers have hydraulic systems that make them bounce up and down or tilt to the side; ''suicide'' doors and hoods that open from the opposite direction; and cameras that replace rear-view mirrors by feeding streaming video into a monitor installed in the dashboard. But the ultimate ornamentation is the customized mural or graphic design.</p>
        <p>Several graphic artists moonlight in auto body shops or residential garages, but Mr. Shivnarain has his own brick and mortar business establishment. The growing numbers of car enthusiasts and car clubs in the city have made him an artist in demand. And while Mr. Lopez said no figures were kept on the amount of money spent on artwork, he estimated that a quarter of the show cars had some kind of design.</p>
        <p>''I'm constantly challenged,'' Mr. Shivnarain said.''Everybody wants to be more complicated than the next car.''</p>
        <p>After consulting with his customers, Mr. Shivnarain sketches their collaborative dream designs on paper. If the client is pleased, Mr. Shivnarain then wields a $60 airbrush pen, used by nail technicians to create designs on acrylic fingernails, to paint his illustrations. Some jobs require the use of stencils; others are done freehand. But each illustration, he said, is one of a kind.</p>
        <p>''I don't repeat a job for anyone,'' Mr. Shivnarain said. ''A person comes to me because they want to be original.''</p>
        <p>On the trunk of a 1996 Lexus SC300, he painted ''City of Dreams,'' a mural in which the Statue of Liberty stands next to a detailed rendering of Manhattan's skyline. He covered the body of a Kawasaki motorcycle with alternating purple and gold slanted lines before painting a scowling bulldog on top of them. He created a full car graphic, a series of powder blue lines and rectangular shapes that intersect at points over the body of the car, for a white Mitsubishi Diamante. And he put a grinning joker on the belly of a gas tank and added the words ''Cruel Intentions'' in backward script, subtle detailing that allows the writing to be legible when mirrors are placed underneath the body of the car at competitions.</p>
        <p>His most peculiar job, he said, was created for an auto repair shop in Brooklyn. He put orange, yellow and red hot-rod flames on the cover of the company's toilet seat.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't seem like anything is unusual,'' Mr. Shivnarain said. ''Anything can be done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shivnarain, 29, who has a degree in illustration and graphic design from Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, started his love affair with airbrushing when he was in high school, after seeing T-shirts being airbrushed at a mall. He taught himself to do it in 1991, and quickly moved from painting characters on clothing to creating scenes and graphics on automobiles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shivnarain, president of Drastic Auto Club, said his customers came from all over the Eastern Seaboard and Canada. They range from car club members to stockbrokers to hobbyists who take second jobs to pay for thousands of dollars' worth of customization with the hopes of winning at competitions.</p>
        <p>''Every year you always have to change the style,'' said George Soto, president of the Brooklyn Kruzers auto club and owner of an orange 1987 Ford Mustang with a female superhero emblazoned on its hood. ''If not, the judges get bored with the car.''</p>
        <p>New and repeat customers earned Mr. Shivnarain $30,000 in sales last year. He is on track to make more money this year because, for the first time in his nine years in business, he has booked jobs well into the winter when the summer car season is over. Still, Mr. Shivnarain plans to hold on to his full-time job until he is sure he can support himself with his auto artwork.</p>
        <p>''It isn't like I'm trying to be a millionaire,'' Mr. Shivnarain said. ''I just do it because I love it.''</p>
        <p>Painting murals like the ''Soul Stealer,'' an illustration on the back of a navy blue Ford Explorer that features a moonlit graveyard with seraphs and headstones bearing the names of the owner's deceased friends, takes Mr. Shivnarain about a week to complete and costs about $500. Full-body graphics take two weeks to a month to finish and cost $2,000 to $8,000.</p>
        <p>Those prices do not deter Eric Monserrate. Mr. Monserrate, 24, a truck driver living in Bushwick, enters his 1997 Honda Accord in car competitions. Since he bought the car three years ago, he has put at least $20,000 into customizing it.</p>
        <p>First, he painted over its green with metallic green to reflect hues of green, black and blue. He also shaved off the car's door handles to create a smooth, unbroken paint job, installed 17-inch rims on its wheels, relocated the gas tank opening to the rear tailight and moved the license plate from the gate of the car to its bumper. Still, he said, the car is far from finished.</p>
        <p>''For me, the car has no life in it yet,'' Mr. Monserrate said. ''I want something to catch the eye of the people.''</p>
        <p>He has charged Mr. Shivnarain with making sure his car turns heads.</p>
        <p>''If you just park the car on the street, you may not notice the work done to it,'' said Mr. Shivnarain, who plans to paint a tribal motif with swooping geometrical lines around the body of the car. ''Graphics are the eye-catcher. Once people see graphics, the word 'custom' comes to mind because you know something has been done.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
