<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beating the Market, Until the Expenses Pile Up</title>
    <meta content="03STRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulbert, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wermers, Russ (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Strategies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDE1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beating the Market, Until the Expenses Pile Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK HULBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulbert, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Hulbert Strategies column, based on studies by University of Maryland finance Prof Russ Wermers, concludes that while average stocks bought by fund manager outperform market, return declines when expenses are factored in; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT first blush, the current issue of The Journal of Finance contains good news for the mutual fund industry, and from a most unlikely source: an academic study.</p>
        <p>In contrast to almost every other scholarly look at fund performance, a new one -- by Russ Wermers, a finance professor at the University of Maryland -- concludes that fund managers have market-beating abilities in picking stocks. Specifically, Professor Wermers found that the average stock bought by a fund manager outperformed the market by 1.5 percentage points a year over the 20 years ended in 1994.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT first blush, the current issue of The Journal of Finance contains good news for the mutual fund industry, and from a most unlikely source: an academic study.</p>
        <p>In contrast to almost every other scholarly look at fund performance, a new one -- by Russ Wermers, a finance professor at the University of Maryland -- concludes that fund managers have market-beating abilities in picking stocks. Specifically, Professor Wermers found that the average stock bought by a fund manager outperformed the market by 1.5 percentage points a year over the 20 years ended in 1994.</p>
        <p>But when that finding is weighed against another from the professor's research, I can only conclude that the study is a devastating indictment of fund-industry inefficiency.</p>
        <p>The average fund, the study found, delivered annual returns that were eight-tenths of a percentage point below the market's over that period. Taken together, the two facts mean that the average mutual fund frittered away 2.3 percentage points of return annually. Today, that would mean $92 billion a year, considering that the industry now manages about $4 trillion in assets.</p>
        <p>Until now, most researchers believed that the average fund produced mediocre performance because managers had subpar ability to pick stocks. But to me, the professor's study shows that the real culprit has been the fund industry's inability to translate good stock-picking to the bottom line.</p>
        <p>For years, we were unable to identify this culprit, because no one had been able to measure funds' pure, theoretical return -- how much they would have made if they had no expenses or trading costs and were always fully invested. The professor filled that gap by constructing a database that contained not only the performance of virtually every fund from 1975 through 1994, but also the stocks that each owned.</p>
        <p>According to Professor Wermers, the largest single source of fund inefficiency was expenses -- investment managers' salaries and administrative and marketing costs. Roughly 1.1 of the difference of 2.3 percentage points was spent on such costs. Today, that is about $44 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The second-largest source is the lower returns of funds' nonstock holdings. The typical fund must hold a significant amount of  cash so that it can meet redemptions. Because returns on cash lag behind those of the stock market over the long term, the typical fund has weaker performance than if it had been fully invested. Professor Wermers estimated that these cash and other nonstock holdings cut the average annual return by 0.7 percentage points -- about $28 billion or so in today's terms.</p>
        <p>The third reason for the gap is transaction costs. Professor Wermers defined this category broadly, to include not only commissions and bid-asked spreads but also the poorer executions that result when a fund tries to buy or sell a large position in a stock. Unlike the average investor, a big fund can move a stock price significantly when trying to buy or sell -- forcing it to buy at a higher price and sell at a lower price, with correspondingly poorer performance. Though commissions and spreads have diminished in recent years, Professor Wermers estimated that transaction costs of all kinds reduced performance by 0.5 percentage points or so a year -- or $20 billion today.</p>
        <p>Note that the study did not even consider front-  or back-end loads, or sales charges. The $92 billion price of the industry's inefficiency is above and beyond the load factor.</p>
        <p>Devastating as the conclusions may be for the fund industry, they contain a silver lining for the rest of us. In contrast to previous studies that found that it was impossible to consistently pick stocks that outperform the market, Professor Wermers shows that not only is it possible, but also that it is not particularly unusual. By creating our own portfolios -- and assuming that we can pick stocks as well as the average fund manager -- we stand a good chance of saving the bulk of the 2.3 annual percentage points spent on fund inefficiencies -- and a betting chance of actually outperforming the market.</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week.  E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week.
&lt;br&gt;E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
