<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where A Teenager Gives Orders</title>
    <meta content="03SHAR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cheerleaders</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Cheerleader (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cheerleaders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D91330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where A Teenager Gives Orders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>After years of disregard and even ridicule, cheerleading is back and bigger than ever; today's cheerleaders sometimes exhibit higher athletic skill than teams they root for; they work with coaches, choreographers and physical trainers, often attending summer boot camps to prepare for both sidelines and competitions with other squads; excerpts from American Cheerleader magazine, suggesting some of forces at play in brave new world of cheerleader empowerment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOOTBALL season is here again, and as anyone who has been to a high school or college game in recent years knows, this is not your Aunt Gidget's cheerleading squad anymore. Today's cheerleaders tumble, vault, build human pyramids -- and sometimes exhibit higher athletic skill than the teams they're rooting for. Like gymnasts, cheerleaders work with coaches, choreographers and physical trainers, often attending summer boot camps to prepare for both the sidelines and competitions with other squads.</p>
        <p>After years of disregard and even ridicule, cheerleading is back and bigger than ever, with a steely, aerobicized attitude that's a long way from old-fashioned pom-poms and sis-boom-bahs. This summer, Hollywood released two major high-school cheerleader movies: ''But I'm a Cheerleader!'' and ''Bring It On,'' a  hit that depicts cheerleaders as serious athletes and socially responsible citizens. And cheerleading is being pushed as a potential Olympic sport in 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOOTBALL season is here again, and as anyone who has been to a high school or college game in recent years knows, this is not your Aunt Gidget's cheerleading squad anymore. Today's cheerleaders tumble, vault, build human pyramids -- and sometimes exhibit higher athletic skill than the teams they're rooting for. Like gymnasts, cheerleaders work with coaches, choreographers and physical trainers, often attending summer boot camps to prepare for both the sidelines and competitions with other squads.</p>
        <p>After years of disregard and even ridicule, cheerleading is back and bigger than ever, with a steely, aerobicized attitude that's a long way from old-fashioned pom-poms and sis-boom-bahs. This summer, Hollywood released two major high-school cheerleader movies: ''But I'm a Cheerleader!'' and ''Bring It On,'' a  hit that depicts cheerleaders as serious athletes and socially responsible citizens. And cheerleading is being pushed as a potential Olympic sport in 2004.</p>
        <p>Today's cheerleading supports an industry of fashion and sports suppliers, instructors, sports doctors, competition organizers and glossy publications. ''Where else can a teenage girl stand up in front of thousands of people and tell them what to do?'' a cheerleader asks in an ad in American Cheerleader magazine.</p>
        <p>The following excerpts, gleaned from the magazine and its Web site (www.americancheerleader.com), suggest some of the forces at play in the brave new world of cheerleader empowerment.</p>
        <p>Vince Lombardi would have been proud: Today's cheerleaders are tough as nails and can play with pain.</p>
        <p>To many, falling from stunts represents the adverse side of cheerleading. Yet in a controlled environment, it's really not! Cheerleaders should know that without failure there would be no success.</p>
        <p>Serious knee injuries are not just for boys!</p>
        <p>Do you need a fun way to get in shape for the summer, but hate those boring step classes and supermodel workout videos? Try kickboxing!</p>
        <p>Hi! I'm a junior high cheerleader [and] I have an idea: Liberty turn with advanced stunts. Start facing to the left of the crowd, go into a lib and do an arabesque, then turn and have your flyer kick a stretch heel, turn again and your flyer will do a waterfall, then turn and kick a heel stretch and turn again to your starting point and pull one more waterfall, then cradle. It's an awesome stunt. I did it on my first try. Good luck!</p>
        <p>Not that the modern cheerleader is completely squeaky clean. A half-page ad for Glass Chalk, an ink marker used to make washable graffiti on glass, depicts a mischievous-looking cheerleader with marker in hand, posed beside summer-camp snapshots showing windows scrawled with gently taunting insults against opposing teams. The ad's text says:</p>
        <p>What we did last summer: Did you hear about cheer camp? . . . We left our team's mark everywhere! It was sooo awesome. You can't believe what a little Glass Chalk does for team spirit! But no worry. It washes right off any glass window with a wet paper towel.</p>
        <p>A little community outreach never hurts, especially if spreading cheer can raise your squad's visibility.</p>
        <p>You've heard the complaint time and time again: The cheerleading team doesn't get enough support. You're athletes, so why does all of the attention focus on football and basketball and not on you? You're not alone.</p>
        <p>While the student body celebrates the biggest game of the week, they probably don't even know that your golf team is undefeated and your swim team is ranked first in the state. As the spirit leaders in your school, you can help gain support for every sport and bring added attention to the cheer squad in the process. A fall sports pep rally dedicated strictly to these athletes will show them they are important to the school.</p>
        <p>And hey, don't we all want to share that invincible team spirit? Even trumpet players and classroom wiseacres are vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Stereotypes say that the cheerleaders and the band never get along. Here are some suggestions to help make you and the band a spirit unit: Teach them some cheers. . . . Put them on the sidelines with you. . . . Invite a few down to do one of your cheers with you, maybe in the later part of the game.</p>
        <p>And you know that kid in your history class who always keeps everyone else laughing? Invite him or her to use those ''class clowning'' skills and join you on the sidelines, running back and forth painted in school colors and flashing ''Go! Fight! Win!'' signs to get the crowd to yell along with you.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
