<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Work and How About Some Play, Too?</title>
    <meta content="03WORK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Itano, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFD81430F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Work and How About Some Play, Too?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE ITANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Itano, Nicole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unusual workplace policies are put in place at a number of Connecticut-based companies with the aim of inspiring employee loyalty and increasing productivity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT Yarde Metals, an aluminum and steel distributor based in Bristol, children and dogs sometimes go to work and employees can occasionally be found napping on the job.</p>
        <p>None of this bothers Craig Yarde, the company's owner and founder, who runs his $115-million-a-year company from a desk in the same large room used by the sales and administrative staff in his central office. He said his company's unusual workplace policies inspire employee loyalty and increase productivity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT Yarde Metals, an aluminum and steel distributor based in Bristol, children and dogs sometimes go to work and employees can occasionally be found napping on the job.</p>
        <p>None of this bothers Craig Yarde, the company's owner and founder, who runs his $115-million-a-year company from a desk in the same large room used by the sales and administrative staff in his central office. He said his company's unusual workplace policies inspire employee loyalty and increase productivity.</p>
        <p>''The only turnover we have is the turnover that we force,'' Mr. Yarde said. Mr. Yarde, 48, is a 60's-style idealist. He believes in profit sharing, family-friendly workplaces, and, in a move that garnered a great deal of attention, coed bathrooms.</p>
        <p>While most companies around the state will still expect their employees' dogs and children be left at home when they return to work after this Labor Day weekend, an increasing number of Connecticut employers are, like Mr. Yarde, recognizing the role of workplace environment in attracting and retaining quality employees. Many of these companies, particularly those in the technology sector, are taking unusual steps to ensure their employees stay happy, healthy and loyal.</p>
        <p>''Companies are having to be more innovative and creative at retaining workers,'' said Marjorie Bynum, vice president of the Information Technology Association of America. ''Salary is important, but it's not the most important thing. Quality of life is really vital as well.''</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, where unemployment rates are at nearly half the national average, competition for employees is particularly stiff. In a survey of small- and medium-sized business conducted last year by the Connecticut Business and Industry Association, more than 80 percent of respondents said they had difficulty finding qualified workers. Forty-eight percent said they had great or extreme difficulty finding qualified employees.</p>
        <p>A number of companies, in both the Internet and traditional markets, are responding to the labor shortage by changing workplace rules to make offices more relaxed and fun. Workplace rules have relaxed and increasing numbers of companies are throwing social events during working hours, allowing casual dress and providing on-site facilities such as kitchenettes, gyms and even nap rooms.</p>
        <p>''Employers are trying to make the workplace almost home-like because they know that workers spend so much time there,'' Ms. Bynum said.</p>
        <p>According to a study by the United Nations, the number of hours the average American worked over the course of a year increased by almost 100 between 1980 and 1997.</p>
        <p>According to a study by the Bureau of Labor Statistics, between 1976 and 1993, the number of non-agricultural workers working more than 49 hours a week increased from 13 percent of the work force to almost 20 percent. And that shift is concentrated among professionals.</p>
        <p>In the Stamford offices of iSolve.com, an Internet company that helps businesses sell or trade their excess inventory, most Friday afternoons are devoted to an office-sponsored social event such as a cappuccino bar or pretzel and beer party.</p>
        <p>Barbara Serf, iSolve's executive vice president of marketing, said the events are important to office morale because with the company's fast growth -- they have hired more than 65 employees since November -- the informal get-togethers are one of the only ways people in the company can meet each other.</p>
        <p>''These social events are important so that people get to know each other's names,'' Ms. Serf said. ''In the dot-com world everyone is trying to pay competitive salaries. What everyone really wants is to have fun and enjoy what they're doing.''</p>
        <p>At Priceline.com in Norwalk, employees are even encouraged to play at work. About a dozen basketball hoops, air hockey and foosball tables scattered throughout the company's three-floor building provide employees a distraction during breaks. The tradition dates to the company's early days when an employee donated a foosball table and it got so much use that when it broke, senior management chipped to buy more tables for  the office to share.</p>
        <p>''We do that recognizing that there are the longer hours here and that some people need to let off stream,'' said Brian Ek, a spokesman for the company.</p>
        <p>Even companies in more traditional industries are relaxing their work environments. Wilton-based accounting and tax firm Deloitte and Touche, for example, provides kitchenettes and nap rooms for employees.</p>
        <p>''It's spawned by the technology companies because intellectual capital is so important to them,'' said Steve Clement of the Connecticut Technology Council. ''It's become more mainstream because the labor market has become more competitive.''</p>
        <p>A number of scholars, however, have expressed skepticism of new workplace policies designed to make the office more homey. In her book, ''The Time Bind: When Work Becomes Home and Home Becomes Work,'' the Berkeley sociologist Arlie Russell Hochschild investigated an undisclosed Fortune 500 company to examine the effect of family-friendly polices.</p>
        <p>She found that even with these policies, workers were spending more time in the office partly, she argues, because with all the stresses on life at home -- children, marriages, housework -- the new workplace is often the more enjoyable place to be.</p>
        <p>Competition for qualified labor has led many companies to offer unusual time-saving and quality of life benefits. Twenty-two percent of the Connecticut Business and Industry Association's survey respondents said they were now offering ''creative benefit packages'' such as catered meals, laundry and dry cleaning services and online concierge services. Companies said many of these new benefits are designed to help employees balance their work obligations with the rest of their lives.</p>
        <p>''In prior years, people tried to artificially separate a person's work life from their work life. In reality, when a person shows up to work, the whole person shows up,'' said James Wall, the managing director of human resources for Deloitte and Touche, which has 30,000 employees around the country.</p>
        <p>One program Deloitte offers helps employees take care of sick family members. The company will help arrange for child care for sick children and even hire temporary help to cook meals or run errands for an employee trying to balance increased home obligations with work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wall said such programs have saved Deloitte millions of dollars by helping the company reduce its turnover rate from 29 to 17 percent in the last eight years.</p>
        <p>The demand for services that help employees save time has even led to the development of a whole new high-tech industry: online concerige services. These companies, which generally contract with companies and charge a per-employee fee for basic services, will run errands, make travel and entertainment arrangements.</p>
        <p>''We're always looking for benefits that will help our employees,'' said Peter Cross, director of human resources for Arthur Anderson's Hartford office. His office contracts with Circles, a Boston-based online concierge service. ''This is one that's a little different than many. It saves time and helps people get things done that would otherwise be difficult.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cross, who also offers his employees free dry cleaning, said his employees use Circles primarily to make travel arrangements and find tickets for events. Jennifer Marino, a spokeswoman for Circles that serves more than one million employees across the country, said the company has even helped plan one customer's wedding.</p>
        <p>While benefits such as online concierge services and office luxuries like nap rooms and game tables are still exceptions in Connecticut workplaces, an increasing number of companies are realizing that sometimes it is the little things that keep employees happy and content.</p>
        <p>''Those things set you apart as a company that cares,'' Mr. Clement said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
