<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The End Seems Near for Garden State Race Track</title>
    <meta content="03RACE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Garden State Park (Racetrack)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cherry Hill (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5DB1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The End Seems Near for Garden State Race Track</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>CHERRY HILL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on impending closing of Garden State Race Track in Cherry Hill, NJ, which opened in 1942; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back in 1942, an evangelical preacher from nearby Collingswood named Carl McIntyre led a prayer vigil for 30 days of rain in southern New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre wanted this epochal storm to wash away any chance a Vineland entrepreneur named Eugene Mori would be able to finish his new horse racetrack. But despite the request for divine intervention and the onset of World War II, and the materials rationing that accompanied it, Mr. Mori built Garden State Race Track. For decades it thrived, even despite a devastating 1977 fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back in 1942, an evangelical preacher from nearby Collingswood named Carl McIntyre led a prayer vigil for 30 days of rain in southern New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre wanted this epochal storm to wash away any chance a Vineland entrepreneur named Eugene Mori would be able to finish his new horse racetrack. But despite the request for divine intervention and the onset of World War II, and the materials rationing that accompanied it, Mr. Mori built Garden State Race Track. For decades it thrived, even despite a devastating 1977 fire.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McIntyre, still alive at age 92, may have his prayers answered. Last month, Pennwood Inc., which operates Garden State, announced it would not seek thoroughbred racing dates from New Jersey's Racing Commission for 2001.</p>
        <p>''Effectively, that is the end of a long tradition of thoroughbred racing at Garden State,'' said John Forbes, president of the New Jersey Thoroughbred Breeders' Association, which is composed of horse trainers and owners. ''I think probably what it means for New Jersey racing is that any semblance of a circuit that would keep horses within the state is certainly dashed at this point.''</p>
        <p>The demise of horse racing in the southern end of the state has been in the offing for at least a decade. Last year, Atlantic City Race Course had a five-day meet, an almost ridiculously short season, just so it could legally keep simulcast race betting at the track.</p>
        <p>Garden State is open seven days a week for simulcast betting as well, but its recent spring meet was a disaster. It had to cut back most weeks from four days of racing to three and instead of having 9 or 10 races a day, it often only had 6. In addition, some races only had four or five horses.</p>
        <p>''We didn't promote ourselves all that well because we had been used to being a big deal in the 1950's and 1960's,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Though there will be a harness season starting Sept. 1 at Garden State, it may well be likely that the track itself will be gone before the next season could start. International Thoroughbred Breeders Inc., which owns the track and leases racing operations to Pennwood, earlier this year confirmed a tentative deal to sell the 223-acre site to Epoch Properties of Orlando, Fla. Neither company would comment.</p>
        <p>Cherry Hill officials are wary of the potential sale of Garden State, but are resigned that it will never return to its glory days, from the 1950's to 1970's, when the annual May Garden State Stakes was the richest horse race in the United States. Cherry Hill's mayor, Susan Bass Levin, has said she would advocate a creative mixed-use development for what would then be the largest open plot of land in the 24-square-mile township. Garden State employs about 1,000 seasonal workers, its barns house hundreds of horses, and it generates more tax revenue for the township than any other property save the Cherry Hill Mall.</p>
        <p>''We have horsemen here who want to race here, but right now it seems we are going to be forced to do our racing out of state,'' he said. ''There used to be as many as 25,000 people employed in the racing industry here. Now there are probably half that many. But it is still something that could thrive here if people in Trenton want it to, and we are certainly ready to work with them.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
