<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On a Summer Stage, Learning More Than Lines</title>
    <meta content="03SURF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Summer Stock" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Surflight Theater (Beach Haven, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0DB1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On a Summer Stage, Learning More Than Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <dateline>BEACH HAVEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series (Summer Stock) describes scene at Surflight Theater in Beach Haven, New Jersey's only summer stock theater and one of few summer stock theaters left in US, as season draws to an end; student-actors comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was three hours before showtime, and the cast of ''West Side Story'' was making dinner at the Surflight Theater cast house in Beach Haven. Officer Krupkey was at the kitchen sink and Maria was eating takeout with some of the Jets' girlfriends. Suddenly they all broke out in song, like in a musical. After living together and performing in six musicals in three months, they had become an irrepressible ensemble.</p>
        <p>But Labor Day was approaching. The group was breaking up. Though the Surflight operates through October, the interns had to go back to college before ''Victor/Victoria'' opened, and some of the professional actors were moving on. Soon they would be another page of fresh faces in Surflight playbills dating to the theater's founding in 1951.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was three hours before showtime, and the cast of ''West Side Story'' was making dinner at the Surflight Theater cast house in Beach Haven. Officer Krupkey was at the kitchen sink and Maria was eating takeout with some of the Jets' girlfriends. Suddenly they all broke out in song, like in a musical. After living together and performing in six musicals in three months, they had become an irrepressible ensemble.</p>
        <p>But Labor Day was approaching. The group was breaking up. Though the Surflight operates through October, the interns had to go back to college before ''Victor/Victoria'' opened, and some of the professional actors were moving on. Soon they would be another page of fresh faces in Surflight playbills dating to the theater's founding in 1951.</p>
        <p>The cast members had auditioned in New York in the spring for the chance to perform in one of the few summer stock theaters left in the United States. They had arrived just before Memorial Day, all smiles and sparkle. By the end of June, they were tired. While others rode bikes and went to the beach in this pretty beach town, the Surflighters worked 12 hours a day, seven days a week.</p>
        <p>Sometimes they did two different plays a day and rehearsed a third. Some had broken up with sweethearts. Some had not eaten right. Had it really been worth it?</p>
        <p>''It's been a whirlwind, hectic,'' said Leah Horowitz, who played Maria in ''West Side Story.'' But her high C was much stronger and she had been able to apply everything she had learned at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts.</p>
        <p>Sean Fenlon, a theater major at Southern Regional State College in Stockton, learned to dance better and to prepare himself mentally before going on stage, and found out he really could do Spanish accents. Matthew Senese, one of the professional actors, said that for the first time he got the chance to play bad guys. ''In 'Joseph' I sold my brother into slavery,'' Mr. Senese said. ''In 'Sound of Music,' I turned Maria Von Trapp in to the Nazis. And in 'West Side Story' I'm Chino, the one who kills Tony. I usually play the sweet roles. It was a lot of fun. I got out a lot of aggression. I'm going home a much happier, relaxed person.''</p>
        <p>Nicole Zachowski of Turnersville, who played Kate Mullins in ''Titanic'' and Anita in ''West Side Story,'' among others, said she was ready to go home. ''Most of us are very worn out,'' Ms. Zachowski said.</p>
        <p>Three hours later, they were silhouetted against Rob Wolin's set evoking Manhattan, Maria on the fire escape, the Jets and Sharks ready to rumble and Anita flashing her skirts and singing about the Isle of Manhattan. Things had changed from earlier in the season when they moved more tentatively. Now the cast owned the stage.</p>
        <p>Steve Steiner, the Surflight's artistic director, said ''West Side Story'' had sold out every single performance, and ticket sales for the entire summer were up by 10 percent.</p>
        <p>There had also been problems. A director and a choreographer dropped out at the last minute, some of the cast had left, and two family members of people in the production had died over the summer. ''But we persevered,'' Mr. Steiner said.</p>
        <p>And then there were financial developments. The Surflight, which is deciding whether to become a nonprofit theater, was offered two grants. One is from the State Council on the Arts for $30,000. The other is a direct grant from the State Legislature for $50,000.</p>
        <p>The direct grant, in the form a budgetary line item, was requested by State Senator Leonard Connors, a Republican who represents Atlantic, Burlington and Ocean Counties. ''We're very much committed to helping the arts in Southern New Jersey and throughout the state,'' he said. ''The Surflight provides a fine introduction to the theater here.''</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman could have cut the item from the budget, he said, ''but she saw the same thing we did, that the Surflight provided high-quality theater in an area that doesn't have a lot of the performing arts.''</p>
        <p>Last Sunday was a special night for Ms. Horowitz, her last performing at the Surflight. After the last performance of ''West Side Story,'' she picked up her makeup and dancing shoes from the dressing room, got in a car with her parents and headed home for Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Out on the streets around the Surf light, audience members were strolling home through the fragrant summer night, some singing songs from ''West Side Story.'' Overhead, the stars were twinkling down on this little Jersey town where other stars are born or try to be.</p>
        <p>VICTOR/VICTORIA</p>
        <p>Surflight Theater, Beach and Engleside Avenues, Beach Haven.</p>
        <p>Through next Sunday. Each day at 8 p.m.; Wednesday matinee at 2 p.m.  (609) 492-9477</p>
        <p>Summer Stock</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are looking at New Jersey's only summer stock theater. The previous articles were about performing and keeping the theater in business.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
