<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Notion of Tax for Super-Rich Hits With a Thud in Trenton</title>
    <meta content="03POL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Policy Perspective (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shue, Jon J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDB1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Notion of Tax for Super-Rich Hits With a Thud in Trenton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Halbfinger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Halbfinger column on proposal by New Jersey Policy Perspective head, Jon J Shure, to raise income taxes and impose 'financial assets tax' on super-rich so that property taxes can be reduced for the middle class; no one in Trenton is ready to jump at the idea; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jon J. Shure knows when he's got an idea that absolutely no one in politics is going to take seriously.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shure, the head of one of New Jersey's few home-grown research organizations,  came out with a proposal last week for a blessedly simple solution to one of the state's most vexing problems: exorbitant property taxes that are choking middle-class homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jon J. Shure knows when he's got an idea that absolutely no one in politics is going to take seriously.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shure, the head of one of New Jersey's few home-grown research organizations,  came out with a proposal last week for a blessedly simple solution to one of the state's most vexing problems: exorbitant property taxes that are choking middle-class homeowners.</p>
        <p>His recommendation? Soak the rich, twice, and give everyone else a much bigger rebate check.</p>
        <p>The response in Trenton was as if someone had left a tremendous, glowing, pulsating, green hunk of radioactive waste in the middle of West State Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shure's group is called New Jersey Policy Perspective, but he is better known from his days as spokesman for Gov. Jim Florio, who was coincidentally the last politician to try raising income taxes as a way to make wealthier residents pay a greater share of the costs of government services.</p>
        <p>A decade wiser, Mr. Shure now is advocating a tax increase for only the wealthiest New Jerseyans. He would raise the income tax rate for the highest bracket of filers from 6.37 to 8.87 percent.</p>
        <p>But best of all, he would impose a new ''financial assets tax'' on the super-rich -- the 1 percent of residents with more than $2 million in stocks, bonds, trusts, and other paper assets. Anything over $2 million would be subject to a yearly tax of a quarter of 1 percent. A minuscule burden, Mr. Shure calls it.</p>
        <p>He estimates there are only 30,000 to 35,000 very wealthy people in New Jersey who would have to pay the yearly F.A.T., as he calls it. (''It just came out that way,'' he insists, about the acronym. ''And I didn't see any reason to change it.'')</p>
        <p>The idea, better known as a wealth tax, has been gaining currency in the last few years among some academics, including former Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich. A leading proponent is Edward N. Wolff of New York University, who contends that the super-rich are being grossly undertaxed, even as they gain control of more and more of the nation's assets.</p>
        <p>Property taxes exaggerate that inequity between the super-rich and everyone else, according to what Professor Wolff found. For the middle class, one's home accounts for nearly 70 percent of total wealth. But the homes of the super-rich make up less than 7 percent of their assets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shure says that the property tax, which began in colonial New Jersey as a levy of a half-penny per acre, arose in a time when only the wealthy owned their own homes and land. Now that the wealthy own so much more intangible property -- financial instruments and other investments -- than real estate, the property tax needs to be updated, he says.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a property tax in New Jersey, we have a house tax,'' Mr. Shure said. ''And when you tax a middle-class homeowner, you're taxing everything they own.''</p>
        <p>Class warfare being all the rage these days, and property taxes in New Jersey being the nation's highest, Mr. Shure's plan could make for a hot-button campaign issue. So which of the state's governor-in-waiting is ready to champion the idea?</p>
        <p>Mayor James E. McGreevey of Woodbridge, the putative Democratic nominee, didn't call back. Nor did  the spokesmen for the two Republican contenders, Assembly Speaker Jack Collins and Mayor Bret Schundler of Jersey City.</p>
        <p>Rae Hutton, a spokeswoman for Senate President Donald T. DiFrancesco, the other likely Republican candidate, barely mustered a sigh of disgust. ''It's sad,'' Ns. Hutton said. ''Democrats only know how to raise taxes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shure said he did not really expect anyone to jump at the idea; he just wanted to get a debate going. ''We're in a climate where no politician wants to be accused of raising anybody's taxes,'' he said. ''But I think the climate's changing, and the politicians are a bit behind the curve right now. I think it's going to come from the bottom up rather than the top down. Because middle-class people know that they're getting clobbered, and what the state's doing for relief isn't very much.''</p>
        <p>As evidence, he pointed to a few grassroots groups cropping up around the state that are actually calling for income tax increases to pay for property tax reductions.</p>
        <p>One, called Progressive Taxation for Education, was formed by John Meyerle, a Point Pleasant retiree. ''I think now is the time to do it,'' Mr. Meyerle said. ''We need to get a candidate who is willing to say, 'Reform is necessary, and I'll step up to the plate.' And if we can't find such a candidate, woe is us.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS David M. Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David M. Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
