<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heading Off High Bills For Heating</title>
    <meta content="03HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Oil</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDF1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heading Off High Bills For Heating</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article offers advice on controlling home heating costs in light of likelihood that heating oil and natural gas prices will skyrocket this winter; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH home heating oil and natural gas prices expected to skyrocket this winter, homeowners now have more incentive than ever to take whatever steps are necessary to keep the cold air out of their houses and the warm air in. Here are some tips for squeezing every last B.T.U. out of every bit of oil or gas your heating system consumes.</p>
        <p>''One of the toughest things about dealing with energy efficiency is that people are always looking for a silver bullet that will make a big difference in their energy bills,'' said Dale Horton, a program manager at the National Center for Appropriate Technology, a nonprofit energy-efficiency organization based in Butte, Mont. ''The problem is, the big differences are usually the result of an accumulation of little things.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH home heating oil and natural gas prices expected to skyrocket this winter, homeowners now have more incentive than ever to take whatever steps are necessary to keep the cold air out of their houses and the warm air in. Here are some tips for squeezing every last B.T.U. out of every bit of oil or gas your heating system consumes.</p>
        <p>''One of the toughest things about dealing with energy efficiency is that people are always looking for a silver bullet that will make a big difference in their energy bills,'' said Dale Horton, a program manager at the National Center for Appropriate Technology, a nonprofit energy-efficiency organization based in Butte, Mont. ''The problem is, the big differences are usually the result of an accumulation of little things.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Horton said, homeowners usually have to ''think like detectives'' when developing a strategy for saving money on home heating costs.</p>
        <p>''You have to look for all the little things that could add up to a big difference,'' he said. ''Sometimes that means examining every window and door for leaks and drafts, and sometimes it means looking at the behavior of the occupants in the house.''</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Horton said, while a small draft from around the perimeter of a single window or door might not, by itself, result in a noticeable increase in energy costs, small drafts from around all the windows and doors in a house could. At the same time, he said, the energy savings achieved by sealing and weatherstripping  every window and door in the house is going to be squandered if even one occupant of the house insists on sleeping with the windows open, even just a crack.</p>
        <p>''We all behave differently in our homes,'' he said. ''And our behavior can make a big difference.''</p>
        <p>Alan Silverstein, director of the Center for Ecological Technology, a nonprofit organization based in Pittsfield, Mass., said homeowners often determine what energy-savings measures are worth taking by trying to figure out how long it will take for the cost of the measure to be recouped. Replacing an old inefficient furnace and water heater with new high-efficiency models, for example, can result in efficiency increases of up to 30 percent. Such upgrades, he said, can easily result in sufficient savings to recoup the cost of the new appliances in just a few years, particularly in times of higher-than-average energy costs.</p>
        <p>''Any energy-saving measure that pays for itself in two or three years is going to be a very good investment,'' he said. ''And when the price of fuel increases, the payback period decreases.'' Mr. Silverstein said the best way for a homeowner to get an idea of a particular home's energy needs -- along with an idea of the time needed to recoup the cost of addressing them -- is to obtain what is known as an energy audit.</p>
        <p>''Energy audits involve a trained auditor doing a computer-based survey of the heating system in the home,'' he said, adding that the audit would involve an assessment of the heating plant itself to determine its current efficiency, as well as an examination of the structure and other equipment in the house to determine where heat loss may be occurring.</p>
        <p>''The auditor might draw some heated air from the exhaust stack to determine the combustion efficiency of the system,'' he said, explaining that as with an automobile, a furnace or boiler that is running inefficiently is wasting fuel.</p>
        <p>Energy auditors will also point out ways that homeowners can save money by increasing the energy efficiency of the house. Such measures typically include increasing the amount of insulation in the attic, wrapping the hot water boiler in an insulating jacket, installing low-flow shower heads, installing a thermostat that will automatically set back the nighttime temperature to 60 degrees or so, cleaning filters on forced-air  furnaces, sealing flues in unused fireplaces, installing drapes on windows and sealing up holes around plumbing and heating pipes.</p>
        <p>''An audit report should also provide the cost-effectiveness of taking different energy-efficiency measures,'' he said, explaining, for example, that while it would always be worthwhile insulating an uninsulated attic, it might not always be cost-effective to supplement existing insulation if the added cost will produce only minimal savings.</p>
        <p>An energy auditor can also determine how ''leaky'' a house is by using a ''blower door.''</p>
        <p>''I use blower doors on new houses to test how tight they are,'' said Chris Benedict, a Manhattan architect, who specializes in energy-efficient home designs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benedict explained that a blower door is a large fan encased in a door-sized panel that is installed in a door opening leading to the outside of the house. With all of the windows and other exterior doors of the house shut tight, the fan is then used to pull air out of the house. That creates a low-pressure condition inside the home, which makes it possible to pinpoint places where air is coming into the house from the outside.</p>
        <p>''You can use a smoke-pencil or a lit cigarette to see where air is flowing,'' Ms. Benedict said, adding that once infiltration points are identified they can be sealed with caulk, weatherstripping or expanding foam insulation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benedict pointed out that it is generally not wise to make a home too airtight because combustion appliances -- like furnaces, gas water heaters and gas dryers -- can pull exhaust gases back into the house if there is no source of fresh air for combustion. And that, she said, could result in a dangerous buildup of deadly carbon monoxide in the house.</p>
        <p>Alex Wilson, editor of Environmental Building News, a trade publication in Brattleboro, Vt., said that for owners of older homes with uninsulated exterior walls, now might be the time to think about having those walls insulated.</p>
        <p>''This will make a huge difference, especially in an old, leaky house,'' he said, adding that there are several types of insulation that can be blown  into the cavities of existing walls.</p>
        <p>''The most common type of blown-in insulation is cellulose,'' he said, explaining that the material is actually ground-up paper that has been treated with a fire retardant. ''But you can also blow in fiberglass and open-celled polyurethane foam.''</p>
        <p>And while insulating existing exterior walls is not inexpensive -- the work must be done by a licensed professional using the proper equipment -- fuel costs may be lowered considerably, particularly in light of the high fuel prices expected for this winter.</p>
        <p>''This may well be the year where significant investments in energy efficiency can be justified from a financial standpoint,'' Mr. Wilson said.  ''And keep in mind that most energy saving measures will also significantly improve the comfort of the home as well.''</p>
        <p>Homeowners who are interested in obtaining an energy audit of their homes can contact their fuel dealer or utility provider. Some utility companies provide audits for their customers and those that do not can usually provide the names of experienced independent auditors. The cost of an audit can be $200 or more, depending on the size of the house and the work performed.</p>
        <p>Those who want to perform their own home energy audit can do so on the internet by going to the Department of Energy's Web site at www.homeenergysaver.lbl.gov and following the instructions found there.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
