<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Fassel and Groh on the Spot, Even Before the Season</title>
    <meta content="Y03AND$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Groh, Al</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5D71030F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Fassel and Groh on the Spot, Even Before the Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses New York Jets coach Al Groh and New York Giants coach Jim Fassel, both under pressure to lead teams to winning seasons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS they prowl the sideline, Al Groh and Jim Fassel will each be surrounded by invisible jackals for different reasons: Groh in his first year as the Jets coach, Fassel in what could be his last year as the Giants coach.</p>
        <p>With any other franchise, Groh would be given the benefit of the doubt that every rookie head coach receives, at least at the start. But as Bill Parcells's successor, he will be judged differently. He must maintain the level of excellence that Parcells established after all those Jets seasons of frustration under so many other uninspiring coaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS they prowl the sideline, Al Groh and Jim Fassel will each be surrounded by invisible jackals for different reasons: Groh in his first year as the Jets coach, Fassel in what could be his last year as the Giants coach.</p>
        <p>With any other franchise, Groh would be given the benefit of the doubt that every rookie head coach receives, at least at the start. But as Bill Parcells's successor, he will be judged differently. He must maintain the level of excellence that Parcells established after all those Jets seasons of frustration under so many other uninspiring coaches.</p>
        <p>Groh has the opportunity to be Parcells's first successful successor. Ray Handley flopped with the Giants. Pete Carroll was eventually dismissed by the New England Patriots, prompting Bill Belichick's hiring there after spurning his Jets contract as Parcells's successor.</p>
        <p>Groh knows the trouble he's in. He was on the Giants' staff in 1991 when Handley was named to succeed Parcells, who had suddenly left the Giants after their Super Bowl XXV victory. Handley, who had been an impressive running-backs coach, had never been a head coach; not in college, not in high school. And as the Giants' head coach, he was a bust.</p>
        <p>Handley's tenure opened with an exciting 16-14 Monday night victory over the San Francisco 49ers, but those Giants struggled to an 8-8 record that season, then drifted to 6-10 before he was fired.</p>
        <p>Groh, who had been the Wake Forest head coach for six seasons, spent only that one season on Handley's staff. In 1992, he was Belichick's defensive coordinator with the Cleveland Browns before rejoining Parcells in New England in 1993 and then going to the Jets with him in 1997.</p>
        <p>''Whatever principles bound our operation together when Bill was the Giants' coach,'' Groh said of the reaction to Handley's takeover, ''Ray departed from those principles.''</p>
        <p>Handley simply could not ''lead the pack'' as a head coach. He was not decisive enough, not tough enough, not stern enough. All the Giants' players soon realized it. Handley was the substitute teacher the students didn't respect. He was everything that Groh now knows he cannot be as Parcells's third successor.</p>
        <p>Handley's mistake was trying to do things his way instead of trying to continue to do them the Parcells way.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Groh wisely wants to do things the Parcells way. If only because the Jets' nucleus is accustomed to the Parcells way. But it won't be easy, especially on defense. For the previous three seasons, the assistant head coach, Belichick, the linebacker coach, Groh, and the line coach, Romeo Crenel (now with the Cleveland Browns), put together the defensive game plans.</p>
        <p>But now Belichick and Crenel are elsewhere, Groh is the head coach and Parcells, as the director of football operations, is no longer directly involved in supervising the defensive thinking.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mike Nolan, the Redskins' defensive coordinator the last three years and the Giants' defensive coordinator for four years before that, is the Jets' new guru. Ray Hamilton is still the defensive line coach, but Bob Sutton, from Army, is now in charge of the linebackers, and Todd Boles, from Grambling, tutors the defensive backs.</p>
        <p>Boles has three Super Bowl rings as a defensive back (two with the Redskins, one with the 49ers), but as an assistant coach, he's a rookie.</p>
        <p>At least for now, the Jets' experienced defensive players are more familiar with the Jets' defensive philosophy than the new assistant coaches.</p>
        <p>In other years, whenever Parcells moved from the Giants to New England and then to the Jets, he took virtually his entire staff with him. As he often explained, ''I didn't want to have to coach the coaches,'' meaning new assistant coaches. But on the Jets now, Groh will be coaching some coaches.</p>
        <p>How well the Jets do this season might depend on how well Groh coaches those coaches as much as on how well he coaches the players.</p>
        <p>As for Fassel, his return will depend on the Giants moving in what Ernie Accorsi, their general manager, called ''the right direction.''</p>
        <p>Accorsi remembered Dick Vermeil insisting that the St. Louis Rams, despite a 4-12 record in 1998, were moving in the right direction. And as the reigning Super Bowl champions now, the Rams obviously were. But under Fassel the last three seasons, the Giants have been moving in reverse: 9-7 (and a wild-card playoff loss), then 8-8, then 7-9 last season.</p>
        <p>Another unfulfilling season and Fassel won't fulfill his one-year contract extension through the 2001 season.</p>
        <p>If the road to the Super Bowl goes through the X-ray room for every contender, the road to Fassel's return could go through the X-ray room, too. The Giants' depth, especially on the offensive line, is skimpy.</p>
        <p>Even if healthy, the Giants look no better than 8-8, but the Jets, if healthy, could go 9-7 and steal a wild card.</p>
        <p>And if Peyton Manning stays healthy, the Indianapolis Colts will outscore the Redskins, 35-27, in Super Bowl XXXV.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
