<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes! It's Him! (Whaddya Mean, Never Heard of Him?)</title>
    <meta content="03LORE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CITY LORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Custen, George F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DD1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes! It's Him! (Whaddya Mean, Never Heard of Him?)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE F. CUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Custen, George F</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes vast differences between celebrity sightings in Brooklyn and Manhattan; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite their statistical rarity, the famous seem to be everywhere in New York. So residents take it for granted that from time to time, they will come face to face with someone famous.</p>
        <p>Naturally, then, in this celebrity-conscious realm, I was not surprised when I recently sighted someone of fame under water. Swimming laps in my neighborhood gym, I saw alongside me Courtney B. Vance, star of John Guare's celebrity-themed play ''Six Degrees of Separation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite their statistical rarity, the famous seem to be everywhere in New York. So residents take it for granted that from time to time, they will come face to face with someone famous.</p>
        <p>Naturally, then, in this celebrity-conscious realm, I was not surprised when I recently sighted someone of fame under water. Swimming laps in my neighborhood gym, I saw alongside me Courtney B. Vance, star of John Guare's celebrity-themed play ''Six Degrees of Separation.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after, from behind the wheel of my Jeep, I found myself staring into a rather mad pair of eyes, which, I soon realized, belonged to John Turturro. This performance was far more powerful than his tour de force in the film ''Barton Fink.'' In this instance, however, the Method had not motivated Mr. Turturro. Here, the likely cause was that I had nearly run him over.</p>
        <p>But wait. I must tell you: these celebrity sightings were not in Manhattan, the spot most people mean when they talk of New York and fame. They were in my neighborhood of Park Slope, Brooklyn. Can it be that my borough is now full of the famous, too?</p>
        <p>Alas, no chance. My encounters with Mr. Vance and Mr. Turturro notwithstanding, the fame game in Brooklyn is far, far different than Manhattan's. Here are some of the distinctions.</p>
        <p>The Lorenz Hart Principle</p>
        <p>It is true that the artist Joseph Cornell seemed so attached to Queens that he could rarely bring himself to leave his house (let alone the borough). And it is true that Henry Miller insisted that outside Brooklyn, the rest of the country didn't ''exist for me, except as idea, or history or literature.'' But most people, certainly most famous people, prefer Lorenz Hart's spin: whether born there or not, they would have Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In fact, stargazing there is like fishing for trout in a stream that is constantly being restocked. Manhattanites go forth armed with confidence fueled by celebrity options closed off to Brooklynites.</p>
        <p>The Second-Tier Rule</p>
        <p>Still, many famous people at least had the good sense to be born in Brooklyn; you can trample upon their names at the Botanical Garden's Walk of Fame. And many writers present and past, from Paul Auster to Marianne Moore, have chosen to live in or near my neighborhood alone.</p>
        <p>But even with such celebrity richness in our midst, Brooklynites are loath to compare their borough's celebrities to Manhattan's. The reason: Brooklyn's leading lights are relatively dim. While Manhattan friends of my teenage years plotted ways to foil hotel security and meet the Rolling Stones,  my youthful nights were spent wondering, could the same Beverly Road building in which my Brooklyn aunt and uncle lived also shelter, as was rumored, a being the stature of Shecky Green, the prince of Borscht Belt comedy?</p>
        <p>There are exceptions, but a Brooklyn star search is akin to being trapped in a world where many stars resemble the misfit entertainers in the Woody Allen movie ''Broadway Danny Rose.'' Many of Brooklyn's big names are the one-hit wonders, baseball players with career batting averages under .215, people related to someone famous (like Scott Baio's cousin, whose picture gazed down on me from the wall of a Bay Ridge restaurant) and former eminences like Helen Morgan, the star of 20's musicals like ''Show Boat,'' who arrive in Brooklyn when they are sadly down on their luck.</p>
        <p>A radical minority go so far as to insist that Brooklyn's specialty is not celebrities at all but their mothers. Their numbers include Mrs. Murphy (Yo! Eddie's mama), Konigsberg (Woody Allen), Streisand, Schrift (Shelley Winters), Moore (Mary Tyler's mom), Marrener (Susan Hayward's mom) and Cansino (Rita Hayworth).</p>
        <p>Celebrity Drift</p>
        <p>After their birth, many celebrities indeed continue to live in Brooklyn; for a time. The trajectory of F. Murray Abraham (the Park Slope Oscar winner who got his statuette playing a jealous composer in ''Amadeus'') illustrates this rule: truly successful celebrities move to Manhattan. Exceptions to the celebrity-migration law -- Louis Armstrong was a longtime resident of Queens -- do exist. But they are rare.</p>
        <p>The Deli Connection</p>
        <p>Brooklyn is densely populated by a unique celebrity genus: those show-biz pod people whose names and rictus-smiling, toupee-rich, airbrushed photos adorn the walls of many establishments. No one has ever heard of them. Fewer still have ever seen them in the flesh. No one (except, perhaps, Joe Franklin) has ever witnessed one of their performances. Yet, they possess one of celebrityhood's undeniable markers: their head shots, complete with inscriptions, hang near the cash register in every diner, deli or dry cleaner in Kings County.</p>
        <p>There is yet another breed of Brooklyn celebrity, as exemplified by my Brooklyn-born great-aunt. She enjoyed a kind of power that came to few souls in any borough. Though not great herself, she was so proximate to greatness that it was hard to distinguish pilot fish from shark. Her aura rested on a single powerful connection. It was rumored, frequently by her, that she and my grandmother Bessie enjoyed triumphant evenings playing cards in the Bronx with no less a figure than ''la mamma di Schnozzola.'' In Brooklyn, this putative link to Mrs. Durante was, for a time, enough to make my once-removed aunt a kind of celebrity, only twice removed.</p>
        <p>All these ruminations forced me to face the sad truth: Brooklyn attracts celebrities who are not true celebrities. Manhattan gets nights of a thousand stars; we get the flights of fading stars.</p>
        <p>''What Is He Doing Here?''</p>
        <p>Brooklyn's great virtue may be that indeed, it is a real place whose people stand in admirable relief to the poseurs and mannequins inhabiting some Manhattan neighborhoods. Yet we nevertheless all hold celebrities to a different standard. Whatever our envy-laden carpings, we expect their demeanor, financial status, place of domicile and the sites they frequent to be more glamorous than ours. So, when we see them hopping out of a Manhattan bistro, fine. But when we bump into them in Brooklyn, we feel as if they have violated some modern-day version of the infamous studio-era morals clause in their contracts. We get suspicious. Long accustomed to seeing media representations of Brooklyn in which every citizen is a Ralph Kramden or a character played by William Bendix, the rootedness of such gods in our humble beloved turf makes them seem out of place.</p>
        <p>The significance of the Brooklyn celebrity connection was doubly brought home to me by a neighbor who, though he requested anonymity, attained his stature via a continuing role in the HBO hit series ''The Sopranos.'' Recently, several fans spotted him not only in Brooklyn, but in line in the unemployment office. The rapture of recognition quickly turned to suspicion. What, he was asked, would a real star be doing with them, on the unemployment line?</p>
        <p>Brooklynites should not conclude they are wanting in the fame department, however. For the greatest concentration of eminent New Yorkers is far removed from Manhattan's bright lights. They have left the city for soothing and peaceful Brooklyn venues: its many fine cemeteries.</p>
        <p>Passing through the massive iron gates of Green-Wood Cemetery, which sprawls between Windsor Terrace and Sunset Park,  you enter a world of improbable gatherings: Horace Greeley chats with Lola Montez, while Boss Tweed skulks in the background in full view of Samuel F. B. Morse and an entire entombment of piano-manufacturing Steinways.</p>
        <p>A short distance to the west, Montgomery Clift has been sighted (again!) in Prospect Park, or rather in the Quaker Cemetery in the park's northeast section. As befitting a deity, this former resident of Manhattan now receives callers beneath a grave designed by the architect of President Kennedy's shrine at Arlington.</p>
        <p>In this light, the title of one of Thomas Wolfe's best-known short stories, ''Only the Dead Know Brooklyn,'' is more prescient than that Brooklyn-hater knew.</p>
        <p>CITY LORE George F. Custen, a resident of Park Slope, is director of the film studies program at the City University Graduate Center and author of ''20th Century's Fox: Darryl F. Zanuck and the Culture of Hollywood.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">George F. Custen, a resident of Park Slope, is director of the film studies program at the City University Graduate Center and author of ''20th Century's Fox: Darryl F. Zanuck and the Culture of Hollywood.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
