<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spano's Tax-Cut Goal Questioned</title>
    <meta content="03SPAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DA1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spano's Tax-Cut Goal Questioned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans question whether Westchester County Executive Andrew Spano will be able to keep pledge to reduce county property taxes by 15 percent without compromising county's long-term financial health (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Andrew J. Spano became the second Democrat ever to be elected county executive in Westchester, he did it partly with a pledge to reduce county property taxes by 15 percent.</p>
        <p>But more than halfway through his administration, and just two months before he must present his third county budget, Mr. Spano has achieved less than a quarter of his goal, and some are skeptical that he will be able to keep his pledge without affecting the county's long-term financial health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Andrew J. Spano became the second Democrat ever to be elected county executive in Westchester, he did it partly with a pledge to reduce county property taxes by 15 percent.</p>
        <p>But more than halfway through his administration, and just two months before he must present his third county budget, Mr. Spano has achieved less than a quarter of his goal, and some are skeptical that he will be able to keep his pledge without affecting the county's long-term financial health.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano says his next budget, to be presented in November, will include more tax cuts, though he would not specify the amount. But Republicans question: at what price?</p>
        <p>''If he does not deliver,'' said James E. Cavanaugh, the chairman of the county's Republican Committee, ''then clearly it is a political problem for him in the next election because he made such a big deal about it when he got elected. It was the centerpiece of his campaign.''</p>
        <p>And James Maisano, a Republican legislator, said that he felt Mr. Spano's pledge was ''irresponsible and impossible'' from the moment he heard it three years ago.</p>
        <p>A 15 percent cut, he said, would cause institutional changes in the county's budgeting practices that might not be felt in good economic times but could prompt financial imbalance in the future.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Spano said that he could make most of the tax cuts he promised without reducing county services or jeopardizing the county's long-term outlook. And he said that naysayers fail to understand the tremendous shift in economics that is occurring in the midst of what he termed an information revolution.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to cut taxes just for the sake of cutting taxes,'' Mr. Spano said. ''But I think we can keep our promise or come very close to it. My problem is when we thought we had it done last year, the state budget came out and it significantly reduced the amount of money we normally get from them.''</p>
        <p>He said Westchester residents ''have already received over 15 percent in tax benefits because of the way we have conducted the government'' despite the cuts in state aid.</p>
        <p>He said that while he has not yet decided if he will run for re-election next year, he would feel comfortable running on his record of reducing taxes and other accomplishments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano's aides call Republican criticism ''sour grapes'' at a time when the economy is humming along, unemployment rates are low and 1,500 people have been cut from the county's welfare caseloads.</p>
        <p>Westchester has long been reluctant to resort to such budget gimmicks as using one-time revenues to pay ongoing costs, a tactic practiced in Nassau County, and it enjoys the highest credit rating on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''We are very comfortable with the county's current financial position,'' said Robin L. Prunty, an analyst with Standard &amp; Poor's rating agency, who monitors Westchester and said that the tax cuts enacted so far have been manageable.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Spano has cut $8.8 million from the $365.6 million total property tax levy he inherited in 1998, in spite of $30 million in additional county costs for state and federal programs, Kathleen M. Carrano, the county budget director, said. To reach his 15 percent goal, Mr. Spano needs to slash another $45 million by the 2002 budget season, when he will present the last budget of his current four-year term.</p>
        <p>On the revenue side, a strong economy is providing a projected $12.3 million more than anticipated in sales tax revenues, the county's mid-year estimates show. The county has a $38 million surplus left from 1999, which can be budgeted for next year. And the county will end this year with a $29.8 million surplus, Ms. Carrano said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano's aides say the county executive has cut 164 jobs, eliminated the Department of General Services, consolidated services and made government more efficient with the use of technology.</p>
        <p>But costs are rising: the county budget has increased by $58 million in the last two years, the Board of Legislators is spending about  $500,000 more than it did in 1998 and labor costs are rising as a result of new contracts.</p>
        <p>''We should prudently budget by putting something in reserve for those times when the economy stalls or downturns,'' said Katherine S. Carsky of Yonkers, the ranking Republican legislator on the Budget and Appropriations Committee. ''The board has to be very prudent.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
