<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Little-Known Artists Add An Air of Optimism to Exhibition</title>
    <meta content="03NEWA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newark Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwabsky, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DC1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Little-Known Artists Add An Air of Optimism to Exhibition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY SCHWABSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwabsky, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Schwabsky reviews annual New Jersey Fine Arts exhibition at Newark Museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE co-curators of the New Jersey Fine Arts  Annual  the Newark Museum's curator of American art, Joseph Jacobs, and the artist Fred Wilson -- have not just adopted the new millennium into the subtitle of their exhibition at the museum here. They've started the new era in an appropriately forward-looking way by representing the state's creative ferment in the present.</p>
        <p>Not that the art they've chosen is free of dark or disturbing overtones. The exhibition includes artists like James Andrew Brown and Barbara Stork, whose work overtly addresses social and political anxieties most people would just as soon suppress. Mr. Brown's video installation on gun violence, with its deliberately crude and taunting tone, is particularly uningratiating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE co-curators of the New Jersey Fine Arts  Annual  the Newark Museum's curator of American art, Joseph Jacobs, and the artist Fred Wilson -- have not just adopted the new millennium into the subtitle of their exhibition at the museum here. They've started the new era in an appropriately forward-looking way by representing the state's creative ferment in the present.</p>
        <p>Not that the art they've chosen is free of dark or disturbing overtones. The exhibition includes artists like James Andrew Brown and Barbara Stork, whose work overtly addresses social and political anxieties most people would just as soon suppress. Mr. Brown's video installation on gun violence, with its deliberately crude and taunting tone, is particularly uningratiating.</p>
        <p>But even those works whose apparent subject matter is more anodyne or whose tone is more playful turn out to have an edge to them. By engaging with a full range of experience, from the grim to the playful, the show serves to affirm the power of the imagination over everything that, by disturbing it, stimulates it.</p>
        <p>Strange as it might seem, the exhibition's optimistic atmosphere may also have something to do with its being smaller in scale than these annuals have been in the past. This has allowed the curators to be stringent in their choices. Although few viewers are likely to enjoy the work of all 14 artists equally -- and their range makes one suspect the curators must have had some pretty heated debates before coming to an agreement -- the show is unusually consistent in quality.</p>
        <p>And that's despite the fact that the selection ranges from artists with international reputations, like the photographer Mac Adams, the sculptor Robert Lope and the conceptual artist Geoffrey Hendricks, to some who are virtually unknown.</p>
        <p>In fact, some of the brightest moments here are among the least expected. A particularly felicitous choice was that of a little-recognized abstract painter named Julius Kramer. Though he was born in 1920, Mr. Kramer paints with freshly minted gusto. His paintings are inventive and complex. Mr. Wilson refers to this artist, in an accompanying wall panel, as an Abstract Expressionist; while the generational connection is apt, the label suits the painter only if it used in a general rather than a specific sense -- in the way that it might refer to Wassily Kandinsky's paintings of the 'teens, for instance. Mr. Kramer shares with contemporaries like Joan Mitchell or Frank Kline their painterly bravado and sense of spontaneity, but his work is at once more impish and more introverted.</p>
        <p>Two other little-known artists show that realism remains a surprisingly strong option for today's artists. Jennifer Krause offers a contemporary viewpoint on landscape painting. Her works are based on photographs taken from moving cars. The subject, therefore, is not just the highway itself but the peculiar combination of speed and stasis one feels while driving. Especially in ''Untitled No. 6,'' this strange combination of opposed sensations becomes palpable on the canvas.</p>
        <p>Five of Peter Cross's 10 delicate little graphite drawings portray landscapes too -- this time evoking, not motion, but stillness so complete that it becomes downright eerie. What makes these drawings really work are the odd in-between spaces that emerge in them. In other drawings, Mr. Cross depicts landscapes with old-fashioned (though astonishingly stylish) locomotive engines seemingly marooned in them -- no cars, no tracks, just the engines. The artist's ultra-refined technique is just as seductive here as in the pure landscapes, but the evocation of nostalgia and a more overt surrealism make them seem more familiar.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
