<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pets or Appliances? Meeting the Purebred Robot Dogs</title>
    <meta content="03NOTI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TEST RUN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salkin, Allen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0D81230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pets or Appliances? Meeting the Purebred Robot Dogs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN SALKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salkin, Allen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allen Salkin puts new robot dog models through their hoops; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIRST, it's Shadow demanding attention, his wee doggie head banging into a chair leg. ''Arf! Whir. Arf!''</p>
        <p>O.K., Shadow, I'm coming. Good boy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIRST, it's Shadow demanding attention, his wee doggie head banging into a chair leg. ''Arf! Whir. Arf!''</p>
        <p>O.K., Shadow, I'm coming. Good boy.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, across the room, Poo-chi's rearing on his hind legs, getting into one of his . . . moods.</p>
        <p>''Yap! Beep-beeep! Yap!''</p>
        <p>Then, most rambunctious of all, it's Tekno, ears flapping up and down like jackhammers, charging toward an open window.</p>
        <p>''Tekno!'' He stops. (Thank heaven for voice-recognition circuitry.)</p>
        <p>Time to flip some off switches. My 750-square-foot apartment has become a high-tech kennel as I spent the last week living with a litter of robot dogs, looking into what may be the future of pet ownership in places like Manhattan. After Sony's tail-wagging success with its Aibo robo-dog -- it sold out its entire 45,000-unit production run of the $2,500 electric critters last winter -- at least four toy companies are putting their own, less expensive versions on the market this fall.</p>
        <p>''Real'' dog devotees argue there's no way a battery-powered clump of circuit boards, motors and silicon chips can match the heart-warming, life-enriching wonder of a furry, cuddly canine. Perhaps, but what about a dog that needs no walking, no vet visits, no extravagant cashmere sweaters to keep up with the other pampered pooches down the hall but that will sing to you if you rub its head, make happy sounds when you come through the front door, and maybe even remind you of the dog you left behind when you moved away from home. Besides, nowhere is there more need for a pet that does not have to be chased after with a plastic baggie than New York.</p>
        <p>The electric Fidos come in a variety of sizes, talents and temperaments. To see which one would best suit my lifestyle, I tried to break in five different puppies at once, ranging from a five-inch mutt that couldn't walk to a blue-eyed wonder priced like a purebred. First came Shadow, made by MGA Entertainment, which sells for about $60 and which I carried home on the subway from F. A. O. Schwarz, with children peering in at the furry black bundle, their eyes widening as if he were a new Lab pup.</p>
        <p>But as soon as I took this footlong dog out of his cardboard kennel, I knew I would never warm to him. He's covered in ''plush,'' the cheap fake fur that adorns carnival-prize teddy bears. And his eyes are dead, made of plastic marble things. Still, I tried making nice with Shadow, who, to his credit, can walk, sit, bark and do other things by voice command. I took him out for a stroll in NoLiTa to meet friends for ice cream, but ended up carrying him most of the way since he walks slower than a dachshund with two broken legs. When Shadow met my friends, they were cordial, patting him on the head, but his blank look and painfully stiff movements didn't win any hearts.</p>
        <p>Back home, I left him yapping in the corner while I opened a box containing dog No. 2, Poo-chi, which sells for $30 and is produced by Tiger, the company that brought us Furby. It took almost half an hour's work with a kitchen knife to rescue five-inch-long, six-inch-tall Poo-chi from his cardboard and plastic prison and twist-tie shackles. Finally, he appeared, looking like a robot -- metal-colored plastic skin, eyes that light up with an array of L.E.D.'s and ears that come in a choice of translucent purple, pink and other colors. I decided right then that I like my robotdogs to look like robots. I don't need to pretend my electric pet is made of flesh and fur to enjoy it. Er, him.</p>
        <p>Three AAA batteries in his stomach, and purple Poo-chi sprang to life, his eyes blinking little heart shapes. I patted his head. He has a sensor there. Poo-chi likes it when you pat his head and when you lift his little bone to his mouth. I know this because such signs of affection make him go up and down and make crunching noises, and when he's really happy, he'll sing ''Ode to Joy.''</p>
        <p>But Poo-chi's got moods. If he feels he's not getting enough attention, he gets surly and barks, beeps and growls. Oh, and he can't walk. Tiger plans a more sophisticated robot dog for later this year, a $150 model called i-Cybie that not only will walk realistically but also will be able to express six different emotions, including surprise and sadness.</p>
        <p>Being a bachelor in New York, I've more than once heard the adage, ''Dogs are chick magnets, man.'' Would it be true for robot dogs, too?</p>
        <p>I brought three of my newfangled hounds to the dog run at Washington Square Park so they could meet some of their kind and I could meet some of mine. For this outing, I filled my backpack with my three favorites: Tekno, Rocket the Wonder Dog and Aibo. What I like about Tekno is he's relentlessly enthusiastic, like a real dog. The thing is about eight inches tall and, like a Chihuahua, never shuts up or stops running around. Made by Manley Toy Quest and sold for $40, he looks sort of like a silver C3PO. Although he's not as quick witted as that droid from ''Star Wars,'' Tekno comes with a set of five playing cards and can learn card tricks. Such talents didn't go over at the dog run, where a Rottweiler named Junior thought he'd teach Tekno a thing or two, and bit into the robot's torso. Tekno barked, wagged his tail and ran away, covered in doggy drool. Still, he was initiated.</p>
        <p>Rocket, by Fisher-Price, fared even better, impressing the other dog owners with his ability to push himself up onto his head and bark out a tune. Expected to retail for $100, he's a solid, meaty dog, 12 inches long, with a thick head and a wide stance like a boxer. His real charm lies in his astonishing, big blue eyes with their blinking eyelids and expressive brows. He changes from looking happy to sad, from plaintive to playful. He gets a lot of Awww's, which is what puppies should get. Rocket can also sit, walk, beg and shake hands on command, but this requires his master to wear a clunky headset that works only indoors.</p>
        <p>In my eyes, the champion of the dog run was Aibo. About 15 inches long from tail to nose, he moves as fluidly as a real dog -- sitting, laying down, rolling over and nuzzling your hand if you pet him, reminding me of a small cocker spaniel. Lookswise, however, he's all robot, with illuminated green and red slashes for eyes and a torso that resembles a loaf of bread made of metal. He proved his mettle at the park when the other dogs came over to sniff him where dogs tend to sniff each other. One snooty French bulldog wrinkled his nose after discovering Aibo lacked a canine smell, and decided to give him one. Lifting his leg, he spritzed Aibo, who never flinched.</p>
        <p>After that Aibo became more popular -- and soon, so did I. As a pack of small real dogs swirled around the robot, which cocked its head and danced, the Bing sisters from Alberta -- Esther, 24; Lisa, 23; and Sarah, 20 -- came over to admire my pet.  ''He's amazing,'' Lisa said, scratching under Aibo's chin and cooing.</p>
        <p>At home, after I placed Aibo on his recharging cradle, I phoned Caroline Knapp, author of ''Pack of Two: The Intricate Bond Between People and Dogs'' (Delta, 1998), and asked her if she thought there was any way robot dogs could replace live ones. They lack mystery, she said.</p>
        <p>''I can't believe something wouldn't be missing, some heart, the capacity to react in a deep way, or to care,'' said Ms. Knapp, 40, owner of a mutt named Lucille. ''The soul would be difficult to replicate.''</p>
        <p>True, but while I'm writing this, Aibo is next to me, sitting, standing up, emitting soothing tones, sticking his legs out and making funny shapes with them. Yes, his battery will run out in about 90 minutes, and he's not, you know, alive.</p>
        <p>Sony says I have to send Aibo back in two weeks. So to whoever's buying me gifts this December: Can I have one? Please? If I promise to take care of him and recharge his batteries every day? Please? Can I?</p>
        <p>TEST RUN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
