<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suggestions for Mounting Dry Wallboard</title>
    <meta content="03WCLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE/OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walls</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Edward R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D71430F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suggestions for Mounting Dry Wallboard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipinski, Edward R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Lipinski Inside/Out column offers suggestions for installing dry wallboard; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEFORE the introduction of gypsum wallboard, interior walls were finished with plaster. Wallboard is essentially a flat sheet of plaster sandwiched between sheets of special paper. Unlike plaster, wallboard is fastened to the studs in a dry state, and for this reason it is frequently called drywall. (It is also sometimes called Sheetrock, but this is a trade name of the USG Corporation and should only be used in reference to its product.)</p>
        <p>The thickness of wallboard varies from one-fourth to five-eighths of an inch in eighth-inch increments. The half-inch thickness is best for most uses. Use the thicker five-eighths-inch board in areas where a firewall is required or on walls to muffle sound transmission. The thinner grades, three-eighths and one-fourth of an inch, should only be used for curved wall surfaces or on walls where the new material will have to match the thickness of a thin adjacent wall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEFORE the introduction of gypsum wallboard, interior walls were finished with plaster. Wallboard is essentially a flat sheet of plaster sandwiched between sheets of special paper. Unlike plaster, wallboard is fastened to the studs in a dry state, and for this reason it is frequently called drywall. (It is also sometimes called Sheetrock, but this is a trade name of the USG Corporation and should only be used in reference to its product.)</p>
        <p>The thickness of wallboard varies from one-fourth to five-eighths of an inch in eighth-inch increments. The half-inch thickness is best for most uses. Use the thicker five-eighths-inch board in areas where a firewall is required or on walls to muffle sound transmission. The thinner grades, three-eighths and one-fourth of an inch, should only be used for curved wall surfaces or on walls where the new material will have to match the thickness of a thin adjacent wall.</p>
        <p>Wallboard is also available with a water-resistant core. This product should be installed in areas where humidity may be a problem, as in damp basements. Water-resistant wallboard is not waterproof, however, and should not be used in wet areas like showers (where it is best to install cement backer board with a waterproof membrane).</p>
        <p>The standard width of wallboard panels is 4 feet. Panels vary in length from 6 to 16 feet. The most popular lengths are 8 and 12 feet. The larger panels cover more area, creating fewer joints to tape, but they are  heavy -- 12-foot panels weigh 82 pounds; 8-foot panels weigh 55  pounds -- and are difficult to maneuver in small rooms.</p>
        <p>You can use drywall nails or screws to secure the panels to the studs, but screws are superior fasteners because they do not pop loose as nails can. Use 1 1/4-inch screws for mounting half-inch-thick wallboard, and 1 5/8-inch screws for five-eighths-inch-thick panels. The ideal tool to use for driving drywall screws is a drywall screwgun (this can be rented at rental centers). It is better than a variable-speed drill because it has an adjustable nose, which allows you to set the screws at a precise depth, and it operates at low torque so the screws will not rip into the plaster core.</p>
        <p>To estimate the quantity of material needed, add the total surface area that you intend to panel. Do not deduct the area of the doors and windows unless they are very large. Then divide that number by the total square feet per sheet. A 4-by-8 panel covers 32 square feet and a 4-by-12 panel covers 48 square feet.</p>
        <p>Drywall does not store well, so try to order the exact number of panels needed. At your work site, stack the panels on edge, making sure they are evenly supported so they do not bend or warp.</p>
        <p>Before mounting the wallboard, check the condition of the plumbing and electrical lines in the walls and make any repairs or additions while everything is still exposed. Next, check the corners where adjacent walls meet and where the walls and ceiling join. Usually the corner posts and the top plates do not extend far enough to provide support for the drywall. It is best to nail backers made of two-by-fours to provide mounting surfaces in these places.</p>
        <p>If you are finishing an entire room, start by installing the ceiling panels (called the lids) first, and then work on the walls from the top down. When the wall panels are in place, they will support the ceiling.</p>
        <p>Lifting drywall panels overhead is hard work. You will need a helper for this.</p>
        <p>You can also rent a drywall jack (also called a lift) at outlets to raise the panels and hold them in place while you secure them to the joists.</p>
        <p>Whenever possible, try to install complete panels so you will have fewer joints to tape over. There will be areas where you will have to cut a panel to fit. First, mark the length needed on the finish side of the board, then score across the line with a utility knife. Use a metal straightedge as a guide. Stand the wallboard on edge and bend it toward the backside; this will snap the board at the score line. Once the board breaks, fold it back to form a right angle. Cut the backing paper at the fold with the utility knife.</p>
        <p>Press the panel against the studs and drive the screws, spaced evenly every 12 inches, through the board into the studs. It is important to drive the screws so the heads are slightly depressed below the surface of the panel yet not so deep that the screw breaks through the paper. If you do drive a screw too deep, install another about an inch away, then remove the improperly set screw.</p>
        <p>INSIDE/OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
