<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; For Jocks, Where Is the Dignity?</title>
    <meta content="03VECS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; For Jocks, Where Is the Dignity?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses revealing clothing worn, and sometimes taken off, by athletes; says double standard is perpetuated by media and advertising; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TUCK in your shirt. That's what our moms always told us, but what did they know? Now, there is a great international shirt-raising movement.</p>
        <p>The other day at a tennis clinic, a number of women asked -- begged, beseeched, goaded, teased -- the young dude Jan-Michael Gambill to raise his shirt high enough so they could get a glimpse of his abs. Needless to say, he obliged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TUCK in your shirt. That's what our moms always told us, but what did they know? Now, there is a great international shirt-raising movement.</p>
        <p>The other day at a tennis clinic, a number of women asked -- begged, beseeched, goaded, teased -- the young dude Jan-Michael Gambill to raise his shirt high enough so they could get a glimpse of his abs. Needless to say, he obliged.</p>
        <p>Show us your abs! Show us your abs! This is the female suburban version of the sound at auto races and the infield of the Kentucky Derby, where roving packs of men chant a somewhat similar demand at women, some of whom cooperate and some of whom keep moving before it gets even uglier.</p>
        <p>Now, shirts are flying. Brandi Chastain at the World Cup. Andre Agassi practicing with his shirt off. Guys with truly ugly bodies running bare-chested in the public streets, badly in need of a citation from the Beauty Police. Soccer players whipping off jerseys at every goal until they start getting yellow-carded, which creates a worldwide 38th Parallel above which they cannot yank.</p>
        <p>Then there is Jenny Thompson, aspirant to swimming gold medals at the Summer Games, who voluntarily pulled off the top of her bathing suit during a photo shoot for Sports Illustrated. She posed with her fists strategically in front of her chest while the old pro from S.I. clicked off a few shots, with Thompson's boyfriend standing nearby, reportedly with no problem whatsoever.</p>
        <p>It was 30 seconds of hi-jinks among friends, or maybe it was calculated, but needless to say the magazine went big with the photo, and the polemics have been raging ever since.</p>
        <p>The debate crosses all the demographics. A guy half my age, whom I often call for advice, thinks it was a tacky move on Thompson's part. One woman I know says, no harm, no foul. A male columnist whom I respect says the prudes should all lighten up. A lot of women I know are offended.</p>
        <p>Personally, I reacted both ways. I read every word of the excellent article, liked Thompson a lot, and enjoyed the photo of her confidence, her muscles, her posture, her athleticism, and so on and so on. Anybody who says her pose was not partly about sex is being hypocritical, but then again, so am I, because I looked more than once, before I asked, ''Gee, I wonder if she should be doing that?''</p>
        <p>Women, after all, are trying to get past the tendencies of men to run in dog packs and throw cold water on women, and start groping them, as was recently done in Central Park in New York. It doesn't do to say that women should not be wearing suggestive outfits on a warm Sunday in the park. The men acted like wanton animals. But is there something going on in our culture that gives men permission to act like that?</p>
        <p>It couldn't have anything to do with the double standard in television, the print media, advertising, movies, videos, pro wrestling sadomasachists, our entire sex-obsessed public life, could it? In this day and age, women are still worth geometrically more if they vamp, even world-level athletes.</p>
        <p>Thompson does not see it that way. The swimmer is en route to Sydney, so her agent, Sue Rodin, spoke for her the other day.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing seductive in that pose,'' Rodin said. ''Jenny said, 'I worked hard for that body and I'm proud of it.' I'd like people to talk more about her accomplishments.''</p>
        <p>That would be fine except that Thompson changed the mood by whipping off her top for the same folks who give us that annual foolishness called the Swimsuit Issue.</p>
        <p>''There are two issues here,'' said Donna Lopiano, the president of the Women's Sports Foundation. ''One was Jenny's decision. Did she stop to think about her impact on younger women? Would a sportswriter tell his 10-year-old daughter, 'You can do that some day?' I doubt it.</p>
        <p>''The other issue is the ethical decision of the media,'' Lopiano added. ''I haven't seen a nude photo of Tiger Woods with his hands in front of him, and I don't think I will.''</p>
        <p>This is not to say that male athletes do not relish the impact of their physiques as well as the aura of their athletic accomplishments. Many enjoy being photographed without shirts on. In American society, there still is a double standard.</p>
        <p>''We go to the beach in Europe and most women don't have tops on,'' said one of my Italian journalist friends. ''Maybe you look, but it's not a big deal.'' Of course, my European friends can't understand Watergate or Clintongate, either. They think we're nuts.</p>
        <p>The debate goes on at the United States Open, where Venus and Serena Williams squeeze their healthy physiques into tennis dresses of their own design, featuring tight fabric and strategic cutouts. I sat with three African-American women with tennis backgrounds during a Williams match not long ago, and they were rolling their eyes as if to say, girl, get some clothes on.</p>
        <p>Then there is Anna Kournikova, who wears outfits that could be labeled Late Lolita or Early Bardot. She can play but has never won a tournament, and is making a ton of money from advertisements commissioned with a knowing leer by all concerned, whether she wants to admit it or not.</p>
        <p>Everybody's into the double-standard act. American Express is using an advertisement that calls Bjorn Borg a ''stalwart'' but Martina Hingis a ''femme fatale.'' What's that all about? I could get really angry about star female athletes mimicking the doxies that many men want them to be, and I'm sure somebody would say, ''Hey, Mack, keep your shirt on.'' Everybody should.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
