<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Return Of the Stock Pickers</title>
    <meta content="WATC03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suria, Ravi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olstein, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Gretchen Morgenson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6D81330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Return Of the Stock Pickers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gretchen Morgenson Market Watch column on return of stock picker's market, where hottest shares are found off the beaten track and where individual stocks can outshine indexes; Olstein Financial Alert Fund manager Bob Olstein and Lehman Brothers analyst Ravi Suria offer picks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR years, investors have won big by following the crowd. Piling into index funds, a handful of big-company technology shares or any stock that happened to be moving up was the name of the game.</p>
        <p>So far this year, however, many of the hottest shares have been of some companies found off the beaten track. Shares of midcap companies and utilities, for instance, have been the market's unlikely stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR years, investors have won big by following the crowd. Piling into index funds, a handful of big-company technology shares or any stock that happened to be moving up was the name of the game.</p>
        <p>So far this year, however, many of the hottest shares have been of some companies found off the beaten track. Shares of midcap companies and utilities, for instance, have been the market's unlikely stars.</p>
        <p>Clearly, this is becoming a stock picker's market, one where individual stocks can outshine the indexes. Getting into stocks ahead of the herd is now the way to go.</p>
        <p>But identifying which stocks have the most promise has never been more difficult for investors. In-depth analysis has virtually disappeared from Wall Street; most equity analysts are so busy bucking for investment banking business from companies that their stock picks can be highly suspect.</p>
        <p>Better to poll investment professionals famous for their skepticism, people who know how to take a sharp pencil to corporate financial statements.</p>
        <p>Two of the few in that group are Bob Olstein, manager of the Olstein Financial Alert fund, and Ravi Suria, the Lehman Brothers convertible-bond analyst who shot to fame last June with his devastating report on Amazon.com.</p>
        <p>Since 1995, Mr. Olstein's fund has risen 25 percent a year, on average; it is up 15.5 percent this year. He says that he tries to avoid investment mistakes by tearing apart company figures. ''We don't talk to management and we do not listen to Wall Street research,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He points to four stocks that he thinks will rise 50 percent in the next two years:</p>
        <p>Emerson Electric, which makes electronics and instrumentation for industrial automation, is an old-economy'' company heading into a rapid-growth phase, he said. The company is generating $1.4 billion in excess cash flow and should earn $3.30 a share this year.</p>
        <p>National Semiconductor has $800 million in cash and no debt on its balance sheet, and its shares have lost almost half their value since March. Mr. Olstein expects the company to earn $2.95 a share next year, giving the stock a price-to-earnings ratio of 15.</p>
        <p>Furniture Brands has new management that will bring earnings growth back to the company, Mr. Olstein said. At $16, the stock has a P/E ratio of 7, yet he thinks the company will soon generate $100 million in excess cash flow.</p>
        <p>Winnebago Industries is an even cheaper stock, trading at less than 6 times earnings. ''The company has $50 million in cash, no debt and $20 million in excess cash flow,'' Mr. Olstein said. Recreational vehicles are a good way for investors to profit from the aging baby boom population.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suria, who remains negative on Amazon.com, is decidedly upbeat on At Home, an Internet service provider offering Web-based content through the Excite network. The company's stock has tumbled from a high of $59.75 last year to $14.50; its two convertible-bond issues yield around 13 percent.</p>
        <p>Investors view At Home through the wrong lens, Mr. Suria said. Rather than weigh its prospects as an Internet portal, he said, At Home should be considered a subscription-based services company whose customers are growing in number -- from 1.8 million subscribers now to 3 million by year-end. ''As long as the subscriber base is increasing, cash flow will increase,'' he said. ''When free cash flow starts opening up, it pushes enterprise valuations. That's what made a lot of people a lot of money in cable companies in the 1990s.''</p>
        <p>Also compelling is the fact that AT&amp;T, which owns 24 percent of the company, has offered to pay $48 a share to buy up to $3 billion of At Home stock owned by Cox Communications and Comcast beginning next January and extending until June 2002. ''To me there is no better indicator of actual value in the company,'' Mr. Suria said.</p>
        <p>MARKET WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
