<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vegetables, Grilled and in Salads, Take on Different Guises</title>
    <meta content="CNFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DB1230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vegetables, Grilled and in Salads, Take on Different Guises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the time summer ends some people get tired of corn, tomatoes, eggplant, zucchini and beets. I'm not one of them. But I do like to prepare them in less predictable ways.</p>
        <p>Instead of serving corn on the cob, I like to scrape off the kernels and make them into a salad with onion and tomatoes. Grilled eggplant is usually sprinkled with basil leaves, but it's very good with ground coriander seed and a dressing of lemon, capers and fresh oregano. Beets are delicious cut in quarters and tossed with watercress and toasted walnuts in a balsamic dressing. With a slice of goat's cheese, this makes a fine first course for dinner. (I don't boil beets. I roast them in their skins. Try this method and you will never boil them again.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the time summer ends some people get tired of corn, tomatoes, eggplant, zucchini and beets. I'm not one of them. But I do like to prepare them in less predictable ways.</p>
        <p>Instead of serving corn on the cob, I like to scrape off the kernels and make them into a salad with onion and tomatoes. Grilled eggplant is usually sprinkled with basil leaves, but it's very good with ground coriander seed and a dressing of lemon, capers and fresh oregano. Beets are delicious cut in quarters and tossed with watercress and toasted walnuts in a balsamic dressing. With a slice of goat's cheese, this makes a fine first course for dinner. (I don't boil beets. I roast them in their skins. Try this method and you will never boil them again.)</p>
        <p>The final touch for these vegetable dishes comes with a dash of that expensive gray French sea salt you can find on the shelves of fancy food stores. At first glance it looks like a pretentious gimmick (one company even goes so far as to put the name of the person who harvested the salt on the box). But this salt does have a lovely texture -- crunchy but not as hard as some coarse salts. It brings out the taste of food like nothing else.</p>
        <p>Salad of Corn, Basil And Tomato  Total time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>6 ears corn  Coarse sea salt  1 small red onion  4 tomatoes, seeded and diced</p>
        <p>1/3 cup extra-virgin olive oil  Red-wine vinegar to taste  Freshly ground pepper  1 cup basil leaves, snipped.</p>
        <p>1. Blanch the corn in salted boiling water. With a sharp kife, scrape off the kernels into a large bowl. Add the onion and the tomatoes.</p>
        <p>2. Combine the oil and vinegar and season to taste with salt and pepper. Add the dressing to the vegetables and toss. Just before serving, add the basil leaves and mix them in.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Grilled Eggplant With Capers and Oregano  Total time: 1 hour  Plus half an hour marinating</p>
        <p>6 Japanese eggplant  Sea salt  Approximately  1/2 cup extra-virgin olive oil  1 tablespoon ground coriander seed  1 clove garlic, green part removed, minced  3 tablespoons lemon juice</p>
        <p>1/4 cup fresh oregano leaves, chopped  3 tablespoons salted capers, soaked, drained and chopped  Freshly ground pepper.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the eggplant lengthwise. Sprinkle the slices with salt and put them in a colander for 30 minutes to drain the bitter juices.</p>
        <p>2. Preheat grill. Lightly brush the eggplant with some of the olive oil and grill the slices on both sides. Put them on a serving dish and sprinkle them lightly with the coriander.</p>
        <p>3. Combine the remaining oil with the garlic and lemon juice. Pour the mixture over the eggplant. Sprinkle with oregano, capers and pepper. Serve at room temperature (do not refrigerate).</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Salad of Roast Beets, Walnuts and Watercress  Total time: 1 hour, 20 minutes</p>
        <p>2 pounds beets</p>
        <p>1/2 cup shelled walnuts</p>
        <p>1/4 cup balsamic vinegar  Coarse sea salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  1 clove garlic, minced (green part removed)</p>
        <p>1/3 cup extra-virgin olive oil  1 bunch watercress, stalks trimmed.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees. Trim the leaves from the beets, leaving an inch of stalk. Put the beets on a rack and roast for 45 minutes to an hour, or until they are tender. Cool and slip off their skins. While the beets are cooking, put the walnuts on a baking sheet and roast for five minutes. Cool and chop.</p>
        <p>2. Cut the beets in halves or quarters, depending on their size, and sprinkle them with the vinegar, salt and pepper while they are still warm.  Allow them to sit for half an hour to absorb the vinegar.</p>
        <p>3. Combine the garlic and olive oil. Add to the beets with the watercress and walnuts and toss gently. Correct seasoning and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
