<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>States Want Curfew at Airport</title>
    <meta content="03AIRP$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EFD81430F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>States Want Curfew at Airport</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FORMER adversaries in the airport border wars between Westchester and Connecticut came together last week to fight a common enemy.</p>
        <p>Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, brought together government representatives from Westchester and Fairfield County to announce a strategy to prevent Atlantic Southeast Airlines, a Delta Airlines subsidiary, from starting a 5:59 a.m. flight from Westchester County Airport that was to begin service in September.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FORMER adversaries in the airport border wars between Westchester and Connecticut came together last week to fight a common enemy.</p>
        <p>Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, brought together government representatives from Westchester and Fairfield County to announce a strategy to prevent Atlantic Southeast Airlines, a Delta Airlines subsidiary, from starting a 5:59 a.m. flight from Westchester County Airport that was to begin service in September.</p>
        <p>Such a flight would occur 31 minutes before the end of the voluntary curfew of midnight to 6:30 a.m. The voluntary curfew has been recognized for 20 years.</p>
        <p>Although other airlines already depart between 6 and 6:30, Mr. Spano insisted that by stopping Atlantic Southeast Airlines he wanted to prevent ''a cascade of events where other airlines will do that as well.'' He was joined at a news conference at the airport by Representatives Nita Lowey and Sue W. Kelly of Westchester and Christopher Shays of Stamford as well as the chairman of Westchester's Board of Legislators, George S. Latimer, and the first selectwoman of Greenwich, Lolly Prince.</p>
        <p>''This issue goes to the very quality of life, not only in Westchester, but also in Connecticut,'' Mr. Spano said. ''This administration has a no-expansion policy at the airport. Even if we solve this problem, there may be another Delta coming down the road. What we're asking today is for our Congressional representatives to look at the legislation and give us a mandatory curfew.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano is seeking a federal law that would require airlines at the county airport to obey a mandatory curfew. Support for such legislation cuts across party lines.</p>
        <p>''We are Republicans and Democrats here,'' Mr. Latimer said. ''We are from different states, but this is a common interest. It's the single most important battle we've had here. If major commercial airlines are flying in and out at will, we've lost the core protection for the airport and the watershed.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lowey added: ''We can't have a voluntary curfew, we're going to work together as a delegation to get a mandatory curfew. This airport was never meant to be a major commercial aircraft center.''</p>
        <p>Besides airport neighbors and environmental activists who turned out, some with hand-lettered signs that read ''Don't Wake Us Up Delta,'' ''Silence Is Golden,'' and ''Atlantic Southeast: Let Us Sleep,'' there were many elected officials in attendance.</p>
        <p>An Atlantic Southeast official said the airline was open to compromise.</p>
        <p>''The 5:59 a.m. departure is not ideal,'' said Sam Watts, the airline's vice president for marketing and corporate communications. ''We would prefer to depart a bit later, but weren't able to obtain another time. We will continue to talk with the appropriate authorities to reach a mutually acceptable agreement. We would hope there would be an open dialogue.''</p>
        <p>But critics of the airline want it to abide by the curfew.</p>
        <p>''The voluntary curfew is a good compromise,'' said Ellen Kaidanow, chairman of the Harrison, N.Y., airport committee. ''For a flight of maybe 30 to 50 people, they'll wake up hundreds of thousands of people.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Prince said: ''Delta is breaking something that we think is sacred. Our goal is to get the teeth that will allow us to have a mandatory curfew. We wholeheartedly support this effort, and want to be part of a solution.''</p>
        <p>To many long-term airport and environmental activists, such cooperation was a welcome step.</p>
        <p>Bruce Carlsten, a member of the Purchase Friends Meeting, whose house of worship borders the airport, said, ''I think it's very exciting, to see a group with different minds on different issues with all their oars in the water pulling together.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
