<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Dead Heat, City Zip Earns Sweep</title>
    <meta content="03RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hopeful Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDB1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Dead Heat, City Zip Earns Sweep</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., Sept. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City Zip and Yonaguska race to dead heat in Hopeful Stakes at Saratoga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a few anxious moments this afternoon, the rain clouds that rolled in and hovered over Saratoga just before the 96th running of the Hopeful looked as if they would be an omen for Linda Rice's star 2-year-old colt, City Zip.</p>
        <p>With every flash of lightning and rumble of thunder during the race, City Zip looked up, the colt's jockey, Jose Santos, said. When Santos shuffled City Zip back from third place to seventh at the half-mile mark, Rice, who trains City Zip, figured something was wrong. And when Santos had to go six wide at the top of the stretch, City Zip seemed to have no chance of catching the front-running Yonaguska before the finish line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a few anxious moments this afternoon, the rain clouds that rolled in and hovered over Saratoga just before the 96th running of the Hopeful looked as if they would be an omen for Linda Rice's star 2-year-old colt, City Zip.</p>
        <p>With every flash of lightning and rumble of thunder during the race, City Zip looked up, the colt's jockey, Jose Santos, said. When Santos shuffled City Zip back from third place to seventh at the half-mile mark, Rice, who trains City Zip, figured something was wrong. And when Santos had to go six wide at the top of the stretch, City Zip seemed to have no chance of catching the front-running Yonaguska before the finish line.</p>
        <p>But catch Yonaguska, City Zip did, just barely. So Rice and D. Wayne Lukas, who trains Yonaguska, had to wait out a photo finish to see which colt had won, as rain began to fall.</p>
        <p>They both did.</p>
        <p>City Zip and Yonaguska hit the wire at the same moment, with Macho Uno a neck back between the horses. The $200,000 Hopeful was ruled a dead heat for the first time in its history after a stirring stretch duel.</p>
        <p>The result was something of a vindication for Lukas, who celebrated his 65th birthday by saddling two winners this afternoon, his first winners here in a month.</p>
        <p>As for City Zip, who captured his fourth consecutive graded stakes race, the result did more than validate his credentials as the top 2-year-old colt. By rallying from what appeared to be impossible circumstances, City Zip became just the fourth horse to sweep Saratoga's three major juvenile stakes: the Sanford, the Saratoga Special and the Hopeful. The other three were Dehere in 1993, Campfire in 1916 and the filly Regret in 1914.</p>
        <p>City Zip's owners, Carl Bowling, Lakland Farm and Chuck Thompson, were not going to let a dead heat, or a little rain, get them down. They chanted: ''History! History!'' as they posed in the winner's circle.</p>
        <p>''This horse can rate, but I was not trying to rate him today,'' Santos said. ''On the backstretch, we tried to get at the Lukas horse, but all of a sudden, it got a little crowded. There was not any room at all. And then, at the three-eighths pole, there were five horses across the track, which is why I went outside. A lot of things went funny. He was lucky to get there in the end.''</p>
        <p>Rice was concerned for her colt when Santos moved City Zip back, which prompted the track announcer Tom Durkin to call out, ''City Zip is dropping off the pace!'' And when City Zip finally rallied, he had to catch six horses and make a wide move off the turn, which did not make Rice any more comfortable.</p>
        <p>''He had a lot to do,'' she said. ''I thought it was going to be close. I wasn't sure if we were going to get there, but this colt never shows any quit down the lane. He doesn't come up with many excuses. He can have things go wrong and still win.''</p>
        <p>City Zip and Yonaguska, who was fractious in the paddock as the storm approached, ran the seven furlongs in 1:24.52 as City Zip returned $2.90 and Yonaguska $3.70 on a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>With the shared victory, Jerry Bailey, who rode Yonaguska, registered his meet-leading 46th victory, two shy of his Saratoga record, with two days left in the meet. It was his first Grade I victory in New York this year.</p>
        <p>As for Lukas, he celebrated his birthday by breaking a 35-race drought when Regent Gold, a chestnut 3-year-old filly, won her maiden in the fifth race. A Lukas-trained horse had not won here since Aug. 2.</p>
        <p>When asked if he felt a monkey had been taken off his back with Regent Gold's victory, Lukas was a little defiant. ''The only monkey was the one you guys put on us,'' Lukas said, referring to the news media, as he walked right past. ''I didn't feel like we were doing anything wrong.'' That might be because more than half of Lukas's horses have finished in the money at the meet. In 48 starts, Lukas has 3 victories, 10 seconds and 12 thirds.</p>
        <p>When his slump was brought up again after the Hopeful, Lukas again walked away.</p>
        <p>City Zip, meanwhile, proved today that he was much more than a pretty good colt.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
