<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.C. Scouting Reports</title>
    <meta content="03NFC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DA1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.C. Scouting Reports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Football Conference scouting reports, team by team; teams are listed in predicted order of finish; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>(Teams are listed in predicted order of finish)</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>1. Washington Redskins  1999 record: 10-6  STRENGTHS -- The off-season spending spree of the principal owner Daniel Snyder has been well chronicled, as it should be. No team has done more to improve itself so quickly. Deion Sanders bolsters the secondary and provides a threat on punt returns. Bruce Smith is still a solid pass rusher. The rookie left tackle Chris Samuels may be one of the best draft picks of the past five years. This team has stocked the cupboard.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Getting all that talent to mesh may take several games. There is also a budding quarterback controversy between the starter, Brad Johnson, and the backup Jeff George. Snyder is the other X factor. If the team stumbles early, will he erupt the way George Steinbrenner has?</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- This team has 12 victories written all over it. Washington is definitely a Super Bowl contender. If Snyder can control his temper, and Coach Norv Turner can blend all the talent, the Redskins may be practically unbeatable.</p>
        <p>2. New York Giants  1999 record: 7-9  STRENGTHS --You know what our biggest asset is? Giants linebacker Jessie Armstead asked.Everybody is picking us to win two games. We're going to sneak up on people.Not with running back Ron Dayne, who has all the stealth of a snowplow. Armstead is of course exaggerating -- in fact, some prognosticators think the Giants will make the playoffs. Dayne gives them a solid ground game and ball control, and quarterback Kerry Collins is one of the pleasant surprises in football. And, please, don't worry about a quiet preseason from Armstead and the Pro Bowler Michael Strahan. When the games begin, they will turn it on.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- A big one -- the secondary. Cornerback Jason Sehorn is playing extremely well, but Sehorn and safety Sam Garnes are the only reliable faces among the defensive backs.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Giants are a playoff team. They have the talent. But their situation is precarious. For the first time in decades the team may rely on the offense to carry it. What will keep the team from advancing deep into the postseason are the gaping holes in the defensive backfield.</p>
        <p>3. Philadelphia Eagles  1999 record: 5-11  STRENGTHS -- Quarterback Donovan McNabb is a talented passer, and Duce Staley rushed for 1,273 yards last season. Staley should only get better because in the off-season the Eagles signed the free agent Jon Runyan, a 330-pound blocking terror.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The Eagles don't have a big-time wide receiver, which means teams will load up the line of scrimmage to stop Staley and blitz McNabb.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Eagles will push the division and can be one of the league's surprise teams. How far they go will depend on McNabb.</p>
        <p>4. Arizona Cardinals  1999 record: 6-10  STRENGTHS -- Jake Plummer played most of last season with a sprained thumb on his passing hand, and it led to his horrid year. Plummer's 9 touchdowns and 24 interceptions shattered his confidence. But only temporarily. He has spent this off-season in the film room and has been working out relentlessly. Look for Plummer to regain his 1998 form. The rookie running back Thomas Jones looks like the real deal.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Wideout is the big question mark. The team lost receiver Rob Moore to a torn left anterior cruciate ligament in the third preseason game against Minnesota. Arizona's pass rush remains weak. The defense allowed 24 points a game last season, and the front office has done little to improve it.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- As Plummer goes so do the Cardinals. If Plummer makes bad decisions this season as he did last season, the offense will struggle again. But if Plummer plays smarter, Arizona can be a threat.</p>
        <p>5. Dallas Cowboys  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- Adding wide receiver Joey Galloway was a brilliant move. He can stretch a defense, and now the Cowboys have to get him to go across the middle consistently. Dat Nguyen is a smallish linebacker who does nothing but make big plays. Leon Lett is still a factor at defensive end.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Quarterback Troy Aikman is still great, and it is silly to say he is a soft spot on the team. Injuries and inexperience have made the defensive back situation so dire that Dallas lured the former Giant cornerback Phillippi Sparks out of retirement.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Cowboys as we know them are dead. Their backs ache, their knees are creaking and they are a step too slow. Their salary cap situation is a mess and no one fears them anymore. They have one last shot to make a run at a championship. It's just that, in all probability, that door has already been slammed shut.</p>
        <p>PLAYER TO WATCH</p>
        <p>Tiki Barber  Running back, Giants  Two of the most important Giants offensive players for much of the last half of the 1990's were fullback Charles Way and running back Tiki Barber. Way was a punishing blocker who off the field was trusted implicitly by teammates. Barber remains one of the most intelligent players the Giants have ever had, and now he seems primed to have one of his biggest seasons. Look for Barber to become heavily involved in the offense with screens and even some deep passing routes. Barber will become more of a weapon, but he will also play an important part in the development of Kerry Collins. Collins is not forcing passes into double coverage as much, and is dumping off in the flats, where Barber will be waiting.</p>
        <p>Central</p>
        <p>1. Tampa Bay Buccaneers  1999 record: 11-5  STRENGTHS -- The defense remains championship caliber, and in what falls under the scary thought department, the Pro Bowl defensive lineman Warren Sapp believes he will play even better. Fullback Mike Alstott, who averaged nearly 4 yards a carry last year, is the most punishing runner in football. Oh, and the Bucs have this guy named Keyshawn Johnson.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- You have to reach to find them. Quarterback Shaun King is still largely inexperienced and left tackle Jason Odom is coming off back surgery. The Buccaneers are sometimes too conservative on offense.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Tampa Bay averaged only 16.9 points a game, 28th in the league, and still made it to the N.F.C. championship game. Now the team adds the spectacular Johnson, so it will be much better. Tampa Bay, with a smart head coach in Tony Dungy, a great defense and Johnson, could easily reach the Super Bowl. The only two things that can stop them are injuries or jealousy from other wide receivers when Johnson starts catching all those passes.</p>
        <p>2. Minnesota Vikings  1999 record: 10-6  STRENGTHS -- People in Minnesota fret more about the Vikings' quarterback situation than they do the latest words from Gov. Jesse Ventura. Memories are short. It was 1998 when Randall Cunningham left his construction business, stepped into the Vikings' offense and went to the Pro Bowl. A year later, Jeff George, who was Ryan Leaf before there was Ryan Leaf, won 9 of 12 starts. Jim McMahon, Warren Moon and Brad Johnson all threw for a billion yards. In other words, it's the system. Daunte Culpepper, the new starter, will be just fine. That's because he has Randy Moss and Cris Carter to throw to.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The usual for the Vikings -- defense. It helped when they signed the free agent cornerback Cris Dishman, but they must still score 25 points a game because that is what's going to be racked up against them.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Coach Dennis Green will put Culpepper in a position to win. In his eight seasons Green has never had a losing record, and his teams have made the playoffs seven times.</p>
        <p>3. Detroit Lions  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- Barry Sanders is playing golf. No problem. Detroit signed the former Jacksonville runner James Stewart to a five-year, $25 million deal, and his quickness has surprised teammates. Charlie Batch remains one of the most underrated throwers in football. The offensive line is excellent.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Defense is the problem. There is no depth, and the secondary is average. The schedule is brutal. Besides the rugged division games, the Lions play Washington, at Indianapolis, at the Giants and at the Jets.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- If Batch and Stewart can stay healthy -- and those are big questions -- the Lions can make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>4. Green Bay Packers  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- The offense will be less predictable. Wide receiver Antonio Freeman reported to camp 10 pounds lighter. He's hungry, just not for pepperoni pizza.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Quarterback Brett Favre is simply wearing out. Last year he threw 22 interceptions because of a badly sprained thumb. This season, he already has a sore throwing elbow.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- When he's healthy, Favre remains one of the most dangerous players in football. If Coach Mike Sherman can control Favre's wild tendencies and freelancing on the field, the Packers can get 10 victories.</p>
        <p>5. Chicago Bears  1999 record: 6-10  STRENGTHS -- The team added a premier defensive end by signing Phillip Daniels from Seattle. He's the biggest star on a mediocre defense.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The often injured, often bizarre Curtis Enis is still not a premier running back. Quarterback Cade McNown is not a natural pocket passer, but he is being asked to be one in Chicago's offense. In the last preseason game, against Tennessee, Titans quarterback Steve McNair completed 13 straight passes against Chicago's defense.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Don't buy into the hype that the Bears have completely turned things around. McNown is solid, but there are too many other holes on this team. Chicago remains a few seasons from contending.</p>
        <p>PLAYER TO WATCH</p>
        <p>John Randle  Defensive tackle, Minnesota Vikings  It is unusual for John Randle to be so, well, quiet. After all, this is a man who does enough talking on the field for 15 men. Yet, is Randle still the impact player he has been for most of his 11-year career? Last season he had 10 sacks, but Randle is seeing fewer double teams. Basically, because of a secondary that may be among the worst in football, Minnesota needs Randle to have 12 sacks -- and more -- this season. Then Randle can do all the talking he wants.</p>
        <p>West</p>
        <p>1. St. Louis Rams  1999 record: 13-3  STRENGTHS -- Speed and depth. Trent Green is the backup quarterback, and he could start for any other team. Running back Marshall Faulk is the most underrated weapon in football. The offensive line played well in the preseason, and the defense is the fastest in the division. Players love Coach Mike Martz. There are few holes.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Only a few. When an opponent looks down the schedule and sees the Rams, it will look at that game as the biggest of the year. That is a tremendous burden and the reason repeating as Super Bowl champion is so difficult.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- This team will easily capture the division. It will also make a strong run at another Super Bowl trip. One piece of good news for the team is that quarterback Kurt Warner, last year's Super Bowl M.V.P., has remained levelheaded despite his newfound fame.</p>
        <p>2. Atlanta Falcons  1999 record: 5-11  STRENGTHS -- Dan Reeves is extremely suspect as a talent evaluator -- he just cut his first draft pick as general manager of the Falcons in 1997, cornerback Michael Booker -- but he is a great head coach. Tim Dwight is emerging as more than a speed burner; he is now a complete player. Running back Jamal Anderson is back from last year's season-ending knee injury.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- This team is built around two frail stars. When Anderson was lost with a torn right anterior cruciate ligament, the Falcons went into free fall, going from 14-2 to only 5 victories. It is unrealistic to think Anderson can return to prime form this season. Quarterback Chris Chandler was sacked 32 times last year.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- If Anderson and Chandler stay healthy, the Falcons will compete for a playoff spot. Atlanta is taking a huge gamble by starting a rookie, Travis Claridge, at right tackle. Basically, there are a lot of ifs for the Falcons.</p>
        <p>3. Carolina Panthers  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- The defensive line of Jason Peter, Sean Gilbert, Tim Morabito, and Chuck Smith should be solid. The Panthers also added Reggie White and Eric Swann. Quarterback Steve Beuerlein had a career season in '99 and should be solid again. The running back who has the most vowels in his name, Tshimanga Biakabutuka, if he stays healthy, will gain at least 1,200 yards. George Seifert is always forgotten when names of top head coaches are mentioned, but he is a brilliant tactician.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The Panthers will not be able to sneak up on people as they did in the final half of last season, when Carolina won five of eight. The team also showed it had a major flaw -- suspect cornerbacks -- and did nothing this off-season to correct the problem.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Anyone who believes the Panthers are a playoff team is being a bit premature.</p>
        <p>4. New Orleans Saints  1999 record: 3-13  STRENGTHS -- Quarterback Jeff Blake throws a nice deep ball. Wide receivers Jake Reed and Joe Horn are not household names but are solid. Willie Roaf is a premier left tackle.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- An overall lack of special players. The former coach, Mike Ditka, after trading his entire 1998 draft for Ricky Williams, has left this team in a world of pain.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- It is between New Orleans and San Francisco as to which team will be the sorriest in the division.</p>
        <p>5. San Francisco 49ers  1999 record: 4-12  STRENGTHS -- Good young receivers in Terrell Owens and J.J. Stokes.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- San Francisco cornerbacks were torched last year. The team made some improvements by letting go Mark McMillian, R.W. McQuarters and Darnell Walker, but any thought that the secondary will make dramatic leaps is a silly one.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The 49ers are in salary cap purgatory, Steve Young retired, and Coach Steve Mariucci must deal with the aging superstar Jerry Rice. That all adds up to three victories.</p>
        <p>COACH TO WATCH</p>
        <p>Steve Mariucci  San Francisco  Few coaches in football face the challenges that Mariucci does. When he took over San Francisco in 1997, the 49ers were a playoff team. He was considered one of the bright young talents in the game. He still is. But the 49ers are not close to what they were three years ago. Because of salary cap problems, the team has been gutted and is only a notch above an expansion team. Mariucci lost the future Hall of Famer Steve Young to retirement. An even bigger challenge will be working in another future Hall of Famer, Jerry Rice. One of the toughest jobs in coaching is dealing with a legend who is no longer playing at a championship level but believes he is. If Rice does not catch enough passes, he will complain, as he has done before, putting Mariucci, and the franchise, in a difficult spot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>(Teams are listed in predicted order of finish)</p>
        <p>East</p>
        <p>1. Washington Redskins  1999 record: 10-6  STRENGTHS -- The off-season spending spree of the principal owner Daniel Snyder has been well chronicled, as it should be. No team has done more to improve itself so quickly. Deion Sanders bolsters the secondary and provides a threat on punt returns. Bruce Smith is still a solid pass rusher. The rookie left tackle Chris Samuels may be one of the best draft picks of the past five years. This team has stocked the cupboard.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Getting all that talent to mesh may take several games. There is also a budding quarterback controversy between the starter, Brad Johnson, and the backup Jeff George. Snyder is the other X factor. If the team stumbles early, will he erupt the way George Steinbrenner has?</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- This team has 12 victories written all over it. Washington is definitely a Super Bowl contender. If Snyder can control his temper, and Coach Norv Turner can blend all the talent, the Redskins may be practically unbeatable.</p>
        <p>2. New York Giants  1999 record: 7-9  STRENGTHS --You know what our biggest asset is? Giants linebacker Jessie Armstead asked.Everybody is picking us to win two games. We're going to sneak up on people.Not with running back Ron Dayne, who has all the stealth of a snowplow. Armstead is of course exaggerating -- in fact, some prognosticators think the Giants will make the playoffs. Dayne gives them a solid ground game and ball control, and quarterback Kerry Collins is one of the pleasant surprises in football. And, please, don't worry about a quiet preseason from Armstead and the Pro Bowler Michael Strahan. When the games begin, they will turn it on.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- A big one -- the secondary. Cornerback Jason Sehorn is playing extremely well, but Sehorn and safety Sam Garnes are the only reliable faces among the defensive backs.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Giants are a playoff team. They have the talent. But their situation is precarious. For the first time in decades the team may rely on the offense to carry it. What will keep the team from advancing deep into the postseason are the gaping holes in the defensive backfield.</p>
        <p>3. Philadelphia Eagles  1999 record: 5-11  STRENGTHS -- Quarterback Donovan McNabb is a talented passer, and Duce Staley rushed for 1,273 yards last season. Staley should only get better because in the off-season the Eagles signed the free agent Jon Runyan, a 330-pound blocking terror.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The Eagles don't have a big-time wide receiver, which means teams will load up the line of scrimmage to stop Staley and blitz McNabb.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Eagles will push the division and can be one of the league's surprise teams. How far they go will depend on McNabb.</p>
        <p>4. Arizona Cardinals  1999 record: 6-10  STRENGTHS -- Jake Plummer played most of last season with a sprained thumb on his passing hand, and it led to his horrid year. Plummer's 9 touchdowns and 24 interceptions shattered his confidence. But only temporarily. He has spent this off-season in the film room and has been working out relentlessly. Look for Plummer to regain his 1998 form. The rookie running back Thomas Jones looks like the real deal.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Wideout is the big question mark. The team lost receiver Rob Moore to a torn left anterior cruciate ligament in the third preseason game against Minnesota. Arizona's pass rush remains weak. The defense allowed 24 points a game last season, and the front office has done little to improve it.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- As Plummer goes so do the Cardinals. If Plummer makes bad decisions this season as he did last season, the offense will struggle again. But if Plummer plays smarter, Arizona can be a threat.</p>
        <p>5. Dallas Cowboys  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- Adding wide receiver Joey Galloway was a brilliant move. He can stretch a defense, and now the Cowboys have to get him to go across the middle consistently. Dat Nguyen is a smallish linebacker who does nothing but make big plays. Leon Lett is still a factor at defensive end.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Quarterback Troy Aikman is still great, and it is silly to say he is a soft spot on the team. Injuries and inexperience have made the defensive back situation so dire that Dallas lured the former Giant cornerback Phillippi Sparks out of retirement.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The Cowboys as we know them are dead. Their backs ache, their knees are creaking and they are a step too slow. Their salary cap situation is a mess and no one fears them anymore. They have one last shot to make a run at a championship. It's just that, in all probability, that door has already been slammed shut.</p>
        <p>PLAYER TO WATCH</p>
        <p>Tiki Barber  Running back, Giants  Two of the most important Giants offensive players for much of the last half of the 1990's were fullback Charles Way and running back Tiki Barber. Way was a punishing blocker who off the field was trusted implicitly by teammates. Barber remains one of the most intelligent players the Giants have ever had, and now he seems primed to have one of his biggest seasons. Look for Barber to become heavily involved in the offense with screens and even some deep passing routes. Barber will become more of a weapon, but he will also play an important part in the development of Kerry Collins. Collins is not forcing passes into double coverage as much, and is dumping off in the flats, where Barber will be waiting.</p>
        <p>Central</p>
        <p>1. Tampa Bay Buccaneers  1999 record: 11-5  STRENGTHS -- The defense remains championship caliber, and in what falls under the scary thought department, the Pro Bowl defensive lineman Warren Sapp believes he will play even better. Fullback Mike Alstott, who averaged nearly 4 yards a carry last year, is the most punishing runner in football. Oh, and the Bucs have this guy named Keyshawn Johnson.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- You have to reach to find them. Quarterback Shaun King is still largely inexperienced and left tackle Jason Odom is coming off back surgery. The Buccaneers are sometimes too conservative on offense.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Tampa Bay averaged only 16.9 points a game, 28th in the league, and still made it to the N.F.C. championship game. Now the team adds the spectacular Johnson, so it will be much better. Tampa Bay, with a smart head coach in Tony Dungy, a great defense and Johnson, could easily reach the Super Bowl. The only two things that can stop them are injuries or jealousy from other wide receivers when Johnson starts catching all those passes.</p>
        <p>2. Minnesota Vikings  1999 record: 10-6  STRENGTHS -- People in Minnesota fret more about the Vikings' quarterback situation than they do the latest words from Gov. Jesse Ventura. Memories are short. It was 1998 when Randall Cunningham left his construction business, stepped into the Vikings' offense and went to the Pro Bowl. A year later, Jeff George, who was Ryan Leaf before there was Ryan Leaf, won 9 of 12 starts. Jim McMahon, Warren Moon and Brad Johnson all threw for a billion yards. In other words, it's the system. Daunte Culpepper, the new starter, will be just fine. That's because he has Randy Moss and Cris Carter to throw to.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The usual for the Vikings -- defense. It helped when they signed the free agent cornerback Cris Dishman, but they must still score 25 points a game because that is what's going to be racked up against them.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Coach Dennis Green will put Culpepper in a position to win. In his eight seasons Green has never had a losing record, and his teams have made the playoffs seven times.</p>
        <p>3. Detroit Lions  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- Barry Sanders is playing golf. No problem. Detroit signed the former Jacksonville runner James Stewart to a five-year, $25 million deal, and his quickness has surprised teammates. Charlie Batch remains one of the most underrated throwers in football. The offensive line is excellent.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Defense is the problem. There is no depth, and the secondary is average. The schedule is brutal. Besides the rugged division games, the Lions play Washington, at Indianapolis, at the Giants and at the Jets.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- If Batch and Stewart can stay healthy -- and those are big questions -- the Lions can make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>4. Green Bay Packers  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- The offense will be less predictable. Wide receiver Antonio Freeman reported to camp 10 pounds lighter. He's hungry, just not for pepperoni pizza.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Quarterback Brett Favre is simply wearing out. Last year he threw 22 interceptions because of a badly sprained thumb. This season, he already has a sore throwing elbow.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- When he's healthy, Favre remains one of the most dangerous players in football. If Coach Mike Sherman can control Favre's wild tendencies and freelancing on the field, the Packers can get 10 victories.</p>
        <p>5. Chicago Bears  1999 record: 6-10  STRENGTHS -- The team added a premier defensive end by signing Phillip Daniels from Seattle. He's the biggest star on a mediocre defense.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The often injured, often bizarre Curtis Enis is still not a premier running back. Quarterback Cade McNown is not a natural pocket passer, but he is being asked to be one in Chicago's offense. In the last preseason game, against Tennessee, Titans quarterback Steve McNair completed 13 straight passes against Chicago's defense.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Don't buy into the hype that the Bears have completely turned things around. McNown is solid, but there are too many other holes on this team. Chicago remains a few seasons from contending.</p>
        <p>PLAYER TO WATCH</p>
        <p>John Randle  Defensive tackle, Minnesota Vikings  It is unusual for John Randle to be so, well, quiet. After all, this is a man who does enough talking on the field for 15 men. Yet, is Randle still the impact player he has been for most of his 11-year career? Last season he had 10 sacks, but Randle is seeing fewer double teams. Basically, because of a secondary that may be among the worst in football, Minnesota needs Randle to have 12 sacks -- and more -- this season. Then Randle can do all the talking he wants.</p>
        <p>West</p>
        <p>1. St. Louis Rams  1999 record: 13-3  STRENGTHS -- Speed and depth. Trent Green is the backup quarterback, and he could start for any other team. Running back Marshall Faulk is the most underrated weapon in football. The offensive line played well in the preseason, and the defense is the fastest in the division. Players love Coach Mike Martz. There are few holes.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- Only a few. When an opponent looks down the schedule and sees the Rams, it will look at that game as the biggest of the year. That is a tremendous burden and the reason repeating as Super Bowl champion is so difficult.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- This team will easily capture the division. It will also make a strong run at another Super Bowl trip. One piece of good news for the team is that quarterback Kurt Warner, last year's Super Bowl M.V.P., has remained levelheaded despite his newfound fame.</p>
        <p>2. Atlanta Falcons  1999 record: 5-11  STRENGTHS -- Dan Reeves is extremely suspect as a talent evaluator -- he just cut his first draft pick as general manager of the Falcons in 1997, cornerback Michael Booker -- but he is a great head coach. Tim Dwight is emerging as more than a speed burner; he is now a complete player. Running back Jamal Anderson is back from last year's season-ending knee injury.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- This team is built around two frail stars. When Anderson was lost with a torn right anterior cruciate ligament, the Falcons went into free fall, going from 14-2 to only 5 victories. It is unrealistic to think Anderson can return to prime form this season. Quarterback Chris Chandler was sacked 32 times last year.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- If Anderson and Chandler stay healthy, the Falcons will compete for a playoff spot. Atlanta is taking a huge gamble by starting a rookie, Travis Claridge, at right tackle. Basically, there are a lot of ifs for the Falcons.</p>
        <p>3. Carolina Panthers  1999 record: 8-8  STRENGTHS -- The defensive line of Jason Peter, Sean Gilbert, Tim Morabito, and Chuck Smith should be solid. The Panthers also added Reggie White and Eric Swann. Quarterback Steve Beuerlein had a career season in '99 and should be solid again. The running back who has the most vowels in his name, Tshimanga Biakabutuka, if he stays healthy, will gain at least 1,200 yards. George Seifert is always forgotten when names of top head coaches are mentioned, but he is a brilliant tactician.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- The Panthers will not be able to sneak up on people as they did in the final half of last season, when Carolina won five of eight. The team also showed it had a major flaw -- suspect cornerbacks -- and did nothing this off-season to correct the problem.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- Anyone who believes the Panthers are a playoff team is being a bit premature.</p>
        <p>4. New Orleans Saints  1999 record: 3-13  STRENGTHS -- Quarterback Jeff Blake throws a nice deep ball. Wide receivers Jake Reed and Joe Horn are not household names but are solid. Willie Roaf is a premier left tackle.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- An overall lack of special players. The former coach, Mike Ditka, after trading his entire 1998 draft for Ricky Williams, has left this team in a world of pain.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- It is between New Orleans and San Francisco as to which team will be the sorriest in the division.</p>
        <p>5. San Francisco 49ers  1999 record: 4-12  STRENGTHS -- Good young receivers in Terrell Owens and J.J. Stokes.</p>
        <p>WEAKNESSES -- San Francisco cornerbacks were torched last year. The team made some improvements by letting go Mark McMillian, R.W. McQuarters and Darnell Walker, but any thought that the secondary will make dramatic leaps is a silly one.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK -- The 49ers are in salary cap purgatory, Steve Young retired, and Coach Steve Mariucci must deal with the aging superstar Jerry Rice. That all adds up to three victories.</p>
        <p>COACH TO WATCH</p>
        <p>Steve Mariucci  San Francisco  Few coaches in football face the challenges that Mariucci does. When he took over San Francisco in 1997, the 49ers were a playoff team. He was considered one of the bright young talents in the game. He still is. But the 49ers are not close to what they were three years ago. Because of salary cap problems, the team has been gutted and is only a notch above an expansion team. Mariucci lost the future Hall of Famer Steve Young to retirement. An even bigger challenge will be working in another future Hall of Famer, Jerry Rice. One of the toughest jobs in coaching is dealing with a legend who is no longer playing at a championship level but believes he is. If Rice does not catch enough passes, he will complain, as he has done before, putting Mariucci, and the franchise, in a difficult spot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
