<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lots of Style, Carefully Prepared Dishes</title>
    <meta content="03DINE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Inferno (Westport, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFDF1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lots of Style, Carefully Prepared Dishes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Inferno restaurant in Westport, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INFERNO in Westport is kin to the restaurant of the same name in Greenwich, but not an identical twin in decor or food. In limited space, Inferno has created a sense of edginess, with paprika- and avocado-painted walls, a water wall that picks up the metallic glints of a copper-faced oven and chimney in the open kitchen, high ceiling, silvery tables and a concrete floor.</p>
        <p>Inferno's menu is also relatively spare, emphasizing pastas and pizzas, with just a few appetizer and entree specials. Certain dishes were very good indeed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INFERNO in Westport is kin to the restaurant of the same name in Greenwich, but not an identical twin in decor or food. In limited space, Inferno has created a sense of edginess, with paprika- and avocado-painted walls, a water wall that picks up the metallic glints of a copper-faced oven and chimney in the open kitchen, high ceiling, silvery tables and a concrete floor.</p>
        <p>Inferno's menu is also relatively spare, emphasizing pastas and pizzas, with just a few appetizer and entree specials. Certain dishes were very good indeed.</p>
        <p>Count among the stars most appetizers: roasted asparagus (slender al dente stalks wrapped in prosciutto and Reggiano cheese with a pile of frisee), bruschetta pomidori (thick toasted slices of good Italian bread, spread with olive oil and garlic, heaped with chopped fresh tomatoes) and funghi misti (various wild mushrooms sauteed with sun-dried tomatoes, smoked mozzarella and balsamic vinegar).</p>
        <p>Also in the plus column were calamari alla griglia (grilled squid served with garlic-lemon oil and the ubiquitous frisee), and polipetti in zimino (tender baby octopus stewed with porcini mushrooms, spinach and plum tomatoes).</p>
        <p>A special, rollatini di mozzarella e prosciutto con pomodoro in conserva, was a visual treat. Little wheels of cheese, prosciutto and basil, surrounded by frisee, were curiously tasteless, no competition for the intensely flavored oven-dried tomatoes served with them.</p>
        <p>Two entree specials one evening were heavy hitters. Pan-roasted veal chop, with toasted pine nuts and sultana raisins in a sauce made with veal stock and balsamic vinegar arrived with excellent roasted and browned potato canoes. Whole pompano, stuffed with herbs and lightly baked in the wood oven, was a firm, delicate and well-seasoned fish, served with a swirl of mashed potatoes. Grilled yellowfin tuna, pink as ordered, had a pungent, robust pesto sauce, a pleasing dish. Seven pasta dishes were on the menu. We hit a home run with ravioli alla noci (spinach and ricotta filled pockets in a luscious walnut sauce). But we struck out with sugo di vitello (a small amount of chopped veal in a tomato-white wine-herb sauce, swamped by penne).</p>
        <p>Brick oven pizzas numbered 14, with a list of 28 topping possibilities. The crust was crisp and flavorful, but we found it to be too thin to hold certain toppings, such as the vegetali Inferno, with six heavy ingredients, crudely chopped (grilled eggplant, green peppers, zucchini, sliced fresh tomatoes and mozzarella). Inferno's crust worked better when it wasn't smothered in ingredients, as in mangi (fresh sliced tomatoes, mascarpone cheese and prosciutto), Margherita (mozzarella, garlic, basil leaves, tomato sauce) and nello (caramelized shallots, ricotta and fontina).</p>
        <p>Desserts were much more than an afterthought. A rich, layered tiramisu, intense mocha chocolate pot de creme and almond-apple tart in a puff-pastry crust, were all exemplary. The chocolate souffle had a deeply satisfying soft, runny center, but was otherwise too dry.</p>
        <p>Dinner for two came to $82, before tax, tip or drinks, though by sticking to pizza or pasta, instead of the special entrees, the tab would be considerably lower. A small wine list, mostly from California and Italy, offered some intriguing choices. Bottle prices begin at $27, with many in the $30's.</p>
        <p>With Inferno's pronounced emphasis on design in its dramatic decor, one wonders why several aspects of diner comfort have been overlooked. The smart-looking wooden chairs are unusually uncomfortable and the oversized menus are awkward to handle on small tables, as are the oversize plates used for both appetizers and entrees.</p>
        <p>Inferno may have a certain cafeteria sparseness, but there is nothing fast-foodish about the carefully prepared dishes. The hard-edged decor may not turn you on, but much of the food should.</p>
        <p>Inferno  33 Jessup Green, Westport  (203) 226-9887</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Edgy, high-tech look. Noise level: high when crowded because of hard, reflective surfaces.  SERVICE -- Unwelcoming, perfunctory and slipshod about basics: refilling water glasses, removing dishes, crumbing the table.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Baby octopus, roasted asparagus, calamari alla griglia, bruschetta pomidoro, funghi misti, ravioli alla noci, grilled yellowfin tuna, pan-roasted veal chop, whole pompano, pizzas (Margherita, nello and mangia), tiramisu, almond-apple tart, biscotti, mocha chocolat pot de creme.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees $6 to $18, dinner entrees $6 to $28.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, Mastercard, Visa.  HOURS -- 11:30 a.m.-2:30 p.m. Monday-Friday, 5:30-9:30 p.m. Sunday-Wednesday, 5:30-10:30 p.m. Thursday-Saturday.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Ground-level access, restrooms at same level.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
