<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Becoming Fed Up With Zero Tolerance</title>
    <meta content="03COV.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D61430F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Becoming Fed Up With Zero Tolerance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public and private school administrators nationwide are taking a second look at zero-tolerance policies on weapons, which have at times led to suspensions of students who have brought toenail clippers to school or used their hands as make-believe guns; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PLAYING mumbletypeg. Whittling a slingshot. Taunting a playground rival. Flinging a paper wad.</p>
        <p>What was once a toy is now a weapon. What was once name-calling is now a threat. What was once a prank is now a cause for police action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PLAYING mumbletypeg. Whittling a slingshot. Taunting a playground rival. Flinging a paper wad.</p>
        <p>What was once a toy is now a weapon. What was once name-calling is now a threat. What was once a prank is now a cause for police action.</p>
        <p>As New Jersey's 1.3 million public school children prepare to put away their bathing suits and pick up their backpacks, the question haunts parents and educators alike: Have the passages of childhood and adolescence been transformed into the telltale signs of sociopathy?</p>
        <p>Even though statistics show that school violence has gone down in New Jersey -- and that the chances of a child being killed in school are about one in a million -- the blood-stained images of school rampages remain etched in people's minds.</p>
        <p>In reaction, public and private school administrators nationwide have been pushed to enforce what have become known as zero-tolerance, or strict discipline, policies. This, in part, is the result:</p>
        <p>*A Montclair high school pupil is suspended after brandishing a cigarette lighter shaped like a handgun and jokingly pointing it at another student.</p>
        <p>*Four kindergarten students in Sayreville were suspended for three days last March after apparently using their hands as make-believe handguns.</p>
        <p>*A 9-year-old boy is suspended and made to undergo a psychological evaluation after threatening to use a rubber band to shoot a wad of paper at a fourth-grade classmate at Upper Elementary School in Plainsboro.</p>
        <p>*A 6-year-old in Harrisburg, Pa., is suspended for 10 days after bringing a toenail clipper to school.</p>
        <p>*In Bucks County, Pa., a 16-year-old high school student is suspended and threatened with a one-year expulsion because he has a small Swiss army knife attached to his keychain.</p>
        <p>Now educators as well as the New Jersey Education Association are beginning to take a second look at some of the schools' more stringent measures and questioning whether they make sense in all cases when applied to young children and teenagers.</p>
        <p>In most cases, the rules were written against the backdrop of the school shootings around the country in recent years.</p>
        <p>In Pearl, Miss., a 16-year-old stabbed his mother to death in October 1997, then shot nine fellow students, two of them fatally. In West Paducah, Ky., three girls were shot by a 14-year-old boy at a morning prayer meeting.  In 1998 in Jonesboro, Ark., two youths set off a false alarm and then opened fire on the exiting crowd, killing four classmates and a teacher. In Springfield, Ore., a 15-year-old boy went on a shooting rampgae, killing 4 and wounded 26. There was Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., where two students went on a killing spree, slaying 12 students and teacher before taking their own lives. And this winter, a first-grade student in Flint, Mich., killed another 6-year-old with a handgun.</p>
        <p>No one sees the clock turning back on fear and anxiety in the near future. Nonetheless, many administrators say strict disciplinary policies must be applied with common sense and a great deal of caution.</p>
        <p>''We're revisiting the zero-tolerance issue this fall,'' said Dr. Jon Cosse, the assistant superintendent for pupil personnel services at West Windsor-Plainsboro Regional School District, which includes 8,300 students in its nine schools. ''Kids do a lot of silly things. Teenagers make mistakes.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Dr. Cosse added, administrators clearly feel pressure from worried parents. ''You have a community that's very hyper about these things. Parents get upset if you don't take action. Society today wants the schools to be the policeman and everything else.''</p>
        <p>For its part, the New Jersey Education Association, which represents 162,000 school employees, continues to support zero-tolerance policies. But at the same time, said Lynn Maher, a spokeswoman for the organization, it is looking how those policies are being applied.</p>
        <p>''We continue to monitor the situation,'' Ms. Maher said. ''It's an ongoing process and we have concerns about it. We are concerned that it be applied with reason and common sense. Sometimes what constitutes a threat is questionable.''</p>
        <p>For instance, the Rutherford Institute, a conservative advocacy group based in Virginia, filed a lawsuit last month against the West Windsor-Plainsboro School Board and several others on behalf of the 9-year-old boy who threatened to shoot the paper wad. The lawsuit claims the youth's rights were violated when the police showed up at the family's house at 12:30 a.m. last April to question the child. The district is now reviewing its policies.</p>
        <p>Harvard University's Civil Rights Project -- a far more liberal organization that was formed in 1996 to examine issues of racial and social justice -- along with the Advancement Project, a policy and legal action group based in Washington concluded in a report made public in June that the widespread use of zero-tolerance discipline policies was creating as many problems as it was solving and that there were many cases around the country in which students were harshly diasciplined for infractions where there was no harm intended or done.</p>
        <p>The report, called ''Opportunities Suspended: the Devastating Consequences of Zero Tolerance and School Discipline Policies,'' went on to say that members of minority groups, as well as those who were poor orweak academically or who had special needs, were suspended more often than those who were not, and that these were the very students whose parents often did not have the resources to help the child.</p>
        <p>The report also found that schools were quicker to call in the police, with 41 states now having rules stating when  officers must be notified rather than leaving the decision to the discretion of administrators.</p>
        <p>Included in the report was a case in which a 14-year-old Boy Scout was recommended for expulsion because he had a pocket knife inside his backpack after a camping trip. He was ultimately reinstated, but he missed 80 days of school.</p>
        <p>''It seems like in so many cases the adults aren't exercising any common sense,'' said Johanna Wald, a writer and researcher at the Civil Rights Project. ''There should be room for lesser punishment. These are kids, not prisoners. They make bad judgments and do silly things. Schools are resorting to kicking kids out simply because they are difficult to manage.''</p>
        <p>In Milwaukee, the report showed about a third of the 21,600 high school students faced at least one suspension during high school and almost one half of the 17,600 middle school students were suspended. And in Maryland -- not including Baltimore, the largest school district in the state -- 44,000 students were suspended in the 1997-98 school year for nonviolent offenses.</p>
        <p>''Middle school students by their nature will exercise bad judgment,'' Ms. Wald said. But she also sympathized with administrators, who were trying to respond to the requests -- motivated by parents, the public and politics -- for safe and orderly schools. ''School administrators are facing intense public pressure,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The opening of the report stated that the country's children ''are being shut out of the education system through the application of zero-tolerance policies. These policies require that children in kindergarten through 12th grade receive harsh punishments, often for minor infractions that pose no threat to safety, and yet cause them and their families severe hardship.</p>
        <p>''A strong body of compelling research indicates that these 'get-tough' disciplinary measures often fail to meet sound educational principles and, in many cases, their application simply defies common sense,'' the report went on. ''More alarming than the punishment meted out in schools is the tracking of children into the juvenile justice system for minor misconduct in school. Often African-American, Latino, and disabled children bear the brunt of the consequences of these policies.''</p>
        <p>Yet the policy of zero tolerance did not materialize out of thin air. Parents and educators were frightened. And so were the children, who were also quick to sense the adults' heightened concern. Most schools in the state, in addition to strict codes of conduct, have added programs and classes to educate students about peaceful conflict revolution. Peer mediation and counseling programs have been put into place. In the 2000-2001 school year, about $4.7 million in state funds has been budgeted for school districts throughout the state to begin character education programs.</p>
        <p>Despite the second thoughts about the zero-tolerance policies, New Jersey's Department of Education attributed a drop in the number of violent incidents to the strict policies -- along with $8 million in federal funds.</p>
        <p>''Things are definitely taken more seriously by teachers and students, and now things are probably taken out of proportion some of the time,'' said Jeff Delaney, a 16-year-old  senior at Montclair High School.</p>
        <p>Referring to the massacre at Columbine, Mr. Delaney said: ''Since that happened they have to pay more attention and everyone is a bit more on edge and more cautious.''</p>
        <p>The zero-tolerance policies largely grew out of the Safe and Drug-Free School Act of 1994, which stipulated that schools had to expel any student found with a weapon, or lose federal aid. Those policies have now gone well beyond drugs and weapons, with many schools having adopted a comprehensive set of standards that apply even to dress and speech as well as personal conduct. The policies' approach, which mostly removes discretion, is intended to ensure fairness and protect schools from lawsuits maintaining that a student was treated with bias. But in the 180 days of each school year, administrators often face tough situations where the lines blur.</p>
        <p>''You have to take a common sense approach,'' said Willie Freeman, director of security and chief investigator for Newark's 82 public schools.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Freeman said, a fourth-grader brought a Swiss army knife to school, though he did not open it. Nonetheless, because of the rules, the principal called the police.</p>
        <p>''Zero tolerance says you arrest this child, but that's ridiculous,'' Mr. Freeman said.</p>
        <p>''We try to impress on our staff to take a look before we jump to conclusions,'' Mr. Freeman added. ''In an urban school, kids threaten. We have to look at the children and see what we have. The verbal is the hardest to decide.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, within the boundaries of zero tolerance, many schools find room for discretion. In Haddonfield, for example, the police were called when a student came to the middle school wearing a costume with a sword. Another student took the sword and began waving it, said Michael Klaszky, the principal at Haddonfield Middle School. The sword was turned over to the police, and the parents had to pick it up at the police station. But no action was taken against the student, Mr. Klaszky said, because he did not intend any harm.</p>
        <p>''The parents were angry with me, and I understand that, but I had to follow procedure,'' he said. ''You have to look at each case separately and the context of the action.''</p>
        <p>Five years ago at another school, Mr. Klaszky said a seventh-grade student wrote a list of names that other students described as a ''hit list.'' The issue was resolved by counseling the student and meeting with parents and other students, he said.</p>
        <p>Today, that incident might have been handled much differently.</p>
        <p>''Those things happen and they are frightening,'' Mr. Klaszky said. ''But, you can't be reactive.''</p>
        <p>In today's heightened climate of fear, it does not take much to set off the alarms. Last March, one or more students wrote on a bathroom wall with red marker at the Haddonfield Middle School: ''Columbine will happen here.'' The police were immediately called in, and the building was swept for bombs. Fear rippled through the community; some parents did not send children to school, and the following week meetings were held to calm jittery nerves.</p>
        <p>So far, one student has been charged and the investigation is continuing.</p>
        <p>One police officer told parents that 5 or 10 years ago, the incident would have been handled in a very low-key manner and looked at as a prank. But not these days.</p>
        <p>''People are much more hyper-vigilant and there's hyper-sensitivity where everything is magnified,'' said Dr. Cheryl E. Laney, a psychologist in Haddonfield. ''The schools are so nervous today and they are often used as a scapegoat. Parents and society have the schools running scared. The schools are in a tough position.''</p>
        <p>The problem is, in the current climate, no one is sure how to judge real danger.</p>
        <p>In a case that captured the nation's attention last March,  four kindergarten pupils in Sayreville were suspended for three days for reportedly making threats and shaping their hands like a make-believe handgun. The district declined to provide a detailed account of the incident because one of the parents is suing.</p>
        <p>The episode occurred only days after the principal at the school -- which does not even have a zero tolerance policy --  had gone to each room and spoken to the children about threatening language and how it was not going to be tolerated.</p>
        <p>''When one first-grader shoots another first-grader, all best are off,'' said Dennis Fyffe, the assistant superintendent in Sayreville, referring the killing in Flint, Mich. ''How do you take anything for granted?''</p>
        <p>In Montclair, a high school sophomore was suspended and later arrested in June for flashing a lighter that was shaped like a gun. Two other Montclair students were allowed to graduate -- though not allowed to enter the school -- after buying guns on the Internet, Dr. Michael Osnato, superintendent of schools in Montclair, said.</p>
        <p>''You have to take a firm stand and you can't equivocate,'' Dr. Osnato said. ''Any weapon, you have to notify the police. What we're dealing with in society compels it.''</p>
        <p>The more difficult issue, he agrees, involves verbal and written words from students.</p>
        <p>''The cloudier issues are threats of violence in an E-mail or in an essay,'' he said. ''It's not as cut and dry as the average person would think. When a 10- or 11-year-old child says, 'I wish Mrs. Smith was dead,' that becomes more difficult.''</p>
        <p>Every year, from 20 to 200 standardized tests are flagged by graders and sent back to the state Department of Education because they contain alarming writing by students. Most of the time the flagged tests suggest that the child has been a victim of abuse or is self-destructive. Less frequently, a paper will be sent to the department because a student has indicated that he or she might commit an act of violence.</p>
        <p>A letter is then sent to the district superintendent, who is the only person to see the writing, said Dr. Robert J. Riehs, the department's acting director of the Office of Assessment.</p>
        <p>''In many cases we've been helpful to students,'' Dr. Riehs said. ''Some students are reaching out for help.''</p>
        <p>As for the state Department of Education, it firmly supports zero-tolerance policies. Districts must report anything to the department involving firearms, assault, gang fights, vandalism, robbery, sexual assault and substance abuse. This year, threats will also be added to that list.</p>
        <p>''School officials are under a great deal of pressure,'' said Barbara Anderson, assistant commissioner in the state's division of student services. ''It's a balancing act, and they are going to have to make judgment calls.''</p>
        <p>Cherry Hill East High School in South Jersey has often been described as similar to Columbine because of its suburban location (outside Philadelphia and Camden), its affluent students, its top athletes and its high College Board scores. It has also had a zero tolerance policy for six years, and the principal, James Gallagher, said the experience at Columbine validated the need for such stringent rules of conduct.</p>
        <p>Any act of violence in the school of 1,900 students is reported to the police. Suspensions are given for violent behavior; video cameras have been installed inside and outside the building, and several education and prevention programs are in place, including a two-week freshman health unit on conflict resolution.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, there were 72 suspensions for fighting or assault-like behavior, Mr. Gallagher said. The next year that number dropped by half, and it has decreased every year since then, he said.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gallagher insisted that these policies are enforced with reason and said his administration and teachers have learned along the way.</p>
        <p>''I don't think zero tolerance is that you have zero common sense,'' he said. ''You have to take it with a cautionary note. We've modified things as we've gained experience. There's a danger of going over the edge with this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
