<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marianne Bailliet, Christopher Williams</title>
    <meta content="03BAIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAILLIET, DR. MARIANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, DR. CHRISTOPHER GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA1230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marianne Bailliet, Christopher Williams</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Marianne Bailliet and Dr. Christopher Gerald Williams are to be married today at Branch Point Farm, in Charlottesville, Va. The Rev. R. Tucker Bartholomew III, a Presbyterian minister, is to perform the ceremony.</p>
        <p>The couple are residents at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore, the bride in anesthesiology and the bridegroom in plastic and reconstructive surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Marianne Bailliet and Dr. Christopher Gerald Williams are to be married today at Branch Point Farm, in Charlottesville, Va. The Rev. R. Tucker Bartholomew III, a Presbyterian minister, is to perform the ceremony.</p>
        <p>The couple are residents at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore, the bride in anesthesiology and the bridegroom in plastic and reconstructive surgery.</p>
        <p>The bride, 30, is keeping her name. She graduated magna cum laude from Lehigh University and received her medical degree from the State University Health Science Center in Brooklyn. She is a daughter of Dr. Esther Bailliet and Dr. Marcelo Bailliet of Manhattan. Her father is a psychiatrist at Maimonides Medical Center in Brooklyn. Her mother is the medical director of the adult outpatient department at Soundview Community Mental Health Center in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 28, graduated summa cum laude from Swarthmore College and received his medical degree from the University of Virginia. He is a son of Alice Williams of Freedom, N.H. and Dr. Willis Williams of Atlanta. His mother is an operating room nurse at Memorial Hospital in Conway, N.H. His father is a cardiothoracic surgeon at Egelston Children's Hospital in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>The couple met in Europe in the summer of 1994. Dr. Williams was traveling with his twin brother, and Dr. Bailliet with a friend. They were all on a train platform in the Pyrenees on their way to Cannes, France.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bailliet recalls that Dr. Williams and his brother looked like ''cute frat boys.''</p>
        <p>''I told my girlfriend, 'You go meet them,' because I had handled the introductions when we were in Spain,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Williams remembers that ''this blonde comes up and asks if we knew the country code for France, because they wanted to make a hotel reservation.''</p>
        <p>The four talked on the platform until the train arrived and soon discovered that they had been assigned the same sleeping car. The group spent the night exchanging stories of their lives in the United States and abroad.</p>
        <p>In Cannes, the four young Americans decided to travel together for their remaining weeks in Europe.</p>
        <p>''I knew Chris was someone special on the train,'' Dr. Bailliet said. He has passion for so many different things.'' In Greece, a week after they had met on the platform, Dr. Bailliet remembered her response when Dr. Williams's brother had asked on the train ride what qualities she was looking for in a husband.</p>
        <p>''When I described that person, I realized I was describing Chris,'' she said.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
