<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Amanda Peet; Whipped Into Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="03NITE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/03/living/03NITE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peet, Amanda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Linda</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Whipped (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5D81230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Amanda Peet; Whipped Into Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Night out with actress Amanda Peet for premiere of her new movie, Whipped, described; photo (Pulse column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE she was, Amanda Peet, but in the crowd on Tuesday night at the premiere of her new movie, ''Whipped,'' there was some confusion about which one she was. A stunning woman in a tight black, backless dress posed for the cameras. ''Is that her?'' one photographer asked.</p>
        <p>No. That was Lauren Holly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE she was, Amanda Peet, but in the crowd on Tuesday night at the premiere of her new movie, ''Whipped,'' there was some confusion about which one she was. A stunning woman in a tight black, backless dress posed for the cameras. ''Is that her?'' one photographer asked.</p>
        <p>No. That was Lauren Holly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peet swept into the Chelsea West Cinema wearing a skimpy, blinding blue dress with teeny little straps. ''I get all my fashion advice from her,'' she confided later in the lobby, while the movie was being shown.</p>
        <p>''Her'' was a friend from her days as a history major at Columbia (and yes, Ms. Peet graduated, too): Tina Chai, another history major, who had found her destiny first at Vogue and now as a fashion editor at Us magazine.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chai was there to support Ms. Peet, who seemed to need a lot of support. She was being attended by her manager, Eric Kranzler, from California, who was so completely involved with his client that his lips moved along with hers as she answered hard-hitting questions from E! Entertainment about what it feels like to kiss three men in one movie. Photographers jostled and the crowd looked stumped, for the most part, by the no-name stars of the movie, who gathered with Ms. Peet for a group photo.</p>
        <p>All breezed into the theater for a few words from the director-writer-producer, Peter M. Cohen, who wore the obligatory baseball cap. And then the movie commenced, 88 minutes about four men sitting around talking about scoring with women, and the woman (Ms. Peet) who brings them to their knees.</p>
        <p>About 20 minutes into the movie, Ms. Peet sneaked out with Stephen Hirsh, her agent, to grab a Cosmopolitan from the vodka bar set up in the lobby. New York was Ms. Peet's hometown. She grew up in Manhattan and attended Friends Seminary; later she worked at City Crab on Park Avenue South and 19th Street.</p>
        <p>Those were the days when she was struggling, and only Mr. Hirsh would take her on as a client.</p>
        <p>''I had been rejected by four agencies,'' she recalled. ''William Morris said, 'You're not ready. You have no confidence.'' So I practiced having confidence.'' She demonstrated a brilliant, tooth-baring smile that, truth be told, looked like that of a beauty queen who had indulged in way too much Vaseline.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Peet has every right to be confident now, even though her manager and agent anxiously followed her through the night like pilot fish. She is taping her second season of ''Jack and Jill,'' a series on the WB Television Network. (Believe it or not, she plays ''Jack.'') And ''Whipped'' is a breakout movie for her, a real starring role. It's her third film to be released this year, following a flurry of blink-and-you-missed-it movies: ''Isn't She Great,'' starring Bette Midler as Jacqueline Susann, and ''The Whole Nine Yards,'' a forgettable movie starring Bruce Willis as a hit man and Matthew Perry as a dentist. Ms. Peet, however, got raves for playing the dentist's receptionist. ''She's like grapefruit sorbet: she cleanses the palate,'' Elvis Mitchell wrote in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>All that only eight years after she started out with Mr. Hirsh, rushing to her first audition and ripping her dress ''all the way up my butt,'' she said, miming how she walked into the casting office holding her skirt together behind her. ''I asked the receptionist for a safety pin,'' she recalled, before doing her monologue from Woody Allen's ''Interiors.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peet didn't get the part, and complained bitterly to her agent. ''I have a potty mouth when I'm disappointed,'' she confided. Surely she didn't learn that at Friends Seminary, a private Quaker high school in Manhattan. ''No,'' she said. ''But you've got to do something since you can't hit people.''</p>
        <p>She and Mr. Hirsh went back to watching the movie through the doors at the Chelsea West Cinema. Then he whisked her into a car for the 10-block ride to the Lotus lounge on West 14th Street, where people like Ms. Holly, Stephen Dorff and Linda Evangelista gathered to celebrate one critic's grapefruit sorbet, Hollywood's latest flavor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
