<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bumper Crop From the Middle Ground</title>
    <meta content="03INSI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oppenheimer &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bartlett, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDC1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bumper Crop From the Middle Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts of conversation with Oppenheimer MidCap senior vice president and manager Bruce Bartlett, who focuses on midcap characteristics and why they are currently doing so well; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of these days, or years, advocates of small-capitalization stocks will be right. One day, the market will again recognize -- and reward -- them as fast-growing companies.</p>
        <p>But not just yet. For the time being, advocates of small-cap stocks must be satisfied that investors are at least starting to look down the food chain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of these days, or years, advocates of small-capitalization stocks will be right. One day, the market will again recognize -- and reward -- them as fast-growing companies.</p>
        <p>But not just yet. For the time being, advocates of small-cap stocks must be satisfied that investors are at least starting to look down the food chain.</p>
        <p>Both big-cap and small-cap indexes have had single-digit gains this year. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 is up 3.5 percent; the Russell 2000 has risen 7.4 percent.</p>
        <p>But stocks in the middle, the midcaps, have been standouts. So far this year, the S.&amp; P. 400 Midcap index is up 23.4 percent.</p>
        <p>Bruce Bartlett, a senior vice president and manager of the $2.3 billion Oppenheimer MidCap, a growth fund, recently discussed those stocks in the middle. Following are excerpts from the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. Midcap stocks, which by your definition have a market capitalization of $2 billion to $12 billion, have been rather overlooked for the last few years. Why?</p>
        <p>A. Historically, midcap companies were lost stepchildren. The main selling point for the group appeared to be as a diversification tool. That was a hard sell, and rightly so, because a mixture of large-  and small-cap investments effectively did the same thing.</p>
        <p>We do not invest in midcaps for diversification. We think the real opportunity for investing in midcap companies is that you have a population of companies with revenue and earnings growth rates that are very similar to smaller companies, but with proven managements, and which can go through very extended growth phases. That is the goal and objective of midcap investing.</p>
        <p>Q. Why are midcaps  doing so well now?</p>
        <p>A. They were good performers in 1999 as well. Liquidity plays an important role. When growth was available in large-cap stocks, as it was in 1997, 1998 and last year, there was very little reason for growth managers to migrate down the capitalization spectrum in search of growth. And managers are finding a lot of growth in the midcap arena.</p>
        <p>Q. What characteristics do you look for?</p>
        <p>A. We are pure bottom-up growth investors who focus on exceptionally strong revenue growth.</p>
        <p>Revenue growth is the most sustainable source of earnings growth. And revenue growth is also the best way to measure, monitor and evaluate the health of a company. Also, I am not going to sell a stock just because it reaches some level of market capitalization. That decision is based entirely on the operating characteristics of the company.</p>
        <p>Nearly 70 percent of the MidCap fund is in technology stocks.</p>
        <p>Revenue growth for the companies we are invested in is in excess of 80 percent. The composite earnings growth rate is about 35 percent. And the average price-to-earnings ratio is 54.</p>
        <p>That price-to-earnings ratio is more than double what the S.&amp; P. 500's is, but the earnings growth rate of the S.&amp; P. 500 is roughly 10 percent. So earnings of companies in our portfolio are growing 3.5 times that rate.</p>
        <p>Q. For the last year or so, the Federal Reserve has been raising interest rates to slow the economy. If growth slows, will that have an adverse effect on your portfolio?</p>
        <p>A. A slow-growth economy is a favorable climate for growth investing over all. That is because if you view growth as a commodity, when the economy is robust, growth is plentiful, and many companies have it. It's when growth becomes scarce that companies that can exhibit strong revenue and earnings growth get higher premiums.</p>
        <p>I might add that since we take our cues from the companies we are analyzing and meeting with, right now we are not seeing any reason not to be optimistic. We make our decisions based on what is going on at the companies, not on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Q. You said technology is a big chunk of your portfolio. Which areas there do you favor?</p>
        <p>A. Almost half our technology holdings are in optical components or networking. JDS Uniphase, which is no longer a midcap stock, is one of my largest holdings. We also own stocks like Juniper Networks, Broadcom, Veritas and Ciena. We also own Corvis, which within the past month was priced as a small cap stock but traded to a midcap the first day it was public.</p>
        <p>Q. Which other sectors do you like?</p>
        <p>A. We have some exposure in retailing.  Tiffany, a company with exceptional growth characteristics, is a favorite. And we like Radio Shack.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you own any Internet stocks?</p>
        <p>A. Not any pure Internet companies. But we do own a tremendous amount of Internet infrastructure companies like Exodus Communications. And we have selective positions in contract manufacturers like Flextronics, Jabil and Celestica. Of those, only Jabil is still a midcap company.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
