<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Are the Alternatives to Zero-Tolerance Discipline Policies?</title>
    <meta content="03JSID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7DC1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Are the Alternatives to Zero-Tolerance Discipline Policies?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Educators and psychologists offer viable alternatives to schools' zero-tolerance weapons policies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EDUCATORS and psychologists agree that after such tragedies as the slayings at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., it will be some time before the fear subsides in this country and the pendulum swings back -- even a bit -- to more permissive policies in the schools.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it will ever go back to where it was before Columbine,'' said Dr. Martha Benoff, an educational psychologist in Philadelphia. ''We've been too bruised. We've had an extreme reaction to an extreme event.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EDUCATORS and psychologists agree that after such tragedies as the slayings at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., it will be some time before the fear subsides in this country and the pendulum swings back -- even a bit -- to more permissive policies in the schools.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it will ever go back to where it was before Columbine,'' said Dr. Martha Benoff, an educational psychologist in Philadelphia. ''We've been too bruised. We've had an extreme reaction to an extreme event.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Benoff said that in the months after the shootings at Columbine -- in which two youths murdered 12 students and a teacher before turning their weapons on themselves -- 8 in 10 patients wanted to talk about the event, and many parents called about their children's anxiousness.</p>
        <p>Despite the lingering fear, the psychologist, whose practice consists mainly of patients from Pennsylvania and New Jersey, said that policies that are too brittle and inflexible will not help.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, it became clear that the students who committed the crimes felt ostracized by and alienated from their peers. In May 1999, Barbara Anderson, New Jersey's assistant education commissioner, took part in a meeting in which about 350 middle and high school students discussed their own experiences.</p>
        <p>''What they feel a need for is a caring adult who is nonjudgmental and who is willing to listen,'' said Ms. Anderson. ''The other message is that we need to consider young people's concerns, feelings and needs.''</p>
        <p>It is the youths who feel like ''outsiders'' who often perpetrate violence in schools, she said.</p>
        <p>That is why school districts around the state are working on programs to address nonviolent solutions to conflict. Students in such troubled districts as Atlantic City, Newark, Irvington and Bridgeton, for instance, are learning about alternative ways to deal with potentially violent situations in a program called Students Against Violence and Victimization of Youth. Peer leadership groups use activities like theater to share their message.</p>
        <p>In the West Windsor-Plainsboro Regional District -- where a student was suspended for threatening someone with a paper wad -- high school students have formed what is called The Human Relations Crew, made up of  students from different ethnic backgrounds. The group sponsors discussions and activities in which multi-cultural issues in the school are discussed.</p>
        <p>It is these kinds of programs as opposed to zero-tolerance policies that some educators and psychologists insist may turn back the tide of fear and panic.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dan Gottlieb, a psychologist in Cherry Hill who is the host of a public radio show in Philadelphia, said zero tolerance was often ''legislation based on fear, and in the long run it makes the situation worse.''</p>
        <p>But he said he believed some of the panic would subside and a more flexible approach would return.</p>
        <p>''It will all come back,'' Dr. Gottlieb said. ''We'll have to come back to respecting humanity and respecting ourselves.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
