<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pair of Sisters and a Stranger</title>
    <meta content="03THEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Theater Works (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Redwood, John Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uggams, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gravatt, Lynda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Harold</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Old Settler, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6DC1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pair of Sisters and a Stranger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews John Henry Redwood play The Old Settler, starring Leslie Uggams and Lynda Gravatt and directed by Harold Scott, at Theater Works, Hartford, Conn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHE was a recording star, a nightclub star, a television star and then, at 23, a Broadway star. But the show business ascent of Leslie Uggams started at the age of 6, on a television series called ''Beulah.'' One year later she was a warm-up act for Ella Fitzgerald, Louis Armstrong and Dinah Washington at the Apollo Theater in Harlem.</p>
        <p>An excerpt from the liner notes of the original cast recording of ''Hallelujah, Baby!,'' Ms. Uggams's Tony Award-winning Broadway debut in 1968, puts the life of a child of stage and television into perspective. In no uncertain terms, the notes read: ''What she did for her first six years is her own business.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHE was a recording star, a nightclub star, a television star and then, at 23, a Broadway star. But the show business ascent of Leslie Uggams started at the age of 6, on a television series called ''Beulah.'' One year later she was a warm-up act for Ella Fitzgerald, Louis Armstrong and Dinah Washington at the Apollo Theater in Harlem.</p>
        <p>An excerpt from the liner notes of the original cast recording of ''Hallelujah, Baby!,'' Ms. Uggams's Tony Award-winning Broadway debut in 1968, puts the life of a child of stage and television into perspective. In no uncertain terms, the notes read: ''What she did for her first six years is her own business.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Uggams's dramatic flair was no secret in that oddly structured Broadway musical, a six-decade socio-musical journey of a black entertainer (in which none of the characters aged). Ms. Uggams played a maid who bursts out of the kitchen of rich white people into a career that, in retrospect, parallels her own pop music triumphs. But her Broadway pizazz -- star quality and a heaven-sent voice that kept soaring back up to celestial heights -- were major distractions.</p>
        <p>Broadway, Las Vegas and Atlantic City didn't care that Ms. Uggams, even with Tony in tow, went after intensive dramatic training. Or that nine years after she conquered Broadway, she showed the real goods in ''Roots,'' the highest rated miniseries of the time. Her portrayal of Kizzie, a life force and a survivor of abuse, in harrowing forms, is a television milestone. But her effervescing image of a pop headliner kept her name in boldface and in neon, while diminishing her completeness as a performer.</p>
        <p>That Ms. Uggams has careened from career to career, to borrow a Stephen Sondheim lyric, and that she's still here, is as much a statement of show business inanity and theatrical shortsightedness as it is of her own resilience. While biding her time, and often wasting it, she has been a box office draw, mostly in concerts and in mishmashes like ''Jerry's Girls'' and ''Blues in the Night,'' on Broadway and on interminable tours.</p>
        <p>Now for the real payoff. It remains for Theater Works in Hartford to reveal the urgency, fire and nuance that can only emanate from the flowering of a talent against practical odds. And it is revelatory indeed.</p>
        <p>In John Henry Redwood's warm and appealing four-character play, ''The Old Settler,'' Ms. Uggams is not so much repeating as deepening her performance in the play's limited-run Off Broadway almost two years ago. That followed her dramatic success in a considerably lesser play, ''Black Girl,'' Off Off Broadway in 1995. Without giving up her countrywide musical gigs, Ms. Uggams goes where the real work is.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redwood's very well made play recalls a golden age when the American theater was a welcoming place for the drama of ordinary people, not astoundingly dysfunctional, just troubled, resilient, comic and (his thematic essence) forgiving.</p>
        <p>Once there was an uncelebrated time in Harlem, between the glamorized Renaissance and ghettoization. That was World War II, which Mr. Redwood's play evokes panoramically. No facile black vs. white diatribe, ''The Old Settler'' looks, without being judgmental, at binding, intrinsic humanity. Two sisters in their 50's (Ms. Uggams and Lynda Gravatt) live together, past animosities surfacing, then receding, until a confrontation occurs.</p>
        <p>A roomer brings it on. He's a country boy, looking for his true love (or so he thinks) who has fled to the big city. He means to find her, marry her, and take her back to Frogmore, S.C. He is an innocent who wants to see the sky; in the city there are ''no trees, no lightning bugs,'' he says.</p>
        <p>But there is Elizabeth (Ms. Uggams) who is significantly older -- but not old, he tells her. And here comes an unbelievable mismatch made in a middle-aged woman's fantasies and a playwright's daring imagination and open heart.</p>
        <p>In a lovely ensemble, Ms. Uggams glows with the discovery of a second act in life, never having had a first. Her penultimate scene, in silence and in repose, is heart stopping. Even though she looks too terrific, she manages to appear transformed and rejuvenated. And her no-nonsense declarations (''Don't play with me,'' she warns her young, young beau) are emblazoned by a classical singer's earth-shaking vibrato.</p>
        <p>In a raucous, then unutterably moving performance, Ms. Gravatt travels from a hands-on-hips haughty terror, always mouthing off, to another dimension, honesty unblocked. Informed by the director Harold Scott's grasp of the play's chameleon-like aspects, the interplay between the two actresses is full of dazzling shifts.</p>
        <p>Godfrey L. Simmons and Lisa Renee Pitts as the sensitive bumpkin and the floozie he set out to woo in the first place help invaluably in giving real life to a story that could veer into soap opera with a few wrong turns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redwood's audience-winning play was developed at the O'Neill Center in Waterford in 1995. In its first production, ''The Old Settler''  moved from the McCarter Theater in Princeton, N.J. to the Long Wharf in New Haven in 1997. In vastly different stagings, it teems with life, open to changing interpretations. At Theater Works, it serves a validating purpose for Ms. Uggams, allowing her to infuse true meaning to all that glitters.</p>
        <p>''The Old Settler,'' Theater Works, 233 Pearl Street, Hartford. (860) 527-7838. Performances through Sept. 17.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
