<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Genuine Haydn With Real Spirit</title>
    <meta content="03MERM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Norwegian Chamber Orchestra</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">London Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mermelstein, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andsnes, Leif Ove</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petri, Michala</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judd, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D91F31F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Genuine Haydn With Real Spirit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MERMELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mermelstein, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Mermelstein reviews recordings by the Norwegian pianist Leif Ove Andsnes and Norwegian Chamber Orchestra and by the Danish recorder player Michala Petri and London Philharmonic Orchestra, conducted by James Judd (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAYDN: PIANO CONCERTOS  Leif Ove Andsnes, pianist and conductor; Norwegian Chamber Orchestra. EMI Classics CDC 5 56960 2; CD.</p>
        <p>The young Norwegian pianist Leif Ove Andsnes has enjoyed much praise of late, and rightly so: he is a thoughtful and resourceful artist. If his records don't always do justice to his talent, his live performances usually make the case. And in Haydn, Mr. Andsnes has fared especially well, as two EMI discs make abundantly clear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HAYDN: PIANO CONCERTOS  Leif Ove Andsnes, pianist and conductor; Norwegian Chamber Orchestra. EMI Classics CDC 5 56960 2; CD.</p>
        <p>The young Norwegian pianist Leif Ove Andsnes has enjoyed much praise of late, and rightly so: he is a thoughtful and resourceful artist. If his records don't always do justice to his talent, his live performances usually make the case. And in Haydn, Mr. Andsnes has fared especially well, as two EMI discs make abundantly clear.</p>
        <p>The first, released last year, presented him in solo sonatas. In the second, just out, Mr. Andsnes plays and conducts three of Haydn's spirited concertos, Nos. 3, 4 and 11. (Though the authenticity of many such works attributed to the composer has been questioned, the ones here appear to be genuine Haydn.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Andsnes clearly has abiding affection for this music. In material easily rushed, the pianist and conductor shapes phrases so that his brisk tempos seem warranted, never forced. And the slow movements unfold with refreshing grace.</p>
        <p>Of the three concertos, the one in D (Hob. XVIII: 11) is Haydn's best known, recorded by everyone from Arturo Benedetti Michelangeli to Trevor Pinnock, so Mr. Andsnes faces stiff competition. Yet in the famous Rondo all'Ungarese, comparisons seem completely beside the point as the pianist plays with jolly abandon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andsnes's piano tone is more clean than rich yet attractive nonetheless. More surprising, perhaps, the pianist also proves an able conductor, effectively balancing a band of (mostly) string players against his own musical efforts.</p>
        <p>'SCANDINAVIAN MOODS'  Michala Petri, recorder player; London Philharmonic Orchestra, conducted by James Judd. RCA Red Seal 74321-67950-2; CD.</p>
        <p>With Frans Bruggen pretty much restricting himself to conducting these days, the Danish recorder player Michala Petri stands almost unchallenged on her instrument. She has earned her fame not only because she is an excellent musician with demonstrable virtuoso skills, but also because she has persevered in championing a particularly underappreciated instrument.</p>
        <p>Yet Ms. Petri's latest record, devoted to short pieces from Scandinavia, is disappointing, marred by poor repertory choices, leaden arrangements and bad engineering. Chestnuts by Grieg and minor works by Carl Nielsen and Hugo Alfven lie uneasily next to more modern, though not very challenging, strains.</p>
        <p>The album opens on a particularly sour note, with Ms. Petri sounding uncharacteristically shrill and mechanical in ''Morning'' from Grieg's ''Peer Gynt.'' (Her version of the composer's ''Last Spring,'' later, is better.)</p>
        <p>''Oh Varmeland, So Beautiful'' and ''Waltz for You'' are more engaging. Ms. Petri, accompanied by double bass or vibraphone, sounds vaguely jazzy and more at ease, although the music sounds as if it had been lifted from a Jacques Demy movie.</p>
        <p>Ms. Petri gets a big boost from the Danish baritone Bo Skovhus in ''In the Deep Calm of the Forest'' and Bellman's ''I See the Winged Butterfly in the Garden.'' But for the most part, she makes do with a soupy-sounding London Philharmonic, limply directed by James Judd.</p>
        <p>DAVID MERMELSTEIN</p>
        <p>RECORDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
