<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers Gets Off to a Good Start</title>
    <meta content="03RUTG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Villanova University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DA1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers Gets Off to a Good Start</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY, N.J., Sept. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rutgers defeats Villanova, 34-21, in college football (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After one game, Rutgers has equaled its victory total for last season. True, this 34-21 triumph was over Villanova, a Division I-AA opponent that usually plays teams a level below the I-A Scarlet Knights. But the result was satisfying nonetheless for Rutgers Coach Terry Shea, who is trying to save his job, and for his starting quarterback, Mike McMahon, who returned from a serious shoulder injury.</p>
        <p>McMahon, not yet at his best, threw five touchdown passes, tying a school record, among his 27 completions in 44 attempts for 323 yards. Shea's team, which was 1-10 last season, survived several special-teams mistakes as well as the hot and humid conditions before 23,752 in Rutgers Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After one game, Rutgers has equaled its victory total for last season. True, this 34-21 triumph was over Villanova, a Division I-AA opponent that usually plays teams a level below the I-A Scarlet Knights. But the result was satisfying nonetheless for Rutgers Coach Terry Shea, who is trying to save his job, and for his starting quarterback, Mike McMahon, who returned from a serious shoulder injury.</p>
        <p>McMahon, not yet at his best, threw five touchdown passes, tying a school record, among his 27 completions in 44 attempts for 323 yards. Shea's team, which was 1-10 last season, survived several special-teams mistakes as well as the hot and humid conditions before 23,752 in Rutgers Stadium.</p>
        <p>''We won the football game,'' Shea said. ''We have 100 miles to travel, and we're going to travel them.'' Regarding his quarterback, Shea said: ''He certainly makes things exciting when he moves around the field. He's got a tremendous arm. He's got that ability to make the play.''</p>
        <p>McMahon, who played just five games in 1999, often worked from the shotgun, for both running and passing plays. And he showed better touch on his shorter throws. He frequently threw while rolling out and seemed to play with poise despite his long layoff. He sustained a bloody nose and was temporarily stunned after making a tackle following an interception in the second half.</p>
        <p>''I didn't feel in danger, panicking like I used to,'' McMahon said. ''It just felt like we were having fun.''</p>
        <p>Rutgers led by 14-7 at halftime and it might have been by more but for a botched punt that helped set up a Villanova score. On fourth-and-18 on the Rutgers 48, snapper Brian Hohmann sent the ball over punter Mike Barr. The play died on the Rutgers 10 and Villanova scored on the next play, a completion from Brett Gordon to Brian Westbrook to make the score 7-7.</p>
        <p>That was not the only strange play involving special teams. When a Rutgers field-goal attempt was blocked, Dennis Thomas of the Scarlet Knights kicked the ball ahead, picked it up and carried it to near the Villanova goal line. But the Wildcats were awarded the ball at their 16 because the play had officially died there. Later in the second quarter, a Rutgers punt hit the helmeted head of Villanova's Braheem Powell and went out of bounds.</p>
        <p>McMahon's first touchdown pass went for 17 yards to Errol Johnson to bring a successful end to Rutgers's first possession. The second touchdown pass, with 2 minutes 43 seconds left in the second quarter, went for 3 yards to L. J. Smith to make the score 14-7.</p>
        <p>On the first drive of the second half, a Villanova fumble gave Rutgers the ball at the Wildcats 33. Seven plays later, the Knights increased their lead to 20-7 when McMahon and Johnson connected again, for 5 yards as the quarterback rolled to the short side.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
