<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="03FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDC1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-16</p>
        <p>Russian Refusal Was Vital To Delay on Missile Shield  President Clinton's decision not to authorize even initial construction of a national missile shield had been shaped by events as far back as January, senior administration and Pentagon officials said, when the Russians first made it clear they would not negotiate changes in the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>U.N. Hosts Millennium Summit  The battle over globalization that brought protests to Seattle and Washington moves this week to the United Nations. The three-day Millennium Summit of more than 150 world leaders called to thrash out problems of poverty and peace is turning instead into a debate about the future of the organization, at a time when national boundaries have become nearly as irrelevant to economic and political tides as they are to popular music.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-16</p>
        <p>Russian Refusal Was Vital To Delay on Missile Shield  President Clinton's decision not to authorize even initial construction of a national missile shield had been shaped by events as far back as January, senior administration and Pentagon officials said, when the Russians first made it clear they would not negotiate changes in the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>U.N. Hosts Millennium Summit  The battle over globalization that brought protests to Seattle and Washington moves this week to the United Nations. The three-day Millennium Summit of more than 150 world leaders called to thrash out problems of poverty and peace is turning instead into a debate about the future of the organization, at a time when national boundaries have become nearly as irrelevant to economic and political tides as they are to popular music.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>China Protests U.S. Lawsuit  China is demanding that American officials dismiss a civil lawsuit filed Monday in federal district court in Manhattan charging Li Peng, chairman of the National People's Congress, with human rights abuses stemming from the 1989 military crackdown that killed hundreds of student protesters in Tiananmen Square.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Hostage on Hunger Strike  An American kidnapped by Muslim rebels in the southern Philippines has gone on a hunger strike, the guerrillas said. The Abu Sayyaf rebels had asked that food and medicine be sent to their camp on remote Jolo island for Jeffrey Schilling, 24, of Oakland, Calif. American officials say he is seriously ill and needs regular prescription medicine.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>18-29</p>
        <p>Candidates Court a Sliver Of Voters: the Undecided  Strategists on both sides agree that more than 90 percent of the electorate has by now settled on either Gov. George W. Bush or Vice President Al Gore. That leaves the outcome in November hinging on a sliver of expected voters -- fewer than 10 percent -- who truly have not made up their minds.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Al Gore returned to an earlier version of himself, as a writer, during a difficult time: He was turning 40, was deeply in debt and he had just waged a failed campaign for president. In that period he wrote ''Earth in the Balance,'' an environmental call to arms and an examination of his own life.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The campaign issue of drug pricing is a complex one, involving the economics of advertising, the dynamics of price controls and the budgets of research laboratories.</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, who is not closely tied to President Clinton's failings or achievements, has taken on the job of praising the president in campaign speeches.</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Vermont Voters at Odds  A backlash is under way among conservative voters in Vermont, a state that has taken liberal stands on issues like property taxes, environmental controls and civil unions for gay couples. Thousands of signs have sprouted on barns and garages and front porches, declaring ''Take Back Vermont.''</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>Tire Workers Stay on Job  The union representing nearly 8,000 Bridgestone/Firestone workers told its workers to remain on the job even though the union and company had not reached a settlement before the strike deadline.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>31-38</p>
        <p>Doing the Mambo Not So Easy Anymore  Call it the mambo wars. It could take place on the dance floor of any Latin club -- two people who dance to the same salsa music on different beats. On one hand there are those who dance ''on 2,'' known as New York style mambo; on the other, those who dance ''on 1,'' a majority. Going out to dance did not use to be such a hassle.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Case Against Troopers Fraying  Two years after two New Jersey state troopers opened fire on three unarmed men on the New Jersey Turnpike, turning racial profiling into a national issue, the criminal case against the troopers is fraying. A series of closed-door decisions by prosecutors and the trial judge during the next several weeks will determine whether the most serious charge, attempted murder, is dropped.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Cynicism on Education Ideas  No self-respecting candidate for public office -- be it president, congressman or county commissioner -- gets on the stump these days without having something to say about public education. But the people who actually work in the schools or send their children there say they are less than impressed with what they hear.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Democrats Hope for End of Era  Over the last three decades, State Senator Roy M. Goodman has become a fixture in the politics of Manhattan's East Side and a leader of the moderate wing of the state's Republican Party. But as Mr. Goodman, 70, runs for a 17th term this year, the Democratic Party is hoping to put an end to the Goodman era in Albany.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>Tatiana Riabouchinska  An international ballet star who was the model for the dancing hippopotamus in the 1940 film ''Fantasia'' and the oldest of the three ''baby ballerinas'' who brought fame to the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo in the 1930's, she was 83. Celebrated for the joyousness and warmth of her dancing, Ms. Riabouchinska began her ballet career at 14 and continued performing into the early 1950's. She danced most notably in works by George Balanchine, Leonide Massine and David Lichine, whom she married in 1943.</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>Harold G. Bowen Jr.  A vice admiral who presided over the Navy's investigation into one of the most wrenching episodes in its history -- the seizure of the electronic surveillance ship Pueblo by North Korea, he was 87.</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>39  Weather</p>
        <p>41</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
