<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Paperless Era, the Problem Is Too Much Paper</title>
    <meta content="03ARCH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Archives Management Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DE1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Paperless Era, the Problem Is Too Much Paper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Archives Management Inc of New Brunswick, NJ, which, despite what is touted as paperless era, is engaged in lucrative business of storing business records; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All of his clients  old economy or new, law firms or tech firms, hospitals and colleges or cellular phone companies -- have the same problem: Paper.</p>
        <p>That is where Leon Kroll, chief executive of Archives Management Inc. here, comes in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All of his clients  old economy or new, law firms or tech firms, hospitals and colleges or cellular phone companies -- have the same problem: Paper.</p>
        <p>That is where Leon Kroll, chief executive of Archives Management Inc. here, comes in.</p>
        <p>''They all think that their paper is unique,'' Mr. Kroll said recently. ''My paper? I need my paper. I want my paper. I love my paper. Every lawyer thinks that his file is more important than all the other files in the world, that no one else has this problem. No one else has this problem? I'm in business because you all have this problem.''</p>
        <p>In this paperless economy -- in which nearly everything is stored on a computer disc and backed up on another -- storing paper records is a billion-dollar business.</p>
        <p>For years, Pierce Leahy and Iron Mountain Inc. slugged it out for control of this country's business records. Last year, Iron Mountain acquired Pierce Leahy for $515 million in stock, and now it controls 40 percent of the market. The rest is divided among smaller regional companies like Archives Management, an 11-year-old company whose remarkable 35 percent a year growth is indicative of the nascent market.</p>
        <p>In the records management business, one talks boxes. Eleven years ago, Archives Management had no boxes. Now it has 600,000. The company has five trucks on the road picking up yet more boxes -- 30 employees in all, 150,000 square feet of storage space and a new warehouse that will allow the company to store a half-million more boxes for clients who come from around the state as well as Manhattan and eastern  Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Men with scanners traverse the catwalks along the 22-foot-high shelves that seem to go on endlessly in all directions. Each box has a bar code and inside each box the files are catalogued.</p>
        <p>Rob Kroll, Leon Kroll's son, and the company's manager of information systems and technology, says some customers are even beginning to ask Archives Management to help them manage the files in their offices as well.</p>
        <p>''Leon and his son came in last month and showed us how we can capture control of our entire filing system,'' said Joseph Berger, executive director of Norris, McLaughlin &amp; Marcus, a law firm in Somerville with offices in Westchester and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger said that when attorneys get busy, it is easy for files get misplaced ''and we lose a lot of valuable time looking for them. So we have looked at Leons' system and are in the early stages of incorporating it in how we do business here.''</p>
        <p>Still, for what most companies would consider a modest fee, records centers provide secure, vermin-free, climate-controlled and smoke-sensored space. Moreover, commercial records centers provide high-tech indexing, retrieval and rapid delivery.</p>
        <p>At Archives Management, a file can be  retrieved within three minutes of a request 24 hours a day and can be faxed or delivered in hours. The company also provides electronic data protection and vault storage.</p>
        <p>''Archives Management has become like a second filing area for us,'' said Robert Pinto, files and supplies supervisor at Greenbaum, Rowe, Smith, Ravin, Davis &amp; Himmel, a law firm in Woodbridge. ''They have it all computerized. We can find everything we want. We fax them every day with requests.''</p>
        <p>The 60-year-old Mr. Kroll used to be in the garment business with his father, manufacturing children's outerware, but when they closed they were left with an empty factory. Some friends asked if they could store business records at the vacant building, and soon he and his friends began learning about records management.</p>
        <p>''Someone suggested there was a guy in Georgia who did this,'' he said. ''We all went to Georgia, and we met this guy and he had a building that looked like a fortress, and he took us around the building and he had boxes. It was the first I had ever seen of this. I said, 'How many boxes you got?' He had about 3 million. He said, 'I get $3 dollars a box.' The next day I went into business.''</p>
        <p>Later he bought out his friends.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kroll recruited his first clients at a New Jersey Bar Association meeting in Atlantic City in 1989 -- even though his  father warned him that there was not enough paper in the world to make a business out of storing it.</p>
        <p>But father doesn't always know best. John Ford, managing director of the equity research group at Bear Stearns &amp; Company Inc., says storing and managing business records is a $2 billion-a-year business in the United States.</p>
        <p>Clients buy boxes and rent space per box. A standard box costs $1.75 and about $3.25 a year to store. There is a modest fee for each retrieval and delivery, but there are a lot of retrievals and deliveries. Some company's require 12,000 a month. Companies may begin with a small amount of boxes, but sooner or later, with mergers, acquisitions, laser printers, E-mail and faxes, the boxes multiply exponentially.</p>
        <p>''We used to do records storage ourselves,'' said Georgine Welch, director of materials management at Bayshore Community Hospital in Holmdel. ''We would lease a warehouse. We tried to run it with our existing staff. It was just a nightmare trying to keep the inventory straight, not to mention it cost a fortune between leasing and personnel resources. So we contracted.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. dt ogilvie, associate professor of strategic management at Rutgers University School of Business, put it: ''If you are going to keep your documents on-site, as time goes on you're going to have more space devoted to your documents than to your business. Commercial storage companies do it more efficiently, cheaply and give you better service.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kroll scoffs at the notion that paper is disappearing. ''Just look at lawyers,'' he says. ''Their main product is paper.''</p>
        <p>Even the technology companies store a lot of paper, he added.</p>
        <p>''There's more paper now than there ever, Dr. ogilvie noted. ''We do more diverse things, make duplicates of E-mail messages. And because this is a more litigious environment, people want to document everything and there are legal requirements stipulating how long different types of documents must be saved.''</p>
        <p>Convincing potential customers that it is cost-effective to store their records with his company has not been hard, said Mr. Kroll, and he explained it this way:</p>
        <p>''I go to a law firm. They say to me, No problem. We have it covered. How do you have it covered? We have it stored at the local mini-warehouse down on Route 22. I say to the lawyer, Excuse me, who is in charge of that? They say, Oh Sara. She sits in the front and the key is in her drawer. So when you need something you tell Sara? How much do you pay her $15 an hour? She drives in her car, gets there and the box she needs is on the bottom and now she has to drive back to get you? And she schleps you back to get the boxes and how long did that take? About two hours? And how much do you get paid? Two hundred dollars an hour? Four hundred dollars? I'm going to do it for $1.75.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kroll remembers what it was like to try sell children's outerwear to buyers. ''They want the button here, you got the button there,'' he remembered. ''They want the blue, you got the red.''</p>
        <p>Convincing someone to store their records, he said, ''is easy compared to selling a snowsuit to a buyer at J. C. Penny's.''</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
