<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broadway Star Heads for Paper Mill</title>
    <meta content="03CHIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Chita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reams, Lee Roy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Anything Goes (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DE1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broadway Star Heads for Paper Mill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Actress Chita Rivera and director Lee Roy Reams comment on upcoming opening of Anything Goes at Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the audience for ''Anything Goes'' has anywhere near as much fun watching the show as the star and the director seem to be having in putting in on, the Paper Mill Playhouse will have an entertaining season opener.</p>
        <p>The show, a hit from the 1930's full of Cole Porter songs like ''I Get a Kick Out of You,'' opens Wednesday  with Chita Rivera in the role of Reno Sweeney. For the director, Lee Roy Reams, that says it all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the audience for ''Anything Goes'' has anywhere near as much fun watching the show as the star and the director seem to be having in putting in on, the Paper Mill Playhouse will have an entertaining season opener.</p>
        <p>The show, a hit from the 1930's full of Cole Porter songs like ''I Get a Kick Out of You,'' opens Wednesday  with Chita Rivera in the role of Reno Sweeney. For the director, Lee Roy Reams, that says it all.</p>
        <p>''Everything I love about the musical theater can be summed up in two words: Chita Rivera,'' he said. ''Everybody who wants to be in the musical theater should come and watch Chita Rivera perform.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reams said that Ms. Rivera, whose acting, singing and dancing have won her two Tony awards, brings to the production a first-in-last-out work ethic, a trouper's sense of teamwork and camaraderie, an expertise that enables the director to talk to her on a technical level and get instant results.</p>
        <p>''There isn't anything that I can think of that she can't execute,'' Mr. Reams said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera, in turn, is just as pleased to be working with Mr. Reams, who has a long list of credits as both a director and an actor, on Broadway and at Paper Mill. They have known each other for years and have worked together, although never in the director-star capacity.</p>
        <p>''He's got an amazing sense of humor and love of the theater,'' Ms. Rivera said. ''And this is a great show for Lee Roy to direct because it's lighthearted and fun.''</p>
        <p>''Anything Goes'' opened on Broadway in 1934, starring Ethel Merman, and ran for more than a year. ''By keeping their sense of humor uppermost, they have made a thundering good musical show out of 'Anything Goes,' '' Brooks Atkinson's review in The New York Times said. ''The product is a rag, tag and bobtail of comic situations and of music sung in the spots when it is most exhilarating.''</p>
        <p>The show was revived in 1962 at the Orpheum Theater and again in 1987 at Lincoln Center. That 1987 version, the one being staged at Paper Mill, featured a substantial reworking of the original book, which was by Guy Bolton, P. G. Wodehouse, Howard Lindsay and Russel Crouse. Mr. Crouse's son, Timothy, did the new book along with John Weidman.</p>
        <p>The show has a bit of a New Jersey connection. Its plot originally involved the humorous aftermath of the sinking of a luxury liner. But on Sept. 8, 1934, just before rehearsals were to begin, the S.S. Morro Castle burned off Asbury Park, killing more than 100 people. Suddenly shipwrecks had lost their comedic value. The Wodehouse/Bolton book was hastily reworked by the Crouse/ Lindsay team into the story of a trans-Atlantic cruise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera, of course, has been a part of many opening nights: ''West Side Story'' in 1957, ''Bye Bye Birdie,'' ''The Rink'' and ''Kiss of the Spider Woman'' (the last winning her Tony awards). But opening nights remain special, she said, and Wednesday will be no different.</p>
        <p>''Of course you're nervous, you're excited, but that's the business we're in,'' she said. ''This has fed me for many years, and I hope I've fed it back.''</p>
        <p>The ''Anything Goes'' cast has plenty of experienced players in it -- George Dvorsky, Bruce Adler, Stacey Logan and Patrick Quinn all have extensive credits at Paper Mill or on Broadway or both. Still, Ms. Rivera's imposing resume has the potential to intimidate other members of the cast. Mr. Reams, though, said the actress was not the type of star who likes a pedestal.</p>
        <p>''She's never condescending or classist,'' he said. ''She comes in as a member of the company.''</p>
        <p>If she has a way of putting other cast members at ease, it comes naturally. ''My dressing room was always the place everyone came to socialize,'' Ms. Rivera said. ''That's why I love the theater: It's a place where you work together.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Rivera these days, that often means working with people considerably younger than she is: she turned 67 in January. But age, Ms. Rivera said, is barely relevant.</p>
        <p>Two current films, ''Space Cowboy'' and ''The Crew,'' have shown that there are no age limits for the movies. Ms. Rivera makes the same case for the stage.</p>
        <p>''Life doesn't stop; why should anything stop?'' she said. ''You just get better and better and know what you can and can't do.''</p>
        <p>And so Ms. Rivera, Mr. Reams and the rest of the cast are plugging away in final rehearsals, enjoying the moment. Which is just the way it should be, because, Ms. Rivera suggested, the crucial ingredient of a good musical comedy is that the performers have fun. If that happens, there's a good chance the audience will catch the spirit as well. ''They can tell,'' she said. ''If you're having a good time, that's your job.''</p>
        <p>ANYTHING GOES  Paper Mill Playhouse, Millburn.</p>
        <p>Through Oct. 15. Wednesday, Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m.; Thursday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m.  (973) 376-4343.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
