<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyers for Ecuador Indians See U.S. Judge Linked to Texaco</title>
    <meta content="03TEXA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/03/world/03TEXA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ecuador</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texaco Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rakoff, Jed (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ecuador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Ecuador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDE1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyers for Ecuador Indians See U.S. Judge Linked to Texaco</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal judicial and tax documents show that Federal Judge Jed S Rakoff, who for four years had been considering whether to hear lawsuit filed against Texaco by Ecuadorean Indians who say oil company polluted their lands, attended an expenses-paid seminar on environmental issues held by foundation receiving regular donations from company; former chief exec of Texaco spoke at conference; lawyers for Indians, saying there is appearance of conflict of interest, file motion with Rakoff requesting that he recuse himself and turn case over to someone else (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge who for four years has been considering whether to hear a lawsuit filed against Texaco by Ecuadorean Indians who say the oil company polluted their lands attended an expenses-paid seminar on environmental issues held by a foundation receiving regular donations from the company, according to federal judicial and tax documents obtained by the Indians' lawyers. A former chief executive of Texaco spoke at the conference.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, saying there was the appearance of a conflict of interest, filed a motion on Friday with the judge, Jed S. Rakoff of Federal District Court in Manhattan, requesting that he recuse himself and turn the case over to someone else.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge who for four years has been considering whether to hear a lawsuit filed against Texaco by Ecuadorean Indians who say the oil company polluted their lands attended an expenses-paid seminar on environmental issues held by a foundation receiving regular donations from the company, according to federal judicial and tax documents obtained by the Indians' lawyers. A former chief executive of Texaco spoke at the conference.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, saying there was the appearance of a conflict of interest, filed a motion on Friday with the judge, Jed S. Rakoff of Federal District Court in Manhattan, requesting that he recuse himself and turn the case over to someone else.</p>
        <p>Clerks for Judge Rakoff said his office could not comment on the motion.</p>
        <p>Chris Gidez, a spokesman for Texaco, said the company would not comment other than to say, ''This is a matter for the court to consider.'' He reiterated Texaco's stance that any lawsuit over pollution in Ecuador should be heard in Ecuadorean courts.</p>
        <p>This is a position that Judge Rakoff took three years ago when he dismissed the case as having no basis in American courts. That dismissal was overruled by a federal appeals court, which sent the case back to Judge Rakoff in October 1998. It has been before him since then with no new move to either dismiss it or take it to trial.</p>
        <p>John C. Bonifaz, one of the Indians' lawyers, said the potential conflict for Judge Rakoff lay not just in Texaco's financial support for the organization that played host to the seminar, but also in those who spoke.</p>
        <p>At the six-day event, held at a Montana ranch in September 1998, one of the lecturers was Alfred C. DeCrane Jr., the retired chairman and chief executive officer of Texaco, who ran the company for part of the time it operated in Ecuador. From 1964 to 1990, Texaco helped Ecuador's state-owned oil company, Petroecuador, develop oil fields in the Amazon River basin.</p>
        <p>In the motion filed on Friday, the plaintiffs' lawyers said Judge Rakoff, once he took up the case again, should have told them that he had attended the seminar with the former Texaco executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeCrane's Montana lecture focused on an environmental cleanup at a Texaco refinery in Texas, not on the Amazon, according to representatives of the group running the seminar, the Foundation for Research on Economics and the Environment.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bonifaz said there would have been ample opportunity for Judge Rakoff and Mr. DeCrane to have informal discussions at the dinners, hikes, fishing trips and other activities offered to participants, all of whom were federal judges.</p>
        <p>Telephone calls on Friday to the home and office of Mr. DeCrane, who is now a consultant, were not returned.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit against Texaco was filed in 1993 on behalf of thousands of Indians and settlers in northern Ecuador, after a team of scientists and doctors found extensive pollution of waters and land around the oil fields developed in part by Texaco.</p>
        <p>The suit contends that Texaco failed to use cleanup methods adopted by many other oil companies, and so was partly responsible for the pollution and any subsequent health problems or environmental damage. It demands, among other things, that the company create a medical fund to help affected Indian tribes and other residents of the area and that it begin a comprehensive cleanup.</p>
        <p>Texaco officials said the company had already paid $40 million to Ecuador to help clean up pollution.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
