<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chef Brings a Taste of the World to Island</title>
    <meta content="03CART$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000917T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="A LA CARTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wild Goose, The (Cutchogue, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coe, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDB1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chef Brings a Taste of the World to Island</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scholem, Richard Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Jay Scholem reviews fare at The Wild Goose restaurant in Cutchogue, Long Island, and profiles its French-trained Irish owner-chef Frank Coe; photo (A la Carte column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FRANK COE is a French-trained Irish chef from Cork whose mother was a pastry chef in Lyon. He learned his craft in the kitchens of France, England, Singapore and Australia. Seven years ago he came to this country and was a line chef at Daniel and Le Bernardin before becoming the kitchen commander at Druid's, a Hell's Kitchen hangout where the city's great chefs often gather after their restaurants close.</p>
        <p>Like so many executive chefs, Mr. Coe wanted a place of his own. He and his American wife, Barbara, looked in Manhattan. But as she (a Wharton M.B.A. candidate) says, ''You need a million dollars to open a restaurant there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FRANK COE is a French-trained Irish chef from Cork whose mother was a pastry chef in Lyon. He learned his craft in the kitchens of France, England, Singapore and Australia. Seven years ago he came to this country and was a line chef at Daniel and Le Bernardin before becoming the kitchen commander at Druid's, a Hell's Kitchen hangout where the city's great chefs often gather after their restaurants close.</p>
        <p>Like so many executive chefs, Mr. Coe wanted a place of his own. He and his American wife, Barbara, looked in Manhattan. But as she (a Wharton M.B.A. candidate) says, ''You need a million dollars to open a restaurant there.''</p>
        <p>She grew up in Shoreham, so their search gravitated to Long Island. In late June they bought a funky, down-at-the-heels bar and restaurant called The Blue Top in Cutchogue, where sophisticated restaurants are about as rare as farm stands in Great Neck. ''We were attracted by the vineyards and beauty of the area,'' Mr. Coe's wife explained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coe's first act was to plant an herb and vegetable garden behind his new acquisition. Then he tackled the cleaning, gutting and redecorating and established sources of supply (the nearby Moonbeam Farm furnishes yellow and red beets, the sea scallops are from Maine and an 83-year-old Italian woman in Queens hand-churns the ice cream).</p>
        <p>The restaurant that emerged in late July from all the dreaming, planning and working is called The Wild Goose,at 4805 Depot Lane (631-734-4145). It is far from fancy but is a comfortable, civilized place with well-spaced tables that make conversation possible. Though modest, a sense of style and a touch of class are evident here. A former phone booth is now a linen closet; shaded candles and bouquets are on the cloth-covered tables; lights are softened by rice-paper cylinders and sconces. The bar room has a pressed tin ceiling and there is a fireplace in one of the three dining rooms.</p>
        <p>The jovial Mr. Coe, who enjoys talking as much as he does cooking, is everywhere: working in the kitchen, serving tables and at the end of the evening joining diners for a glass or two of wine. (It was on a bring-your-own basis when I visited.)</p>
        <p>The Wild Goose is, as the sign outside says, ''a distinctive restaurant,'' one with refined food of the sort served on the South Fork, in rustic, humble North Fork surroundings at prices somewhere in between. Soups are $5, almost all desserts are $6 and many entrees are in the $16-to-$19 range.</p>
        <p>The menu changes every two or three days, but there are some regular dishes worth noting. Among the memorable, though small, appetizers are a galette of three types of local organic beets and gigante beans ($9), a layered affair topped with a nugget of goat cheese and dressed with watermelon vinaigrette; and smoky strips of tangy goose with wedges of fresh figs on arugula ($12) enlivened with cinnamon sauteed apples and specks of spiced pears. A fresh, straightforward salad of baby greens ($8) and one with a cluster of portobello mushrooms and strips of roasted peppers and beets atop baby arugula ($9) are worth ordering, as is salmon gravlax ($9.50) on melon rounds with English cucumbers and lightly bathed in a dill and lime dressing. Soups -- gazpacho and a thin, mint-touched English pea -- are unexciting while a salad of artichokes and crab ($10) yielded recognizable shards of crab (not a mash), but its hard artichoke leaves were inedible.</p>
        <p>The kitchen goes into overdrive at entree time. The warm duck breast salad ($18) is terrific, alternating duck and spiced pear strips over a mound of baby greens. Also worth trying are the three jumbo seared scallops ($20) under a tangle of saffron pasta, fennel and zucchini in a lobster bouillabaisse broth ; the apricot-glazed roasted free-range chicken ($19), resting on mashed potatoes and baby bok choy; or the pink, soft strips of free-range lamb tenderloin in a veal stock sauce that incorporates everything from cranberries to marjoram.</p>
        <p>The chef had the good sense not to improvise with a classic, seared tuna nicoise ($18) that boasts anchovies on halved hard-boiled eggs, marinated pitted black olives, reedy green beans and a tender, rare slab of fish. Other worthwhile picks among the medium-size main course choices are a gleaming, ivory-hued halibut steak ($24), enhanced with lemon, mint, parsley and tomatoes; a substantial, fat-fringed grilled rib-eye steak ($25) running with juices; and spinach fettuccine ($16) thick with moist slivers of chicken breast, fennel and zucchini in a hearty tomato pesto broth.</p>
        <p>The warm, made-to-order chocolate truffle cake ($7) with melting white chocolate ice cream and raspberry coulis is a great dessert, and the apple tarte Tatin ($6), with cinnamon and vanilla ice cream, is a close second.</p>
        <p>Service is concerned but not polished. Yet, despite breadbaskets and water glasses going unfilled, most diners leave the warm, welcoming Wild Goose happy: it is a good chef that makes a good restaurant, and one is at work here.</p>
        <p>Openings</p>
        <p>Milano-Napoli, a 90-seat restaurant at 40l Central Avenue in Bethpage (516-822-7479), will replace the 28- year-old Milano later this month. Angelo Morinelli, the chef and owner of La Cisterna in Mineola, says his new spot will serve both Northern and Southern Italian dishes accompanied by pasta and vegetables at entree prices of $14 to $20 with the tab for most full meals in the $20-to-$25 range. Milano-Napoli, decorated in shades of ivory and mauve, features Neapolitan and Milanese specialties like osso buco, braciola Napoli and cotoletta Milanese.</p>
        <p>A. W. Stevens, at Carlyle on the Green, a new restaurant at Bethpage State Park, is the result of an extensive renovation at the site of the 2002 U.S. Open. The 1930's-style spot is a grill serving steaks, chops and seafood. Winnie Togonon, who was the head chef when its owner, Steven Carl, catered the Oheka Castle, is the kitchen commander and Jim Dunn, formerly of the Crescent Beach Club and Star Boggs in Westhampton, manages it. The restaurant, at 99 Quaker Meetinghouse Road in Bethpage State Park in South Farmingdale (516-501-9700), serves breakfast, lunch and dinner indoors and outdoors overlooking the Black Course.</p>
        <p>Marc Weiss, a chef, and Brian Fishman have opened Silhouette Cafe at 274 Merrick Road in Rockville Centre (516-255-9022) at a site that was Scotty Dee's Cafe. The 35-seat Silhouette Cafe is open for breakfast, lunch and dinner, with takeout and prepared foods as well. Foods prepared with health factors in mind will be featured.</p>
        <p>A LA CARTE Email: licarte@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 17, 2000, Sunday  The A la Carte column on Sept. 3, about the Wild Goose, a new restaurant in Cutchogue, misstated the ownership of its building. The property is owned by a company called Trois Ange; Frank and Barbara Coe, the restaurant proprietors, lease it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 17, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The A la Carte column on Sept. 3, about the Wild Goose, a new restaurant in Cutchogue, misstated the ownership of its building. The property is owned by a company called Trois Ange; Frank and Barbara Coe, the restaurant proprietors, lease it.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Email: licarte@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
