<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Last Dance, Candidates Eye The Wallflower</title>
    <meta content="03SWIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D71030F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Last Dance, Candidates Eye The Wallflower</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>TOLEDO, Ohio, Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Strategists on both sides of presidential campaign agree that more than 90 percent of electorate has by now settled on either Gov George W Bush or Vice Pres Al Gore; that leaves outcome in November hinging on sliver of expected voters--fewer than 10 percent--who truly have not made up their minds; this narrow pool of voters reflects what pollsters say has been appreciable shift in electorate in two weeks since Democratic convention: Gore consolidated base vote in his party, something Bush accomplished weeks, if not months, earlier; estimated 5 million of voters who are expected to vote are seen undecided; table shows demographics of undecided voters in most hotly contested states (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor Day is the unofficial opening of the general election campaign, but for most voters the race is already over. Strategists on both sides agree that more than 90 percent of the electorate has by now settled on either Gov. George W. Bush or Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>That leaves the outcome in November hinging on a sliver of expected voters -- fewer than 10 percent -- who truly have not made up their minds. This narrow pool of voters reflects what pollsters say has been an appreciable shift in the electorate in the two weeks since the Democratic convention: Mr. Gore consolidated the base vote in his party, something Mr. Bush accomplished weeks, if not months, earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Labor Day is the unofficial opening of the general election campaign, but for most voters the race is already over. Strategists on both sides agree that more than 90 percent of the electorate has by now settled on either Gov. George W. Bush or Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>That leaves the outcome in November hinging on a sliver of expected voters -- fewer than 10 percent -- who truly have not made up their minds. This narrow pool of voters reflects what pollsters say has been an appreciable shift in the electorate in the two weeks since the Democratic convention: Mr. Gore consolidated the base vote in his party, something Mr. Bush accomplished weeks, if not months, earlier.</p>
        <p>Both sides will still strive to ensure the highest possible turnout from their most faithful partisans. But the campaigns are now devoting their two most precious commodities -- time and money -- in the remaining two months to persuading up-in-the-air voters to side with them.</p>
        <p>Of the 148 million registered voters, 103 million are expected to vote. Of those, an estimated 5 million are undecided. But if this pool is further narrowed to include undecided voters in important battleground states, the actual number of voters that both camps -- and to a lesser degree the third-party contenders -- are fighting over may be fewer than one million. That is minuscule, especially when contrasted with a voting-age population of more than 205 million.</p>
        <p>''That's the gold,'' said John Zogby, a pollster who is not affiliated with either party. ''Kind of sobering, isn't it? Three-quarters of a million to a million voters in 10 states.''</p>
        <p>The competition over these swing voters is driving the political calculations of each side. It explains why Mr. Bush traveled to Ohio today to visit a high school -- his 100th school visit -- and in fact spent all week promoting his education plan. It also explains the Gore campaign's decision to celebrate the Labor Day weekend with a 24-hour ''American Workathon,'' for which the vice president will travel to five cities to spend time with people who are working.</p>
        <p>The push and pull over swing voters is particularly intense and of utmost consequence this year because both sides acknowledge that the electoral dynamic has changed significantly, with polls now showing a dead-even race between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush. For months leading to the party conventions, Mr. Bush  clung to a small but unmistakable lead. In some current polls, Mr. Gore has even pulled ahead.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Gore's aides, citing private and public polls in several states, are confidently declaring for the first time that they are leading in the Electoral College tally. ''We're ahead substantially,'' said Tad Devine, a top strategist for Mr. Gore. ''I've been surprised at the depth of the movement to Gore.''</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, the architect of the Bush strategy, conceded that Mr. Gore had made inroads. Yet Mr. Rove disputed the surveys cited by the Gore camp and insisted that the Texas governor was still dominant in the Electoral College. But, sounding a bit frustrated by questions about his candidate's potency in the polls, Mr. Rove added: ''Tune in, man. We've been saying for about three weeks that the race will essentially be dead even by Labor Day. Welcome to reality!''</p>
        <p>While the undecided voters are not a monolith, surveys show that they do share some characteristics: More than half consider themselves independents. They are mostly married, between the ages of 45 and 64. They hold moderate stands on issues. They voted overwhelmingly for President Clinton's re-election. They are generally from working-class families in which both parents work and the income is between $30,000 and $50,000. Many live in suburbs in the Midwest, and some in rural areas. More than half are women.</p>
        <p>One swing voter is Francis Steffee, 76, a retired food services worker in Kent, Ohio. ''This one is hard to figure out,'' she said. ''One day I'm leaning for one and the next day, well, I'm leaning for the other. I thought I'd wait until they have the debates and see what goes on.''</p>
        <p>Whom does she favor today? ''I'm thinking of Gore,'' she said, explaining that she was put off by Mr. Bush's promises about improving education. ''Everybody says they're going to do this and do that. You know it never happens that way.''</p>
        <p>Arland Van Kirk, 68, a retired worker in a carburetor shop in Lock Haven, Pa., also has not decided. She identifies more with Republicans than Democrats, she said, but voted for Mr. Clinton twice -- and is torn between Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''I think they are both trying too hard,'' Ms. Van Kirk said. ''If they'd just give a straight answer on the tough questions, without all the hemming and hawing.''</p>
        <p>Explaining that she was not inclined to back Mr. Bush, she said: ''I never liked Bush the father. I always thought he was too mealy-mouthed.'' Her problem with Mr. Gore was also one of style. ''He sometimes acts like he's Mr. Big,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush battle over these voters, the candidates' target audiences are slightly different. Strategists on each side said that among undecided voters, Mr. Bush was aiming at a younger, slightly more upscale pool by promoting measures like privatizing Social Security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is struggling to hold on to a chunk of women voters in that swing group who polls show are slipping back to the Democratic fold. That, his advisers said, was the impetus behind his visits to schools because women are particularly supportive of improving schools.</p>
        <p>With his emphasis on prescription drugs and protecting Medicare, Mr. Gore is fashioning his appeals for slightly older swing voters who are faring adequately economically but not as well as they would like. Although his campaign has had far more success with women than men, Mr. Gore is trying to eat into the support for Mr. Bush among working-class men.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign has been more aggressive than the Gore operation in homing in on those swing voters.</p>
        <p>That relentless focus was on display this week in the northwestern corner of Ohio, a crucial battleground state. After Mr. Bush's plane landed at the Toledo airport, one of his aides told reporters that the media market here had the fourth-largest number of swing voters in the state.</p>
        <p>It was no accident that when he arrived, Mr. Bush was greeted by what he called ''a real family of four,'' with an annual income of $50,000, that he said would benefit from his tax cut plan. And it was no accident that on his one stop in Ohio, Mr. Bush headed for Springfield High School in Holland to promote  himself as the candidate most dedicated to improving education.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign could afford to be more narrow in aiming at swing voters, Mr. Rove explained, because Republicans rallied behind Mr. Bush faster than Democrats did behind Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''Elections are won by doing two things: mobilizing your base and winning the independent swing voters,'' Mr. Rove said. ''Our base is mobilized and we're winning independent voters. It's just a question of grinding it out, keeping a focus on the agenda, on your issues -- and pushing it through.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Devine acknowledged that his campaign has been less surgical in pursuing swing voters. He said that was not because the campaign was still trying to woo core supporters but because at this point ''it would be a mistake for us to limit the target audience too narrowly.''</p>
        <p>''We're casting a pretty wide net,'' he said. ''We're not into laser surgery here. It's not like a piece of direct mail that will land in the last two weeks of the election. We're still very much in a very broad, thematic, formative stage of the election.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush was in Ohio today, Mr. Gore was stumping in Seattle with a message of his own for the undecided. Rather than specifically refer to a family with the demographics he is seeking to reach -- as did Mr. Bush -- Mr. Gore broadly appealed to voters who acknowledge the nation's prosperity but worry that they have not benefited sufficiently from it.</p>
        <p>''We've got to fight to make sure that everybody participates in the prosperity,'' Mr. Gore said at an outdoor rally in downtown Seattle, ''that nobody is left behind.''</p>
        <p>That Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are competing over slightly different profiles of swing voters is apparent in their television commercials. Since the Democratic convention, advertising by the Bush campaign and the Republican Party has included images of 40 children or young adults, 18 adults and 15 elderly people, according to an examination by Kathleen Hall Jamieson, dean of the Annenberg School of Communication at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>By contrast, in keeping with Mr. Gore's focus on older voters, Ms. Jamieson found that the Gore and Democratic Party advertisements in that same period featured 23 children or young adults, but 56 adults and 25 elderly people.</p>
        <p>Given that most voters have made up their minds, it is striking that the campaigns' onslaught of advertising is only beginning in earnest.</p>
        <p>Each of the two party nominees receives about $68 million in federal money. So if that money were intended to influence one million voters, that would amount to roughly $136 that both campaigns are spending to sway each of those all-important voters. And while the networks estimate that 50 million people could watch nationally televised candidate debates, the audience the candidates are trying to reach in those debates is far narrower.</p>
        <p>For all the emphasis on swing voters, neither camp wants to neglect its own supporters who may not be as loyal -- and could be susceptible to entreaties from the other side. Mr. Rove said that while his campaign's strategy ''is principally aimed at swing voters, you want to get some of the weak identifiers on the other side.''</p>
        <p>But mostly, the campaigns are debating how to find the formula to entice those swing voters. The problem is that while those voters have been polled again and again, no one can say what moves them.</p>
        <p>''Neither of these guys,'' said Paul Maslin, a Democratic pollster, ''is so strong right now to assume they have the magic answer.''</p>
        <p>Some voters, of course, are out of reach.</p>
        <p>Joe Hesler, 48, a house painter in Collingswood, N.J., said he planned to support Ralph Nader, the Green Party nominee. Asked what it would take to change his mind, he laughed and replied: ''A million dollars. On my doorstep. In cash.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ELECTORATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
