<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carroll Gardens And Thereabouts</title>
    <meta content="03REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EED81230F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carroll Gardens And Thereabouts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from previously published reviews of restaurants in and around Brooklyn's Carroll Gardens (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Banania, French, Asian and Mideast; Ferdinando's Recalls Turn of Century (20th)</p>
        <p>BANANIA CAFE  +  (718) 237-9100; 241 Smith Street, at Douglass Street; $$; no smoking; cash or personal check only.</p>
        <p>Though Banania, named for a French children's drink, feels French, it has added Asian and Middle Eastern touches. Appetizers include cornmeal-crusted Bluepoint oysters with celery root puree and tomato seed vinaigrette; escargot with lemon, parsley and garlic; and grilled asparagus, roast tomato with Gorgonzola-smoked bacon sauce.  Entrees include poached chicken breast with spicy sweet potato dumplings and broccoli with mushroom vinaigrette; grilled pork chop with garlic mashed potatoes, caramelized pearl onions and apples with a pork sage sauce; and wild mushroom phyllo strudel, stewed leeks and red pepper vinaigrette. ($25 and Under: 1/19/00)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At Banania, French, Asian and Mideast; Ferdinando's Recalls Turn of Century (20th)</p>
        <p>BANANIA CAFE  +  (718) 237-9100; 241 Smith Street, at Douglass Street; $$; no smoking; cash or personal check only.</p>
        <p>Though Banania, named for a French children's drink, feels French, it has added Asian and Middle Eastern touches. Appetizers include cornmeal-crusted Bluepoint oysters with celery root puree and tomato seed vinaigrette; escargot with lemon, parsley and garlic; and grilled asparagus, roast tomato with Gorgonzola-smoked bacon sauce.  Entrees include poached chicken breast with spicy sweet potato dumplings and broccoli with mushroom vinaigrette; grilled pork chop with garlic mashed potatoes, caramelized pearl onions and apples with a pork sage sauce; and wild mushroom phyllo strudel, stewed leeks and red pepper vinaigrette. ($25 and Under: 1/19/00)</p>
        <p>FERDINANDO'S FOCACCERIA  +++  (718) 855-1545; 151 Union Street, between Columbia and Hicks Street; $$; no smoking; cash only.</p>
        <p>Ferdinando's is a throwback to turn-of-the-century Brooklyn, even before Ebbets Field opened in 1913.  It serves old Sicilian dishes, like chickpea-flour fritters and a focaccia made with calf's spleen. Current starters include stuffed sun-dried tomatoes; eggplant salad; and stuffed artichoke. Entrees include stuffed calamari with mussels; squid marinated in lemon, herbs and spices;  and tripe in tomato sauce with peas.  (New York Today: April 1998)</p>
        <p>MIGNON  +  (718) 222-8383; 394 Court Street, between Carroll Street and First Place; $$; smoking in the garden; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Mignon, to its credit, wears the face of a restaurant that knows what it's doing. Service in the lace-curtained dining room is friendly, courteous and efficient. Food arrives at an acceptable pace, and it is delicious. Appetizers include homemade seafood bisque; house smoked salmon with goat cheese and roasted beet salad; and spicy lamb sausage with apricots, dates, onions and peppers with oil provencale. Main dishes include salmon and vegetables in a shallot-white wine jus baked in a parchment pouch; braised half-chicken with olives and lemon; and Argentine beef with pommes frites with or without black peppercorn sauce. ($25 and Under: 9/1/99)</p>
        <p>PATOIS  +  (718) 855-1535; 255 Smith Street, between Douglass and Degraw Streets; $$; smoking in the garden; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This French restaurant serves rich, gutsy bistro fare that can range from sauteed sweetbreads to juicy tenderloin of pork and steak frites.  Current appetizers include seafood salad of shrimp and squid with pastis vinaigrette; tuna tartare, radicchio, tellicherry pepper and chive oil; and garlic snails, puff pastry with spinach and chives. Entrees include vegetable pizzetta, wild mushrooms, Parmesan and virgin olive oil; grilled salmon, couscous, marinated prunes and pickled vegetables; and pan-roasted cod, grilled asparagus, cured orange with a light cream fume. ($25 and Under: 1/21/98)</p>
        <p>SUR  +  (718) 875-1716; 232 Smith Street, between Butler and Douglass Streets; $$; no smoking; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Sur, whose name means South in Spanish, attracts a sprinkling of families from 6 to 8 o'clock, but really gets busy afterward. Starters include eggplant au gratin; mussels with parsley, garlic and white wine sauce; and Argentine beef salad with ginger lemon grass vinaigrette. Main dishes include vegetarian cannelloni, stuffed with spinach and ricotta and tomato sauce; poppy-seed-coated red snapper with potatoes, black olives and basil-balsamic-fennel sauce; and filet mignon with braised fennel gratin and haricot verts in a red wine and shallot sauce. ($25 and Under: 12/2/98)</p>
        <p>ZAYTOONS  +  (718) 875-1880; 283 Smith Street, at Degraw Street; $; no smoking; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>The walls are hand-painted here to resemble the thick bricks and archways of an ancient Middle Eastern coffeehouse. The pita bread is a revelation, a soft, pillowy bread that is perfect for scooping up the cool spreads and salads that make up mezze, the Middle Eastern platter of appetizers. House specials include spinach pie, vegetable kebab of portobello mushroom, zucchini, squash, red and green pepper, broccoli and onion; leg of lamb served with mint mayonnaise; marinated lamb chops served with couscous and green salad; and a shrimp kebab platter served with steamed vegetables, couscous and tabouleh. ($25 and Under: 7/7/99)</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
