<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/Dear Abbie; Or, How He Learned to Stop Worrying And Love to Sell Books</title>
    <meta content="03WORD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Connecticut</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Abbie (1936-89)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED91330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/Dear Abbie; Or, How He Learned to Stop Worrying And Love to Sell Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column excerpts letters written by Abbie Hoffman over period of 30 years to his brother, Jack, who donated these and other papers to University of Connecticut; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABBIE HOFFMAN, Yippie, media performer and author, was the say-no-to-war, yes-to-drugs face of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman and his seven years underground, fleeing a 1973 charge of dealing cocaine, are the subject of a new film, ''Steal This Movie,'' which may enlighten young Americans who know some 60's music but regard his life and times as remote from their own dot-com lives. The movie's associate producer, Mr. Hoffman's longtime lawyer, Gerald Lefcourt, recently said, ''Now you can't trust anyone under 30.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABBIE HOFFMAN, Yippie, media performer and author, was the say-no-to-war, yes-to-drugs face of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman and his seven years underground, fleeing a 1973 charge of dealing cocaine, are the subject of a new film, ''Steal This Movie,'' which may enlighten young Americans who know some 60's music but regard his life and times as remote from their own dot-com lives. The movie's associate producer, Mr. Hoffman's longtime lawyer, Gerald Lefcourt, recently said, ''Now you can't trust anyone under 30.''</p>
        <p>The founder of the Youth International Party, Mr. Hoffman died in 1989, in an apparent suicide. His Yippie stunts included scattering dollar bills at the New York Stock Exchange, causing a near stampede; plotting to disrupt the 1968 Democratic National Convention, resulting in him being charged with conspiracy and leading to the famous Chicago Seven trial; and nominating a pig for president.</p>
        <p>He became an environmental activist while in hiding; he surrendered in 1980 and served a brief sentence. Throughout his life Mr. Hoffman wrote, including the letters below to his brother, Jack, who ran the family's medical supply company in Worcester, Mass. His correspondence and F.B.I. documents, along with items like red, white and blue socks, were recently given to the University of Connecticut in Storrs by his brother.</p>
        <p>DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</p>
        <p>On Feb. 14, 1970, jurors began deliberating in the Chicago Seven trial. Judge Julius J. Hoffman had declared Mr. Hoffman, his co-defendants and their lawyers in contempt of court 159 times. Writing to his brother, three days later, he describes his sentence of eight months in prison as laughably lenient.</p>
        <p>2/17/70</p>
        <p>Jack:</p>
        <p>Everything OK -- pressure Casdin [mayor of Worcester] &amp; democrats to pressure congressmen to call for Congressional review of contempt citations, impeachment of Judge Hoffman, Isuance of bail, etc. Really put [them] to the wall. Cook County Jail ain't Grossinger's but we really socked in a hell of a case. . . . I was lucky on the contempt. I should of got over 2 years everybody thinks he made a mistake. He is a total nut. Boston will be a very heavy scene if the verdict comes down against us as will a lot of places. Already a # of bombs have gone off &amp; thousands of demonstrations . . . The tendency for the liberals is to just sweat about the lawyers &amp; forget us, which ain't too good. There should be a demonstration at the Federal Bldg. Saturday if possible -- there are a lot of things to do &amp; quick. Before it's all forgotten.</p>
        <p>Make up a letter for the paper . . . &amp; say it came from me. A revolution needs a few con-artists.</p>
        <p>love,  Abbie</p>
        <p>Four days later, the jury acquitted the defendants on charges of conspiring to disrupt the Democratic National Convention, but convicted five of them, including Mr. Hoffman, of crossing state lines with intent to riot. Their five-year sentences were later overturned but not before much hair, emblematic of the era, was shorn.</p>
        <p>Feb. 2?, 1970</p>
        <p>I've just been moved out of isolation. Just so the newsmen could see me in a cage that was clean and neat. It's unbelievable. I was told it's illegal for the guards to sell mug shots to the newspapers, yet I'm told our pictures are all in every paper today, as I predicted. . . .</p>
        <p>The warden had orders to cut off our hair now rather than wait until next week in the event we got bail and were let out on the streets. . . . Jerry [Rubin] and I had to be handcuffed to the chair. I began to understand for the first time why barber shop poles are red, white and blue. Those colors have come to represent the sadism and brutality present in Amerikan thinking and policy.</p>
        <p>All Amerika is a prison. The president is a warden and the people are all inmates.</p>
        <p>love,  Abbie</p>
        <p>I just saw the haircut story on TV and it is a total obscene lie. I never said anything the way they said except that ''it was an act of racism.'' They all want to make it sound cute but my long-haired brothers and sisters will understand the truth of it and see through their short-haired pig lies.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 28, 1973, Mr. Hoffman was arrested for trying to sell $36,000 worth of cocaine to undercover police officers. About a week later, he wrote to his brother about his arrest and with instructions for sales of his 1971 book, ''Steal This Book.''</p>
        <p>Jack:</p>
        <p>Well what can I say. It was agonizing to see you through the glass darkly. It's Labor Day -- hot -- oh, about 105 in here. I'm in much better shape than when you were here but I have trouble holding the pen right since my writing finger has a huge bunion from finishing my last book. . . .  There's not much I can say about the arrest in a letter. There is a good chance of a legal defense based on the theory you and I agreed on when you visited. Things have made some movement along these lines of investigation and we could discuss this better if you were in New York when I got out probably in a week. Meanwhile, could you try to sell the Steal This Book's [that] you have.</p>
        <p>First call Dick Glassman at Irvall Distributors if you can't reach him, Danny Zimmerman has his number. Danny is at Lancer Books in New York City (on Broadway). Sell them 70 cents each. If Glassman doesn't buy them then ship them all, or the remainder, to Barry Reid in Westminster, Calif. You should have his address from a postcard I sent you a few weeks ago asking you to send him 600 books.</p>
        <p>He's giving me 25% of the profits in a mail order operation handling everything in my next book. Which is already completed. We worked out a nice contract with lawyers etc. I'm counting on ''honor among thieves.'' . . . The publisher wants to print 300,000 now. First run I hope in 2 years Barry could do a revision of the book &amp; we'd split profits on it &amp; all subsequent ones. . . . That way I could have an income for some time.</p>
        <p>In February 1974, Mr. Hoffman jumped bail and disappeared, living as a fugitive in the United States and in Europe until he surrendered in 1980. He uses a pseudonym in the following letter, which was written on stationery from the St. Moritz Hotel in New York City, shortly after the death of his father, John, on March 27, 1974.</p>
        <p>March 1974</p>
        <p>Hello Jack!!</p>
        <p>Sorry we couldn't get together last time you were here in New York. I was tied up a little. Getting along just fine. Staying out of trouble mostly. Sorry about you having to take all responsibility for dad's death but suppose you have some mixed feelings about it all . . . I learned about it peeling off the bandages. New looks are incredible -- I . . . write a lot -- take voice &amp; karate lessons to change voice and gait and for discipline. I've not seen anyone I love for 3 months. Seems forever -- I'm writing a host of letters to folks now because I plan to go into a more isolated state than now even in another month and maybe even stop writing. Although I don't feel too much heat on the scene -- have to dig in for the long haul. Lawyers all over the world are working on things but I like it here in U.S. anyway &amp; want to finish my next book. It will take at least that. It's good if papa didn't get a chance to read it. Wrote mama a letter &amp; assume she showed it to you. Anxious to hear how you are handling everything. Maybe there's something I have to sign or something although notarization could be a problem. Now couldn't it? Lefcourt, by the way, has full power of attorney for me -- legally &amp; can sign anything.</p>
        <p>Your friend, Bebe</p>
        <p>Less than a year before his death, Mr. Hoffman was writing a book about George Bush and the 1988 presidential campaign, including a chapter that was sold as an excerpt to Playboy about Mr. Bush's role in the Iran-Contra affair. A postscript reveals Mr. Hoffman's fears of continuing government surveillance.</p>
        <p>6-1 88</p>
        <p>Jack,</p>
        <p>Because of the explosive contents of this article &amp; a pact I have with Playboy, no one is to make a copy of this article or read it without you present &amp; in possession of all the pages. This is the first chapter of a book by Abbie Hoffman &amp; Jon Silvers [''The Faking of the President''] . . .  The article should present some serious problems for George Bush. . . . Congress may indeed want another whack at why pre-1985 arms sales (we have tons more evidence on this point) weren't pursued more vigorously by the past panels -- that's up to [Representative John Conyers Jr.] &amp; Congress . . . During the research, we just felt it was our obligation to our country &amp; the truth to do a good a job as we could. But if Bush doesn't lose 500,000 votes on this I'll eat the article raw!</p>
        <p>[Postscript] Jack we have every reason to believe the current administration is on our tail &amp; don't trust telephones at this time.</p>
        <p>For all his scoffing at capitalism, Mr. Hoffman showed a passion for marketing and an eye for turning a profit. In one of his last letters, he discussed his latest ventures.</p>
        <p>7/21/88</p>
        <p>Jack:</p>
        <p>These notes refer to [Contemporary Classics, a publishing venture] which I think can be a real steady money maker. I got tons of fans out there -- like a cult rock singer -- who simply aren't covered by mass distribution techniques &amp; desperately want stuff. I auctioned my No Bush . . . T-shirt for $65 for a group. Now I want to start making profit &amp; need your help.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
