<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Goodthumbs To the Rescue</title>
    <meta content="03COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DD1530F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Goodthumbs To the Rescue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Marks Coping column describes his and his wife's reliance on wide variety of service providers to keep their New York City apartment up and running; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHOCKING but true: We paid a guy $82.50 to figure out how to plug in our DVD player.</p>
        <p>I think his name was Tony. I'm not sure because I mostly hid in the bedroom while Tony showed me up in the living room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHOCKING but true: We paid a guy $82.50 to figure out how to plug in our DVD player.</p>
        <p>I think his name was Tony. I'm not sure because I mostly hid in the bedroom while Tony showed me up in the living room.</p>
        <p>Thanks largely to my technical know-how, the DVD sat, unusable, for months. It took Tony about 15 seconds to determine which of the 44 or so holes marked Aux and Input in the back of our new 32-inch flat-screen television were DVD compatible. The job was so elementary, he said, he didn't want to take our money.</p>
        <p>But we were adamant. So for no additional fee, he showed us how the television remote could be programmed to do the work of the 16 other remotes that now took up much of the available table space in our apartment. We gathered excitedly around him as he demonstrated functions we would never in a million years have thought to take advantage of.</p>
        <p>''Ahhhhhh,'' my wife and I said in unison, as if we had been lost on the outskirts of Tehran and just received highway directions in Farsi.</p>
        <p>Moments after he departed, neither of us retained a word of what Tony had said. But what the hay. This was New York, the city that never sleeps and always delivers. We could always drop another $82.50 on some other expert because, well, the city is teeming with them. Yes, friends can be pleasant in a pinch. But it is strangers with skills who are the really desirable guests.</p>
        <p>Having no discernible household skills or talents of our own, my wife and I welcome into our domicile a wide circle of people we don't know. And since our apartment is about the size of a modest hotel suite, we like to think of these home visits not only as our contribution to the local economy, but also as something akin to room service.</p>
        <p>Yes, I know, other New Yorkers are confirmed do-it-yourselfers. We stood by in awe as a friend virtually sacked and pillaged the local Home Depot for fixtures and tools with which she could renovate a bathroom. (We were also treated to a growing repertory of war stories as the project dragged on and the complications mounted.) She deserved a pat on the back when the water finally flowed. Flush with victory, she was. Yet we were not swayed.</p>
        <p>''I'm calling someone'' remained our family motto.</p>
        <p>The concentration of people who know things in this city is a marvel. When, for instance, my daughter's Maltese, Lucky, displayed incipient antisocial tendencies -- he urinated on everything; we screamed; he yawned -- our despair was short-lived because my wife called someone. Reached by cell phone, a dog trainer who made house calls was at our door within hours.</p>
        <p>Linda the trainer was none too impressed with our abilities to tame our six-pound indoor sprinkler. A few minutes of diagnostics, and Linda had his number.</p>
        <p>Moments later, Lucky was fetching slippers, laying out the tea service and dusting down the coffee table. I stood there, feeling a little stupid. ''Hey, who's the alpha male here, anyway?'' I thought to myself. But along with the humiliation came relief. Now, in the future, Lucky would know exactly who was boss. It was Linda.</p>
        <p>Not all our encounters with service providers end quite so satisfactorily. Last fall, we decided that someone should paint and wallpaper our daughter's room. My wife went the smart-consumer route and took bids. The low bidder was a paint-and-paper vet from Canarsie, a garrulous sort who reminded me vaguely of an annoying relative. My wife was filled with the joy of economizing. I was filled with dread.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, on the appointed morning, he walked in the door and the first thing he said to me was: ''I'll have some coffee.''</p>
        <p>I rushed to the kitchen to make some. ''Cream?'' I called out.</p>
        <p>Al -- I've blocked on his name, so I will call him Al -- had wandered into Lizzie's room. He was already deep into the task of determining how not to paint the room and drive me out of my mind in one easy payment of $700. ''Uh-oh,'' Al said. ''Mildew. You have mildew on the walls.'' He pointed to a nearly invisible black dot. ''I can't paint the walls in this condition. A friend of mine worked on a wall with mildew, and he lost his voice for three months.''</p>
        <p>Al promised to return some day, after the walls had been scoured with an industrial-strength cleanser that was out of stock in most hardware stores near you. He did actually return several weeks later to our sterilized apartment to tell me he didn't feel well enough to work. We parted as close friends.</p>
        <p>Oh well. Probably served me right. By the way, does anyone out there know why my PC claims there is no CD in the CD-ROM drive, when in fact there is one? Never mind. I'm calling someone.</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
