<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Pro Football; An Energetic Cowher Lays Foundation To Rebuild The Steelers</title>
    <meta content="03COWH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Steelers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowher, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DD1130F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Pro Football; An Energetic Cowher Lays Foundation To Rebuild The Steelers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses rebuilding of Pittsburgh Steelers, focusing on coach Bill Cowher in his ninth season with team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pittsburgh Steelers have already moved their offices into a $10 million complex renovated from an old mill. A year from now, the Steelers will leave their game-day home of the last 31 years, rusty Three Rivers Stadium, and play in a glistening new $260 million stadium in downtown Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Now to renovate and remodel the team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pittsburgh Steelers have already moved their offices into a $10 million complex renovated from an old mill. A year from now, the Steelers will leave their game-day home of the last 31 years, rusty Three Rivers Stadium, and play in a glistening new $260 million stadium in downtown Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Now to renovate and remodel the team.</p>
        <p>Actually, the Steelers are rebuilding, and the notion has been hard for all involved to accept. But they are what they are -- a team that has crawled to 7-9 and 6-10 records in the last two seasons, missing the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Bill Cowher, the Steelers' coach, survived the gutting process. He went to the Steelers' owner, Dan Rooney, after last season -- one full of trying times and a 1-7 finish -- and told Rooney he was willing to step down if he was the problem. Rooney said no. But Cowher's relationship with Tom Donahoe, the team's former personnel chief, had soured. One had to go. It was Donahoe.</p>
        <p>Cowher watched last season and this preseason as Kordell Stewart kept slipping and suffering at quarterback. A move was required. When Pittsburgh opens the season at home today against the Baltimore Ravens, Kent Graham starts as the new quarterback.</p>
        <p>So, for now, no more Donahoe or Stewart migraines for Cowher.</p>
        <p>No wonder the coach has a new pep in his voice and in his walk.</p>
        <p>''I guess we're reshaping ourselves and I have a renewed energy about that,'' Cowher said. ''We've got a good blend going and we're trying to strike gold again. When you sit back and reflect, it's been hard. We've been through some tough times in the last two years. We're moving past that.''</p>
        <p>If you coach in the National Football League for as long as Cowher has, stuff happens. Weird stuff. This is his ninth season in Pittsburgh and, along with Minnesota's Dennis Green, he is currently the most tenured coach with one team in the league. For Cowher, 43, for all longtime coaches, the cycle of winning and losing is consuming, engulfing. And, often, somehow, the valleys swallow the peaks.</p>
        <p>For Cowher, it seems like yesterday that he was 34, having been a defensive coach in Cleveland and Kansas City for seven years and a linebacker with the Browns and Eagles for five years before that. It was when Cowher was 34, in 1992, that Rooney turned to Cowher for leadership.</p>
        <p>Remember the Cowher start as Pittsburgh coach? An 11-5 record and a divisional championship in his first season. And then his Steelers went 9-7, 12-4 and 11-5, winning two more divisional titles and earning a Super Bowl berth. He was 38 when he coached his Super Bowl team that lost to Dallas in Super Bowl XXX and that made him the youngest head coach ever in a Super Bowl. That was followed with two more winning seasons and two more playoff teams. This was nice. Cowher was making winning look so easy. He was intense on the sideline, prepared before and during games and his players responded to his emotional brand of coaching.</p>
        <p>Now he leads a cast that has lost six consecutive divisional games and one that went 2-6 at home last season.</p>
        <p>Now he is overcoming two seasons where his players and coaches said he was a brooding Bill, a less-excited coach, one that appeared frazzled and sapped.</p>
        <p>Cowher said of Donahoe: ''It didn't work out.''</p>
        <p>Rooney said: ''We had conversations in December and January after the season,  and it was obvious that some relationships in this organization had become strained,  and that it was not a comfortable situation for anyone. It was obvious that the way it was going was not going to work. Basically, my job is to do what is best for this team. I think the way we went was and is.</p>
        <p>''I have to say Bill is more relaxed this year, more energized and positive. He wants to develop our young players. We are being realistic -- we are not running around here saying we'll be in the Super Bowl. We are building and improving, and that is something that goes against the grain for us because our object is to win. We approach things in ways that a lot of people think is antiquated, but we believe in drafting and developing our players and making decisions in free agency that really count.</p>
        <p>''We've made mistakes. I, for one, for example, did not want to lose Rod Woodson a couple of years ago and we probably shouldn't have. But right now we are approaching things as a team in management and coaching, in unison, and we go from here.''</p>
        <p>For Cowher, that means juggling his quarterbacks. He will give Graham the chance to lead, but chances are Stewart will emerge at quarterback sometime during the season because Graham, throughout his career, has not been able to maintain the starting job. Cowher's offensive line needs more manpower. His defensive line, too. And his receivers are talented -- especially the rookie Plaxico Burress -- but awfully young and very hesitant, showing a reluctance to go after the football and swipe it.</p>
        <p>''The players felt like Bill would be back this year,'' said the running back Jerome Bettis. ''When you have two straight losing seasons, there is a feeling of desperation. But we've lost players and have not been able to keep talented guys and the coach can only work with what he's got. Bill wears his heart on his sleeve and what you see is what you get. He's straitlaced. He's a motivator. Some people think some of his actions on the sideline are staged, but he's just into the game and his players.</p>
        <p>''He's toughened up now. He used to have a veteran team and allowed guys to lead and gave them room. Now he has a lot of young players and I see him going back to his early days of establishing order. And guys like that because he is straight and fair.''</p>
        <p>The season could be lost for Pittsburgh just about the time it starts. The Steelers play eight of their first nine games against divisional opponents and have recently struggled mightily in the American Conference Central, even losing last year at home to the expansion Cleveland Browns. But as long as the Steelers simply show progress, Cowher, a Pittsburgh native, will be around for a while.</p>
        <p>''It is a young team and I'm communicating more and trying to make them feel what it really means to be a Steeler and the joy of winning,'' Cowher said. ''I am thrilled about the new complex and the new stadium because, with that built-in excitement, it just makes everything easier.''</p>
        <p>Cowher knows he cannot go back to old glory.</p>
        <p>But at least he has a shot to create it anew.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
