<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Lines Harden Over Syosset Mall</title>
    <meta content="03MALL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syosset (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taubman Centers Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDA1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Lines Harden Over Syosset Mall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>SYOSSET</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Six-year battle over Taubman Co's proposed Mall at Oyster Bay in Syosset, Long Island, comes closer to resolution as Town Board holds public hearing on proposal; photo; drawing; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE six-year battle over an upscale shopping mall in Syosset will draw a little closer to a resolution on Thursday when the Oyster Bay Town Board holds a public hearing on the proposal. The developer, the Taubman Company of Bloomfield Hills, Mich., is asking for a special-use permit to build the 860,000-square-foot project, to be called the Mall at Oyster Bay, on the 39-acre site formerly owned by the Cerro Wire and Cable Company.</p>
        <p>Since 1994, when the development was first proposed, the project has been a source of controversy in the Town of Oyster Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE six-year battle over an upscale shopping mall in Syosset will draw a little closer to a resolution on Thursday when the Oyster Bay Town Board holds a public hearing on the proposal. The developer, the Taubman Company of Bloomfield Hills, Mich., is asking for a special-use permit to build the 860,000-square-foot project, to be called the Mall at Oyster Bay, on the 39-acre site formerly owned by the Cerro Wire and Cable Company.</p>
        <p>Since 1994, when the development was first proposed, the project has been a source of controversy in the Town of Oyster Bay.</p>
        <p>''This has become an emotionally charged issue,'' Supervisor John Venditto said. ''Everybody has an opinion and everybody wants the last word. We're dealing with an application that could have a significant impact on the personality of the Town of Oyster Bay and that could change the direction of its future.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Venditto said he expects the town board to vote on the project next month.</p>
        <p>If approved, the Mall at Oyster Bay will be a fashion-oriented shopping center, with a Neiman Marcus and two other anchor stores. One of them may be Saks Fifth Avenue, which was thwarted last year when it tried to move its Garden City store to Roosevelt Field. There will be 125 to 150 smaller shops and a three-level parking garage.</p>
        <p>Harry Murphy, the senior vice president for development at Taubman, said: ''We're not interested in building another Roosevelt Field. We've discovered in our research that many fashion-oriented stores, like Neiman Marcus, have been looking to get into Nassau County for a long time because it's a ripe market. We have a list of tenants who have no presence on Long Island who we think might be interested in coming out here.''</p>
        <p>The mall's supporters contend that it will generate jobs and tax revenues, but its critics argue that Nassau County does not need another mall, that it will adversely affect stores already established in other shopping centers and that it will drive out smaller local merchants. They contend that traffic will be a problem, with an estimated 24,000 cars going to and from the mall each day, causing bottlenecks on major arteries. Further, they fear that drivers will cut through residential streets to get to the mall, endangering children in the neighborhood and at two elementary schools nearby.</p>
        <p>''I don't know of anyone in the community who approves of this project,'' said Susan Sariego, who lives in the East Birchwood section of Syosset, near the site. ''We are all concerned about how this will affect our quality of life. They keep talking about upscale, but upscale is unimportant when it still generates traffic and pollution to our community. Cars are still cars. I can't imagine how our children will be able to cross the street.''</p>
        <p>Traffic congestion and safety are the most pressing concerns for local residents, said Todd Fabricant, the chairman of the Cerro Wire Coalition, a group of some two dozen civic associations united to block the mall.</p>
        <p>''Jericho Turnpike is already a disaster at 5 o'clock,'' he said. ''The mall's primary entrance will be very close to the Long Island Rail Road crossing, which will result in dangerous conditions. When you put 3,000 cars an hour in front of a railroad crossing on an ongoing basis, there is no way that people will be able to move. There is also no public transportation for workers to get to the mall. Just wait until Christmastime and when the mall runs sales.''</p>
        <p>Residents are concerned that the proposed mall will destroy existing businesses, said Len Gutterman, a board member of the West Birchwood Civic Association, which represents a neighborhood near the site.</p>
        <p>''We've seen Home Depot, BJ's and Costco come to the Island and knock out many small stores,'' he said. ''We wonder, if another mall comes in, what will happen to the small merchants along Jericho Turnpike and Northern Boulevard? And what will happen to the Broadway Mall and Walt Whitman Mall that are not far away?''</p>
        <p>Last month, the Nassau County Chambers of Commerce, representing 6,000 businesses, came out against the mall.</p>
        <p>''The county is malled out,'' said Gary Hudes, the organization's president. ''From a business standpoint, another mall would result in cutting the retail pie into smaller and smaller pieces. People only have so much money to spend, and unless you bring in new shoppers from outside Nassau County, which is unlikely, the existing money will just be spread around even more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy, the executive at Taubman, which was responsible for the Mall at Short Hills, in New Jersey, said that community resistance to a proposed mall was a common initial reaction, one that usually disappears once the mall opens.</p>
        <p>''We developed a similar project in an affluent neighborhood in Short Hiills, and there were many concerns, but now they love us there,'' he said. ''We intend to do the same things to make this work in Nassau County.''</p>
        <p>The Taubman Company is a 50-year-old publicly owned manager of retail malls at 28 locations throughout the United States. Working with the Tribune Company, the Chicago newspaper publisher that now owns the Cerro property, Taubman took control in 1990, four years after Cerro closed its plant and sold the site.</p>
        <p>The Cerro Wire and Cable Company built its plant in the early 1950's, and with a work force of 600 it manufactured electrical conduits and copper rods there. The state Department of Environmental Conservation declared it an inactive hazardous waste site in 1983, but after a  cleanup, it was removed from the list in 1994.</p>
        <p>Proponents of the mall say it will create 4,500 construction jobs and 1,900 permanent jobs and bring in $7 million in property taxes and $22.5 million in sales taxes each year.</p>
        <p>''This is a responsible project that will provide $100 million in wages'' in three years, during the site preparation and the mall's construction, said Morton Weber, the Melville lawyer who represents Taubman. ''Local residents are complaining that they don't want it here, yet these will be the same people who will be among the first to shop there.''</p>
        <p>The Nassau-Suffolk Building Trades Council, which represents about 60,000 construction workers on Long Island, recently endorsed the project.</p>
        <p>''We need work opportunities for our people,'' said its president, Jack Kennedy. ''We're talking about a lot of employment over a long period of time. The property has been an economic black hole that contributes next to nothing in way of tax revenue to the county or town. It's time to build and get rid of this eyesore.''</p>
        <p>Gary Lewi, Taubman's community affairs representative, said: ''The mall is the only thing on the boards that stands between us and tax increases that could be so onerous as to erode our property values. This is something that critics will have to wrestle with, because it's an economic fact of life.''</p>
        <p>But critics think otherwise. ''This is a zoning and planning issue that should not consider the fact that Nassau County is having fiscal troubles,'' said Howard Avrutine, a Syosset lawyer who represents the Birchwood Civic Association. ''It's about how the land should be used appropriately in a way that is harmonious with the surrounding area. Why should residents nearby this property bear a disproportionate burden because Nassau County has financial problems? This shouldn't be a bailout on anybody.''</p>
        <p>In anticipation of the hearing, Mr. Venditto, the supervisor, said: ''There are two very strong positions. It seems that regardless of the final decision by the board, the matter will be the subject of litigation in the Supreme Court and probably beyond. We are determined to make sure that our decision is adequately supported in law by the evidence presented on Thursday.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
