<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Escape the Hamptons: Paddle!</title>
    <meta content="03VIEW$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montauk (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chaplin, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DB1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Escape the Hamptons: Paddle!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA CHAPLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chaplin, Julia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Surfer scene on Montauk, Long Island, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS I was gliding over the chop on my surfboard last Saturday afternoon, wearing a red bikini and matching long-sleeve rash guard, hair matted with salt, I greeted the members of the motley bronzed gang I'd known for three months, but whose names I still hadn't caught: ''Hey man, catch any good rides today?''</p>
        <p>This wasn't exactly how I had planned on spending my summer in the Hamptons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS I was gliding over the chop on my surfboard last Saturday afternoon, wearing a red bikini and matching long-sleeve rash guard, hair matted with salt, I greeted the members of the motley bronzed gang I'd known for three months, but whose names I still hadn't caught: ''Hey man, catch any good rides today?''</p>
        <p>This wasn't exactly how I had planned on spending my summer in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>True, after learning surf basics during recent vacations in Mexico and Los Angeles, I had purchased a 1987 black Monte Carlo SS so I could cart my long board in style to a cramped surf shack near Ditch Plains, Montauk's surf mecca. But I wasn't ''hard core'' or anything. I had only rented the place, sight unseen, with seven other Manhattan surfers I'd met by chance at a club just before Memorial Day. (That I claimed I could surf and pay rent served as adequate reference.)</p>
        <p>In addition to working the tube, I admit that I also had designs on that party circuit featured in ''The Mix'' pages of Hamptons magazine. But after the first few weekends of making the 45-minute commute to party alongside 18-year-old models with sharp elbows, my will began to wane. The moment of truth came after Jay Z's Fourth of July barbecue. Around 3 a.m., at Conscience Point, I found myself showing off my prized surf bruises to a man wearing shiny loafers, a tennis sweater over his shoulders and a totally glazed look.</p>
        <p>That night, the tug of the Montauk tide won out. I headed east and never looked back. I gave up trying to tame my hair against the forces of the ocean humidity and went with the sun-damaged, nappy look. I closeted my Gucci heels in favor of flip-flops, shelved the hip-hop CD's and bought the Beach Boys' ''Pet Sounds.'' The adjectives ''stoked,'' ''gnarly'' and ''epic'' filtered into my vocabulary. I was converted.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, I was just joining the wave. While there have been surfers in Montauk since the 1960's, over the last few years a new set of boarders is turning out in record numbers. Hipsters, models, photographers and architects can be spotted riding the soup alongside local teenagers and fellow Manhattanites, including the artist Julian Schnabel, the designer Tracy Feith, the Razorfish co-founder Jeff Dachis, Paper magazine's David Hershkovits (though he's actually a boogie boarder), and the nightclub impresario Will Regan of Union Bar and Lotus.</p>
        <p>Stuart Foley, who opened the Air &amp; Speed Board Shop in Montauk five years ago, says his business has taken off in the last two seasons. ''There's more surfers than ever, particularly among women and beginners,'' said Mr. Foley, who started holding surf camps this summer to meet the demand for lessons. East Deck, a 50's-style motel with rickety wood-paneled suites is a favorite surfer hangout -- the Four Seasons of Montauk -- because of its choice beach location in Ditch Plains. The motel has had to implement a waiting list for the rooms closest to the break, known as the ''A'' section, and is planning to install a digital camera on the roof that will feed real-time images of the waves to a surf forecast Web site.</p>
        <p>Gerri Tomitaz, a real estate agent at Remington Realty Ltd., who has been renting homes in Montauk for almost 10 years, says that she has been getting calls from more and more surfers and that as a group surfers are gaining greater social status. ''Years ago nobody wanted to rent to surfers because they had a reputation for being slobs and bums,'' Ms. Tomitaz said. ''But this new breed is more affluent and upscale. They're restaurateurs and architects, and are considered very desirable tenants.''</p>
        <p>Alison Haas, 24, a public relations associate at Chanel, started surfing this summer, after renting a splintery shack in Ditch Plains with 14 other people. She has abandoned the tonier Hamptons for good. ''Out here you can wear flip-flops and sarongs all day,'' she said, peeling off her rash guard shirt and spraying herself with Chanel sunscreen. ''There's no scene out here at all.''</p>
        <p>Fast-lane dropouts may be heading to Montauk as much for surf-worthy waves as for its anti-Hamptons attitude, but the laid-back vibe can take some gelling. In Montauk, tiny houses are seen as a conceptual style choice, not a sign of an anemic bank account. Even so, when I first laid eyes on my summer rental, decent by surf share standards, I was somewhat taken aback. It was hardly the sprawling bachelor lair I had envisioned; instead, it was a flimsy pre-fab modular, a low-rent version of the kind in ''The Truman Show.'' In place of a pool or a hot tub in the yard there was a mosquito-ridden swamp, and the view consisted of a bulldozer and a few tricycles abandoned by the kids across the street.  Getting my equipment out of the basement was always worrisome: a cute surfer housemate with a knack for picking up girls slept down there on a double mattress.</p>
        <p>It took some adjusting to give up all addictions to gourmet coffees and food. Most of the restaurant fare in Montauk is greasy, overcooked or fried. Brawny athletic types in board shorts lounge about sipping coffees -- no cappuccinos -- outside delis and packing post-surf-session carbohydrates at hokey diners like Mr. John's Pancake House. The most nouvelle option is the Ditch Witch, a health-food truck that sells wraps and smoothies in the dirt lot in front of the main break.</p>
        <p>Social life out East might not require a lot of thought about what logos to wear to polo matches, but it has its own etiquette, like not ''dropping in'' on other people's waves or ''bailing off'' boards on crowded, two-foot waves. Name-dropping is another no-no, largely because people don't even know each other's names. Like American Indians or mobsters, surfers tend to be identified by their most prominent physical characteristics, though admittedly they're less inventive (''the cute blond guy with the red board'').</p>
        <p>Even the calendar is different out here. While most Hamptonites pack up on Labor Day, the surfer season peaks from August through October, when the hurricane storms create the best swells.</p>
        <p>Of course, even fall waves on Long Island aren't that big compared with  the macking towers of power found in California and Hawaii. But that's not necessarily a bad thing. In Montauk, the summer swells are typically a manageable one to three feet, so it's easy to come off looking like a pro. Status is measured in other ways. You're somewhere near the top of the pecking order if you: 1) have friends who are pro surfers or have met Kelly Slater, 2) have lived/ surfed in Hawaii or know someone who does, 3) know Peter Beard well enough to cut through his property to get to the break called Ranch or 4) are self-employed so that you can take off at a moment's notice if the surf's up.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the word is out. Surfers and ''posers'' alike are flocking to have a piece of the local motion, the main road through town is lined with cars and SUV's toting piles of boards on their roofs and, contrary to the idyllic images on local postcards, on the weekends the waves are so packed with surfers and boogie boarders that it looks like the Long Island Expressway during rush hour. In fact, it's starting to resemble the showy beach scene at Sagaponack's Sagg Main. One day when a guy who looked like a banker pulled up in a silver Mercedes carrying an expensive board with no wax on it (a sure sign of little usage) my housemate Tommy shook his head and sneered, ''What a Barney,'' surfer-speak for a rich guy who has the latest gear but can't surf.</p>
        <p>But you can't stress on the bunk vibes. Montauk has its own low-key charms, the kind of mindless, grungy summer pleasures you might have had when you were a teenager. We bought a few Tiki torches, a hammock and Hula-Hoops from Kmart. With the dozens of surfboards leaned up against the house, I had to admit it looked pretty authentic.</p>
        <p>We held backyard cookouts and made cozy beach bonfires where we debated the day's rides and made wide-eyed plans to go on surf safaris to such tubular paradises as Fiji and Mexico. On the days when the waves weren't ''working'' we huddled on our sandy couch, reading surf magazines and watching surf videos and the Weather Channel. Sometimes at night, we'd pile into my housemates' giant cargo van and drive to local bars like Cantina, a Mexican-themed dive with too many cactus paintings, for its weekly surf social.</p>
        <p>There we'd consume beer and chips in front of a big-screen TV and watch more surf footage. A favorite was the amateurish ''Big Wednesday,'' shot last August off Ditch Plains during eight-foot hurricane swells. Whenever people at the bar saw someone they knew riding the tube they'd wave a fist and cheer: ''Ye-ah! Shred it up, dude!''</p>
        <p>By mid-August, tanned and buff, we all decided to make our summer as endless as possible and extend our rental till November.</p>
        <p>VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
