<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parking Fines Rise, and Tempers Follow</title>
    <meta content="03TICK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE1730F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parking Fines Rise, and Tempers Follow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frustrated motorists show up in traffic courts in Hamptons, NY, to protest sharp rise in fines for parking near beaches; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN East Hampton Town Justice Court last Monday, there were about a dozen people with frustrated looks on their well-tanned faces.</p>
        <p>Some wore suits, and some wore sandals. Some lived nearby, while others had trekked out from Manhattan. Most held little white parking tickets with big fines -- $125 to be exact, or about the cost of dinner for two at Nick &amp; Toni's -- for illegally parking near a beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN East Hampton Town Justice Court last Monday, there were about a dozen people with frustrated looks on their well-tanned faces.</p>
        <p>Some wore suits, and some wore sandals. Some lived nearby, while others had trekked out from Manhattan. Most held little white parking tickets with big fines -- $125 to be exact, or about the cost of dinner for two at Nick &amp; Toni's -- for illegally parking near a beach.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Town of East Hampton increased the fine for illegally parking near its beaches from $40 to $125, and this year the Town of Southampton raised its fines, too, from $50 to $100.</p>
        <p>Now, this has become a common sight on the East End this summer: visitors, especially those who were in a rush to park and head to the surf  after a hot, slow ride eastward, return to their cars and discover some unpleasant news on their windshields. Many drivers go into summons shock over the stiff penalties. And more of them are showing up in court to fight the fines.</p>
        <p>Last Monday, one driver after another tried to persuade Town Justice Catherine A. Cahill that they were wrongly ticketed.</p>
        <p>There was Rachel Feingold, a manager of the Cynthia Rowley boutique in East Hampton who got a $125 parking ticket on June 17 -- her 21st birthday -- for parking in the lot at Indian Wells Beach in Amagansett without a beach parking permit. It was her first time there, she said, and there were no signs near where she parked.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feingold, a college student from Atlanta, said she had gotten the first three parking tickets of her life this summer, her first in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cahill told her she could plead her case at trial, but that would have to be during the Christmas vacation or next summer. She explained that the ticketing agent, another college student, had already gone back to school.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feingold replied that she, too, was going back to college and could not appear again. Finally, Ms. Cahill reduced the fine to $40, in part, she said, ''because you're a college student.''</p>
        <p>The next to appear was Louise Nigro, who got a $125 ticket in July for parking at the Ditch Plains beach in Montauk without a proper permit.</p>
        <p>She showed the judge the parking permit she had displayed, one issued by a local homeowners' association. But a town prosecutor informed her that many Montauk beaches are run by East Hampton and need East Hampton permits. Ms. Cahill ruled that the matter of multiple permits was confusing enough to warrant dismissing the ticket.</p>
        <p>Outside the court, Ms. Nigro, who lives in Croton-on-Hudson in Westchester County but vacations in Montauk, called the steep fine absurd.</p>
        <p>''It costs more than a traffic violation,'' she said. ''And I had to miss out on the nice beach weather to come and fight it.''</p>
        <p>Town officials defend the fines. ''It's more a deterrent than anything else,'' said Wanda Azmoodeh, the account clerk for the Town of Southampton's parking violations division. ''Beach parking is so limited that we need to charge a lot for the rules to really be effective.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the Town of Southampton, which includes Sag Harbor, Bridgehampton and Water Mill, issued 10,000 parking tickets and took in $750,000 in fines, she said.</p>
        <p>To park at most of the town's 16 beaches, drivers must have seasonal parking permits, which are available to residents for $10 and for nonresidents for $100. Day parking is available for $10.</p>
        <p>Though the parking signs do not indicate the amount of the fine, word has spread that the amount has gone up, Ms. Azmoodeh said.</p>
        <p>''It's a common topic at cocktail parties,'' she said. ''A lot of people say: 'It's outrageous. I only pay $14 overtime for parking in Manhattan.' You look on their ticket, and the car is a Porsche, or it's a Bentley, but they still fight it.''</p>
        <p>''When it was $50, believe it or not, some people considered it worth it to pay for the day,'' she added. ''Now that it's $100, there are far less violations.''</p>
        <p>The fine for parking illegally at Long Wharf in Sag Harbor was increased this year from $30 to $50, she said, and the number of violations has dropped.</p>
        <p>''Every weekend you had people who would go out on their boat all day and just pay the $30 parking ticket,'' she said. ''It's cheaper than a parking garage in Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>In the Town of East Hampton, which includes Montauk, Amagansett and Wainscott, parking at ocean beaches is generally prohibited without a seasonal parking permit. But several beaches in Montauk allow daily parking, and Atlantic Beach in East Hampton does, too, but only on weekdays. Most of the tickets issued by the town are for illegally parking at the beach, said Capt. Todd Sarris of the Town of East Hampton Police Department.</p>
        <p>The town issued some 8,000 tickets last year and took in $444,627 in fines. This year the town has issued 3,639 tickets so far, so it appears that the higher fines are having a deterrent effect, Captain Sarris said.</p>
        <p>The same thing happened in 1996 when the town increased beach parking fines from $25 to $40, he said. The town usually issues 5,000 to 6,000 tickets a year, he said, but only 3,494 were issued in 1996.</p>
        <p>Jay Schneiderman, the East Hampton town supervisor, said that the town board voted to raise the beach parking fine in July 1999. The town offers seasonal parking permits to nonresidents for $125, he said, and the board decided to make the fine the same amount.</p>
        <p>''We increased the fines as a deterrent, not as a moneymaker,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The undeterred still consider the fines outrageously high. Jimmy Halperin, a jazz saxophonist from Northport, recently returned to his white Mustang parked at Main Beach in Southampton to find a $100 ticket on the windshield.</p>
        <p>''I thought, 'Well, it's Southampton, so it'll probably be like 55 bucks,' '' he said. ''But when I saw $100, I was like 'What, are these people nuts?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
