<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pursuit of Less</title>
    <meta content="03FEAT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erikson, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DE1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pursuit of Less</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS ERIKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erikson, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Yorkers are joining groups dedicated to voluntary simplicity and the renunciation of materialism and consumerism in favor of more spartan lifestyle; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT dusk on a midsummer evening, not long after trading on Wall Street has closed for the day,  nine people gather in a Greenwich Village living room to talk money.  But this group speaks not of wringing more profits out of a bull market. They want to make do with less.</p>
        <p>Money is also on the agenda in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, as half a dozen women of varying ages sit around a kitchen table, sipping tea and picking at fruit and cookies. The topic for tonight is community, and they ponder in particular this assertion: that the culture's raging materialism will go unchecked as long as people feel an absence of meaningful social ties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT dusk on a midsummer evening, not long after trading on Wall Street has closed for the day,  nine people gather in a Greenwich Village living room to talk money.  But this group speaks not of wringing more profits out of a bull market. They want to make do with less.</p>
        <p>Money is also on the agenda in Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, as half a dozen women of varying ages sit around a kitchen table, sipping tea and picking at fruit and cookies. The topic for tonight is community, and they ponder in particular this assertion: that the culture's raging materialism will go unchecked as long as people feel an absence of meaningful social ties.</p>
        <p>Such groups, which have a growing audience in New York, share a dedication to voluntary simplicity, the national back-to-basics movement whose followers renounce consumerism in favor of stripped-down living. Seeing spiritual  bankruptcy in an American Dream that equates success with possessions, they have deliberately decided to earn and spend less.</p>
        <p>Asceticism isn't a groundbreaking concept, of course; as long as there have been possessions, there have been simplifiers, from Buddha to Thoreau. Nor is the current trend brand-new. With roots in environmentalism, it has been gathering steam for a decade in the Northwest, ground zero for voluntary simplicity.</p>
        <p>Skepticism about the movement is not new, either. Critics dismiss it as budget-cutting dressed in New Age clothes, and even some adherents reject the ideological proselytizing that can accompany the practical advice.</p>
        <p>But the movement has been on the rise in the last year in New York, a city virtually synonymous with conspicuous consumption and fast-track living. Last  fall, a voluntary simplicity conference at the Open Center in SoHo drew more than 300 people for workshops with names like ''Are We Possessed by Our Possessions?'' and ''Leading a Life of Integrity.'' This fall the School of Continuing Education and Professional Studies at New York University will offer a course on voluntary simplicity.</p>
        <p>When an Upper West Sider named Mary Barknecht posted a few lines on a Web site called the Simple Living Network (www.slnet.com) in August 1999 in  hopes of starting a voluntary simplicity discussion group, the response was overwhelming. She has since started 10 groups and has a waiting list of people eager to join new ones. Her e-mail list has grown to a couple of hundred names. ''It has just snowballed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Of course, any movement trumpeting the virtues of austerity has a tough row to hoe in a city where earning and spending is something of a contact sport; where too much is never enough; where dinner for four at Alain Ducasse is nearly $1,500; and $150-a-head dinners are as common as pigeons in Central Park.</p>
        <p>''You've got the belly of the beast right here,'' said Pat McDonald, a psychotherapist and career counselor who will teach the N.Y.U. course on simplicity. ''More people than ever are into this, but New York is the last place you'd expect to find it.''</p>
        <p>Paul Wachtel, a clinical psychologist who lives and works in Greenwich Village and the author of ''The Poverty of Affluence'' (New Society, 1989), also senses growing disenchantment amid the current economic bonanza. Some of those who have not been swept up in a spending frenzy are repelled by what they see around them, he says. Others feel an emptiness no matter how many things they stockpile.</p>
        <p>''When people are in the midst of what they think is the American Dream and their lives don't feel very good, that's when they can begin to question,'' Mr. Wachtel said. ''And I hear it much more now than I did even five years ago.''</p>
        <p>WHEN it comes to downsizing, Mary Barknecht knows of what she speaks. Dressed neatly in a plain red cardigan and a white button-down shirt, her graying hair tied back in a ponytail and her face free of makeup, she projects an aura of contented calm. But there was a time when her life was very different. She once ran a court transcription business and spent much of the go-go 80's working round the clock.</p>
        <p>''I was mentally and physically exhausted all the time, and I compensated for that by spending my money on the usual stuff,'' she said. ''I had enough beautiful designer linens for a 10-bedroom house, and I lived in a studio apartment. At that point I realized something was a little out of sync.''</p>
        <p>So in the early 90's, she did an about-face. With a healthy nest egg, thanks to careful saving, she quit her job. Out went the designer linens, along with bags of shoes and boxes of knickknacks. She canceled her magazine subscriptions and put a stop to the catalogs that stuffed her mailbox. Beyond essentials, she says, she stopped buying. Last summer she bought a pair of sandals on sale, her first new shoes in five years.</p>
        <p>Today she lives on $11,000 a year, most of which goes for rent and health insurance. Her other expenses total about $100 a month. Her Upper West Side apartment is airy and attractive, and at first glance it looks like the home of an average city dweller, but on further inspection it reveals itself as a laboratory of nonconsumption.</p>
        <p>Take the kitchen: no microwave; no food processor; cloth towels substitute for paper. Cloth shopping bags hang on the doorknob, and a compost bucket sits next to the sink. Its contents go to a community garden.  There are no commercial cleaning products. Ms. Barknecht scrubs her bathroom with baking soda and her copper pans with vinegar and salt.</p>
        <p>For transportation she uses the subway and a secondhand bike. For entertainment, she goes to free concerts or volunteers as an usher to get free theater tickets.</p>
        <p>Her dedication to dirt-cheap living might make her an object of pity to New Yorkers for whom $100 wouldn't cover a night out, but she says she has never been happier. In her late 40's, she does a lot of volunteer work, which increasingly involves promoting the simple life.</p>
        <p>As well as simplicity circles, Ms. Barknecht runs groups on finance, the Greenwich Village one among them. They are called Your Money or Your Life groups, after the book by that name (Viking, 1992). Written by Joe Dominguez and Vicki Robin, a former stock analyst and his wife who moved to Seattle and downsized, the book offers a nine-step program to financial independence, advising participants to track their spending and to think of purchases in terms of the ''life energy'' expended to buy them.</p>
        <p>At a recent meeting, members of the Village group, who are from their 20's to their 60's, set other goals: to meditate, watch less television, fight clutter. They also discussed the environmental damage caused by Central American coffee growers. (The solution: buy free-trade coffee.)</p>
        <p>The word addiction surfaces several times, as when talk turns to the temptation to break out the credit cards.</p>
        <p>''It's like when someone is quitting smoking, and they go walk around the block instead of having a cigarette,'' said Rachel Aydt, 28, a research editor for YM magazine, who attends the meetings with her fiance, Jim Burton, an actor and contractor. ''You walk into a store and see something on sale, and you think, do I want this?''</p>
        <p>If voluntary simplicity sounds vaguely like a 12-step program, it is a little like one, says Pat McDonald, a group member. Participants say they are quitting something that is hard to shake: a mind-set that measures people by what they own.</p>
        <p>And if resisting that temptation is hard  elsewhere, in New York it can be downright brutal.</p>
        <p>''New York City is like one big shopping mall,'' Ms. McDonald said. ''Wherever you go, you're faced with choices to buy this and buy that. It's all about consuming.'' One woman in the Carroll Gardens group spoke of having ''an episode'' at Macy's.</p>
        <p>WHILE the concept of paring down is straightforward enough, in practice it can be complicated. Once past the basic tenet that less is more, a host of alternative practices enter the picture, from yogic breathing to vegetarianism to composting.  The philosophy is not just to spend less but to be aware of the effects, environmental and otherwise, produced by choices.</p>
        <p>Not everyone buys every principle. Ms. Aydt says the financial advice she gets from her group has helped her be conscious of money, but she doesn't always appreciate the political proselytizing.</p>
        <p>''It's like you're given a list of ideologies to follow,'' she says. ''I do find it alienating.''</p>
        <p>Some find the entire movement off-putting, sanctimonious or just silly. To James Twitchell, an English professor at the University of Florida at Gainesville who studies consumerism, the only thing new about voluntary simplicity is the extent to which the consumer disillusionment of middle-aged women has been exploited by publishers of self-help books. He chafes at the ''victim language'' adopted by the movement and what he calls the ''medicalization of consumption, where you need help, namely the 12-step method, to wean yourself away from the habit.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Twitchell notes, telling people how to downsize is a growth industry: a flock of groups are dedicated to spreading the simple life, and a growing pile of books touts its virtues. ''I mean, to have to buy books to stop buying things, to have to attend meetings to stop buying things, to see yourself as a victim to stop buying things?'' Mr. Twitchell said. ''Good God, woman, just take your credit cards and rip them up.''</p>
        <p>Erin Oates, 42, a public relations executive in Manhattan, said she once ''shopped with the best of them.'' But the simplicity message hit home a few years ago, around her 40th birthday. ''I started reassessing what my life is all about, and I don't want it to just be about collecting things,'' she said. Her first foray into simpler living was to make a family pact to stop exchanging Christmas gifts. Then she moved into a smaller apartment, shedding a lot of stuff along the way. Now she carefully tracks her expenses and is still paying off  credit card debt. She brings her lunch to work and dips into a box of Quaker Oats for breakfast instead of stopping at Au Bon Pain.</p>
        <p>She has also stopped prowling clothing stores before every new season or social event. Keeping her wardrobe up to date ''used to be a lot of what my life was about,'' she said, but now  her formerly jammed closet contains only a  few modest feet of hangers and eight or nine pairs of shoes.</p>
        <p>As she gives a tour of her tidy, antiques-filled one-bedroom on the Upper West Side, Ms. Oates is dressed plainly but stylishly in a purple cotton blouse (marked down to $17 at Ann Taylor) and a black skirt (a recent splurge she justified because the skirt is all-season and doesn't need dry cleaning).</p>
        <p>On her salary, she says, she can still afford her old way of life. But, she added: ''I want to feel like I'm living more intelligently. It's a matter of slowing down and not feeling like a rat caught in a maze.''</p>
        <p>THE spike in interest in voluntary simplicity in New York mirrors a  pattern in other cities. Betsy Taylor,  executive director of the Center for a New American Dream, a nonprofit group  in Maryland that promotes nonconsumerist  choices, said hits on the center's Web site had risen from under 125,000 in 1997 to nearly 1 million in 1998 to more than 3 million for the first seven months of 2000.</p>
        <p>During that time, simplicity has become a marketing buzzword, and the principle behind a pair of new monthly magazines, Time-Warner's Real Simple and Simply City, which published its third issue last month in New York. With fashion layouts and articles about spa etiquette and a Parisian water bar, Simply City promotes a  citified vision. Its editor and publisher, Danielle Chang, says the goal is to strip simplicity of its New Age aura and make it ''more accessible, less ascetic and more fun.''</p>
        <p>She said: ''The people I've spoken to in New York say things like, 'I want to embrace simplicity, but that doesn't mean that I don't care about fashion. I like shopping, I like wearing makeup, I like all of the traps, so to speak, but that doesn't make me a hypocrite.' ''</p>
        <p>WHILE the contradiction of a glossy magazine packed with fashion as it promotes downsizing has hard-core simplifiers gritting their teeth, Ms. Taylor says that it still reflects a widespread desire to relax the pace of life. She says many parents are  alarmed at the sway commercialization has over their children. In a recent poll by the center, 87 percent of parents said their offspring were too materialistic.</p>
        <p>This is a concern for Vicki Madden and Jim Ebersole of Park Slope, Brooklyn, who are raising Ms. Madden's 8-year-old son, Jacob, and have a 3-week-old baby of their own, Samuel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Madden, who teaches ''very part time,'' and Mr. Ebersole, who works for a company that ships fine art, have a budget of $200 a week for food, transportation, entertainment and other expenses, not counting rent and insurance. They track their spending in minute detail, cracking down on casual expenditures, like a morning latte, that many take for granted.</p>
        <p>Yet striving for simplicity in New York can be lonely. ''You're definitely swimming against the tide,'' Ms. Madden said.</p>
        <p>The philosophy can also complicate social life. Jean Thilmany, 33, who writes for writes for the trade publication Mechanical Engineering, says for her friends, a typical night out involves ''spending $9 for a movie and then going out for an expensive dinner.''</p>
        <p>''I'm constantly trying to get out of dinner invitations,'' said Ms. Thilmany, who lives in a railroad flat in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, where country and jazz records clutter the shelves and a stacked pair of old suitcases serves as a coffee table. ''I usually make an excuse, like that I'm having money problems. I don't feel comfortable telling people about it. I just feel like I have to get into a whole political thing that's not going to be appreciated.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thilmany, a soft-spoken blond with pale features and a taste for prowling vintage clothing stores, came to voluntary simplicity after a disconcerting stint at a paper covering the retail industry, where she ''started to become aware of how many ads there are, and all the ways one is manipulated to buy.''</p>
        <p>It's a particular issue in New York, she said, where ever-present billboards are much more intrusive than in her native Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Which leads to this question: Why live in New York at all if simplicity is what you're after? Isn't it a bit like moving to the hills of Montana to become a stockbroker?</p>
        <p>The answer, simplifiers say, is that they live here for much the same reason as anyone else: the culture, the diversity, the creative energy. They say that inflated housing costs aside, New York is a great place to live cheaply. A car is unnecessary, and inexpensive ethnic restaurants abound, along with free concerts and art galleries.</p>
        <p>Also, living in the shadow of big spenders has its benefits, like thrift shops where designer goods can be found with the tags still attached. There is plenty of free stuff for the taking, too.</p>
        <p>Roger Kaufman, who used to run a graphic design business and now works as a home health care aide, said he had collected many a treasure discarded by fellow tenants at his Bay Ridge apartment building.</p>
        <p>''I went from one TV to three,'' he said. ''And I have cast iron and Pyrex cookware beyond belief.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
