<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; Most Presidents Had a Counselor. One Had a Shrink.</title>
    <meta content="03CLYM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Washington; Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nixon, Richard Milhous (1913-94)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Arrogance of Power, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDE1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; Most Presidents Had a Counselor. One Had a Shrink.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Revelations about Pres Nixon's psychiatric treatment, in Anthony Summers' book, The Arrogance of Power: The Secret World of Richard Nixon, raise important questions; overwhelming majority of politicians still hide their mental difficulties; many will speak openly about family or close friends who struggle with mental illness, but not about themselves; several politicians who did publicly acknowledge mental illness and treatment have been re-elected to Congress, but there is general agreement that candidate for president would face tougher barrier; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE only president whose wild mood swings prompted his own secretary of defense to issue orders designed to block him if he called out the Marines for protection against impeachment is also the only president known to have been treated by a psychotherapist.</p>
        <p>That president was Richard M. Nixon, and both of those experiences are chronicled in ''The Arrogance of Power: The Secret World of Richard Nixon,'' by Anthony Summers (Viking). And while other accounts in his book, including episodes of wife-beating and pill-popping, are angrily contradicted by Mr. Nixon's defenders, the revelations about the secret order and the president's psychiatric treatment have not been widely disputed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE only president whose wild mood swings prompted his own secretary of defense to issue orders designed to block him if he called out the Marines for protection against impeachment is also the only president known to have been treated by a psychotherapist.</p>
        <p>That president was Richard M. Nixon, and both of those experiences are chronicled in ''The Arrogance of Power: The Secret World of Richard Nixon,'' by Anthony Summers (Viking). And while other accounts in his book, including episodes of wife-beating and pill-popping, are angrily contradicted by Mr. Nixon's defenders, the revelations about the secret order and the president's psychiatric treatment have not been widely disputed.</p>
        <p>But they raise important questions. While the physical health of presidents and politicians has become a fit topic for public discussion, the overwhelming majority of politicians still hide their mental difficulties.</p>
        <p>The evidence is purely anecdotal, but talking to psychiatrists in Washington, it is clear that while there have been some changes since Mr. Nixon's time (when his therapist, Dr. Arnold A. Hutschnecker, visited the White House rarely and used false destinations when he signed in), they have largely been around the edges.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fred Solomon, a practicing psychiatrist here since the early 1960's, said, ''I don't think the politicians are any more eager, more relaxed than they used to be about therapy for themselves.'' But, he said, they are ''a lot more willing to have family members get help.''</p>
        <p>''The recognition of usefulness for psychiatric care for family members is just moving along just fine,'' he continued. ''Marital counseling is sought by a number of people, and there is recognition in general that mental health problems can be just as disabling as physical health problems.''</p>
        <p>Senator Paul Wellstone, a Minnesota Democrat who has crusaded for legislation  to force insurance companies to treat mental health the same as physical health, recalled a meeting at Vice President Al Gore's house a few years ago about a proposed bill.  More than 30 senators were there, most with their wives or husbands. They spoke ''very personally about members of their own family or close friends who struggled with mental illness, but not to the point of talking about themselves.''</p>
        <p>Psychiatrists here say they understand why politicians fear disclosure. Dr. Dorothy Starr said, ''I think there remains a good deal of uncertainty in the public mind about people who have been mentally ill.'' Another psychiatrist, Dr. Harvey Rich, said, ''We hold our politicians up to a different kind of standard -- you can't have a weakness of any kind.''</p>
        <p>Representative Jim McDermott, who was a Seattle psychiatrist before coming to Congress and who has referred other members of Congress to psychiatrists, said the fear of being found out discouraged others who talked to him about getting help.</p>
        <p>But the experiences of those politicians who have publicly acknowledged mental illness -- in each case treatment for depression -- raise questions about that widespread fear. Senator Thomas Eagleton, who was dropped as a vice-presidential candidate in George McGovern's campaign in 1972 after failing to disclose electroshock treatments for depression, was re-elected to the Senate in Missouri in 1974 and 1980. Lawton Chiles, who left the Senate in 1989, recovered from depression and was twice elected governor of Florida. And three current members of the House -- Lynn N. Rivers of Michigan, Nydia M. Velazquez of New York and Patrick J. Kennedy of Rhode Island -- have survived such disclosures.</p>
        <p>The last time a high-profile campaign tried to damage an opponent by accusing him of seeking psychiatric help was in 1988, when the Bush campaign and President Reagan sought to discredit Michael A. Dukakis. John Deardourff, a longtime Republican consultant, said he believed that ''there are enough people in both parties'' today ''who would speak out against anybody who tried to raise that issue against a candidate that it would be very dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Peter D. Hart, a Democratic pollster, said it could make a difference what office a politician was seeking. For a Congressional candidate, he said, the examples of entertainment and sports figures suggested disclosure was safe, phrased in terms of ''Here's a challenge that I faced.''</p>
        <p>But a candidate for president, he said, ''faces a tougher barrier.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deardourff agreed, saying the public understands that the presidency is an ''intensely demanding job demanding mental stability.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fred Goodwin, a former head of the National Institute of Mental Health, said it was important to distinguish between different sorts of mental illness -- a treatable depression is one thing and schizophrenia  another. ''I don't think the public concerns are entirely unfounded,'' Dr. Goodwin said.  ''When we fight stigma, we shouldn't pretend that mental illnesses are just the same as physical illness. If you're talking about a disorder that affects thinking, behavior, that's different from high blood pressure or diabetes.</p>
        <p>''When the public is uneasy about something, their views may be exaggerated, there may be a lot of irrationality, a lot of fear. But when it's pervasive and hangs around, the public is at least partially on to something.''</p>
        <p>DR. SOLOMON pointed out that some politicians, like President Clinton, publicly engage in spiritual counseling while rejecting psychiatric help. And even those who discuss mental illness often do so using murky terminology. ''They also pick their words very carefully, like 'counseling,' not 'therapy,' '' he said. ''They get medication from their internal medicine doctors, like Vince Foster did, but didn't really want to see a psychiatrist.''</p>
        <p>Even Tipper Gore, praised by one psychiatrist after another for discussing her depression and treatment last year, spoke of ''counseling.'' And when an article in The New York Times Magazine in 1993 described the family therapy received by the Gores after their son was struck by a car and nearly died, the vice president's office complained that the article should not have said he had weekly visits from a ''therapist,'' but from a ''facilitator.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
