<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking After His Father, Sort Of</title>
    <meta content="03PROF$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIVATE SECTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">HOWARD G. BUFFETT</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DA1330F930A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking After His Father, Sort Of</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <dateline>DECATUR, Ill.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOWARD G. BUFFETT, the 45-year-old son of Warren E. Buffett, does not spend his days surveying stock charts or analyzing corporate growth prospects. He surveys cornfields from the cab of his John Deere tractor.</p>
        <p>He also drives a Ford pickup, wears battered blue jeans and flashes an aw-shucks grin. And if people still don't understand, he puts it more pointedly: he may have a dad who is worth roughly $29 billion, but his grain bins here are not Fort Knox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOWARD G. BUFFETT, the 45-year-old son of Warren E. Buffett, does not spend his days surveying stock charts or analyzing corporate growth prospects. He surveys cornfields from the cab of his John Deere tractor.</p>
        <p>He also drives a Ford pickup, wears battered blue jeans and flashes an aw-shucks grin. And if people still don't understand, he puts it more pointedly: he may have a dad who is worth roughly $29 billion, but his grain bins here are not Fort Knox.</p>
        <p>''I really don't have that much money,'' he said with a grin burnished by frequent use. ''I'm not the guy listed on the Forbes 400 list.''</p>
        <p>But as the eldest son of the Oracle of Omaha, Howard stands to become the next chairman of Berkshire Hathaway, his father's holding company-turned-gold mine.</p>
        <p>Succession is a delicate subject with Howard Buffett these days, because of the way rumors swirled on the Internet last winter about his father's supposedly failing health. In fact, though the senior Mr. Buffett did have surgery in July to remove a section of colon containing noncancerous polyps, he celebrated his 70th birthday last week in good health.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't feel better,'' he said in a telephone interview last week. But if he were hit by a car tomorrow, he said, his chairmanship would pass to Howard.</p>
        <p>The elder Mr. Buffett has arranged matters so that, although his son will not run the company himself, he will provide crucial oversight. ''I want Berkshire and the culture to continue, and he would be there to ensure that happens,'' Warren Buffett said. ''And he has my ideas about who I think should be running it.''</p>
        <p>Howard Buffett, meanwhile, is content to farm a 700-acre spread outside Decatur, where he lives with his wife, Devon, a 16-year-old son, Howard, and one of his four stepdaughters. He also serves as chairman of the GSI Group, a privately held maker of agricultural equipment; does charitable work on conservation and health issues; and travels regularly to countries like Uganda and Zimbabwe to photograph exotic wildlife.</p>
        <p>''I just love wildlife,'' he said. ''I used to sleep out in the back yard with my dog when I was growing up.''</p>
        <p>In short, Howard Buffett and his two siblings, Susan, 47, and Peter, 42, have staked out their own lives, quite apart from the world of value investing that Warren Buffett has come to dominate.</p>
        <p>Peter found music, and made a name for himself in Hollywood by writing the score for a scene in ''Dances With Wolves.'' Susan worked at The New Republic and at U.S. News &amp; World Report, then switched to philanthropy.</p>
        <p>And Howard? Well, Howard chose tractors.</p>
        <p>''I've always loved the outdoors,'' he said. ''I'm very mechanical. When I got out of college, I just wanted to run a bulldozer.''</p>
        <p>Even on his farm, though, he cannot avoid intrusive questions about his father's publicly stated intention to leave the bulk of his fortune to charity rather than to his family. ''As long as he leaves me 1 percent, I'll be O.K.,'' he joked.</p>
        <p>Even scraps of the Buffett empire would be a colossal inheritance. As things stand now, a mere 10 percent bequest divided among the children would still give them each nearly $1 billion, to add to the ''small gifts'' of stock that Howard Buffett said he and his siblings have received from their father at Christmastime.</p>
        <p>And what the Buffett children do not inherit, they may yet control. Susan and Peter already serve on the board of the Buffett Foundation, which is expected to become one of the world's largest; Howard has a seat on Berkshire's board. And all three have charitable foundations of their own, financed by their parents.</p>
        <p>If Warren Buffett planted a seed of succession early on, it may have been in naming his first son, Howard Graham Buffett, after two men he greatly admired: his own father and Benjamin Graham, his mentor and former professor.</p>
        <p>He also passed along to his son a love of sports. Saying that Howard worships the Nebraska Cornhuskers football team doesn't really tell it: His office at GSI is festooned with Cornhuskers autographed footballs, helmets and photographs.</p>
        <p>Howard jumped around a bit early in life, attending three colleges, doing farm and real estate work, running a bulldozer, and even serving as a county commissioner in Omaha, before moving to Decatur to become a corporate vice president and assistant to the chairman of Archer Daniels Midland, the giant grain handler.</p>
        <p>In 1995, after the company became mired in a price-fixing scandal in which he was not involved, he resigned, sold his stock and bought the farm -- a proposition that did not pass his father's value-investing test but won paternal approval anyway. ''It's not a good business,'' Warren Buffett said of farming last week. ''But it's a satisfying business.''</p>
        <p>Howard Buffett also bought a stake in GSI, one of the largest makers of grain storage bins, betting -- as his father might -- that the growth of genetically engineered crops would oblige farmers to erect separate storage facilities for conventional and biotech grain.</p>
        <p>SO is he, after all, a chip off the old block? He answers with an avuncular, plain-spoken tour of his office, a joke about his weight and an admission that he has been known to accept chocolate milk shakes during interviews.</p>
        <p>''I believe in my dad's philosophy, buying for the long term and holding,'' he said at last.</p>
        <p>Unlike his father, Howard Buffett has bought a few technology stocks. But both men have a weakness for well-known brands and neither is above a bit of boosterism. Howard speaks effusively of his love for John Deere tractors; his father is often seen at Berkshire's annual meeting swigging Cherry Coke and snacking on Dairy Queen ice cream, both made by companies in the Berkshire portfolio.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, when Howard Buffett met a reporter at a local restaurant for a meal of pork chops and mashed potatoes, he jokingly snarled at a waiter who was showing off a Pepsi logo tattooed on his arm.</p>
        <p>When his guest ordered a Coke -- and was rebuffed -- Mr. Buffett feigned a trot to the men's room. In fact, he left the restaurant and made a beeline for a Coca-Cola vending machine in the parking lot of a nearby building.</p>
        <p>''Here's your Coke,'' he said when he returned. ''The Buffetts don't drink Pepsi.''</p>
        <p>PRIVATE SECTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
