<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bus Driver Lost? Agitators Banned? 'No Worries' for an Anxious Nation</title>
    <meta content="20AUSS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/olympics/20AUSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BEHIND THE SCENES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED8143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bus Driver Lost? Agitators Banned? 'No Worries' for an Anxious Nation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes how Australians are reacting to pressure of staging 2000 Summer Olympic Games in Sydney; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doesn't anyone here worry? Ever?</p>
        <p>Don't have exact change for the bus? No worries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doesn't anyone here worry? Ever?</p>
        <p>Don't have exact change for the bus? No worries.</p>
        <p>Don't know how to get to the Olympic Stadium? No worries.</p>
        <p>Running late for a Dream Team game? No worries.</p>
        <p>It's the inevitable rejoinder to any expression of anxiety, an all-purpose palliative for the stressed-out visitor. No phrase better captures the laid-back veneer of Australian life. One hears it so regularly in Sydney that it ends up being devoid of meaning -- a Down Under version of ''have a nice day.''</p>
        <p>That's just as well because the no-worries Australian is as threadbare a cliche as the guy who swills Foster's, wrestles crocodiles and wears a leather hat with bobbing corks to swat away the flies.</p>
        <p>Australians worry all the time, and this high anxiety helps explain why these Olympic Games are shaping up as among the smoothest in memory. Far from relaxing, tens of thousands of Australians are sweating every detail of what they describe as the greatest peacetime logistical exercise in history.</p>
        <p>''Australians are some of the most self-critical people in the world,'' said Daniel Mulcahy, a local businessman. ''They're incredibly insecure. And everybody knows that we're in the world spotlight.''</p>
        <p>For Australia, the Games are an opportunity to demonstrate that this geographically isolated country is a full member of the global economy. For Sydney, they are a chance to showcase a city with ambitions to become a Pacific Rim financial center on the order of Tokyo or Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>''We've never been tested on something this big before,'' said Milton Cockburn, a spokesman for the Sydney organizing committee. ''The closest thing to it in complexity is a military operation.''</p>
        <p>The comparison is apt because, for a freewheeling city, Sydney is putting on a remarkably locked-down Olympics. Security is airtight, with a series of checkpoints around the Olympic Park. The police have closed down more than 90 roads throughout the city to reduce the number of cars.</p>
        <p>To discourage terrorist attacks, more than 2,000 hidden cameras survey Olympic sites and popular tourist areas like Darling Harbor in central Sydney. Nearly 5,000 police officers patrol the park at Homebush Bay, augmented by 4,000 soldiers who can be deployed in an emergency.</p>
        <p>The security net has spared nobody, including the singer Olivia Newton-John, who performed at the opening ceremony. Newton-John had to wait at the stadium gate while her car was searched by the police.</p>
        <p>Sydney's massive security has not come without sacrifices. In some far-flung towns -- places with names like Tullibigeal and Quandialla -- the lone police officer has been transferred to Sydney for duty at the Games. Sydney's police commissioner, Peter Ryan, has promised to compensate these towns by assigning extra police officers after the Olympics.</p>
        <p>Australia's Parliament laid the legal groundwork for the heightened security by passing the Olympic Arrangements Act. The act curtails a wide range of activities -- from street demonstrations and ticket scalping to parking in ''clearways'' and flying in closed airspace -- for the duration of the Games.</p>
        <p>Parliament also granted Australia's defense forces unprecedented powers to help in law enforcement, including the right to enter buildings and to stop and search vehicles.</p>
        <p>Critics say these acts would alarm civil-liberties advocates in the United States. But there was barely a peep of protest here.</p>
        <p>Nor did anyone protest when Bob Carr, the premier of New South Wales, threatened to jail demonstrators who had disrupted an economic conference in Melbourne if they carried their placards and megaphones to Sydney.</p>
        <p>''For a long time, we were at the end of the earth and on the dark side of the moon,'' said Thomas Keneally, the author and critic, ''so when there is a chance to shine, we tend to seize it with both hands.''</p>
        <p>The pressure to put on a trouble-free Olympics is so intense that individualistic Australians are willing to accept a dash of authoritarianism. Freedom and authority have always coexisted in Australia. This is, after all, a country where one can be fined for failing to vote in elections.</p>
        <p>''The roots of Australia were laid-back convicts and authoritarian jailors, and we're seeing a bit of both today,'' said Keneally, who is best known for his Holocaust novel, ''Schindler's List.''</p>
        <p>The desire to show a good face to the world extends even to Australia's disenfranchised. Last week, a group of dissident students milled in Victoria Park, debating whether to join an anti-Olympics rally.</p>
        <p>''Be sure to tell the world what a terrible country Australia is,'' a young man with earrings in his nose and eyebrows said to a reporter standing nearby. His friend whispered: ''Actually, this is a pretty good country. We just choose to live outside the system.''</p>
        <p>Yet even the strict rules and exhaustive planning have not eliminated all the bugs. In the first week of the Games, Sydney has been plagued by problems with its bus service. The city hired hundreds of extra drivers to operate buses that carry passengers to sports sites and tourist destinations.</p>
        <p>Many of these drivers come from country towns and are unfamiliar with Sydney's crazy-quilt streets. Not surprisingly, the drivers are getting lost -- sometimes on the way to Olympic events. Making matters worse, they are being put up in lodgings so spartan that some quit after a few days.</p>
        <p>Cockburn, the organizing committee spokesman, said the city government pressed soldiers into service as drivers. He also said that navigators, known as tour leaders, now ride with the out-of-town drivers to show them the way.</p>
        <p>While officials have scrambled to fix the buses, they note with satisfaction that the problems here are minuscule compared with the chaos of the transportation system in the first week of the Atlanta Games.</p>
        <p>The same goes for the I.B.M. computers that supply scores and other statistics. While Atlanta was embarrassed by errant scores and wayward statistics, the only lapse in Sydney, Cockburn said, was on the first day of the archery competition, when a computer was baffled by a tie score.</p>
        <p>Some of Sydney's triumphs have been unsung. During the four-hour opening ceremony, an estimated 200,000 cellular calls were made by the 110,000 spectators inside Olympic Stadium. About 125,000 of those were carried on the mobile-phone network of Telstra, the state-controlled phone company.</p>
        <p>Telstra said more than 97 percent of the calls were completed without a delay or a cutoff in service. The company invested more than $50 million to upgrade its network for the Olympics, installing what it says is the world's densest cellular network in a single building.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the opening ceremony, Telstra's executives displayed a characteristic mix of Australian bravado and nerves. Brian Pilbeam, the general manager of special events and Olympics, said he would be relieved, but not surprised, if the cellular network worked well.</p>
        <p>What explains the stubborn desire of Sydneysiders to convince the world that the Olympics are a walk in the park?</p>
        <p>''This is a very irreverent country,'' said Malcolm Turnbull, the head of the so-far-unsuccessful movement to turn Australia into a republic. ''The other side of that coin is something we call the 'tall poppy' syndrome. We tend to be suspicious of people who come across as too clever or successful.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BEHIND THE SCENES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
