<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Web Makes Going Global Easy, Until You Try to Do It</title>
    <meta content="20WHIT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SMALL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5D81139F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Web Makes Going Global Easy, Until You Try to Do It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN First Net Card was started in 1999, it had a vision of using the Internet to provide credit for online transactions to anyone in the world.</p>
        <p>But even with two lawyers working for nearly two years on international banking issues, First Net Card is still licensed only in the United States, Canada and Britain to provide credit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN First Net Card was started in 1999, it had a vision of using the Internet to provide credit for online transactions to anyone in the world.</p>
        <p>But even with two lawyers working for nearly two years on international banking issues, First Net Card is still licensed only in the United States, Canada and Britain to provide credit.</p>
        <p>Although the company has gained 75,000 customers and attracted 100 merchants online, ''the costs outweigh the benefits'' of doing business in many countries, said Eric DePrano, the president of First Net Card, which offers a debit option in countries where it is not licensed to provide credit.</p>
        <p>Mike Krill, a chief financial officer with Atlas Consulting, which advises small businesses in their first year, said: ''The reality is, going global is difficult. What we found is it's typically something that's an undertaking for larger ventures.''</p>
        <p>For many small businesses, the Internet has been promoted as a way to expand sales by simply installing a modem and establishing a Web site. Online, the businesses could compete with the giant multinational corporations. But the truth has not been that simple.</p>
        <p>''The notion that the playing field is leveled is hyped and not realistic,'' said Bob Parker, a senior analyst specializing in e-commerce at AMR Research Inc. To illustrate his point, Mr. Parker referred to an I.B.M. advertisement featuring an Italian woman selling olive oil.</p>
        <p>In reality, he said, ''that little old lady gets crushed.''</p>
        <p>With worldwide e-commerce projected to grow to $6.8 trillion by 2004 from $657 billion today, the Internet is obviously an integral part of any business strategy. And the Web is fueling global opportunities for some 25 million small businesses nationwide, said Fred P. Hochberg, a deputy administrator with the United States Small Business Administration.</p>
        <p>But a Web site alone does not guarantee success. To do business overseas, companies must deal with tariff, language and currency issues and the difficulty of establishing distribution networks. While the Internet can certainly reduce costs and enhance competitiveness, expansion often requires partnerships that are increasingly complex. Not just partners with money, said Robert W. Price, founder of the Global Entrepreneurship Institute, but those with complementary expertise.</p>
        <p>''I think there is a successful strategy for small businesses,'' Mr. Krill said ''and that is to try and take advantage of the ecosystem around the industry.''</p>
        <p>That's the approach being taken by Chris Yeh's Click Rebates, which provides tools for companies on the Internet to attract and keep customers. The company offers perks and rewards to consumers who are willing to share information about themselves and their buying habits. The information is used by businesses wanting to reach a specific audience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeh said he had intended to keep the business, which is based in Santa Clara, Calif., in the United States at first, but within two to three months, the company found that 35 percent of its customers were outside the United States, primarily in Canada and Britain.</p>
        <p>But while the demand is there, meeting it is complicated.</p>
        <p>''How do you work on Internet time? How do you work on Internet time on a global scale?'' he said. ''Now you're dealing with different languages, rules and regulations.  To tackle that, we really look to local partners.'' In China, for example, the company is working with a Hong Kong investment firm that owns a stake in the Chinese portal Sohu. Click Rebates hopes to provide its services to the site one day.</p>
        <p>''We're just in the beginning stage,'' Mr. Yeh said, noting that the company had about 20 partners and had signed up 300,000 consumers in 150 countries worldwide.</p>
        <p>That stage can often be slow going, as First Net Card, also based in Santa Clara,  found. The online credit card system was introduced by Marrowcast Media, an online advertising agency, which saw an opportunity to fill a global niche.</p>
        <p>''For us to try and do this in the offline world would be largely impossible,'' Mr. DePrano said. ''The nice thing about launching this service online is that the number of merchants we need is significantly lower.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. DePrano found in researching banking and credit laws, trying to do business in other countries can be mind-boggling. For example, one of the company's first customers was a man in Oman. But First Net was unable to provide credit in the country, so instead it issued the customer a debit card that he had to finance up front in dollars.</p>
        <p>To avoid such problems, some small businesses form partnerships with overseas companies. This, however, can be fraught with difficulty, too. For example, Garden.com, an online seller of plants, tools and other gardening-related merchandise in Austin, Tex., wanted to expand into Europe and decided that a partnership would offer the best opportunity, given the company's limited resources.</p>
        <p>After much research, said Cliff Sharples, the chief executive of Garden.com, the company decided to form a partnership with Garvita, a European site.</p>
        <p>''They were a start-up and looking for funding,'' Mr. Sharples said. The two companies reached an agreement and started making the rounds of venture capitalists late last winter. Then, Mr. Sharples said, ''the bottom dropped out of the market. With the new valuations, our ownership of the company would be too small. When we go to Europe, we need to have a meaningful chunk of the company.''</p>
        <p>For now, Garden.com is focusing on the United States market. ''Prioritization is a problem,'' Mr. Sharples said. ''There's so much to do in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''It's challenging for a small company to take what they have and translate it overseas.''</p>
        <p>Other small online retailers are reaching the same conclusion. Laurie McCartney, whose company, eStyle, an online retailer geared to busy women, introduced Babystyle in 1999 and Kidstyle in April, said she  would most likely roll out her concept in Europe and Asia but was focusing on the United States first.</p>
        <p>''We see a huge demand for our product, and we also see lots of potential partnerships,'' Ms. McCartney said. ''That said, the market here is fairly large and significant. We really want to continue to focus on the U.S. market.''</p>
        <p>SMALL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
