<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miller, Top Threat to Jones, Drops Out of 100</title>
    <meta content="20INGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Inger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EED6153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miller, Top Threat to Jones, Drops Out of 100</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Wednesday, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inger Miller, only real sprinting threat to Marion Jones and her fastest teammate on American 4x100-meter relay team, has withdrawn from 100 meters and may not be able to run 200 or relay at Sydney Olympics because of hamstring injury; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inger Miller, the only real sprinting threat to Marion Jones and her fastest teammate on the American 4x100-meter relay team, has withdrawn from the 100 and may not be able to run the 200 or the relay at the Olympics because of a hamstring injury.</p>
        <p>Miller strained her left hamstring while training on Sept. 7 in Los Angeles and has not been able to sprint at top speed for nearly two weeks. Her absence could both markedly help and hurt Jones's chances of becoming the first female track and field athlete to win five gold medals at the same Games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inger Miller, the only real sprinting threat to Marion Jones and her fastest teammate on the American 4x100-meter relay team, has withdrawn from the 100 and may not be able to run the 200 or the relay at the Olympics because of a hamstring injury.</p>
        <p>Miller strained her left hamstring while training on Sept. 7 in Los Angeles and has not been able to sprint at top speed for nearly two weeks. Her absence could both markedly help and hurt Jones's chances of becoming the first female track and field athlete to win five gold medals at the same Games.</p>
        <p>She said today that she hopes to be able to run the 200 and the relay.</p>
        <p>''It's been a difficult decision for me, but I didn't want to jeopardize my other events,'' Miller said at a news conference. ''I'm hoping a few more days will help me heal.''</p>
        <p>In the 100, Miller is the only sprinter to have pushed Jones this season, losing by a hundredth of a second to her on Aug. 11 in Zurich; she ran 10.96 seconds to 10.95 for Jones.</p>
        <p>Miller also finished second to Jones in the 100 at the 1999 world championships in Seville, Spain, posting a career best of 10.79 seconds. She will be replaced in the event by her training partner Torri Edwards, who finished fourth at the Olympic trials.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry I won't be there to give her great competition, but I wish her good luck,'' Miller said of Jones.</p>
        <p>Miller, 28, also won the world championship in the 200 in Seville after Jones had withdrawn because of back spasms. Miller's winning time of 21.77 seconds was faster than Jones ran all of last season. That 200 was the only sprint Jones did not win in the past two years.</p>
        <p>''It's no longer a one-woman show,'' Miller said in an interview this season.</p>
        <p>Rounds of the 100 begin Friday (Thursday, Eastern time), with the semifinals and final scheduled for Saturday. Miller would have more time to heal her leg before the 200 rounds, which do not begin until next Wednesday, with the semifinals and final scheduled for Sept. 28. The 4x100 relay final is scheduled for Sept. 30. If she is healthy, Miller could run the final without having to run the relay's preliminary rounds, as is often the case with top sprinters.</p>
        <p>Asked about her chances of running the 200 and the relay, Miller said she was unsure.</p>
        <p>''It's day to day,'' she said. ''Come Wednesday, I think I should be all right. I have been able to do some training but not at the level I want to be at this time of year.''</p>
        <p>While Miller's absence from the sprints would remove the most searing threat to Jones, her withdrawal from the relay would make a gold medal more uncertain for the Americans. Without an injured Jones, for instance, the Americans finished fourth in the 4x100 relay behind the Bahamas, France and Jamaica at the 1999 world championships. The other three members of the American relay final will most likely be Jones; Gail Devers, the two-time Olympic champion at 100 meters; and Chryste Gaines. Miller finished second to Jones in both the 100 and 200 at the Olympic trials in July, while Gaines was third in the 100. If Miller cannot run the relay, she would be replaced by Edwards, Nanceen Perry, Carlette Guidry or Passion Richardson.</p>
        <p>''It's unfortunate Inger can't compete in the 100; I know how hard she's worked and how she wanted to win a medal,'' Edwards said. ''But I've been training hard and I'm prepared to step up.''</p>
        <p>At the 1996 Atlanta Olympics, Miller finished fourth in the 200 but won a gold medal on the American 4x100 relay.</p>
        <p>Her father, Lennox Miller, now a dentist in Pasadena, Calif., won a silver medal in the 100 for Jamaica at the 1968 Mexico City Olympics and a bronze in 1972 at the Munich Games. He and Inger are the only father and daughter to have won Olympic medals in track and field. Both attended the University of Southern California.</p>
        <p>Miller was formerly coached by her father. Last year, however, she began training at U.C.L.A. with the Hudson Smith International training group, known as H.S.I. The group is coached by John Smith and includes Maurice Greene, the world record-holder at 100 meters, and Ato Boldon, a bronze medalist in the 100 and 200 at the Atlanta Olympics.</p>
        <p>''It's out of my hands,'' Miller said of the injury. ''Last year, when I was very successful in the 100 and 200, I didn't ask the Lord why he chose me. I can't say now: 'Why me? Why am I injured?' I can't be upset if I'm not 100 percent and if I don't achieve the goals in my plan. I'm disappointed, but I've got to go with the flow. It's not the end of the world. I'm young; I've got many other aspirations. If it doesn't work out, it doesn't. I hope by Wednesday, things will look a little better.''</p>
        <p>Miller becomes the latest American track and field athlete to withdraw because of an injury or illness. The men's world champion shot-putter C. J. Hunter had knee surgery and a gold-medal favorite in the women's 1,500, Regina Jacobs, has a respiratory viral infection.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
