<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defying Forecasts, Census Response Ends Declining Trend</title>
    <meta content="Y20CEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/national/20CENS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Census Bureau</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Steven A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD9153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defying Forecasts, Census Response Ends Declining Trend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holmes, Steven A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Census Bureau reports 67 percent of 120 million households that got census form in mail completed and returned form, up from 65 percent in 1990; surprise gain, attributed to aggressive marketing drive, reverses three-decade trend away from participation; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A higher percentage of households completed and returned census forms this year than in 1990, reversing a three-decade trend away from participation in the national population count, census officials said today.</p>
        <p>The officials said 67 percent of of the 120 million households that received a form in the mail filled it out and sent it back, compared with the 65 percent that returned the forms 10 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A higher percentage of households completed and returned census forms this year than in 1990, reversing a three-decade trend away from participation in the national population count, census officials said today.</p>
        <p>The officials said 67 percent of of the 120 million households that received a form in the mail filled it out and sent it back, compared with the 65 percent that returned the forms 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>The results, which census officials attributed to an aggressive marketing campaign, surprised outsiders who had predicted that this year would continue a trend of declines in the percentage of households completing and returning census forms.</p>
        <p>In 1970, the first year officials conducted the initial part of the census by mail, 83 percent of households returned the questionnaires. In 1980, 75 percent of households sent them back, and the response rate hit 65 percent in 1990.</p>
        <p>Before the start of the census this year, bureau officials had predicted that 61 percent of households would return forms. Preliminary figures released in May showed that 66 percent of households were responding.</p>
        <p>''A decade-long trend line in social behavior is hard to change, hard to reverse,'' said Kenneth W. Prewitt, director of the census. ''Trend lines are stubborn things.''</p>
        <p>Some experts called the Census Bureau achievement all the more remarkable because it comes as participation is declining in community activities, like voting, church attendance and philanthropic giving.</p>
        <p>''Against that background, to have successfully produced a two-percentage-point increase in mail-back response rates is actually stunning,'' said Robert Putnam, a political scientist at Harvard University who wrote ''Bowling Alone: The Collapse and Revival of American Community'' (Simon &amp; Schuster).</p>
        <p>Census Bureau officials credited the improvement to their enhanced marketing, which stressed the involvement of local officials, and a $103 million advertising campaign that strongly suggested people who returned census forms would help their communities win new schools, day-care centers and firehouses.</p>
        <p>Some Census Bureau officials have fretted that the campaign may have promised too much. Federal and state financial aid is sometimes based on population, but no direct correlation exists between completed census forms and more services.</p>
        <p>Census officials warned that the relatively high response rate did not mean the census would be able to avoid the problems of 1990, when 8 million people were missed and 4 million more were counted twice.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some experts worry that the larger number of returns may result in more people being counted twice, known as inclusions.</p>
        <p>''I've sat in the room with people who argued that the public relations campaign and the extensive activities have increased the chances of erroneous enumeration,'' said Stephen E. Fienberg, a statistician and social scientist at Carnegie Mellon University. ''I've also heard the bureau describe the process of entering the data and how they believe they will have fewer duplicates.''</p>
        <p>Census Bureau figures indicate that 29 states raised their response rates from 1990, with five states -- California, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Nevada and Wyoming -- lifting rates by five percentage points.</p>
        <p>The improved response came in spite of a falloff in responses to the long-form questionnaire. This year, the gap between long-form and  short-form returns was 11 percentage points, double that of 1990. Some politicians, including Gov. George W. Bush, had suggested people might not return the long form because its questions were too intrusive.</p>
        <p>Officials said the bureau's preliminary analysis suggested that the higher response rates could be attributed to improved performance by Hispanic households. Many cities showing the greatest increases over 1990 -- Hialeah, Fla.; El Paso; and Santa Ana, Anaheim and San Diego, Calif. -- have large and growing Hispanic populations.</p>
        <p>Response rates in white communities showed much less improvement over 1990, and in some cases produced declines. Several states, including Iowa, North Dakota, South Dakota, Missouri and Tennessee, did not improve at all from 10 years ago. And response rates declined in Minnesota, Kansas, Washington, Wisconsin, Idaho, Vermont and Delaware.</p>
        <p>Among counties with the most significant improvements was New York County -- Manhattan -- which raised its response rate to 60 percent, from 52 percent in 1990. It was the third-best improvement among the nation's 100 most populous counties.</p>
        <p>Census officials hope to factor in those missed in this census by using a survey of 330,000 households to adjust final population counts.</p>
        <p>Republicans have fought against -- and Democrats have supported -- this sampling because they believe it will raise the numbers of minorities living in traditionally Democratic areas, giving Democrats an advantage when boundaries for Congressional districts are redrawn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
