<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y20BRI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/world/20BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D9153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>IVORY COAST: POLITICAL BAN -- The government suspended all political activities until campaigning for the presidential election officially opens on Oct. 7, linking the move to an assassination attempt on the country's military ruler. Gen. Robert Guei said he had escaped an assassination attempt on Monday when young soldiers attacked his residence. He blamed ''certain people'' whom he did not identify. Supporters of the former prime minister, Alassane Ouattara, one of General Guei's rivals in the election, said they believed that the accusations were directed at their party.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: COMMUNIST POSITION ON AIDS -- The Communist Party joined its political ally, the Congress of South African Trade Unions, in stating that it acknowledged that H.I.V. causes AIDS, a stance the third alliance partner, the governing African National Congress, has not endorsed. The A.N.C. leader, President Thabo Mbeki, and members of his cabinet, along with dissident scientists dismissed by the mainstream medical world, maintain that AIDS can also be caused by poverty, poor nutrition and repetitive infections.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>IVORY COAST: POLITICAL BAN -- The government suspended all political activities until campaigning for the presidential election officially opens on Oct. 7, linking the move to an assassination attempt on the country's military ruler. Gen. Robert Guei said he had escaped an assassination attempt on Monday when young soldiers attacked his residence. He blamed ''certain people'' whom he did not identify. Supporters of the former prime minister, Alassane Ouattara, one of General Guei's rivals in the election, said they believed that the accusations were directed at their party.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: COMMUNIST POSITION ON AIDS -- The Communist Party joined its political ally, the Congress of South African Trade Unions, in stating that it acknowledged that H.I.V. causes AIDS, a stance the third alliance partner, the governing African National Congress, has not endorsed. The A.N.C. leader, President Thabo Mbeki, and members of his cabinet, along with dissident scientists dismissed by the mainstream medical world, maintain that AIDS can also be caused by poverty, poor nutrition and repetitive infections.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>KUWAIT: PARRYING IRAQ -- Iraqi accusations that Kuwait has been stealing its oil have raised tension in the region to levels that existed in July 1990, days before Iraqi troops invaded Kuwait, said Kuwait's minister for cabinet affairs, Sulaiman Majed al-Shaheen. He said Iraq is only attempting to escape international obligations, especially requirements to comply with United Nations Security Council resolutions. Iraq has repeatedly accused Kuwait during the last week of stealing its oil, with one report saying it involved at least 300,000 barrels a day from oilfields near the border.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CUBA: PLEA TO END SANCTIONS -- Testifying in Washington before the International Trade Commission, Cuba's top diplomat in the United States, Fernando Remirez de Estenoz, called for an end to all sanctions on Havana rather than the smaller step now being fought in Congress for fewer limits on sales of American food and medicine. The rare appearance by a Cuban official before a federal agency was protested by two Florida lawmakers.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: FATAL EXPLOSION -- A bomb placed in a crate of grapes exploded in a vegetable market in the capital, Islamabad, killing 16 people and wounding at least 75, the police said. No one took responsibility for the blast, which the military ruler, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, called a ''dastardly act of terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE PHILIPPINES: HOSTAGES FREED -- Four days into a military campaign to free 19 hostages held by Muslim rebels, government troops rescued two of them, both French journalists, President Joseph Estrada said. Speaking in a radio interview, Mr. Estrada said that Jean-Jacques Le Garrec and Roland Madura of state television France-2 had been rescued unharmed by troops pursuing Abu Sayyaf rebels in Jolo island.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>SOUTH KOREA: FAMILY REUNIONS -- South Korea's Red Cross selected 300 names from 52,000 applicants by computer lottery for the next reunions of families divided for decades. All those chosen were over 70. Seoul hopes new meetings will go ahead next month, but details on the final numbers and the time of reunions will be hammered out at new talks with the North starting today. After the June summit meeting between the leaders of the South and North, 100 people from each side held reunions in Seoul.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: ARMY ATTACKED -- Tamil rebels detonated an anti-personnel mine, killing 24 soldiers in northeastern Sri Lanka, a military spokesman and the police said. Since 1983, more than 62,000 people have died in the rebels' campaign for independence in the island's northeast.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: NATO CITES FOILED PLOT -- Two suspected undercover members of the Yugoslav Army's special forces were caught in central Kosovo on what NATO peacekeepers called a mission to sow terror. A cache of weapons and explosives was also seized in Gracanica, south of the capital, Pristina. NATO has frequently warned that Yugoslav forces, after being driven from Kosovo last year, were infiltrating the province. Belgrade argues that NATO has failed to keep order and protect minorities.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: INVESTIGATION OF MEDIA GROUP -- The prosecutor general's office began an inquiry into the newspaper and broadcasting business of Vladimir V. Gusinsky, as the conflict between Mr. Gusinsky and his largest creditor intensified. The creditor, the gas giant Gazprom, which is partly owned by the government, said it would take the dispute to court after Mr. Gusinsky reneged on a secret agreement signed in July to sell his company, Media-Most. On Monday, Gazprom asked the prosecutor's office to investigate Mr. Gusinsky's business, particularly its charge that Mr. Gusinsky moved parts of his company offshore to evade creditors.</p>
        <p>Sabrina Tavernise (NYT)</p>
        <p>LUXEMBOURG: DUCAL SUCCESSION DEFERRED -- The coronation of Crown Prince Henri, left, as ruler was postponed out of concern for the health of his younger brother, Prince Guillaume, who remains in a coma a week after he was injured in a car crash outside Paris. Henri was scheduled to be sworn in as Grand Duke on Sept. 28 to succeed his father Jean, who is stepping down after 26 years as head of state. The abdication and coronation ceremonies have been postponed until Oct. 7.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ITALY: ARTIST FOUND? -- Two Italians announced that they had identified the remains of Giotto, the early Renaissance painter, which were discovered 30 years ago in the crypt beneath the Duomo in Florence during excavation work. Some scholars suspected that the painter, who died in 1337, might have been buried in the cathedral. Using modern forensic tools, the two men, a journalist and an anthropologist, partly reconstructed his cranium, and said it bore a striking resemblance to a self-portrait in Giotto's ''Last Judgment'' fresco in the Scrovegni chapel in Padua.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
