<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="20FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDE123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-17</p>
        <p>China Trade Bill Approved By Wide Margin in Senate  A bill to remove restraints on trade with China passed the Senate in a strong bipartisan vote, giving President Clinton what he considered one of his crowning foreign policy goals. Coupled with approval by the House in May, the vote ended the annual Congressional review of China's trade status, which some had argued was necessary to force China to improve its record on human rights.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mixed Signals on Laser Sale  The White House said Russia had suspended a contract to sell Iran advanced laser technology that Washington says can be used to make fuel for nuclear weapons. But the Russian scientific institute involved says it still plans to make the sale.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-17</p>
        <p>China Trade Bill Approved By Wide Margin in Senate  A bill to remove restraints on trade with China passed the Senate in a strong bipartisan vote, giving President Clinton what he considered one of his crowning foreign policy goals. Coupled with approval by the House in May, the vote ended the annual Congressional review of China's trade status, which some had argued was necessary to force China to improve its record on human rights.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mixed Signals on Laser Sale  The White House said Russia had suspended a contract to sell Iran advanced laser technology that Washington says can be used to make fuel for nuclear weapons. But the Russian scientific institute involved says it still plans to make the sale.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Peru Leader Addresses Nation  President Alberto K. Fujimori, whose government has been roiled by a bribery scandal, entered the Palace of Government to the cheers of supporters and assured the nation that he was in full control and would remain in office until a successor was sworn in next July.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Off Again, On Again in Mideast  Israel canceled a meeting with Palestinian negotiators, raising concerns that the peace effort had reached another potential breaking point. Palestinian negotiators quickly condemned the Israelis for what they described as an indefinite suspension of negotiations, but by day's end the Israelis had scheduled another meeting, for today.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Angola May Restrict Media  The government of Angola, moving to restrict the independent news media, proposed legislation that would send journalists to prison for criticizing or questioning government officials. Journalists say the new law will make it impossible for them to do their jobs and will violate their constitutionally protected right to freedom of expression.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Furor Over Irish Nominee  A wave of public anger forced the withdrawal of the Irish government's nomination of a former Irish Supreme Court judge to a highly paid European Union job. The former judge, Hugh O'Flaherty, was accused in 1999 of arranging the early parole hearing and eventual release of a family acquaintance who had been convicted of killing a young mother while driving drunk.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-24</p>
        <p>With a Hollywood Crowd, Democrats Mute Criticism  Vice President Al Gore and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, appearing at a Beverly Hills fund-raiser Monday night, muted criticism of the entertainment industry as they reassured Hollywood that their calls for stricter marketing practices were not an effort to squelch creativity.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush on 'Oprah'  Gov. George W. Bush appeared on Oprah Winfrey's program, whose audience is three-fourths women, sitting for an interview that emphasized biography over policy.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Polls show that while most single women support Vice President Al Gore, Mr. Bush leads among married women, particularly those under 50 with children still at home.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, citing news reports casting doubt on a cost comparison Mr. Gore had made between human and animal medications, said the vice president ''simply makes some things up out of whole cloth.''</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Study on Drug Advertising  Advertising has stimulated a big rise in retail spending on prescription drugs, the fastest-growing item in the nation's health care budget.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Immigration Official Leaving  David Beebe, the top immigration official in Portland, Ore., said he was retiring. Complaints about abusive treatment by immigration agents have given Portland the unwanted nickname of ''Deportland.''</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Census Return Rate Improves  Census officials said 67 percent of households that received a form in the mail filled it out and sent it back, slightly higher than 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Plane Crash Off Florida  A small plane that Cuba said had been hijacked apparently ran out of fuel and crashed into the Gulf of Mexico, killing one man; nine people were rescued by a freighter.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Plan to Give Students Laptops  The New York City Board of Education is pushing ahead on a proposal to provide portable computers to most public school students, as well as Internet access over a Web site that will include commercial advertising, all at a cost now estimated at $900 million over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>City to Get U.S. Monitor To Oversee AIDS Services  A federal judge in Brooklyn found that New York City had failed to provide adequate services for thousands of people with AIDS and ordered federal oversight of the city's AIDS support agency for three years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Senator Linked to Inquiry  Federal investigators were said to be examining the possibility that political allies of Senator Robert G. Torricelli, Democrat of New Jersey, sent men to a New Jersey jail to intimidate David Chang, who had been arrested on charges of illegally donating to the senator's campaign.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Lazio Rejects Debate Criticism  Representative Rick A. Lazio said it was sexist to suggest that he should not have walked over to Hillary Rodham Clinton's lectern.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Tunnel Fire Disrupts L.I.R.R.  Railroad officials said an East River tunnel closed by a fire during the evening rush might not be reopened until after the start of this morning's rush, and they urged commuters to listen to radios for updates.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>A Skyscraper to Call Home  The Skyscraper Museum, which has had several addresses, is getting a home in the 38-story Ritz-Carlton hotel and condominium tower, now rising at Battery Park City.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>New Face for Brooklyn Museum  Brooklyn Museum of Art officials unveiled a $55 million plan to transform the institution's front entrance into a major civic plaza, with amphitheaters, reflecting pools and programmable fountains flanking a modernistic new lobby of glass and steel.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Olympics TV Audience Down  NBC-TV's ratings for the Sydney Olympics are thus far the lowest in the event's history.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
        <p>S1-8</p>
        <p>Gold for Romanian Women  Romania won the gold in women's team gymnastics; the United States, which won in 1996, finished fourth.</p>
        <p>S1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-23</p>
        <p>Greenberg Leaves A.I.G.  A.I.G. said its president, Evan Greenberg, 45, a son of Maurice R. Greenberg, who built A.I.G. into the country's most powerful insurance company, had resigned. Mr. Greenberg said in an interview that he felt it was time to leave ''home.''</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Strong Quarter for Goldman  Goldman Sachs Group, one of the biggest investment banks, said it earned $824 million in the last quarter, up 29 percent from the same quarter last year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Pepsi Suit Is Thrown Out  A federal judge dismissed a suit in which PepsiCo accused Coca-Cola of unfairly wielding its influence to control beverages served in restaurants, theaters and other businesses.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Tire Death Toll Rises  Federal officials said that since Aug. 31 they had received complaints of 15 more deaths attributed to Firestone tires on sport utility vehicles and pickups, raising the total to 103.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C23-24</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: A ''tilt'' toward India; sound strategy on forest fires; medical marijuana and free speech.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
