<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peru's President, Cheered by Supporters, Vows to Stay in Office Until Next Summer</title>
    <meta content="Y20PER$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/world/20PERU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peru-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montesinos, Vladimiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E4DD123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peru's President, Cheered by Supporters, Vows to Stay in Office Until Next Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peru Pres Alberto K Fujimori, cheered by supporters, makes first public appearance since calling for new elections and dismantling of National Intelligence Service; assures nation he is in full control and will remain in office until his successor is sworn in next July, televised speech; says he acted in response to videotape showing Vladimiro Montesinos, his close aide and intelligence chief, offering bribe to opposition congressman; holds military backs government; denies United States pressed him not to seek re-election; several cabinet ministers say Montesinos is in Lima and not under arrest; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first public appearance since he called for new elections and the dismantling of the National Intelligence Service, President Alberto K. Fujimori entered the Palace of Government tonight to the cheers of supporters and assured the nation that he was in full control and would remain in office until his successor is sworn in next July.</p>
        <p>After climbing atop the palace gate and waving to the crowd, he went inside to give a televised address in which he said his decision last Saturday was a moral obligation to ensure stability and one that he made after a videotape surfaced that showed his close aide and intelligence chief apparently offering a $15,000 bribe to an opposition congressman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first public appearance since he called for new elections and the dismantling of the National Intelligence Service, President Alberto K. Fujimori entered the Palace of Government tonight to the cheers of supporters and assured the nation that he was in full control and would remain in office until his successor is sworn in next July.</p>
        <p>After climbing atop the palace gate and waving to the crowd, he went inside to give a televised address in which he said his decision last Saturday was a moral obligation to ensure stability and one that he made after a videotape surfaced that showed his close aide and intelligence chief apparently offering a $15,000 bribe to an opposition congressman.</p>
        <p>The aide, Vladimiro Montesinos, has not been seen since Mr. Fujimori's announcement, and opponents have worried about the possibility of a coup, given Mr. Montesinos's close ties to high-ranking officers and the continued silence of the military.</p>
        <p>''I am not saying goodbye yet,'' Mr. Fujimori said during an address that was by turns animated and jovial. ''This message does not signify my immediate resignation. I am in full function.''</p>
        <p>He also insisted that he enjoyed the support of the commanding generals.</p>
        <p>''There is no power vacuum,'' he said. ''We will keep working intensively until the last days. The country is at peace and there is liberty for demonstrations and freedom of expression.''</p>
        <p>He was emphatic in saying that he arrived independently at his decision to call for new elections in which he would not run. He denied that he had been under pressure from the United States government, which along with other nations had questioned Mr. Montesinos's role in his government.</p>
        <p>''I never received a call from anyone, and the United States does not act in that manner,'' he said. ''We have good communication. We have been in dialogue and cooperation. But absolutely no calls or insinuations. Nothing. Zero. These decisions were the sovereign decisions of the President of Peru.''</p>
        <p>But when asked about Mr. Montesinos's whereabouts, Mr. Fujimori passed the microphone to the cabinet ministers who flanked him. Several times, the ministers said they did not know Mr. Montesinos's exact location, but added that he was in Lima and not under arrest. They said that he was still receiving official protection, given his role in combating terrorism and illegal narcotics, and that he was also entitled to due process regarding any criminal charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori also criticized his opponents, who he said had attacked him despite his success in fighting terrorists and improving the economy.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, several of his opponents said that while they were willing to resume talks with his government to find a solution to the political crisis, they also had more videotapes with evidence of official misconduct. They had previously conditioned participation in such talks on Mr. Montesinos's arrest.</p>
        <p>Their change of heart came one day after Mr. Fujimori instructed his cabinet to submit to Congress the necessary bills to have a new election.</p>
        <p>The day's events came against a backdrop of deepening mystery about the whereabouts of Mr. Montesinos, and a continued silence from the military about the changes in government.</p>
        <p>''There is a real situation of emergency and misinformation, so we can no longer remain on the margins,'' said Fernando Olivera, a congressman with the Independent Moralizing Front Party. ''This does not mean we withdraw our demand for the arrest of Vladimiro Montesinos. What would happen is, it would be put on the table for discussion so together we can make the correct decision.''</p>
        <p>Opposition groups had been taking part in talks with the Fujimori government under the aegis of the Organization of American States, which was trying to bolster confidence in Peru after Mr. Fujimori won a controversial third term this year.</p>
        <p>It was unclear today if the main opposition leader, Alejandro Toledo, who withdrew from the presidential race after accusing the government of rigging the election, had agreed to new talks. On Monday night he was acting like a candidate as he addressed a crowd of 10,000 cheering supporters at Plaza San Martin to propose a transitional government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olivera said today that this was not the time to campaign, but to find solutions, hoping that talks would bring about elections soon.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Olivera, who set off the crisis when he made public the incriminating videotape, also tinged his overture with its own mystery when he announced that he had other damning videotapes. His assertion was backed up by Susana Higuchi, an opposition lawmaker and Mr. Fujimori's former wife.</p>
        <p>''Obviously the military is pressuring Fujimori so there would not be a coup,'' she said at a midday news conference. ''That is why we do not plan to release the other videos, because there would be chaos.''</p>
        <p>A senior Clinton administration official, however, said he did not think there was much appetite among officers for a coup in support of Mr. Montesinos.</p>
        <p>The opposition released more details today about how Mr. Montesinos responded to the first videotape. Mr. Olivera said Mr. Montesinos's emissaries contacted him soon after the videotape was leaked and urged Mr. Olivera to reach an accommodation or face the possibility of a coup that would sweep away him and other opponents.</p>
        <p>''We did not accept any pact,'' he said. ''We are sure that no military adventure, no matter how bloody, would last for more than 24 hours.''</p>
        <p>He said the videotape had been given to him by ''a patriot'' who had risked his life and now had a bounty on his head. ''Even to this day he is risking his life because he knows the methods they use to take reprisals,''  Mr. Olivera said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
