<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Step Right Up and Buy a Megawatt!</title>
    <meta content="20WALD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Gas and Electric Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DD1039F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Step Right Up and Buy a Megawatt!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pacific Gas and Electric has started online program in California called E-Bid that pays some big electric customers to cut their consumption during peak periods; program detailed; graph (special section, E-Commerce) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY Web sites scream about what they will sell you for next to nothing, or less. But how about a site that pays you not to buy?</p>
        <p>A strange notion, but one that has more solid economic underpinnings than many of those desperate give-it-away dot-coms. Then again, the commodity in question is not the typical stuff of e-commerce transactions, like a plane ticket from Cincinnati to Nashville next Thursday or a vintage Barbie doll or 20,000 widgets of a certain shape. This promising new business is using e-commerce for a commodity that absolutely everybody needs: electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY Web sites scream about what they will sell you for next to nothing, or less. But how about a site that pays you not to buy?</p>
        <p>A strange notion, but one that has more solid economic underpinnings than many of those desperate give-it-away dot-coms. Then again, the commodity in question is not the typical stuff of e-commerce transactions, like a plane ticket from Cincinnati to Nashville next Thursday or a vintage Barbie doll or 20,000 widgets of a certain shape. This promising new business is using e-commerce for a commodity that absolutely everybody needs: electricity.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, one kilowatt may look like another, but its price may vary by a factor of more than 100 in a single day. At night a kilowatt-hour -- the amount of electricity needed to light 10 100-watt bulbs for an hour -- may sell for a penny or two, because most of the generating capacity is unused. But on a hot afternoon, in places where the market is deregulated, the same amount of power could cost $1 or $5, or even more.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, though, utilities charge most customers pretty much the same price for the kilowatt-hour no matter what they pay to buy it or if they generate it themselves. Even companies with time-of-day rates are charging a price that varies by only a few pennies from peak to off-peak.</p>
        <p>But as California approached a summer of tight electricity supplies this year, Pacific Gas and Electric started an e-commerce marketplace where customers could be paid not to buy. In theory, the system would work with any customer, but it is only practical with big consumers, mostly businesses, because otherwise the number of transactions becomes hard to manage.</p>
        <p>As the state danced on the edge of rotating blackouts, the company quickly applied to regulators for permission to expand its program, called E-Bid. The system works like this: every afternoon, the utility gets an estimate of what power will cost on the wholesale market the next day. When the price is high, the utility notifies big customers that have signed up for its program,  alerting them to log on to a secure Web site.</p>
        <p>There, according to Ronald K. Lowe, a company spokesman, the estimated price is posted. If the customer, generally a factory, is willing to cut its consumption 20 percent from its normal level, then it accepts the bid, and the utility pays the customer the posted price, minus the normal retail cost per kilowatt-hour. If the bulk price is $250 a megawatt-hour, for example, that makes electricity 25 cents a kilowatt-hour, compared with a typical price to the factory of 5 cents or so. For every kilowatt-hour that the factory does not use on the next day, the company pays 20 cents.</p>
        <p>The transaction has two functions. It cuts the risk of the grid running short of power and causing a blackout. And by reducing the peak demand, it takes a few buyers out of the market and makes the price lower for the remaining buyers. As the summer ended, proponents of this kind of marketing said that the unanticipated price swings, especially in places like San Diego, where some customers faced bills that had tripled, showed the necessity for making hourly prices obvious to electricity users, so that they would not blithely continue with normal consumption patterns at times of extraordinary price spikes.</p>
        <p>But the California program is still small; on one tough day this summer, July 31, 29 customers participated, cutting demand by 40 megawatts, compared with a peak demand of 21,000 megawatts.</p>
        <p>Pacific Gas and Electric charges customers $600 to enter the program and requires that they be able to cut demand by at least 500 kilowatts, which is enough to run about 100 big houses. But it has applied for permission to cut the entry fee to $100 and take applicants who can cut demand by only 250 kilowatts.</p>
        <p>Such transactions are only possible through electronic commerce, but by setting just one price in a 24-hour period, P.G.&amp; E.'s system is hardly taking full advantage. Wisconsin Electric Power began a more flexible system this summer in which it invites big customers to log on to a site,  where it offers a price per kilowatt-hour not used. If it does not attract enough bidders to meet its needs, it can post a new bid price a few minutes later.</p>
        <p>Such transactions could apply the market forces that already exist at the wholesale level to the level of the electricity user, possibly even a homeowner.</p>
        <p>''There's been a whole lot of debate over the years as to whether or not an average consumer will ever shift consumption based on price principles,'' said Scott A. Weiner, a senior vice president of Sithe Northeast, an independent power producer. ''On the other hand, people who run large office buildings or factories can get those price signals in a very strong way,'' said Mr. Weiner, a former environmental commissioner for New Jersey.</p>
        <p>BUT, he said, at the moment, there is a supply curve -- a changing level of the amount available, depending on the price offered -- but no real demand curve, because the buyers do not know what the price is and thus cannot respond. Demand is therefore not affected by price.</p>
        <p>''In the absence of a demand response, nobody can ever say, 'The price is too high, I'm not going to pay that,' '' Mr. Weiner said. ''As load response programs come into development, it's clear the Web will play a very vital part of making that real and accessible.''</p>
        <p>A second form of e-commerce is emerging on a business-to-business model, and it's one of the few forms that the government has required. It is called Oasis, for Open Access Same-Time Information System, ordered by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. Oasis gives companies that build free-standing power plants a way to market their power and for companies that consume electricity a way to see the market. Oasis systems are increasingly operated by new entities called Independent System Operators, which have been formed on the East Coast and in California to run the transmission grids that were formerly controlled by electric utilities.</p>
        <p>The systems vary from place to place, but are supposed to show the price of electricity, sometimes broken down by location, to take account of transmission bottlenecks.</p>
        <p>At the California Independent System Operator, William H. Simmons, the manager of market applications, development and support, said that some aspects of electricity trading existed years ago on electronic bulletin boards. But the ability of users to identify available transmission links and schedule their use depended on the Web. ''It could not have happened if it were not for the Internet,'' he said. The Independent System Operator works with the California Power Exchange to arrange delivery of the power that generators and customers contract for on the exchange.</p>
        <p>Both Oasis and programs like E-Bid have the potential to adjust electricity use to reflect costs, experts say, and that would be one way to hold down peak demand and thus make the system less prone to overload.</p>
        <p>Eric Hirst, an energy consultant in Oak Ridge, Tenn., and a former scientist at the national laboratory there, speaking at a conference in Washington this spring on reliability problems, said the result would contrast with the former pattern of electricity use. When people know the price of a product they are consuming, they behave differently, economists say; in the case of electricity, they will consume it in relation to its seasonal price or even hourly price.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Hirst said, ''When people used to pay 5 cents a kilowatt-hour, it didn't matter to them whether electricity was free or $2 a kilowatt-hour.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
