<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Pro Football; Dungy of the Buccaneers A Stickler for the Defense</title>
    <meta content="20BUCS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/sports/20BUCS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dungy, Tony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DD123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Pro Football; Dungy of the Buccaneers A Stickler for the Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses success of Tampa Bay Buccaneers defensive unit under coach Tony Dungy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He was a rookie and was ready to play in his first preseason game in 1977. Tony Dungy was a Pittsburgh defensive back and the Steelers were at New England, at Foxboro Stadium.</p>
        <p>''And I didn't play a down -- not one play,'' Dungy recalled today. ''The first preseason game, and you don't get in for one play? I just knew I was going to get cut the next day. But I didn't.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He was a rookie and was ready to play in his first preseason game in 1977. Tony Dungy was a Pittsburgh defensive back and the Steelers were at New England, at Foxboro Stadium.</p>
        <p>''And I didn't play a down -- not one play,'' Dungy recalled today. ''The first preseason game, and you don't get in for one play? I just knew I was going to get cut the next day. But I didn't.''</p>
        <p>No, Dungy, 44, started and played the entire game the next week against Philadelphia. He would play two seasons and eventually work as a Steelers assistant coach for eight years, learning from that franchise that defense wins games.</p>
        <p>And what he learned there, he believes in.</p>
        <p>Dungy grew up in Jackson, Mich., a city he describes as ''a small industrial town where all parents looked after all kids.''</p>
        <p>''I had 10 to 12 close buddies who I played ball with all the way from elementary to high school,'' he said. ''That is where I learned to compete.''</p>
        <p>And there -- from his mom, Cleo, and his dad, Will, along with three siblings -- Dungy learned the value of good manners and family commitment and how he would conduct himself in whatever profession he chose.</p>
        <p>''And what I learned there, I believe in,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tony Dungy said he believes that big-play offenses are in vogue in pro football but there remains a place for tough-minded, defense-led teams. Dungy is a firm believer that winning teams have quickness and explosiveness on defense.</p>
        <p>He believes that the difference between winning players and losing ones at the pro level is a state of mind, a willingness to perform individual tasks in the framework of a team.</p>
        <p>Tony Dungy believes in his Tampa Bay Buccaneers.</p>
        <p>This is his fifth season as Buccaneers coach, and this team is unlike his first four in terms of talent and offensive propensity. The Buccaneers are 3-0 because they have a defense that has allowed only two touchdowns (none rushing) and earned 18 sacks and 8 turnovers. The Buccaneers are 8-2 with Shaun King starting at quarterback and are averaging 31 points a game with receiver Keyshawn Johnson in the mix.</p>
        <p>Dungy's teams were 6-10, 10-6, 8-8 and 11-5 in his first four seasons. Last year Tampa Bay lost, 11-6, to St. Louis in the National Football Conference championship game. It was a game that Tampa Bay led in the fourth quarter, 6-5.</p>
        <p>''We expected to win and feel like we should have won that game, 6-5, and should have played Tennessee in the Super Bowl,'' Dungy said. ''That's how everybody here feels about it because we had the lead late in the game. And we would not have apologized for winning, 6-5. I learned from Chuck Noll in Pittsburgh that speed and explosiveness on defense is the way to build a team. Both are difficult for your opponent to assimilate in practice and then in games it is even harder to match. I was surprised when we played the Rams last year that not many people gave our defense much of a chance to slow them down. I mean, we've been very good at what we do.''</p>
        <p>The Buccaneers are a throwback team with a coach who could lead in any season, any decade.</p>
        <p>There are few people in the National Football League -- owners, coaches, players, the league office -- who command the respect Dungy does. He is more than a players' coach. He is a people coach. He exudes class and charisma and intelligence. No wonder the people in this community consider him one of their own, along with his team.</p>
        <p>He has built the Bucs with defense but all the while has tinkered with the offense. King started the final five games of last season, replacing Trent Dilfer, who had been Dungy's quarterback during his entire Bucs tenure. Les Steckel left Tennessee and joined Tampa Bay as offensive coordinator. There was the addition of the Pro Bowl linemen Jeff Christy and Randall McDaniel from Minnesota. And, of course, there was the trade with the Jets for Johnson.</p>
        <p>But it is unlikely that offense will overshadow defense on any Dungy team. The Buccaneers feature four down linemen, led by Warren Sapp, who create havoc and pressure. For Dungy, that is key, along with outhitting opponents and each player knowing his responsibilities.</p>
        <p>Exactly the way Dungy learned it.</p>
        <p>''We were running the punt team once in Pittsburgh, and Coach Noll came over and told me that I was the wide guy and there was no way that I could let those two guys out wide blocking me keep me from getting down field and making the tackle,'' Dungy said. ''I mean, he was emphatic about it. So, the next day, I was working on the receiving side of the punts as one of the two wide guys blocking. And Coach Noll came over and said there was no way the two of us could let that one wide guy get downfield and make the tackle. And I made the mistake of asking him how yesterday I was over there on that side and today I'm over here and you're telling me no way on both sides. And he looked at me and said, 'Son, it's a state of mind.' ''</p>
        <p>And football, life, is like that for Dungy, a state of mind. He has made his choices on how his team will win with defense, how he will coach with tenacity and how he will conduct himself with class.</p>
        <p>His parents will be here from Michigan for the Jets game on Sunday. Last week, when Tampa Bay won at Detroit, Dungy relished 86 family members attending.</p>
        <p>He saw Pittsburgh win four Super Bowl rings and he was a part of one, as a player, in Super Bowl XIII. He started this season by winning at New England, at Foxboro Stadium, winding up in the same locker room he was in 23 years ago as the rookie who did not play. If he can win the Super Bowl for Tampa Bay this season in a game that will be played right here in Raymond James Stadium, it would be another stamp on all that he believes in. Another way to teach his three sons that his beliefs are winning ones.</p>
        <p>That his remarkable reputation is not an accident -- it was earned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
