<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Figs Are Good Enough Without the Blather</title>
    <meta content="20FIGS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/living/20FIGS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Figs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DA143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Figs Are Good Enough Without the Blather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros comments on cooking with green and black figs that are now in season; photo; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLIE BALDUCCI, who has sold produce for decades, has made me feel so much better about figs this summer. For years I have listened to seemingly knowledgeable food lovers become positively ecstatic about fresh figs and the nuances that make one variety better than another. Try as I may, I can barely tell the difference. All I know is that the green ones have slightly thicker skins.</p>
        <p>Last week I called Mr. Balducci, who is the produce buyer for the Baldor Specialty Foods Company in the Bronx, a distributor of fruits and vegetables, to ask if he could help me with my lack of sophistication about the green and black figs now in season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLIE BALDUCCI, who has sold produce for decades, has made me feel so much better about figs this summer. For years I have listened to seemingly knowledgeable food lovers become positively ecstatic about fresh figs and the nuances that make one variety better than another. Try as I may, I can barely tell the difference. All I know is that the green ones have slightly thicker skins.</p>
        <p>Last week I called Mr. Balducci, who is the produce buyer for the Baldor Specialty Foods Company in the Bronx, a distributor of fruits and vegetables, to ask if he could help me with my lack of sophistication about the green and black figs now in season.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I could tell them apart either if I was blindfolded,'' he said. ''There is a slight difference in the skin.''</p>
        <p>So why are people always raving about their differences?</p>
        <p>''When people come from Italy and say the fruit was wonderful, it's because it was just picked off the tree,'' he said. ''If you picked them off the tree here it would be the same thing, but when you get them they have gone through the distribution system; they've been refrigerated.''</p>
        <p>Since our conversation, I have read extensively about figs, and everyone seems to agree: the differences, at least among those grown in the United States, are minimal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Balducci added that the first figs of the year, the green Calimyrna that come in June, look distinctively different from the green kadota on the market now. Both are green-gold, but the kadota are slightly more pear-shaped, like the black or purple Mission figs in season now. Larger, more elongated Black Turkey figs are also in season. One variety or another should be available into November.</p>
        <p>Most figs sold in this country come from California, where they were first planted by Spanish missionaries. For years Americans outside California never saw a fig until it had been dried or ground up and put in a Fig Newton. Today figs are popular enough that street vendors in Manhattan sell them along with bananas and oranges.</p>
        <p>The best figs are plump and very soft; the small opening at the bottom should be slightly open, but there should be no blemishes or oozing. Figs can be refrigerated, but are best eaten at room temperature.</p>
        <p>Figs are very perishable: they spoil quite quickly. Unripe figs can improve only so much, and if they are at all firm will have none of the juicy sweetness for which they are prized. Select carefully, and plan to use them within two days. Figs sold loose, then, are generally worth the higher prices they fetch than those in sealed pint boxes.</p>
        <p>Figs are popular in all Mediterranean countries, where they are used in appealing savory combinations. Italians, of course, wrap them in prosciutto, the salt and sweet, the juicy and dry providing a great flavor medley. The combination also makes a spectacular salad if bitter arugula is added.</p>
        <p>A buttery sheep's milk cheese from Portugal, queijo de Serra, is wonderful eaten with figs and a touch of aged balsamic vinegar poured over them. They also work well with tangy cheeses like gorgonzola or blue, as well as creamier types like mascarpone.</p>
        <p>I like figs eaten out of hand, but sweets made with figs leave me cold. Figs can be roasted, or even battered and deep-fried, but less is more with this sweetness.</p>
        <p>Some of the best treatments are the easiest. Slice them in half, top each half with a dollop of sour cream and sprinkle with finely grated orange peel. Or quarter them and serve them with heavy cream spooned over.</p>
        <p>Or marinate quartered figs in a tiny bit of brandy for 30 minutes, mix sour cream with just enough orange liqueur to flavor it and spoon the mixture over the figs.</p>
        <p>As inviting as those combinations are, last week I had the most indulgently elegant dish of fresh figs ever. At a party at Osteria del Circo, the figs were halved and topped with a dollop of foie gras mousse. They were even better than with prosciutto.</p>
        <p>ROASTED FIGS WITH BLUE CHEESE AND HAM  Time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>8 ripe black Mission figs  6 tablespoons soft sharp blue cheese  3 tablespoons pine nuts  4 very thin slices cured country ham like Smithfield, cut in half  Pan spray.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 450 degrees.</p>
        <p>2. Wash figs. Cut them partway through vertically into 4 quarters, leaving the bottoms intact.</p>
        <p>3. Mix cheese with pine nuts, and stuff into figs. Arrange in a baking pan coated with pan spray, and roast just long enough for the cheese to begin to melt, about 5 minutes.</p>
        <p>4. Place 2 halves of a ham slice on each of 4 salad plates; put a fig on top of each half, and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings as first course.</p>
        <p>Note: Any variety of strong, salty blue cheese will work, especially Great Hill blue from Massachusetts or Humboldt Fog, Morbier style.</p>
        <p>SALAD OF FIGS, ARUGULA AND PROSCIUTTO  Time: 10 minutes</p>
        <p>1 1/2 tablespoons red-wine vinegar  2 1/2 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon Dijon mustard  2 large or 3 small bunches arugula, thoroughly washed and dried, tough stems removed  6 ripe fresh figs, washed and quartered  8 slices prosciutto, cut into 1-inch pieces.</p>
        <p>Whisk the vinegar, oil and mustard together. Toss the arugula with the dressing, and arrange on 4 salad plates. Arrange figs on arugula, and scatter prosciutto over.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
