<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Guided Tour Through a Writer's Mazy Mind</title>
    <meta content="20HAUP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/arts/20HAUP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ozick, Cynthia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Quarrel &amp; Quandary (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFD8143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Guided Tour Through a Writer's Mazy Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christopher Lehmann-Haupt reviews Cynthia Ozick's Quarrel &amp; Quandary, collection of essays; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>QUARREL &amp; QUANDARY  Essays  By Cynthia Ozick  247 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Is politics a distraction from art, or is it how we pay attention to the life that gives rise to art?'' This question, posed by Cynthia Ozick in the foreword to her challenging new collection of essays, ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary,'' is as old as the Saturday night bar debate, as a walk in the Lyceum with Aristotle, as art and politics themselves.</p>
        <p>Yet in the best, most aroused of these 19 essays, Ms. Ozick makes the question of art's relation to politics blaze anew. In ''Who Owns Anne Frank?'' she implicitly asks if posterity had a right to prettify the image of Anne Frank in the interest of offending fewer feelings and creating a figure of sentimental appeal. No, she answers in thunder, for in the act of transforming the original ''Diary of a Young Girl'' into a stage hit, the truth of the Holocaust was usurped, and a tragic figure was cartooned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>QUARREL &amp; QUANDARY  Essays  By Cynthia Ozick  247 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Is politics a distraction from art, or is it how we pay attention to the life that gives rise to art?'' This question, posed by Cynthia Ozick in the foreword to her challenging new collection of essays, ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary,'' is as old as the Saturday night bar debate, as a walk in the Lyceum with Aristotle, as art and politics themselves.</p>
        <p>Yet in the best, most aroused of these 19 essays, Ms. Ozick makes the question of art's relation to politics blaze anew. In ''Who Owns Anne Frank?'' she implicitly asks if posterity had a right to prettify the image of Anne Frank in the interest of offending fewer feelings and creating a figure of sentimental appeal. No, she answers in thunder, for in the act of transforming the original ''Diary of a Young Girl'' into a stage hit, the truth of the Holocaust was usurped, and a tragic figure was cartooned.</p>
        <p>In ''The Rights of History and the Rights of the Imagination'' Ms. Ozick asks if William Styron was free in his novel ''Sophie's Choice'' to portray his Auschwitz victim as a Pole instead of a Jew. Was it all right for Bernhard Schlink in ''The Reader'' to present a former Nazi as an illiterate when in fact the Germany that perpetrated the Holocaust was highly cultured? No, she answers in sorrow. Where the imagination impinges on history, certain truths must be respected. These novels are ''softly rhetorical'' works that deflect from ''the epitome,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ozick seems somewhat perplexed by the firmness of her conclusions in these and other pieces in ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary.'' She had always thought of the essay as an occasion for ''loafing and inviting one's soul,'' she writes in her foreword. Elsewhere, in ''She: Portrait of the Essay as a Warm Body,'' she praises that form ''as a thing of the imagination.'' She continues, ''A genuine essay has no educational, polemical, or sociological use; it is the movement of a free mind at play,'' ''a stroll through someone's mazy mind.''</p>
        <p>And in the latter half of this volume she ambles without axes to grind. In ''The Ladle'' she describes her late discovery of that kitchen instrument, comparing it finally, in its capacity to dip, to the human mind. In ''A Prophet of Modernism,'' she dips into the mind of Gertrude Stein, concluding about Stein's phrase ''Rose is a rose is a rose'' that ''this endearing, enduring, durable and derisible chant of a copycat Cubist is almost all that is left of Gertrude Stein'' but that she remains ''modernism's outermost manifestation and prophet.''</p>
        <p>In ''A Drugstore Eden,'' ''Lovesickness'' and ''How I Got Fired From My Summer Job,'' she writes of her childhood and youth, digging down to her roots in the Pelham Bay section of the Bronx, where her parents built their own drugstore.</p>
        <p>Yet while these essays are full of arresting turns of phrase, they disappoint somehow, disappearing too often into what Ms. Ozick herself calls the softness of metaphor. The book trails off until you reach its final piece, ''The Synthetic Sublime,'' a strong evocation of a New York City that ''disappears and then . . . disappears again; or say that every 75 years or so another city bursts out, as if against nature -- new shapes, new pursuits, new immigrants with their unfamiliar tongues and worried uneasy bustle.''</p>
        <p>Where Ms. Ozick is best is in the more complex of her ruminations on art's collision with politics. Is Dostoyevsky's Raskolnikov, the protagonist of ''Crime and Punishment,'' simply a forerunner of Theodore Kaczynski, she asks in ''Dostoyevsky's Unabomber,'' a ''philosophical criminal of exceptional intelligence and humanitarian purpose who is driven to commit murder out of an uncompromising idealism''? No, she concludes. While Dostoyevsky intended to condemn such radical utopianism, his genius was too complex to reduce his novel to a manifesto.</p>
        <p>Was Kafka's mind formed by the history and politics of the Austro-Hungarian empire? she asks in ''The Impossibility of Being Kafka,'' an acute meditation on the problems of translation. To be sure he was, she decides, although his writing transcends such a perspective.</p>
        <p>Was Henry James right so insistently to separate ''the deliberate and always sacral space of art from the vagaries, contingencies, and frustrations of the artist's life''? she asks in ''The Selfishness of Art.'' Perhaps, but she seems slightly shocked by the revelations in Lyndall Gordon's ''Private Life of Henry James: Two Women and His Art'' of the degree of James's callousness to the suffering of people he rejected.</p>
        <p>In essays like these Ms. Ozick seems surprised not only by her conclusions but also by the process through which she arrives at them. ''Two cheers, then -- when there is no choice -- for being engage,'' she concedes in her foreword, citing E. M. Forster's famous ''Two Cheers for Democracy,'' ''but three cheers and more for that other bravery, the literary essay, and for memory's mooning and maundering.''</p>
        <p>But after reading ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary'' you want to reverse Ms. Ozick's terms. One cheer for her apolitical essays, for her memory's ''mooning and maundering,'' and three cheers for when art's encroachment on politics serves to bring out the best in her. Even when you disagree with her, she electrifies your mind.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
