<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buck the System, Cosby Tells Teachers</title>
    <meta content="20COSB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/nyregion/20COSB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Teachers College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cosby, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7D7153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buck the System, Cosby Tells Teachers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Cosby, in his trademark avuncular fashion, leans on pew in Riverside Church and discusses education with audience of 2,000 Teachers College professors, students and trustees (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Cosby, in his trademark avuncular fashion, leaned on a pew in Riverside Church yesterday afternoon and addressed an audience of 2,000 as though he were standing in his yard chatting with a neighbor.</p>
        <p>He spoke of his fifth-grade teacher, Mrs. McKinney, who instructed her students one day to refuse to sing a minstrel song, ''Old Black Joe,'' at a school assembly, then stormed into the principal's office, presumably to tell administrators that she considered the song degrading. The next time the students were asked to sing in the auditorium, Mr. Cosby said, the song was ''Lift Every Voice and Sing,'' which many blacks consider a black national anthem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Cosby, in his trademark avuncular fashion, leaned on a pew in Riverside Church yesterday afternoon and addressed an audience of 2,000 as though he were standing in his yard chatting with a neighbor.</p>
        <p>He spoke of his fifth-grade teacher, Mrs. McKinney, who instructed her students one day to refuse to sing a minstrel song, ''Old Black Joe,'' at a school assembly, then stormed into the principal's office, presumably to tell administrators that she considered the song degrading. The next time the students were asked to sing in the auditorium, Mr. Cosby said, the song was ''Lift Every Voice and Sing,'' which many blacks consider a black national anthem.</p>
        <p>The anecdote, one of several Mr. Cosby told the professors, students, teachers and trustees of Teachers College of Columbia University, bolstered a primary theme of his lecture: that when teachers recognize the failings of the educational system, they should challenge them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby, who has a doctorate in education, was asked to speak as part of an annual series called the Virginia and Leonard Marx Lecture, established by two Teachers College alumni in 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby's rambling 75-minute address was meant to focus on the special educational needs of children with learning disabilities. But it touched on a variety of subjects, including the New York City schools chancellor, extraterrestrials, the similarity between drug dealers and serial killers, and refried beans.</p>
        <p>He returned time and again to the same refrain, asking teachers to question the system, although he did not say exactly how they should do so. ''I want you to realize who you are and stop these people from grading you until they grade the system,'' he said. ''How can you teach if you have no books? The system ties their legs and says, 'Run.' It ties their arms and says, 'Defend yourself.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby kept the crowd giggling throughout, with charming quips and clever stories. He also showed clips from his CBS network television show, ''Kids Say the Darndest Things,'' focusing on an 8-year-old boy named Joe-Joe, who was falling behind in class despite clear signs of intelligence, because of undiagnosed nutritional problems.</p>
        <p>One topic Mr. Cosby did not broach was his son, Ennis William Cosby, who was working toward a second master's degree and a doctorate in special education at Teachers College when he was slain in January 1997 in a robbery attempt while changing his tire on a Los Angeles highway.</p>
        <p>Ennis, who was 27 at the time of his death, had struggled with dyslexia as a child, and had hoped one day to start a school for children with learning disabilities. He was so close to completing his course work that Teachers College presented the master's degree to his family posthumously in May 1997.</p>
        <p>To honor their son's dream, Mr. Cosby and his wife, Camille Cosby, established the Hello Friend/Ennis William Cosby Foundation in 1997, to support teacher training and special education programs for people with dyslexia and other language-based learning disabilities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
