<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irregulars Provide the Fun at Lands' End</title>
    <meta content="20CALL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/business/20CALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Catalogs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lands' End Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olsen, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D7143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1191" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irregulars Provide the Fun at Lands' End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA R. OLSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olsen, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Lands' End and the 2,000 or so sales agents who work phones in Dodgeville, Wis; agents comment on some of customers' odd requests; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting at a computer and taking phone orders for parkas, socks, sheets and luggage eight hours a day might seem like a pretty boring job. But ask the sales representatives at Lands' End how they cope, and they are likely to tell you a funny story.</p>
        <p>Cindy Kitelinger tells this one. A customer called, but her words were drowned out by her dog's barking. The woman apologized and tried to shush her pet, but the barking only worsened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting at a computer and taking phone orders for parkas, socks, sheets and luggage eight hours a day might seem like a pretty boring job. But ask the sales representatives at Lands' End how they cope, and they are likely to tell you a funny story.</p>
        <p>Cindy Kitelinger tells this one. A customer called, but her words were drowned out by her dog's barking. The woman apologized and tried to shush her pet, but the barking only worsened.</p>
        <p>Finally, in exasperation, the customer made an unusual request. ''My daughter just left for college, and every time the phone rings the dog thinks it's her,'' Ms. Kitelinger recalled her saying. ''She calls and talks to him every day -- it's her dog. If I put the phone to his ear, would you say a few words? He'll think you're my daughter, and he'll stop barking.'' So Ms. Kitelinger talked to the dog, and he stopped barking.</p>
        <p>When you get right down to it, most jobs can get pretty tedious. A list of the most boring occupations would probably have to include assembly-line worker, data processor, security guard, parking-lot attendant, toll taker and cashier. At the higher end of the income scale, lawyers, accountants and even investment bankers have been known to complain about drudgery.</p>
        <p>So the 2,000 sales agents (3,000 in peak season) who work the phones at Lands' End in Dodgeville, Wis., for pay that averages about $24,000 a year are in good company. And like just about anyone else who finds himself fighting the monotony of a workplace routine, they are finding that it is the unpredictable, often eccentric behavior of the people they interact with that adds a little spice to their day.</p>
        <p>Consider a recent call handled by Ruth Lang. Ms. Lang, who raises llamas in her spare time, works the night shift. At 11:30 one Friday in July, a woman called to ask for a favor. She was being married the next day, the woman said, and was spending the night with her sister at a hotel that did not have a wake-up service. ''I'm petrified we're going to oversleep,'' she said. ''We've been trying to think of who might be awake early, and I know Lands' End is open 24 hours. Would you mind calling me in the morning and making sure I'm up?'' Ms. Lang stuck a Post-it on her computer to remind her. At 5 a.m., she called the woman and announced: ''This is your Lands' End wake-up service.''</p>
        <p>Calls about impending weddings seem to gravitate to Lands' End. Just last month,  Sunny Bresett took an order from a distraught bride-to-be. The woman was being married on Saturday, four days away, and her husband had forgotten to order a suit. Ms. Bresett arranged for a custom-hemmed suit, a belt, shoes and socks to be delivered to the groom's hotel the day before the wedding.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, employees go so far beyond the call of duty that their behavior seems to defy rational explanation. It could have been boredom with her routine, it could have been Midwestern hospitality or it could have been simple generosity that motivated Di McCormick in customer service to act as she did. When a man in Missouri called this summer to complain about the crease in the sleeve of the pink mesh polo shirt he had ordered from Lands' End and asked if she could please send him a shirt without such a crease, she sprang into action.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCormick picked 10 identical pink shirts, steamed them all with an industrial steamer, washed them, steamed them again and sent the man the best one. Now he's her steady customer. She did the same with yellow and orange polo shirts for him this summer.</p>
        <p>That kind of service may be hard to beat, but a couple of winters ago, Ruth Shober, another employee who is also a llama farmer, came close. Ms. Shober received a call from a woman who had dropped a Lands' End canvas purse while crossing the street. The purse was plastered with mud and road salt, the customer said, and she wanted to know how she should clean it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shober had learned from her husband, an engineer with the Wisconsin Transportation Department, that rock salt is a calcium compound. She suggested that the caller take a stiff brush and rub the rock salt off. If there was any residual dirt, the woman should wipe the purse with a damp cloth. That night, Ms. Shober found a piece of burgundy canvas comparable to the purse fabric, walked to a busy highway, dropped the canvas in the mud and rock salt and then followed her own cleaning instructions. They worked.</p>
        <p>''If they hadn't,'' Ms. Shober said, ''I was prepared to call the customer back with a few more ideas.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, most of the calls that pour into Lands' End are pretty run of the mill. On a recent Tuesday morning, Jean Slapak, a 14-year employee, helped Donna Passwaters from Severn, Md., buy monogrammed, hooded bath cover-ups for her twin infant grandsons and easily dispatched slipcovers to Cornelia Barrentine from Pass Christian, Miss. She assisted another customer picking out just the right color sheets, advising her that garnet is a ''blueish or ruby red'' and suggesting, ''Wouldn't either the pale yellow or cappucino cases go well with the garnet, for a nice, soft complementary color?'' She assured a caller from Los Angeles that the vacation clothes she had ordered at the last minute would arrive by Friday for a small extra charge. She helped Christine Pinson of Yorba Linda, Calif., order school-uniform shirts monogrammed with her daughters' school logo.</p>
        <p>No material here for the Lands' End ''calls of fame'' list. But never mind. She will get another oddball request soon enough, she assumes; she averages three or four a day.</p>
        <p>Almost every sales representative has her favorite yarn. Jeanne McGuire got an urgent plea on the company's fax hotline not long ago from a man who had been on his way out the door to a formal affair when he realized he did not know how to tie his bowtie. Ms. McGuire faxed him directions and saved the day.</p>
        <p>And Eldora Alexander remembers helping a woman find just the right size of children's Polartec pajamas for her Dalmation. The woman planned to cut the feet out of the one-piece sleeper as well as a hole for the dog's tail, but could not decide whether to order it in small or large. Ms. Alexander had her measure the dog's girth and then compared this figure with the child chest measurements for the pajamas. The verdict: large.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
