<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Redskins Can't Buy A Winner</title>
    <meta content="20FREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/sports/20FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Mike Freeman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4D8153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Redskins Can't Buy A Winner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LANDOVER, Md.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Freeman Sports of The Times column discusses problems facing Washington Redskins, losers of two of first three games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Washington, the Redskins are more than a professional sports team, they are also a passion, more valuable to the city than the politicians who run it. Only someone who was born and raised there might fully understand this. When the Redskins are doing well, the crime doesn't seem so bad and the potholes are not so numerous. When the Redskins aren't doing well, fans begin begging for presidential intervention.</p>
        <p>This was going to be a great year in Washington, because the win-now owner Daniel Snyder had whipped out his checkbook and purchased an all-star team. The Redskins were hot again. They were the talk of the town, and almost every other town, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Washington, the Redskins are more than a professional sports team, they are also a passion, more valuable to the city than the politicians who run it. Only someone who was born and raised there might fully understand this. When the Redskins are doing well, the crime doesn't seem so bad and the potholes are not so numerous. When the Redskins aren't doing well, fans begin begging for presidential intervention.</p>
        <p>This was going to be a great year in Washington, because the win-now owner Daniel Snyder had whipped out his checkbook and purchased an all-star team. The Redskins were hot again. They were the talk of the town, and almost every other town, too.</p>
        <p>That may explain why celebrities and politicians, knowing this was as good a moment as any to get some television face time, showed up at the Monday night game between Washington and Dallas. This was a contest in which the Redskins were supposed to beat up on the lowly Cowboys and start their Super Bowl run, and many people wanted to catch the beginning of something great.</p>
        <p>There was the CNN anchor Bernard Shaw, a regular. There was New York Governor George E. Pataki and Orrin G. Hatch, a senator from Utah. Even the former Knick Charles Oakley showed up, dressed in a dapper suit that will probably appear later in an issue of GQ magazine. They were all there to watch Washington romp. One big party.</p>
        <p>So when the Cowboys upset the Redskins, 27-21, there was a sense of outrage from fans and celebrities alike, that the hype coming into this season had been a mirage, that everyone had been bamboozled. You could almost hear the senators, actors, Internet moguls and cabdrivers say in unison: We skipped Jay Leno for this?</p>
        <p>As one politician was leaving his luxury box Monday night, a member of his entourage said rather loudly, ''What a disaster.''</p>
        <p>What a disaster, indeed. Very early, the Redskins are crumbling under the crushing G-forces of their own expectations, and the heavy hand of Snyder, the micromanager with the short fuse, who sank lower into his chair as the ugly night dragged on. Super Bowl? With a 1-2 record, a last-place spot in the division and a schedule that includes a road game against the Giants on Sunday, followed by games against Tampa Bay, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Jacksonville and Tennessee -- teams with a combined 12-5 record -- the Redskins need lower expectations. Can you say wild card?</p>
        <p>It may be unfair to declare that the Redskins are on life support after only three games. After all, this team has oodles of talent, like Deion Sanders, Bruce Smith and Stephen Davis.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of top ballplayers on this team,'' wide receiver Irvin Fryar said. ''We'll see if the guys with the big names are going to pull us out of this, or is there going to be finger-pointing. We're in the storm. We'll see how we handle this.''</p>
        <p>Unfair, yes, but also realistic. One problem is the lack of cohesion among all that talent. They may be a team of all-stars, but unlike the less-talented Giants, who have more rhythm than a marching band, the Redskins are a group of egos flailing around like freshly netted fish.</p>
        <p>In the locker room, there is already a sense of dread. ''Everyone is hitting the panic button,'' wide receiver Andre Reed said. ''We need to just calm down.''</p>
        <p>Snyder has stayed out of the way so far, but everyone knows his reputation for screaming at coaches, firing secretaries and meddling with the football nuts and bolts. There is little question coaches and players are walking delicately, waiting for a Snyder outburst.</p>
        <p>What is hurting the Redskins the most are themselves, or better yet, the threat of themselves. Fryar said, ''I'm sure coaches on the teams we play are saying to the players, 'They have all that talent, but hard work beats talent every time.' ''</p>
        <p>''You know what other teams are saying?'' Reed said. '' 'The Redskins are done.' I'm sure other owners are mocking what Mr. Snyder did in assembling all these great players. We have to prove them wrong.''</p>
        <p>At halftime Monday, with the Redskins trailing, 14-7, the former coach Joe Gibbs and the former Redskins stars Art Monk and Dexter Manley were inducted into the team's Ring of Fame. When Snyder was introduced to play host for the ceremony, he was roundly booed. If the Redskins lose a few more games, celebrities may opt for the hockey team instead. Nothing like some puck action to fire up the town.</p>
        <p>Those potholes are looking bigger all the time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
