<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Hard to Be Funny When You Can't Hear Them Laugh</title>
    <meta content="20STEI$18" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ENTERTAINMENT"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DA1339F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Hard to Be Funny When You Can't Hear Them Laugh</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN STEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMEDY isn't funny. Or, to put it another way, it's not always easy to make people laugh.</p>
        <p>Humor that is planned, as opposed to the really funny, spontaneous kind, takes a certain combination of surprise, familiarity, aggression, recognition -- a stunning something that can be met with humor or not met at all, a surrender, a journey into the forbidden -- or just being very monotonic to the point that it makes the listener either cringe or laugh.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMEDY isn't funny. Or, to put it another way, it's not always easy to make people laugh.</p>
        <p>Humor that is planned, as opposed to the really funny, spontaneous kind, takes a certain combination of surprise, familiarity, aggression, recognition -- a stunning something that can be met with humor or not met at all, a surrender, a journey into the forbidden -- or just being very monotonic to the point that it makes the listener either cringe or laugh.</p>
        <p>I know these things because I earn my living doing all of them in movies, commercials, television shows and even in person. I know that it takes an entire large-scale picture and a combination of the visual, the aural and even a lunge into the unconscious to really get a good laugh. There's also a bit of the collegial.</p>
        <p>Alas, the Internet, despite its charms, offers only some of these elements, and therefore to convey humor on the Web, you have to double up on some elements and get a laugh out of a two-dimensional situation, although you can also have certain features that no other medium offers.</p>
        <p>I hereby offer a few examples, comparisons and contrasts. (By the way, humor is even harder to get in newsprint, but we'll come to that in a moment.)</p>
        <p>When I did my well-known turn as the boring teacher in ''Ferris Bueller's Day Off,'' I had an audience of stagehands, grips and extras at Stage 15 at Paramount Pictures. I could see them out of the corner of my eye, clearly enjoying what I was doing.</p>
        <p>This told me I was doing something right and to keep doing it. I was also being shot by a 35-millimeter camera that could record every nuance of my facial expression, especially since I would have a face about 10 feet high on the screen.</p>
        <p>Then, when the scene was shown, if a few people in the theater started to laugh, others -- just by human nature and the contagion of laughter -- were encouraged to laugh along. As the movie became a classic and was shown over and over, audiences knew to laugh at exactly the same spots over and over again, if only to prove they were in the club of people who ''got it.''</p>
        <p>Now, alas, much of this does not happen when one is trying to be funny on the Internet. There is no one in the sight of the comedian offering encouragement. There is no ripple of laughter patting the performer on the back. There is precious little even seen of the performer, and absolutely no instantaneous feedback, the sauce on which a comedian feeds.</p>
        <p>The Internet, except in the rarest of cases, does not even try to offer live humor or even a facsimile. Much of what takes place on the Internet in the name of humor is simply a teletyping of jokes. It's much like a continuous updating of a joke book. Many of these are funny jokes and can make the reader smile or even laugh.</p>
        <p>But you cannot get the power-packed hits of a truly great stand-up doing his humor with expressions and pauses and stares and giggles.</p>
        <p>Written humor can be fine, but it rarely makes people gag with laughter. It's nothing compared with the words and music and pratfalls and complex visuals and sound and buildup and windup of a humorous sketch in a good movie or even a great TV show like ''Saturday Night Live.'' There is nothing of the atmosphere of a great sitcom like ''The Wonder Years,'' where comedy can be thrown against real pathos.</p>
        <p>Also, humor often involves a sight gag combined with unexpected language and encouragement or else humiliation of someone on the set by the comedian, or else the humiliation of the comedian. Our television game show, ''Win Ben Stein's Money,'' has my co-host and me come out in funny costumes, say something raunchy and unexpected, and then have the audience roar along with this combination to really get a firestorm of laughter going (when it's working).</p>
        <p>Either the contestants or yours truly are humiliated or at least embarrassed every night.</p>
        <p>This is difficult to do online. On the Internet, if you have truly great graphics, like the ones I work with when I do my online game show with the software Shockwave, you can get some surprises and some great visuals. But you cannot get that audience approval that virtually forces everyone in the room to laugh. You cannot deliver the humiliation of a contestant in front of his pals or a national audience that is cruel but funny.</p>
        <p>You also do not get really top- notch, motion-picture-size graphics that show every single possible move and idiosyncrasy of the event. You don't get Jimmy Kimmel or Nancy Pimental's sneer or leer or my collapsing in puritanical shock. You don't get many of the dimensions of what might be called a good room.</p>
        <p>What we are working on to fix that absence of encouragement and the inability to communicate nuance is shock value, innovation and an invocation of that TV or movie or real-life room. For example, on Shockwave.com, there are many series of cartoons -- cartoons work almost perfectly on the Internet because the format is so similar to television, and subtlety is rarely a part of a cartoon, even a good one.</p>
        <p>But to make up for the smaller format and the lack of definition for some viewers, Shockwave is giving viewers cartoons with, well, shocking story lines about ground-up fish and missing genital parts and ''South Park'' type stunners that leave the viewer gasping -- for laughs, one hopes.</p>
        <p>For our online game show, we hope to evoke, but certainly not imitate, the setting and the ambience of a real-life game show. We'll have funny questions and categories, and we'll have my voice with a cartoon likeness deliver sneering mockery when a contestant gets something right or wrong. If the contestant is playing in a group either in one place or nationwide, the embarrassment of getting a question wrong can still sting and be amusing.</p>
        <p>But what we can deliver online that makes up for much of what we cannot deliver is immediacy and interactivity. Humor is in some senses a prescription medication to ward off loneliness, sorrow and boredom. Online, we can serve up this humor at 3  in the afternoon or 3 in the morning.</p>
        <p>Maybe we won't deliver the belly laughs that you would get if you were drunk at a comedy club with your pals, but we can give you humor and a feeling of participating in something funny, instead of just watching, whenever you are lonely or sad or just want to change your mood. With my online game show, either the smaller one on the Comedy Central site, or the far more elaborate one on Shockwave, we can let viewers not just laugh along but play along.</p>
        <p>We are like the pizza place that might not have as good a meal as you would get at the best restaurant in town, but it's there when you need it, and the delivery man stops for a chat to keep you company. We offer less intensity, but we offer company and a smile, and we offer it when you need it.</p>
        <p>As the Internet and connections improve, we will be able to link fraternities and sororities across the country so that their members can play our online quiz game and can hear each other giving the right or wrong answer and laugh along with it. We will be able to have audiences whose laughter the performer will be able to hear. That encouragement and group feeling will come soon if not immediately. Add in the interactivity, and, at least for comedy game shows, you may have largely offset what's been missing online.</p>
        <p>The large tapestry that a movie or a well-mounted TV show allows are still in some nerd's head. But to get to where a live show at a club or in a TV studio is -- that's coming close -- and when it can be summoned on demand, then you will really have serious competition from the Internet in the yucks department.</p>
        <p>And we have stock options, and boy, are we motivated.</p>
        <p>ENTERTAINMENT Ben Stein is the host of ''Win Ben Stein's Money'' and ''Turn Ben Stein On'' on Comedy Central.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ben Stein is the host of ''Win Ben Stein's Money'' and ''Turn Ben Stein On'' on Comedy Central.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
