<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; A Man and a Woman</title>
    <meta content="20DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/opinion/20DOWD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DF123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; A Man and a Woman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column sees Rep Rick Lazio's Senate campaign trying to portray Hillary Clinton as angry, castrating woman; holds Lazio erred at campaign debate by displaying poor sense and manners, acting like angry man (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ad is anything but subtle or subliminable.</p>
        <p>A woman's hand, representing Hillary Clinton's, reaches out with an electric prod, digs into the most sensitive part of the male anatomy, and -- bzzzzz!!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ad is anything but subtle or subliminable.</p>
        <p>A woman's hand, representing Hillary Clinton's, reaches out with an electric prod, digs into the most sensitive part of the male anatomy, and -- bzzzzz!!</p>
        <p>The New York Conservative Party attack ad, which has been running since Sunday, including twice during ''Meet the Press,'' depicts Hillary as a castrating rhymes-with-rich.</p>
        <p>The text is about how she got her hands on her (henpecked) husband's health care plan and messed it up. The visual is an old children's game, ''Operation,'' which has a flat figure of an alarmed-looking naked male patient, with an electric tweezer/ scalpel attached to let you play doctor and extract bones and organs.</p>
        <p>Except, in this case, Hillary is ominously portrayed doing the ''operating'' with a pulsating instrument of torture. (Bzzzz!!)</p>
        <p>Little Ricky is desperately trying to prove he's manly enough for the New York Senate job by painting Hillary as not womanly enough -- i.e., a cold, bitter, biting harpy.</p>
        <p>Usually, female candidates have to prove they're tough enough. Hillary Clinton is in the odd position of having to prove she's tender enough.</p>
        <p>In case anyone failed to get the Medusa message, the New York G.O.P. chairman, William Powers, has sent out a new fund-raising letter that reads, ''I have high hopes that you'll help us . . . stop this ambitious, ruthless, scheming, calculating, manipulating woman from fooling voters.'' He ends: ''Hillary Clinton is an angry woman.''</p>
        <p>Never has American politics been so fraught with gender gyrations.</p>
        <p>The national race may be decided by a kiss. Al Gore's convention smooch won the hearts of all those female voters who had been playing hard to get.</p>
        <p>Yesterday W., who was nicknamed ''Lip'' in high school but only for his smart mouth, played hardball on lip lock. Wooing the women's vote on ''Oprah,'' he came out and gave the surprised talk show host a buss on the cheek -- one-upping Al Gore, who merely gave Oprah a half-hug last week, prompting her flirtatious request, ''No kiss?''</p>
        <p>W. also replied ''Kiss to my wife,'' when asked to name the best gift he had ever given.</p>
        <p>While the presidential race may turn on a lingering kiss, the Senate race may turn on a wagging finger.</p>
        <p>The debate last week left Hillary and Ricky both trying to portray themselves as victims of sexism.</p>
        <p>Many of the women who had liked the glowing Long Island congressman recoiled from his glowering performance in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a women's lunch on Monday, Mrs. Clinton mocked Mr. Lazio's alpha bits: ''I knew I was going to share a stage. I didn't think I was going to have to share a podium.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio spent yesterday defending himself for acting like a bully at the pulpit. ''The idea that somehow that there's a double standard because you're a man or a woman, and you can't make a point forcefully if you're a man, and the person you're making the point with is a woman, I just think that's sexist,'' he said, adding, ''I don't think people in the Senate worry about whether you're a man or a woman.''</p>
        <p>Traditionally, of course, it is conservatives who make the case that men and women have to be viewed differently, and liberals who make the case that men and women should be treated the same.</p>
        <p>Most pathetically, the Lazio campaign sent reporters an old picture of Hillary, from her days as Arkansas first lady, wagging a finger at a political opponent to show that she, too, could be a space invader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio Just Doesn't Get It. His race is charged with gender, but his problem at the debate was more a matter of sense and manners.</p>
        <p>Once Tim Russert had made Mrs. Clinton uncomfortable by showing an old tape of her defending her feckless husband, the smart thing for Mr. Lazio to do was be magnanimous.</p>
        <p>A man who felt confident of his own masculinity, of course, would never have marched over to bluster at the first lady. It's impossible to imagine Ronald Reagan trying to cow a female opponent with such muscular histrionics.</p>
        <p>The Republicans should stop worrying about Hillary as the angry women, and start worrying about Ricky as the angry man.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
