<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Face of Australia Is Free to Be Herself</title>
    <meta content="20RHOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Cathy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D6143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Face of Australia Is Free to Be Herself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column discusses Australian track star Cathy Freeman, aborigine who lit Olympic torch in Sydney for 200 Summer Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CATHY FREEMAN was wonderfully poetic yesterday afternoon as she described the feeling of the final tension-filled seconds before a big race, the feelings shooting through her mind and body as they became one.</p>
        <p>''Twenty seconds before a race, there's absolute focus,'' she said. ''The key thing is to achieve relaxation, but at the same time you've got to have this absolute total control. You've got to find the balance between being totally ready to go and being really at peace with yourself as well.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CATHY FREEMAN was wonderfully poetic yesterday afternoon as she described the feeling of the final tension-filled seconds before a big race, the feelings shooting through her mind and body as they became one.</p>
        <p>''Twenty seconds before a race, there's absolute focus,'' she said. ''The key thing is to achieve relaxation, but at the same time you've got to have this absolute total control. You've got to find the balance between being totally ready to go and being really at peace with yourself as well.''</p>
        <p>This was Freeman's first news conference since she lighted the Olympic caldron last Friday and became the face of Australia. For the next week, an international audience will home in on Freeman, and she used yesterday's gathering to describe how she zones the world out.</p>
        <p>''Usually your heart's beating really fast,'' said Freeman, who is competing in the 400 meters, of her previous Olympic races in 1992 and '96. ''It feels like your heart's going to jump out of your chest. And it feels like everything around you isn't going on because you're so focused.''</p>
        <p>In this state, Freeman said, the crowd becomes ''this big, living jelly-like thing that's full of color and noise that's sort of going around you.''</p>
        <p>''But you're not really quite sure of what's going on around you,'' she added. ''All I see is the starting blocks and the lane in front of me; all I hear is being told what do -- 'Get your gear off' -- and the starter's command. It's only something you experience before an Olympic race.''</p>
        <p>Even though it was a well-guarded secret, Freeman, 27, said she was asked last April to ignite the caldron. When John Coates, president of the Australian Olympic committee, extended the invitation, Freeman said, she nearly fainted.</p>
        <p>''I was shocked and numbed,'' she said. ''My mind was totally blown away. 'How can I say nay? ''</p>
        <p>Freeman went so far as to tell Coates that she would understand if the committee changed its mind and selected someone else.</p>
        <p>''There were so many who were appropriate, so many gold-medal winners,'' she said. ''I was very honored, very proud. It gave me an extra little bit of incentive to train even harder, if that was possible, than what I already was. Gave me that extra focus, if that was possible.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone was pleased. There were pages of letters in the local newspapers asking why Freeman was chosen.</p>
        <p>The answer may lie in a deeper sense of history that she represents. At the Atlanta Games in 1996, Freeman won silver in the 400 meters, the first Aborigine to win an Olympic medal in an individual event.</p>
        <p>Someone asked Freeman if her lighting the caldron was a call for Aboriginal reconciliation.</p>
        <p>''I don't like to comment on any political issues such as reconciliation,'' she said. ''I know that a lot of people got a kick out of me lighting the flame. I got through it.''</p>
        <p>Though she will compete before a home crowd, as the most highly visible Aborigine, Freeman feels added pressure to represent her people.</p>
        <p>''When I got the flame,'' she said, ''I was really embarrassed because, more than anything, my main focus was being concerned about what other people would think about Cathy Freeman being the one who is lighting the torch and all of the criticism.</p>
        <p>''But all of that went out of my head when I got the flame, and I just felt the absolute energy and emotion coming from all of the people in the stadium.''</p>
        <p>The most important question is: How will Freeman respond to being the hometown heroine? The swimmer Ian Thorpe has done a marvelous job of setting the tone for the Australian Olympic team. Freeman will assume center stage on Friday, when she begins qualifying for the 400, in which she is a favorite. She will also run on the 4x100 relay team and perhaps in the 200.</p>
        <p>The international news media contingent is swarming; everyone has to do the Cathy Freeman story, and everyone must do the Aboriginal story. The scale and magnitude at these Olympics is so much larger than at any other event.</p>
        <p>''I have to admit, the attention is really overwhelming,'' Freeman said. ''I'm such a shy thing, it's hard. But it's part of what this life I have is. I love running, I love competing. It's simple.</p>
        <p>''I'm just really, really determined to have a good time. I don't want this to be stressful. I'll just go out there with a lot of pride in my heart. I just want to go out there and do the best I can, and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>Someone made the comparison between Freeman and Marion Jones of the United States. There's an ocean of difference between them.</p>
        <p>Jones's pressure is self-imposed: she wants to win an unprecedented five gold medals in track and field in the same Olympics. For Freeman the pressure to succeed is coming from a number of places.</p>
        <p>The United States is not counting on Jones or anyone else to be the face it shows to the world.</p>
        <p>In Australia this month, Cathy Freeman is it. Yesterday someone asked Freeman, ''Who are you running for?''</p>
        <p>The question always come up. The answer is always the same: herself, her people, her country.</p>
        <p>''I like to typify any young Aboriginal person in Australia today, where we're living in a country of unity and enjoying the opportunities that are available for everybody,'' Freeman said. ''That's what I'm about. I want to be free to be who I am in my own home.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
