<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vatican Looks to New Cardinals and Papabili</title>
    <meta content="20VATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/world/20VATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000923T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cardinals (Roman Catholic Prelates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">John Paul II (Pope)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Re, Giovanni Battista (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moreira Neves, Lucas (Cardinal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cardinals (Roman Catholic Prelates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4D9153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vatican Looks to New Cardinals and Papabili</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Top Roman Catholic officials at Vatican seem to be working behind closed doors during Holy Year to reorganize top echelons and prepare for future; reassignment of Bishop Giovanni Battista Re, Pope John Paul II's deputy secretary of state, as head of office that selects bishops signals effort; he succeeds Cardinal Lucas Moreira Neves; Vatican is preoccupied with selection of up to 20 new cardinals, probably including Re, who could be both electors and potential papal candidates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Catholics, a Holy Year is a time to make pilgrimages to Rome and throw open the doors of their faith.</p>
        <p>At the Vatican, however, there are signs suggesting that top church officials are working behind closed doors during this Holy Year to reorganize top echelons and prepare for the future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Catholics, a Holy Year is a time to make pilgrimages to Rome and throw open the doors of their faith.</p>
        <p>At the Vatican, however, there are signs suggesting that top church officials are working behind closed doors during this Holy Year to reorganize top echelons and prepare for the future.</p>
        <p>The most glaring signal was the reassignment of a close aide to Pope John Paul II, Bishop Giovanni Battista Re, 66, the deputy secretary of state, whose Vatican job description is akin to that of a White House chief of staff. Last weekend, the bishop, a career Vatican diplomat, was put in charge of the office that selects bishops, a powerful post that will almost certainly result in his elevation to cardinal.</p>
        <p>That administrative reshuffle, which was prompted by the resignation of Cardinal Lucas Moreira Neves, a 75-year-old Brazilian, for reasons of illness, also suggested a deepening awareness of the 80-year-old pope's failing health.</p>
        <p>The number of cardinals under age 80 -- and therefore eligible to vote in a conclave to choose a new pope -- has shrunk to 100, from the maximum 120 allowed. That means that John Paul could soon appoint as many as 20 cardinals who are within the age range to be both electors and potential papal candidates. If Bishop Re is made a cardinal, for instance, he would be eligible to be elected pope, or at least to help shape the election process.</p>
        <p>The busy Holy Year calendar has not deflected preoccupation in the church administration with the cardinal-selection process, which is expected to be completed by February. ''All you hear is talk about cardinals and when they may be named,'' Bishop Joseph Fiorenza of Galveston-Houston said this summer after visiting Vatican offices.</p>
        <p>The reassignment of Bishop Re, moreover, has prompted Italian reporters to re-handicap the race among ''papabili,'' the Italian word for candidates who could be elected pope. In its Sunday issue, the daily newspaper La Repubblica printed a giant chart dividing major cardinals into seven conclave categories, including ''moderates,'' ''third world'' and ''traditionalists.''</p>
        <p>Vaticanisti, as Italian experts on the subject call themselves, have long debated whether the cardinals, building on the precedent of a Polish pope, would move toward electing a candidate from Africa, Latin America or Asia, or whether they would return to an Italian. But the oft-cited battle between so-called liberals and conservatives inside the Vatican may be a bit of an exaggeration. John Paul has appointed almost all of the current cardinals, and they share his basic views.</p>
        <p>John Paul, however, shows no signs of winding down his mission after the Holy Year comes to a close, Vatican officials say. In recent weeks, plans have been floated for the pope to visit Armenia either this year or in early 2001. The Vatican secretary of state, Cardinal Angelo Sodano, said last week that the pope wanted to resurrect his plan to make a pilgrimage to Ur, a holy city in Iraq, a trip that was canceled in December after the Iraqi government withdrew its consent.</p>
        <p>But there were other recent signs in the Vatican that the pope's closest advisers are seeking to nail down his legacy. Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger, who directs the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, issued a stern 36-page document this month on the primacy of the Roman Catholic Church, which declared that it cannot be any group's ''sister church'' because that would imply a ''plurality.'' And it said non-Christian religions, while holding out the possibility of divine grace, ''are in a gravely deficient situation in comparison with those who in the church, have the fullness of the means of salvation.''</p>
        <p>To some, the document seemed to deflate the pope's bold efforts to further ecumenicism and interfaith dialogue, most notably with his silent prayer at the Western Wall in Jerusalem last March. The document offended many leaders of other churches, who saw it as a tactless step backward.</p>
        <p>John Paul, who on Monday opened a joint commission on dialogue between Catholics and the World Alliance of Reformed Churches, did not allude to any change in his own thinking, saying, ''The commitment of the Catholic Church to ecumenical dialogue is irrevocable.''</p>
        <p>Mostly, the Ratzinger document was aimed at Catholic theologians who have sought to reduce the distinctions between different faiths. The day before issuing the document, the Rev. Jacques Dupuis, a French Jesuit, was summoned before Cardinal Ratzinger, whose office was once called the Holy Inquisition.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Father Dupuis was ordered to stop teaching at the Pontifical Gregorian University in Rome, after Cardinal Ratzinger opened a heresy investigation into his book, ''Toward a Christian Theology of Religious Pluralism.'' The investigation has not yet published a conclusion, but the cardinal's document hinted at the probable outcome.</p>
        <p>But as Vatican officials lay down the law, other Catholic institutions have been searching for signs of change. America, a Jesuit magazine published in New York, this month ran an article suggesting that the Vatican was growing more tolerant about the use of condoms to combat the spread of AIDS.</p>
        <p>The authors, John D. Fuller and James F. Keegan, drew on an article by a French Vatican official, Jacques Suaudeau, published in the Vatican newspaper, L'Osservatore Romano, in April. It condemned the use of condoms to fight AIDS but allowed that in Thailand, the government's distribution of condoms to prostitutes to contain the spread of H.I.V. was a ''lesser evil,'' though it ''cannot be proposed as a model of humanization and development.''</p>
        <p>Reached in his Vatican office, Father Suaudeau insisted that his article did not seek to enlarge church teaching, but simply to explain it. He said his article reiterated the church's stance that abstinence before marriage and conjugal fidelity remain the only effective method for preventing AIDS.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand why people want to interpret what I stated clearly in my article,'' Father Suaudeau said with a sigh. ''But there is no change in church teaching.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 23, 2000, Saturday  An article on Wednesday about reassignments at the Vatican misspelled the given name of one co-author of an article in the Jesuit magazine America that suggested that the Vatican was growing more tolerant about the use of condoms to combat the spread of AIDS, and misspelled the surname of the other. The authors are the Rev. Jon D. Fuller (not John) and the Rev. James F. Keenan (not Keegan).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 23, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Wednesday about reassignments at the Vatican misspelled the given name of one co-author of an article in the Jesuit magazine America that suggested that the Vatican was growing more tolerant about the use of condoms to combat the spread of AIDS, and misspelled the surname of the other. The authors are the Rev. Jon D. Fuller (not John) and the Rev. James F. Keenan (not Keegan).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
