<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killer Toys and Wonder Woman: When a Soft Sell Is a Big Deal</title>
    <meta content="20SMIT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center for Exhibition Industry Research</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D71739F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killer Toys and Wonder Woman: When a Soft Sell Is a Big Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Nev.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Center for Exhibition Industry Research says that in $84 billion-a-year commercial exhibition business, high technology ranks third among major industries that allocate large part of their marketing dollars to trade shows and conferences; at 18 percent, high technology trails health care at 21.3 percent and manufacturing at 18.6 percent; photos (special section, E-Commerce) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIS angular ivory face framed by the upturned collar of a black magician's cape, Gary Norcigian cut a monochromatic figure amid the technicolor of the convention floor. It was as if Grandpa from ''The Munsters'' somehow wandered onto the set of ''The Wizard of Oz.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Norcigian attracted a small knot of conventiongoers, goatee-wearing software developers with sleepy eyes and overloaded tote bags. Ambushing a bystander, he used the man's wristwatch for an overly dramatic series of sleight-of-hand tricks. Then the crowd dispersed among the exhibits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIS angular ivory face framed by the upturned collar of a black magician's cape, Gary Norcigian cut a monochromatic figure amid the technicolor of the convention floor. It was as if Grandpa from ''The Munsters'' somehow wandered onto the set of ''The Wizard of Oz.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Norcigian attracted a small knot of conventiongoers, goatee-wearing software developers with sleepy eyes and overloaded tote bags. Ambushing a bystander, he used the man's wristwatch for an overly dramatic series of sleight-of-hand tricks. Then the crowd dispersed among the exhibits.</p>
        <p>''The only thing that counts is stopping traffic next to your booth,'' said Mr. Norcigian, who works dozens of trade shows and conferences each year. ''The best traffic-stopper you can get is a female contortionist. People find it perversely interesting and can't resist staring.''</p>
        <p>No contortionists here, but a cluster of female impersonators wandering among the 4,000 attendees of the conference sponsored by I.B.M. had the same mesmerizing effect. It was an extravaganza that seemed to cross-pollinate graduate-level computer science courses with equal parts hospitality suite and Lollapalooza rock concert.</p>
        <p>''I'm here to create visual excitement,'' said John Gonzales, who was flawlessly dressed as Wonder Woman and handing out coupons for a digital music player giveaway to attendees huddled around steam trays of meatballs. ''Honestly, I don't even know what an MP3 player is,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Bungee jumps. Poetry slams. Radio-controlled model car races. Holographic projections of severed heads beckoning passers-by to a booth. This is trench warfare in the ''attention economy,'' where companies vie to win fleeting consideration among software developers who will determine the architecture of electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>''Back when the people making purchasing decisions were the chairmen of banks, Wall Street firms, insurance companies, manufacturers, you tried to look like them and be of their culture,'' said Bob Timpson, who started at I.B.M. more than 30 years ago, when employees were required to wear suit jackets at their desks. ''We're doing the same thing now. Today, those decisions are not being made by C.E.O.'s and C.I.O.'s. They are being made down in the depths of organizations by people of this software culture. You have to talk to them where they live, on the Web, and then draw them out to places where they can mingle.''</p>
        <p>Hence, this ''real world'' creation of I.B.M.'s software developer Web site, a spectacle-saturated conference highlighting technology from I.B.M. and its business partners at the MGM Grand Hotel unabashedly dubbed ''No Limits: Building the Open E-Business Universe.'' Between training sessions with arcane titles and keynote speeches from techno-dreamers and specialized ''evangelists,'' attendees were treated to rock guitar solos, belly dancers, disco parties, salsa bands, comedians and performance artists decrying computer hardware that ''has the life expectancy of wooden stirrers at Starbucks.''</p>
        <p>''These computer trade shows look nothing like they did five years ago,'' said Albert Segars, director of the Institute of Technology and Strategic Change at the University of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''They now look more like Cirque du Soleil, with trapeze artists, mimes, magic,'' Mr. Segars said. ''It's all about who can outhype the other, who has the biggest celebrity, who has the coolest giveaways.''</p>
        <p>In the $84 billion-a-year commercial exhibition business, high technology ranks third among major industries that allocate a large part of their marketing dollars to trade shows and conferences, according to the Center for Exhibition Industry Research in Chicago. At 18 percent, high technology trails health care at 21.3 percent and manufacturing at 18.6 percent. But on the hype meter, high-technology trade shows bury the needle.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Segars cautioned that companies hoping to solicit business through gimmicks or attractive ''booth bunnies'' must be able to deliver more than ''vaporware,'' much-promoted applications that are months or years from release.</p>
        <p>''These exhibitors have to retain an underlying theme of credibility because the kids in software development can see right through the smoke and mirrors,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These days, he said, companies are staffing exhibits with people knowledgeable about the products.</p>
        <p>''I've noticed the saleswomen now at these shows,'' Mr. Segars said, ''seem to be more like pharmaceutical reps, with an attractiveness or appeal, but lingering behind that is real industry expertise.''</p>
        <p>As part of a campaign for ''relationship acquisition'' among software engineers, I.B.M. hired a cultural anthropologist to create psychological profiles of how the fiercely independent developer community thinks.</p>
        <p>''They're primarily male, and, because they are smart, as a whole they have paranoid tendencies,'' said Chris Bahr, who directs I.B.M.'s Developer Works, a Web site that offers software entrepreneurs tools and techniques for creating applications. ''They are very hard to fool and almost impossible to market to. If they feel they are being sold to, they are out of here.''</p>
        <p>They are also merciless in their critiques of traditional brick-and-mortar corporations, including the magnanimous host that has courted them with T-shirts, backpacks and a perpetually open bar. The longest commentary string on the conference computer network billboard is a diatribe over the slow speed and unreliability of the I.B.M. system on site. The original posting described it with an expletive, and subsequent replies went downhill from there.</p>
        <p>''They are not restrained in showing their opinions,'' Mr. Timpson of I.B.M. said. ''We're willing to subject our technology to flame mail, harsh and adverse criticism, so that we can create the best of the breed. There's a lot of extreme hype out there, but at the end of the day, people respect performance and results.''</p>
        <p>And honesty. When Al Zollar, president and chief executive of the Lotus Development Corporation, which I.B.M. bought in 1995, opened an address by saying, ''This is a developer crowd, and I know you don't like talking to people,'' heads in the audience nodded in agreement.</p>
        <p>But human interaction seems to be the primary desire at these county fairs for denizens of the faceless digital economy. There is an air of high school prom expectancy about the gatherings, where gangly, awkward e-business chief executives wander around hoping to chat up a ''rock star V.C.,'' venture-capitalist speculators who bankroll start-ups.</p>
        <p>''What happens in a lot of these dot-com cases is the head of the company is more socially challenged and really doesn't like to be at these events, but they know if they don't learn those skills, they may ultimately fall back into the role of chief technical officer,'' Mr. Segars said. ''When the V.C.'s get involved, if they have someone in charge of the company who doesn't have good business sense, knowing what to say when, they usually shuffle them back into the C.T.O. role and bring in a new C.E.O.''</p>
        <p>In the argot of Silicon Valley, participating in computer conferences helps stimulate ''deal flow,'' the progression from idea to initial public offering.</p>
        <p>''I can't tell you how many deals I've gotten from people who heard me speak at MacWorld 10 years ago,'' said the chief executive of Garage.com, Guy Kawasaki, a former Macintosh computer guru whose company helps dot-com enterprises find start-up capital.</p>
        <p>Yet the booming popularity of these bacchanal computer conferences and trade shows is not solely for profit's sake. On another level, they fill a need for face-to-face contact among a notoriously isolated workforce.</p>
        <p>''Geeks need community, too,'' Mr. Bahr said.</p>
        <p>And no matter how flush with vested stock options, developers apparently still need to fill suitcases with giveaway trinkets that are the signature souvenirs of trade shows.</p>
        <p>''Nowadays, people attending these shows expect to be entertained and go home with a ton of freebies,'' said Susan Ratliff, author of ''How to Be an Exhibit Expert'' and president of a Phoenix firm that creates trade show displays. ''They act like kids.''</p>
        <p>Within two hours of opening the doors of the hangar-sized exhibition floor, the ''killer toy'' had been identified by a stampede of techies. It was a palm-sized foam rubber locomotive with a sound card that emits ''choo-choo'' noises when squeezed, the most prized of dozens of similar rubber statuary passed off as ''stress relief'' devices by vendors.</p>
        <p>''These are the bonus items,'' said Curtis Cartmill, a Canadian software engineer, revealing the contents of his goody bag like a triumphant trick-or-treater. ''We are acquiring knowledge here, but we are also acquiring a few projectiles.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Waespe, a colleague, added: ''Someone at work will yell 'war' and you've got to have projectiles to retaliate. This is like an arms show for cubicle wars.''</p>
        <p>Some Survival Tips For E-Conventions</p>
        <p>UNMUZZLED exhibitry can be intimidating to rookies. Here are a few tips on survival:</p>
        <p>''Remember, look like you have purchasing authority,'' advised Benn Konsynski, a business professor at Emory University. ''And don't make eye contact. It's a sign of weakness.''</p>
        <p>Do say you ''forgot'' your business cards. ''That way, no one can bug you after the conference,'' said Nancy Anderson Smith of MQ Software. Follow-up contact avoidance is more difficult for vendors. ''If you're an exhibitor, remember 10 percent of the population is plagued by mental illness.''</p>
        <p>Do ask others at the show for attraction advice. ''Every show has five 'must see' innovations and word gets out after the first day where these are,'' Mr. Konsynski said.</p>
        <p>Don't hesitate to grab the shiny giveaway baubles without enduring a sales demonstration. ''The sales reps want you to take them because if you don't, they have to lug them back home on the plane,'' said Albert Segars, an e-commerce researcher at the University of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHER SMITH</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS Christopher Smith is a regional reporter for The Salt Lake Tribune in Utah.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Christopher Smith is a regional reporter for The Salt Lake Tribune in Utah.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
