<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Sign Florida Is Now in Play, Bush Increases Buying There</title>
    <meta content="20ADS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/politics/20ADS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstein, Ken (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EED7153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Sign Florida Is Now in Play, Bush Increases Buying There</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New study finds Gov George W Bush and Republican Party have vigorously stepped up advertising efforts in Florida in recent weeks, outspending Democrats on television there by over $2 million; analysts say large spending reflects close race in state viewed as crucial to Bush and earlier viewed as state Bush was likely to win; study, by Prof Ken Goldstein, finds Republicans have bought advertising time massively in last two weeks in many contested markets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Underscoring how crucial and competitive the race for president has become in Florida, Gov. George W. Bush and the Republican Party have vigorously stepped up their advertising efforts in the state in recent weeks and have outspent the Democrats on television there by more than $2 million, a new study shows.</p>
        <p>The large Republican expenditure is significant, analysts say, because polls indicate that the state, viewed as vital to Mr. Bush's chances of winning the presidency, is now a tossup. And though both parties have been advertising in Florida all summer, it did not figure prominently in the early calculations about those states seriously up for grabs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Underscoring how crucial and competitive the race for president has become in Florida, Gov. George W. Bush and the Republican Party have vigorously stepped up their advertising efforts in the state in recent weeks and have outspent the Democrats on television there by more than $2 million, a new study shows.</p>
        <p>The large Republican expenditure is significant, analysts say, because polls indicate that the state, viewed as vital to Mr. Bush's chances of winning the presidency, is now a tossup. And though both parties have been advertising in Florida all summer, it did not figure prominently in the early calculations about those states seriously up for grabs.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised by the magnitude of what I saw in Florida,'' said Ken Goldstein, a political science professor at the University of Wisconsin who is tracking expenditures for political commercials in the top 75 markets, which encompass 80 percent of the nation's population.</p>
        <p>Partly because of Florida's frequent support for Republican presidential candidates and partly because its governor, Jeb Bush, is Mr. Bush's brother, the state was initially thought to be in the Republican column.</p>
        <p>Strategists on both sides say that where the national parties and candidates choose to run commercials in heavy rotation often indicates which states are the most competitive. For much of the summer, both parties' advertisements have concentrated on 17 to 20 battleground states, including Michigan, Missouri, Ohio and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also recently ran commercials for about 10 days in North Carolina, Mr. Goldstein and Republicans there say. North Carolina had been viewed as safe for Mr. Bush. ''It's an insurance policy,'' Dan Gurley, political director of the North Carolina Republican Party, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein, who is analyzing and releasing the advertising data in a project with the Brennan Center for Justice at the New York University School of Law, said that the Republicans have ''bought massively'' in the last two weeks in many contested markets.</p>
        <p>The advertising buy in Miami, he said, had created a particularly sharp disparity between the Bush and Gore campaigns. The most recent buys have raised the Republicans' expenditures there to $1.8 million since June, while Vice President Al Gore and the Democrats have spent just $125,000 in the period.</p>
        <p>As of Sept. 14, Mr. Bush and the Republican Party spent about $4.8 million in the state, and Mr. Gore and the Democrats about $2.7 million. Across the nation, Mr. Goldstein said, the increased Republican spending since the conventions has brought the two parties to approximate parity. In other markets, like Philadelphia and Detroit, it was Mr. Gore who was outspending Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The figures were tabulated by the Campaign Media Analysis Group, a company retained by news organizations and other institutions to track and calculate the advertising expenditures across the country.</p>
        <p>Democrats in Florida contend that Republicans were caught off guard by Mr. Gore's strong showing in recent polls, and that moves like his selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman as his running mate lifted the ticket's fortunes.</p>
        <p>''Al Gore owns the momentum now in Florida,'' asserted Tony Welch, a spokesman for the Florida Democratic Party. ''The language of this race has changed. It has gone from 'Maybe it's in play' to 'Definitely, it's a horse race.' ''</p>
        <p>Republican officials acknowledged that they had increased their focus on Florida. But they maintained that their advertising was a response to unfair efforts by Mr. Gore to alarm Florida voters about Mr. Bush's proposals about health care and Social Security.</p>
        <p>''Florida is a swing state, and it's a state in which Al Gore and other Democrats have reverted to their 'Medi-scare' tactics,'' said Clifford D. May, communications director for the Republican National Committee. ''We will use our resources to tell voters the truth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. May also contended that the Democrats, for their part, are also advertising heavily in some states that should be considered reliable for them, like Washington and Oregon. Both states' electoral votes went to the Democrats in 1992 and 1996.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
