<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why This Consumer Giant Isn't About to Sell to Consumers</title>
    <meta content="20BARB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TO BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D81139F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why This Consumer Giant Isn't About to Sell to Consumers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CINCINNATI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble Co is investing in Internet exchanges to make its factories more efficient; it hopes that work of chemists in Health Care Research Center in Mason, Ohio, can be combined with Web site to create products personalized to customer's tastes; photos (special section, E-Commerce) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS consumers gravitate to the Web, more and more are expecting retailers to deliver highly specialized packages -- books, clothing, compact discs, software -- to their doors.</p>
        <p>Some consumers would even pay a premium for delivery of groceries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS consumers gravitate to the Web, more and more are expecting retailers to deliver highly specialized packages -- books, clothing, compact discs, software -- to their doors.</p>
        <p>Some consumers would even pay a premium for delivery of groceries.</p>
        <p>So you might think a giant like Procter &amp; Gamble, with a $40-billion-a-year stable of popular brands like Scope, Tide, Pampers and Crest, would be rushing to get in on the action -- to reinvent itself as a dot-com, bypassing retailers and going directly to consumers through the Internet.</p>
        <p>Think again. Companies like P.&amp; G. are keenly aware of the need to be in cyberspace (or anywhere their customers happen to be), and they know that home delivery is a fast-growing part of the market. But few experts said that online commerce would ever replace bricks and mortar -- especially for unglamorous staples like hair spray, soap and toothpaste. Instead, they expected companies like Procter to invest more heavily in business-to-business applications.</p>
        <p>''Our estimates are that there'll never be more than 10 percent of groceries sold online,'' said Evie Black Dykema, an analyst at Forrester Research in Cambridge, Mass. ''There'll be lots of specialty items online -- Indian spices and Pepperidge Farm cookies. But Bounty paper? Not a chance.''</p>
        <p>Consumers are also searching for more information on the products they use or intend to use and that is forcing everyone, including consumer product giants, to have a presence on the Web.</p>
        <p>Here at Procter &amp; Gamble's sprawling headquarters, officials said that for all its promise, the Internet held nothing compelling enough to justify destroying relations with retailers or overhauling a colossal distribution system.</p>
        <p>Instead, executives have concluded that the best route to continued success is to travel as many high-technology roads as possible. When it comes to the Internet, the company's motto might be ''Experiment, experiment, experiment.''</p>
        <p>So over the last year, Procter has moved aggressively to forge relationships with the online grocers Webvan Group Inc. and HomeGrocer.com Inc. It has also created its own venture capital arm to invest in Internet start-ups, allowing it to tiptoe into new product lines.</p>
        <p>Procter is teaming up with popular Web sites, like iVillage.com and Women.com, to promote its beauty and health care products. It is rolling out new brands online, seeking consumer reaction before the items reach store shelves. And it is using the Web to gather information about consumers.</p>
        <p>Procter has also joined other consumer-products giants, like Coca-Cola and Sara Lee, in a business-to-business Internet exchange that seeks to use their combined weight to reduce the costs of buying materials and shipping goods.</p>
        <p>And the company is using the Internet to induce better cooperation among its 8,500 researchers and scientists, who spend about $1.8 billion a year on research and development.</p>
        <p>In rejecting the idea of shipping directly to consumers, executives and analysts cited buying patterns and market relationships that they said were too durable to be displaced by the Internet.</p>
        <p>It would be suicidal, they said, to spend billions of dollars to build distribution networks to compete with the likes of Wal-Mart, Kmart and Target, just for the privilege of wrapping $3 and $5 items individually and shipping them to consumers.</p>
        <p>''P.&amp; G.'s primary customers right now are the big mass retailers, and so if you go direct you compete with them,'' said William Steele, a consumer products analyst at Banc of America Securities. ''Wal-Mart has 2,800 stores. If you decide to ship case one of Tide directly to consumers, you get yourself thrown out of 2,800 stores. Why would you do that?''</p>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble's distribution system is geared to shipping in bulk to warehouses and retail outlets. To overhaul that system in favor of one that is more splintered would be inefficient and costly, executives said. Nor is there evidence that consumers are clamoring for the service.</p>
        <p>''We've done extensive research,'' said Stephen N. David, the company's chief information officer. ''We find consumers want aggregation; they don't want a box of Tide coming in the afternoon.''</p>
        <p>Of course, companies like Procter know that change is constant and that technological developments could someday force them to go straight to consumers.</p>
        <p>Executives worry that the Web's interactive and open format could give a big advantage to more nimble and inventive competitors.</p>
        <p>So like other companies, Procter is hedging its bets. It is investing heavily not just in working with Web companies but also in creating and tracking Web developments.</p>
        <p>IVentures, the venture capital fund Procter started this year, has bought stakes in half a dozen companies, typically with investments of $2 million to $5 million. The idea is to find additional outlets for products and to help Procter better understand where the Internet is headed.</p>
        <p>''This is also helping change the culture of P.&amp; G. because start-ups are leading edge,'' said Richard Kiley, the head of  iVentures. ''We're putting general managers and vice presidents on the boards of companies so they observe.''</p>
        <p>One of Procter &amp; Gamble's biggest forays onto the Web came a year ago, when it invested $35 million in its own Silicon Valley start-up, Reflect.com, devoted to creating custom beauty products.</p>
        <p>The company goes where Procter is not ready to go: not only does it manufacture products, it also ships them to consumers. The way executives at Reflect.com explain it, the company is almost the antithesis of its parent.</p>
        <p>''When a consumer-products company does testing on a new product, it has to meet the needs of a large group; they throw out what doesn't meet the broad needs of people,'' said Richard Gerstein, a vice president for design and marketing at Reflect.com in San Francisco. ''With us, a woman comes online, answers a set of questions, and then we help her create a product just for her.''</p>
        <p>Reflect.com is a kind of laboratory for Procter &amp; Gamble, a window into an online future in which the cosmetics industry could shift from generic, mass-produced scents, colors and brands toward more expensive, highly individual ones.</p>
        <p>It is even possible that biotechnology will enable companies to use a person's genetic blueprint to match skin, body and hair types with the right product.</p>
        <p>Executives at Procter said that for all the emphasis on the mass market, on shipping truckloads of one-size-fits-all products to the Wal-Marts of the world, they were preparing for a day when custom products are  more than a niche market. It is a possibility that could upset some of their moves toward greater efficiency through giant manufacturing plants and distribution depots.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Procter &amp; Gamble has introduced two products on the Web: Physique, a line of shampoos, conditioners, gels, mousses, creams and lotions; and a Crest whitening strip that bleaches teeth. Both products were started with Web sites, advertising and free samples.</p>
        <p>The company said that the Web was an ideal tool for direct marketing and communicating with consumers who want to know about new products or ask questions about existing ones.</p>
        <p>''Why spend time pushing at consumers who aren't interested?'' asked David Worth, the associate director for information technology.</p>
        <p>But for Procter &amp; Gamble, which is basically a business-to-business company selling to big retailers, the Web's most promising aspect may lie in the savings that could result from teaming with other companies to create a more efficient procurement and distribution network.</p>
        <p>The network, Transora, is to begin operating this year. Its members -- including Coca-Cola, Sara Lee, Kraft, PepsiCo and Gillette, along with Procter &amp; Gamble -- will try to leverage their size in obtaining better prices for raw materials and share data to find less expensive and more efficient ways to ship products and track inventory. And they are expected to work more closely with retailers to root out inefficiencies.</p>
        <p>''Billions of dollars are wasted in inefficiencies every year,'' said Judith Sprieser, the chief executive of Transora, which is based in Chicago. ''There are estimates that we carry too much inventory in our supply chain because we don't know what's going to be purchased.''</p>
        <p>The alliance shows that online commerce is changing the rules of the marketplace even if most consumers never abandon their supermarkets and shopping malls.</p>
        <p>''The winner in the future is going to be the one who can mobilize the best access to information and make the best use of it,'' Ms. Sprieser said. ''And they'll all have fewer clerks correcting invoice errors.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TO BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
