<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out-of-Favor Americans Start Playing With an Edge</title>
    <meta content="20BASK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: MEN'S BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D7143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out-of-Favor Americans Start Playing With an Edge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US defeats Italy, 93-61, in men's basketball at Sydney Olympics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Gates paid the United States men's basketball players a visit in their locker room tonight, moments after another nettlesome competitor tried to toy with their global monopoly.</p>
        <p>Gates did not commiserate with the American multimillionaires about high taxes. But with all these uppity foreign opponents grabbing at their jerseys and making the superior Americans come across as bullies when they retaliate, the kinship is natural.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Gates paid the United States men's basketball players a visit in their locker room tonight, moments after another nettlesome competitor tried to toy with their global monopoly.</p>
        <p>Gates did not commiserate with the American multimillionaires about high taxes. But with all these uppity foreign opponents grabbing at their jerseys and making the superior Americans come across as bullies when they retaliate, the kinship is natural.</p>
        <p>''These guys don't even ask for autographs anymore,'' Gary Payton lamented after Italy begrudgingly lost to the United States, 93-61.</p>
        <p>World domination is clearly beginning to wear on the Americans, who won the game but hardly failed to win over the crowd of 8,368 at the Dome in Olympic Park.</p>
        <p>Yes, Vince Carter threw down a tremendous alley-oop dunk in the first half, which left the fans in a state of disbelief. And with 22 points off the fast break, the Americans entertained everyone.</p>
        <p>But the masses jeered in the second half when Carter and the feisty Italian guard Alessandro Abbio grabbed and held each other until Carter planted a forearm on Abbio's throat and knocked him down.</p>
        <p>Coach Rudy Tomjanovich quickly sicced a full-court press on the defiant Italians with less than nine minutes left. The score at the time: 78-46.</p>
        <p>Team USA apparently feels it does not merely have to win; it must win so convincingly that not a single soul comes away with the notion that the team was ever in trouble. ''There are good international players,'' Tomjanovich began matter-of-factly, ''but the other countries don't have 12 of them on the same team.''</p>
        <p>An ornery resilience is creeping into international play, though. You can see it in each game the Americans play. Whether they have been watching Heat-Knicks playoff contests on tape is unclear, but somewhere Italy and the other nations are beginning to learn the art of the well-placed elbow in the small of the back.</p>
        <p>From the opening tip, when Italy's best player, Gregor Fucka, caught Alonzo Mourning with an open hand to the face, the Italians showed none of the great respect afforded other teams made up of National Basketball Association players in international play.</p>
        <p>Payton, Carter and Kevin Garnett took the physical challenge to heart, going at their opponents hard. It was not uncommon to see the 7-foot Garnett bodying up his man near halfcourt, trying any tactic to take the ball away.</p>
        <p>Garnett, the Minnesota Timberwolves' All-Star, bristled at one reporter's suggestion that the Americans should again send college players to the Olympics to make the competition fair.</p>
        <p>''It's like fighting,'' Garnett said. ''I get my five. You get your five from the neighborhood. I'm going to try and find the grimiest, dirtiest cats I can.''</p>
        <p>That is how the gold-medal pursuit is apparently going to go. With three preliminary games left, the United States is 2-0 in Group A. Italy is 1-1.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Carter was the game's leading scorer with 13 points, Mourning added 12 points and 6 blocked shots and Jason Kidd contributed 7 assists for the United States.</p>
        <p>In the first half, Carter rose for an alley-oop pass from Garnett on the left side of the rim. The ball was out of his reach, so he waited for it to come off the backboard before slamming it through for the cameras.</p>
        <p>Even Abbio was impressed by Carter, despite the forearm to the throat. ''A wonderful personality,'' he said through a translator. ''He is a special player.''</p>
        <p>Proof that the only incredible news the United States can make is to somehow lose, the crowd cheered wildly for the Italians as they held on for most of the first half. They came within 35-33 with less than three minutes left. Then Allan Houston, making his Olympic debut after jamming his right wrist and missing the first game, connected on two 3-pointers before the half ended, and the less talented but unfawning Italians never challenged again.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: MEN'S BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
