<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Deaths Are Attributed To Faulty Firestone Tires</title>
    <meta content="Y20TIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/business/20TIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D9153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Deaths Are Attributed To Faulty Firestone Tires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Highway Traffic Safety Administration says that since Aug 31 it has received complaints of 15 more deaths attributed to Firestone tires on sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks, raising to 103 the number of deaths under review (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal regulators announced this evening that since Aug. 31 they had received complaints of 15 more deaths attributed to Firestone tires on sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks, raising to 103 the number of deaths under review.</p>
        <p>Officials at the regulatory agency, the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, cautioned that they had not determined how many of the complaints involved tires that had actually failed. The agency accepts complaints from consumers, lawyers, manufacturers and law enforcement agencies, and has not had time to investigate each complaint, officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal regulators announced this evening that since Aug. 31 they had received complaints of 15 more deaths attributed to Firestone tires on sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks, raising to 103 the number of deaths under review.</p>
        <p>Officials at the regulatory agency, the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, cautioned that they had not determined how many of the complaints involved tires that had actually failed. The agency accepts complaints from consumers, lawyers, manufacturers and law enforcement agencies, and has not had time to investigate each complaint, officials said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, today's release of the data was delayed as the safety agency sifted through the 2,226 complaints it had received to determine how many were duplicates of deaths previously reported to investigators. While the agency concluded, after eliminating duplicates, that there were complaints about 103 deaths, it simply estimated the number of injuries as ''more than 400 reported injuries.''</p>
        <p>Firestone recalled 14.4 million light truck tires on Aug. 9, of which 6.5 million are still believed to be in use. Two-thirds of the tires were mounted on Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles as factory equipment, while the rest were either installed on other Ford light truck models or were sold in the replacement tire market. Most of the deaths cited in complaints to regulators have occurred in Explorers, and almost all of them involved a rollover after a tire shed its tread during high-speed driving.</p>
        <p>As the inquiry continued, Continental A.G., Germany's leading tire maker, announced today that it would replace 160,000 tires mounted mostly on Lincoln Navigator sport utility vehicles, but would do so as part of a ''customer satisfaction program'' and not a safety recall.</p>
        <p>Bernd Frangenberg, the chief executive and president of Continental General Tire Inc., the American unit of Continental A.G., said that the company had received only one report of a tire-related injury, which he described as a ''minor injury'' in Florida two weeks ago that was still being reviewed.</p>
        <p>Continental announced the tire replacement program after meeting with regulators this morning at the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, which is part of the Transportation Department. Tim Hurd, a spokesman for the agency, confirmed that the agency had not required Continental to replace the tires as part of a safety recall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frangenberg said that regulators had not actually ruled against a safety recall, however, and that regulators ''reserved the right to ask for more information.''</p>
        <p>Safety recalls tend to hurt a company's legal standing if it is sued, although Continental said it was not in litigation as a result of the tires.</p>
        <p>Continental is replacing the first 160,000 ContiTrac AS tires it produced of the P245/75R16 size. About 20,000 of these tires were sold in the replacement market, while the Ford Motor Company installed the rest on 1998 and 1999 Navigators, Mr. Frangenberg said. A problem in some tires can cause the vehicles to vibrate and sometimes cause pieces of the tread to break off, but the entire tread does not peel off, he added.</p>
        <p>Treads that peel off entirely and without warning during highway driving have been blamed for dozens of deaths in Ford Explorers equipped with Firestone tires.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Representative Billy Tauzin, the Louisiana Republican leading a House Commerce Committee inquiry on the Firestone problem, accused Firestone today of having known since 1996 about quality problems with the tires now being recalled. The spokesman, Ken Johnson, said that investigators poring through tire test data submitted by Firestone had found a high rate of test failures during routine quality control tests conducted in 1996, and a notation that a tire manufacturing process was changed in 1997 as a result.</p>
        <p>Julia Sutherland, a Firestone spokeswoman, said the company had found in 1996 that the sidewalls of some tires had failed in tests. But the sidewall problem was unrelated to the tread separations now blamed for many accidents, she said.</p>
        <p>Firestone was not aware of sidewall problems occurring on tires actually out on the streets, but still made changes so that the sidewall problem stopped showing up in the company's tests, Ms. Sutherland said, adding that, ''It is not a failure we saw in the real world, but we saw it in the test and we corrected the problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
