<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lyrically and Reverently Blessing the Stage Manager</title>
    <meta content="20GLOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/arts/20GLOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glorsky, Maxine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D9143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lyrically and Reverently Blessing the Stage Manager</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews dance program at Joyce Theater that is tribute to longtime dance stage manager Maxine Glorsky (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those who labor backstage are seldom acknowledged in the theater. But colleagues of Maxine Glorsky, the longtime dance stage manager, paid tribute to her last Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater in an impressively produced program of witty reminiscences and good dance by seasoned performers and choreographers who worked with her. And she made a gesture of her own.</p>
        <p>The evening, organized by the dancers Richard Daniels, Rebecca Rigert and Vernon Scott and the lighting designer Clifton Taylor, opened with just the right lyrical benediction from Lori Belilove in Isadora Duncan's ''Blue Danube.'' Next came a flamelike excerpt from Nancy Turano's ''Carmen,'' its three Carmens danced with stylized passion by Benedetta Capanna, I-Fang Huang and Ms. Turano. Scott Rink contributed a duet, which he danced with Lenna Parr, that was an earthy yet mysterious embrace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those who labor backstage are seldom acknowledged in the theater. But colleagues of Maxine Glorsky, the longtime dance stage manager, paid tribute to her last Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater in an impressively produced program of witty reminiscences and good dance by seasoned performers and choreographers who worked with her. And she made a gesture of her own.</p>
        <p>The evening, organized by the dancers Richard Daniels, Rebecca Rigert and Vernon Scott and the lighting designer Clifton Taylor, opened with just the right lyrical benediction from Lori Belilove in Isadora Duncan's ''Blue Danube.'' Next came a flamelike excerpt from Nancy Turano's ''Carmen,'' its three Carmens danced with stylized passion by Benedetta Capanna, I-Fang Huang and Ms. Turano. Scott Rink contributed a duet, which he danced with Lenna Parr, that was an earthy yet mysterious embrace.</p>
        <p>Janie Brendel claimed the stage with formidable delicacy in an excerpt from Peggy Baker's ''Her Heart.'' As strong were the presences of Dirk Platzek and Christine Wright, a performer of exquisite acuity, in a clinging duet from Zvi Gotheiner's ''Amber Room.''</p>
        <p>Four members of the Joyce Trisler Danscompany injected a dose of revivifying old-time modern-dance force and grandeur in an excerpt from Trisler's ''Four Against the Gods,'' performed by Cathleen Sweeney, Jocelyn Soulet, Dana Parrott and Regina Larkin. And Elisa Monte and David Brown came out of retirement for an excerpt, danced with affecting power and simplicity, from Ms. Monte's ''Treading.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rigert and Mr. Platzek were iconic figures, tethered yet airborne, in a duet from Lar Lubovitch's ''Meadow.'' Ms. Glorsky took the stage on video in Nuria Olive-Belles's ''Voice Amidst the Wings,'' an affectionate, revealing look at the woman, her profession and the dance history she has witnessed firsthand in her 40 years on the job.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baker, big, bold and invincible in her solo ''Words Fail,'' was followed amusingly by three offhand, flighty temptresses in Amy O'Brien's ''Vessel,'' performed by Raquel Aedo, Emily Coates and Emmanuele Phuon of the White Oak Dance Project. Richard Daniels allowed every moment to breathe in his ''Ghazi.'' And eight members of Buglisi/Foreman Dance ended the evening with a ballroom dance from Donlin Foreman's ''Last Call'' that was like a gentle wave goodbye.</p>
        <p>The musicians who performed live were the singer Jack Donohue and the instrumentalists Jono Mainelli, John Gavalchin, Shauna Rolston and Pedja Muzijevic. The speakers included an impassioned Mr. Lubovitch and an urbane Glen Tetley, with Ms. Rigert reading a message from Carmen de Lavallade. Ms. Glorsky also spoke briefly, calling an obviously surprised Marguerite Mehler, the evening's young stage manager, out for a bow of her own.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
