<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full of Banter, Bush Goes On the 'Oprah' Circuit</title>
    <meta content="20BUSH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/politics/20BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winfrey, Oprah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5DD123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full of Banter, Bush Goes On the 'Oprah' Circuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>LEXINGTON, Ky., Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush appears on Oprah Winfrey's show and seeks out other television opportunities; is no longer playing it as safe and scripted as he did in spring and into summer as he strives to regain lead in tight race; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question came by way of an e-mail message to Oprah, the queen of confessional television, and Gov. George W. Bush took it head on: What is the public's biggest misconception of him?</p>
        <p>''I'm running on my daddy's name,'' he answered instantly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question came by way of an e-mail message to Oprah, the queen of confessional television, and Gov. George W. Bush took it head on: What is the public's biggest misconception of him?</p>
        <p>''I'm running on my daddy's name,'' he answered instantly.</p>
        <p>''Really?'' she prodded.</p>
        <p>''You know, if my name was George Jones I'd be a country and western singer,'' said Mr. Bush, the son of a president. ''I've lived with this all my life. Of course, I love my dad a lot. He's a fabulous man and I'm proud to be his son.''</p>
        <p>For an hour today, Mr. Bush took his turn in Oprah Winfrey's chair in her Chicago studio, just a week after Al Gore did, trying to woo her 7 million daily viewers, most of them women. He gave her a kiss, which Mr. Gore did not. He resisted some of her efforts to force him into introspection and joked at others. He talked of God and why he stopped drinking. And his eyes welled up as he spoke of his wife and the birth of his twins.</p>
        <p>''Tell us about a time when you needed forgiveness?'' Ms. Winfrey asked.</p>
        <p>''Right now,'' Mr. Bush deflected, then added: ''When my heart turns dark. When I am jealous. Or when I'm spiteful.''</p>
        <p>But Oprah wanted more. ''I'm looking for specifics,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I know you are,'' Mr. Bush retorted. ''But I'm running for president.'' The audience laughed.</p>
        <p>As he tries to find a way back into the lead in a tight race, the Texas governor is no longer playing it as  safe and scripted as he did all spring and into the summer. Now, he is taking questions everywhere. Right after he taped Ms. Winfrey's show, he answered the queries of schoolchildren at the Beethoven Elementary School on Chicago's South Side, where he promoted his ideas for bolstering school safety by shielding teachers from lawsuits resulting from their disciplining of students.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush is also seizing television opportunities. He sat for an interview with Paula Zahn of Fox on Monday. Today he sat not just for Ms. Winfrey but also for Diane Sawyer of ''Good Morning America.'' On Thursday he will be on the Regis Philbin show. And the Bush campaign tried to work out an appearance with David Letterman this week, during a brief visit to New York City, but found out that Mr. Letterman was not taping.</p>
        <p>Still, the Bush campaign seemed to get what it wanted from Ms. Winfrey's show. Aides said they were delighted that he had the chance to speak to voters for an hour, ''unfiltered'' by the news media. Viewers, said Karen P. Hughes, his chief press aide, ''got to see the Governor Bush I know and work with every day.''</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign, though, tried its best to keep Mr. Bush off balance. Seizing on Mr. Bush's comment to Ms. Winfrey that ''a leader is someone who is not afraid to take positions,'' it peppered reporters covering Mr. Bush with an instant news release pointing out issues Mr. Bush had not taken clear positions on and attacking his positions on others.</p>
        <p>Ms. Winfrey made no secret of the fact that she was trying to break through the ''wall'' of sound bites  usually put up by politicians. So her interview dealt mostly with biography, not policy.</p>
        <p>She pressed Mr. Bush on his father, asking whether he was running to restore his family's name and legacy. When Mr. Bush said he was not, she wondered whether ''not even in the teeniest, tiniest part'' of himself he was seeking to avenge his father's defeat in 1992.</p>
        <p>''Not even in the teeniest, tiniest part,'' Mr. Bush insisted. ''Basically, what you're saying is, 'Are you running to get revenge?' Revenge is such a negative thought. I'm running for positive reasons.''</p>
        <p>She asked him to talk about his having given up drinking at age 40.</p>
        <p>''Alcohol was beginning to compete for my affections,'' Mr. Bush said, ''compete for my affections for my wife and my family. It was beginning to crowd out my energy and I decided to quit.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Winfrey wondered whether his wife, Laura, had ever given him an ultimatum.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it was quite that,'' Mr. Bush said, but added, ''she got disappointed some evenings.''</p>
        <p>''I wasn't drinking all the time,'' he said, ''But there were some times when she said, 'You need to think about what you're doing.' ''</p>
        <p>For one moment a heckler tried to shout a question from the audience and Ms. Winfrey cut him off and moved to a commercial break. She said it was the first heckler in 15 years of the show.</p>
        <p>Later, Ms. Winfrey asked Mr. Bush to describe a time when he was overwhelmed with doubt. He recalled going to preparatory school in the East after a childhood in Texas and in the process seemed to respond to critics who question whether he is intellectual enough to be president.</p>
        <p>''I remember thinking how brilliant all the other kids were,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Eventually, I realized smarts are not only whether or not you can write well or whether or not you can do calculus, but smarts also is instinct and judgment and competence.'' He said: ''I've got a lot of experience, I'm well educated. But I'm certainly not the kind of person who talks down to people because of my education.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Winfrey quizzed Mr. Bush about a long list of his favorite things, just as she had with Mr. Gore. Sandwich? Peanut butter and jelly on white bread. Gift to give? ''Kiss to my wife.'' Fast food? Taco. Thing he cannot live without? Running. (''I'm up to a seven-and-a-half-minute mile three miles a day -- another reason why I should be president.'') Historical figure? Winston Churchill. Prized possession? His Texas ranch.</p>
        <p>His favorite dream? Mr. Bush looked taken aback, blushed, said nothing and then lifted his hand. Ms. Winfrey clasped it and raised it in the air. Ms. Hughes later said that Mr. Bush's gesture was a reference to being sworn in as president.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Mr. Bush talked to another set of questioners, at a town-hall meeting here in Lexington. At times, he hit the same kinds of soft notes he had on ''Oprah,'' but at other moments he was more pointed. He accused Mr. Gore of wanting ''nationalized health care.''</p>
        <p>He also took on Mr. Gore on tax cuts. ''You've heard the rhetoric we're for the rich and he's for the people,'' he said, paraphrasing Mr. Gore. He said that his opponent had promised middle-class tax relief in 1992 but instead delivered a ''targeted tax increase.'' ''You've had your chance, Mr. Gore,'' he said. ''You have not led, we will.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
