<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; From an Alternate to a 'Miracle Kid' in a Flash</title>
    <meta content="20ARAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwikert, Tasha</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1D8143BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; From an Alternate to a 'Miracle Kid' in a Flash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses career of US gymnast Tasha Schwikert-Warren; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE one thing a teenager can count on is change, abrupt and ongoing, but even by that hormonal standard, Tasha Schwikert-Warren's Olympics were extreme. She came to Sydney as an alternate, a dreamer, a 15-year-old with metal in her smile. By late last night, she was hailed as the foundation and future of the United States women's gymnastics team.</p>
        <p>''The miracle kid,'' Bela Karolyi raved, but only in part because she was all he had left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE one thing a teenager can count on is change, abrupt and ongoing, but even by that hormonal standard, Tasha Schwikert-Warren's Olympics were extreme. She came to Sydney as an alternate, a dreamer, a 15-year-old with metal in her smile. By late last night, she was hailed as the foundation and future of the United States women's gymnastics team.</p>
        <p>''The miracle kid,'' Bela Karolyi raved, but only in part because she was all he had left.</p>
        <p>Four years after Kerri Strug, there was no Hollywood ending to the women's team final, no U.S. medal. The only carrying-on was over Karolyi himself, a powerful and divisive presence who, depending on the post-meet source, helped elevate the U.S. to fourth place or impeded its chances to climb even higher.</p>
        <p>It all sounded like fallout from unrealistic expectation, based on a four-year-old fairy tale. In this sport, unless you have some kind of warehouse operation like the gold medal-winning Romanians, four years may as well be 40. Even teenaged gymnasts have the potential to gain weight, get bored, go to school and grow up.</p>
        <p>After Karolyi was rushed back this year to supervise a faltering team, after the Magnificent Seven of Atlanta shrank to two at the trials, it was difficult to determine if the Americans were operating in the past or living in the present. There was around this group an air of uncertainty, a tossing of the dice, not unlike the craps games Schwikert-Warren's parents can be found conducting on the night shift at Caesars Palace back home in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Her mother, Joy, was a professional tennis player in the 1970's, who played tour doubles with her identical twin, Jill. Joy Schwikert's daughter Tasha was also a twin, but her sister died in premature childbirth, and those two months turned out to be the difference in Tasha's eligibility for selection as an alternate for these Olympics under the new age-restriction rules.</p>
        <p>''I came thinking it would be a great experience just being around the team,'' she said. Yet something strange was in the air, the vortex of adolescent change. Seventeen-year-old Morgan White pulled out early last week with a stress fracture in her foot. The team's preliminary results were flat. Schwikert-Warren suddenly found herself in three of the four routines last night, and acquitted herself on the uneven parallel bars and in the floor exercise with poise that even startled her coach from the Gymcats Club in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>''The pressure was so enormous, I started to think she might lose it,'' Cassie Rice said. ''But she went out on the bar and nailed it. That's been the story of her career so far, performance under pressure.''</p>
        <p>Rice had ushered Schwikert-Warren into the interviewing area known as the mixed zone, and stood by as reporters informed her that the great Karolyi had called her ''the one with the work ethic, the one following directions, a leader in the next generation.''</p>
        <p>From high above the mats, bouncing high off muscular legs, she hadn't looked much like the prototypical pixie. But here, standing all of 4 feet 11 inches tall, it seemed incongruous, almost unfair, to burden this 10th grader in braces with the newly improvised set of expectations, now the result of those unmet.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the girls who competed here are going off to college,'' Schwikert-Warren said. ''Realistically, I'm going to be the only one left from this group. It is pretty scary, but I'm going to go in there and lead the new ones the best I can.''</p>
        <p>Her 14-year-old sister and an elite junior, Jordan, could be her teammate by 2004, assuming, of course, that she will still have the appetite, so to speak, for this demanding life herself. College basketball coaches call their players kids, so what does that make these girls? Candidates to morph into an Olympic has-been as fast as a hand can slide off an uneven parallel bar.</p>
        <p>With such youth and volatility, you might expect the attending adults to create the most stable working environments for these girls to perform in, which was certainly not the case this year.</p>
        <p>''I wanted him to coach the coaches,'' the USA Gymnastics president, Bob Colarossi, said of Karolyi, and of his own shortsighted decision to bring him back as a supervising presence but not as the Olympic coach. That was Kelli Hill's job, but men such as Karolyi do not kindly offer advice and quietly take a seat. They step on toes with pointed heels. The Romanians, the Russians and the Chinese were barely off the medal pedestals last night before the American contingent was picking sides, praising or burying Bela.</p>
        <p>This was one routine that Schwikert-Warren wasn't competing in. She was too new at this, too young, and the only contact she had ever had with Atlanta was when she rubbed Amy Chow's souvenir ring for good luck last night. Schwikert-Warren had the best luck of all the Americans. A teenager's luck could change quickly, though, especially if the adults in her life don't clean up their act.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
