<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Banner Ads Keep On Waving, But They're Singing a Different Tune</title>
    <meta content="20STAM$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKETING"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3D71139F933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Banner Ads Keep On Waving, But They're Singing a Different Tune</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD STAMLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WAY back when, say in 1995, they were still something of a curiosity. That was the year that Yahoo first decided to put advertising on its site, a time when the words ''advertising banners'' still conjured images of cloth signs trailing from airplanes on hot summer days.</p>
        <p>But Internet banners -- advertisements appearing on Web pages, often randomly, and usually in rectangular boxes -- did not remain a rarity for long. Cheap to put on the Internet, easy to design, they soon were everywhere. And euphoric Web site owners and eager advertisers were convinced that they could do just about anything.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WAY back when, say in 1995, they were still something of a curiosity. That was the year that Yahoo first decided to put advertising on its site, a time when the words ''advertising banners'' still conjured images of cloth signs trailing from airplanes on hot summer days.</p>
        <p>But Internet banners -- advertisements appearing on Web pages, often randomly, and usually in rectangular boxes -- did not remain a rarity for long. Cheap to put on the Internet, easy to design, they soon were everywhere. And euphoric Web site owners and eager advertisers were convinced that they could do just about anything.</p>
        <p>''Like all new advertising formats, banners went through a strong novelty phase,'' said Nigel Hollis, executive vice president of Millward Brown Interactive, an online research firm in Fairfield, Conn. Great claims were made -- for example, that banner advertisements would drive customers in droves to the Web sites of companies that used them. And that, once there, the customers would buy.</p>
        <p>It did not happen. In the general confusion attending the dot-com meltdown earlier this year, banners fell into disrepute. Suddenly, they were decried as being useless or worse: a waste of precious advertising dollars in an all-too-competitive world. But banners have not disappeared. And advertisers still think they serve a purpose.</p>
        <p>It just is not the one that people originally thought it would be.</p>
        <p>Today, banners are for branding.</p>
        <p>''In the early days, the guys doing this stuff were technology people, not marketing people,'' said Marianne Foley. Now an independent Internet industry consultant, she was formerly a senior vice president of Ipsos-ASI, an advertising research company in Norwalk, Conn., that has conducted extensive testing regarding banners. ''The technology seduced them,'' Ms. Foley said.</p>
        <p>Certainly, the technology was breathtaking. Advertisers could count the number of people who actually saw their banners, which are referred to as ''eyeballs,'' or impressions. They could measure the number of people who actually clicked on the banner after seeing it and then traveled to the site being advertised, known as ''click-throughs.'' No medium had ever been capable of anything like it before.</p>
        <p>So advertisers began paying for their banners accordingly, usually on the basis of a certain cost per thousand impressions, or C.P.M.'s. And they looked eagerly for a correlation between click-throughs and actual sales.</p>
        <p>Trouble was, things did not work out quite that way. Sure, impression numbers were huge, but they had little, if any, discernible effect on product sales or Web-site traffic. Click-through rates were miserable. (They have remained extremely low, Mr. Hollis said, amounting to only one-half of 1 percent today, industrywide.) And the click-throughs themselves, well, they produced incredibly disappointing results.</p>
        <p>That should not have surprised anyone, industry experts say. Using the click-through rate the way they did was illogical, said Jim Nail, an analyst at Forrester Research in Cambridge, Mass., who specializes in online marketing and advertising. Advertisers have long known that there is no foolproof way of linking traditional newspaper advertisements or television and radio commercials directly to increases in a product's sale; why should it have been otherwise with banner advertisements?</p>
        <p>''Marketing is about a lot of things,'' Mr. Nail said. ''Including getting people to consider your product now,'' even if they buy it later. ''Generating awareness is the best that banners can do.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''If you think of them as a branding tool, then they're not so bad.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Foley agreed. Though she conceded that all the new talk was to some degree a face-saving exercise in 20/20 hindsight, she insisted that marketing people always knew that the measures being used for banners were incorrect, and that branding was the way to go.</p>
        <p>''The best thing banners do is to create an opportunity to put a product in front of someone,'' she said. ''At the very least, they get a glance.''</p>
        <p>So how does the industry try to harvest those glances now? And how does it pay for them?</p>
        <p>In its fourth annual survey of Internet advertising, released in May, the Association of National Advertisers, a trade group in New York, polled some 100 member companies about their use of online media. Two-thirds of the respondents said they were advertising on the Internet, and 98 percent said that banners were included in their mix, with other formats like e-mail, used by 60 percent of participants, and interstitials, which were used by 51 percent. (Interstitials are the advertisements that appear, either in full or in small size, when an Internet user is calling up another site but before that other site loads.)</p>
        <p>BUT while companies are still primarily buying online media on the basis of C.P.M.'s (69 percent of respondents), those C.P.M.'s are going down, to $20 this year from a median of $28 in 1998, said Robin Webster, executive vice president of the association. Moreover, many have begun buying on the basis of flat fees or other models, like sponsorship programs.</p>
        <p>Greg Koerner, a vice president of national advertising sales for Doubleclick Inc. in New York, the Internet advertising firm, confirmed the trend.</p>
        <p>''People are using banners in different ways today,'' he said, ''and a higher percentage of them are traditional advertisers, who understand these things better.</p>
        <p>''Either they put the ads in a place where their customers are likely to be,'' like General Motors, which he said was advertising heavily on Kelley's Blue Book (www.kelleysbluebook.com), a used- and new-car information site, in effect becoming a ''sponsor'' as in the old days of network television. Or advertisers used technology ''to identify potential customers and advertise only to them,'' he said, like people who live in certain geographic areas or those who use only certain Internet service providers.</p>
        <p>''These people used to be buying impressions,'' Mr. Koerner said. ''They're not anymore.''</p>
        <p>Still, they are buying. Doubleclick had more than 5,000 advertiser clients in the second quarter of this year, up from 3,100 in the same period a year ago, according to company-released statistics. And it placed some 148 billion advertisements for them during those three months alone. In the second quarter of 1999, it placed only 30 billion.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile at Yahoo, ''banners are a very important part of the toolbox and will continue to be,'' said Murray Gaylord, the director of so-called fusion marketing, which the company  (www.fusion.yahoo.com) defined as ''an integrated set of sales and marketing tools'' built upon its total audience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaylord, too, thought that clicks and click-throughs were ''the wrong metric'' and suggested what he called a better measure: ''looking at people who have had the opportunity to see a banner, and seeing whether they later purchased'' the product.</p>
        <p>That, of course, would depend upon whether people remember banners. In Internet branding campaigns, in all branding campaigns, the most important issue is recall.</p>
        <p>So how do banners measure up?  Research by Millward Brown, Mr. Hollis's firm, suggested that people remembered them, but only to a point. ''Up to 40 percent of people we survey will say they remember a banner,'' he said. ''But we lose anywhere from 50 percent to 100 percent of them when we ask them to link the ad to the right brand.''</p>
        <p>Why? ''Banners are just like other advertising formats,'' he said. ''Some work, and some don't.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Foley put it more bluntly.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it,'' she said. In terms of their creative aspect, ''most banners are junk.''</p>
        <p>And there is nothing technology can do about that.</p>
        <p>MARKETING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
