<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EMI Says It and Time Warner Make Deal Concessions</title>
    <meta content="Y20ONL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/technology/20ONLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emi Group Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DA153BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EMI Says It and Time Warner Make Deal Concessions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time Warner and EMI Group, in an attempt to keep European regulators from blocking $20 billion merger, propose what they call 'substantial' concessions that might include selling some of their record labels; deal still faces skepticism of European antitrust officials, who have threatened to block it if companies do not make big concessions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an attempt to keep European regulators from blocking a $20 billion merger, Time Warner and the EMI Group today proposed what they called ''substantial'' concessions that might include selling some of their record labels.</p>
        <p>But the deal, which would unite two of the world's major music distributors, still faces the skepticism of European antitrust officials, who have threatened to block it if the companies do not make big concessions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an attempt to keep European regulators from blocking a $20 billion merger, Time Warner and the EMI Group today proposed what they called ''substantial'' concessions that might include selling some of their record labels.</p>
        <p>But the deal, which would unite two of the world's major music distributors, still faces the skepticism of European antitrust officials, who have threatened to block it if the companies do not make big concessions.</p>
        <p>Without spelling out details, an executive at EMI said today that the companies ''offered substantial undertakings that go far beyond'' the limited proposals they made earlier this month and are both ''structural and behavioral in nature.''</p>
        <p>Reuters reported today that the companies had offered to sell several record labels in Spain, Denmark and other countries; to withdraw from manufacturing compact discs in Europe; and to make changes in their distribution and production.</p>
        <p>Today was the deadline for Time Warner and EMI to propose remedies aimed at allaying concerns of the European Commission, the day-to-day administrative arm of the 15-nation European Union. The Europeans worry that the proposed merger of Time Warner's music businesses into a joint venture with EMI would reduce the number of major record distributors to four companies from five, further limiting competition.</p>
        <p>The EMI deal is seen by some as closely related to the $165 billion merger proposed between America Online and Time Warner. That deal faces objections on the ground that it would create an integrated media giant controlling much entertainment as well as the world's biggest online information service.</p>
        <p>Officials on the merger task force, part of the European competition directorate headed by Commissioner Mario Monti, have already circulated a draft recommendation that calls for rejecting both deals.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Monti's aides have met with Time Warner and AOL executives to discuss possible compromises. The European Commission must decide on the EMI deal by Oct. 18 and on the AOL deal by Oct. 24. Mr. Monti is trying to adhere to tough deadlines that prohibit the companies from making new proposals any later than a month before the deadline for a decision.</p>
        <p>After he recommends a decision, the case is to be discussed by an advisory committee of antitrust officials from the 15 European Union nations and then voted on.</p>
        <p>People close to the discussions said EMI had already volunteered to make its music available to competitors of America Online, as well as to agree on adhering to the prices on the use of copyrighted music set by national copyright organizations.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Monti seems to want the companies to sell some of their catalogs and perhaps some record labels before any recommendation of approval. EMI signaled that it had proposed divestitures, but it and Time Warner own so many record labels that the crucial details lie in which ones they offer to sell.</p>
        <p>In the next few days, European officials in Brussels will circulate EMI's proposals to rivals, consumer groups and other music industry companies. Among the most vocal critics is Walt Disney, which has strongly suggested that both deals are too anticompetitive to repair.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
