<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Says Debate Critics Are Sexist</title>
    <meta content="20LAZI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/politics/20LAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DD123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Says Debate Critics Are Sexist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>SYRACUSE, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Lazio says it is 'sexist' to suggest that he should not have walked over to Hillary Clinton's podium in challenging manner during their New York Senate campaign debate; Clinton advisers say he was bullying, and would not have tried unusual televised confrontation if opponent were a man; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio today issued his strongest rebuke yet to critics of his debate tactics, saying it was ''sexist'' to suggest he should not have walked over to Hillary Rodham Clinton's lectern in a challenging manner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, the Republican Senate nominee, said the criticism of his tactic during last Wednesday's debate in Buffalo suggested that ''you can't make a point forcefully if you're a man and the person you are making a point with is a woman.'' He said, ''I just think that that's sexist.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio today issued his strongest rebuke yet to critics of his debate tactics, saying it was ''sexist'' to suggest he should not have walked over to Hillary Rodham Clinton's lectern in a challenging manner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, the Republican Senate nominee, said the criticism of his tactic during last Wednesday's debate in Buffalo suggested that ''you can't make a point forcefully if you're a man and the person you are making a point with is a woman.'' He said, ''I just think that that's sexist.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, responding to suggestions from Mrs. Clinton and her aides that he was overbearing, said a ''double standard'' was at play when he was criticized for physically confronting Mrs. Clinton, bringing talk about the role of gender in the campaign to the forefront. In his remarks, Mr. Lazio suggested that he would not have faced such criticism if his opponent were a man; Mrs. Clinton's advisers have argued that he would not have tried such an unusual televised confrontation if he were running against a man.</p>
        <p>During the debate, Mr. Lazio walked over to Mrs. Clinton's lectern, waving a sheet of paper, gesturing at her and demanding that she sign a pledge abstaining from using unregulated campaign contributions known as soft money. She declined. Mrs. Clinton's advisers have portrayed his actions as bullying and likely to alienate women.</p>
        <p>And Mrs. Clinton and her campaign have sought to encourage that reaction among women. In a speech Monday before supporters, the first lady portrayed Mr. Lazio as yelling, pointing his finger and invading her space. ''I knew I was going to share a stage,'' Mrs. Clinton said, ''I didn't think I was going to have to share a podium.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's advisers moved today to take advantage of what they saw as a misstep by Mr. Lazio at the debate, releasing a new advertisement that portrayed Mrs. Clinton as something of a victim, fighting against forces that have tried to defeat her on issues like  health care.</p>
        <p>''Today the political world was rocked by the bizarre accusation that Rick Lazio has been the victim of sexism,'' said Mrs. Clinton's campaign communications director, Howard Wolfson. ''Poor Rick. Let me be the first to offer him my support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, as he has traveled across the state in the last several days, has repeatedly been questioned about his actions by journalists and occasionally by some of the people he has visited, like schoolchildren. Today, after touring a Buffalo information technology firm, he was asked by a reporter to respond to Mrs. Clinton's remarks on Monday, and in doing so went beyond his usual reply that he had done nothing wrong during the debate.</p>
        <p>''I think the idea that somehow, you know, men and women have different standards in contemporary life is wrong,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''I don't think people in the Senate worry about whether you're a man or a woman.''</p>
        <p>Later, questioned again, he did not use the word ''sexist'' but reiterated:  ''I think there ought to be a fair, level playing field, that we should have the same expectations whether you're a male or female, that we ought to be held to the same standard. And that's what I tried to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio also said his tactic was necessary to force Mrs. Clinton to address his pledge to ask all independent groups to cease supporting his candidacy by such means as advertising and mailings if Mrs. Clinton agrees to give up her soft money.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Lazio said he had disbanded a state political action committee, Friends of Rick, and returned the $75,000 in donations it had received. Mrs. Clinton's camp had classified the group as a soft-money PAC, though Mr. Lazio said none of the money went toward supporting his Senate candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's aides, apparently concerned that news of his remarks would overtake his plan to use today's upstate visit to emphasize high technology as a route to statewide prosperity, sought to portray Mrs. Clinton as hypocritical.</p>
        <p>By midafternoon, his campaign office had sent an e-mail message pointing reporters to an article in the September 1999 issue of Brill's Content magazine on how Mrs. Clinton dealt with the press as the first lady of Arkansas. The article includes a 1990 photograph of Mrs. Clinton pointing her finger at the Republican candidate for governor, Tim McRae. She had interrupted his news conference to castigate his criticism of Bill Clinton, then governor, for extensive out-of-state travel.</p>
        <p>''Mrs. Clinton obviously feels that the first candidate debate was a little  too New York for her,'' said Bill Dal Col, Mr. Lazio's campaign manager.  ''But she should realize that what's good for the goose is good for the gander, and she can't give a spirited performance in Arkansas and then play the victim when things don't go her way in New York.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's campaign declined to comment on the article.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio went on to a celebration of the opening of his Syracuse campaign headquarters and a reception here by the New York State Aftermarket Association, a trade group of auto parts dealers that his father had belonged to.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton did not discuss the debate today as she campaigned in the Bronx. She attended the opening of the children's emergency ward at the Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx, delivering a detailed speech about the deficiencies of pediatric health care and restating her pledge not to give up on health care reform for both children and adults.</p>
        <p>''I don't quit,'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''I don't think any of us can afford that.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton promised to pursue legislation that would allow imports from Canada of pharmaceuticals that are sold cheaper there and to ''keep working across party lines'' to make everyday health care more affordable in other ways. She said the United States should not only be the richest country in the world, but the healthiest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
