<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Mets In Atlanta, Rock Bottom Looks Closer</title>
    <meta content="20METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/20/sports/20METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DD123BF933A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Mets In Atlanta, Rock Bottom Looks Closer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Braves defeats New York Mets, 12-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His fingers drummed the hardwood desktop to a forceful and ominous beat. Bobby Valentine was mad, and he was not going to take it anymore. There was no positive spin as Valentine, the Mets' manager, addressed reporters in his office at Turner Field  after an awful 12-4 loss to the Atlanta Braves tonight. He was angry, and he had just told his players so, too.</p>
        <p>''It was a human thing,'' Valentine said. ''I'm being human here. If someone doesn't think I'm allowed to be ticked off, it's their mistake. It's my right and I exerted it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His fingers drummed the hardwood desktop to a forceful and ominous beat. Bobby Valentine was mad, and he was not going to take it anymore. There was no positive spin as Valentine, the Mets' manager, addressed reporters in his office at Turner Field  after an awful 12-4 loss to the Atlanta Braves tonight. He was angry, and he had just told his players so, too.</p>
        <p>''It was a human thing,'' Valentine said. ''I'm being human here. If someone doesn't think I'm allowed to be ticked off, it's their mistake. It's my right and I exerted it.''</p>
        <p>For 5 or 10 minutes in a private meeting, Valentine's players listened to his exasperation. He addresses the team periodically, once a month by his count, but the significance of this meeting was the setting. It is September, and the Mets are doing it again. They are losing to the Braves in Atlanta and jeopardizing their postseason hopes.</p>
        <p>Valentine scolded the team and pumped them up, said Mets starter Glendon Rusch, who was knocked out in a seven-run second inning. It was a message, Todd Zeile said, that needed to be delivered.</p>
        <p>'' 'Get it together, let's go,' '' John Franco said Valentine told the team. '' 'We've played too long and too hard to play like this. We're a much better team than we've showed.' ''</p>
        <p>That much is obvious. The Mets (85-66) are a good team, and they still have a comfortable lead for the National League wild card, with Arizona five games behind after losing, 1-0, to the Dodgers in Los Angeles tonight. But the National League East crown will probably elude them again.</p>
        <p>The Braves lead by five games with 11 to play, and any combination of seven Braves victories and Mets losses will give Atlanta its ninth consecutive division title.</p>
        <p>''The last thing on our minds is worrying about the playoffs,'' catcher Mike Piazza said. ''It gets kind of ridiculous, analyzing all the scenarios. The bottom line is, we have to win today, win tomorrow and let everything else take care of itself.''</p>
        <p>As the Mets appeared to self-destruct down the stretch last September, Valentine said that he should be fired if the team did not make the playoffs. The Mets survived, of course, but they are nearly staging a re-enactment. They began this September alone in first place but have gone 6-12. Nerves are fraying again.</p>
        <p>''I just haven't had them ready to play, I guess,'' Valentine said, with obvious sarcasm. ''What other explanation could there be?</p>
        <p>''We've got a good team and we just haven't played well. I'll try to get them to play better the next 11 games.''</p>
        <p>The Mets started two pitchers in the first two games of this series who had never pitched for them in Atlanta. It made no difference. Both came into the series pitching well and turned in their worst outings in a while. Mike Hampton was hit hard on Monday, and Rusch (10-11) was pounded tonight.</p>
        <p>The Mets have now dropped 20 of their last 22 games at Turner Field, including three in last year's National League Championship Series. Zeile, a first-year Met, said there is a different feeling here than there is at other parks when things start to go wrong. When the Braves get a borderline pitch, make a great play or have a blooper fall for a hit, the Mets let it bother them.</p>
        <p>''Things that normally would slip off our back, I think, affect us a little bit more here,'' Zeile said. ''We have a sense, because of what we perceive in our own minds and what people make this rivalry out to be, that we have to be perfect to beat them. That's a perception that needs to be shattered. You don't have to be perfect to beat these guys. There's a lot of teams that do beat them.''</p>
        <p>The Mets are rarely one of those teams. They have won just three of nine games from the Braves this year, and tonight's was never close. The offensive blackout that plagued the Mets in early September seems to have returned. Before scoring in the fifth inning tonight, the Mets had failed to score in 22 of their previous 23 innings.</p>
        <p>Andy Ashby mastered them this time, allowing one unearned run, five hits and a walk over seven innings. Ashby (11-12) shut out the Mets in July. Rusch, who was roughed up by the Braves in July, also held form.</p>
        <p>He allowed extra-base hits to the first three batters in the second inning, the third a double by Braves left fielder Reggie Sanders, who, in Valentine's opinion, was given ''six strikes'' by the home plate umpire, Mike Winters.</p>
        <p>The Braves were ahead, 2-0, and after an out, third baseman Robin Ventura let Ashby's grounder bounce off his leg for an error, bringing in another run. Rafael Furcal's smash up the middle bounced from Rusch's glove to second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo, who threw to second for a forceout.</p>
        <p>But Rusch could not get the third out of the inning. Andruw Jones walked, and Chipper Jones singled in a run. Valentine called on Pat Mahomes, the first of six Mets relievers, and Mahomes faced three hitters, retiring none. The Braves scored seven runs in the second -- the most they have scored in one inning this year, and the most the Mets have surrendered.</p>
        <p>Valentine had the rest of the game to prepare his postgame speech. The players could summon few suggestions.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what's needed,'' Piazza said. ''We just need to win. How many ways can you keep saying it? It's obvious we're playing bad baseball.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Though the hysteria over the Atlanta reliever JOHN ROCKER has died down, the Mets are taking no chances for next week's three-game series with the Braves at Shea Stadium. Mets officials will meet later this week with police personnel to plan for the series, said DAVID HOWARD, the Mets' senior vice president for business and legal affairs. ''It will still be a noticeable police presence; put it that way,'' Howard said. The Mets' security measures, which included a roof over the bench and mounds in the visitors' bullpen and tall fencing on the bordering seats, were largely effective the last time. . . . Tickets to the first two home games of the division series at Shea Stadium will go on sale by telephone only (718-507-TIXX) on Saturday at 10 a.m. Dates and times -- and the Mets' participation -- are to be determined.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
