<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting Franks on the Side of Government's Enemies</title>
    <meta content="04ADBO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/politics/04ADBO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DA113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting Franks on the Side of Government's Enemies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of 30-second commercial, titled Dismantle, released by Jon S Corzine, Democratic candidate for Senate from New Jersey; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This 30-second commercial, titled ''Dismantle,'' was released yesterday by Jon S. Corzine, the Democratic candidate for the Senate from New Jersey. It is being broadcast on television stations in New York City and Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Shrum, Devine &amp; Donilon</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This 30-second commercial, titled ''Dismantle,'' was released yesterday by Jon S. Corzine, the Democratic candidate for the Senate from New Jersey. It is being broadcast on television stations in New York City and Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Shrum, Devine &amp; Donilon</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- The commercial, like an earlier attack ad by Mr. Corzine, shows his Republican opponent, Representative Bob Franks, in videotape apparently taken from a recent television interview. The tape has been slowed down, so that Mr. Franks's usually sunny facial expressions look more like snarls, and his skin tone looks positively green, as if someone had played with a tint knob to make him appear not merely unelectable but unearthly. Subtitles amplify the script: ''Slash Medicare,'' ''Cut Environmental Protection Agency,'' ''Beaches at Risk, Rivers at Risk, Air at Risk, Water at Risk.''</p>
        <p>THE SCRIPT -- Narrator: ''He voted to slash Medicare, first by $270 billion, then by $158 billion. He voted to abolish the Department of Education. He voted to cut funding for the Environmental Protection Agency, putting our beaches, our rivers, our air and our water at risk. He was one of the members of Congress who in 1995 shut down the United States government.</p>
        <p>''Bob Franks. More interested in dismantling the government than he is in making the government work.''</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- Mr. Franks voted for the 1995 budget reconciliation bill, in which House Republicans made good on promises to cut taxes and balance the budget, and for a 1996 budget compromise. Included in both bills were reductions in future Medicare spending. The Franks campaign notes that Medicare spending continued to grow, but at a slower pace. In May 1995, Mr. Franks voted for a budget resolution that would have eliminated the Department of Education. That proposal was dropped in a House-Senate conference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks says he supports more federal money for education, but that it should be spent at the local level. In March 1996, during wrangling between Congressional leaders and the White House, Mr. Franks voted with his party for an interim measure that would have considerably reduced financing for the Environmental Protection Agency, but this measure, too, was dropped in conference after President Clinton threatened a veto. Financing for the E.P.A. in 1996 was later restored to $6.5 billion, $100 million less than the year before.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks voted with his party during the confrontation with President Clinton that gave rise to the 27-day government shutdown in 1995. The shutdown occurred after  Republicans passed a short-term spending bill but included a measure canceling a reduction in Medicare premiums, over President Clinton's threat of a veto.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- With this ad, Mr. Corzine continues to portray Mr. Franks as unfavorably as possible to New Jersey voters who so far have heard little about him from other sources. At the same time, Mr. Corzine is inoculating himself against an argument that Mr. Franks would be likely to make if he ever raises enough money for his own campaign ads: that Mr. Corzine's political proposals amount to a return to old-time, big-government, big-spending liberalism. Mr. Corzine instead places himself on the side of ''making government work,'' a distinction that he hopes voters will make in November.</p>
        <p>DAVID M. HALBFINGER</p>
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
