<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Taiwan's Bourgeoisie and Its Affecting Charms</title>
    <meta content="04YIYI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/arts/04YIYI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yang, Edward</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Yi Yi (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DA103DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Taiwan's Bourgeoisie and Its Affecting Charms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie Yi Yi, directed by Taiwanese filmmaker Edward Yang, shown at New York Film Festival; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Midway through ''Yi Yi,'' a morose, skeletally thin teenager (whose nickname is Fatty) tells his date: ''Movies are lifelike. That's why we like them.'' In his view, movies don't only resemble the world we live in -- they expand it. ''We live three times,'' he declares, his passion overwhelming his arithmetic. ''Two times as much life at the movies!'' After watching this lovely, absorbing film you'll be inclined to agree. In exchange for three hours of your time, ''Yi Yi'' will give you more life.</p>
        <p>Edward Yang, the Taiwanese filmmaker who wrote and directed this intimate epic of a middle-class Taipei's family's everyday struggles, knows that for a movie to be full of life, it must above all concern itself with specific lives. ''Yi Yi'' begins with the chaotic bustle of wedding preparations -- a portrait of the bride and groom is hung upside down, the groom's jilted girlfriend arrives uninvited and makes a scene -- and ends with the somber calm of a funeral.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Midway through ''Yi Yi,'' a morose, skeletally thin teenager (whose nickname is Fatty) tells his date: ''Movies are lifelike. That's why we like them.'' In his view, movies don't only resemble the world we live in -- they expand it. ''We live three times,'' he declares, his passion overwhelming his arithmetic. ''Two times as much life at the movies!'' After watching this lovely, absorbing film you'll be inclined to agree. In exchange for three hours of your time, ''Yi Yi'' will give you more life.</p>
        <p>Edward Yang, the Taiwanese filmmaker who wrote and directed this intimate epic of a middle-class Taipei's family's everyday struggles, knows that for a movie to be full of life, it must above all concern itself with specific lives. ''Yi Yi'' begins with the chaotic bustle of wedding preparations -- a portrait of the bride and groom is hung upside down, the groom's jilted girlfriend arrives uninvited and makes a scene -- and ends with the somber calm of a funeral.</p>
        <p>In the long interval between these events, the members of the Jian family collectively and individually traverse what feels like the full spectrum of human experience, from the mundane to the catastrophic. NJ (Wu Nienjen), the wiry, sad-eyed patriarch, must deal with setbacks at his software company and a midlife crisis triggered by the reappearance of Sherry (Ke Suyun), his high-school sweetheart. NJ's wife, Min-Min (Elaine Jin), despondent over her mother's crippling stroke, retreats first into depression and then into a religious cult. Their teenage daughter, Ting-Ting (Kelly Lee), undergoes her own identity crisis, caught between loyalty to her troubled best friend and the slightly dangerous appeal of Fatty (Yupang Chang). There is a birth, a suicide attempt and a murder. Friendships are made and broken. Ting-Ting's runty younger brother, Yang-Yang (Jonathan Chang), is harassed at school by a gang of bigger girls. There is a lot of music (NJ's passion), eating and drinking, all of it set amid the sleek cosmopolitan kineticism of Taipei and, briefly, Tokyo, where NJ goes in search of an investor to save his business and a second chance with Sherry, who is now married to an American businessman.</p>
        <p>But ''Yi Yi'' is more than a soap opera, which is to say it's less. The mood is restrained and gentle and the narrative rhythm fluid and easy, meandering from story to story. Although it rises on occasion to a high pitch of intensity, this movie never feels overwrought or melodramatic. The title is nothing more than the Chinese word for ''one'' repeated twice; the Chinese characters, which appear in the opening titles, look like birds in flight seen from afar. The English translation, ''A One and a Two,'' suggests a bandleader counting off, and ''Yi Yi,'' composed with the meticulous discipline of a symphony, nonetheless has the swing and spontaneity of group improvisation.</p>
        <p>It's no accident that the 8-year-old Yang-Yang shares his name with the filmmaker, since he functions within the film as a kind of alter ego, a watcher and recorder of the world's enigmas. In the privacy of his bath Yang-Yang conducts elaborate experiments with funnels and bottles and wanders from scene to scene with a camera. He's a half-pint philosopher, complaining to his father: ''I can't see what you see and you can't see what I see. So how can I know what you see?'' To remedy this condition, he takes pictures of the backs of people's heads.</p>
        <p>As a filmmaker, Mr. Yang is like a wiser, less anxious version of this boy. He uses the limitations of visual perspective to convey chaos without succumbing to it. He likes to shoot people in groups at medium range, allowing sound and movement to spill in from outside of the frame. He also likes to shoot through glass, and even to aim his camera at closed doors, as though to suggest both the transparency and the opacity of experience. The film's most extraordinary shot is of a woman weeping alone in a hotel room. The camera is outside the window, and the woman is barely visible through the reflected phantoms of skyscrapers and passing traffic.</p>
        <p>None of this feels gimmicky or contrived. Mr. Yang's style is like a novelist's prose -- lucid, unobtrusive and absorbing. Mr. Yang's earlier films, especially ''A Brighter Summer Day,'' his exquisite, disturbing 1991 story of adolescence in Taiwan, have gained him a passionate following among critics and international festivalgoers. ''Yi Yi,'' the first of his movies to be released commercially in the United States (it will open at the Film Forum on Friday, after being shown at the New York Film Festival tonight), is the work of a master in full command of the resources of his art. Movies are an inherently, sometimes cheaply emotional medium, but it takes a lot to make a grown critic cry. As I watched the final credits of ''Yi Yi'' through bleary eyes, I struggled to identify the overpowering feeling that was making me tear up. Was it grief? Joy? Mirth? Yes, I decided, it was all of these. But mostly, it was gratitude.</p>
        <p>YI YI  A One and a Two</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Edward Yang; in Mandarin, with English subtitles; director of photography, Yang Weihan; edited by Chen Bowen; music and production design by Peng Kaili; produced by Shinya Kawai and Naoko Tsukeda; released by Winstar Cinema. Running time: 173 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown with an eight-minute short, Adam Elliot's ''Brother,'' tonight at 6:30 at Alice Tully Hall as part of the 38th New York Film Festival.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jonathan Chang (Yang-Yang), Yupang Chang (Fatty), Chen Xisheng (A-Di), Elaine Jin (Min-Min), Ke Suyun (Sherry Chang-Breitner), Kelly Lee (Ting-Ting), Adrian Lin (Lili), Issey Ogata (Mr. Ota), Tang Ruyun (Grandma), Michael Tao (Da-Da), Wu Nienjen (NJ Jian), Xiao Shushen (Xiao Yan), Xu Shuyuan (Lili's Mother) and Zeng Xinyi (Yun-Yun).</p>
        <p>FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
