<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Look in the Mirror And See the 1-3 Steelers</title>
    <meta content="04JETS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/sports/04JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Steelers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED9113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Look in the Mirror And See the 1-3 Steelers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Jets preparing for game against Pittsburgh Steelers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even while they lounged on their sofas this weekend, the Jets won.</p>
        <p>It has been that kind of charmed season so far for the undefeated Jets, who had a bye last Sunday, but still had the relief of watching the Steelers, whom they face on Sunday, get their first victory of the season against Jacksonville. Nobody wants to play a desperate team, particularly not one that, in Coach Al Groh's description, sounds suspiciously like the Steel Curtain teams of the 1970's instead of the floundering 1-3 franchise of 2000. Pittsburgh will most likely start at quarterback a mediocre Kent Graham, who was without a victory in three starts, over a mediocre Kordell Stewart, who won on Sunday in his only start of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even while they lounged on their sofas this weekend, the Jets won.</p>
        <p>It has been that kind of charmed season so far for the undefeated Jets, who had a bye last Sunday, but still had the relief of watching the Steelers, whom they face on Sunday, get their first victory of the season against Jacksonville. Nobody wants to play a desperate team, particularly not one that, in Coach Al Groh's description, sounds suspiciously like the Steel Curtain teams of the 1970's instead of the floundering 1-3 franchise of 2000. Pittsburgh will most likely start at quarterback a mediocre Kent Graham, who was without a victory in three starts, over a mediocre Kordell Stewart, who won on Sunday in his only start of the season.</p>
        <p>''I see a lot of our team in the Steelers,'' Groh said today. ''They fight right until the very end. If you watch the last six minutes of all four Steelers games, you can't tell what the score is. The biggest difference is they've had two games that came down to the final play or so that went the other way, and when we've had those games, they've gone our way.''</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh has lost two games on its final drive and received two apologies from the league for blown calls that might have changed the outcomes. But on Sunday, led by a revived Jerome Bettis, the Steelers displayed a powerful running game that produced 209 yards and 3 touchdowns in dominating the Jaguars, who had entered the season as one of the favorites in the American Football Conference.</p>
        <p>''Those who said he was done haven't had to hit him recently,'' Groh said of Bettis. ''When you hit this guy, you're going to get hurt. After the 17th or 18th time you hit him, you've got to decide if you want to hurt again.''</p>
        <p>The Steelers are seventh in the league in rushing yards per game, with an average of 131. And their defense has been outstanding. They are fourth in the league against the run, and third in the league in rushing yards (312) and average rushing yards (78) allowed. They are yielding an average of only 2.9 yards per rush, while they are rushing for 4.4 yards per attempt. Pittsburgh is also second in the conference in defense inside the 20-yard line, allowing only 3 touchdowns in the 14 attempts.</p>
        <p>The Jets faced top-ranked defenses in recent games against Buffalo and Tampa Bay. Groh will warn his team this week that, although the Steelers' record is not as impressive as the Bills' or the Buccaneers', they remain a threat -- especially for a team like the Jets that has to guard against feeling too good about after playing inspired but uneven football in the first month of the season.</p>
        <p>''I was rooting for them,'' receiver Wayne Chrebet said of Pittsburgh's game against Jacksonville. ''There is nothing scarier than a winless team and a team like us coming off a bye. This is a very dangerous situation for us, especially coming off the bye.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>WAYNE CHREBET, christened the Green Lantern by a fan in a message to his Web site after his performance against Tampa Bay, wore a Green Lantern T-shirt today, a gift from an HBO crew. Chrebet also showed off the special Green Lantern plastic ring he now owns. Chrebet's new moniker is taken from the comic book character, but he was not quite clear on the legend. ''It's something like an average, normal man turns into a superhero,'' Chrebet said. ''I like that. They said the only color that affects me is yellow. Unless I wear the ring.'' Considering the Steelers' colors (black and gold), Chrebet better figure out a way to get that past the referees. . . . With the weekend off, Coach AL GROH went to an 85th birthday party in Syosset, N.Y., for JOE THOMAS, his football coach at Chaminade High School in Mineola, N.Y. Thomas also coached DAN ROONEY, the Steelers' owner, when he was at North Catholic High in Pittsburgh. So for whom will Thomas root for this weekend? ''Who went to the birthday party?'' Groh said. . . . Receiver VINCENT BRISBY said the groin injury that rendered him inactive against Tampa Bay is better, but he did not know what his role would be against Pittsburgh, especially after LAVERANUES COLES played well against the Bucs.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
