<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="04BULL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/nyregion/04BULL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DE113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE, ABBY GOODNOUGH and KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W; Goodnough, Abby; Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bulletin Board column discusses college and school news and events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Headmaster to Step Down</p>
        <p>LANCE ODDEN, who has been headmaster of the Taft School in Watertown, Conn., for 29 years, will retire at the end of this school year. The youngest person to lead a major American private school when he was named to the post at age 32, Mr. Odden founded the Taft Education Center, which provided training and help in designing Advanced Placement courses to more than 3,000 public-school teachers. Under his leadership, the boarding school's campus expanded substantially, as did its endowment, to $132 million from $3 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Headmaster to Step Down</p>
        <p>LANCE ODDEN, who has been headmaster of the Taft School in Watertown, Conn., for 29 years, will retire at the end of this school year. The youngest person to lead a major American private school when he was named to the post at age 32, Mr. Odden founded the Taft Education Center, which provided training and help in designing Advanced Placement courses to more than 3,000 public-school teachers. Under his leadership, the boarding school's campus expanded substantially, as did its endowment, to $132 million from $3 million.</p>
        <p>Web Radio for Teachers</p>
        <p>Scholastic Inc., the Manhattan publisher of children's books and instructional materials, has started an Internet radio program intended to provide teachers with education news, teaching tips and interviews with educators and child development experts. The half-hour program, Teacher Radio, is being offered  Monday through Thursday, beginning this week. NINA JAFFE, a faculty member at Bank Street College of Education, and LOU GIANSANTE, a former National Public Radio producer, are the hosts. The program is accessible from www.scholastic.com.</p>
        <p>Pre-Med, and Travel, Too</p>
        <p>Continuing its effort to send more students abroad for at least a semester, New York University has unveiled a new partnership with the University of London, where premedical students will be able to take required science courses and not lose ground in their efforts to get into medical school. L. JAY OLIVA, above, N.Y.U.'s president, and MARTIN LIPTON, its chairman, presided over the official opening of the N.Y.U. in London Center last week.</p>
        <p>The center, N.Y.U.'s sixth foreign study site, will also offer courses in other areas, including British civilization and culture and the political, social and economic issues of western Europe. DAVID-HILLEL RUBEN, a philosopher, will direct the center.</p>
        <p>Cash for Business Ideas</p>
        <p>Baruch College is about to join the growing list of business schools running contests in which students submit competing entrepreneurial plans. Two alumni, LARRY ZICKLIN, managing principal of the investment firm of Neuberger &amp; Berman, and ARTHUR S. AINSBERG, chief financial officer of the investment firm of Brahman Partners in New York, have agreed to sponsor the competition for three years. Winners will receive prizes up to $5,000. Especially promising business plans will be eligible for as much as $50,000 in seed money. BARRY DUMAS, the faculty coordinator, said the judges would be looking for ''anything hip and happening, not just the next pizza parlor.'' Preliminary plans are due Oct. 9 and final plans by next spring.</p>
        <p>Giving and Giving and . . .</p>
        <p>JAMES P. HYNES and his wife, ANNE MARIE, had already given $1.5 million to Iona College for a natural science center, to be named after them. Then, as everybody gathered to celebrate the center in late September, they added another $8.5 million. Most of the new money will go for an athletic center that will also be named for the Hyneses. Mr. Hynes, who graduated from Iona in 1969 and now serves as a trustee, is an investment manager and venture capitalist, and Mrs. Hynes runs the Analysis Group, a consulting firm.</p>
        <p>KATE ZERNIKE, ABBY GOODNOUGH and KAREN W. ARENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
