<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD CHAIN</title>
    <meta content="04CHAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EEDC103DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD CHAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Mold Ruins a Cheese</p>
        <p>Q.  If there is mold on cheese, should you discard the entire cheese? Or is it safe to eat the cheese as long as the mold is cut off?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Mold Ruins a Cheese</p>
        <p>Q.  If there is mold on cheese, should you discard the entire cheese? Or is it safe to eat the cheese as long as the mold is cut off?</p>
        <p>A.  It depends on the type of cheese. Mold on a hard or semifirm cheese like Swiss, Cheddar, Gouda, provolone or Parmesan can be trimmed off; cut at least half an inch past the mold on all sides. Use the cheese shortly afterward.</p>
        <p>Soft cheeses like cream cheese, ricotta, goat cheese, mozzarella, Brie and Camembert are spoiled if they develop mold and should be thrown out. Their higher moisture content allows mold to grow tendrils that can permeate the interior of the cheese, dispersing any toxic substances in the mold. Drier, harder cheeses do not have that problem.</p>
        <p>To discourage mold, keep cheese cold and dry, wrapped well in plastic wrap, aluminum foil or waxed paper. Change the wrapper every few times you take out the cheese.</p>
        <p>To Trim an Artichoke</p>
        <p>Q.  How do you trim an artichoke and then cut out the choke?</p>
        <p>A.  With a mature artichoke, carefully pull off and discard the outermost layer of petals. (Be careful: they have sharp spikes at their tips.) For recipes in which the artichoke is eaten by pulling off the petals, only one or two layers of petals need be removed. For dishes using the entire artichoke, strip away all the tough petals, leaving only the innermost ones.</p>
        <p>Using a large knife, trim off the top half-inch of the whole artichoke. Then, with kitchen scissors, snip the sharp tip from each remaining petal.</p>
        <p>The stems do not have to be trimmed unless you want the artichoke to stand straight up. Instead, just peel them with a paring knife. When cooked, they are as tender as the heart.</p>
        <p>To remove the choke, the hairy section that is unpleasant to eat, quarter the artichoke and use a paring knife to cut it out from the center. If you want to leave the artichoke whole, you can cook it and then cut out the choke.</p>
        <p>As you trim artichokes, immediately place them in a bowl of water with a lemon squeezed into it to keep them from discoloring.</p>
        <p>Baby artichokes do not require as much preparation. The chokes are too small and underdeveloped to be a problem and can be left intact. The outer petals need to be removed and the spikes and top have to be trimmed.</p>
        <p>Island Spiciness in Kuchela</p>
        <p>Q.  A few years ago I was introduced by a friend to a mango condiment from the West Indies called kuchela. What is it exactly?</p>
        <p>A.  Kuchela is a spicy condiment somewhat like chutney and is usually made from green mangos, with chilies, garlic and plenty of seasonings like ginger, allspice and mustard seeds. In the Caribbean, it is served with rotis and other dishes.</p>
        <p>It was traditionally made by mixing all the ingredients together and letting them preserve in the sun for two weeks.</p>
        <p>You can buy kuchela at West Indian markets. It is $4.99 for a three-and-a-half-ounce jar at Kalustyan's, 123 Lexington Avenue, at 28th Street; (212) 685-3451.</p>
        <p>MELISSA CLARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
