<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suharto's Son Admits Guilt In Maneuver To Stay Free</title>
    <meta content="Y04IND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/world/04INDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suharto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutomo Mandala Putra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wahid, Abdurrahman (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D6103DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suharto's Son Admits Guilt In Maneuver To Stay Free</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Indonesian Pres Suharto's son, Hutomo Mandala Putra, who is known as Tommy Suharto, admits he is guilty of corruption by asking for presidential pardon to avoid serving 18-month prison term, meeting with prosecutors; his lawyers say they do not expect Pres Abdurrahman Wahid to grant pardon, but that Hutomo will remain free to pursue appeal during three months it takes to process clemency bid; constitutional scholars score government's failure to detain him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stepping up pressure on the government, the youngest son of former President Suharto admitted today that he was guilty of corruption and asked for clemency to avoid serving an 18-month prison sentence imposed by the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with prosecutors, the son, Hutomo Mandala Putra, who is known as Tommy Suharto, formally requested a presidential pardon. His lawyers said that though the request amounted to an admission of guilt by Mr. Hutomo -- the first Suharto family member to be convicted of graft -- it was intended to prevent him from going to jail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stepping up pressure on the government, the youngest son of former President Suharto admitted today that he was guilty of corruption and asked for clemency to avoid serving an 18-month prison sentence imposed by the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with prosecutors, the son, Hutomo Mandala Putra, who is known as Tommy Suharto, formally requested a presidential pardon. His lawyers said that though the request amounted to an admission of guilt by Mr. Hutomo -- the first Suharto family member to be convicted of graft -- it was intended to prevent him from going to jail.</p>
        <p>They said they did not expect President Abdurrahman Wahid, who has publicly denounced Mr. Hutomo as a criminal, to grant a pardon. But they asserted that their client would remain free to pursue an appeal during the three months that the clemency application would take to be processed.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Supreme Court reversed a lower court decision and found Mr. Hutomo and a business partner guilty of corruption in a land deal that prosecutors said cost the Government $10.8 million but illegally enriched the two men, who were sentenced to 18 months in jail.</p>
        <p>While Indonesian law allows defendants to petition the Supreme Court to review its decisions, prosecutors and defense lawyers disagreed today about whether convicts could remain free during such appeals or requests for clemency.</p>
        <p>Even so, the government did not detain Mr. Hutomo, a millionaire businessman with a reputation for extravagant living. As he squeezed through a crowd of reporters and onlookers at the district attorney's office, Mr. Hutomo wore a nervous grin. Asked if in return for a pardon he would give back the money from the land transaction, which was made while his father was still in power, he said, ''Just wait and see.''</p>
        <p>Constitutional scholars were quick to denounce the government's decision not to detain Mr. Hutomo.</p>
        <p>''This shows that the government is not really serious about implementing and upholding law and justice, especially when it comes to the Suharto family,'' said Mulyana W. Kusumah, a professor of criminal law at the University of Indonesia.</p>
        <p>''If you are convicted today, you should begin serving your sentence today and any appeals will have to be made from behind bars,'' Mr. Kusumah said. ''Requests for clemency do not negate a court's ruling that a defendant go to jail.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutomo's clemency plea proved yet another obstacle to the government in its floundering pursuit of the family and friends of Mr.  Suharto. Prosecutors say corruption was widespread during his 32-year rule, which ended in 1998.</p>
        <p>The government suffered another major setback last week when a court pronounced Mr. Suharto, 79, too ill to stand trial on charges that he embezzled hundreds of millions from government charities. Though Mr. Suharto thus escaped prosecution, government authorities vowed to put Mr. Hutomo behind bars.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hutomo's lawyers, who have proved skillful in manipulating Indonesia's complex criminal law, have made it difficult for the government to make good on that promise.</p>
        <p>President Wahid, who is on an official visit to Canada and is expected to return to Indonesia on Wednesday, could not be reached for comment on the development. But officials of his administration said he was unlikely to pardon Mr. Hutomo, whom he ordered arrested last month in connection with bombings in Jakarta that officials said were intended to derail Mr. Suharto's trial.</p>
        <p>Even if Mr. Wahid denies clemency in this case, the public measure of his government's ability to administer justice impartially will be whether he is willing to imprison Mr. Hutomo.</p>
        <p>Nudirman Munir, a lawyer for Mr. Hutomo, said in an interview today that he expected the clemency request to take three months to process, during which he said the Parliament was likely to appoint a new Supreme Court justice who was not under Mr. Wahid's control and would assign impartial judges to review Mr. Hutomo's case.</p>
        <p>Indonesia's Supreme Court has 51 judges, three of whom heard the government's appeal and reversed Mr. Hutomo's acquittal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutomo is among the more notorious of Mr. Suharto's six children, who became vastly wealthy through their control of many state businesses and franchises. He established a wide network of businesses under the Humpuss Group of companies and in the 1990's set up a monopoly to handle the huge domestic trade in cloves.</p>
        <p>Mr. Munir said, ''I suggested to Tommy that he might consider seeking asylum in another country, but he told me that he was loyal to Indonesia and no matter what happened he would not abandon his native land.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
