<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Both Senate Candidates Blame Palestinians for New Violence</title>
    <meta content="04SENA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/politics/04SENA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DA113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Both Senate Candidates Blame Palestinians for New Violence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton and Repr Rick Lazio, on eve of peace talks aimed at ending spasm of violence between Israelis and Palestinians, both stake out positions critical of Palestinians, in nod to influence of Jewish voters; both call on US to consider cutting off aid to Palestinian Authority if violence continues (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of peace talks aimed at ending a spasm of violence between Israelis and Palestinians, the Senate candidates from New York both staked out positions critical of the Palestinians yesterday, in a nod to the influence of the Jewish vote.</p>
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican nominee, suggested that the blame lay squarely with the Palestinians for the violence in the West Bank, Gaza and East Jerusalem, in which at least 54 people have been killed. He called for the United States to cut off aid to the Palestinian Authority if the talks today in Paris, moderated by Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, collapse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of peace talks aimed at ending a spasm of violence between Israelis and Palestinians, the Senate candidates from New York both staked out positions critical of the Palestinians yesterday, in a nod to the influence of the Jewish vote.</p>
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio, the Republican nominee, suggested that the blame lay squarely with the Palestinians for the violence in the West Bank, Gaza and East Jerusalem, in which at least 54 people have been killed. He called for the United States to cut off aid to the Palestinian Authority if the talks today in Paris, moderated by Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, collapse.</p>
        <p>His Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton, also sided with the Israelis, and said last night that the United States should consider cutting off aid if violence persists.</p>
        <p>Both candidates have courted the Jewish vote, making synagogues and private meetings with Jewish leaders campaign stops. Polls suggest that the race is close, with Jewish voters seen as crucial to the outcome. In stepping up his criticism of the Palestinian role in the violence, Mr. Lazio seemed to be responding to criticism by some Republicans that he was ceding the Jewish vote to Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>While debates ensue over whether the visit by Ariel Sharon, the Israeli opposition leader, to a sacred Islamic site provoked the violence and whether the Palestinian reaction was spontaneous or orchestrated, Election Day realities have forced the Senate candidates to take sides.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the week, Mr. Lazio said President Clinton had not taken firm enough action to bring the parties to the negotiating table. Yesterday, Mr. Lazio suggested some conditions for the talks, putting the onus on the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''I hope the peace summit in Paris is productive and successful,'' Mr. Lazio told reporters after visiting East Islip High School on Long Island. ''I'm hopeful about that, but if it breaks down and there is a resumption of violence, I think we should make it very clear that there will be a cutoff of aid to the Palestinian Authority.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio said peace depended on whether Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, ''issues the instructions to stop the violence.''</p>
        <p>Likewise, Mrs. Clinton, taking a break from her upstate campaigning to hold a news conference on the Middle East, clearly sided with the Israelis, urging Mr. Arafat to end the bloodshed.</p>
        <p>''I believe we need a very strong, unequivocal public statement calling on everyone to cease the violence and respect the cease-fire,'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''There has to be a willingness to go out into the community and try to quell the emotion and anger and rage that seems to be fueling a lot of the young people.''</p>
        <p>While not mentioning Mr. Sharon by name, she defended the right of any Israeli to visit holy sites in Jerusalem. Mr. Sharon is accused of igniting the recent violence by leading a delegation to the compound Haram al Sharif, the most sacred Muslim site in Jerusalem. Israelis call the site the Temple Mount.</p>
        <p>''I certainly don't think visiting a holy site, as long as it is done respectfully, should be grounds for a violent reaction,'' said Mrs. Clinton, who met with business leaders in Hamburg, N.Y., and opened regional campaign headquarters in north Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The disturbances have provided the candidates with a platform to declare their support for Israel, but the Middle East has proved troublesome to both.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton was criticized by Jewish groups last year after embracing Mr. Arafat's wife, Suha, following a speech Mrs. Arafat gave blaming Israel for poisoning Palestinian children. The White House last month released a photograph of Mr. Lazio, who had criticized Mrs. Clinton for embracing Mrs. Arafat, grinning and shaking hands with Mr. Arafat, an image that shocked some Jews.</p>
        <p>The campaigns did not focus entirely on the Middle East. Mrs. Clinton said she had not yet begun preparing for Sunday's debate with Mr. Lazio -- beyond engaging in ''lots of prayer'' -- because she has been too busy raising money. She said she was adding dozens of fund-raisers to her schedule, including one that was held Monday night in Buffalo, because Mr. Lazio is raising more money than she is. Recent campaign figures show that Mr. Lazio has $6.2 million on hand, while Mrs. Clinton has $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio toured East Islip High School and spoke with students in civics classes. His campaign announced that his wife, Patricia, and Libby Pataki, the wife of Gov. George E. Pataki, were expected to visit Buffalo, Syracuse and Rochester today and the New York metropolitan area Thursday to promote awareness of breast and cervical cancer.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lazio, who is a nurse at a breast cancer clinic, appeared in a health-care-related commercial for her husband in July and is often at his side on the campaign trail. But this is the first time that she will venture on the stump without him and the first time that she will appear together with Mrs. Pataki.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
