<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disney to Deter Children From Some Areas of Its Web Sites</title>
    <meta content="Y04WEB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/technology/04WEB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DC113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disney to Deter Children From Some Areas of Its Web Sites</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SCHWARTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Online arm of Walt Disney Co says it will take steps to deter children from wandering into areas of its Web sites that contain inappropriate material (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The online arm of the Walt Disney Company said yesterday that it would take steps to deter children from wandering into areas of its Web sites that contain inappropriate material.</p>
        <p>The Walt Disney Internet Group made the pledge under an agreement with the Council of Better Business Bureaus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The online arm of the Walt Disney Company said yesterday that it would take steps to deter children from wandering into areas of its Web sites that contain inappropriate material.</p>
        <p>The Walt Disney Internet Group made the pledge under an agreement with the Council of Better Business Bureaus.</p>
        <p>Disney said it would do more to ascertain the ages of children registering for interactive activities on Disney sites. And it said it would bar children under 13 from certain areas, including chat rooms where lusty banter and explicit images can be found.</p>
        <p>The company also said it would increase the information it provides parents about what their children have signed up for, where they will be allowed to go, and what content might be a matter of concern. Those under 13 are already asked to supply a parent's e-mail address when registering.</p>
        <p>Because children in chat rooms may divulge information that can identify them, enforcement of the age restrictions is important to protect their privacy, officials of the Council of Better Business Bureaus said.</p>
        <p>The council found that Disney's sites asked for new members' ages in three categories: 12 or younger, 13 to 17, and 18 or over. It said such categories could ''encourage children to provide inaccurate information'' to get access to more adult fare.</p>
        <p>Disney agreed to remove the ages from the categories and to follow up with a request for the new user's birthdate. It said it would also take steps to prevent children from altering their birthdates, once registered, to get greater access.</p>
        <p>Protecting children in the online world has become the focus of several legislative and regulatory efforts. Congress passed the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998 to restrict the ways that commercial Web sites, like Disney's, collect information on children under 13. The Federal Trade Commission issued rules this year based on that law.</p>
        <p>For its part, Disney said it had consistently exceeded the requirements of laws governing children's online safety. ''We have been working to enhance our registration and notification systems, which have been above and beyond both the law and advocacy group guidelines,'' the company said.</p>
        <p>A federal regulator who oversees online advertising applauded yesterday's agreement. ''It's a good example of self-regulation working,'' said the official, Lee Peeler, associate director for advertising practices at the Federal Trade Commission. ''That frees up government resources to address more substantial issues'' like the recent commission action against Toysmart, a bankrupt company that tried to sell its mailing list data -- including information about children -- despite longstanding promises to keep such information private.</p>
        <p>An advocate of regulation of child-oriented Web sites, however, said that calling yesterday's agreement with Disney ''self-regulation'' only told half of the story. ''It isn't just self regulation -- it's self-regulation within a regulatory context,'' said Kathryn C. Montgomery, president of the Center for Media Education, a Washington-based policy group. ''Had we not passed the law to protect children's privacy, it's doubtful that there would be effective self-regulation.''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Lascoutx, director of the Children's Advertising Review Unit of the Council of Better Business Bureaus, said the child privacy act was a ''boon'' since in the past the bureaus had little to hold over recalcitrant offenders besides bad publicity. The law, she said, ''gives us somewhere to refer noncompliance.'' She estimated that just 2 percent of companies contacted over child privacy violations by her group refuse to change their ways.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
