<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Son Conceived To Provide Blood Cells For Daughter</title>
    <meta content="04BLOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/science/04BLOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grady, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Molly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wagner, John (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDC113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Son Conceived To Provide Blood Cells For Daughter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grady, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Nash, born in Aug, is first baby born from embryo conceived in laboratory dish and selected using genetic tests to produce child with exact traits needed to provide cell transplant for sibling ill with genetic disease; blood from his umbilical cord and placenta, which is rich in stem cells, was used for transplant for his sister, Molly, 6, who has rare and deadly form of anemia; use of tests to select embryo as tissue donor raises host of new ethical questions; Dr John Wagner, who performed transplant, says 10 other families are preparing to use procedure and two other mothers are already pregnant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time, genetic tests have been used to help parents have a baby with the exact traits needed to provide a cell transplant to treat a desperately ill sibling.</p>
        <p>The baby, Adam Nash, was born in Englewood, Colo., on Aug. 29. Adam was conceived in a laboratory dish along with several other embryos, and genetic tests conducted a short time later showed that only his tissues matched those of his 6-year-old sister, Molly, who has a deadly blood disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time, genetic tests have been used to help parents have a baby with the exact traits needed to provide a cell transplant to treat a desperately ill sibling.</p>
        <p>The baby, Adam Nash, was born in Englewood, Colo., on Aug. 29. Adam was conceived in a laboratory dish along with several other embryos, and genetic tests conducted a short time later showed that only his tissues matched those of his 6-year-old sister, Molly, who has a deadly blood disease.</p>
        <p>Molly received a transplant of his cells last week by Dr. John Wagner at Fairview-University Medical Center in Minneapolis. The transplant involved no pain or risk for Adam, because it used only the blood from his umbilical cord and placenta, blood that is normally discarded. The blood was given to his sister as a transfusion, which took about 45 minutes. Like bone marrow, cord blood is rich in stem cells, which can create a new blood supply and immune system in the recipient.</p>
        <p>Although Molly could have received a bone-marrow transplant from an unrelated donor, the odds of success would have been only 40 percent to 50 percent, compared with an 85 percent rate with cells from a  matched sibling like Adam.</p>
        <p>Doctors do not yet know whether Adam's cells will cure his sister, who has Fanconi anemia, a rare, inherited disease that often leads to leukemia.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, Dr. Wagner said Molly's blood tests were already improving. He said that if Molly needed additional stem cells, they could be taken from Adam's bone marrow. But he said that seemed unlikely.</p>
        <p>Genetic testing has already been used in hundreds of cases to help parents who carry disease-causing genes to select healthy embryos. But using the tests to select an embryo as a tissue donor raises a host of new ethical questions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jeffrey P. Kahn, director of the Center for Bioethics at the University of Minnesota, said, ''We've crossed the line that we really never had crossed before, selecting based on characteristics that are not the best for the child being born, but for somebody else.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants babies to be born strictly for the parts they could create,'' Dr. Kahn said, ''but by the same token I don't think we're willing as a society to ask people why they're having children and to say, 'That's not a good enough reason.' ''</p>
        <p>Dr. Wagner said 10 other families were preparing to use the procedure, to have babies who would be free of genetic disorders carried by the parents and who would also provide cord blood transplants for siblings who  have disorders that include sickle-cell anemia, thalassemia and Fanconi anemia. Two other mothers are already pregnant.</p>
        <p>To create the embryos, couples start with in vitro fertilization, in which the parents' sperm and eggs are joined in the laboratory. But then, instead of implanting the embryos in the uterus, doctors carry out another step. When the embryos reach the eight-cell stage, one cell is removed and tested genetically, a procedure called preimplantation genetic diagnosis. The testing is used to select embryos that do not have the same genetic disease as the sibling, but do have tissue compatible for transplant.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wagner said he and Molly's parents, Lisa and Jack Nash of Englewood, began discussing the possible use of genetic techniques to help Molly in 1997.</p>
        <p>The Nashes had been hoping to have more children but had decided against it because there was a one-in-four chance that the infant would have the same illness as Molly. Although the disease can be detected before birth and an affected fetus aborted, Mrs. Nash said, ''I could not have done that.'' The preimplantation genetic diagnosis allowed the Nashes to select an embryo that did not have Fanconi anemia but shared Molly's tissue type.</p>
        <p>''You could say it was an added perk to have Adam be the right bone marrow type, which would not hurt him in the least and would save Molly's life,'' Mrs. Nash said. ''We didn't have to think twice about it.''</p>
        <p>The Nashes had embryo screening done by doctors from the Reproductive Genetics Institute in Chicago, but despite several efforts at in vitro fertilization with compatible embryos, Mrs. Nash did not become pregnant.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Molly had developed a blood condition that Dr. Wagner called ''preleukemia.'' About a year ago, he arranged for a bone marrow transplant from an unrelated donor. ''I didn't think they could wait anymore,'' he said. But then Mrs. Nash called to say that she was pregnant.</p>
        <p>''We were sitting on the edge of our seats,'' Dr. Wagner said, ''hoping Molly would not develop leukemia during the nine months it would take for the baby to be born, and fortunately she didn't.''</p>
        <p>On Sept. 26, Molly sat holding Adam in her lap as his cells dripped into her veins, and, her mother said, the little girl explained to visitors, ''My brother's going to give me some of his blood to make me feel better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
