<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Greening Of the Martini</title>
    <meta content="04TINI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/living/04TINI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apples</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D8103DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Greening Of the Martini</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marin, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Marin comments on crisp new cocktail known as the apple martini; recipes; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE long, sticky summer of the chocolate martini is at last behind us. Its replacement is a crisp new cocktail made from vodka and some variety of apple spirit, with a Granny Smith slice floating on top.</p>
        <p>The apple martini is officially in season. Nutritious and delicious? Well, let's say sweet and refreshing. And in sufficient quantity, capable of producing a healthy -- you might even say apple-cheeked -- glow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE long, sticky summer of the chocolate martini is at last behind us. Its replacement is a crisp new cocktail made from vodka and some variety of apple spirit, with a Granny Smith slice floating on top.</p>
        <p>The apple martini is officially in season. Nutritious and delicious? Well, let's say sweet and refreshing. And in sufficient quantity, capable of producing a healthy -- you might even say apple-cheeked -- glow.</p>
        <p>What cocktail could be more Big Apple? One a day keeps the therapist away! Too bad it was invented in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''Five or six months ago, a friend came back from L.A. and she was telling me about it,'' said Julie Reiner, the bar manager at C3, a restaurant in Greenwich Village. Shortly after Ms. Reiner began serving it,  the apple martini replaced the blood-orange Cosmopolitan as her most-requested drink.</p>
        <p>Too new to be in any of the standard cocktail bibles, the apple martini has already mutated into abundant variations. At a magazine party catered by Mood Food at the Morgan Library two weeks ago, Slushee versions made the rounds: pureed apples and Calvados, run through a blender. The cocktail menu at Hudson Cafeteria, the restaurant and bar in Ian Schrager's new Hudson hotel on West 58th Street, includes a Polish Apple, which sounds like a euphemism for a stale potato but turns out to be Zubrovka vodka and honey shaken with apple juice.</p>
        <p>City Hall, in TriBeCa, started serving apple martinis a year and a half ago, after Robert De Niro came in asking for one and the bartender was unable to oblige. The next day, the owners ordered a case of DeKuyper Sour Apple Pucker, a 30-proof bright green liqueur advertised on the label as ''sweet and sour schnapps.''</p>
        <p>Frank Smith, the daytime barman at City Hall, recounted the De Niro business -- which did not go down on his watch -- as he muddled two thin slices of Granny Smith (no relation) with one ounce of Pucker and an ounce of Berentzen's apple schnapps, in the bottom of a big glass he usually uses to make an old-fashioned.  He uses both liqueurs because he feels the Pucker is too sour and the Berentzen's not sour enough. Ms. Reiner of C3 refuses to use any liqueur at all on the grounds that it makes the drink taste like a Jolly Rancher.</p>
        <p>She first infuses Skyy vodka with apples.  Then, in a martini glass that has been touched with no more than a rinse of Pucker, she adds the vodka and a splash of Martinelli's sparkling cider.</p>
        <p>''I'd heard of apple Manhattans,'' Mr. Smith said. ''And mixing apple with bourbon and rye, the brown liquors.'' Applejack, also brown, would hardly work in a martini. But not even in his studies with the cocktail king Dale DeGroff had he come across the apple martini.</p>
        <p>He shook the apple mixture with two and a half ounces of Ketel One vodka, strained it into a medium martini glass and balanced a wedge of Granny Smith on the side. The drink landed on the bar with a slight fizz from the muddled apples.</p>
        <p>''If one gets ordered, it's like wildfire,'' Mr. Smith said. ''I think it's the color. It's very visual, a nice light green.''</p>
        <p>Diane Gordon, the owner of Entertaining Ideas Catering in Manhattan, has a sort of cold toddy twist on the apple martini. She mixes two ounces of Ketel One with half an ounce of cinnamon vodka, an ounce of Calvados and two ounces of apple cider or juice.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, the young swingers have taken to drinking their apple martinis with sushi. Some are known to pound shots of the stuff until the fear of violence impels their hosts to cut them off.</p>
        <p>''They go a little wild,'' said Michael Cardenas, an owner of the two Los Angeles Sushi Roku restaurants. ''The ladies love it, the green-apple sweetness of it, it's a turn-on.'' First the women, then the men started drinking them, Mr. Cardenas said. His vodka sales have skyrocketed, he said, since  customers started drinking apple martinis as a sake substitute. One of his restaurants used to go through three or four bottles a night, but now it's up to seven or eight, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's become like a staple drink here in L.A.,'' said Mr. Cardenas, who uses two ounces of Smirnoff vodka and one of Pucker. ''It was a specialty drink a year and a half ago. Now, it's a must-have item.''</p>
        <p>Linq, a fusion-y Los Angeles restaurant that opened in January, adds a splash of 7-Up to pump some air into what might otherwise be a slightly cough-syrupy mix of three parts vodka to two parts Pucker.</p>
        <p>''It's our signature,'' said Pierre Vilay, the manager. ''Everybody talks about it.'' He said his restaurant was the first and only one he knew of serving apple martinis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cardenas was more modest. ''It started at Lola's,'' he said, naming another trend-conscious Los Angeles restaurant. ''They make the best apple martinis in town.'' His opinion, Mr. Cardenas allowed, may have been influenced by Lola's Big Gulp portion: an eight-ounce martini glass.</p>
        <p>Is Lola's really the ur-source, the Tigris and Euphrates of apple martini culture? Loren Dunsworth, who opened Lola's in West Hollywood four years ago, confidently takes credit for the craze. She said it started at a Fourth of July party three and a half years ago.</p>
        <p>''We had a bottle of DeKuyper's lying around and the bartenders were playing around with it,'' she said. ''One of them threw it in with some Ketel One, and we called it an Adam's Apple Martini because the bartender's name was Adam.''</p>
        <p>The recipe was a one-to-one pour -- a DeKuyper-heavy mix Ms. Dunsworth describes as a ''horrible martini.'' Her customers were more enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''It was like heroin!'' she said. ''There were so many drunk girls we started limiting people to two, and for six months I took it off the menu.''</p>
        <p>Demand compelled her to put it back. Word spread, eventually to New York, where DeKuyper's magical green elixir is still hard to find at most liquor stores. ''I've had several bartenders from New York come in and say, 'What is this apple martini people keep asking me for?' '' she said.</p>
        <p>A word of caution as this drink spreads around town: You're not supposed to eat the worm.</p>
        <p>LINQ'S APPLE MARTINI  Adapted from Linq restaurant, Los Angeles  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1 ounce DeKuyper Sour Apple Pucker  1 ounce vodka</p>
        <p>3/4 ounce sweet and sour mix  Splash of 7-Up  1 thin round slice of Granny Smith apple.</p>
        <p>Mix liquid ingredients together in a cocktail shaker with ice. Strain and pour into a martini glass. Place apple slice on top.  Yield: 1 cocktail.</p>
        <p>SOUR APPLE MARTINI  Adapted from City Hall restaurant  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1/4 Granny Smith apple, cut into three wedges  1 ounce apple schnapps  1 ounce DeKuyper Sour Apple Pucker  2 ounces vodka.</p>
        <p>In a cocktail shaker, muddle 2 apple pieces, mashing the pulp into a smooth paste. Add both schnapps and vodka. Shake with ice, then strain into a cocktail glass. Garnish with remaining apple wedge, and serve.  Yield: 1 cocktail.</p>
        <p>APPLE CIDER MARTINI  Adapted from Entertaining Ideas Catering  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>2 ounces vodka  1 ounce Calvados</p>
        <p>1/2 ounce cinnamon vodka  2 ounces apple cider or apple juice.</p>
        <p>Fill a martini glass with ice water, and set aside. Pour ingredients into a cocktail shaker over ice. Stir vigorously with a cocktail spoon. Pour ice water out of prepared glass. Strain apple martini into glass.  Yield: 1 cocktail.</p>
        <p>APPLE CIDER MARTINI  Adapted from Entertaining Ideas Catering  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>2 ounces vodka  1 ounce Calvados</p>
        <p>1/2 ounce cinnamon vodka  2 ounces apple cider or apple juice.</p>
        <p>Fill a martini glass with ice water, and set aside. Pour ingredients into a cocktail shaker over ice. Stir vigorously with a cocktail spoon. Pour ice water out of prepared glass. Strain apple martini into glass.  Yield: 1 cocktail.</p>
        <p>GREEN APPLE MARTINI  Adapted from Mood Food Catering  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1 ounce vodka  1 ounce Calvados  1 ounce frozen green apple puree (see note)</p>
        <p>1/2 cup crushed ice.</p>
        <p>Place all ingredients in a blender to combine. Pour in martini glass, and serve.  Yield: 1 cocktail.</p>
        <p>Note: One kilogram of frozen green apple puree, made by Sicoly of Italy, is $8.50 at Buon Italia in the Chelsea Market, 75 Ninth Avenue (15th Street).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
