<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida Appeals Court Rules In Favor of Voucher Program</title>
    <meta content="Y04VOU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/national/04VOUC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DC113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida Appeals Court Rules In Favor of Voucher Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three-judge Florida appeals court panel rules state can use taxpayer-financed vouchers for students in poor-performing schools who cannot afford private school tuition; overturns trial court ruling; teachers' unions, other voucher opponents to appeal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Florida appellate court ruled today that the state could use taxpayer-financed vouchers for students in poor-performing schools who could not afford private school tuition.</p>
        <p>A three-judge panel of the First District Court of Appeals in Tallahassee ruled unanimously that a trial court erred in March in ruling that the vouchers violated the State Constitution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Florida appellate court ruled today that the state could use taxpayer-financed vouchers for students in poor-performing schools who could not afford private school tuition.</p>
        <p>A three-judge panel of the First District Court of Appeals in Tallahassee ruled unanimously that a trial court erred in March in ruling that the vouchers violated the State Constitution.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for various teachers' unions and other groups who sued to block the program said they would appeal to the Florida Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>The decision means that the state voucher program, which began last year with 51 students, can continue.</p>
        <p>In a 16-page decision, Judge Charles Kahn Jr., writing for the court, said that nothing clearly prohibited the State Legislature from allowing the use of public funds for private school education.</p>
        <p>Judge Kahn said the State Constitution does not ''unalterably hitch the requirement to make adequate provision for education to a single, specified engine, that being the public school system.''</p>
        <p>Florida has been a battleground in the debate over vouchers. Last year, with the support of Gov. Jeb Bush, a Republican, the Legislature enacted a voucher law that provided private school tuition payments in the worst-performing schools. But, the next day, a group of parents and teachers' unions sued, arguing that the law was unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Critics of the voucher law, who include the Florida Education Association and the Florida Parent Teacher Association, argued that the State Constitution prohibited lawmakers from providing free education outside the public school system because it called for a ''uniform, efficient, safe, secure and high-quality system of free public schools.''</p>
        <p>But supporters of the law said that the Constitution did not prohibit that type of use of taxpayer money and that the state funded similar programs for disabled children and juvenile offenders.</p>
        <p>''The kids won a big one today,'' said Clint Bolick, litigation director of the Institute for Justice in Washington and a defending lawyer in the case. ''This brings new life to a very important program. It is a life preserver for these kids.''</p>
        <p>Those opposed to the program said they believed that it was a disservice to everyone involved.</p>
        <p>''This is a terrible education program,'' said Bob Chanin, the general counsel of the National Education Association, who is one of the plaintiffs. ''Too bad the court of appeals did not put it out of its misery.''</p>
        <p>In Tallahassee today, Governor Bush said he was gratified by the court's decision.</p>
        <p>''Nothing in Florida's Constitution prohibits the state from allowing the use of public funds for private school education,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Particularly when used to help children trapped in chronically failing schools.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
