<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't count on next year's air fare increases holding to the 5% that has been projected.</title>
    <meta content="Y04TRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/business/04TRAV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TRAVEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Express Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Business Travel (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E1DC113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't count on next year's air fare increases holding to the 5% that has been projected.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Sharkey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Express Co, which predicted in September that typical business air fares would increase about 5 percent in 2001, now says increase in likely to be greater because of carriers adding surcharges for oil price increases; final forecast for 2001 will be published in January (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the preliminary 2001 business-travel forecast it released last month, American Express predicted that typical business air fares would increase about 5 percent next year. With airlines wailing about oil prices and slapping on fare increases and surcharges, the question now for corporate travel departments is: Will the number hold?</p>
        <p>Don't count on it. American Express said yesterday that the typical domestic business fare in July -- $1,078 round trip -- was 11 percent higher than July 1999, partly because of airline fare increases earlier this year. According to Rusty Carpenter, the vice president of American Express Consulting Services, the more recent round of broad-based fare rises, and any that might follow this year, could be bad news for companies hoping to hold the line at 5 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the preliminary 2001 business-travel forecast it released last month, American Express predicted that typical business air fares would increase about 5 percent next year. With airlines wailing about oil prices and slapping on fare increases and surcharges, the question now for corporate travel departments is: Will the number hold?</p>
        <p>Don't count on it. American Express said yesterday that the typical domestic business fare in July -- $1,078 round trip -- was 11 percent higher than July 1999, partly because of airline fare increases earlier this year. According to Rusty Carpenter, the vice president of American Express Consulting Services, the more recent round of broad-based fare rises, and any that might follow this year, could be bad news for companies hoping to hold the line at 5 percent.</p>
        <p>The preliminary forecast was intended to help corporate travel departments put their budgets together for next year, he said. The final forecast for 2001 will be published in January.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carpenter wouldn't hazard a guess on how much the air fare estimate might rise, except to say, ''Clearly, what's gone on in the last few weeks is putting lots of pressure on our preliminary forecast, and depending on what happens in the next few months it would put upward pressure on that number, for sure.''</p>
        <p>The typical business fare as calculated by American Express reflects what Mr. Carpenter informally calls the ''rack rate'' -- the lowest available fully refundable average coach fare, as calculated from more than 300 key business-travel routes. But in air travel, as in hotels, not everybody pays retail. American Express tracks another benchmark price, the average fare paid, which reflects the actual air fares paid by corporate clients.</p>
        <p>In July, the average round-trip fare paid was $624, 6 percent higher than July 1999. Since January 1996, this benchmark has increased 36 percent, while the rack rate has shot up 65 percent.</p>
        <p>That gap, which Mr. Carpenter said was steadily widening, reflects tighter and stricter company travel-policy planning that is often the talk in airport lounges when business travelers congregate to compare notes and complaints about the travails of life on the go. Increasingly, corporate travelers are required to adhere to stringent company travel policies that limit choice but enable travel managers to drive harder bargains by delivering specified business volumes to selected airlines, hotels and other suppliers.</p>
        <p>At some companies, business travelers are also being prodded to use in-house online booking portals that are jointly managed by the corporate travel department and a big outside travel agency. Mr. Carpenter said that this trend had recently begun to accelerate. At companies offering this option, he continued, about 15 percent of travelers book online, saving about 20 percent. This, however, requires more advance travel planning and more careful monitoring of the cheaper, nonrefundable tickets, which usually expire within a year and sometimes are lost when travel plans change.</p>
        <p>With a lot of bad blood remaining from this summer's calamitous period of delays and terrible service, the airlines, meanwhile, appear to be paying more attention to the new corporate travel department muscle-flexing -- though not by lowering fares.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing, in some instances, airlines are doing such things as waiving change fees, or offering various perks and upgrades to try to placate the corporate customer for the bad service,'' Mr. Carpenter said. ''In some instances, the airlines are actually being proactive about it, not waiting for the client to ask. Our perception is they are strategically targeting accounts they think may be at risk.''</p>
        <p>Ranking Airports</p>
        <p>The article rating domestic airports in the October issue of Consumer Reports got a lot of press that struck me as pretty unskeptical. I was baffled by the magazine's approach. For example, John Wayne International Airport in Anaheim, Calif., which I regard as one of the more pleasant and convenient airports in the country, got the lowest ranking for services. Fort Lauderdale-Hollywood International in Florida -- in my opinion the domestic airport most resembling a film-noir bus station, but with worse food -- got better-than-average marks. Logan International in Boston came in second, after Hartsfield International in Atlanta, over all.</p>
        <p>Go figure. Consumer Reports aside, I'm curious, fellow travelers. Which airports do you consider the best and the worst, and why?</p>
        <p>Car Talk</p>
        <p>Trip for trip, most business travel is done by car. The most expensive metropolitan area to operate an automobile? Los Angeles, at $9,254 a year, according to a study by Runzheimer International. Philadelphia; Providence, R.I.; Bridgeport, Conn.; and Detroit make up the rest of the top five. The New York metropolitan area is No. 9. The estimates take into account depreciation and routine costs for a 2000 Ford Taurus, based on a four-year, 60,000 mile trade-in cycle. The cheapest place to drive? Sioux Falls, N.D., at $6,171.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TRAVEL The Business Travel column appears each Wednesday. E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">The Business Travel column appears each Wednesday. E-mail: jsharkey@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
