<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A beer importer sponsors a series of concerts, but is keeping the tickets under tight control.</title>
    <meta content="Y04ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/business/04ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beck's Beer</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Third Eye Blind (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0DF113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A beer importer sponsors a series of concerts, but is keeping the tickets under tight control.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Stamler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Beck's beer is sponsoring series of concerts by Third Eye Blind in Chicago, New York and San Francisco; only way tickets can be obtained is through Beck's, which is running national sweepstakes to distribute tickets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE San Francisco band Third Eye Blind -- which produced the hummable tune ''Semi-Charmed Life'' in 1997 -- has sold millions of records and attracted legions of fans, including the decision makers at the company that imports Beck's beer into the United States. They are using the band in a new marketing campaign.</p>
        <p>''Our target group of consumers is 21-  to 29-year-olds, primarily male, people who are very open to trying new things,'' said Rainer Meyrer, executive vice president for marketing at Beck's North America, which is based in Stamford, Conn., and is a subsidiary of Brauerei Beck of Bremen, Germany. ''And Third Eye Blind fits right in with this target group.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE San Francisco band Third Eye Blind -- which produced the hummable tune ''Semi-Charmed Life'' in 1997 -- has sold millions of records and attracted legions of fans, including the decision makers at the company that imports Beck's beer into the United States. They are using the band in a new marketing campaign.</p>
        <p>''Our target group of consumers is 21-  to 29-year-olds, primarily male, people who are very open to trying new things,'' said Rainer Meyrer, executive vice president for marketing at Beck's North America, which is based in Stamford, Conn., and is a subsidiary of Brauerei Beck of Bremen, Germany. ''And Third Eye Blind fits right in with this target group.''</p>
        <p>So much so, in fact, that Beck's is featuring the band in three concerts between Nov. 30 and Dec. 9 in Chicago, New York and San Francisco. And it will be spending nearly $5 million to promote the shows, billed as the company's second annual Spotlight Concert Series. The first series, held last year, featured lesser-known acts like the alternative band Filter. That is a hefty chunk of the roughly $40 million in total marketing expenditures, which includes the band's fee, that the brand will make this year, said Mr. Meyrer, who added that ad spending, in millions of dollars, would be ''between the high teens and the high 20's.''</p>
        <p>Of course, corporate sponsorships of rock concerts or rock tours are nothing new. And most of today's rock stars apparently do not feel that their artistic integrity or anti-establishment credibility are compromised when Sears or Pepsi-Cola banners are hanging over the stages at their performances. But the Beck's deal with Third Eye Blind is exclusive; the concerts, in effect, are private. No tickets will be sold, and the only way prospective audience members will be able to obtain them is through Beck's.</p>
        <p>To distribute the tickets, the company is running a national sweepstakes, which began on Sept. 15 and is supported by television commercials on ESPN, radio advertising and a print campaign in magazines including Playboy, Maxim, Men's Fitness and Rolling Stone. Entry forms for the contest will be available at beer retailers, and there will be 50 winners nationwide, each of whom will receive two tickets to a show in the city of their choice, transportation, hotel and a chance to meet the band.</p>
        <p>Beginning in early November, one rock radio station in each market -- WXRK in New York, WKQX in Chicago and KLLC in San Francisco -- will also be giving away tickets to the concerts, up to 20 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>But most of the tickets have been reserved for Beck's national sales force, Mr. Meyrer said, who will do ''local promotions or even small sweepstakes, if that is allowed.''</p>
        <p>''We could have sponsored a concert tour,'' he said. ''But we decided we wanted to go a different route and to offer a different experience.'' The total number of tickets available will be relatively small, he said -- the concert venues, like Irving Plaza in New York, hold only 1,200 to 1,500 people -- but Beck's expects that the impact of the concerts will be great.</p>
        <p>''Our wholesalers tell us that this is exactly what we need to attract customers to our brand franchise,'' Mr. Meyrer said.</p>
        <p>They may well be right, to judge by the experience of some other companies that have held private concerts for their customers, like American Express, which introduced its Blue card in a private Central Park concert last year, and Best Buy,  which heralded its arrival in the New York market last month with a private Central Park concert by Sting for 25,000 fans that was broadcast over the Westwood One radio network.</p>
        <p>''We thought it was a statement about who we are as a company, and about music and technology,'' said Mike Linton, Best Buy's senior vice president for strategic marketing. Sting was chosen, he said, because of his broad appeal and his ties to New York, where he spends a great deal of time.</p>
        <p>''In a market where it's hard to get noticed,'' Mr. Linton said, ''the show exceeded our expectations in terms of energy and as breakthrough news.''</p>
        <p>How will Beck's measure the success of its concerts? According to the July 10, 2000, issue of Modern Brewery Age, a trade journal, the brand was sixth last year in sales of imported beer in the United States, with a 3.6 percent share of total imports, or 639,290 barrels. That is way behind the leader, Corona, the Mexican beer, which sold 5,574,956 barrels and had 31.3 percent share of the import market and the No. 2 brand, Heineken, which sold 3,412,108 barrels, or 19.2 percent. And while Beck's sales were actually up 4.2 percent in 1999 compared with figures in the previous year, it has slipped behind Foster's of Australia, the No. 5 import, and No. 4 Tecate, from Mexico, both of which used to sell less than Beck's. The other brand rounding out the top five is Labatt of Canada, at No. 3.</p>
        <p>''We will be looking to our display activities, to see how many stores take them,'' said Mr. Meyrer, who acknowledged that it would be impossible to show a direct connection between the concerts and beer sales.</p>
        <p>''And we will check with our sales force and our wholesalers about effectiveness, and about the feedback from retailers.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
