<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Germany Celebrates a Decade of Unity With 'a Bit of Pride'</title>
    <meta content="Y04GER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/world/04GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">France-International Relations-Germany</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dresden (Ger)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dusseldorf (Germany)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiegel, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rau, Johannes (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/The Rhineland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/The Rhineland/Dusseldorf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDE113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Germany Celebrates a Decade of Unity With 'a Bit of Pride'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>DRESDEN, Germany, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Germany marks 10th anniversary of its unification with modest celebration, Dresden; day is marred by firebomb attack on synagogue, Dusseldorf; no one is hurt in attack and damage is minimal; police arrest two youths linked to rightist groups; Jewish leader Paul Spiegel, at Dresden rite, scores German failure to demonstrate against far right; questions government effort to rebuild Jewish life in Germany by attracing Jews from former Soviet Union; Pres Johannes Rau calls for fight against anti-foreigner sentiment; French Pres Jacques Chirac gives keynote speech; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Germany celebrated a decade of unity today with speeches that dwelled on the country's place at the heart of a unifying Europe. But the day was marred by a firebomb attack on a synagogue in Dusseldorf.</p>
        <p>''Germany is a strong democracy at the center of Europe, globally respected, surrounded by friends,'' said President Johannes Rau, whose office is largely ceremonial. ''We have no reason for self-satisfaction, but can allow ourselves a bit of pride.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Germany celebrated a decade of unity today with speeches that dwelled on the country's place at the heart of a unifying Europe. But the day was marred by a firebomb attack on a synagogue in Dusseldorf.</p>
        <p>''Germany is a strong democracy at the center of Europe, globally respected, surrounded by friends,'' said President Johannes Rau, whose office is largely ceremonial. ''We have no reason for self-satisfaction, but can allow ourselves a bit of pride.''</p>
        <p>It was a typically understated observation in the midst of an understated ceremony in a country still wary of ostentatious celebration. No German flags adorned the interior of Dresden's magnificent Semper Opera House, and the uplifting music of Bach was balanced with a gloomy modern composition.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no other state would celebrate its nationhood with such modesty -- President Jacques Chirac of France gave the keynote speech. But, as the attack in Dusseldorf showed, it is difficult to escape history in this country.</p>
        <p>The police said assailants threw three gasoline bombs against the glass of the synagogue's main entrance after throwing bricks at the door to try to open it. A neighbor who saw the attack quickly extinguished the fire. Nobody was injured, and the damage was minimal.</p>
        <p>Two youths, ages 15 and 16, were arrested early today, several hours after the attack late Monday night, and the police said they had connections to rightist groups. But they were not immediately charged, and their exact role remained unclear. Some witnesses said there were four assailants in all.</p>
        <p>The firebombing follows a terrorist bomb attack in Dusseldorf in July that wounded 10 immigrants from the former Soviet Union, 7 of them Jewish. The culprits have not been found.</p>
        <p>Paul Spiegel, the leader of the the main association of German Jews, reacted angrily. Speaking in Dresden, where he was invited for the 10th-anniversary celebrations, he said that Germany is a place where tens of thousands of people are ready to demonstrate against new laws to curb violent dogs, but only a few hundred are ready to demonstrate against the far right.</p>
        <p>''After such repeated attacks on synagogues, one is justifiably entitled to ask whether it was right to rebuild Jewish communities in Germany,'' he said. For a man who normally measures his language, it was an unusually vehement outburst.</p>
        <p>Most of the 6,300 Jews in Dusseldorf, a western city, have arrived in the last decade, part of a large influx of Jews from the former Soviet Union lured by the generous welcome offered by German authorities determined to rebuild Jewish life in Germany. The number of Jews in Germany has risen to more than 100,000 from less than 30,000 when the Berlin Wall fell. Before Hitler, the figure was about 500,000.</p>
        <p>In a second attack on Monday night, the police said, swastikas were scrawled on the bell tower at the former Nazi concentration camp of Buchenwald in eastern Germany. Over 50,000 people died in the camp, near Weimar, during the Nazi era.</p>
        <p>The incidents appeared to be the work of Germany's small but well organized rightist, anti-immigrant and anti-Semitic groups.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Rau did not refer specifically to the Dusseldorf attack, but he said it is essential to combat ''anti-foreigner sentiment'' in Germany. Such sentiment is concentrated in, but not exclusive to,  eastern Germany, where high unemployment and the frustrations of adapting to life in a united Germany have fed rightist movements.</p>
        <p>The president suggested that although the country is suffering from some ''self-inflicted disappointments'' at the pace of integration, it has much to celebrate. ''European and German unity are two sides of the same coin,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In perhaps the most moving of the speeches to an audience that included Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, Lothar de Maiziere, the last leader of East Germany before its dissolution, alluded in thinly veiled terms to the disappointments of many eastern Germans with the materialism of the west.</p>
        <p>It often appears, he said, that freedom as interpreted in the west is merely the freedom to ''amass personal advantage.'' But freedom, rightly understood, should include a sense of responsibility to future generations and an awareness that real prosperity also embraces the notion of justice for all.</p>
        <p>In a remark that appeared aimed at the many western Germans who tend to look down on eastern areas they have never visited, Mr. de Maiziere said, ''Freedom is also the freedom of others to think differently.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac chose as his central theme the ''unity of the destinies'' of France and Germany, both committed to building a united Europe that will soon draw post-communist neighbors of Germany like Poland and the Czech Republic into the European Union. ''We await you with impatience,'' he declared to leaders of these Central European countries.</p>
        <p>But 11 years have gone by since the fall of the Berlin Wall, and no Central European state has been admitted to the European Union. Obstacles remain, not the least of which is how to make decisions in a union that already has 15 members and could become hopelessly cumbersome with 18 or more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac reserved his highest praise for Helmut Kohl, who did not attend the celebration because he felt snubbed by an invitation that did not include an opportunity to speak. The former chancellor has been involved in a party financing scandal that has damaged his opposition Christian Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Kohl will remain in history as a great German and a great European,'' Mr. Chirac said. Referring to the way Mr. Kohl seized a limited opportunity to unite the country, Mr. Chirac added: ''It needed courage to move so fast.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
