<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Random House to Aid Holocaust Memoir Project</title>
    <meta content="04SURV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/arts/04SURV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Holocaust Survivors' Memoirs Project</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Random House</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Jewish Congress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiesel, Elie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D8103DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Random House to Aid Holocaust Memoir Project</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Random House pledges $1 million to Holocaust Survivors' Memoirs Project set up by World Jewish Congress to find and publish written accounts of those who suffered under Nazis during World War II; Elie Wiesel will serve as honorary chmn of project; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Random House has pledged $1 million to the Holocaust Survivors' Memoirs Project set up by the World Jewish Congress to find and publish the written accounts of those who suffered under the Nazis during World War II.</p>
        <p>Elie Wiesel, the author of ''Night,'' a memoir of Auschwitz, among many other works, will serve as honorary chairman of the project. ''I have been urging it for years and years and years,'' he said recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Random House has pledged $1 million to the Holocaust Survivors' Memoirs Project set up by the World Jewish Congress to find and publish the written accounts of those who suffered under the Nazis during World War II.</p>
        <p>Elie Wiesel, the author of ''Night,'' a memoir of Auschwitz, among many other works, will serve as honorary chairman of the project. ''I have been urging it for years and years and years,'' he said recently.</p>
        <p>As Holocaust survivors grow old and die, Mr. Wiesel's effort to preserve their memoirs has taken on a new urgency. Steven Spielberg, through his Survivors of the Shoah Visual History Foundation, and Geoffrey Hartman, through the Fortunoff  Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies at Yale, have preserved survivors' spoken memories. But despite well-known exceptions like Primo Levi's ''Survival in Auschwitz,'' Alexander Donat's ''Holocaust Kingdom'' and Anne Frank's ''Diary,''  the vast majority of Holocaust memoirs remain unpublished and in the hands of survivors and their descendants.</p>
        <p>Others are in the archives of Holocaust remembrance institutions like Yad Vashem in Jerusalem and the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington. One aim of the project will be to translate the accounts, written in many different languages.</p>
        <p>The survivors' ''stories are all unique and what they have to say nobody else has to say,'' Mr. Wiesel said, adding, ''They should feel that people want to know what they went through.''</p>
        <p>Wherever he goes, Mr. Wiesel said, he urges survivors to write down their memories. He said: ''They say: 'We are writing. We are doing what you told us; now help us publish.' I would send the manuscripts to publishers, and they say the field is saturated.'' He said he hoped to bring out about 10 books a year. ''And if we have the means, I will suggest more,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Menachem Z. Rosensaft, director and editor in chief of the project and founding chairman of the International Network of Children of Jewish Holocaust Survivors, said that the project would spend six to seven months collecting material.</p>
        <p>Among publishers, he said, Random House will have the right of first refusal. Thereafter, the project may decide to reach an arrangement with other publishing houses or publish accounts on its own through the World Jewish Congress, Mr. Rosensaft said.</p>
        <p>''We might want to do an anthology of a particular camp or particular ghetto,'' he said. He added that he hoped that the first books would be published at the end of 2001 and that the project would secure ''substantially more'' funds.</p>
        <p>Random House's parent company, Bertelsmann, has been accused in the past of misleading the public about its activities during the Nazi period. In January an independent commission appointed by the company to investigate its corporate history issued a preliminary report saying that Bertelsmann had been closed during the war not because it opposed Hitler, as it had claimed, but because it was deemed not critical to the military effort. The commission reported that Bertelsmann was the largest supplier of books to the German military, and that Heinrich Mohn, a leader of the company, contributed money to the SS.</p>
        <p>Peter Olson, the chief executive of Random House, said that criticism of the company had nothing to do with its decision to support the publication of the accounts. ''This is a project Random House would have done on its own,'' he said, calling it ''a project of unique historical importance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosensaft said that manuscripts could be sent to the Holocaust Survivors' Memoirs Project, the World Jewish Congress, 501 Madison Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>''We want every survivor to know that if a manuscript arrives, it will be reviewed and kept in a special place with great respect,'' Mr. Wiesel said. ''I want eventually to establish a principle that every manuscript should be published.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
