<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christie's Ordered to Answer in Antitrust Suit</title>
    <meta content="Y04AUCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/business/04AUCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Lewis A (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubman, A Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDD113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christie's Ordered to Answer in Antitrust Suit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL and RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol; Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Lewis A Kaplan, hearing civil antitrust lawsuit against Sotheby's and Christie's, questions Christie's good faith in refusing to answer questions posed by defendant A Alfred Traubman, former chairman of Sotheby's, and orders auction house to respond or face possible sanctions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal judge hearing a civil antitrust lawsuit against Sotheby's and Christie's yesterday questioned Christie's good faith in refusing to answer questions posed by one of the defendants and ordered the auction house to respond or face possible sanctions.</p>
        <p>The judge, Lewis A. Kaplan of Federal District Court in Manhattan, ruled that Christie's had to respond ''fully and completely'' by Oct. 14 to the questions posed by lawyers for A. Alfred Taubman, a former chairman of Sotheby's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal judge hearing a civil antitrust lawsuit against Sotheby's and Christie's yesterday questioned Christie's good faith in refusing to answer questions posed by one of the defendants and ordered the auction house to respond or face possible sanctions.</p>
        <p>The judge, Lewis A. Kaplan of Federal District Court in Manhattan, ruled that Christie's had to respond ''fully and completely'' by Oct. 14 to the questions posed by lawyers for A. Alfred Taubman, a former chairman of Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>Judge Kaplan said, ''There is genuine ground to suspect Christie's good faith here.''</p>
        <p>Shepard Goldfein, a lawyer with Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom, representing Christie's, said he had no comment.</p>
        <p>John Scanlon, a spokesman for Mr. Taubman, said, ''We're delighted with the judge's decision, and beyond that, there's really nothing else to say.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taubman agreed last month to pay $186 million of a $512 million settlement that Sotheby's and Christie's together agreed to pay to about 120,000 buyers and sellers to resolve accusations that the auction houses had cheated them by fixing prices and other collusive practices going back years. But two cases brought abroad by auction house customers were not covered by the settlement. They were the subject of yesterday's court ruling.</p>
        <p>In those cases, lawyers defending Mr. Taubman sought explanations from Christie's about documents turned over by a former chief executive of Christie's, Christopher M. Davidge.</p>
        <p>The documents, which Judge Kaplan said ''apparently are important evidence of the alleged conspiracy,'' and which have been described as records of secret meetings between top executives of both auction houses, were given to Christie's late last year by Mr. Davidge as part of his departure settlement with the company. Christie's then gave them to the Justice Department as part of a deal for conditional amnesty from criminal prosecution. The criminal investigation is pending.</p>
        <p>In the overseas lawsuits, Mr. Taubman's lawyers have been pressing Christie's for answers about the Davidge documents, including the authors and the meanings of certain abbreviations and unclear references to unnamed people. But Christie's has taken the position, the judge said, that it cannot provide the information because Mr. Davidge is the one who knows and Christie's does not control him.</p>
        <p>The judge said, however, that with Christie's having agreed to pay Mr. Davidge about $7.5 million contingent on his cooperation with the company -- and with about $3 million of the amount still unpaid -- Christie's had ample means of gaining Mr. Davidge's cooperation.</p>
        <p>And so, Judge kaplan said, he was ordering Christie's to respond to Mr. Taubman. If the company did not, he said, the court would consider what efforts Christie's had made to secure Mr. Davidge's cooperation, and if it failed, ''whether the imposition of sanctions is appropriate and, if so, what those sanctions should be.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
