<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Comes to Knicks Talk, An Absent No. 33 Is Easily No. 1</title>
    <meta content="04KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/sports/04KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0D9113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Comes to Knicks Talk, An Absent No. 33 Is Easily No. 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at New York Knickerbockers training camp described; players discuss trade of Patrick Ewing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They spoke respectfully about being stunned when they first heard that Patrick Ewing had been traded, about how odd it was not to see his nameplate above his old locker at their practice facility, and about how great a player he had been during his 15 years with the Knicks franchise.</p>
        <p>But beneath the polite comments by Ewing's former teammates today, for some there was a growing sense of excitement that stemmed from the absence of the domineering No. 33 from the lineup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They spoke respectfully about being stunned when they first heard that Patrick Ewing had been traded, about how odd it was not to see his nameplate above his old locker at their practice facility, and about how great a player he had been during his 15 years with the Knicks franchise.</p>
        <p>But beneath the polite comments by Ewing's former teammates today, for some there was a growing sense of excitement that stemmed from the absence of the domineering No. 33 from the lineup.</p>
        <p>At times last season the Knicks wondered how they would have fared without the 38-year-old Ewing slowing them down and demanding the ball in the post. And now that Ewing is playing 3,000 miles away for the SuperSonics in Seattle, Larry Johnson and Allan Houston admitted that the Knicks' latest scenario was invigorating.</p>
        <p>''It's something where it's not as much of an: 'Oh, oh. What do we do now?' '' Houston said today after the opening practice of training camp. ''It's more of an, 'All right, we all thought about how it would be sometimes and here it is.' Now we're facing an opportunity and a challenge. Everybody's going to be asked to take more responsibility and more of a role and everybody is kind of looking forward to it, I think.''</p>
        <p>While the players addressed the prospects of their new group, they also acknowledged that the roster could be revamped in short order.</p>
        <p>Coach Jeff Van Gundy did nothing to douse that flame in his opening remarks to the team, telling his players that Shaquille O'Neal was the only untradeable player in the National Basketball Association and that if someone was going to be dealt, the Knicks would let the player know.</p>
        <p>Both Houston and Latrell Sprewell, the team's two biggest stars and hottest commodities, acknowledged that the thought of being traded had entered their minds after the Knicks acquired forward Glen Rice from the Los Angeles Lakers.</p>
        <p>Like several observers, they could not explain the rationale in trading Ewing for essentially Rice, Luc Longley and Travis Knight. Before catching himself, Houston even began to say that, from a basketball standpoint, the trade ''doesn't make sense.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell said: ''I think that there could be another trade. I don't know if I expect it, though. You have to understand that they're going to leave that door open, and if it happens, you just kind of have to pack your bags and move on.''</p>
        <p>Marcus Camby seemed more distraught than anyone about the potential of being traded. He is fully aware that his name was mentioned in several trade scenarios this summer and was bothered by the Knicks' hot pursuit of the free agent Brian Grant, particularly when he walked into the locker room in July and saw a poster of the former Portland Trail Blazers power forward.</p>
        <p>Camby was glum while speaking today and seemed to think he might not be with the Knicks much longer.</p>
        <p>'''It remains to be seen if I'm here for the long haul, but I just have to take it a day at a time and try to progress,'' said Camby, who said his right knee is not quite 100 percent healthy. ''It's definitely tough, especially with me supposed to be getting traded ever since June.</p>
        <p>''I think the Knicks have confidence in me. But no one has come up to me and said, 'You're going to be here,' or 'don't worry about the rumors' or stuff like that.''</p>
        <p>While Camby would most likely be included in any package that would bring the Atlanta Hawks' Dikembe Mutombo to New York, he also has a better chance of starting than he ever has since joining the Knicks in 1998.</p>
        <p>With Longley out for three to six weeks with a bruised right knee, Camby and Kurt Thomas are the viable starters at center, and Thomas said today that the 6-foot-11-inch Camby is the better suited of the two to play in the middle.</p>
        <p>Also in line for an increased role is Johnson. For the first time since the 1995-96 season, when he was a 20-point scorer for the Charlotte Hornets, Johnson will be the primary low-post option on his team.</p>
        <p>As banged-up a 31-year-old as there is, it is unclear whether Johnson is up to the task. But he is nonetheless looking forward to seeing what he and the Knicks can do without Ewing either to carry them or slow them down.</p>
        <p>''Some players, myself included, probably would've wanted to see our team at times without Patrick on the floor to see if we could get some good running going,'' Johnson said. ''That's not to say we didn't want Patrick on the team.</p>
        <p>''But we needed him on the team because if we would have got past Indiana, you're looking at Big Shaq.''</p>
        <p>It is one thing to entertain the thought of playing without Ewing when he is there just in case you need him, but quite another to experience it now that he is gone for good. The Knicks, trade or no trade, will find out the difference soon enough.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>St. John's LAVOR POSTELL signed a nonguaranteed contract Tuesday, meaning he is far from a lock to make the Knicks.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
