<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cleveland Orchestra and Pollini Open Carnegie Season</title>
    <meta content="04CARN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/arts/04CARN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dohnanyi, Christoph Von</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EED7113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cleveland Orchestra and Pollini Open Carnegie Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews performance of Cleveland Orchestra, directed by Christoph von Dohnanyi, at Carnegie Hall (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is the time of grand openings and season renewals. The New York City and Metropolitan Operas have reintroduced themselves, also the New York Philharmonic. The fourth shoe to drop was heard at Carnegie Hall last night when the Cleveland Orchestra, Christoph von Dohnanyi and Maurizio Pollini played to a gala audience of first-nighters ready for art but happy as well to contemplate the food-and-drink festivities that accompany such events.</p>
        <p>If so many opening nights tend if not to pander at least to giggle excessively, the Cleveland ignored public relations strategies, abjuring glitz and instant indulgence in favor of a deeply serious German program. On it were Schumann's Second Symphony and the Brahms B-flat Piano Concerto with Mr. Pollini as soloist. This was the first of three concerts by the orchestra. Tonight and tomorrow offer important pieces by Henze, Berio and Magnus Lindberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is the time of grand openings and season renewals. The New York City and Metropolitan Operas have reintroduced themselves, also the New York Philharmonic. The fourth shoe to drop was heard at Carnegie Hall last night when the Cleveland Orchestra, Christoph von Dohnanyi and Maurizio Pollini played to a gala audience of first-nighters ready for art but happy as well to contemplate the food-and-drink festivities that accompany such events.</p>
        <p>If so many opening nights tend if not to pander at least to giggle excessively, the Cleveland ignored public relations strategies, abjuring glitz and instant indulgence in favor of a deeply serious German program. On it were Schumann's Second Symphony and the Brahms B-flat Piano Concerto with Mr. Pollini as soloist. This was the first of three concerts by the orchestra. Tonight and tomorrow offer important pieces by Henze, Berio and Magnus Lindberg.</p>
        <p>The Cleveland may not be the greatest of all orchestras, but with Mr. Dohnanyi as music director it has become the most deeply satisfying. Its program last night was not the kind from which virtuoso reputations are made: few ear-catching sonorities, few brilliant flights of velocity. As Schumann's lyric gifts began to fade, his sense of organization grew. The first movement of the symphony is one long convincing sweep of music. The wonderful Adagio is the rise and fall of a four-note figure that the composer transforms again and again into something complete and satisfying.</p>
        <p>Schumann, on the other hand, had either no talent for beautiful orchestra sound or no use for it. Brilliant debates between different parts of the orchestra are absent; rather, the music emerges in a gray and viscous mass of sound out of which occasional details are allowed to peep. The Cleveland and Mr. Dohnanyi showed us another kind of virtuosity and a deeper one: the ability to rise above color and striking effects and create lines that grow and ebb, phrases that have beginnings, middles and ends in the profoundest sense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dohnanyi, by the way, spent much of the night as a left-handed conductor, having thrown his right shoulder out of whack while carrying a suitcase full of scores. Music can indeed be physically dangerous.</p>
        <p>If Schumann's orchestra is gray and dense, Brahms's is gray and hard: stringy, muscular, devoid of fat. Think of a Haydn symphony dried in the sun. The concerto, to my mind one of his two or three best pieces, is the subject of anguish among pianists, who with few exceptions blanch at its difficulties. The first two movements, and some of the fourth, contain technical problems of frightening obtuseness. Some performers simply flee in horror; others engage in artful omissions not likely to be noticed in the heat of action. The slow movement, with its wonderful cello solo (elegantly played last night by Stephen Geber),  is a dream surrounded by furor, the eye of a magnificent storm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pollini has always had the technique not only to play what Brahms wrote but also to make it absolutely clear. Last night one heard other things: a relaxation of rigidity and literalness, and a generosity not always common to his playing. Age seems to play benevolent tricks on musicians. Or maybe we are just too tired to insist as adamantly as we once did. This was at any rate a superior performance. The otherworldly technical prowess was in full play, but so were the musical impulses.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
