<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Extras, Mariners' Experience Pays Off</title>
    <meta content="04SOXX$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/sports/04SOXX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D6113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Extras, Mariners' Experience Pays Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seattle Mariners defeat Chicago White Sox, 7-4, in first game of American League division series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Game 1 of this American League division series tied at 4-4 in the top of the 10th inning tonight, Seattle's Mike Cameron led off with a single and was surprised to see his manager, Lou Piniella, coming out of the dugout to talk to him after the next batter made an out.</p>
        <p>''I really haven't seen that since Little League,'' Cameron said with a smile. He joked that Piniella had promised that they would go out for drinks to celebrate a victory. Piniella joked that they had discussed the stock market. Neither would disclose the substance of their conversation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Game 1 of this American League division series tied at 4-4 in the top of the 10th inning tonight, Seattle's Mike Cameron led off with a single and was surprised to see his manager, Lou Piniella, coming out of the dugout to talk to him after the next batter made an out.</p>
        <p>''I really haven't seen that since Little League,'' Cameron said with a smile. He joked that Piniella had promised that they would go out for drinks to celebrate a victory. Piniella joked that they had discussed the stock market. Neither would disclose the substance of their conversation.</p>
        <p>So it is fair to speculate. Perhaps Piniella simply said to Cameron, ''Don't get picked off.'' Or he might have elaborated: ''Why not stay right here for a pitchout, then steal second base and rattle the pitcher? Then, Edgar Martinez can hit a two-run home run and John Olerud can follow with a solo homer, and we can win this one.''</p>
        <p>Because that's what happened. The Mariners defeated the Chicago White Sox, 7-4 in 10 innings, to take a 1-0 lead in the three-of-five-game American League division series.</p>
        <p>The Sox, younger and less experienced, seemed more nervous at first, but they overcame a 3-0 deficit and led by 4-3 for the middle hours of this 4-hour-12-minute affair. Nevertheless, the Mariners tied it in the seventh and the White Sox squandered numerous chance to go ahead, leaving 10 men on base. The worst was in the fourth inning, when they loaded the bases with one out before Jose Valentin and Frank Thomas were retired on easy fly balls.</p>
        <p>This allowed the patient Mariners to wait for their old pros, Martinez and Olerud, who seized the opportunity in a game that included 12 pitchers, several sparkling fielding plays and 45,290 chilled fans. ''There's no substitute for experience in this business,'' Piniella said. ''Basically, we threw about everything we had at them. We pinch-hit a few times, we pinch-ran, we used up our roster.''</p>
        <p>Of his clutch hitters, Martinez and Olerud, Piniella said, ''You want your big people up there in situations like that.'' During the regular season, Martinez had 37 home runs and 145 runs batted in. Olerud included 14 home runs among his 103 R.B.I.</p>
        <p>With Cameron on second and first base open in the top of the 10th, Jerry Manuel, the Chicago manager, could have walked Martinez. But Manuel let Keith Foulke pitch to him, and Martinez lashed a 2-1 pitch over the wall in left field. He said Cameron's stolen base had forced him to adjust his swing, for the better.</p>
        <p>''When he was on second, I tried to make contact, and that makes my swing shorter,'' Martinez said. ''When I do that, most of the time, I make better swings.''</p>
        <p>Chicago wasted a respectable outing by starter Jim Parque, who gave up six hits in the first three innings but settled down to retire the final 10 batters he faced. The Seattle starter, Freddy Garcia, lasted only three and a third innings. Asked why he pulled Parque before the seventh, Manuel said he had thrown 97 pitches and had had only three days' rest.</p>
        <p>Game 2 is here Wednesday afternoon, with the left-hander Mike Sirotka scheduled to pitch for the White Sox against the right-hander Paul Abbott. The teams will travel to Seattle for day games scheduled for Friday and Saturday. A fifth game would be played here Sunday afternoon. The winner of this series will meet either the Yankees or the Oakland Athletics for the A.L. pennant.</p>
        <p>The Mariners took a 3-0 lead on a home run by Joe Oliver in the second, but the White Sox pulled ahead with two runs in the second inning and two in the third. Ray Durham, the Chicago second baseman, tied the score at 3-3 with a leadoff home run in the third, and right fielder Magglio Ordonez gave the White Sox the lead with a triple that scored Valentin.</p>
        <p>The Mariners made it 4-4 in the top of the seventh and could have scored more after loading the bases with one out. But after Cameron singled to right off reliever Chad Bradford with two outs to drive in the tying run, David Bell was thrown out at home plate by Ordonez; catcher Charles Johnson made the tag.</p>
        <p>The tension built in the top of the eighth as the sky darkened into early evening, the autumn air chilled and the Mariners put men on first and second base. Manuel used three relievers in the inning, the final out coming on Bell's deep fly to right-center off Bill Simas.</p>
        <p>Johnson led off the home ninth with a bloop hit, his third single of the day, and he was replaced by pinch-runner Josh Paul. Piniella replaced pitcher Jose Paniagua with Arthur Rhodes.</p>
        <p>With the crowd roaring and many fans on their feet, Durham moved the runner to second with a sacrifice bunt. With the fans chanting, Valentin, the next batter, flied out to left. With two outs, Piniella replaced Rhodes with Jose Mesa and walked Thomas intentionally. Ordonez stepped to the plate and hit the first pitch on the fly to right field to end the inning and Chicago's last good chance to win.</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez, the Seattle shortstop, had three hits but said he felt guilty for being thrown out trying to steal third base with no outs in the third inning. Although Durham's team won the Central Division, it is perceived as the underdog to the wild-card Mariners. Are the Sox worried?</p>
        <p>''Actually, we're relaxed,'' Durham said. ''We know we must win. But everybody's calm. We're just going to come out and play and have fun and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
