<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Candidates' Positions Reflect Party Stances</title>
    <meta content="MB032511" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLICY -- THE BUDGET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDF1E3DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Candidates' Positions Reflect Party Stances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush clash in presidential debate on how to apportion budget surplus; Gore repeatedly attacks Bush for proposing tax cut he holds would provide more money for wealthiest Americans than for other key programs; Bush holds his tax plan would require wealthiest taxpayers to shoulder bigger portion of tax burden; charges Gore's tax cut would provide no benefits to 50 million people (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On several issues in the debate, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush stood on principles that have divided their parties for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush favored large tax cuts, Mr. Gore more federal spending. Mr. Gore stood for abortion rights, Mr. Bush did not. Mr. Gore advocated expanding Social Security and Medicare. Mr. Bush pressed for partial privatization of the programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On several issues in the debate, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush stood on principles that have divided their parties for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush favored large tax cuts, Mr. Gore more federal spending. Mr. Gore stood for abortion rights, Mr. Bush did not. Mr. Gore advocated expanding Social Security and Medicare. Mr. Bush pressed for partial privatization of the programs.</p>
        <p>They challenged each other's logic and budget numbers, offering a array of charges and countercharges, numbers and statistics, diplomatic catch-phrases, military jargon and economic theories. But the basic disagreement was over philosophy.</p>
        <p>Here is an examination of the candidates' positions on many of the issues that were points of contention in the debate and have been throughout the election year.</p>
        <p>The candidates agreed that a central issue was how to apportion the budget surplus, which the Congressional Budget Office projects to total $4.56 trillion over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore repeatedly attacked Mr. Bush for proposing a tax cut, amounting to $1.3 trillion over nine years starting in 2002, that would provide more money to the wealthiest 1 percent of Americans than Mr. Bush has proposed to spend on education, health care, prescription drug coverage for the elderly and national defense combined.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's numbers were basically correct. According to Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal research group, 42.6 percent of Mr. Bush's tax cuts, when they are fully phased in, would go to the top 1 percent of households by income, those making $319,000 a year or more.</p>
        <p>If that percentage were applied to the $1.3 trillion pricetag that Mr. Bush put on his tax plan, it would mean that $554 billion would go to the wealthiest 1 percent. Mr. Bush's proposal calls for $475 billion in additional spending over 10 years on the areas cited by Mr. Gore and others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush responded that his tax plan would actually result in the wealthiest taxpayers shouldering a bigger portion of the tax burden. His assertion was based on an analysis done by his economic advisers that showed that people at lower income levels would get a larger tax income tax cut in percentage terms, though not in dollar terms, than people at higher income levels.</p>
        <p>The analysis showed that people earning $200,000 or more would pay 40.9 percent of all income taxes under the Bush plan, compared to 39.1 percent under current law. The analysis covered only income taxes, and therefore excluded the effects of Mr. Bush's proposal to repeal the federal tax on large estates, those valued at $675,000 or more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said 50 million people, including anyone who is single and people above certain income thresholds, would receive no benefits from Mr. Gore's $480 billion tax cut plan.  The Gore campaign disputed Mr. Bush's figure but could not provide an estimate of its own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said his plan would split the projected surplus among additional spending, tax cuts and shoring up Social Security. He said he would use half the surplus for Social Security.</p>
        <p>That figure coincided with the portion of the surplus being generated by excess Social Security payroll taxes hat both parties have agreed should go only to reducing the national debt or improving the financial condition of the retirement system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he would use a quarter of the surplus for ''important projects.'' The remaining quarter, he said, would go to his tax cut. At $1.3 trillion, his tax cut actually would use up 28.5 percent of the surplus.</p>
        <p>RICHARD W. STEVENSON</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLICY -- THE BUDGET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
