<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="04MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/04/nyregion/04MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1D6113DF937A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: MAYOR CRITICIZES BOND PLAN -- The state's proposed $3.8 billion transportation bond act received a lukewarm critique yesterday from Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who said he was not convinced the city would ''come out with anything real'' if the measure, sponsored by Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, was adopted by voters in November. The bond act, the largest in the state's history, would pay for engineering studies of a new Second Avenue subway. Mr. Giuliani criticized the proposal for failing to designate money for his preferred subway project, the extension of the No. 7 line to the West Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: MAYOR CRITICIZES BOND PLAN -- The state's proposed $3.8 billion transportation bond act received a lukewarm critique yesterday from Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who said he was not convinced the city would ''come out with anything real'' if the measure, sponsored by Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, was adopted by voters in November. The bond act, the largest in the state's history, would pay for engineering studies of a new Second Avenue subway. Mr. Giuliani criticized the proposal for failing to designate money for his preferred subway project, the extension of the No. 7 line to the West Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: $95-A-NIGHT SCHRAGER HOTEL -- Ian Schrager, a club owner turned hotel magnate, opened his first new Manhattan hotel in a decade yesterday. The hotel, the Hudson, at 356 West 58th Street, will have substantially lower rates than other fashionable Midtown hotels. Rates begin at $95; rates at others typically exceed $200 a night. Mr. Schrager, who is known for his hotels in Manhattan, Miami Beach and Hollywood, describes his new hotel as ''the next generation of cheap chic.''</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: GIRL REPORTS RAPE AT SCHOOL -- A 15-year-old Manhattan girl told the police on Monday that she was sexually assaulted by two teenage boys in a bathroom at Central Park East High School. The girl, a ninth grader, reported the assault at 8:45 p.m., about six hours after the alleged attack. The police said she told them that two 17-year-olds forced her into a bathroom on the second floor of the school, on Madison Avenue near 105th Street, and assaulted her. The girl was taken to Mount Sinai Medical Center for observation. No arrests had been made as of last night.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNIONS PICKET TIMES -- Scores of commercial actors on strike against advertisers picketed The New York Times yesterday. The actors protested what they called the newspaper's refusal to publish letters and articles from their unions, as well as the publication on Sept. 29 of a column on the Op-Ed page by a nonunion actor. ''Coming right after the breakdown of talks with advertisers last week, the publication seemed manipulative and biased,'' said Jay S. Potter, a senior organizer for the unions, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists. Kathy Park, a spokeswoman for The Times, said the timing of the Sept. 29 column was unrelated to the union negotiations.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: CHANGE IN LICENSE PLATES -- After almost 15 years, New York is changing its license plates. Instead of the Statue of Liberty, the plates will feature a panorama of Niagara Falls, the Adirondack Mountains and the Manhattan skyline. The new plates will have seven, rather than six characters: three letters on the left and four on the right, separated by a silhouette of the state. With the additional character, the state increases its production capacity from 17.5 million to 175 million plates. The new plates will start going out in January.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PARKING LOT MANAGER KILLED -- The manager of a Midtown parking lot died on Monday after he was punched in the face by a driver, the police said. The driver entered the lot, on 42nd Street between Eighth and Ninth Avenues, about 5 p.m., trying to drive through it to 43rd Street. After the manager, Methis Weingarten, 47, tried to stop him, the driver backed his car out of the lot, parked it, then came back and punched Mr. Weingarten in the face, said Harold Sam, a lot attendant. Mr. Weingarten, who fell to the ground, was taken to St. Vincents Hospital and Medical Center, where he was pronounced dead at 6:55 p.m. The driver ran out of the lot and took off in his car, said Novela Lacroix, another worker.</p>
        <p>Edward Wong (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: MAYOR NAMES CULTURE CHIEF -- Mayor Douglas Palmer named Francis Blanco as the new director of the city's Department of Recreation, Natural Resources and Culture. She succeeds Merkle Cherry, who was dismissed after holding the job for four years. Ms. Blanco is the former executive director of the Mercer County Hispanic Association. She will earn a salary of $82,713. Mayor Palmer said he expected Ms. Blanco to improve the efficiency of the department, which has a budget of $3.4 million.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>ELIZABETH: DISPUTED CARGO PROJECT BEGINS -- Ground was broken yesterday on a $175 million cargo terminal for Maersk Sealand, the company that recently threatened to move out of state and had been at the center of a feud between New York and New Jersey. Maersk Sealand plans to build the nation's largest cargo port. Last June, an 18-month feud between the governors of New York and New Jersey over terms of the Maersk lease with the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey was resolved. Maersk had been considering a move to Baltimore, Boston or Halifax, a potential blow to the region's shipping industry.</p>
        <p>Andrew Jacobs (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: ROWLAND SEEKS CUTS AT COLLEGES -- Gov. John G. Rowland has asked Connecticut's public colleges and universities to cut $9 million from their budgets so the state can avoid exceeding its constitutionally mandated limit on annual budget increases. The governor is seeking to trim about 2 percent of the state's share of budgets for the University of Connecticut, the Connecticut State University system and the state community colleges. Mr. Rowland's budget chief, Marc S. Ryan, predicted the state's current $12.3 billion budget could exceed the spending limit by more than $125 million.</p>
        <p>Paul Zielbauer (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>HEARING ON PRISON OVERCROWDING -- The Connecticut State Senate plans a public hearing on easing prison overcrowding, with testimony from government officials and others. Room 2-D, Legislative Office Building, 300 Capitol Avenue, Hartford, 3:00 p.m. Information: (860) 240-0414.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
