<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Gets A New Rival On the Right</title>
    <meta content="01SENA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Movements (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Joseph J. DioGuardi</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conservative Party (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Right-to-Life Party</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Independence Party (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DioGuardi, Joseph J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7DE1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Gets A New Rival On the Right</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former United States Congressman from Westchester County Joseph J DioGuardi, in move that could complicate Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's campaign for United States Senate, says that he will seek support of Conservative, Right-to-Life and Independence Parties in campaign for Senate; repeatedly assails Giuliani as being out of step with Conservative-minded Republicans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move that could complicate Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's campaign for the United States Senate, a former United States congressman from Westchester County, Joseph J. DioGuardi, announced yesterday that he would seek the support of the Conservative, Right-to-Life and Independence Parties in a run for the Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi repeatedly assailed Mr. Giuliani as out of step with conservative-minded Republicans, and he pledged to run an aggressive campaign against the mayor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move that could complicate Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's campaign for the United States Senate, a former United States congressman from Westchester County, Joseph J. DioGuardi, announced yesterday that he would seek the support of the Conservative, Right-to-Life and Independence Parties in a run for the Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi repeatedly assailed Mr. Giuliani as out of step with conservative-minded Republicans, and he pledged to run an aggressive campaign against the mayor.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi, who lives in Ossining, said in an interview that he would send a letter to the three parties' leaders today, formally indicating his intention to seek their lines. The leaders of two of those organizations, the Right-to-Life and Conservative Parties, who have both been critical of Mr. Giuliani's ideological positions, praised Mr. DioGuardi and described him as the leading contender to win their support, which will be decided at party conventions over the next six weeks.</p>
        <p>''I am running for the United States Senate,'' Mr. DioGuardi declared. ''We have two social liberals in the race. There's a clear need for a conservative alternative.</p>
        <p>''Am I a spoiler?'' Mr. DioGuardi asked, anticipating a charge raised by some of Mr. Giuliani's supporters. ''No. I'm in this race to win. That might spoil someone's day.''</p>
        <p>The statement by Mr. DioGuardi came as Mr. Giuliani went to some lengths to show that his public life had not been altered by a diagnosis of prostate cancer. The mayor announced on Thursday that he had an early stage of the disease and that his race for the Senate against Hillary Rodham Clinton was uncertain. But yesterday, he attended a Holocaust memorial at Temple Emanu-El on Fifth Avenue, and then, taking advantage of a warm and sunny spring afternoon, took a leisurely stroll along 65th Street, startling passers-by and alfresco diners who shouted out calls of support and good wishes. He then drove to Westchester County for a  fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi has been considering the race for weeks, and he told Conservative Party leaders of his decision last week. Mr. DioGuardi said that Mr. Giuliani's health announcement had not affected his timetable, and that he had offered a prayer for Mr. Giuliani at a Mass yesterday evening.</p>
        <p>The announcement by Mr. DioGuardi, a former two-term representative from Westchester, was notable because it gave the Conservative Party -- whose leader, Michael Long, has been increasingly estranged from Mr. Giuliani -- a credible candidate who could end up running on three separate lines. That could be worrisome to Mr. Giuliani for two reasons: first, no Republican candidate in New York has won a statewide race without Conservative Party support since 1974; and second, Mr. DioGuardi made clear that he would attack Mr. Giuliani just as strongly as he attacks Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi acknowledged that he was unlikely to raise the large sums of money needed to keep up with Mr. Giuliani or Mrs. Clinton. But most politicians believe that this race will be decided by a small number of votes, and thus have been paying particular attention to the independent parties.</p>
        <p>In the 1998 race for Senate, about 275,000 votes were cast on the Conservative Party line, out of a total 4.9 million, and 105,000 more were cast on the Right-to-Life line. Alfonse M. D'Amato, the Republican incumbent who lost, was the Conservative and Right-to-Life candidate that year. The Independence Party, which endorsed Charles E. Schumer that year, drew 109,000 votes in 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's associates have said that the mayor is hoping to run, again assuming he stays in the race, on four separate lines this November: Republican, Liberal, Conservative and Independence. And Mr. Giuliani's campaign responded to the news of Mr. DioGuardi's announcement by warning that it might seek to force a Conservative Party primary to win Mr. Giuliani its line.</p>
        <p>''Given the mayor's support with Conservative voters, it would be interesting to see if the Conservative Party would be open to a primary, which is certainly an option that we will explore,'' Bruce Teitelbaum, Mr. Giuliani's campaign manager, said last night. Then, suggesting a bit of disloyalty on Mr. DioGuardi's part, Mr. Teitelbaum added, ''The mayor also knows DioGuardi very well, having supported him and helped raise money for him in the past.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Long responded caustically to Mr. Teitelbaum's primary idea, noting that under state law, Mr. Giuliani  could not get on the primary ballot without persuading a majority of the party's 51-member Executive Committee to give him a waiver that permits someone who is not a party member to participate in a Conservative primary.</p>
        <p>''I think he'd be making a big mistake,'' Mr. Long said. ''The mayor is not a conservative, he's a liberal. He's seeking the Liberal Party's support. I think Conservative voters will reject him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani is meeting with the Liberal Party, which is headed by his close friend Raymond B. Harding, on Saturday to ask for its support. Mrs. Clinton's aides said that the first lady, aware that Mr. Harding has steered the Liberal Party behind Mr. Giuliani in all his mayoral races, had not decided whether to make a formal appeal for its support.</p>
        <p>Mr. DioGuardi, 59, a certified public accountant, said Mr. Giuliani was ideologically distant from most conservatives and Republicans.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to all social issues, Hillary Clinton and Rudy Giuliani are the same,'' Mr. DioGuardi said. He mentioned Mr. Giuliani's support of abortion rights and some forms of gun control. And he said he would remind suburban voters that Mr. Giuliani had objected, unsuccessfully, when Albany repealed a New York City tax on commuters. ''That has to be a big issue in this campaign,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Regardless of how the party lines shake out, several consultants said, it is not in Mr. Giuliani's interest to have an opponent reminding Republican voters, particularly upstate, of times that he has strayed from traditional Republican stands. Mr. DioGuardi could, they said, rekindle doubts about Mr. Giuliani that emerged when the mayor supported a Democrat, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, in his unsuccessful bid for re-election against George E. Pataki in 1994.</p>
        <p>''This could be a major problem for Giuliani,'' said Nelson Warfield, a Republican consultant and a frequent critic of the mayor. ''A conservative candidate can appeal to the majority of New Yorkers who voted against Mario Cuomo. DioGuardi is the only candidate for Senate who voted for George Pataki.''</p>
        <p>PROFILE  Joseph J. DioGuardi</p>
        <p>BORN -- Sept. 20, 1940, the Bronx.</p>
        <p>HOMETOWN -- Ossining, N.Y.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION -- Fordham Preparatory School, 1958; B.S., Fordham University, 1962.</p>
        <p>CAREER -- Accountant and partner, Arthur Andersen &amp; Company, 1962-1984; member of Congress, 1985-89; financial consultant and author, 1989-present; president, Albanian American Civic League, 1989-present; president, Truth in Government, 1989-present.</p>
        <p>FAMILY -- Married June 28, 1998, to Shirley Cloyes; first wife, Carol Asselta, died in 1997. One daughter, Kara, born Dec. 9, 1970; one son, John, born Oct. 15, 1973.</p>
        <p>INTERESTS -- Golf, fishing and public speaking on human rights.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
