<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; Campaign Prognosis for Giuliani: Putting Cancer in Its Place and Feeling in Control</title>
    <meta content="01MATT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostate Gland</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Prostate Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostate Gland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DF1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; Campaign Prognosis for Giuliani: Putting Cancer in Its Place and Feeling in Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column discusses question of whether Rudolph W Giuliani will pursue his Senate campaign now that he has prostate cancer; predicts that Giuliani, if his prognosis remains favorable and his cancer is treatable, will continue his campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILL Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani pursue his Senate campaign now that he has prostate cancer?</p>
        <p>That is the question many are asking right now, and mostly the matter is being analyzed in political terms. You have no doubt heard the theories. The prevailing one: That maybe Mr. Giuliani will not run because he was never all that fired up about being a senator anyway. Others say that of course he will run, that he is even stronger now, more sympathetic and acting more congenial. The mayor will not decide about the campaign for a few weeks, after he selects a course of treatment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILL Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani pursue his Senate campaign now that he has prostate cancer?</p>
        <p>That is the question many are asking right now, and mostly the matter is being analyzed in political terms. You have no doubt heard the theories. The prevailing one: That maybe Mr. Giuliani will not run because he was never all that fired up about being a senator anyway. Others say that of course he will run, that he is even stronger now, more sympathetic and acting more congenial. The mayor will not decide about the campaign for a few weeks, after he selects a course of treatment.</p>
        <p>I certainly do not presume to have any insights into his thinking. But I will presume to make a few informed predictions, the central one being that the mayor's decision will not be political. It will be deeply personal. And if his prognosis remains favorable and his cancer is treatable, as his doctors now say, then for sure he will continue his campaign for the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>Predictions can be risky. But I do not think this one is, for a reason about as basic as you can get: the force of human nature.</p>
        <p>When confronted with a life-threatening disease, people overwhelmingly want to do precisely what they were doing before that awful day in the doctor's office when they got the news.</p>
        <p>Unless hit with an incapacitating condition, most patients want normalcy.</p>
        <p>Some may choose to go on a world tour, or, as a friend did temporarily, indulge a desire to write poetry. Some collapse under the pressure. But most want things to be the way they were, because that helps you feel normal at a time when nothing else does.</p>
        <p>Joe Torre went back to managing the Yankees after his treatment for prostate cancer last year. Edward I. Koch went back to being mayor after he had a minor stroke in 1987. David Letterman returned to his television program after his quintuple bypass surgery in January. A dear colleague who recently died of AIDS-related pneumonia stayed on the job, choosing to work his regular night shift as an editor, after his diagnosis years ago.</p>
        <p>ANOTHER friend, a freelance writer, celebrated when she got a routine magazine assignment while she was in chemotherapy for breast cancer. She could be herself again, she said.</p>
        <p>I remember feeling the same way when, after a lumpectomy for breast cancer seven years ago, I continued to work while I underwent radiation and chemotherapy. It's not that you want to be heroic. It's that you want to prove -- to yourself more than to anyone else -- that you are still you.</p>
        <p>That a few errant cells wreaking havoc on your body had not impeded your ability to function as ever you had.</p>
        <p>I remember, too, being resentful of the cancer's frightful power. When you have a serious illness that you cannot control, you want to control what you can, especially your daily life.</p>
        <p>''Working gives you strength, brings you back into the world,'' Barbara Barrie, the actress, said yesterday. She appeared in a starring role in Anne Meara's ''After-Play'' during her chemotherapy treatments for colo-rectal cancer in 1994. ''I instinctively knew that working would help my recovery,'' said Ms. Barrie, who wrote about her illness in ''Don't Die of Embarrassment'' (Scribner, 1999). ''George Bernard Shaw called it a life force -- what you experience as a human being, a determination to get back into life, be a part of life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's life is politics. It is very possible that he does not relish being one of 100 senators; that, facing the end of his mayoral tenure next year because of term limits, he decided to run for Senate by default. He would probably rather be governor, running things. But Gov. George E. Pataki may run again in 2002 and that would leave Mr. Giuliani in limbo.</p>
        <p>That was clearly the mayor's calculation when he decided to try for the Senate. The betting here is that, prognosis permitting, he will return to sparring with Hillary Rodham Clinton after he recovers from his course of treatment -- not because his illness changed the political calculus, though it might.</p>
        <p>But because, despite his often fierce demeanor, Mr. Giuliani is not all that different from the rest of us.</p>
        <p>Surely, he, too, will want to thumb his nose at cancer.</p>
        <p>He, too, will want to feel in control, connected to the world and his prediagnosis life. When he got the bad news last Wednesday, he was a politician running for office. He still is.</p>
        <p>Watch Rudy run.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
