<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Britain Finally Gets A Vertical Big Man</title>
    <meta content="01ANDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Lennox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4D61539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Britain Finally Gets A Vertical Big Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column on Lennox Lewis retaining his world heavyweight boxing championship with second round knockout of Michael Grant (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LENNOX LEWIS has done what many boxing aficionados thought could never be done. He has given British heavyweights a good name.</p>
        <p>With ripping right uppercuts that chopped Michael Grant into firewood at Madison Square Garden on Saturday night, Lewis's second-round knockout enhanced his reign as the heavyweight champion of the world no matter what the World Boxing Association decrees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LENNOX LEWIS has done what many boxing aficionados thought could never be done. He has given British heavyweights a good name.</p>
        <p>With ripping right uppercuts that chopped Michael Grant into firewood at Madison Square Garden on Saturday night, Lewis's second-round knockout enhanced his reign as the heavyweight champion of the world no matter what the World Boxing Association decrees.</p>
        <p>''Whoever picks it up is still a paper champion,'' he said, alluding to the W.B.A. version of the title. ''I'm still the undisputed.''</p>
        <p>Even though Lennox Lewis is the best of a bad lot, he's still the best around. And there hasn't been a British heavyweight this dominant for more than a century, not since Bob Fitzsimmons dethroned Gentleman Jim Corbett in a 14th-round knockout in rough-and-tumble Carson City, Nev., in 1897.</p>
        <p>All the early documented heavyweight champions were Englishmen, of course, beginning with James Figg as long ago as 1720, but after Fitzsimmons lost the title to Jim Jeffries and until Lewis, the occasional British challenger justified the description of a ''horizontal'' heavyweight.</p>
        <p>When Don Cockell arrived from Britain for his 1955 title bout with Rocky Marciano in San Francisco, his manager demanded a 20-foot ring.</p>
        <p>''What difference does it make,'' the humorist Arthur (Bugs) Baer wrote. ''His man isn't that tall.'' His man didn't last the ninth round.</p>
        <p>In 1959, another British challenger, Brian London, didn't last the 11th round against Floyd Patterson in Indianapolis. But in 1963 in London, Henry Cooper threw the most memorable left hook in British boxing history and flattened the young Cassius Clay, now Muhammad Ali, just before the end of the fourth round.</p>
        <p>''I was looking at Liz Taylor at ringside,'' the boxer then known as the Louisville Lip said later.</p>
        <p>Wherever Clay was looking when the punch landed, when the bell rang he had to be dragged back to his corner. His left glove had been slightly split in an earlier round and now his trainer, Angelo Dundee, put a finger into the split and lifted the leather up.</p>
        <p>''Hey, referee,'' Dundee yelled. ''This glove's bad.''</p>
        <p>The referee hurried over to the British commissioners, who sent somebody back to the dressing-room area for another left glove. But another left glove was not found. The commissioners agreed to let Clay resume with the slightly split glove.</p>
        <p>''The glove had never been off my guy's hand, never,'' Dundee has often said. ''I had just bought some time. I don't know how much, but it was enough.''</p>
        <p>Enough for Clay to knock out Cooper in the fifth round. When he returned to London as Ali in 1966 for a title bout, he knocked out Cooper in the sixth. That one punch, Cooper's left hook in 1963, was British boxing's only heavyweight moment until Frank Bruno dethroned Oliver McCall for the World Boxing Council title in 1995 in London.</p>
        <p>Bruno had been stopped in three previous title bouts -- with Tim Witherspoon in 1986, Mike Tyson in 1989 and Lennox Lewis in 1993. Now he was the first British-born, British-raised heavyweight (Lewis was raised in Canada) to win even a share of the title in a British ring. Union Jacks were waving all over Wembley Stadium that night.</p>
        <p>Six months later, frozen in fear before being knocked out by Tyson in Las Vegas, Bruno again was another horizontal heavyweight in Britain's long level line of horizontal heavyweights.</p>
        <p>When Lewis was stopped by McCall in 1994, he had appeared to be just another horizontal heavyweight, too. But that is his only loss. With a 36-1-1 record with 28 knockouts, the 6-foot-5-inch vertical Englishman can boast that the sun never sets on his empire, even if that empire is recognized by only the W.B.C. and the indicted International Boxing Federation.</p>
        <p>Lewis virtually toyed with the inexperienced Grant (now 31-1) whose trainer, Don Turner, thought Lewis didn't like to be roughed up. As soon as Grant tried to rough him up, Lewis started throwing those right uppercuts and Grant dissolved into a horizontal heavyweight.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, Lewis is still the best of a bad lot. But it's not his fault. Except for Tyson, whom Lewis may fight someday if Tyson can ever get serious, there are no marquee challengers out there.</p>
        <p>As proof, consider Lewis's next two opponents: South Africa's Francois Botha in London on July 15 and New Zealand's David Tua, probably in Las Vegas in November.</p>
        <p>But by remaining vertical, Lennox Lewis has given British heavyweights a good name.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
