<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Hard Questions for Government Advisers</title>
    <meta content="01PLAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhill, Robert F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holson, Laura M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DA1539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Hard Questions for Government Advisers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stock analysts hold affidavit prepared for Justice Department by investment banker Robert F Greenhill lacks financial data to back up his stand that Microsoft breakup would not hurt market value of company's stock; say his proposal that Microsoft be forced to spin off one of its businesses in initial public offering is too simple an approach; graph of Microsoft stock price in face of antitrust proceedings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As stock analysts pored over Friday's filings in the government's proposal to split Microsoft in two, some marveled as much about what was missing as what was included.</p>
        <p>In particular, bankers and analysts who have read an affidavit prepared by the firm of the investment banker Robert F. Greenhill, which defended the feasibility of such a step, said the affidavit fell short of justifying why a breakup would be good for Microsoft shareholders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As stock analysts pored over Friday's filings in the government's proposal to split Microsoft in two, some marveled as much about what was missing as what was included.</p>
        <p>In particular, bankers and analysts who have read an affidavit prepared by the firm of the investment banker Robert F. Greenhill, which defended the feasibility of such a step, said the affidavit fell short of justifying why a breakup would be good for Microsoft shareholders.</p>
        <p>Analysts criticized the lack of financial data to back up Greenhill &amp; Company's assertion in the affidavit that ''there will not be a material decrease in the market value of the current Microsoft shareholders' holdings.''</p>
        <p>''My response is, show me the numbers,'' said David Readerman, an analyst who tracks Microsoft for the investment firm Thomas Weisel Partners in San Francisco. ''At 9:30 a.m. Monday morning, the bell will go off and investors will have to calibrate the impact of this legal document on their personal net worth,'' Mr. Readerman said. ''But there are no numbers to substantiate the claims.''</p>
        <p>Analysts also say that the breakup technique Greenhill proposes, which includes spinning off one of the Microsoft businesses in an initial public offering, is too simple an approach. They note that most of the dozen or so companies cited in the affidavit as successful spinoffs, and which Mr. Greenhill compares with Microsoft, made such moves voluntarily.</p>
        <p>In December, Greenhill &amp; Company, an investment boutique, was hired by the Justice Department to help the government study the financial implications of a Microsoft breakup.</p>
        <p>It was a logical choice: Mr. Greenhill, the firm's chairman, is a 37-year Wall Street veteran and a well-respected deal maker. He has been assisted in the Microsoft study by another Greenhill partner, Jeffrey P. Williams, a banker who has counseled AT&amp;T and once headed Morgan Stanley's telecommunications and media group. The two prepared the affidavit jointly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenhill and Mr. Williams declined to comment on the filing.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the federal government and 17 states asked Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson to split Microsoft into two separate companies: one focused on operating systems like Windows, the other devoted to software applications and Internet activities. The Greenhill affidavit outlined the process for making that happen, including the initial public offering for a new class of stock in the spun-off company.</p>
        <p>At times, though, the affidavit reads mainly like a business school primer, explaining at length how stock analysts value companies, while doing little to address Microsoft specifically. The only reference to any financial analysis of their own was on page 17, when Messrs. Greenhill and Williams wrote that they ''performed a sum-of-the-parts analysis assuming a range of assumptions and believe our estimates and adjustments to be based on reasonable and rational business judgments based on the currently available public information.'' But they did not include the analysis itself in the affidavit.</p>
        <p>Other salient details were also absent, analysts said. The document did not detail growth or revenue projections for the separate concerns, and the consumer market was largely ignored. And when addressing other companies that might be comparable in size and profitability to the operating-systems concern, Mr. Greenhill and Mr. Williams were vague, giving no example except for Microsoft itself.</p>
        <p>''I was very surprised, said Ed Yardeni, chief global economist and investment strategist at Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown. ''It was a fairly minimalist analysis.'' But given the sensitivity of the Microsoft case, Mr. Yardeni said that keeping to what he described as a ''limited mandate'' may have been appropriate. Mr. Yardeni said he believed that Mr. Greenhill and Mr. Williams, or their lawyers, might have left out their financial analysis because they did not want the specific data to become the target of criticism.</p>
        <p>''Sharing numbers is a no-win situation,'' he said. ''They didn't want to be the baseline at which everyone shoots.''</p>
        <p>Mary Meeker, the Morgan Stanley Dean Witter analyst who has followed Microsoft for more than a decade, said that Friday's filings, including the Greenhill document, were only a first step in what was sure to be a complicated negotiating process.</p>
        <p>''We've entered a new century where the complexity of breaking up companies that rely on code and people is far more complex than anything seen before,'' Ms. Meeker said. ''A breakup is an extraordinarily aggressive tactic by the government, given the root of the problem.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meeker, like the other analysts, took issue with the companies the Greenhill affidavit cited as successful spinoff models. She noted that many of them, including the retailer The Limited, which spun off Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, were not technology concerns.</p>
        <p>And she noted that most of the spinoffs had been voluntary. This was a point the affidavit conceded, although it added, ''Even court-ordered separations such as the Standard Oil and the 1984 AT&amp;T breakups are perceived as having produced sizable positive returns to shareholders, assuming they held on to the original holdings.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, analysts said, companies in recent years that have chosen to spin off businesses have generally done so because the newly separate company was worth more on its own. The network equipment maker Lucent Technologies, spun off from AT&amp;T in 1996, now has a stock market value of $198 billion, surpassing AT&amp;T, which is valued at $146 billion.</p>
        <p>But AT&amp;T spun off Lucent in part because local telephone companies were sometimes wary of buying networking equipment from AT&amp;T, a company that was planning to compete for their local calling customers.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's situation is very different. To begin with, Microsoft is holding steadfast in its desire to remain a single company. And it is not clear that customers would be more likely to buy Microsoft applications software if that business was separate from Microsoft's Windows operating-system business.</p>
        <p>Rick Sherlund, the analyst at the Goldman Sachs Group who follows Microsoft, warned,  too, that the company's viability depends in part on how well it delivers on the next generation of Windows products. As such, he said Greenhill &amp; Company's findings ''do not seem to address the full range of issues'' needed to assess Microsoft's future.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is taking a retrospective view, not a prospective view,'' Mr. Sherlund said. But that again might be due to the limited scope of Mr. Greenhill's mandate, he added.</p>
        <p>The investing public has already had some opportunity to register its reaction to a Microsoft breakup. As the prospects of a forced split have become more plausible, and analysts have warned that the company's overall growth was slowing, the stock price has sharply fallen, down 19 percent since April 4 when the court found that Microsoft violated antitrust law.</p>
        <p>At any rate, it is likely that Mr. Greenhill and Mr. Williams will get their day in court -- literally -- to explain their opinion. Judge Jackson is expected to begin hearings on May 24 in preparation for issuing his final decision on how to deal with Microsoft. And Microsoft says it will ask for extensive discovery and in-court testimony. If so, Mr. Greenhill and Mr. Williams will most likely be asked to produce any data they have prepared to back up their findings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
