<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gomez's Drop in Production Puzzles Robinson</title>
    <meta content="01DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gomez, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DF1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gomez's Drop in Production Puzzles Robinson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problems besetting New Jersey Devils hockey player Scott Gomezduring playoffs noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Gomez was the only Devil to play in every one of New Jersey's 82 regular-season games this season. Because his play has suffered in the playoffs, however, Gomez -- the favorite to win the Calder trophy as the National Hockey League's top rookie this season -- was nearly a healthy scratch from the lineup in Toronto on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, yes,'' Devils Coach Larry Robinson said today when asked if he had been close to holding out Gomez for Game 2 of the second-round Stanley Cup playoff series with the Toronto Maple Leafs. But after talking things over with Gomez, Robinson finally decided to play the 20-year-old center, if sparingly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scott Gomez was the only Devil to play in every one of New Jersey's 82 regular-season games this season. Because his play has suffered in the playoffs, however, Gomez -- the favorite to win the Calder trophy as the National Hockey League's top rookie this season -- was nearly a healthy scratch from the lineup in Toronto on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, yes,'' Devils Coach Larry Robinson said today when asked if he had been close to holding out Gomez for Game 2 of the second-round Stanley Cup playoff series with the Toronto Maple Leafs. But after talking things over with Gomez, Robinson finally decided to play the 20-year-old center, if sparingly.</p>
        <p>Gomez logged just 9 minutes 34 seconds of ice time (16 seconds fewer than he had played in Game 1) in the Devils' 1-0 victory, which tied this four-of-seven-game series at 1-1.</p>
        <p>Gomez's 12 shifts were the fewest for the evening on a team that dresses three other rookies: Brian Rafalski, John Madden and Colin White, the burly 22-year-old defenseman who scored the game's only goal on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Gomez led all N.H.L. rookies in scoring with 70 points this season,  and was only 2 points behind Patrik Elias for the team lead.</p>
        <p>Gomez scored the game-winner in Game 3 of the Devils' four-game sweep of Florida in the first round, but that is the only point that Gomez has recorded during the postseason. Of the Devils' four rookies, Gomez has the fewest points in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I just said that he wasn't moving his feet,'' Robinson said when asked about what he had discussed with Gomez before Game 2. ''I told him he has to move his feet, jump into holes, do things quicker.''</p>
        <p>After the game, Robinson said he liked what he saw in Gomez's effort on Saturday night. Still, when asked if Gomez would be in the lineup Monday night for Game 3 at Continental Arena, Robinson was coy.</p>
        <p>''Tomorrow's another day,'' said Robinson, who thinks that Gomez has yet to adjust to the faster pace of playoff hockey.</p>
        <p>Robinson's only other option Saturday was starting another rookie, Steve Brule, in Gomez's place. Brule led Albany of the American Hockey League, the Devils' top minor-league affiliate, in scoring this season. But he has yet to play a regular-season game in the N.H.L., much less a playoff game.</p>
        <p>Sergei Brylin, who has not played since Game 2 of the Devils' first-round series, when a knee-to-knee collision with Oleg Kvasha knocked him out of action, went through his first full practice with the Devils here today since sustaining the injury to his right knee. But Brylin, who had the flu last week, doubted he would be ready for Game 3.</p>
        <p>''It's not likely,'' Robinson said.</p>
        <p>That means that Gomez will probably get the nod again on Monday night. But Gomez is also well aware that he is close to losing his job, at least for a night.</p>
        <p>''At this point, you want to go as far as you can as a team,'' Gomez said. ''Personally, it doesn't matter. That said, I hope it doesn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Gomez's linemate for much of this season, Claude Lemieux, is also struggling. In six playoff games, Lemieux, long known for his postseason play, has just one assist.</p>
        <p>Once Lemieux or Gomez starts to score, the other one could follow.</p>
        <p>''There will definitely be a time when we need more goals,'' said Lemieux, mindful that the Devils have scored just two in two playoff games against the Maple Leafs. ''And I think we'll get them.''</p>
        <p>The question is whether any of them will come from Gomez and Lemieux.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Devils Coach LARRY ROBINSON led his team through a full practice Sunday afternoon, then said there would be no morning skate before Game 3.  ''I didn't like to do it as a player,'' Robinson said. . . . Robinson said he gave a few of his players the option of taking Sunday off. Only JASON ARNOTT accepted.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
