<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drawing Lessons From the Opponent's Father</title>
    <meta content="Y01GOR$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George (Former Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dukakis, Michael S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDE1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drawing Lessons From the Opponent's Father</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of Vice Pres Al Gore's foreign policy address in Boston in which he criticized Gov George W Bush as having risky foreign policy scheme; Gore is using classic incumbent strategy made especially classic by Bush's father in 1988, when he raised questions about record and readiness of Michael Dukakis, then governor of Massachusetts, to be president; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a fullblown attack today on Gov. George W. Bush over foreign policy, Vice President Al Gore seemed to be executing a classic incumbent strategy, one made especially classic by Governor Bush's father, then the vice president, against another sitting governor in 1988.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign has been sifting through the detritus of the elder Mr. Bush's steamrolling of Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts and has unearthed useful lessons. Those lessons, for an incumbent vice president defending a relatively popular administration against a sitting governor, are becoming increasingly evident. The basic thrust: try to hamstring the opponent by raising questions about his record and his readiness to be president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a fullblown attack today on Gov. George W. Bush over foreign policy, Vice President Al Gore seemed to be executing a classic incumbent strategy, one made especially classic by Governor Bush's father, then the vice president, against another sitting governor in 1988.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign has been sifting through the detritus of the elder Mr. Bush's steamrolling of Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts and has unearthed useful lessons. Those lessons, for an incumbent vice president defending a relatively popular administration against a sitting governor, are becoming increasingly evident. The basic thrust: try to hamstring the opponent by raising questions about his record and his readiness to be president.</p>
        <p>Neither the Gore campaign nor the Bush campaign particularly likes the analogy. The Gore team says it is having a high-minded policy debate and is not employing negative personal attacks. The Bush campaign says Mr. Gore, unlike Vice President George Bush in 1988, is misrepresenting the governor's record.</p>
        <p>Their routes may be different, but the Gore campaign arrives at the same place Governor Bush's father arrived a dozen years ago. They both present a sitting vice president as the responsible steward of the current peace and prosperity. And they both cast the challenger as risky and irresponsible and his state as an alien universe that is culturally out of the mainstream. Already, Texas has been portrayed as such an aberration that it almost resembles, well, Massachusetts in 1988.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush began this campaign much the way Governor Dukakis began his, as the respected if little-known executive of a state that had appeared to make strides economically and socially.</p>
        <p>By the end of the 1988 campaign, of course, Mr. Dukakis had become a laughingstock. His ''Massachusetts Miracle'' was in shreds. Boston Harbor had become synonymous with pollution and neglect. And Mr. Dukakis himself had become the emblem of effete liberalism, impractical ineffectuality and, perhaps worst of all, insufficient patriotism.</p>
        <p>Part of this was Mr. Dukakis's  fault. He did not think Vice President Bush's attacks were worth answering. And he slapped on a helmet and climbed into a battle tank, providing perhaps the most enduring, if hapless, image of his campaign.</p>
        <p>This time around, Mr. Gore's chief criticism of Mr. Bush was initially confined to the governor's ''risky tax scheme.'' But he has ratcheted up that criticism every day. Now the word ''risky,'' supplemented by ''irresponsible'' and ''reckless,'' is applied to the entire Bush world view. The risky tax scheme begets a risky economic plan, which encompasses risky health and education plans and so on.</p>
        <p>So in a major foreign policy speech in Boston today, Mr. Gore criticized Mr. Bush for talking about a costly and controversial Star Wars missile defense plan in his meeting with the foreign minister of Russia and said the Texan ''chose the worst possible venue in which to launch -- for lack of a better phrase -- his risky foreign policy scheme.''</p>
        <p>He continued, ''I won't even guess at the new math needed to make his risky foreign policy scheme and his risky tax scheme add up.''</p>
        <p>On the domestic policy front, Mr. Gore has portrayed Mr. Bush's Texas as a backwater with substandard education and inadequate health insurance and its residents as so gun-happy that the governor signed a bill allowing them to take weapons into churches. Further, Mr. Gore likes to link Governor Bush with the ''failed'' policies of his father and refers often to ''the Bush-Quayle recession.''</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Gore said Mr. Bush was ''stuck in a cold war mindset'' and that he would have to fill in the ''gaps'' in his knowledge of foreign policy with the right-wing isolationist ideology of Congressional Republicans like Senator Jesse Helms.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Gore has learned from the 1988 campaign, so has Governor Bush. Instead of allowing Mr. Gore to define him the way Vice President Bush defined Governor Dukakis, Governor Bush has tried to the avoid the extremist conservative box Mr. Gore has tried to put him in.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has spent much time reaching for the political center, especially on issues like education and health care, which have traditionally been viewed as more favorable to Democrats. And he has emphasized bipartisanship and his ability to work with Democrats.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has also been quicker to respond to attacks than was Governor Dukakis. Unlike Mr. Dukakis, Governor Bush is not only resisting Mr. Gore's caricature of him but is constructing his own caricature of Mr. Gore, as the candidate who does not tell the truth and is bent on a campaign of destruction. The constant refrain from the Bush campaign is that Mr. Gore ''will say anything to get elected.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has pushed away any suggestion that he is being negative, saying he believes the country wants a healthy debate on the issues people care about. He has already signaled what some of those issues will be and how he intends to use them, as in recent days, when he excoriated Mr. Bush's record on the environment by calling Texas the most polluted state in the country, citing Houston's chronic air pollution as an example.</p>
        <p>And while some in the Gore campaign have been studying the 1988 campaign -- its similarities include an incumbent vice president who began the campaign in double digits behind a governor -- his spokesman rejects the idea that the 1988 Bush campaign is any kind of model.</p>
        <p>''We're putting out our positive vision,'' said Chris Lehane, a spokesman for Mr. Gore. ''The difference is that in 1988, Bush's goal was to pull down Dukakis.''</p>
        <p>For an incumbent to portray a challenger as too much of a risk is hardly unprecedented. Lyndon B. Johnson's devastating ''countdown'' commercial imprinted on television viewers the image of nuclear destruction should they elect Barry Goldwater. And Jimmy Carter suggested that Ronald Reagan was too extreme to have his finger on the nuclear button.</p>
        <p>It was in this long tradition that Vice President Gore's first television commercial, once he secured the nomination, said to viewers: ''Al Gore is ready. Is George W.?''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
