<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buffett Holds Court at Berkshire Weekend</title>
    <meta content="01BERK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Berkshire Hathaway Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buffett, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4DB1539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buffett Holds Court at Berkshire Weekend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <dateline>OMAHA, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investors at Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting take comfort from drop in New Economy stocks shunned by company head Warren E Buffett and improvement in company's own depressed stock; Buffett again bars investing in technology stocks; says it its so hard to find good values of any kind in stock market that he may cut holdings in publicly traded companies to about 10 percent (from estimated 33 percent) and buy more companies outright; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the stock of Berkshire Hathaway on the rise again after taking a beating in the last year -- and the New Economy stocks Warren E. Buffett has shunned now looking more risky -- shareholders came to his annual meeting over the weekend willing to grant him some vindication. But maybe -- just maybe -- he could pep up his portfolio, some said, by venturing into technology.</p>
        <p>''Two months ago, when Berkshire stock was trading at around $45,000 -- down from almost $80,000 last year -- people were ready to throw tomatoes at Warren Buffett,'' said Andrew Kilpatrick, a Birmingham, Ala., stockbroker and author of a book on Mr. Buffett. ''But, by gosh, the price is coming back and the mood is changing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the stock of Berkshire Hathaway on the rise again after taking a beating in the last year -- and the New Economy stocks Warren E. Buffett has shunned now looking more risky -- shareholders came to his annual meeting over the weekend willing to grant him some vindication. But maybe -- just maybe -- he could pep up his portfolio, some said, by venturing into technology.</p>
        <p>''Two months ago, when Berkshire stock was trading at around $45,000 -- down from almost $80,000 last year -- people were ready to throw tomatoes at Warren Buffett,'' said Andrew Kilpatrick, a Birmingham, Ala., stockbroker and author of a book on Mr. Buffett. ''But, by gosh, the price is coming back and the mood is changing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett himself is not the sort to claim vindication. But he said it was so difficult to find good values of any kind in the stock market that, over the coming decade, he may cut his holdings in publicly traded companies to about 10 percent of his investments (from an estimated 33 percent now) and put the rest into buying companies outright.</p>
        <p>Most of the 10,000 shareholders gathering at the Omaha Civic Auditorium on Saturday were fierce Buffett loyalists, come to enjoy the parties and perhaps have their photos snapped with their hero.</p>
        <p>But several gently asked why Mr. Buffett could not find a way to make money on technology stocks. Gaylord Hansen from Santa Barbara, Calif., said he had lost money on his Berskshire investment last year but made up for it with four tech stocks.</p>
        <p>''Are we asking too much,'' he asked, ''that you put your brain to work and spend a little bit, maybe 10 percent of our money, in the only play in town, which is technology?''</p>
        <p>Nothing doing, replied Mr. Buffett, repeating his stock answer: ''We will never buy anything we don't understand.'' Later, he said he doubted anybody -- not even his friends Bill Gates and Andrew Grove of Intel -- truly knew which technology stocks would be doing best 10 years from now.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett's willingness to shun publicly traded shares more generally reflects his conviction that the market is overvalued. Alice D. Schroeder of PaineWebber, often regarded as the leading analyst of Berkshire, estimated that the company now has about 33 percent in publicly traded stocks, with the rest representing wholly owned companies like Geico, the rapidly growing auto insurer and Dairy Queen.</p>
        <p>Several other well-known investors also have acknowledged that tech stocks are beyond them. Only last Friday, George Soros said that because of his losses in technology investments, he was shifting to a more conservative strategy.</p>
        <p>Thomas Kamei, a 10-year-old shareholder from Kentfield, Calif., whose mother Nancy is an investment analyst, asked if the Internet might hurt some of Berkshire's investments, including The Washington Post and Wells Fargo bank. Mr. Buffett said he recognized a threat but said he did not know how it would play out.</p>
        <p>Many Berkshire investors are just as happy to treat it like a value-oriented mutual fund. Leaving the meeting, Jack Rhodes, a retired executive from Peoria, Ill., and his wife, Betty, said that they could invest in high-fliers on their own.  ''Berkshire is just the safe part of our portfolio,'' Mrs. Rhodes said. ''We have lots of technology and telephone stocks -- the ones that are moving, the ones that make you nervous.''</p>
        <p>Many Berkshire shareholders were happy to concentrate on the long term, saying that their faith in Mr. Buffett's philosophy of investing in old economy standbys had not been shaken. ''It's going to be all right,'' said Sam Park, a neurologist from Tulsa, Okla., who has 90 percent of his portfolio in Berkshire Hathaway. ''The underlying business value is there.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Park said that, even at the current price, most of the Berkshire stock he has been accumulating for years are ''still way ahead.'' To discourage short-term trading, Mr. Buffett has never split Berkshire's shares, although a few years ago the company issued B shares that represent a small fraction of an original share's value.</p>
        <p>After outperforming the Standard  &amp; Poor's 500 index of stocks for most of the last 35 years, Berkshire gained only half a percentage point last year. On March 10th the shares hit a low of $40,800. In his annual report a few days later, Mr. Buffett said he might consider buying shares of Berkshire back. With that expression of confidence, the stock rebounded.</p>
        <p>The meeting, conducted by Mr. Buffett with his vice chairman and alter ego, Charles T. Munger, rambled along for six hours, with the two graying executives playing the role of business school professors and shareholders the awe-struck students. Mr. Buffett may be one of the few chief executives to have a shareholder seriously ask whether he wanted to succeed Alan Greenspan (no).</p>
        <p>Some shareholders asked how the big commercial insurance company that Berkshire bought in 1998, General Re, could be turned around after  losing more than $1 billion last year. General Re, Mr. Buffett said, would seek higher prices.</p>
        <p>A shareholder whose brother works at Coca Cola complained to Mr. Buffett, who sits on the Coke board as one of the company's major investors, about the generous severance package for Douglas Ivester, the recently replaced chief executive. ''It was definitely the right decision for Coke,'' to reach a severance agreement, Mr. Buffett said, while adding, ''I would not want to defend the small details.''</p>
        <p>On one technology matter, Mr. Buffett did have some opinions. While not explicitly condemning the Government's proposal to break Microsoft in two, Mr. Buffett said, ''We've got something that works very well and it probably doesn't make a lot of sense to tinker with it -- I would not go in with a meat ax.''</p>
        <p>Berskshire's performance showed no signs of cooling the weekend's usual carnival spirit, including a jazz and champagne reception at Borsheim's, Berkshire's Omaha jewelry store that is one of the nation's largest.</p>
        <p>In a film that opened the meeting, Mr. Buffett strummed a ukulele and sang about investing. Later, he pulled on a baseball uniform and strode to the mound at Omaha's minor league baseball stadium to hurl a few looping pitches that he described as fast balls.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
