<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; A patent lawyer wins protection for a product intended to help others win protection for theirs.</title>
    <meta content="01PATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rockwell International Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">petruzzi, james d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">mason, robert m</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DA1539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; A patent lawyer wins protection for a product intended to help others win protection for theirs.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patent attorney James D Petruzzi and Robert M Mason win first of its kind patent for technology for preparing patent applications; say technology has already been used to win patents; Rockwell International Corp patents method of creating software that allows shoppers on e-commerce Web sites to choose time and place for customer service representative to call them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PATENTS that cover methods of doing business may be controversial, but perhaps only one patent is genuinely redundant. A Dallas company has won a patent for a method of applying for a patent.</p>
        <p>The company, Kernel Creations Ltd., says this is the first time the patent and trademark agency has awarded a patent for a technology for preparing a patent application.  And it says that inventors have already been awarded patents based on applications prepared using the software.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PATENTS that cover methods of doing business may be controversial, but perhaps only one patent is genuinely redundant. A Dallas company has won a patent for a method of applying for a patent.</p>
        <p>The company, Kernel Creations Ltd., says this is the first time the patent and trademark agency has awarded a patent for a technology for preparing a patent application.  And it says that inventors have already been awarded patents based on applications prepared using the software.</p>
        <p>There are any number of how-to and do-it-yourself books and manuals offering inventors guidance through the patenting process. There are videos and software that advise applicants. Some people are skilled enough in the arcane language of patent applications to prepare their own; they can even produce technical drawings that meet the exacting standards of the patent and trademark agency. But applying for a patent is an ambitious undertaking that requires knowledge of patent law, agency regulations and examiners' procedures, as well as a draftsman's steady hand.</p>
        <p>If anecdotal evidence is any measure, many inventors who submit their own applications end up turning to a patent attorney or agent after their documents are rejected as inadequate. That requires the inventor to explain his invention to the attorney so the application can be made  as legally binding as possible. And the lawyer's expertise costs money.</p>
        <p>James D. Petruzzi says inventors can avoid some of that trouble and expense with his software. Mr. Petruzzi is a patent attorney himself -- but he does not believe his invention will harm those in the business.</p>
        <p>''We found in our practice that a lot of people don't have the resources to pay a patent attorney to go through the process, and they're being cut out,'' Mr. Petruzzi said. ''This software enables a lot of people to get into the system and apply for patents.''</p>
        <p>He also thinks the software will enable patent lawyers to avoid complications that can arise when they try to write a patent application without enough consultation with the inventor.</p>
        <p>''I've seen many patents drafted by attorneys, and once they got into litigation, I saw that the inventor was not involved in the drafting process, and that caused problems down the road,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>The software divides the task of writing a patent application into sections.</p>
        <p>''A patent application is sort of like a short story, not a fill-in-the-blanks process,'' Mr. Petruzzi said. ''The software takes you through the sections of the application to build an entire document. It starts with a central analysis of the invention, and from that it generates other fields, claims and abstracts.</p>
        <p>''The real key to the patent and the process is the fact that the sections are interlinked. As you do Section 1, it creates something in Section 2, and 1 and 2 build Section 3. As you go through it, it builds the format commonly used in patent applications, and then you can go through and edit it.''</p>
        <p>The software draws words from the inventor's title and primary descriptions to write the application in the prose and format particular to the United States Patent and Trademark Office.</p>
        <p>''When you think about a patent, 95 percent of it is a technical description of the invention,'' Mr. Petruzzi said. ''That doesn't require legalese, but for the inventor to disclose what the invention is, how it works, what are the significant modifications. We really push the fact that the claims need to be written in a clear manner.''</p>
        <p>The company is already selling the software under the name PatentPro (www.4patpro.com).</p>
        <p>''A lot of people use the program to prepare a draft application and give it to their patent attorney and reduce costs,'' Mr. Petruzzi said. He and his partner, Robert M. Mason, won patent 6,049,811.</p>
        <p>For Online Shoppers, A Call-Back Feature</p>
        <p>Thousands, and possibly millions,  of people went shopping online for Christmas gifts and other holiday gifts last winter, proving the attraction of buying by computer. Those shoppers encountered some new business methods, like one-click buying, that have set off fights over who owns e-commerce technologies.</p>
        <p>Now the Rockwell International Corporation, which builds customer contact products like those used in airline call centers, has won a patent that is aimed at adding another customer convenience to online shopping. The patent allows a Web site to display a ''call me'' button so people can choose a time and place for a customer service representative from an online business to call them.</p>
        <p>The invention is already in use on the Internet, but Rockwell's vice president of development, Roger Sumner, does not think the patent will generate the disputes that have arisen around Amazon.com's patent for one-click shopping.</p>
        <p>''If you look at when the product was first introduced, and when the patent application was first filed, the method certainly wasn't in the public domain and wasn't something you often saw,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>Rockwell began designing the technology in the mid-1990's. ''Web site design was still fairly immature,'' Mr. Sumner said, ''and people would get to a dead end, couldn't get the information they wanted, and needed to talk to a person.''</p>
        <p>Researchers began to design a call-back system that would allow a customer to choose a range of times for receiving a call. After providing a name and phone number, the customer could choose to be called immediately or at a predetermined time, from five minutes later to a different day.</p>
        <p>''Basically the patent covers the method for creating software that conducts a call-back function based on Web interaction,'' said Mr. Sumner, who is also the company's chief technology officer.</p>
        <p>''People still feel a need to talk to a live person to complete a transaction,'' Mr. Sumner said. ''Even in today's environment, where companies have become extremely good at Web site design, customers still get roadblocked, lost, or feel a need to talk to an individual.''</p>
        <p>The inventors, Anthony J. Dezonno and William R. Quayle, won patent 5,991,394 for Rockwell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
