<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chekhov Is Recast: Laughter Plays Painkiller</title>
    <meta content="01VANY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roundabout Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chekhov, Anton (1860-1904)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayer, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobi, Derek</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Uncle Vanya (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DC1539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chekhov Is Recast: Laughter Plays Painkiller</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Roundabout Theater Co production of Anton Chekov's play Uncle Vanya, directed by Michael Mayer; Derek Jacobi stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Scenes From Country Life'' is the official subtitle that hangs, with the humility of a disclaimer, from the brooding masterpiece known as ''Uncle Vanya.'' But such self-effacing modesty doesn't fit the guffaw of a production that opened last night at the Brooks Atkinson Theater. No, some other appellation is required, something with a more vaudevillian punch. Perhaps something like ''Uncle Vanya, or Take My Life . . . Please.''</p>
        <p>Anton Chekhov, meet Henny Youngman. The director Michael Mayer's ill-advised new interpretation of the 1897 drama for the Roundabout Theater Company, which manages to dim even the luster of the extraordinary British actor Derek Jacobi, seems determined to trace the borscht belt back to Mother Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Scenes From Country Life'' is the official subtitle that hangs, with the humility of a disclaimer, from the brooding masterpiece known as ''Uncle Vanya.'' But such self-effacing modesty doesn't fit the guffaw of a production that opened last night at the Brooks Atkinson Theater. No, some other appellation is required, something with a more vaudevillian punch. Perhaps something like ''Uncle Vanya, or Take My Life . . . Please.''</p>
        <p>Anton Chekhov, meet Henny Youngman. The director Michael Mayer's ill-advised new interpretation of the 1897 drama for the Roundabout Theater Company, which manages to dim even the luster of the extraordinary British actor Derek Jacobi, seems determined to trace the borscht belt back to Mother Russia.</p>
        <p>This is a world of stand-up sufferers, folks who never look more contented than when expounding on their profound unhappiness directly to the audience from the center of the stage. These plaints are usually delivered in loud, attention-demanding voices and embellished with big, flapping gestures. Get thee behind me, Stanislavski.</p>
        <p>The idea of Chekhov's theatrical chronicles of disappointment as comedies has long been a subject of interpretive debate. Americans, in particular, have recently seemed most comfortable in emphasizing the farcical aspects of the playwright, as if that were the only way to avoid being boring in portraying people who are terminally bored. Several seasons ago, the physically overwrought Lincoln Center production of ''Ivanov,'' which starred Kevin Kline, turned existential ennui into something like an aerobics class.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mayer appears to be working from the principle that in Chekhov's world life must be acknowledged as one big joke, albeit one without an explanatory punch line. The characters -- as embodied by an ensemble that includes, in addition to Mr. Jacobi, such estimable performers as Roger Rees, Brian Murray and Anne Pitoniak -- have accordingly arrived at the conclusion that given the futility of it all, you might as well laugh. This isn't, in theory, a terrible idea. But as executed here, it leads to a broad, disconnected style of performance that is as short on compassion as it is on psychological continuity. There are a few lightning flashes that illuminate the pain in the forced frivolity, mostly from Mr. Jacobi and Mr. Rees.</p>
        <p>But by and large, you don't believe that these noisy showoffs even know one another, much less that they are capable of inflicting deep mutual pain. It is a sure sign that there has been serious miscalculation when the audience starts laughing during Sonya's final consoling speech to Vanya about life's cruelties.</p>
        <p>Your heart aches for Amy Ryan, the young actress playing Sonya, but then your heart aches for pretty much everyone, though for reasons unintended by Chekhov. Ms. Ryan plays one of the country drudges whose lives are thrown out of joint when the estate on which they toil is visited by Sonya's father, the pompous professor Serebryakov (Mr. Murray), and his beautiful young wife, Yelena (Laura Linney).</p>
        <p>These cosmopolitan arrivals are diverting and destructive for the provincial stay-at-homes like Sonya's embittered uncle, Vanya (Mr. Jacobi), and the more vibrant Astrov (Mr. Rees), one of Chekhov's piercing portraits of a disillusioned doctor. Astrov and Vanya are both in love with Yelena, while Astrov is worshiped by the unlovely Sonya. This doesn't keep everyone from being bored, bored, bored.</p>
        <p>At least that's what the script, translated here in a doggedly vernacular manner by Mike Poulton, tells us. The feelings that emanate from the stage are mostly autoerotic. This has something to do with the widely divergent acting styles on display and probably more to do with the sense that the performances only rarely tally with the descriptions given by the characters of themselves and of one another.</p>
        <p>Yelena, for example, is famously talked about as being charismatically listless, a languishing mermaid. (Janet McTeer took the idea to fascinating, somnambulistic extremes in the London production of 1992.) Yet Ms. Linney, who has previously registered most appealingly on stage (''Sight Unseen'') and film (''The Truman Show''), is here as brisk, vital and exhortative as a gym teacher who all but shouts most of her lines.</p>
        <p>And where is the dutiful, long-suffering Sonya everyone keeps talking about? Ms. Ryan comes across as an impatient, testy virago, her face plastered with a frown that says, a la Paddy Chayevsky, ''I'm mad as hell and I'm not going to take it anymore!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murray brings his juicy flamboyance to the dry-as-dust Serebryakov and as a consequence registers as something closer to a minor Dickensian villain than anything out of Chekhov. Nor do Ms. Pitoniak as the comforting old nanny, David Patrick Kelly as the pathetic hanger-on known as Waffles and Rita Gam as Vanya's annoying and unloving mother provide any anchoring sense of credibility.</p>
        <p>It is these smaller roles that are most essential in creating the atmosphere that defines and circumscribes the major characters. And that thick, enclosing ambience just isn't evident here, for all the show's glamorous production values: Tony Walton's truly ravishing set, David van Tighem's tapestry of rural sound effects and Kenneth Posner's handsomely moody lighting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rees and Mr. Jacobi could obviously, in other contexts, do marvelous things with their assigned parts. But here, being fed little emotionally by the other performers, they are forced to overcompensate with jokey flourishes and exaggerated line readings.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Rees is a familiar presence on the New York stage, Mr. Jacobi is the sadder casualty. This master of psychological nuance, so memorably seen in New York with the Royal Shakespeare Company, certainly isn't lacking in stylishness here, or in intriguing ideas about his character, whom he has played before in England.</p>
        <p>His Vanya isn't the constricted, emotionally cramped creature of Ian McKellen's fine performance opposite Ms. McTeer for the Royal National Theater. He is instead extravagantly effete and discontented, given to grand gestures that he regrets as soon as he makes them.</p>
        <p>This tendency is most spectacularly realized in Vanya's gale-force tantrum in Act III. It's a bravura moment, but so much of Mr. Jacobi's preceding performance has been pitched so close to that same level that it doesn't jolt as it should.</p>
        <p>It is Mr. Jacobi, however, who provides the evening's only real moments of fresh insight. In particular, he gives a tantalizing new dimension to the relationship between Vanya and his sister, whose name he cannot mention without melting into misty affection.</p>
        <p>Of course, the sister is long dead when the play begins. That she is half of the only believable relationship to be found in this ''Uncle Vanya'' is a sad indication of the production's failings.</p>
        <p>UNCLE VANYA</p>
        <p>By Anton Chekhov; translated by Mike Poulton; directed by Michael Mayer; sets and costumes by Tony Walton; lighting by Kenneth Posner; original music and sound by David van Tieghem; hair/wig design by Paul Huntley; vocal consultant, Elizabeth Smith; fight director, J. Steven White; director of production, Nancy Harrington; technical supervision by Unitech; production stage manager, Lori M. Doyle; associate artistic director, Scott Ellis. Presented by the Roundabout Theater Company, Todd Haimes, artistic director; Ellen Richard, managing director; Julia C. Levy, executive director, external affairs. At the Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street.</p>
        <p>WITH: Roger Rees (Astrov), Anne Pitoniak (Marina), Derek Jacobi (Vanya), David Patrick Kelly (Telegin), Brian Murray (Serebryakov), Amy Ryan (Sonya), Laura Linney (Yelena) and Rita Gam (Maria Vasilyevna).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
