<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Cabby, a Night of Calculating Risks</title>
    <meta content="01NIGH$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miranda, Angel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DD1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Cabby, a Night of Calculating Risks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chronology of nine-hour overnight shift of livery cab driver, Angel Miranda, who works some of toughest sections of upper Manhattan and Bronx; his strategy for accepting customers in wake of murders of nine livery drivers since start of year discussed; he relies mainly on dispatchers to screen out those considered potentially dangerous; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nine hours into his overnight shift, Angel Miranda drove his livery cab back to his base in Manhattan at 12:30 yesterday morning. It was turning into a good night: he had already picked up a dozen fares and $270, tucking the bills into his ashtray, his shoes and a compartment on the driver-side door.</p>
        <p>He double-parked his Lincoln Town Car in front of First Class Car and Limo Service, on Broadway at 211th Street, and fell asleep in the front seat. Thirty minutes later, he headed out again, for another three and a half hours on the streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nine hours into his overnight shift, Angel Miranda drove his livery cab back to his base in Manhattan at 12:30 yesterday morning. It was turning into a good night: he had already picked up a dozen fares and $270, tucking the bills into his ashtray, his shoes and a compartment on the driver-side door.</p>
        <p>He double-parked his Lincoln Town Car in front of First Class Car and Limo Service, on Broadway at 211th Street, and fell asleep in the front seat. Thirty minutes later, he headed out again, for another three and a half hours on the streets.</p>
        <p>After five years driving a livery cab on weekend nights through some of the toughest neighborhoods of upper Manhattan and the Bronx, Mr. Miranda, 34, has a particular way of doing things, for his sanity and survival.</p>
        <p>He will not pick up anyone wearing a ski cap -- a potential robber's mask -- or anyone with what he calls a thuggish style of dress.</p>
        <p>He relies on his dispatchers, who sound like auctioneers as they shout out addresses over the radio in crackling rapid-fire Spanish, to screen out those who are considered potentially dangerous customers. If he hears a call for a pickup in Harlem or one of the rougher neighborhoods in the Bronx, Mr. Miranda will not take the fare unless the dispatcher says something reassuring, like the coded message ''11-4 positivo.'' That means the passenger, 11-4, has used the car service before.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Miranda gets really tired, he parks and naps -- but only outside First Class, or at a 24-hour gas station, or near a police station house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda -- known on the job as ''78,'' the number on his car's bumper and on the gold ring on his right pinky -- has good reason to be careful. Two drivers for First Class have been murdered on the job in the last four years, men known to Mr. Miranda only as ''264,'' who was killed in 1997, and ''313,'' who was shot on Jan. 12, in the second of nine killings of livery drivers this year. The victims' real names are Anthony Hernandez and Jose Torres.</p>
        <p>This year's killings have confounded the police and panicked the industry, whose drivers work in poor, high-crime neighborhoods where yellow cabs are seldom seen.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Miranda said he was not nervous.</p>
        <p>''I believe in destiny, and if that's my destiny, I guess that will be it,'' he said. ''But anything could happen to anyone, and I can't let that stop me from driving.''</p>
        <p>Above all else, Mr. Miranda said, he depends on his instincts for protection. He used his own tricks of perception and judgment often over a three-and-a-half-hour drive yesterday, from 1 to 4:30 a.m., in deciding whom to pick up and where to go.</p>
        <p>1:15 a.m.</p>
        <p>Two young women returning from a party walk into First Class and ask for a ride to 169th Street and Grant Avenue in the Bronx. Mr. Miranda takes them in his car, turning on the radio as he leaves, to KISS-FM at 98.7, a rhythm and blues station. Mr. Miranda, who was born in New York but grew up in Puerto Rico before returning to the city, says he prefers Spanish-language radio, but plays that station or CD 101.9 FM -- light jazz -- when he has passengers.</p>
        <p>On the way, near University Avenue, he passes a livery cab that has been pulled over by the police. As part of increased security measures in response to the killings, patrol officers have been stopping livery drivers and questioning them to ''make sure everything is O.K.,'' as one officer explained. They do this mostly along main thoroughfares in the Bronx, where five of the livery slayings have occurred.</p>
        <p>1:45 a.m.</p>
        <p>Dispatchers send Mr. Miranda to a pickup on Townsend Avenue, in the Mount Eden section of the Bronx. On the way, he sees another cab pulled over by officers.</p>
        <p>2:45 a.m.</p>
        <p>After picking up the Townsend Avenue fares -- a woman and her three young children -- Mr. Miranda drops them off at Gerard Avenue in the Concourse Village section. Another fare comes over the radio. ''St. Nicholas and 145th,'' the dispatcher shouts: a corner in Harlem. No one responds. There are about 100 drivers cruising the streets on the overnight shift. If none of them press the button on their microphones indicating they want a fare, the dispatchers shout out the location again, up to five or six times. After the fifth broadcast of ''St. Nicholas and 145th,'' the dispatcher clarifies things: ''Hispanic female.'' Another driver quickly takes the call.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda acknowledges that the exchange appeared racist.</p>
        <p>Then he adds that although he uses the dispatchers' codes as a guide, when he picks up a passenger on the street, he goes by appearance, clothing, eye contact -- ''a vibe,'' not race. During the night he will drive past several people hailing him, all young men of different races, explaining that they ''just didn't look right.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda says that Hispanic drivers are generally more comfortable with Hispanic passengers, though he adds that drivers at his service generally do not discriminate through racial stereotyping.</p>
        <p>In dangerous neighborhoods, he says, drivers simply avoid people who look threatening -- and threatening people can be of any color.</p>
        <p>The Taxi and Limousine Commission prohibits livery drivers from picking up passengers off the street, but Mr. Miranda says night shift drivers do it all the time, though less so after the recent killings.</p>
        <p>2:50 a.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda decides to cruise by Jimmy's Bronx Cafe, a popular nightclub in the University Heights section. He says livery drivers often head to nightclubs in Manhattan and the Bronx between 3 and 4 a.m., when many people are leaving.</p>
        <p>2:55 a.m.</p>
        <p>He picks up a couple standing in front of the club and drives them a short distance home, to Bailey Avenue and 233rd Street.</p>
        <p>He then answers a call to pick up a passenger in East Harlem. He picks up a young woman and takes her back to the Bronx, dropping her off at the River Park Towers in the Morris Heights section, near the Major Deegan Expressway. Then he decides to drive back to Jimmy's.</p>
        <p>3:20 a.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda gets on the Major Deegan, going north, and within a few minutes is stuck in a traffic jam. His car edges slowly toward an accident scene. He can see a yellow taxicab parked diagonally across two lanes of the highway, several police officers, a motorcycle and someone lying in the road. Mr. Miranda immediately exits the highway at 179th Street and takes back streets to Jimmy's.</p>
        <p>[The police said yesterday that an accident on the Major Deegan caused the congestion, but that they did not have information about the person on the highway. Three passengers in the yellow cab got into a dispute with the driver during the traffic jam, and one later slashed the driver, wounding him in the face and the chest, said the police, who were investigating the attack last night.]</p>
        <p>3:25 a.m.</p>
        <p>Back at Jimmy's, Mr. Miranda makes what he later says was a bad judgment call, picking up two young men on the street. The first, wearing a baseball cap and slurring his words, approaches and asks for a ride to what Mr. Miranda later says is one of the worst neighborhoods of the Bronx, the Morrisania section. Mr. Miranda stares back, looking uncomfortable. The man tells Mr. Miranda he wants to wait for his friend, who then appears from an alley. (Mr. Miranda says later that that was a red flag that would normally persuade him not to take the fare.) The two get in the cab.</p>
        <p>3:40 a.m.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, the men are drunk but harmless, and Mr. Miranda drops them off on 167th Street and Union Avenue, charging $8 for the ride. Mr. Miranda now has about $350 in cash in his car. He has no bullet-resistant partition or security camera in his car, but soon he will have to. Three days after the seventh livery driver was killed, the Taxi and Limousine Commission voted to require all cab drivers to install one or the other safety device by May 18.</p>
        <p>Asked if he would feel safer with a partition, Mr. Miranda says it would make his life miserable. To install a partition, he would have to move his seat all the way forward, locking it into place. Then he would not be able to recline and nap in either of the front seats. He plans instead to purchase a digital security camera.</p>
        <p>3:45 a.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda is heading back to base, after a 12 1/2-hour day, when a group of young men flag him down. They are disc jockeys who have just finished a job at a party. The men offer Mr. Miranda $50 to take them and their equipment to Valentine Avenue, in Bedford Park. The men, speaking in Spanish, tell him they have called 15 car services and all refused to come to the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>4:10 a.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda drops the disc jockeys off and counts his earnings: $406. He typically makes $150 to $300 on an overnight shift, so this is a good run. Mr. Miranda, along with other drivers he met at another car service, Riverside, was one of the founders of First Class, which opened in 1995, and he owns his cab, a 1994 Lincoln, so he takes home all the money he earns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda works seven days a week. He works Monday to Friday, typically from 7 a.m. to 7 p.m., as a printing press operator for Manhattan Color on Varick Street, and then drives the overnight shift for First Class on Fridays, when he works from 7 a.m. to about 3 a.m. between the two jobs. He does the overnight again on Saturdays. On Sundays, he drives from about 1 p.m to 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>He lives in the Castle Hill section of the Bronx and says he is helping to support three children by two mothers who live elsewhere. The cab driving is lucrative; he makes $500 to $600 a weekend, but he says he needs the day job to get health benefits and save for his future, in a 401(k).</p>
        <p>4:20 a.m.</p>
        <p>On his last trip of the night, driving west on the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway to drop off a reporter in Brooklyn -- making another $39.50 -- Mr. Miranda is asked if he ever gets sick of being in the car for 12 to 14 hours.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he says. ''I love the car. I like the excitement of the city, driving around and looking at everything. I look at these streets like an obstacle course.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
