<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honduras Gives Meaning To a Meaningless Match</title>
    <meta content="01SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ecuador</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ecuador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Ecuador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE1239F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honduras Gives Meaning To a Meaningless Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>HERSHEY, Pa., April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Honduras defeats United States, 2-1, to win regional Olympic qualifying tournament in soccer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Honduras defeated the United States, 2-1, today to win the regional Olympic qualifying tournament in soccer, ecstatic fans held blue-and-white Honduran flags in two hands and waved them as a matador waves a cape. They serenaded the team with loud horns at Hersheypark Stadium, while the players carried Coach Ramon Enrique Maradiaga on their shoulders for a victory lap.</p>
        <p>Ten days earlier, when players temporarily boycotted the tournament over nonpayment of bonuses, there had been a different reaction toward the team in Honduras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Honduras defeated the United States, 2-1, today to win the regional Olympic qualifying tournament in soccer, ecstatic fans held blue-and-white Honduran flags in two hands and waved them as a matador waves a cape. They serenaded the team with loud horns at Hersheypark Stadium, while the players carried Coach Ramon Enrique Maradiaga on their shoulders for a victory lap.</p>
        <p>Ten days earlier, when players temporarily boycotted the tournament over nonpayment of bonuses, there had been a different reaction toward the team in Honduras.</p>
        <p>''They wanted to stone us,'' Maradiaga said.</p>
        <p>Today's match, played before 12,129 fans, was not particularly meaningful in terms of the Olympics, as both teams had qualified Friday for the 2000 Games in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Yet the conclusion represented a stunningly improbable resurrection for a Honduran team that arrived as a national shame the day the tournament began, lost, 3-0, to the United States and then recovered to win the North American, Central American and Caribbean regional tournament, defeating the heavily favored Americans and Mexicans in three days.</p>
        <p>''The team was trashed in our country,'' Maradiaga said. ''We had to overcome it. The leaders, when we left, they were desiring that we do bad here. That's how bad it was.''</p>
        <p>Today, the enmity turned to celebration as forward Oscar David Suazo scored both goals for Honduras. The Central American nation will be making its first trip to the Olympics, a soccer minnow having defeated the whales of North America, and the fans who had driven from New York and Washington shouldered together to wave flags, take photographs and ask for autographs.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is watching on television in Honduras,'' said Pedro Martinez, a native of Honduras who owns a cleaning business in Hempstead, N.Y. ''It was everyone's dream to see Honduras in Sydney. I think my country will make a Carnival.''</p>
        <p>That was not the case when the players, owed $2,200 each in bonus money by the Honduran soccer federation and private sponsors, decided to boycott the tournament when they were not paid. News reports in Honduras said the enraged players were made to walk eight miles from the airport in Tegucigalpa, the capital, to their training camp. No such forced walk took place, the team captain, coach and a top federation official said today. Still, the players decided to boycott, said the captain, Maynor Suazo.</p>
        <p>The boycott ended when the players were threatened with two-year suspensions and the Honduran national team faced removal from the qualifying tournament for the 2002 World Cup. Promises were made to pay the bonus money, which the players eventually received in Hershey, said Sergio Sabillon, the leader of the Honduran delegation.</p>
        <p>''There are no more problems,'' Sabillon said. ''It has been resolved.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Honduran citizenry and news media did not react kindly toward the players.</p>
        <p>''They called us thieves,'' said Maynor Suazo, the cousin of Oscar David Suazo.</p>
        <p>It did not help that the money squabble interfered with travel plans and Honduras arrived at the Olympic qualifying tournament early on the morning of its opening match against the Americans, tired and distracted. Or that Oscar David Suazo was not available to play. He had not been released in time by his club team, Cagliari of the Italian league.</p>
        <p>Fast and powerful and playing on fresh legs, Suazo made the difference in today's rematch after the Americans took a 1-0 lead in the 12th minute on a slicing header by Josh Wolff. In the 29th minute, Suazo stepped around Danny Califf in the penalty area and scored after a give-and-go. In the 56th minute, he created the winning goal on a spectacular play, diving to flick a header into the net.</p>
        <p>''Honduras has shown the whole world that it can play soccer,'' said Rene Mena, a New York-based journalist who writes for El Tiempo, a Honduran sports weekly. ''It shows that the small countries play with a big heart.''</p>
        <p>And big-money problems, too. Maradiaga, the coach, said Honduran soccer players struggled with financial support and sufficient fields for training. It costs plenty of money to send a team to the Olympics. The International Olympic Committee and FIFA, soccer's world governing body, will help defray some costs. Still, potential exists for another bonus dust-up. Having qualified for the Sydney Games, the Honduran players are now owed another $4,000 each by the federation.</p>
        <p>''We have to wait to see if they fulfill their promise,'' Maradiaga said.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
