<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Decisions Give Workers New Hope in Kaiser Dispute</title>
    <meta content="Y01KAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aluminum</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Steelworkers of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Labor Relations Board</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kaiser Aluminum Corp</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EED71539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Decisions Give Workers New Hope in Kaiser Dispute</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Workers at Kaiser Aluminum, who have been on picket line for 19 months in one of nation's biggest and fiercest labor disputes, are given stronger hand by two federal agencies in showdown with management; National Labor Relations Board announces plans for unfair labor practices suit, charging company with illegally locking workers out for 15 months; Energy Dept moves to deny company access to heavily discounted electricity it has relied on for decades in Pacific Northwest following lobbying by United Steelworkers of America, which represents 2,900 striking Kaiser workers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 19 months on the picket line in one of the nation's biggest and fiercest labor disputes, 2,900 workers at Kaiser Aluminum have been given a stronger hand by two federal agencies in their showdown with management.</p>
        <p>First, the general counsel of the National Labor Relations Board announced plans last week to bring charges of unfair labor practices, saying Kaiser illegally locked out workers for 15 months. If those charges are upheld by administrative judges, Kaiser could be ordered to pay more than $200 million in back pay, which would make it the largest such award in the history of the labor board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 19 months on the picket line in one of the nation's biggest and fiercest labor disputes, 2,900 workers at Kaiser Aluminum have been given a stronger hand by two federal agencies in their showdown with management.</p>
        <p>First, the general counsel of the National Labor Relations Board announced plans last week to bring charges of unfair labor practices, saying Kaiser illegally locked out workers for 15 months. If those charges are upheld by administrative judges, Kaiser could be ordered to pay more than $200 million in back pay, which would make it the largest such award in the history of the labor board.</p>
        <p>In another unusual move, the federal Department of Energy took a step that could deny Kaiser access to the heavily discounted electricity that it has relied on for decades in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>The United Steelworkers of America, which represents the 2,900 Kaiser workers, had lobbied the Bonneville Power Administration, a federal agency, to deny the electricity discount to Kaiser because the company is not a good corporate citizen.</p>
        <p>Heeding the union's pleas, the Department of Energy and Bonneville Power proposed last week that from now on discounts on electricity could be denied to companies that were not good corporate citizens, a move that could cost Kaiser more than $10 million a year. Public comment is now being accepted on the proposal.</p>
        <p>''We've picked up tremendous momentum,'' said Dave Foster, president of the steelworkers' Northwest district. ''All this has solidified and encouraged our membership after an extraordinarily long fight. And all this can't help but increase our leverage at the bargaining table.''</p>
        <p>At meetings last week in Spokane, Wash., which has two Kaiser plants with 2,000 employees, many workers said the developments would put pressure on Kaiser to settle.</p>
        <p>The union went on strike against five Kaiser aluminum plants on Sept. 15, 1998, after rejecting the company's demands to reduce health benefits and eliminate 240 jobs. When many strikers grew disheartened, the union told Kaiser in January 1999 that the strikers wanted to return to work while negotiations continued. But Kaiser imposed a lockout and refused to let any union members back unless the steelworkers accepted all of Kaiser's demands.</p>
        <p>The steelworkers asked the National Labor Relations Board to bring 24 unfair labor practice charges against Kaiser. The general counsel, Leonard R. Page, rejected 22 of those proposed charges, but will file two of them, one accusing Kaiser of giving too little information about its salary proposal to allow for informed bargaining. Mr. Page also accused Kaiser of improperly insisting on having agreements for each of the five aluminum mills take precedence over a nationwide agreement.</p>
        <p>Raymond J. Milchovich, Kaiser's president, welcomed the dismissal of 22 of the 24 charges.</p>
        <p>''We are confident that the allegations on the remaining two issues are groundless and that, following a trial, they will be dismissed as well,'' Mr. Milchovich said.</p>
        <p>Kaiser officials accused Bonneville Power of playing politics and insisted that Kaiser was a good corporate citizen. Hoping that Bonneville Power would be persuaded not to adopt the good citizenship rule, Pete Foresyte, a company vice president, questioned whether it was proper for a utility to be ''judge and jury for a broad range of vague and ambiguous social issues.''</p>
        <p>Scott Lamb, the company's vice president for investor relations, said that except for a plant in Louisiana that blew up last year, the company's mills are operating better with replacement workers than they did with their regular work force.</p>
        <p>But union leaders say workers inside the plants tell them that production and productivity have fallen sharply.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
