<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surprises, Please, and Hold the Self-Glorification</title>
    <meta content="01REVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REVISIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Margo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Joni</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdonald, Audra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemper, Ute</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DB1539F932A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surprises, Please, and Hold the Self-Glorification</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margo Jefferson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jefferson, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margo Jefferson Revisions column reviews new recordings by Joni Mitchell, Audra McDonald and Ute Lemper; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who wants to be a millionaire or a diva today? The whole point of the now infamous television show is its cheery contempt for those workaday contestants who struggle to answer ordinary questions and then often blow their chances for the big money by choosing to go with what they've won instead of risking it all on one more try. Watch the smirk that Regis Philbin barely conceals when he  tells those wusses that they had the right answer and, if they had the guts, they could have walked off with a lot more cash.</p>
        <p>What VH1's popular ''Divas'' concerts display is contempt for music fans. They tell us that people get the rulers they deserve. Most of us don't have the money to elect politicians, but we do have the money to buy records: if we have made them stars, then we deserve pop goddesses like Celine Dion, Shania Twain, Faith Hill, Mariah Carey, Donna Summer and Diana Ross.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who wants to be a millionaire or a diva today? The whole point of the now infamous television show is its cheery contempt for those workaday contestants who struggle to answer ordinary questions and then often blow their chances for the big money by choosing to go with what they've won instead of risking it all on one more try. Watch the smirk that Regis Philbin barely conceals when he  tells those wusses that they had the right answer and, if they had the guts, they could have walked off with a lot more cash.</p>
        <p>What VH1's popular ''Divas'' concerts display is contempt for music fans. They tell us that people get the rulers they deserve. Most of us don't have the money to elect politicians, but we do have the money to buy records: if we have made them stars, then we deserve pop goddesses like Celine Dion, Shania Twain, Faith Hill, Mariah Carey, Donna Summer and Diana Ross.</p>
        <p>Aretha Franklin is exempt. Her voice is a faint outline of what it was, but it was lovely once, and she can still outsmart pretenders. (It's as if she's saying: ''You just keep climbing that hill of notes, Mariah and Celine. I'll float a few well-placed ones between breaths and you'll end up sounding like the pop-gospel engine that couldn't.'') Tina Turner and Cher also come from a far better place and time. And they have kept up. Ms. Turner has become a deluxe designer edition soul queen, while Cher is a wisecracking self-made fetish object.</p>
        <p>But as for Diana Ross, the object and subject of the ''Divas 2000'' concert, she has not bothered to make a decent recording or movie for years,  and her concert appearances have been few. The vanity is outlandish now; the performing skills are minimal. ''She's Norma Desmond,'' said a friend. ''If you're a baby boomer you pretend you still worship her. If you're young, you get turned into  horror-stricken William Holden.''</p>
        <p>Diva has always been a treacherous word, even in the opera world where it began. It's part of the melodrama of fan worship. We encourage divas to go beyond their talents and risk pure hubris, to worship themselves as much as we worship them. Then we watch a struggle that begins with self-caricature and ends, as tragedy dictates, with self-destruction.</p>
        <p>Today the diva machinery is a marketing tool, in opera as in pop, and it makes audiences prematurely greedy and cynical. So when I listen to new recordings by three singers, all with extensive diva credentials, I think: Please! Give them some elbow room. Just let them keep mapping out new routes on the landscape of popular music.</p>
        <p>Joni Mitchell has been born and reborn as a goddess of song. In her new CD, ''Both Sides Now'' (Warner Brothers), she takes standards from Tin Pan Alley and joins them to standards of her own (''A Case of You'' plus the title song) to make a song cycle. It follows a love affair from its start (''You're My Thrill'' and ''At Last'') to its disintegration and demise (''You've Changed'' and ''Don't Worry 'Bout Me''). And then on to those recovery efforts that start with defiance (''I Wish I Were in Love Again,'' though she doesn't make it taut or tart enough) and end with philosophizing (''Both Sides Now,'' which she does beautifully). Desolation recollected in tranquillity.</p>
        <p>You hear the singers she has listened to -- Billie Holiday in her ''Lady in Satin'' period, Etta James in her soul-torch mode -- but Ms. Mitchell isn't just basking or borrowing. She's working with a changed instrument, a voice that's no longer high and pearly, but (which I like much better) is lower and grainy.  She has worked with jazz musicians for some time, and her songs have gotten more and more unpredictable. She is experimenting with different ways of shaping language and music.</p>
        <p>How can this not be a good thing for a singer-songwriter? Why are so many of them content to live year after year not only with their own gifts, but within their own limitations?</p>
        <p>Neither Audra McDonald nor Ute Lemper writes songs. What they do is push at the boundaries of their repertories, musical theater and cabaret respectively. And in doing that they challenge the forms' limitations and our expectations.</p>
        <p>Ms. McDonald has won three Tony Awards (the first for that musical-theater classic ''Carousel''), and performed gorgeously in a serious but less-than-gorgeous opera written for her (Michael John LaChiusa's ''Marie Christine''). She sings what her contemporaries write; she doesn't just lay vocal laurels on the graves of the worthy dead.</p>
        <p>She has a delicious, lieder-ready voice, loads of dramatic talent and all the vernacular gifts, such as unmannered diction and rhythmic flexibility. She understands off-the-beat phrasing and blue notes; she can summon all-out operatic majesty, too.</p>
        <p>''How Glory Goes'' (Nonesuch), her second recording, includes standards from ''Show Boat'' and ''West Side Story,'' and sweet, modest songs by young composers in varying modes (a lullaby here, a calypso tinge there, a parlor ballad setting of a 19th-century love poem). There is an ambitious recitative-like hymn by Adam Guettel, probably the best known of the new breed. And, glorious indeed, there are five songs by that not-quite-celebrated enough master, Harold Arlen: ''I Had Myself a True Love,'' ''A Sleepin' Bee,'' ''I Never Has Seen Snow,'' ''Anyplace I Hang My Hat Is Home'' and ''The Man That Got Away.'' Sumptuous harmonies and melodies that make their way through unexpected intervals without ever sounding forced.</p>
        <p>Her interpretations are so intelligent, so centered emotionally. None of the excess fuss and fervor that have for years burdened ''Bill'' and ''Somewhere.'' Just tenderness and rue. And when she does ''The Man That Got Away'' you don't listen for Judy Garland, not even once. But I could happily listen to her give a whole album over to Arlen songs. It's true, I don't enjoy any of the young composers as much, but they have time and so do I. I only wish that Ms. McDonald will go further afield, looking for composers who reside in the classical, folk, jazz and new-music territories.</p>
        <p>The German-born Ms. Lemper is best known in the United States for her sublimely intense cabaret performances. If you want to hear her mastery of that idiom, listen to her CD ''All That Jazz: The Best of Ute Lemper'' (London Classics). She does songs by Kurt Weill and Bertolt Brecht made famous by Dietrich and Piaf, and some louche and mocking  Weimar Republic ditties. Theatricality is everything: story, stance, hairsbreadth timing. She's a terrific actress in German, French or English. Her voice can belt out, mute itself seductively or go full tilt toward electronic shrieks.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lemper is not interested in nostalgic, tasteful cabaret. She is pushing it back toward the aggressive and outrageous. She turns songs into psychological case studies.</p>
        <p>On her new CD, ''Punishing Kiss'' (Decca), she enters the worlds of art-rock and new music. Elvis Costello is here, with lyrics that nail all the nasty little tricks of people's hearts and minds; so is Tom Waits, with his hobo-poet ballads. Most of the arrangements are by the band the Divine Comedy; they are lavish, flashy and smart.</p>
        <p>The two best songs are the two most daring. In the ghostly ''Little Water Song'' by Nick Cave and Bruno Pisek, a woman describes her final moments as her lover drowns her; ''Scope J'' by Scott Walker is a 10-minute soliloquy, or mad scene, that takes Ms. Lemper into the dramatic world of a nuclear holocaust and the musical worlds of John Cage and Luciano Berio.</p>
        <p>What will she do next? What a pleasure to have no predictions. No more fawning or self-worship -- they get in the way. Let the divas of the future surprise themselves and us.</p>
        <p>REVISIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
