<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Checking Title Insurance</title>
    <meta content="10QAQA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="Q. &amp; A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DE1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Checking Title Insurance</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: We purchased a home in Nassau County 50 years ago and have a title insurance certificate. How do I know if this title insurance company is still in business and, if so, how to get in touch with it? Also, can these title insurance companies go out of business in New York and leave us without coverage? . . . William F. Greis, Malverne, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A: Wayne Cotter, director of research for the New York State Department of Insurance, said that title insurance companies doing business in New York must be licensed by the department. Accordingly, he said, information about the company that insured the letter writer's home should be on file with the department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: We purchased a home in Nassau County 50 years ago and have a title insurance certificate. How do I know if this title insurance company is still in business and, if so, how to get in touch with it? Also, can these title insurance companies go out of business in New York and leave us without coverage? . . . William F. Greis, Malverne, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A: Wayne Cotter, director of research for the New York State Department of Insurance, said that title insurance companies doing business in New York must be licensed by the department. Accordingly, he said, information about the company that insured the letter writer's home should be on file with the department.</p>
        <p>''He can find out if that particular company is still licensed by checking our Web page,'' Mr. Cotter said, adding that the Internet address for the Department of Insurance is www.ins.state.ny.us.</p>
        <p>He said that if the name of the title insurance company on the certificate cannot be found on the Web site, it is likely that the company has been bought out or has merged with another company.</p>
        <p>''It's conceivable that the company went out of business,'' Mr. Cotter said. ''But it's more likely that it was bought out by some other company. So if the letter writer calls our insurance hot line at (800) 522-4370, we should be able to track down that information.''</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Cotter said, since title insurance companies are licensed by the state, their customers are protected by the department's Insurance Guarantee Fund, which is used to pay claims against companies that have gone out of business or become bankrupt.</p>
        <p>Elections At a Condo</p>
        <p>Q: I live in a town-house development with 120 families. We vote only for the board. The elected board then designates the officers, who are usually members of the board. Is it a conflict of interest for the board to conduct the entire election process when four board members will be running for re-election? There is nothing in our bylaws or declaration of condominium that addresses who may conduct the election. Can a group of fed-up homeowners take over the election? . . . Joseph Mastroberardino, Poughkeepsie, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A: Bruce A. Cholst, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, said that since conducting elections is typically a management function, the board would be within its legal rights in deciding to preside over the process.</p>
        <p>''This is so even though a majority of its members may be seeking re-election,'' Mr. Cholst said.</p>
        <p>He added, however, that the electoral process must be conducted strictly in accordance with the association's governing documents.</p>
        <p>If the board violates any OK? Mike provision of the governing documents in the course of administering the election, the election can be challenged if the board's misconduct has materially affected the outcome.  That challenge would take the form of a legal action filed against the board in State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cholst said that the letter writer might consider asking the board to appoint him as an inspector of election so that he will be in a position to oversee the tabulation of ballots and proxies. Alternatively, he might ask the board to consider engaging an independent auditing company to conduct the election.</p>
        <p>''Either one of these measures would foster the perception of fairness in the conduct of the election,'' Mr. Cholst said. ''But the board cannot be legally compelled to undertake them.''</p>
        <p>Q. &amp; A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
