<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Sharp Play Like This, Who Needs an Endgame?</title>
    <meta content="10CHES0AE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biel International Chess Tournament</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byrne, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Svidler, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1DD1E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Sharp Play Like This, Who Needs an Endgame?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Byrne, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Byrne chess column discusses Biel Chess Festival in Switzerland, won by Peter Svidler of Russia; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The crowning event of the 33rd Biel Chess Festival in Switzerland, from July 24 to Aug. 4, was a double-round all-grandmaster invitational tournament with six players. Peter Svidler of Russia took first place with 7 1/2-2 1/2.</p>
        <p>But it only became easy toward the end. He was closely followed by Loek van Wely of the Netherlands until the ninth round, when Svidler won the decisive game from him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The crowning event of the 33rd Biel Chess Festival in Switzerland, from July 24 to Aug. 4, was a double-round all-grandmaster invitational tournament with six players. Peter Svidler of Russia took first place with 7 1/2-2 1/2.</p>
        <p>But it only became easy toward the end. He was closely followed by Loek van Wely of the Netherlands until the ninth round, when Svidler won the decisive game from him.</p>
        <p>After both had draws in the final round, van Wely tied for second place with a fast-rising 16-year-old, Ruslan Ponomariov of Ukraine, at 5 1/2-4 1/2.</p>
        <p>Svidler got off to a nice start in this competition, winning his first- and second-round games. In Round 1, he toppled Vadim Milov of Switzerland with sharp opening play followed by an aggressive middle game. He had no need for an endgame.</p>
        <p>The Paulsen Variation of the Sicilian Defense arises after 4 . . . a6. Black's e6 and a6 pawns cover the major invasion squares into his position, so he can afford to concede White an advantage in space.</p>
        <p>Milov's 8 . . . Bc5 has almost always been answered by a timid 9 Be2, but Svidler went for something big with 9 Nce2!?</p>
        <p>His point was 10 b4!? to expose the black defenses after 10 . . . Bb4 11 Nf5 Bc5 12 Ng7 Ke7 (or 12 . . . Kf8 13 Bh6 Bf2 14 Rf2 Ng4 15 Ne6 Ke7 16 N6d4 Nh6 17 Qd2 Ng8 18 Qg5 Kf8 19 Raf1 f6 20 Rf6, winning outright) 13 Bg5 d6 14 Nh5 Nd7 15 Qd2 Bd4 16 Nd4 Qd4 17 Qe3 Qc5 18 Qc5 dc 19 Nf6 Nf6 20 e5, winning a piece.</p>
        <p>With 10 . . . Bd4 11 Bd4, Milov gave Svidler the bishop pair along with a clear advantage.</p>
        <p>After 11 . . . Qc7 (11 . . . Qd6? 12 e5, Qc6 13 f3 Nd5 14 Bc5 would be overwhelming for White), Svidler opened lines sharply with 12 c4! If 12 . . . bc, then 13 Rc1 d5 14 ed Bd5 (14 . . . ed 15 Re1 O-O 16 Bf6 gf 17 Bb1 yields White powerful attacking chances against the enemy king) 15 Bf6 gf 16 Bc4 Bc4 17 Qd4 O-O 18 Rc4 yields White the upper hand.</p>
        <p>After 13 Bb2, Milov desisted from 13 . . . bc 14 Rc1 d5 15 ed Bd5 16 Bc4 Bc4 17 Qc2 Nbd7 18 Qc4 Qc4 19 Rc4 Ke7 20 Rfc1 because Svidler would have had superior development in the endgame.</p>
        <p>After 15 Nc3, Milov should perhaps have captured with 15 . . . Nb4, although 16 Nb5 Qb8 17 Ba3 Ra3 18 Na3 Nd3 19 Qd3 Be4 20 Qc3 probably does not give Black enough for his Bishop plus pawn against a white rook.</p>
        <p>In any case, after 17 Bd3, Svidler was a pawn ahead with the superior position. With a little technique, Milov would be lost.</p>
        <p>After 31 Rce4, Svidler was two pawns ahead and there was no miracle in view to save Milos.</p>
        <p>Milos tried to be clever with 32 . . . Ng3, but after the precise 33 Qc8! Rd8 (or 33 . . . Kh7 34 Qc2 g6 35 Rd5) 34 Qd8!, Milov gave up.</p>
        <p>After 34 . . . Qd8 35 Re8 Qe8 36 Re8 Kh7 37 fg, Black is a piece down.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
