<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop (and Mom) Quiz</title>
    <meta content="10SOAP$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOAPBOX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DC1239F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop (and Mom) Quiz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Humorous back-to-school pop quiz for parents; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PSHEW.</p>
        <p>The good news is you made it through a summer of constant rain, mosquito paranoia and camps that charge for two months about what it costs to send a kid to Harvard for a year. The bad news is you have to come back to the real world, which is far worse. Assuming you survived the first week of school, here's a back-to-school pop quiz to help you realign your brain with those of your children. Calculators and laptops allowed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PSHEW.</p>
        <p>The good news is you made it through a summer of constant rain, mosquito paranoia and camps that charge for two months about what it costs to send a kid to Harvard for a year. The bad news is you have to come back to the real world, which is far worse. Assuming you survived the first week of school, here's a back-to-school pop quiz to help you realign your brain with those of your children. Calculators and laptops allowed.</p>
        <p>1. What is the correct weight of a backback for a 90-pound sixth grader?</p>
        <p>A. 20 pounds.</p>
        <p>B. 35 pounds.</p>
        <p>C. The approxmiate weight of Volumes A through P of the World Book.</p>
        <p>D. The approximate weight of the defensive line of the New York Jets.</p>
        <p>2. When should you start worrying about where your child will go to college?</p>
        <p>A. When you get your baby's APGAR score.</p>
        <p>B. When you figure out by second grade that your child will not get a basketball scholarsip to UConn or a football scholarship to Florida State.</p>
        <p>C. When the probation officer tells you there are no problem kids, just kids with problems.</p>
        <p>D. When the other children's early admission decisions start coming back.</p>
        <p>3. How many pockets are there in the typical pair of cargo pants worn by the typical New Jersey middle school student?</p>
        <p>A. 6.</p>
        <p>B. 11.</p>
        <p>C. 7 cubed.</p>
        <p>D. One of those infinite numbers like the number of planets in the galaxy.</p>
        <p>4. Britney Spears, Mandy Moore, Christina Aguilera and all those other blond nymphets on MTV are:</p>
        <p>A. Appropriate role models for 9-year-old girls.</p>
        <p>B. Appropriate role models for 45-year-old women.</p>
        <p>C. Appropriate romantic fantasy figures for 13-year-old boys.</p>
        <p>D. Appropriate romantic fantasy figures for 50-year-old men.</p>
        <p>E. All of the above.</p>
        <p>F. Houston, we have a problem.</p>
        <p>5. Your children may be overscheduled if:</p>
        <p>A. Your daughter goes to ballet class in her tai chi uniform.</p>
        <p>B. You have school-optional weeks so your children can catch up on their lessons, classes and practices.</p>
        <p>C. For the rest of the year, you will only see them on Thanksgiving, Christmas and New Year's.</p>
        <p>D. Your piano teacher is driving a Lexus and you're working three jobs.</p>
        <p>6. Which of the following is not biologically essential to survival for the average high school student.</p>
        <p>A Water.</p>
        <p>B. Cell Phone.</p>
        <p>C. Discman.</p>
        <p>D. Diet Coke.</p>
        <p>E, Their own car.</p>
        <p>7. Which form of body piercing would force you to disown your child forever and deny any knowledge of his or her existence?</p>
        <p>A. Navel.</p>
        <p>B. Eye.</p>
        <p>C. Nose.</p>
        <p>D. Chin.</p>
        <p>E. Tongue.</p>
        <p>F. The ones we can't mention in this newspaper.</p>
        <p>8. Nutritionists say a healthy breakfast for a high school student should consist of:</p>
        <p>A. Cereal, fruit, juice, milk, vitamins.</p>
        <p>B. Egg McMuffin, Coke and hash browns.</p>
        <p>C. Chocolate doughnut and Jolt Cola.</p>
        <p>D. Frappucino and Cheez Doodles.</p>
        <p>9. True or false?</p>
        <p>A. Regis Philbin.</p>
        <p>B. ''And he wrote every word of the college application essay himself!''</p>
        <p>C. ''College admissions consultants? No, we didn't use any.''</p>
        <p>D. ''Steroids? No, no one on the wrestling team is using any steroids.''</p>
        <p>10. According to the best education research, the optimal way for teenagers to do their homework is:</p>
        <p>A. Wearing headphones, listening to Mozart sonatas.</p>
        <p>B. Wearing headphones, listening to Nine Inch Nails.</p>
        <p>C. Wearing headphones, listening to Nine Inch Nails and watching ''Dawson's Creek.''</p>
        <p>D, Wearing headphone, listening to Nine Inch Nails, watching 'Dawson's Creek'' and talking to friends on the phone.</p>
        <p>E. Your child doesn't do homework.</p>
        <p>11. What's the correct term for the boy with the thick glasses, pocket protector and 800's on his math SAT's who stays up all night playing esoteric computer games?</p>
        <p>A. Nerd.</p>
        <p>B. Wonk.</p>
        <p>C. Dweeb.</p>
        <p>D. Doof.</p>
        <p>E. Boss.</p>
        <p>SOAPBOX Peter Applebome is a deputy metropolitan editor of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Peter Applebome is a deputy metropolitan editor of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
