<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's September and, for the Mets, the Fall Has Arrived</title>
    <meta content="Y10MET0AD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/sports/10METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D91E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's September and, for the Mets, the Fall Has Arrived</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia Phillies defeat New York Mets, 6-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the frustration was going to show on the Mets last night, at least they expressed it safely. Unlike Mike Hampton, who had whipped his glove and toppled two water coolers in his rage on Friday night, Turk Wendell walked off the mound and merely tossed his glove into the stands at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''Just get rid of your stuff and start over again,'' Wendell deadpanned afterward. ''A new, clean slate. Time for a new one. I'm surprised anyone even wanted it and didn't throw it back.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the frustration was going to show on the Mets last night, at least they expressed it safely. Unlike Mike Hampton, who had whipped his glove and toppled two water coolers in his rage on Friday night, Turk Wendell walked off the mound and merely tossed his glove into the stands at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''Just get rid of your stuff and start over again,'' Wendell deadpanned afterward. ''A new, clean slate. Time for a new one. I'm surprised anyone even wanted it and didn't throw it back.''</p>
        <p>The Mets had good reason to toss gloves, bats or just about anything else as their September troubles continued. By the time Armando Benitez was touched for a three-run homer in the ninth inning, the fire was gone and he simply placed his glove on the bench and toweled off.</p>
        <p>The Mets' bats were silent again, almost a given by now. But on this night, their gloves failed, too, or at least the glove of the usually steady Edgardo Alfonzo, who committed a pair of gaffes in the seventh inning, an error and another misplay that was later changed from an error to a double. Alfonzo's troubles helped the Philadelphia Phillies to a pair of runs and a 6-3 victory that sent the Mets to their third consecutive loss and their seventh in eight games since the calendar rolled to September. With the loss, the Mets (80-61) remained three and a half games behind Atlanta and saw their lead over Arizona in the wild-card race shrink to three and a half games.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo had just given the Mets their first run in two nights with a two-out, run-scoring double in the bottom of the sixth inning, evening the score at 1-1. But he allowed one ball to bound past him, and then another to slip through his hands. Then, after Derek Bell homered in the bottom of the eighth to cut the lead to 3-2, Benitez was brought on in the ninth to try to keep the score close. But he got a fastball up, and Brian Hunter delivered a three-run homer into the bullpen in left.</p>
        <p>And the Mets had found a new way to lose, bringing further reminders of September 1998, when they lost the final five games of the season to fall out of the playoff race, and September 1999, when they were swept in a three-game series by these same Phillies.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it's a good thing that a bunch of weird stuff happened tonight, and we can get it out of the way in one game,'' Wendell (7-5) said. ''Get all this garbage out of the way now, and tomorrow we can turn it around, start on a new fresh path.</p>
        <p>''We just have to go back to what we've been before. Things clicked for us and we were successful.''</p>
        <p>But finding the positives was easier said than done. It took just three outs to see that the Mets' troubles were not going to be solved by closed-door meetings, just as they had not been solved by the arrival of the league's worst team. A 2-0 shutout at the hands of five Phillies pitchers on Friday was followed by a meeting after the game and then last night by blanks from the former Met Robert Person (8-5).</p>
        <p>In the first inning, Bell was retired on a hard line drive that shortstop Alex Arias went to his knees to snag. With two runners on and two out, Robin Ventura ripped a line drive down the first-base line, but right at Hunter.</p>
        <p>In the third, Timo Perez drilled a single to right, and when Bell laced a 1-0 pitch back through the box for an apparent hit, Perez was running on the pitch, bringing Marlon Anderson over to cover second base. Anderson easily scooped up the grounder, stepped on the bag and started a double play to end the inning.</p>
        <p>''This game is impossible to play when you're pressing, trying to force pitches, trying to force swings, trying to make things happen,'' Mets catcher Mike Piazza said. ''We're just reaching for something that's not there.''</p>
        <p>If the bats were not waking from their September slumber, the Mets were at least hanging even thanks to the arm of Glendon Rusch, as well as the glove of Bell. Rusch eased through the first three innings, as Hampton had on Friday night. But Hampton was undone by a two-run homer by Scott Rolen. This time, Pat Burrell's bid for a solo blast was foiled by Bell, who raced back and leaped to snare the ball at the top of the right-field wall.</p>
        <p>But in the sixth inning, the Mets fell behind again as Burrell lined a run-scoring double just over the head of Perez. Rusch escaped with the bases loaded, but with the Mets searching for a way to score a run, he was removed for a pinch-hitter leading off the bottom of the inning on the downside of a 1-0 score.</p>
        <p>The Mets finally scored -- their first run in two nights -- in the bottom of the sixth when Matt Franco, pinch-hitting for Rusch, walked and, after moving to second on a groundout, scored on a two-out double to center by Alfonzo. But Alfonzo uncharacteristically gave the run back in the seventh, allowing a hard grounder by Bobby Abreu to get through on a play that was eventually changed to a double, putting runners on second and third with none out. Travis Lee then scored on a sacrifice fly by Glanville, beating the throw from Perez. After an intentional walk, Burrell lined a single just out of Alfonzo's reach to score Abreu. Alfonzo then bobbled a routine grounder to load the bases, but the Mets got out of the inning with no further damage.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
