<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theme Out of Africa and Fire-Grilled Meat</title>
    <meta content="10DINE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mighty Joe Young's (Hartsdale, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DB1439F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theme Out of Africa and Fire-Grilled Meat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>HARTSDALE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Mighty Joe Young's restaurant in Hartsdale, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF one's idea of dining is merely to ''eat at Joe's,'' then this is probably not the right Joe. As at most theme restaurants, Mighty Joe Young's tries for spectacle: beyond the torches at the entrance, diners pass a couple of life-size stuffed wild animals, then encounter film posters and a lounge resembling a colonial outpost on the edge of the veld. The mise-en-scene -- Africa via Hollywood -- suggests the primal and the slightly dangerous, but the hunt is only through the menu.</p>
        <p>Unlike that of chain extravaganzas -- those trendy backdrops for burgers, fries and other fast foods --  Mighty Joe Young's menu is ambitious. What sets dishes apart and up a few notches are wood-fired grills and stone ovens that with few exceptions, contributed to the sweet, subtle, deliciously smoky flavor of the food. A brush with marinades or sauces altered the nuance from dish to dish. (Look for the crossed-log logo on the menu.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF one's idea of dining is merely to ''eat at Joe's,'' then this is probably not the right Joe. As at most theme restaurants, Mighty Joe Young's tries for spectacle: beyond the torches at the entrance, diners pass a couple of life-size stuffed wild animals, then encounter film posters and a lounge resembling a colonial outpost on the edge of the veld. The mise-en-scene -- Africa via Hollywood -- suggests the primal and the slightly dangerous, but the hunt is only through the menu.</p>
        <p>Unlike that of chain extravaganzas -- those trendy backdrops for burgers, fries and other fast foods --  Mighty Joe Young's menu is ambitious. What sets dishes apart and up a few notches are wood-fired grills and stone ovens that with few exceptions, contributed to the sweet, subtle, deliciously smoky flavor of the food. A brush with marinades or sauces altered the nuance from dish to dish. (Look for the crossed-log logo on the menu.)</p>
        <p>Scented with cilantro and stretched onto skewers impaling a pineapple top, crisped shrimp Konga proved outstanding. Also profiting from ovens' smoke, pleasantly chewy tentacles of octopus came  with a good lemony black and white bean salad. And a special of three huge, gently charred sea scallops  arrived on a bed of earthy wild mushroom risotto.</p>
        <p>Although studded with hunks of crab meat, compared with other starters, crab cake amounted to nothing special, and a mound of fresh mussels needed a broth of more substance. A collaboration of lemon grass, ginger and fresh basil was promised but undetectable.</p>
        <p>Orders for the preferred degree of doneness are taken seriously. Medallion of ostrich makes a frequent appearance on the menu, and it would be a mistake to miss it. This dark meat was lean, supple and flavorful.  It would please any diner who appreciates first-rate filet mignon, which was also one of the winners here.  Judging by these successes, we would bet on Joe's T-bone steak as well. Only hanger steak -- an old favorite -- disappointed; called ''steak frites,'' ours proved coarse and grainy, and the refried frites were stale. Roasted chicken can be a bore, but fire-roasting brought out its juicy best, and a lovely corn risotto added luxury. Silky tuna steak Japanese style arrived properly rare; we preferred it to salmon in horseradish crust, the fish itself unappealingly hard at the edges.</p>
        <p>Key lime tart left a nice citrus pucker, and luscious, soft-centered black and white chocolate cake lived up to its ''gooey'' billing. Served in huge goblets, ice creams might be shared, unless the flavor is espresso, which came with chocolate-covered coffee beans tucked discreetly into the mix.</p>
        <p>The crunchy beans delivered an astonishing hit of coffee. But banana,  baked in hardened pizza dough, seemed pointless, and creme brulee under a thick topping of torched sugar was as heavy as pudding.</p>
        <p>Although diners can have a tasty meal here, standards seem to have slipped, supervision nonexistent. In a half-empty dining room, a hostess had trouble finding another place for our party seated at a table under a faulty, grinding vent. We were told that the air-conditioning system blasting cold air into an already chilly dining room could not be controlled.</p>
        <p>Some of the fancy drinks from the Mighty Bar were overly sweet, and the frozen concoctions were overly  blended into ice that made mouth and sinuses ache.</p>
        <p>Young children are frequent and sometimes noisy diners. (To escape, dine late.) Chairs and floors were  sticky and wet.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $37 without drinks, tax and tip. The restaurant is at the intersection of Routes 100A and 100B.</p>
        <p>Mighty Joe Young's  610 West Hartsdale Avenue,  Hartsdale. (914) 428-6868.</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Deliberately kitschy hunt-and-jungle motif. Large noisy dining areas, lounge and semi-enclosed patio. Fireplace. Paper-covered tables. Careless housekeeping and maintenance. Excellent table service; unaccommodating greeting and seating.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- Bar and lounge.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Shrimp Konga, grilled octopus, filet mignon, ostrich, yellowfin tuna steak, ice creams, Key lime pie, black and white chocolate cake.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Lunch and brunch, main dishes, $7 to $22. Dinner, main dishes, $15.50 to $30; $12.50 to $19 for pasta. Children's menu, $8 (includes drink and dessert).</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch, Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 3 p.m. Dinner, Mondays through Thursdays, 5 to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5 to 11 p.m.; Sundays, 4 to 9 p.m. Brunch, Sundays, noon to 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- A good idea on weekends.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Ramp.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
