<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Into Politics, Retiring Too Soon</title>
    <meta content="10PEAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scher, Pearl Crystal</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1D91539F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Into Politics, Retiring Too Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Pearl Crystal Scher of Somers, NY, Westchester County's oldest elected official, who began her political career in 1995 at age 80 and has just resigned from Town Council; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEARL CRYSTAL SCHER had a strong opening gambit for her first campaign for elective office. Approaching voters with her hand outstretched and an impish grin, she would say, ''You know, I'm running for office for the first time at the age of 80.''</p>
        <p>''That stopped them dead, and they always took another look,'' Ms. Scher recalled. ''It was such a good line -- I was so proud of it. Who else can use that kind of line?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEARL CRYSTAL SCHER had a strong opening gambit for her first campaign for elective office. Approaching voters with her hand outstretched and an impish grin, she would say, ''You know, I'm running for office for the first time at the age of 80.''</p>
        <p>''That stopped them dead, and they always took another look,'' Ms. Scher recalled. ''It was such a good line -- I was so proud of it. Who else can use that kind of line?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Scher's political career began in 1995 with a run for the County Board of Legislators and ended on Sept. 1, when her resignation from the Somers Town Council took effect. Now 85, she had been Westchester's oldest elected official.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scher said she hated having to give up her seat, but problems with her eyesight had forced her to give up driving, making it nearly impossible for her to lead the independent life she treasures. She is moving to an assisted-living residence in Manhattan this month.</p>
        <p>To call her life in politics a second act would be to diminish a career that has been rich in experiences, including stints as a teacher, a marine, a school principal, a recruiter for paralegals, a travel agent and a real estate manager.</p>
        <p>But it is unusual to get the political bug so late in life, and once Ms. Scher was bit, she was hooked.</p>
        <p>It began five summers ago with a phone call from Andrew J. Spano, then chairman of the Democratic Party in Westchester. Mr. Spano, who is now the county executive,  asked Ms. Scher to be the Democratic candidate for the fourth legislative district. Her reaction was vintage Pearl.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Are you drunk?' '' Ms. Scher recalled. ''I can't tell you how amazed I was. I had never run for anything, not even dog catcher.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano said that he needed a well-known name to put on the ticket. Ms. Scher had long been active in Somers, where she belonged to many civic organizations. The district covered Somers as well as Croton-on-Hudson and parts of Cortlandt and Yorktown. Ms. Scher said she thought over the proposition for about a minute and decided to run out of loyalty to the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>It was only later, Ms. Scher said, that she realized Mr. Spano had not expected her to mount an active campaign against the popular Republican incumbent, Andrew Donovan. But Ms. Scher discovered that she loved campaigning and soon became a ubiquitous presence in the district.</p>
        <p>''I remember when she was running, and she was everywhere,'' said Mary Beth Murphy, Somers' town supervisor. ''Every time you turned around, there was Pearl, smiling and laughing and telling everyone who she was and what she hoped to accomplish.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Scher lost, but the election was closer than anyone had expected. The then-80-year-old carried Somers and Croton-on Hudson, losing by about 900 votes.</p>
        <p>She was not out of action long. The next year, a vacancy opened on the Somers Town Board with the death of Councilman Michael DePaoli. Ms. Scher won a special election to complete his term and was then overwhelmingly re-elected in 1997.</p>
        <p>Running three campaigns in three years did not tire her, Ms. Scher said. ''Listen, you can be as old as Methuselah, but if you want to do something to make other people's lives a little better, you can do it,'' she said. ''Like everybody else my age, I have a load of stuff wrong. I can sit down and tell you tales of woe from here to China. But what's the point?''</p>
        <p>A petite woman with strawberry blonde hair and a voice that reveals her Brooklyn origins, Ms. Scher was the lone Democrat on the five-member board.</p>
        <p>She was also, she pointed out, the only woman, the only resident of Heritage Hills -- a development for the elderly -- and the only veteran. ''And, of course, I was the only Jew,'' she added. ''And they never mentioned it, which was fine with me.''</p>
        <p>On the board, Ms. Scher was known as forthright and feisty. She read countless documents from town government and made it a point to visit the head of each town agency. During a contentious battle over rezoning, she fought for affordable housing.  She also championed making advanced life support service available and affordable for elderly residents.</p>
        <p>''Pearl has more energy than lots of people, and she really immersed herself in all aspects of the town,'' Ms. Murphy said. ''She had a lot of good ideas that she was never afraid to share, and she has left a lasting impression on many residents.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Scher said she enjoyed working with Ms. Murphy. ''When I was pleased with her, I used to say, 'You know, Mary Beth, the only thing wrong with you is that you are a Republican.' ''</p>
        <p>Born to Russian immigrants, Ms. Scher lived in Brooklyn until she was 5. The family then moved to Granite, N.Y., in the Catskills to run a small boardinghouse. When she was 19, she taught in a one-room school in Granite. She received a bachelor's degree from Hunter College and later a master's degree from Columbia University. Ms. Scher was married briefly, but she said, ''it wasn't a marriage that lasted because I was simply impossible as a wife.''</p>
        <p>During World War II, she signed up for the Marine Corps because her male relatives were all too old or too young to serve, Ms. Scher said, and she felt it was her duty to represent her family.</p>
        <p>Later, she became a high school social studies teacher in Manhattan and ultimately an elementary school principal. At 57, she retired from the city school system and pursued a variety of careers, moving to Somers 25 years ago.</p>
        <p>Leaving Somers is like leaving her family, said Ms. Scher, who often attended several town events a day, ranging from children's basketball games to senior citizen gatherings. ''I was so unhappy when I decided to leave, because this has been my life,'' she said. ''But I've done my crying. I refuse to dwell on something about which I can do absolutely nothing.''</p>
        <p>Recently, Ms. Scher has been honored by many groups, and her virtues have been extolled in editorials in local papers. She said she was getting ''a huge bang'' out of all the attention.</p>
        <p>''I'm honored up to my ears and over,'' she said. ''I'm so glad they didn't wait until I died, or I wouldn't have heard a single word.''</p>
        <p>She intends to keep up her active life in her new home.</p>
        <p>After reviewing her new lease, she called the management to point out that there was nothing in the contract about residents' rights. ''I told them,'' Ms. Scher said, '' 'what you need is a residents' council. And I suggest very strongly that you would do well to see to it that I'm elected chairman and let me tell you why. I've had a lot of experience and I'm not a troublemaker, I'm a trouble-shooter. In fact, you should campaign for me.' ''</p>
        <p>COMMUNITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
