<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hitting Executives Where They Live</title>
    <meta content="MB233641" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS: DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Peerlogic (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Camp/Arbues</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'brien, Kathleen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DC1139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hitting Executives Where They Live</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kathleen O'Brien</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'brien, Kathleen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Camp/Arbues of San Francisco opens retro-looking, attention-getting pony give-away print and TV ad campaign for PeerLogic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suppose you have a corporate infrastructure software product to sell to top executives at big, technologically adept companies -- a notoriously hard bunch to reach. How do you stand out from the other thousand companies clamoring for their attention?</p>
        <p>In one of the cheekier tongue-in-cheek campaigns that the new economy has produced, PeerLogic has tried an end run. Under a big, retro-looking headline that reads ''Hey, Kids,'' the company's advertisements in The Economist, The Industry Standard and Infoweek promise children their very own ponies if they can get their chief-executive moms and dads to call PeerLogic or register on its Web site. The ads even offer tips on tantrum-throwing technique, in case of parental resistance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suppose you have a corporate infrastructure software product to sell to top executives at big, technologically adept companies -- a notoriously hard bunch to reach. How do you stand out from the other thousand companies clamoring for their attention?</p>
        <p>In one of the cheekier tongue-in-cheek campaigns that the new economy has produced, PeerLogic has tried an end run. Under a big, retro-looking headline that reads ''Hey, Kids,'' the company's advertisements in The Economist, The Industry Standard and Infoweek promise children their very own ponies if they can get their chief-executive moms and dads to call PeerLogic or register on its Web site. The ads even offer tips on tantrum-throwing technique, in case of parental resistance.</p>
        <p>How many pony-loving children, even of chief executives, are likely to thumb through any given issue of The Economist is open to debate. Still, PeerLogic's ad urged any children who did see it to move fast, ''because we're running out of ponies.'' Television commercials on six cable channels made a similar pitch.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to put an ad out there that would make people stop and take notice,'' said Eileen Arbues, president of Camp/ Arbues, the San Francisco agency that handled the campaign.</p>
        <p>Name recognition was the goal cited by Julie Judd, PeerLogic's vice president for communications, who said the initial response was quite promising: hits on the company's Web site tripled after the campaign began on Aug. 14, she said, yielding a number of solid sales leads.</p>
        <p>But will exclusive suburbs across the country soon see an outbreak of barn-raisings? Not exactly.</p>
        <p>To begin with, ''Boo-Boo the pony,'' which the ads promise can even sleep in children's  rooms, turns out to be 4 inches tall and made of soft plastic, a point that struck a few people who saw the living pony in the TV ad as a tad deceptive, despite a disclaimer.</p>
        <p>But not all the respondents were what they were supposed to be, either.</p>
        <p>News of the pony giveaway, stripped of the retro-ironical 1970's-style presentation in the ads, found its way to a number of Web sites that advise visitors how to take advantage of free-merchandise marketing offers. Once that happened, Ms. Judd said, PeerLogic was inundated with inquiries from people with no interest in infrastructure software, just in the pony.</p>
        <p>The company's initial supply of 700 Boo-Boos ran out quickly, and a reorder was exhausted last week. Though ads already in the pipeline will keep appearing for another week or two, no more Boo-Boos will be ordered, because just as the campaign was beginning, PeerLogic, which was closely held, agreed to be acquired by Critical Path, an Internet messaging services company, for about $416 million in stock.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, a few real children did see the ads, and did not get the joke. Ms. Judd said that one distraught mother called PeerLogic and begged a company representative to tell her disbelieving daughter that there really was no live pony giveaway; the girl was sure that her mother simply did not want her to have a pony in the house.</p>
        <p>Kathleen O'Brien</p>
        <p>BUSINESS: DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
