<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drugged-Out American Dreamers</title>
    <meta content="10WINT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="68" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10WINT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winters, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selby, Hubert Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aronofsky, Darren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burstyn, Ellen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Connelly, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leto, Jared</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayans, Marlon</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Requiem For a Dream (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDB1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drugged-Out American Dreamers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA WINTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winters, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Winters profiles and interviews director Darren Aronofsky, whose second film, Requiem for a Dream, is based on Hubert Selby Jr's 1978 novel; location has been switched to South Brooklyn, where Aronfsky grew up; stars are Ellen Burstyn, Jennifer Connelly, Jared Leto and Marlon Wayans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 31-year-old director Darren Aronofsky explains the kinetic, brazen style of his second film, ''Requiem for a Dream,'' with a bit of background: ''I grew up in Coney Island riding the Cyclone, which is the best roller coaster in the world. And the one thing it taught me is that you've got to keep the thrills coming.''</p>
        <p>But in ''Requiem,'' which is based on the 1978 Hubert Selby Jr. novel, Mr. Aronofsky employs technical razzle-dazzle not for escapist effect but as the dramatic underpinning of a visceral four-character tale of addiction. ''I think my films are for people who want to feel unsafe for a little while,'' he said, sitting in his West Side apartment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 31-year-old director Darren Aronofsky explains the kinetic, brazen style of his second film, ''Requiem for a Dream,'' with a bit of background: ''I grew up in Coney Island riding the Cyclone, which is the best roller coaster in the world. And the one thing it taught me is that you've got to keep the thrills coming.''</p>
        <p>But in ''Requiem,'' which is based on the 1978 Hubert Selby Jr. novel, Mr. Aronofsky employs technical razzle-dazzle not for escapist effect but as the dramatic underpinning of a visceral four-character tale of addiction. ''I think my films are for people who want to feel unsafe for a little while,'' he said, sitting in his West Side apartment.</p>
        <p>With ''Requiem,'' which opens Oct. 6, Mr. Aronofsky is certainly not playing it safe. The film received a five-minute standing ovation when it played at the Cannes International Film Festival in May and promises to cause a stir this fall -- both because of its brilliant camera technique and because of its occasionally harrowing imagery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky first emerged on the film scene with ''Pi,'' a wildly original black-and-white no-budget film about math, cabala and the stock market. It earned him the award for best director at the 1998 Sundance Film Festival and then became a cult hit. Though ''Requiem'' is a bigger film than ''Pi,'' it is still independent and iconoclastic.</p>
        <p>''Darren is one of the few directors now who is honestly taking risks and changing the genres within which he works,'' said Geoffrey Gilmore, co-director of the Sundance Film Festival. ''He's a spectacularly creative filmmaker.''</p>
        <p>He's not the only one to reach for superlatives when talking about Mr. Aronofsky. The Academy Award-winning actress Ellen Burstyn, who stars in ''Requiem,'' said, ''I think he's to movies what Picasso is to art, in the way he fractures the image on the screen.''</p>
        <p>Considering these advance notices, it's a relief to find Mr. Aronofsky irreverent and unpretentious in person, with an abrasive humor that masks an undercurrent of vulnerability. In his small apartment, intellectual and hip touches vie for attention: there's the microscope he used in ''Pi,'' an old stereo he's repairing, original comic-book art on the walls. He himself is many things at once: the public-school kid who went to Harvard, the loving son (his parents have bit parts in ''Requiem'') and the streetwise provocateur who grew up, as he put it, ''among the wild kids and yentas'' that Mr. Selby depicts in his book.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky had made a short film in film school based on one of Mr. Selby's short stories, but was unable to finish reading ''Requiem'' the first time he started it. ''It was so disturbing and deep in my head that I couldn't handle it,'' he said. ''But then my producer, Eric Watson, took it on a ski trip and when he came back he said it had ruined his vacation, but that I must read it.''</p>
        <p>''Requiem,'' Mr. Selby's fourth novel (after such gritty classics as ''Last Exit to Brooklyn''), is about Harry Goldfarb; Harry's girlfriend, Marion; his best friend, Tyrone; and his mother, Sara (Ms. Burstyn, in the film). All of these characters pursue elusive dreams of success and love; all of them become hooked on various substances -- the young people on heroin, Sara on a mixture of television and diet pills.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Selby, ''Requiem'' is not a tale just of drug addiction; it's also a story of what he calls ''obsessions of the mind.'' ''Darren was true to the essence of my book, which is about what happens when you get obsessed with a lie like the Great American Dream,'' said the author, speaking on the telephone from California.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky sees the story as universal. ''What unites all of these characters is that they're addicted to a fantasy and will use any means to get lost in that fantasy again and escape their present lives,'' he said. ''Selby shows us that the psychology is the same, whether it's an addiction to coffee, cigarettes, food, sex, drugs, even hope.''</p>
        <p>He feels, for this reason, that ''Requiem'' is different from other so-called drug films. ''It's not just the old familiar story of kids getting in over their heads,'' he said. ''There is a counterpoint to the kids in the lonely older woman who goes on the same trip.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Aronofsky retained much of the book's dialogue and worked with Mr. Selby in adapting it to the screen, he updated it from the 70's to something like the present, and changed its setting from the Bronx to the area where he grew up. ''In South Brooklyn, there is this magical timeless atmosphere,'' he said. ''Because I felt that this was a universal story, I wanted to give the film a fable-like feel.''</p>
        <p>Since ''Pi,'' Mr. Aronofsky has worked closely with a small group of collaborators that includes his producer, Mr. Watson, and his cinematographer, Matthew Libatique, both of whom he met at film school. Seeking ways to make a grim story alluring, Mr. Libatique and Mr. Aronofsky came up with what they call ''hip-hop montages'' -- rapid-fire sequences of images, like the repetitive riffs in hip-hop music, that recur in the film. (They're present in ''Pi'' as well.) One such sequence in ''Requiem'' includes, in several seconds, a thumb igniting a lighter, a powder being stirred and a pupil dilating. Mr. Aronofsky also uses split-screen technique and cameras rigged directly onto the actors as part of what he calls ''subjective movie-making.''</p>
        <p>''Most movies mix together all different points of view,'' he said. ''But in 'Pi,' I was interested in making a fully subjective movie from the sole point of view of my protagonist. With 'Requiem,' I also wanted to make a subjective movie but was faced with the challenge of four protagonists, not one.''</p>
        <p>In his quest to plunge the audience directly into these characters' heads, Mr. Aronofsky relied on the all-out performances of his actors: Ms. Burstyn, Jennifer Connelly (Marion), Jared Leto (Harry) and Marlon Wayans (Tyrone). All the actors went through extensive preparation; during the shoot, Ms. Burstyn had a grueling daily four-hour makeup session, numerous wigs and two separate fat suits to depict Sara's weight swings. ''I was required to go places I had never had to go before creatively,'' she said. ''But I feel better about this film than anything I've ever done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leto, who, unbidden, lost 25 pounds to incarnate Harry's gaunt desperation, recalled: ''Darren maps everything out beforehand. We worked on everything from my Brooklyn accent to the gradual changes in how my character would walk and move.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky was not only demanding, however, but also, said Ms. Connelly, supportive. Her character, Marion, starts prostituting herself in order to get drugs. ''We discussed what he wanted to film and what I would be comfortable doing,'' she said. ''I felt really safe with him.''</p>
        <p>Because of some of its sexual imagery, the film has been given a prohibitive NC-17 rating by the Motion Picture Association of America. Mr. Aronofsky and Artisan Entertainment, the film's distributor, appealed that rating, which is known to limit a film's commercial potential.  But their appeal was denied, so they are opting to release ''Requiem for a Dream'' unrated rather than alter it -- as was done with ''Eyes Wide Shut'' and ''American Psycho'' -- in order to get an R rating.</p>
        <p>MR. ARONOFSKY is fervent in his wish to release the film uncut. ''This film is about the limits we go to in order to believe in our dreams,'' he said. ''Once you start pulling back and censoring that, it undermines exactly what the film is about. The film may be shocking to some, but we were very serious about not having it be either exploitative or untrue. What happens in the movie may be intense, but it's nothing compared to what goes on behind closed doors in America all the time.''</p>
        <p>Although the film is dark, Mr. Aronofsky intended to make it entertaining as well through his high-wire visuals. In fact, he embraces Hollywood's tradition of flashy, super-charged action films. ''In Brooklyn, we didn't have an art theater,'' he said. ''I grew up on Hollywood film. I loved big movies, and I've seen every one of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky's parents, Charlotte and Abe, are both retired public-school teachers, and Mr. Aronofsky went to Edward R. Murrow High School, in Brooklyn. There, he says, he ''learned mainly to cut class''; but he did well enough to be admitted to Harvard. After graduating in 1991, he studied film at the American Film Institute in Los Angeles. Then, in late 1995, he and Mr. Watson decided to move back to New York and produce a low-budget film. Over the next six months, Mr. Aronofsky hashed out a story with Mr. Watson and Sean Gullette, the friend from Harvard whom he had cast as the lead. ''We started with the idea of a guy who sees patterns everywhere in the world,'' Mr. Gullette recalled, ''and then we thought: 'Who would see numbers everywhere? A mathematician.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronofsky, who says he writes by ''fusing elements together like a jigsaw puzzle,'' wanted to meld the genres of art film and thriller into the tale of a man being pursued -- by Hasidic Jews, by Wall Street operators -- for his mathematical knowledge. He decided to shoot on black and white reversal, a seldom-used and expensive stock, because its contrasts are especially stark. The financing took ingenuity: at one point, the associate producer, Scott Franklin, came up with the idea of sending out a letter to everyone's friends and family asking for $100. If the movie made money, each contributor would receive $150 in return, as well as tickets to a special screening. This netted the production approximately $8,000 (and all the contributors ended up getting their $150).</p>
        <p>Shooting ''Pi'' was a 28-day guerrilla-film affair, ''running down the middle of Canal Street at midday with the camera,'' as Mr. Libatique recalls it. Mr. Aronofsky's mother provided the food for the crew; the main set was part of a lighting factory in Bushwick.</p>
        <p>The acclaim that ''Pi'' received at Sundance stunned the whole team. ''Before that, we would sit around and talk about how we would get jobs at Kinko's to pay back our investors,'' Mr. Aronofsky said. The success of ''Pi'' meant that Mr. Aronofsky began to receive Hollywood offers. He says he would like to try his hand at studio filmmaking; and in fact he is under consideration to direct the next ''Batman'' film for Warner Brothers. He is also, however, already writing his own next project, which will be a science-fiction fantasy.</p>
        <p>Whatever the genre, it's a fair bet that Mr. Aronofsky will continue to write about restless souls and to demand all-out participation from his audience. ''I think the catharsis happens after this film, when people start to think about it,'' he said, ''and when they say, 'What does this mean for me and the people around me?' The best compliment that I've been getting with 'Requiem' is that people two days later are still thinking about the film.''</p>
        <p>Laura Winters's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the director Jeremy Podeswa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Winters's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the director Jeremy Podeswa.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
