<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tough Abstractionist on Her Own Merits</title>
    <meta content="10KIMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="91" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10KIMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krasner, Lee (1908-84)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DA1230F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tough Abstractionist on Her Own Merits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman profiles artist Lee Krasner in light of upcoming retrospective at Brooklyn Museum of Art; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Lee Krasner traveling retrospective arrives at the Brooklyn Museum of Art on Oct. 6, it will be a homecoming for this Brooklyn-born painter. Over the years, different shows have kept her work in sight, but this is the first museum survey in New York in a long time, and no doubt it will come as a revelation to some people. New Yorkers will see what the rest of the country has seen while the exhibition made its cross-country tour: that Krasner's best paintings are as beautiful as any abstract paintings America has produced.</p>
        <p>The question: is it possible to recognize her work for what it is and not get stuck, as usual, in the quagmire of her marriage to Jackson Pollock? The answer: no, but we should try. Born Lena Krassner in 1908, the daughter of recently emigrated Russian Orthodox Jews who ran a grocery store, Krasner trained in art schools around town, including Hans Hofmann's, where she learned about Cubism. By the 1930's she had evolved into what Alfred Kazin meant by ''New York Jew'': intellectual, curious, political, acerbic, with a personality that her friend Edward Albee once said gave ''comfort and ammunition to those who were unwilling to grant her her artistic due.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Lee Krasner traveling retrospective arrives at the Brooklyn Museum of Art on Oct. 6, it will be a homecoming for this Brooklyn-born painter. Over the years, different shows have kept her work in sight, but this is the first museum survey in New York in a long time, and no doubt it will come as a revelation to some people. New Yorkers will see what the rest of the country has seen while the exhibition made its cross-country tour: that Krasner's best paintings are as beautiful as any abstract paintings America has produced.</p>
        <p>The question: is it possible to recognize her work for what it is and not get stuck, as usual, in the quagmire of her marriage to Jackson Pollock? The answer: no, but we should try. Born Lena Krassner in 1908, the daughter of recently emigrated Russian Orthodox Jews who ran a grocery store, Krasner trained in art schools around town, including Hans Hofmann's, where she learned about Cubism. By the 1930's she had evolved into what Alfred Kazin meant by ''New York Jew'': intellectual, curious, political, acerbic, with a personality that her friend Edward Albee once said gave ''comfort and ammunition to those who were unwilling to grant her her artistic due.''</p>
        <p>Intelligence and astringency were traits she brought to her marriage, along with a depth of art-historical knowledge that Pollock lacked. He learned from her. She learned from him. As she was the first to acknowledge, in their relationship, as in all meaningful marriages, the flow of ideas was undeniably in both directions, and neither she nor he would have turned out the same without the other. But she took ideas from Matisse, Picasso and a slew of others, too, and at the end of the day made paintings distinctly her own, which is what matters.</p>
        <p>These include some of the busy, all-over canvases of the 1940's, impacted hieroglyphs and gossamer webs of thin white lines over flickering color, as in ''The Mouse Trap'' (1949). They include a few bright collages of the mid-50's, in which she starts elaborating the split-moon and eyelet shapes, the slashing leaf forms and arabesques that increasingly appear in her art. And most notably, they include the pictures she did after Pollock's death in 1956, when the scale of the paintings got bigger, the results more tempestuous and extravagantly handsome.</p>
        <p>You might say that works like ''The Seasons'' (1957) are fully ripe: ripe not just in terms of their allusion to vegetal shapes, hot pink and green, interweaving and dense, but also in terms of maturity and sheer emotion, the emotion mixing elements of violence with sex.</p>
        <p>Some critics have talked about the femininity of Krasner's art, I suppose to compliment the voluptuousness of her imagery and feathery touch. The feathery touch proves Krasner's mastery of line, but it is balanced, always, by toughness. Krasner wanted the struggle of painting to be visible in the pictures, and it is: ferocious shapes jostling for dominance in consistently heavy weather.</p>
        <p>Krasner's struggle, apart from the formal one, was partly against the indifference of the New York art world to women, although that gradually changed during her lifetime, and partly it was against the inevitable shifting tide of fashion, which denied Abstract Expressionism's value when she was coming into her own as an Abstract Expressionist.</p>
        <p>Clearly she thrived because of the challenge, making provocatively unquiet paintings in the midst of Minimalist quietude, Krasner's pictures having the last word by still speaking across the years. But she didn't exactly reject what else was going on. Shrewdly recognizing Minimalism's potential for her work, in various pictures she hardened the edges of shapes, pared things down, flattened colors, slowed the pace, even while keeping up the same basic tune. So ''Palingenesis'' (1971), for example, is like ''The Seasons'' but frozen: the forms, once wet, are now like cut ice.</p>
        <p>From this derive the odd later works made of collaged scraps of old charcoal drawings (mostly of studio models she drew in the 1930's), abstracted into monumental epigrams on raw canvas. Appropriating from herself was a kind of postmodernism before the fact, the dissonance of old and new increasing the spiky agitation of the collages (see ''Imperative'' and ''Imperfect Indicative,'' both 1976).</p>
        <p>These give way to the last works, which return, occasionally, to figuration while sustaining an abstract organizational logic that goes back to her days with Hofmann: from beginning to end (Krasner died, at 75, in 1984), her grasp of organizing space let her experiment with different styles without ever losing essential track of herself.</p>
        <p>''One could go on forever as to whether the paint should be thick or thin, whether to paint the woman or the square, hard-edge or soft, but after a while such questions become a bore,'' she famously told an interviewer. ''They are merely problems in aesthetics, having only to do with the outer man. But the painting I have in mind, painting in which inner and outer are inseparable, transcends technique, transcends subjects and moves into the realm of the inevitable.''</p>
        <p>Krasner's forthcoming show, organized by Robert Hobbs for the Independent Curators International and on view through Jan. 7, will be one of the few inevitable pleasures of the new art season in New York.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
