<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/Castle Village and Hudson View Gardens in Upper Manhattan; Shadows of an Uptown Castle, and Its Builder</title>
    <meta content="10SCAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paterno Trivium (NYC Park)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paterno, Charles (1876-1946)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6DD1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/Castle Village and Hudson View Gardens in Upper Manhattan; Shadows of an Uptown Castle, and Its Builder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on recently completed Paterno Trivium, small triangular park commemorating Charles Paterno, developer of Castle Village apartment complex in Manattan's Washington Heights section as well as scores of other apartment buildings; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE day I moved in someone knocked on my door and said, 'You've got to start working on this,' '' said Thomas Navin, an architect and garden designer who bought an apartment in 1998 at Castle Village on Cabrini Avenue north of 181st Street in upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Now, two years later, Mr. Navin's project, a small triangular park commemorating Charles Paterno, the developer of Castle Village and scores of other apartment buildings, is officially finished. But Mr. Navin said he has plenty of work left on his memorial to one member of a family that left a distinctive legacy in Manhattan real estate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE day I moved in someone knocked on my door and said, 'You've got to start working on this,' '' said Thomas Navin, an architect and garden designer who bought an apartment in 1998 at Castle Village on Cabrini Avenue north of 181st Street in upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Now, two years later, Mr. Navin's project, a small triangular park commemorating Charles Paterno, the developer of Castle Village and scores of other apartment buildings, is officially finished. But Mr. Navin said he has plenty of work left on his memorial to one member of a family that left a distinctive legacy in Manhattan real estate.</p>
        <p>Charles Paterno's father, John, left Castelmezzano, Italy, near Naples, in the 1880's with his wife, Carolina, after an earthquake destroyed one of his building projects. One of John and Carolina Paterno's sons, Saverio, stayed in Italy, but two others came over: Charles, born in 1876, and Joseph, born about 1881. The couple had more children, among them Michael, born about 1889, and Anthony, born about 1891.</p>
        <p>Although real estate is often a family business, Charles planned another career and graduated from Cornell Medical College in 1899. That same year his father died, leaving a half-finished apartment building at 507 West 112th Street.</p>
        <p>To make good on their inheritance, Charles and Joseph completed the building, and continued in the business as other projects presented themselves. Gradually their other brothers joined the firm, and what had started as John Paterno &amp; Sons evolved into the Paterno Brothers Construction Company. They worked on one or two projects a year as business continued to flourish, although in 1905 all the sons were still living with their mother in a row house at 557 West 183rd Street.</p>
        <p>Some accounts say that Charles Paterno decided to return to medicine during the Panic of 1907, but times must not have been too bad. From 1907 to 1909 he built one of the most unusual houses in New York, a cliff-top marble fantasy that quickly became known as the Paterno Castle, which stood to the north of Mr. Navin's present building.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Paterno designed much of the building itself -- the architect listed on the building permit is John C. Watson, who otherwise did only small apartments and commercial buildings for the family.</p>
        <p>Period descriptions said it included rooms of various styles -- including one in a Japanese motif -- a mushroom cellar, a swimming pool surrounded by bird cages and a 20-by-80-foot master bedroom. It was surrounded by an extensive series of greenhouses and gardens -- Paterno ultimately expanded the site to seven acres -- and a giant pergola-topped retaining wall, 1,000 feet long, still visible from the northbound lanes of the Henry Hudson Parkway below.</p>
        <p>From his unusual house Paterno expanded his real estate empire. In 1910 he built, with Joseph, the curving, near-twin buildings at 435 and 440 Riverside Drive at 116th Street. But by the mid-1910's the brothers had apparently formed separate companies. Joseph Paterno built an apartment building at 1220 Park Avenue, at 95th Street; Michael built one at 775 Park Avenue, at 72nd Street; and Anthony built one at 1040 Fifth Avenue, at 85th Street.</p>
        <p>Charles Paterno built large apartment buildings with elevators on the West Side, among them 300, 575 and 885 West End Avenue and 280, 285 and 290 Riverside Drive. By 1918 he had put up about 75 buildings housing perhaps 28,000 people.</p>
        <p>In an interview in American Magazine in 1918 he noted that the average apartment tenant stayed two years and would pay 30 percent more in rent to reduce the business commute by 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>IN 1918 Charles Paterno built the full-block 270 Park Avenue, between 47th and 48th Streets and running back to Madison Avenue, a sumptuous building with a central courtyard. (It was replaced by the Union Carbide building, completed in 1960.) Paterno said that the annual rent roll was $1.2 million. In a 1920 interview in the magazine  Buildings and Buildings Management he noted that ''people who are willing to pay high rents usually do not like to live in an apartment house with a name.''</p>
        <p>In 1924 Paterno told the American Institute of Architects that ''there is no progress in building; we lay bricks just as was done 500 years ago,'' and he predicted the invention of mechanical bricklaying, plastering and even painting.</p>
        <p>In the same year he built Hudson View Gardens, across from his estate, on the block between Northern (now Cabrini) Boulevard and Pinehurst Avenue. This picturesque apartment complex looked out on his expansive gardens. Later in the 1920's he announced a plan for a 90-story apartment house across the Hudson on the Palisades, but the plan was never carried out.</p>
        <p>By the mid-1930's he was spending more time away from the Paterno Castle and was building a country house in Greenwich, Conn. In 1938 he demolished the castle, building in its stead the $6 million Castle Village, five 13-story neo-Georgian brick towers with 580 apartments sharing his large garden. The retaining wall survived, and a few fragments of the estate, among them a single marble pillar at the entrance gate on Cabrini Avenue. But otherwise the Paterno Castle was destroyed. Charles Paterno died in 1946.</p>
        <p>Two years ago Mr. Navin, who is an architect and garden designer, bought a high-floor apartment at 120 Cabrini Boulevard, the southernmost of the Castle Village towers. Filled with architectural artifacts, the apartment has transfixing views of the Hudson, the Palisades and the gardens of Castle Village.</p>
        <p>He said that Van Stone, a community activist, first approached him about creating a small park in an empty space up the street at the intersection of Cabrini, 187th and Pinehurst Avenue. Mr. Navin conceived the idea of naming it for Charles Paterno.</p>
        <p>''I admire him for the way he made Hudson View Gardens and, later, Castle Village, so responsive to the site, the way the river views are shared with the passersby,'' Mr. Navin said, adding that the more typical waterfront development blocks off the water views with walls. Castle Village does not even have a fence at the sidewalk line, an unusually gracious gesture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Navin, working with Mr. Stone, put together a proposal for a Paterno Trivium at the 187th Street intersection -- ''trivium'' means an intersection of roads. Last spring the New York City Parks Department, as part of its Greenstreets Program, created a planted concrete pedestrian island where there had been only bald asphalt.</p>
        <p>MR. NAVIN designed the concrete to be scored with radial lines, and the planting consists of Winter King Hawthorn trees that grow to 25 feet, and a ground cover of Cowberry. Both change appearances over the seasons, with flowers, berries and leaves.</p>
        <p>The Trivium still looks incomplete, and Mr. Navin has created an organization, the Friends of the Paterno Trivium, to seek funds for additional plantings and benches.  He estimated that he needs $10,000 for low, protective hoop fencing and a curved bench. His plan is that the trivium would be a rest stop for elderly shoppers coming up the steep hill from Fort Washington Avenue.</p>
        <p>The architectural historian Andrew Dolkart is working on text for a sign. Mr. Navin would also like to make a cast of the medallion bust of Charles Paterno that is on one of the Castle Village buildings and install it in the concrete.</p>
        <p>None of the five buildings at the intersection were built by Paterno, but looking down Pinehurst Avenue and Cabrini Boulevard, both Hudson View Gardens and Castle Village are clearly evident.</p>
        <p>Tired shoppers stopping at the Paterno Trivium and looking west on 187th Street have a magnificent view of the Palisades, the same view that must have attracted Charles Paterno when he built his unique castle almost a century ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
