<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Boston Pops Make Fairfield County Debut</title>
    <meta content="10VALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Pops Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lockhart, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EED71739F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Boston Pops Make Fairfield County Debut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Keith Lockhard, in his sixth season with Boston Pops, prepares for debut in Fairfield County, Conn, in concert at Sherwood Island State Park (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT will Keith Lockhart do this time? Will the 40-year old conductor of the Boston Pops make his Fairfield County debut on a scooter? Will he reprise the Rollerblades? Might Elvis reappear?</p>
        <p>Maybe Mr. Lockhart will wind surf onto the shore at Sherwood Island State Park, where the Pops Esplanade Orchestra will play on Saturday evening. The concert (rain or shine) is to benefit the Stewart B. McKinney Foundation in Fairfield whose mission is to help people who are H.I.V. positive or have AIDS with housing, education, medical, personal and emergency needs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT will Keith Lockhart do this time? Will the 40-year old conductor of the Boston Pops make his Fairfield County debut on a scooter? Will he reprise the Rollerblades? Might Elvis reappear?</p>
        <p>Maybe Mr. Lockhart will wind surf onto the shore at Sherwood Island State Park, where the Pops Esplanade Orchestra will play on Saturday evening. The concert (rain or shine) is to benefit the Stewart B. McKinney Foundation in Fairfield whose mission is to help people who are H.I.V. positive or have AIDS with housing, education, medical, personal and emergency needs.</p>
        <p>So youthful looking that he still gets carded, Mr. Lockhart keeps his audience guessing with his on-stage antics. Now in his sixth season with the internationally known orchestra, he follows such distinguished Pops conductors as Arthur Fiedler and John Williams. Mr. Lockhart and the Pops (which has been a staple of public television for 30 years) have five albums to their credit, ''The Celtic Album'' having been nominated for a Grammy Award in a new classical cross-over category. Due for release this fall is the group's sixth CD, a collection of Latin music.</p>
        <p>''Latin Pop has taken over the American airwaves,'' said the conductor by telephone from Massachusetts. ''The album is a stepping off point, a wide-angle lens on Latin music,'' he explained. The album's musical origins are Argentine, Mexican, Brazilian, Afro-Cuban and Peruvian, among others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lockhart, whose father was raised in Stratford and whose grandfather worked at Sikorsky Aircraft, said the outdoor concert program would emphasize American music. ''The first half features music by three of the leading American composers: Copland, Bernstein and Williams,'' he said. ''The second half really goes in all sorts of directions, with Big Band stuff, material from both the 30's and the 40's; Basie, Miller, musical theater, Gershwin and some movie music.''</p>
        <p>''And,'' he added with a hint of mischief, ''we're doing a little Elvis 'Hound Dog,' 'Jail House Rock,' a wide range; I may get in to my Elvis thing.'' Unlike serious classical music concerts, the Boston Pops cultivates a light-hearted experience. ''We encourage yelling and dancing on the tables,'' said Mr. Lockhart, referring to the audience at Symphony Hall in Boston. ''We try to get people to behave a little less,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lockhart, in spite of his Pops persona, remains a serious musician. Now in his third season as music director of the Utah Symphony, he said, ''It's wonderful. It balances my plate of Pops.'' He said he enjoys working on the repertory, using the skills of being a music director and having a different sort of community involvement and responsibility.</p>
        <p>The Stewart B. McKinney Foundation -- which is currently supporting three homes, two in Fairfield County and one in Washington, D.C., housing eight families and a dozen adults among them -- began working to bring the Boston Pops to Fairfield County more than two years ago.</p>
        <p>For 19 years, his widow, Lucie McKinney, said, Congressman McKinney was committed to getting people off the street and into transitional housing. ''Then when he died of AIDS in 1987,'' she said, ''all the staff and all the family said we're going to continue but we're going to concentrate on people who have H.I.V. or AIDS.''</p>
        <p>The Boston Pops Esplanade Orchestra, conducted by Keith Lockhart, will perform on Saturday at Sherwood Island State Park in Westport, at 6 p.m., rain or shine. Tickets range from $5 for children under 12 accompanied by an adult, to benefit tickets at $200 and $150, which include pre- and post-concert activities and preferred concert seating. General admission (blanket seating) is $25. The number to call for tickets is (203) 255-7965 or (203) 255-6611.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
