<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jacobs Won't Battle Russian in 1,500</title>
    <meta content="10OLYM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/sports/10OLYM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4D61139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jacobs Won't Battle Russian in 1,500</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>BRISBANE, Australia, Sept. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American runner Regina Jacobs withdraws from Olympic team because of viral infection in her lungs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Finally, Regina Jacobs would break the cycle of brilliant Olympic trials and unsatisfying Olympic Games. At 37, she was at the peak of her running career. Having won a pair of silver medals in the 1,500 meters at the world championships, she would challenge for gold in the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>All those expectations dissolved today when Jacobs announced from her home in Oakland, Calif., that she was withdrawing from the American Olympic team because of a viral infection in her lungs. She could not breathe properly in training, she said, and an insufficient oxygen supply gave her no chance of challenging the defending champion in the metric mile, Svetlana Masterkova of Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Finally, Regina Jacobs would break the cycle of brilliant Olympic trials and unsatisfying Olympic Games. At 37, she was at the peak of her running career. Having won a pair of silver medals in the 1,500 meters at the world championships, she would challenge for gold in the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>All those expectations dissolved today when Jacobs announced from her home in Oakland, Calif., that she was withdrawing from the American Olympic team because of a viral infection in her lungs. She could not breathe properly in training, she said, and an insufficient oxygen supply gave her no chance of challenging the defending champion in the metric mile, Svetlana Masterkova of Russia.</p>
        <p>Craig Masback, the chief executive officer of the United States track and field federation, called the development ''a terrible loss for the U.S. team and for her, given how hard she had worked to get to this moment.''</p>
        <p>Another gold-medal favorite, the world-champion shot-putter C. J. Hunter, remains questionable after undergoing orthoscopic knee surgery.</p>
        <p>This is the second major meet from which Jacobs has withdrawn. She missed the 1995 world track and field championships in Goteborg, Sweden, with a foot problem. Now she is out of the Olympics in the metric mile, having previously finished 10th at the Atlanta Games and having failed to make the final in 1992 and 1988. Shayne Culpepper, who finished fourth at the Olympic trials in July, will replace Jacobs in Sydney, but she has no expectation of winning a medal.</p>
        <p>It was Jacobs, winner of both the 1,500 and the 5,000 meters at the Olympic trials, who seemed to have a real chance to bring the American women their first Olympic gold medal in the 1,500 meters. She had won silver medals at the 1997 and 1999 world championships, overcoming an iron deficiency with supplements and a change in diet. A more efficient stride encouraged her that she could finally challenge Masterkova's blistering kick in the 1,500.</p>
        <p>Jacobs set an American record of 14 minutes 45.35 seconds in the 5,000 meters on July 21. In hindsight, some track experts today questioned why Jacobs, who has a history of allergies and illness, subjected her body to the stress of that 3.1-mile race at the trials when she had no intention of running the event in the Olympics.</p>
        <p>''If you wanted a recipe for making yourself vulnerable to a viral infection that was it, especially after a tough 1,500,'' an American Olympic official said, speaking on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Phone calls to Jacobs and her coach and husband, Tom Craig, were not returned. She said her respiratory troubles began Aug. 11, three weeks after the Olympic trials, when Jacobs finished 14th out of 16 runners in a 3,000-meter race in Zurich. Her time of 8:50.12 was 24 seconds behind that of the winner, Gabriela Szabo of Romania.</p>
        <p>''I was feeling very fatigued and sluggish,'' Jacobs said in a statement.</p>
        <p>After a regimen of antibiotics, Jacobs appeared to have recovered from the viral infection, according to her agent, Emanuel Hudson. But on Tuesday she grew exhausted after two repetitions of a planned workout of 9 x 500 meters, he said, and a doctor's examination showed she was breathing at only 65 percent of capacity.</p>
        <p>''I had hoped to get it under control before Sydney, but we seem to have run out of time,'' Jacobs said of her relapse. ''Further, Tom and I felt that competing could put me at risk of injury.''</p>
        <p>Jacobs's withdrawal will be particularly relevant to the chances of her longtime rival, Suzy Favor Hamilton, who has the world's fastest time in the 1,500 this year at 3:57.40. She is clearly capable of winning the gold medal if she runs assertively from the beginning of the Olympic final on Sept. 30 and does not rely on her kick after a tentative, tactical race.</p>
        <p>Jacobs seemed to hold a psychological and competitive edge over Favor Hamilton, beating her repeatedly. Now that that mental impediment has been removed, Favor Hamilton may have a better chance against Masterkova, who appears vulnerable after surgery on both Achilles' tendons.</p>
        <p>''Suzy has run well this year, but she has not performed well in big meets,'' said a teammate, Joetta Clark-Diggs, a four-time Olympian at 800 meters. ''This is the meet for her to dispel any notion that she can't run on this level.''</p>
        <p>Jacobs was the most accomplished runner to withdraw from the Sydney Games since China's Dong Yanmei, a former world record-holder in the women's 5,000 meters, exited several days ago. Dong's departure was part of a withdrawal of 27 Chinese athletes, a number of whom had failed blood tests at home. Chinese officials appeared to be concerned that the athletes might fail a new test for the endurance drug EPO at the Sydney Games, jeopardizing Beijing's chances to host the 2008 Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>Hudson, Jacobs's agent, said she had not failed a drug test. Track officials said they were appreciative that Jacobs had withdrawn in time for Culpepper to replace her before the entry deadline Monday.</p>
        <p>''There has not been any failed drug test, and there is no issue with EPO,'' said Hudson, who added that Jacobs still planned to come to Sydney and to be available for interviews.</p>
        <p>''She told me, 'My chances of medaling are zero and none, and I don't want to waste a spot on the team,' '' Hudson said.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
