<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Adventure Can Start With a Click</title>
    <meta content="10CYBE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/travel/10CYBER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4D81230F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Adventure Can Start With a Click</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Tedeschi article on Web sites geared toward adventure travel; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ADVENTURE travelers represent the fastest growing segment of the $447 billion leisure travel market, according to the nonprofit Travel Industry Association. It is no surprise, then, that Internet entrepreneurs have flocked to this category with all the reckless abandon of the travelers they hope to serve.</p>
        <p>On paper at least, the notion of an adventure travel Web site for information and bookings is a perfect Internet idea. Relatively few conventional travel agencies specialize in this type of business, in part because the trips are very labor intensive to plan, and therefore offer meager financial returns. But Internet travel agents can operate much more efficiently than their offline counterparts, since, in theory, travelers assume most of the burden of researching and selecting trips and itineraries</p>
        <p>For consumers, the Web contains a multitude of sites that offer more information on adventure travel destinations than one could find in an entire bookstore -- where someone might spend $70 on five books about hiking treks in Montana -- and, often, a way to reserve a trip.</p>
        <p>What's more, information on these sites is typically better, or at least more extensive, than the offerings of the adventure-travel publishing world. That's because sites like GORP.com, away.com, REIadventures .com, Adventureseek.com, iExplore.com and Altrec.com, frequently establish agreements with travel publishers to use their information, then bolster that with an abundance of other tips and features.</p>
        <p>Away.com is one example. The site operators say users can find over 100,000 pages of information about trips, from African safaris to spelunking in Arizona. But those who want even more information have several other options. First, they can type in questions for one of eight experts who specialize in a region, like Latin America, or a theme, like ecotourism.</p>
        <p>The questions and answers are displayed in a forumlike format, and the postings are archived, just in case you have a question like one asked before. If you're considering a trip to Madagascar to see rare lemurs in the Ankarafantsika Reserve, for instance, the ecotourism section of the site has some suggestions already waiting.</p>
        <p>If you've forgotten how to spell Ankarafantsika and want to lean on a human being to find more information about the trip, Away also provides phone support, e-mail support, and online chats with other travelers or an Away travel consultant.</p>
        <p>The last option can be as much fun as building a campfire in the rain. I recently asked a question on Away.com about hiking in Kauai, since my wife and I were headed there with our year-old daughter, and we figured that if this child was to fit in with her peers, she really needed to toughen up and get with the whole adventure travel idea.</p>
        <p>During the online chat, a service representative ''pushed'' onto my screen a page  about horseback riding in Molokai -- the connection between that and hiking in Kauai was unclear -- and another page with general information about traveling to Kauai.</p>
        <p>Within two minutes, there were so many pages opened on my screen that I had to bushwhack my way through the browser to find the pop-up window where I'd been chatting with the service representative. Before I found it, I suspended the search to catch my breath and check e-mail, which was a bad idea, because my computer flashed a message about a ''connection failure'' and cut off the chat.</p>
        <p>The phone was much better. A friendly Hawaii specialist on Away.com told me that the company doesn't take reservations for day-tour companies in Hawaii, because it wouldn't be financially feasible, but she told me about the Web site of a tour operator who might help me. The call took three minutes, and I was able to check my e-mail at the same time.</p>
        <p>The top-tier adventure sites include many of the same features, like online chats and phone support, as well as tips from regional experts and lists of the most popular tours. But they are also prone to using unedited versions of sales literature sent by their tour providers -- which sell their products on multiple sites, so it's not unusual to feel like you're retracing your tracks while comparison shopping.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best differentiator for these sites is their search functions, which let you narrow the universe of available options quickly. Of those I visited, adventureseek .com had the most nimble and useful search feature. It let me set my price range, the number of days I wished to travel, and even the tour company. And when I chose a particular trip, it gave far more online information about the tour company than other sites, which leave such issues to their phone representatives.</p>
        <p>IExplore.com -- now partly owned by National Geographic -- also had a decent search engine, and some nice features, including one that allowed users to e-mail a page to a friend -- a particularly useful feature for people traveling in groups.</p>
        <p>Even if you found the perfect trip on these sites, however, you would not be able to book it online. Adventure sites typically ask their prospective customers to call an 800 number to reserve a trip.</p>
        <p>The reasons for this are both pragmatic and technological. Most of the companies in the market are small businesses run by people who are much more in tune with nature than e-commerce. They lack both the budget and the inclination to spend thousands of dollars on Internet booking systems.</p>
        <p>The adventure travel Web sites that depend on those tour operators for inventory have, in some cases, begun the long process of helping build reservation tracking systems for the operators, so everyone knows when a booking has been made, and how many available spots there are on a given trip.</p>
        <p>But even then, tour operators and their Internet partners prefer to have some interaction with the customer -- other than a mouse click that delivers a credit card number. By discussing the itinerary with a customer, travel agents can steer less-qualified adventurers toward less-strenuous trips, and make sure that those who are fit enough to climb a mountain have the right equipment and expectations for the vacation.</p>
        <p>Carla Kinney, 31, an acquisitions editor in Sugar Hill, N.H., recently tested the waters of online adventure travel planning while researching a backpacking trip to Montana. Her husband, Luther, 29, is a whitewater and backpacking enthusiast, and although Ms. Kinney says she is fit, she has not gone on overnight backpacking trips with him because she is not sure how she'd hold up with a heavy pack for several days.</p>
        <p>Her plan was to try a guided backpacking trip on her own first, to ease into the experience, so she checked a number of online search engines to find such a tour. Eventually, Ms. Kinney said she landed on the GORP .com site, where she had a 90-minute online chat with a travel consultant named Melissa. The chat ended abruptly when Ms. Kinney's computer dropped her Internet connection.</p>
        <p>But because she had typed in her phone number at the beginning of the chat session, Melissa called immediately, and they resumed their conversation. Twenty minutes later, they settled on a weeklong backpacking and horseback riding trip with nine other participants and five guides in the Bob Marshall Wilderness in Montana, for roughly $1,600, not including air fare or gear.</p>
        <p>''It was easy,'' Ms. Kinney said. ''And it could've been very difficult because I was so vague about what I wanted.''</p>
        <p>After the trip, Ms. Kinney was impressed. ''The outfitters met me at the airport, even though I'd never spoken to them,'' she said. ''GORP handled it.''</p>
        <p>As for whether the trip gave her confidence enough to go solo the next time, Ms. Kinney said: ''Absolutely. Most nights I didn't even sleep in the tent. It was awesome.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ADVENTURE travelers represent the fastest growing segment of the $447 billion leisure travel market, according to the nonprofit Travel Industry Association. It is no surprise, then, that Internet entrepreneurs have flocked to this category with all the reckless abandon of the travelers they hope to serve.</p>
        <p>On paper at least, the notion of an adventure travel Web site for information and bookings is a perfect Internet idea. Relatively few conventional travel agencies specialize in this type of business, in part because the trips are very labor intensive to plan, and therefore offer meager financial returns. But Internet travel agents can operate much more efficiently than their offline counterparts, since, in theory, travelers assume most of the burden of researching and selecting trips and itineraries</p>
        <p>For consumers, the Web contains a multitude of sites that offer more information on adventure travel destinations than one could find in an entire bookstore -- where someone might spend $70 on five books about hiking treks in Montana -- and, often, a way to reserve a trip.</p>
        <p>What's more, information on these sites is typically better, or at least more extensive, than the offerings of the adventure-travel publishing world. That's because sites like GORP.com, away.com, REIadventures .com, Adventureseek.com, iExplore.com and Altrec.com, frequently establish agreements with travel publishers to use their information, then bolster that with an abundance of other tips and features.</p>
        <p>Away.com is one example. The site operators say users can find over 100,000 pages of information about trips, from African safaris to spelunking in Arizona. But those who want even more information have several other options. First, they can type in questions for one of eight experts who specialize in a region, like Latin America, or a theme, like ecotourism.</p>
        <p>The questions and answers are displayed in a forumlike format, and the postings are archived, just in case you have a question like one asked before. If you're considering a trip to Madagascar to see rare lemurs in the Ankarafantsika Reserve, for instance, the ecotourism section of the site has some suggestions already waiting.</p>
        <p>If you've forgotten how to spell Ankarafantsika and want to lean on a human being to find more information about the trip, Away also provides phone support, e-mail support, and online chats with other travelers or an Away travel consultant.</p>
        <p>The last option can be as much fun as building a campfire in the rain. I recently asked a question on Away.com about hiking in Kauai, since my wife and I were headed there with our year-old daughter, and we figured that if this child was to fit in with her peers, she really needed to toughen up and get with the whole adventure travel idea.</p>
        <p>During the online chat, a service representative ''pushed'' onto my screen a page  about horseback riding in Molokai -- the connection between that and hiking in Kauai was unclear -- and another page with general information about traveling to Kauai.</p>
        <p>Within two minutes, there were so many pages opened on my screen that I had to bushwhack my way through the browser to find the pop-up window where I'd been chatting with the service representative. Before I found it, I suspended the search to catch my breath and check e-mail, which was a bad idea, because my computer flashed a message about a ''connection failure'' and cut off the chat.</p>
        <p>The phone was much better. A friendly Hawaii specialist on Away.com told me that the company doesn't take reservations for day-tour companies in Hawaii, because it wouldn't be financially feasible, but she told me about the Web site of a tour operator who might help me. The call took three minutes, and I was able to check my e-mail at the same time.</p>
        <p>The top-tier adventure sites include many of the same features, like online chats and phone support, as well as tips from regional experts and lists of the most popular tours. But they are also prone to using unedited versions of sales literature sent by their tour providers -- which sell their products on multiple sites, so it's not unusual to feel like you're retracing your tracks while comparison shopping.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best differentiator for these sites is their search functions, which let you narrow the universe of available options quickly. Of those I visited, adventureseek .com had the most nimble and useful search feature. It let me set my price range, the number of days I wished to travel, and even the tour company. And when I chose a particular trip, it gave far more online information about the tour company than other sites, which leave such issues to their phone representatives.</p>
        <p>IExplore.com -- now partly owned by National Geographic -- also had a decent search engine, and some nice features, including one that allowed users to e-mail a page to a friend -- a particularly useful feature for people traveling in groups.</p>
        <p>Even if you found the perfect trip on these sites, however, you would not be able to book it online. Adventure sites typically ask their prospective customers to call an 800 number to reserve a trip.</p>
        <p>The reasons for this are both pragmatic and technological. Most of the companies in the market are small businesses run by people who are much more in tune with nature than e-commerce. They lack both the budget and the inclination to spend thousands of dollars on Internet booking systems.</p>
        <p>The adventure travel Web sites that depend on those tour operators for inventory have, in some cases, begun the long process of helping build reservation tracking systems for the operators, so everyone knows when a booking has been made, and how many available spots there are on a given trip.</p>
        <p>But even then, tour operators and their Internet partners prefer to have some interaction with the customer -- other than a mouse click that delivers a credit card number. By discussing the itinerary with a customer, travel agents can steer less-qualified adventurers toward less-strenuous trips, and make sure that those who are fit enough to climb a mountain have the right equipment and expectations for the vacation.</p>
        <p>Carla Kinney, 31, an acquisitions editor in Sugar Hill, N.H., recently tested the waters of online adventure travel planning while researching a backpacking trip to Montana. Her husband, Luther, 29, is a whitewater and backpacking enthusiast, and although Ms. Kinney says she is fit, she has not gone on overnight backpacking trips with him because she is not sure how she'd hold up with a heavy pack for several days.</p>
        <p>Her plan was to try a guided backpacking trip on her own first, to ease into the experience, so she checked a number of online search engines to find such a tour. Eventually, Ms. Kinney said she landed on the GORP .com site, where she had a 90-minute online chat with a travel consultant named Melissa. The chat ended abruptly when Ms. Kinney's computer dropped her Internet connection.</p>
        <p>But because she had typed in her phone number at the beginning of the chat session, Melissa called immediately, and they resumed their conversation. Twenty minutes later, they settled on a weeklong backpacking and horseback riding trip with nine other participants and five guides in the Bob Marshall Wilderness in Montana, for roughly $1,600, not including air fare or gear.</p>
        <p>''It was easy,'' Ms. Kinney said. ''And it could've been very difficult because I was so vague about what I wanted.''</p>
        <p>After the trip, Ms. Kinney was impressed. ''The outfitters met me at the airport, even though I'd never spoken to them,'' she said. ''GORP handled it.''</p>
        <p>As for whether the trip gave her confidence enough to go solo the next time, Ms. Kinney said: ''Absolutely. Most nights I didn't even sleep in the tent. It was awesome.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
