<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Least Likely Burning Man</title>
    <meta content="10PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/living/10NURB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Burning Man Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Black Rock Desert (Nev)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Burning Man Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D61339F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Least Likely Burning Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes trip to Burning Man, weeklong logo- and brand-free festival in Black Rock Desert, Nev; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE aren't many rules at Burning Man -- the weeklong cyberhippie carnival in the middle of the Nevada desert that ended on Labor Day. But one of them is ''No logos.'' I was warned about this before I went. Unfortunately, I don't own any clothing without logos. Who does? So as an anti-anticommercial statement on my first morning there, I wore an old Creative Artists Agency T-shirt.</p>
        <p>''C.A.A!'' a female voice shouted as I biked past her encampment. ''Burn in hell!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE aren't many rules at Burning Man -- the weeklong cyberhippie carnival in the middle of the Nevada desert that ended on Labor Day. But one of them is ''No logos.'' I was warned about this before I went. Unfortunately, I don't own any clothing without logos. Who does? So as an anti-anticommercial statement on my first morning there, I wore an old Creative Artists Agency T-shirt.</p>
        <p>''C.A.A!'' a female voice shouted as I biked past her encampment. ''Burn in hell!''</p>
        <p>I turned the shirt inside out. And after four days in this branding-free zone, I would come to see her point.</p>
        <p>Burning Man, as you may or may not know, is devoted to ''radical self-expression.'' In 1986 its founder, Larry Harvey, burned a stick-man effigy on a Bay Area beach after breaking up with his girlfriend. As the pyrocentric event grew into an annual rite, authorities told Mr. Harvey to take his followers elsewhere. Now, 25,000 of them make the pilgrimage to the Black Rock Desert, a vast dry lake bed 120 miles north of Reno. Artists. Performers. College kids. Partyers. Techno-geeks. Ravers. Neo-paganists. Dot-com yuppies. Professional and amateur nudists. The effigy has grown to a 40-foot neon skeleton stuffed with wood and fireworks, whose spectacular torching is the event's ritualistic climax.</p>
        <p>A small temporary city springs up on this lifeless playa, so flat and desolate it can be used only for land speed tests and fashion shoots. Imagine a hallucinogenic state fair that combines elements of Woodstock, Mardi Gras, ''Alice in Wonderland'' and Cirque du Soleil. In short: not my scene, in the extreme.</p>
        <p>Years of professionally mandated cynicism have shut off whatever synapses are required to participate in a drum circle. I'm not a hugger. I hate camping. But a couple of San Francisco friends who had gone last year persuaded me I could enjoy it.</p>
        <p>Maybe, I figured. As long as I got the big bed in a state-of-the-art recreational vehicle and would never be forced to use a Porta-John.</p>
        <p>I was curious. Another friend was so affected by his Burning Man experience last year that it inspired him to take an unscheduled sabbatical from his New York television production business and embark on a three-month ''tour of the planet.'' And elsewhere.</p>
        <p>So I found myself way out of cell phone range, spending almost 12 hours setting up a Moroccan tent. I had never set up a tent, much less an 18-by-30-foot canvas Ali Baba number. My friends John and Ted (who made a quiet killing as an Internet entrepreneur) sent a woman to Morocco to buy it for the occasion -- an order that included pillows, ottomans and a few caftans. These guys, along with John's brother, David, and I were the core team, as they say in Silicon Valley, of a group that would swell to two more RV's and a Chevy Suburban. It was a sprawling frat party free of the civilizing influences of wives or girlfriends.</p>
        <p>We camped on Anal Avenue. I hasten to explain that Black Rock City is laid out like a clock face, with some streets fanning straight out from 2 to 10 o'clock, at half-hour intervals, and other curved concentric ones named for parts of the body. We were between Knee Lane and Sex Drive. Look, it was the best parking spot we could find in the middle of the night. Last year, the street theme was the solar system, and my friends wound up on Uranus.</p>
        <p>John, who works for a health care start-up, and his brother, a composer, filled our pseudo-souk with world-music instruments. There were Indian and African drums, flutes, a zither, not one but two didgeridoos, which by some standards is two didgeridoos too many.</p>
        <p>Once the logistical nightmare of erecting the tent was over, it was a hit. You could tell. People kept stopping to admire it. A young woman on a bicycle promised to come back later to belly-dance. And the people across the street -- who spent their entire time drinking, grilling and shouting obscenities -- hated us for it. When one of our happy-face pinatas went missing, they offered unconvincing denials.</p>
        <p>That night, we started our wanderings with a round of minigolf on a clothing-optional course at the bottom of our street. Our day had already featured a conversation with the owner of a pair of pierced nipples. So we were becoming inured to all the female nudity, partial and full.  (Not really, but we were getting better at not staring.)</p>
        <p>Spectators are the only kind of people Burning Man doesn't want -- yahoos and squares like me in jeans and black windbreakers and orange ''Lake Tahoe'' baseball caps. I could see that I was seen as a nonparticipant who didn't contribute to the madness, but only gawked at it. Twice I was described as ''funny looking.'' It was getting to me.</p>
        <p>Almost everyone had a gimmick, some bit of personal performance art -- a pope costume, a fur-covered bicycle, a tricked-out ''Mad Max'' car. At night, they turned themselves into walking light installations, festooned with fluorescent glow sticks, neon headgear sculptured into a fish shape (there was a whole school of them swimming around), or flashing red LED displays tracing arteries and a beating heart.</p>
        <p>The more ambitious revelers ran moving sideshows. A perennial favorite was a physicist who calls himself Dr. Megavolt. This mad scientist stands on top of a truck rigged with two huge tesla coils shooting deafening bolts of man-made lightning through his metal suit. Perfectly safe, he says. But you couldn't help wondering if the doc's brain hadn't accidentally been switched, Frankenstein-style, with some stoner in the crowd gaping slackjawed at his act.</p>
        <p>The air was cold and clear, but bad weather was coming. The next day, Ted and I rode bikes out to ''the Man'' himself, the towering effigy at the end of a promenade of monumental sculptures. Suddenly, a dust storm rolled over us, filling the air with choking white dust loaded with alkali from the lake bed. With no more than five feet of visibility, we pedaled in the general direction of our camp. I felt like Lawrence of Arabia, my C.A.A. T-shirt tied over my mouth and nose to keep out the cancer dust. Others who have seen the pictures thought it looked more like a scene out of ''Ishtar.''</p>
        <p>At least now I'd participated. I'd have a tale to tell at the Center Camp cafe, a tented 24-hour freak show that made the bar in ''Star Wars'' look like a T.G.I. Fridays. An image from the cafe that will haunt my dreams is the old man I saw walking out of it one afternoon, shaking and stark naked, like somebody's lost grandfather or the ghost of Timothy Leary back for one last crazy trip.</p>
        <p>The druggy component of Burning Man cannot be denied. A bulletin board in Center Camp posted results of a survey taken at last year's festival. About half the respondents said they had indulged in illicit substances. Half of them cited marijuana, and 20 percent Ecstasy. The Pershing County Police patrolled the streets, always in cars and trucks, some marked ''K-9 Unit.'' Drug-taking appeared to be clandestine, not brazen. Black Rock Rangers, volunteers in overalls with no official authority or status, ran interference between the ''citizens'' and the law, discouraging blatant drug consumption or other illegal behavior.</p>
        <p>One Black Rock Ranger told us he had stopped a bout of domestic violence in a tent and been punched by a drunk the night before. We asked if either he or the police ever stopped any public nudity. ''Are you kidding?'' he said. ''If ain't too cold and I ain't working, I'm naked.'' The Ranger then informed us that his nickname was Nude Marty.</p>
        <p>I wasn't about to get naked, but by the second and third nights, I did have a nighttime get-up that I hoped would at least shield me from public ridicule. I took an orange-and-black wool poncho that John had brought and tied red glow sticks to the fringe. A half-baked effort compared with the simple but powerful dreadlock effect Ted's younger brother Mark (a sculptor) created by safety-pinning dozens of glow sticks to his fishing hat. The fuzzy yellow bunny suit and happy-face head that Roland, one of our other camp mates, had on outdid us all. I looked like a chili-pepper promotion at Taco Bell. Still, the poncho got me my first hug, from a slightly plump young woman outside one of the miniraves on the playa. She must have been on drugs.</p>
        <p>To escape a flash rainstorm, we ducked into Space Cowboy, a tented theme rave populated almost entirely by men and women in Western gear. Until then, I'd never really understood the appeal of raves and the poundingly repetitive techno beat that drives them. I remember my niece telling me she felt old at raves when she was 23. How in tarnation do these kids move like that? I used to think I had rhythm. At 150 beats a minute, all I could do was try to blind people with my flashing red New York Taxi Wand (a gift!) to distract them from the geezer in their midst.</p>
        <p>But at Space Cowboy, in my dusty jeans and Day-Glo poncho, I felt like I'd finally found my tribe.</p>
        <p>The rain turned the ground into mud that locked bicycle wheels and turned shoes into platforms. Shades of Woodstock. I hated Woodstock, all three of them -- not that I ever went. The whole hippie commune ideal it conjures, the woolly politics turn me off. There are no politics at Burning Man, except a practical environmental commandment -- ''Leave no trace!'' -- that keeps the peace with the Bureau of Land Management, and a libertarian social contract.</p>
        <p>''Do anything you want as long as it doesn't interfere with anyone else's good time,'' as I read in the daily alternative paper; there is also an official daily paper, which is already pretty alternative. Adam Smith could have lived with that. So could a Deadhead or any Silicon Valley chief executive in our camp.</p>
        <p>For all the tribal drum beating, what really drives Burning Man is individualism. In the 1960's, hippies young and old basically wore the same pair of bell-bottoms. Here, the point is not to wear the same thing as anyone else. ''I just want to be different like all the other different people'' was Ted's joke about all the nonconformist conformism around us. But it was energizing. And what we labeled the ''obnoxious friendliness'' of most of the Burners was infectious. Before long, you stop fighting it.</p>
        <p>I went soft. I drummed -- once. For my last night, I asked Tracy, our resident face-paint artist, to give me a couple of red-glitter tears. When the Man burned, the sad chili-pepper salesman would bear witness! I hugged that chubby chick back.</p>
        <p>Besides the nudity, the allure of Burning Man is aesthetic. Aesthetic escapism from Disney and MTV and Old Navy and Starbucks. I understood why people covered up the sign on their Ryder rental trucks.</p>
        <p>Even for a hard-core free-market capitalist like me, branding is starting to seem like a plague, turning cities into billboards, foreign countries into fast-food courts. In his book on globalism, ''The Lexus and the Olive Tree,'' Thomas L. Friedman argues that no two countries with McDonald's franchises have ever gone to war. The price of this supersized Pax Romana is, well, a McDonald's in every country.</p>
        <p>Driving back into civilization -- or, rather, Reno -- I looked at the Emporio Armani logo on my sunglasses case. I'd never given it a second thought. It looked kind of stupid.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
