<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small but Bold: Theaters That Dare</title>
    <meta content="10THEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DC1239F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small but Bold: Theaters That Dare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on plays to be presented this season at small, out of the way theaters and performance spaces in New Jersey; several examples given; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE surprises of the new season are likely to be found in the state's small, out of the way theaters, or in performance centers where a play is a sometime thing.</p>
        <p>A favored, even an award-winning, cult favorite flop of 1991, David Hirson's Moliere-like ''La Bete,'' which is written in rhymed couplets, is a daring choice for Two River Theater Company in its theater in Manasquan. Broadway couldn't deal with it, but then Two River is enterprising, even when it delves into the familiar (''Heiress'' and ''American Buffalo,'' three decades and immeasurable worlds and styles apart, both on this season).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE surprises of the new season are likely to be found in the state's small, out of the way theaters, or in performance centers where a play is a sometime thing.</p>
        <p>A favored, even an award-winning, cult favorite flop of 1991, David Hirson's Moliere-like ''La Bete,'' which is written in rhymed couplets, is a daring choice for Two River Theater Company in its theater in Manasquan. Broadway couldn't deal with it, but then Two River is enterprising, even when it delves into the familiar (''Heiress'' and ''American Buffalo,'' three decades and immeasurable worlds and styles apart, both on this season).</p>
        <p>And Twelve Miles West promises ''The Notebook of Trigorin,'' Tennessee Williams's little-known take on Chekhov's ''Seagull,'' postponed from last year. And isn't it venturesome for a little theater in Montclair to end the season with Ibsen (the newest ''Doll's House'' adaptation by Frank McGuiness) after beginning with ''Shakespeare's R &amp; J,'' the boys' prep school variation?</p>
        <p>Montclair's other little theater that can, Luna Stage, has a one-woman show with music by Tom Waits on tap, a new play, and an old Fugard. For a new Fugard, the McCarter in Princeton will close its season with ''Sorrows and Rejoicing.''</p>
        <p>Even Dreamcatcher Repertory in Bloomfield is producing a repertory of risks, including last season's off-Broadway peculiarity, ''Fuddy Meers.''</p>
        <p>But the unexpected becomes more unexpected. One expects to see the famed Flying Karamazov Brothers at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center in Newark, and they'll be there, not flying but juggling and ''utilizing technologies never before exploited on the stage,'' in the words of the center's calendar. Not so expected is Julie Harris in a replay of ''The Belle of Amherst,'' her 1977 Tony Award winning performance in William Luce's one-woman play about Emily Dickinson.</p>
        <p>That may suggest that the arts center, with its two concert halls, is getting a grip on theater, beyond the obvious big-time touring musicals (this season it's ''Fame -- The Musical,'' ''Ragtime'' and a new ''Peter Pan'' production).</p>
        <p>The return of Savion Glover, Newark's native son, this time in ''Foot Notes,'' the evolution of his tryout one-night stand last year, is an unqualified theater event, Mr. Glover having starred off-Broadway in various incarnations of his jubilant, elegant dancefests. And this one is on for two nights. It pays homage to Jimmy Slade, Dianne Walker and Carter Williams, who will all appear.</p>
        <p>Cutting edge is hardly the handle for New Jersey theater, so when NJPAC's World Festival IV books the rapper Mos Def as well as an evening called ''Speaking in Tongues: Theater of the Spoken Word'' -- both belongng to hip-hop culture -- one is assured that the performing arts are not out of touch. But don't worry: The Vienna Choir Boys will drop in, and Handel's Messiah is not forgotten.</p>
        <p>At the John Harms Center for the Arts in Englewood, where two of the musical theater's true, dramatic divas, Betty Buckley and Audra McDonald, gave a joint concert last season, fulfilling Ms. McDonald's prophesy that ''it'll be dangerous,'' the designation ''theater'' can be stretched to encompass a live appearance by Philip Glass and the Kronos Quartet in a performance of the Glass score for ''Dracula: The Music and Film,'' while the 1931 classic is being screened.</p>
        <p>Such an event is eminently more theatrical than ''Love Letters,'' a faux play, which fits handily into a theater series. Of course, it depends on who the letter readers of the occasion are, and at the Harms, they will be Robert Wagner and Jill St. John, married in real life, so that's all in the ears of the listener.</p>
        <p>But talk of cutting edge, ''The Worst of Eric Bogosian,'' ranted and raved all by himself, and Lisa Kron's extraordinary solo performance piece, ''2.5 Minute Ride'' are not what the New Jersey theater in general or Englewood's arts center in particular are accustomed to.</p>
        <p>Of New Brunswick's two major theaters, George Street Playhouse is opening with Margaret Edson's life-affirming play, ''Wit,'' a script that was rejected by the theater's last ill-advised regime. And then a new artistic director, David Saint, came along. If it looks as though Mr. Saint has developed his own coterie of resident playwrights, who are also veteran, even venerable playwrights, one must wait and see what delights and revelations, sorrows or rejoicing, not one but two new plays by Arthur Laurents and yet another by the prolific A. R. Gurney are in the wings.</p>
        <p>It is worrisome to contemplate a new season without considering a schedule for Crossroads, the theater next door. A recorded message tells callers, ''Our season begins in October with 'Conversations on a Dirt Road' by Samm Art Williams.'' But a member of the theater's box office staff said on Thursday that the play is no longer under consideration and that a new announcement will be made shortly.</p>
        <p>Paper Mill is ever upbeat with musicals, musicals, musicals, musicals -- yes, four of them, well known and big time. ''Art'' with Judd Hirsch as star and as director, is in one of the two nonmusical slots, but then ''Art'' is everywhere, currently at Cape May Stage. So New Jersey theatergoers can see ''Art'' small and big, and that isn't easy.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
