<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/New Jersey; In Neptune, a Tech Park Plan for Route 66</title>
    <meta content="10NJZO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Neptune Township (Nj)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garbarine, Rachelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4D71F30F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/New Jersey; In Neptune, a Tech Park Plan for Route 66</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garbarine, Rachelle</byline>
      <dateline>NEPTUNE TOWNSHIP</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on plan by group of New Jersey investors to build four-million-square-foot technology and office park on 167 acres along Route 66 in Neptune Township; corridor in Monmouth County is becoming known as Silicon Parkway; drawing; maps (In the Region/New Jersey) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 167 hilly acres dotted with wetlands and thick woods along Route 66 in the north-central portion of this Monmouth County township have long defied development. But now, a group of New Jersey investors has advanced a plan to turn most of the property into a four-million-square-foot technology and office park.</p>
        <p>Last month, Garden State Hi-Tech Park  L.L.C., a Neptune development company, was granted general site plan approval from the Neptune Township Planning Board to develop the commercially zoned property. The $400 million project, to be called Garden State Hi-Tech Park, will consist of 18 two- to six-story buildings and a 12-story, 200-room hotel and conference center, the developers said. The park, which will be built in phases over 10 to 20 years, depending on market demand, will also have underground parking for up to 12,000 cars as well as a helipad, the developers said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 167 hilly acres dotted with wetlands and thick woods along Route 66 in the north-central portion of this Monmouth County township have long defied development. But now, a group of New Jersey investors has advanced a plan to turn most of the property into a four-million-square-foot technology and office park.</p>
        <p>Last month, Garden State Hi-Tech Park  L.L.C., a Neptune development company, was granted general site plan approval from the Neptune Township Planning Board to develop the commercially zoned property. The $400 million project, to be called Garden State Hi-Tech Park, will consist of 18 two- to six-story buildings and a 12-story, 200-room hotel and conference center, the developers said. The park, which will be built in phases over 10 to 20 years, depending on market demand, will also have underground parking for up to 12,000 cars as well as a helipad, the developers said.</p>
        <p>About 70 acres of the site, most of them containing wetlands, will remain undeveloped. Under state law, wetlands are protected from development.</p>
        <p>Construction of the project's first phase, with 150,000 to 450,000 square feet of office space, is expected to start by next spring, said Kenneth E. Himsel, director of development for the group. The first phase must still receive final approval from the township, and developers say that construction will not begin until a tenant leases a percentage of the space.</p>
        <p>Financing for the initial phase is to be provided by banks and the partners, who have developed residential and commercial projects in New Jersey, Connecticut and New York. The partners have invested $2 million in the Neptune project, Mr. Himsel said.</p>
        <p>''We looked beyond the wetlands and saw that it had great potential, given its location,'' he said. In addition to being on Route 66, the site is bisected by Route 18 and is close to Exits 100 and 102 of the Garden State Parkway and to Interstate 92, making access convenient. The site's development, Mr. Himsel added, also comes at a time when large buildings are needed for the high-technology businesses that are moving  expanding in Monmouth County.</p>
        <p>Though the county has been known more for its seaside resorts than for its technology industry, it is home to operations of AT&amp;T and Lucent Technologies. In addition, it has a variety of housing and a labor pool balanced with skilled and unskilled workers, said Joseph J. Sarno, a senior director at Cushman &amp; Wakefield, the real estate services firm, which is the project's leasing agent.</p>
        <p>Indeed, many commercial brokers are using the phrase ''Silicon Parkway'' for the area in Monmouth County stretching from Exits 102 to 120 of the Garden State Parkway, describing it as New Jersey's emerging version of the technology-rich Silicon Valley in California, Route 128 in Boston and Research Triangle Park in North Carolina.</p>
        <p>The Neptune Township technology park, Mr. Sarno added, is being marketed as a place ''where larger companies can establish a presence and smaller ones have the flexibility to grow.'' Prospective tenants include telecommunications and biotechnology firms.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said, his company has been working with six tenants who together are looking for up to 1.25 million square feet of space in the county. In its midyear office market survey, his company reported that the vacancy rate in the county was 5.4 percent, down from 6.5 percent in mid-1999.</p>
        <p>The project is moving forward after two years of discussions with Neptune Township officials, who wanted ''to take advantage of the strong economy and the southward migration of businesses'' by promoting Neptune as a place to do business, said Mayor Kevin B. McMillan. Commercial development, local officials said, would help balance the economic base of their eight-square-mile township of 30,000 people and help keep property taxes stable.</p>
        <p>The initial phase of the high-tech park is estimated to generate $726,000 in annual tax revenue for the township and, when complete, a yearly total of nearly $8 million. Over the years, it is also expected to produce at least 5,000 permanent jobs.</p>
        <p>Mayor McMillan stressed, however, that the township wanted development that would ''improve the overall health of the community'' and benefit residents, not overburden municipal services.</p>
        <p>STILL, when the township's seven-member Planning Board unanimously voted to approve the project last month, some residents, particularly those who live near the site, expressed concerns about increased traffic and noise. They said they were also worried that a few buildings would be too close to some homes and that so large a project would detract from the area's semirural character.</p>
        <p>Michael J. Bascom, the township's economic development director, said the developers would be required to make the necessary road and other improvements to accommodate their project. Mr. Bascom, who is also the township's chief financial officer, added that over the last two years, Neptune has updated its master plan to reflect its direction of growth and created the nonprofit, semiautonomous Neptune Township Economic Development Corporation to attract businesses.</p>
        <p>''We were missing out on the economic boom,'' said Kurt Cavano, president of the economic development group. ''We have available land and people looking for jobs.''</p>
        <p>The results so far include efforts to boost particular neighborhoods in the township, like Ocean Grove, its historic beachfront section. But much of the new development has taken place along Route 66, where most of the township's available commercially zoned land exists, Mr. Bascom said.</p>
        <p>During the mid-80's building boom, before the recession of the early 90's, the corridor, touted as the Golden Mile, attracted office structures with a total of about 700,000 square feet. But in the last year, it has drawn commercial developments like a 135,000-square-foot Home Depot store, which is part of a larger project that is expected to add up to 315,000 square feet of retail space. Two other projects planned or nearing completion are expected to add 350,000 square feet of retail space.</p>
        <p>The high-tech park, Mr. Bascom said, will serve as the easternmost anchor to the Route 66 corridor, which extends west to Exit 100 of the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>The township formerly owned about 70 acres of the park's site. Decades ago, the newspaper that owned the property divided it into small lots that were given to subscribers as part of a promotion. Over time, lot owners who could not develop their sites because the sites were too small stopped paying taxes, and by the early 1980's, the owners lost their land to the township through foreclosure. Others deeded their sites to the township, Mr. Bascom said, noting that the property has been zoned for commercial use for 17 years.</p>
        <p>In 1995, the township tried to sell its 70 acres at a public auction. But Mr. Bascom said the property's topography and environmental concerns frustrated developers, who thought the site was too expensive to build on. But he said the township always believed that the site was ripe for development because of its location and because it was connected to public water and sewer services.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the township sold its 70 acres for $500,000 to a developer for a retail project that never moved ahead. That year, Garden State bought it for $750,000. Mr. Himsel said buying up the remaining 97 acres of vacant land from various owners provided enough buildable land to accommodate the project as well as add access to the site.</p>
        <p>The buildings, to be designed by a Neptune architect, James J. Monteforte, are to have a minimum floor area of 50,000 square feet and follow the natural contours of the land, which rises in elevation from 60 to 150 feet. The developers also intend to offer tenants dual power sources and access to fiber-optic lines. And the grounds will feature man-made waterfalls and ponds, the latter doubling as retention basins for storm water runoff, Mr. Himsel said.</p>
        <p>The offices will be laid out with few indoor columns and 9- to 10-foot-high ceilings to accommodate raised floors so that high-tech tenants can install the wires needed for their businesses, added Mr. Sarno, the broker. He said average rents were expected to be $20 a square foot. In Cushman &amp; Wakefield's midyear market survey, the average rent for office space in Monmouth County was listed as $21.69 a square foot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Himsel, talking about the county, added, ''This is not a case of 'Build it and the tenants will come,' because the tenants are already here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
