<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Among Unpaid Wages of a Revolution: Competing Claims on Land in Nicaragua</title>
    <meta content="10NICA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/world/10NICA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nicaragua</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Somoza Debayle, Anastasio (1925-80)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DA1E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Among Unpaid Wages of a Revolution: Competing Claims on Land in Nicaragua</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <dateline>NAGAROTE, Nicaragua</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than decade after elections removed Sandinistas from power in Nicaragua thousands of Nicaraguans, as well as about 900 American citizens and even descendants of former dictator Anastasio Somoza, are grappling with legacy of Sandinista revolution, namely, confiscated land, homes and businesses that were distributed to peasants and party loyalists alike; while few expect to get back all they owned, even skeptics decry what they say is convoluted, lengthy administrative and legal process that too often result in paltry settlements paid in low-value government bonds; undoing tangle is proving vexing for government, which has little cash and many concerns about social unrest that could result from attempts to dislodge thousands of people who acquired land through urban development plans and agrarian reform laws that were legitimate at time; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where Emilio Aguilar once raised cattle, hundreds of families now raise their children. Small houses line bumpy dirt roads cut through what were the pastures of Mr. Aguilar's 200-acre ranch. He fled to Honduras after the Sandinistas declared him a counterrevolutionary in 1979, and since then mayors in this town about 25 miles northwest of the capital of Managua have handed out plots to the poor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aguilar returned to Nicaragua in 1991 to reclaim his land, or at least get compensation. In 1993, the government offered him 15-year bonds with a face value of $340,000, but he refused to settle because the securities were denominated in Nicaraguan cordobas, a currency that has lost about half its value since then.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Where Emilio Aguilar once raised cattle, hundreds of families now raise their children. Small houses line bumpy dirt roads cut through what were the pastures of Mr. Aguilar's 200-acre ranch. He fled to Honduras after the Sandinistas declared him a counterrevolutionary in 1979, and since then mayors in this town about 25 miles northwest of the capital of Managua have handed out plots to the poor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aguilar returned to Nicaragua in 1991 to reclaim his land, or at least get compensation. In 1993, the government offered him 15-year bonds with a face value of $340,000, but he refused to settle because the securities were denominated in Nicaraguan cordobas, a currency that has lost about half its value since then.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Aguilar is intent on suing the mayors who gave away his ranch. If that day ever comes, Exhibit A could be the site of the courthouse itself, since it is in the middle of his old spread.</p>
        <p>''They put the courthouse here saying it was to impose justice, but they did it on stolen land,'' said Mr. Aguilar, 65. ''I feel this is all a joke. If there were justice, they would have gotten this legally.''</p>
        <p>More than a decade after the elections that removed the Sandinistas from power, thousands of Nicaraguans -- as well as about 900 American citizens and even the descendants of the country's former dictator, Anastasio Somoza -- are grappling with the legacy of the Sandinista revolution: confiscated land, homes  and businesses that were distributed to peasants and party loyalists alike.</p>
        <p>While few people expected to get back all they owned, even skeptics decried what they described as convoluted, lengthy administrative and legal processes that too often result in paltry settlements paid in low-value government bonds.</p>
        <p>Undoing the tangle has proved vexing for the government, which has little cash and lots of concerns about the social unrest that could result from dislodging thousands of people who acquired land through urban development plans and agrarian reform laws that were legitimate at the time.</p>
        <p>''Imagine having to say to someone, 'You have to leave the land you had for the last 15 years of your life,' '' said the foreign minister, Eduardo Montealegre, whose own family has yet to recoup its confiscated properties. ''You either have to resolve it with new land from the state or pay bonds to the old owners. It is not simple.''</p>
        <p>Many Nicaraguans said that resolving complex and competing property claims is the biggest hurdle to attracting foreign investment in the Western Hemisphere's second-poorest nation. (Haiti is at the bottom of the list.) The task grows more complicated as time passes because current owners are selling the confiscated land to new buyers -- including the current president, Arnoldo Aleman, who purchased a farm from an agricultural cooperative.</p>
        <p>''What is happening in this country regarding property is serious denial of rights,'' said Lino Hernandez, the president of the Permanent Commission of Human Rights of Nicaragua. ''If there is no solution to the property question, there will be no security or investment in this country. Ten years have passed and we feel powerless that we cannot find a solution to this problem.''</p>
        <p>In its 11 years in power, the Sandinista government confiscated about 170,000 properties, including many that were seized right before it handed power to President Violeta Chamorro's administration in 1990. The property claims began soon after she took office, increasing under pressure from American lawmakers who urged her government to settle claims of Nicaraguans who became American citizens while in exile.</p>
        <p>Finance Minister Esteban Duque Estrada did not respond to repeated requests for an interview, nor did the official in charge of evaluating property claims. The Finance Ministry's Web site indicates that more than 7,000 people have filed claims covering 17,000 properties, with almost 6,800 claims pending resolution.</p>
        <p>Most claims that have been resolved were settled with 15-year bonds that currently trade for about 20 cents on the dollar. Not many more landowners are willing to wait 15 years for the bonds to mature and for the government to pay their face value. There were expectations that the bonds would be bolstered by profits from the sale of state-run industries, but Mr. Aleman's administration scuttled those hopes.</p>
        <p>Yet, even if the plan had proceeded, it would have meant little to the Willey family of Tampa, Fla. In 1951, John Willey, a Californian who moved to Nicaragua to mine gold, set up an electric company in Matagalpa. The company stayed in his family until the Sandinistas nationalized it in 1979.</p>
        <p>At the time, the power company had 6,000 customers; it has since grown to about 32,000 customers, and on Tuesday the government is scheduled to sell the company to private investors for anywhere from $500 to $1,000 a customer. Mr. Willey's heirs have been waging an unsuccessful battle to receive what they regard as a fair price for their share of the company. While they estimate they could be entitled to as much as $9 million, the Nicaraguan government in 1998 offered them bonds with a face value of 2.3 million cordobas, then about $216,000. But they could have sold immediately for only $38,000 -- about half what they had been offered in 1996.</p>
        <p>''Not only did my grandfather give a lot to that country, but he built it for his descendants, and I think the Nicaraguan government should be fair,'' said Carrie Willey-Gagnon, Mr. Willey's granddaughter. ''I don't know if we're ever going to get anything at this rate. I do not believe the Nicaraguan government is willing to give up a chunk of what they believe is their property.''</p>
        <p>Despite letters from American diplomats and congressmen, the Nicaraguan government has yet to resolve the issue. The American government could withhold foreign aid if it felt that claims on confiscated properties were not being resolved, but it issued a waiver this month that kept the aid flowing. At the same time, the American government has urged Nicaragua to take steps to increase the value of the bonds and make them a more attractive option.</p>
        <p>But a bill recently introduced by Representative Benjamin A. Gilman, Republican of New York, would require the President to submit to Congress the 50 most pressing American property cases and prevent him from issuing another waiver until they had been resolved.</p>
        <p>''The problem is the Nicaraguan government has grown complacent,'' said a congressional staff member. ''They think they will automatically get the waiver and that they are somehow entitled to it. But this cannot be business as usual. People are very upset.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Montealegre, the foreign minister, said that the Aleman administration had resolved more than 1,300 property claims -- at least four times the number managed under Mrs. Chamorro.</p>
        <p>''The fact that one or two particular cases have not been resolved does not mean others have not, and we are making an effort to resolve all,'' he said. ''It is complicated. We have problems in health, education and housing. We have much poverty the Sandinistas left us with. It has set us back years. No country is giving us foreign aid to pay for property. The majority of the people understand that.''</p>
        <p>The Sandinistas, now in a strained alliance with the Aleman party in the National Assembly, said they favored efforts to compensate people whose property was given to others. But they also said it was important that the country continue its current program of granting land title to thousands of people who are occupying small plots of land for homes and farms. Edwin Castro, a Sandinista member of the National Assembly, said that land titling was as important as reparation.</p>
        <p>''If we legalize it, and if we want to talk about guarantees to private property, then we should talk about guaranteeing the property of all people,'' he said. ''But you cannot raise the flag of private property to favor 500, 50, or 20 claimants to the detriment of a half million people.''</p>
        <p>If there was any failure in the revolution, Mr. Castro added, it was not proceeding quickly enough with granting title to new owners.</p>
        <p>Among the people seeking to recover property are relatives of the dictator dislodged by the Sandinistas. Led by Luis and Alejandro Sevilla-Somoza, two American-born nephews, the Somoza family has so far had no luck, saying their case is politically untouchable.</p>
        <p>The Somoza nephews insisted that the bulk of their properties, from stock holdings to vast farms and estates, were obtained by their grandfather legally. Like others who have been frustrated in reclaiming their land, they have bought some of it on the open market. They said they wanted their day in court, however, to begin to clear the family name.</p>
        <p>''We're the last excuse of the revolution,'' Luis said, ''the evil Somozas who raped the country.''</p>
        <p>The family, like others who have lost properties, said Sandinista officials benefited from the confiscations, including party leaders who still live in luxury homes taken from exiles.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, what have they done?'' Alejandro said. ''They transferred the wealth from one group to another group. And who pays for it? The people of Nicaragua.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castro dismissed the idea of returning property to the former dictator's relatives or to his soldiers. ''Don't ask about returning the property of the National Guard or the Somoza family,'' he said. ''That's why there was a revolution. No one with a historical consciousness would accept that Versailles should be given back to the French royalty. No one would dare say that because it would be a historical absurdity.''</p>
        <p>For-sale signs are tacked to fence posts and telephone poles along the road to El Volcan, a 257-acre farm that belonged to Genaro Molina's family until the Sandinistas gave it to an agricultural cooperative. But the biggest business these days is in real estate, as members of the cooperative sell parcels to people seeking to build houses. With developments being built to accommodate a flood of people from the city, the region is rife with speculation.</p>
        <p>Among the people who have bought from the cooperative are an American citizen, the sister of a judge and the leader of a political party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Molina and the government have yet to agree on how much he should be compensated for the land, so last year Mr. Molina decided to take back a tiny piece, where he built a guard house and put up a sign warning potential buyers that the property is in litigation. Since then he has been able to buy back some of the land from the cooperative for about $5,700 an acre, less than half the $14,300 an acre he thinks it is worth.</p>
        <p>''I took this part by force, so let them take me out,'' Mr. Molina said. ''The Molina family is clear. We will take this to the end.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
