<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="10BENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DA1339F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elizabeth and Essex  TUESDAY -- The opening night of the New York City Opera season, a black-tie benefit gala at the New York State Theater in Lincoln Center, will present Donizetti's ''Roberto Devereux'' with the soprano Lauren Flanigan in the role of Queen Elizabeth. The evening, which will raise money to support the company's performance and public outreach programs, will also honor Murray H. Bring, the former vice chairman and general counsel of Philip Morris Companies and a City Opera board member. A cocktail reception at 5:30 p.m. will be followed by the performance at 6:30, and dinner and dancing to the Peter Duchin Orchestra at 9:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 870-4235.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Elizabeth and Essex  TUESDAY -- The opening night of the New York City Opera season, a black-tie benefit gala at the New York State Theater in Lincoln Center, will present Donizetti's ''Roberto Devereux'' with the soprano Lauren Flanigan in the role of Queen Elizabeth. The evening, which will raise money to support the company's performance and public outreach programs, will also honor Murray H. Bring, the former vice chairman and general counsel of Philip Morris Companies and a City Opera board member. A cocktail reception at 5:30 p.m. will be followed by the performance at 6:30, and dinner and dancing to the Peter Duchin Orchestra at 9:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 870-4235.</p>
        <p>Celebrating a Grande Dame  SATURDAY -- Kitty Carlisle Hart's 90th birthday, which was last Sunday, will be celebrated with a black-tie dinner at the Neuberger Museum of Art at the State University College at Purchase, N.Y. The event, which will begin at 6:30 p.m. with cocktails at the museum, will raise money for Westchester County cultural organizations like the Neuberger, the Katonah Museum of Art, the SUNY Performing Arts Center and the Caramoor Center for Music and the Arts. Dinner will follow at 8 at the nearby SUNY Performing Arts Center. Tickets, $250, or $50 for the cocktail party alone, from (914) 251-6116.</p>
        <p>Sporting Chances  NEXT SUNDAY -- Guests attending a party at Chelsea Piers can choose to participate in activities like soccer, gymnastics and basketball. The event, which runs from 4 to 7 p.m, will include live and silent auctions of sports memorabilia, art and other prizes. The proceeds will  aid New Yorkers for Children, a nonprofit organization that works with the Administration for Children's Services to provide recreational and cultural activities for children in foster care. Food and refreshments will be served. Tickets, $125, or $50 for those 12 and under, from (212) 921-9070.</p>
        <p>Jazz for the Conservatory  SEPT. 18 -- Dr. Billy Taylor, the jazz pianist and composer, will be awarded the Brooklyn Conservatory of Music's first $25,000 award for music education at a dinner to raise money for the school's scholarship program. The evening, at the Supper Club in Manhattan, 240 West 47th Street, near Broadway, will begin with drinks at 6. Dinner and musical performances by students, faculty members and colleagues of Dr. Taylor will follow at 7. Tickets, $150, from (718) 622-3300.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
