<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With a New Release, A Reluctant Makeover</title>
    <meta content="10SCHO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="86" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10SCHO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP/JAZZ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osborne, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schoemer, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DC1030F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With a New Release, A Reluctant Makeover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN SCHOEMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schoemer, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Schoemer interviews pop singer Joan Osborne, who comments on new album, her first in five years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE woman who greets you in front of a Manhattan soul food joint is not someone you would recognize. She is tall and imposing, beautiful but remote. She wears slender black stretch capris and a chic blue three-quarter-sleeve gingham shirt with matching decorative eyeshades. Her posture is so perfect she could balance books on her head; her cheeks have a spa-fresh glow. Demure honey ringlets frame her face. She tells you that this home-cooking place is a bit crowded and noisy for her liking; she would prefer the upscale French boite across the street. She glides into a booth, tucks her Bebe shopping bag under the table, orders a cappuccino -- no food today; she is staying slim for some forthcoming television appearances -- and fixes you with a humorless, rather unhelpful stare. You feel perplexed, a little thrown off. You look over her shoulder, half expecting a wild-haired, grinning, explosive, bluejeans-clad hippie babe to leap out from behind a pillar and rescue you. You're not sure what to say to this creature. How about: Nice to meet you -- now where's Joan Osborne?</p>
        <p>The music business has a long tradition of making over its female artists, whether it's the Supremes in finishing school or just the latest battery of stylists dispatched to a video shoot. What's odd about Ms. Osborne's situation is that she seems to have forced this transformation upon herself, and she's not entirely comfortable with it. Is that a designer shirt? you can't help asking. ''Well, yes, it's Agnes B.,'' she answers with a slight squirm. ''I have a weird relationship to the whole celebrity glamour thing, so I'm wary of saying that I bought a designer shirt. I don't like that musicians have become mannequins for designers, and that everything people wear gets reported on in the media, and people don't have their own style anymore. But I did buy it; they didn't give it to me. I mean, I like nice things, and I don't have to buy my clothes at Goodwill anymore. It's nice to be able to go into a store and pick out something beautiful and wear it and like it. I don't think there's anything wrong with that.'' Then she allows herself a wee extra measure of defensiveness. ''It's not like it's Versace or anything,'' she grumbles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE woman who greets you in front of a Manhattan soul food joint is not someone you would recognize. She is tall and imposing, beautiful but remote. She wears slender black stretch capris and a chic blue three-quarter-sleeve gingham shirt with matching decorative eyeshades. Her posture is so perfect she could balance books on her head; her cheeks have a spa-fresh glow. Demure honey ringlets frame her face. She tells you that this home-cooking place is a bit crowded and noisy for her liking; she would prefer the upscale French boite across the street. She glides into a booth, tucks her Bebe shopping bag under the table, orders a cappuccino -- no food today; she is staying slim for some forthcoming television appearances -- and fixes you with a humorless, rather unhelpful stare. You feel perplexed, a little thrown off. You look over her shoulder, half expecting a wild-haired, grinning, explosive, bluejeans-clad hippie babe to leap out from behind a pillar and rescue you. You're not sure what to say to this creature. How about: Nice to meet you -- now where's Joan Osborne?</p>
        <p>The music business has a long tradition of making over its female artists, whether it's the Supremes in finishing school or just the latest battery of stylists dispatched to a video shoot. What's odd about Ms. Osborne's situation is that she seems to have forced this transformation upon herself, and she's not entirely comfortable with it. Is that a designer shirt? you can't help asking. ''Well, yes, it's Agnes B.,'' she answers with a slight squirm. ''I have a weird relationship to the whole celebrity glamour thing, so I'm wary of saying that I bought a designer shirt. I don't like that musicians have become mannequins for designers, and that everything people wear gets reported on in the media, and people don't have their own style anymore. But I did buy it; they didn't give it to me. I mean, I like nice things, and I don't have to buy my clothes at Goodwill anymore. It's nice to be able to go into a store and pick out something beautiful and wear it and like it. I don't think there's anything wrong with that.'' Then she allows herself a wee extra measure of defensiveness. ''It's not like it's Versace or anything,'' she grumbles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Osborne, 37, has a strong motivation for remaking herself. On Tuesday she releases ''Righteous Love,'' her first album in five years and the long-delayed follow-up to her Grammy-nominated major-label debut, ''Relish.'' What's on the line? Only her future as a recording artist and her ability to continue making a living at the thing she loves, music. Five years ago, Ms. Osborne, along with Sheryl Crow and Sarah McLachlan, helped set a new standard for strong, self-sufficient female singer-songwriters in the pop marketplace. Ms. Osborne was the most unconventional of the three: raised in Kentucky, with a gutsy stage presence nurtured in New York City dives and a voice that teetered between angelic ecstasy and sexual abandon, she expressed an affinity for the blues that had rarely been heard in a white girl since Janis Joplin. ''Relish'' was the success story of the year. By early 1996 she had been nominated for seven Grammy Awards; the album crept into Billboard's top 10, and the single ''One of Us,'' a quirky musing on God, hit No. 4. Rolling Stone put her on the cover, and Entertainment Weekly dubbed her ''Saint Joan.'' Her natural image was a huge part of the appeal: her kinky hair, lack of makeup and exuberant smile suggested that a woman could be herself, look like herself and still win the love of millions.</p>
        <p>BUT behind the scenes, problems were brewing. By the time of the Grammys -- and by the way, she left empty-handed -- Ms. Osborne was already starting to psych herself out. Wrestling with the notion of a follow-up, she embarked on a compulsive spree of collaborations with different producers, including David Lowery of the band Cracker; Aaron Comess of the Spin Doctors; the hip-hop producer Mike Mangini, and T-Bone Burnett, who had coaxed hits out of the Wallflowers and Counting Crows. Most of the sessions were fruitless. She even dallied once again with Rick Chertoff, who had produced ''Relish'' and signed her to Mercury Records. But she was uneasy about giving Mr. Chertoff too much control. For all the accolades, she was dissatisfied with ''Relish.''  ''I think I have a lot more in me than what's on there,'' she told Spin magazine.</p>
        <p>Her restlessness went beyond the recording studio. She traveled to India to perform at a benefit for the Dalai Lama and studied vocal technique with the qawwali singer Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan. Finally, after three years of searching, she hit a groove with the producer Mitchell Froom (his credits include albums with Suzanne Vega and Elvis Costello). And then out of nowhere she became the victim of a music-industry drive-by. Mercury's parent company, Polygram, was bought by Seagram and merged with Universal. Late in 1999, her album still unfinished, Ms. Osborne was dropped.</p>
        <p>She says she tried not to take it personally. ''My first reaction was: Wow! That's a bad business decision. If I were a business person, I would not choose to drop me.'' She decided to continue work on the album using her own money. ''It became a little scary when I realized that if I couldn't get another deal, I was going to lose my house,'' she says matter-of-factly. She did get another deal, curiously enough, with Interscope, a label within the Universal fold. ''It was a risk,'' Ms. Osborne says now. ''But I think it would have been a greater risk for me not to do it. I didn't have anything to fall back on. It's not like I could start making a living at Wall Street the next day. I just thought, well, this is one of those moments that you read about in people's stories, when they're up against a wall and they have to take a chance and believe in themselves.''</p>
        <p>''Righteous Love'' is ready to be heard, but Ms. Osborne's struggles probably aren't over. The pop world is a completely different place now than it was five years ago. Studio-sculptured, choreographed and scripted idols like Britney Spears and Christina Aguilera have become the new female role models. The momentum of Lilith Fair has expired for a more up-to-date example of gung-ho female togetherness -- check out ''The Powerpuff Girls.'' Ms. Osborne, who lives in Manhattan, insists she's not starting from scratch. ''As fickle as audiences or the media can be, I still walk around the streets of New York and strangers ask me, 'When is your new record coming out?' '' she says. ''That will happen a couple of times a day. So I do have a feeling like they're still out there. I don't know how many people are out there, but there's somebody that still wants to hear more.''</p>
        <p>And yet she realizes that she is under pressure, even if it's self-inflicted, to conform to a less forgiving and indulgent set of music-business rules. ''I know the word artist has been adulterated in the context of the music business, but I still believe in what that means for myself,'' she says. ''So to keep functioning within a system where it doesn't really matter if you're an artist or not -- you just have to sell records and whatever sells is acceptable and legitimate -- well, that can be difficult.''</p>
        <p>WITH ''Righteous Love,'' Ms. Osborne is trying to have it both ways: she wants to express raw passion and sexual heat but do it in a restrained enough way to be digestible by a wide audience. She needs to deliver a product that will make a healthy return on her label's investment, or risk losing the financial backing that allows her to work at a broad mainstream level; yet she also needs to satisfy a core audience that looks to her for music of lasting substance. It's a lot to accomplish. ''Righteous Love'' has some glorious moments: the title track shimmies and sways like a beefed-up version of early 60's Brill Building soul, and ''Poisoned Apples (Hallelujah)'' equals the best moments on ''Relish'' for its conflation of the sexual and the spiritual. Her cover of Bob Dylan's ''To Make You Feel My Love'' is so sublime, you are tricked into thinking it's one of the best songs he ever wrote.</p>
        <p>But much of the rest of the album feels strangely stillborn. The keyboard-heavy production strives for a feeling of raucous barroom funk but often winds up sounding clattery and untender. Some of the songs lack clear characters or lyrical points of view. ''Righteous Love'' falls victim to a myth that's at work in the music industry at least since Nirvana's ''Nevermind'' made the leap from critical favorite to blockbuster smash: that great music is only truly validated if it becomes popular. It's a crippling notion. Great music is great music, whether it's acclaimed by 10 people or a tittering throng. If Ms. Osborne wanted to make an incredible album, she had to please only one person: herself.</p>
        <p>In that respect, ''Righteous Love'' seems to have fallen short. Ms. Osborne herself admits that at times she has been too distracted by other aspects of the business to focus on the goal at hand. ''I'm jealous of people like Neil Young who came of age in the 60's and 70's, when it wasn't part of your job to pose for a million magazine pictures and look like a model,'' she says. '' 'Cause I don't, and it's hard to try. I think my music has suffered because of the time I have to put into other things. I often struggle with the thought that here I am spending an hour at the gym because I have to look a certain way, because otherwise I won't be palatable to an audience. When in reality I would rather be learning to play the guitar better or spending more time writing. It is a compromise; it is a balancing act.''</p>
        <p>Her eyes become intense, and for the first time in the interview she allows some real emotion into her voice. It's fear, and regret, and a hunger for the creative fulfillment she still hasn't achieved. But as long as she has that desire, she'll keep working at it. And once she gets it right, it'll be worth the wait for all of us.</p>
        <p>POP/JAZZ Karen Schoemer is senior editor for music for Us Weekly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Karen Schoemer is senior editor for music for Us Weekly.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
