<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Improviser's Art In the Realm of Jazz</title>
    <meta content="10WOOS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenholz, Harry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brackeen, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coleman, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reedus, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staudter, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D71739F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Improviser's Art In the Realm of Jazz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS STAUDTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staudter, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chief organizer Harry Rosenholz comments on upcoming Friday Night Jazz at Wooster music series at Wooster School in Danbury, Conn, which will open with appearance by pianist Joanne Brackeen, bassist Ira Coleman and drummer Tony Reedus; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NEW concert series will offer jazz aficionados something rare in the suburbs: a chance to indulge in the improviser's art in a small, homey and, most importantly, stress-free setting.</p>
        <p>''Friday Night Jazz at Wooster,'' a monthly series to be held at the Wooster School in Danbury, begins this Friday at 8 p.m. with an appearance by the pianist Joanne Brackeen, along with Ira Coleman on bass and Tony Reedus on drums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NEW concert series will offer jazz aficionados something rare in the suburbs: a chance to indulge in the improviser's art in a small, homey and, most importantly, stress-free setting.</p>
        <p>''Friday Night Jazz at Wooster,'' a monthly series to be held at the Wooster School in Danbury, begins this Friday at 8 p.m. with an appearance by the pianist Joanne Brackeen, along with Ira Coleman on bass and Tony Reedus on drums.</p>
        <p>Harry Rosenholtz, whose two sons attend the school, is chief organizer of the concert series. ''My idea was to bring great musicians to play in what'll seem like somebody's living room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The nine shows scheduled by the nascent Wooster School Jazz Society will feature such musicians as the saxophonist Benny Golson, the guitarist John Abercrombie and the pianist Kenny Barron. The concerts will take place at the Schwartz Reception Center, which can accommodate about 75 seats and a small stage. Mr. Rosenholtz described the center's acoustics as excellent, saying, ''You can hear a pin drop in there.''</p>
        <p>Although two of the Wooster School's music teachers, Marian McAleavey and Barbara Maisonpierre, have been instrumental in planning the concerts, Mr. Rosenholtz, 46, is by all accounts the force responsible for initiating the series.</p>
        <p>His love of jazz began in college when he spent his junior year abroad in Denmark, a house guest of Phil Abrams, an expatriate jazz saxophonist. ''Phil would wake me up every morning with a different jazz record,'' recalled Mr. Rosenholtz, ''and in the evenings he'd take me to the Club Montmartre in Copenhagen, where he introduced me to the musicians who often played there, like Dexter Gordon, Kenny Drew and Tete Montoliu.''</p>
        <p>It was at the club, in 1975, that he first heard Joanne Brackeen, playing in Stan Getz's quartet.</p>
        <p>After college Mr. Rosenholtz became a sales manager for a legal forms company, but a fetish for hats led him to go to work for Harvey Kane, a legendary figure in Manhattan's retail hat business, at Worth &amp; Worth. In 1980 he bought the business from Mr. Kane, and a year later he married Mr. Kane's daughter, Heidi.</p>
        <p>Worth &amp; Worth had two shops in midtown, and the one at the Astor Hotel on 48th Street was frequented by jazz musicians. Often, as a token of his affection for their artistry, Mr. Rosenholtz would present a hat to a musician, and soon word spread of the giveaways, with the hat man becoming fast friends with many jazz personalities. Miles Davis, in fact, used to send Mr. Rosenholtz demo tapes and solicit his opinion of the recordings.</p>
        <p>The hat business is gone, and today Mr. Rosenholtz, who lives in Ridgefield, runs a business that specializes in imported leather goods.</p>
        <p>''There is an intentional balance here at Wooster of different realms,'' said the school's headmaster, John Cheeseman, ''academic, spiritual, moral, aesthetic -- and jazz is part of that balance in life that every individual, if lucky, will have exposure to.</p>
        <p>Tickets to the nine shows are available in three-night packages for $135. More information is available from Marilyn McAleavey at the Wooster School at (203) 830-3963.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
