<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bumpy Days for Mr. Bush</title>
    <meta content="10SUN1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/opinion/10SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3D61039F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bumpy Days for Mr. Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on the troubles Gov George W Bush's presidential campaign has run into since Democratic National Convention; says Bush is being forced to deal with issues for the first time and Vice Pres Al Gore appears to be gaining on or pulling ahead of him in states that once looked safe for Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is too soon to tell whether Gov. George W. Bush's campaign has simply hit a rough patch or is heading into a steep dive. He was smart to listen to alarmed Republican elders and open talks with the presidential debate commission about meeting Vice President Al Gore. He also promised to be more spontaneous and hold town meetings. But the larger problems faced by Mr. Bush's campaign may be harder to solve, since they have to do with substantive issues and electoral geography.</p>
        <p>The presidential campaign has reached the stage when state-by-state tallies are more meaningful than the numbers nationwide. While the national polls have the candidates about even, only a handful of big states are in play. These states may also be among the least receptive to Mr. Bush's agenda of tax cuts and restricted government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is too soon to tell whether Gov. George W. Bush's campaign has simply hit a rough patch or is heading into a steep dive. He was smart to listen to alarmed Republican elders and open talks with the presidential debate commission about meeting Vice President Al Gore. He also promised to be more spontaneous and hold town meetings. But the larger problems faced by Mr. Bush's campaign may be harder to solve, since they have to do with substantive issues and electoral geography.</p>
        <p>The presidential campaign has reached the stage when state-by-state tallies are more meaningful than the numbers nationwide. While the national polls have the candidates about even, only a handful of big states are in play. These states may also be among the least receptive to Mr. Bush's agenda of tax cuts and restricted government.</p>
        <p>State polls show Mr. Gore ahead or suddenly competitive in two places, Louisiana and Florida, that once looked safe for Mr. Bush. With the three biggest states hardly in doubt -- Texas is solid for Mr. Bush, and California and New York seem safe for Mr. Gore -- the emerging battleground is turning out to be the industrial heartland of Ohio, Michigan, Missouri, Pennsylvania and Illinois.</p>
        <p>Since the era of Ronald Reagan, working-class Democrats in these states could be tempted into voting Republican. In recent years, they have gone for Republican governors like Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania and John Engler of Michigan, who favor a strong government role in health and education. But it is also true that swing voters in these states have often voted Democratic and may be ready to do so again this year. The polls suggest that the anti-government conservatism so popular in Mr. Bush's Sun Belt base may not play as well among the undecided voters in the hottest combat zone of 2000.</p>
        <p>An irony is that at the outset of his campaign, Mr. Bush promised to be a ''compassionate conservative'' along the lines of Mr. Ridge and Mr. Engler. But in recent weeks Mr. Bush has gotten off that message, sidetracked by the squabble over debates and distracted by his own indecision over how hard to hit the vice president in attack ads.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, partly because of adroit moves by Mr. Gore, Mr. Bush has been pulled onto issues terrain. He is being asked to define proposals, rather than depict them with broad strokes. One result last week was that Mr. Bush wound up sounding more conservative than compassionate, as when he unveiled his bifurcated Medicare drug program. Social issues like gun control, the environment and abortion rights are also strong for Democrats in the critical Midwest.</p>
        <p>It was significant that Mr. Bush's campaign on general themes of personality and leadership was struggling just as Republicans in Congress gave ground on specific issues in order to avoid a budget confrontation with President Clinton. The House speaker, Dennis Hastert, has signaled a willingness to accept a minimum wage bill and is said to be looking for a compromise on the patient's bill of rights. Republicans are even said to be willing to accept more spending on school construction, foreign aid and other Democratic initiatives.</p>
        <p>Picking a fight with the Democrats, the Congressional Republicans are saying, can only play into the enemy's hands. That underscores the reasons that Mr. Bush has had a rough time since the Democratic convention. Mr. Gore has succeeded for the time being in making this a campaign season that is turning on specifics rather than generalizations about values and governmental philosophy. And the concentration on issues by his campaign seems especially important in the cluster of contestable states expected to decide the election.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
