<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mao's Summer Camp</title>
    <meta content="10JOSHT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John Burnham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wang, Lulu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Velmans, Hester</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lily Theater, The: A Novel of Modern China (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED91230F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1219" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mao's Summer Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Burnham Schwartz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, John Burnham</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Burnham Schwartz reviews book The Lily Theater: A Novel of Modern China by Lulu Wang, translated by Hester Velmans; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LILY THEATER</p>
        <p>A Novel of Modern China.</p>
        <p>By Lulu Wang.</p>
        <p>Translated by Hester Velmans.</p>
        <p>434 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LILY THEATER</p>
        <p>A Novel of Modern China.</p>
        <p>By Lulu Wang.</p>
        <p>Translated by Hester Velmans.</p>
        <p>434 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $25.</p>
        <p>Not every novel can hook you with a translator's note, but try this one: ''The novelty of a book written in Dutch by a young Chinese immigrant who had only just mastered that tongue took the Netherlands by storm in 1997, catapulting 'The Lily Theater' to an almost permanent place at the top of Holland's best-seller list.'' And that's just for openers. The note goes on, extolling the ''liberties'' taken by the first-time author, Lulu Wang, in her adopted tongue -- a characteristic ''preference for concrete imagery and colloquial idioms''; for ''onomatopoeic transcriptions'' in the manner of traditional Chinese oral narration; for the juxtaposition of ''flowery'' prose with the brute epithets of barnyard and street; and finally for the conscious use of cliche as a kind of linguistic looking glass through which the Western reader might consider the ''new and often startling significance'' of such secondhand phrases when ''seen through Chinese eyes.''</p>
        <p>You chew on the possibly brilliant, probably disastrous implications of it all. And yet the note, by the gifted translator Hester Velmans, is an oddly relevant primer to Wang's novel, which turns out to be an honest, sprawling, sometimes frustrating, avowedly fictionalized account of the author's childhood during the Cultural Revolution. Wang is an original, a writer of real talent, even when her heart proves mightier than her pen.</p>
        <p>Wang's ''liberties'' with Western language are in evidence right from the start, there in all their eccentricities. Hers is a voice in the making -- which in ''The Lily Theater'' is the voice of an energetic and spirited teenager who finds herself in the grip of history, both public and her own. It's 1972, and the Cultural Revolution is still in progress. Lian's parents -- a doctor and a history professor -- have been stripped of their privileged status and banished to the provinces to ''learn from the peasants.'' But then Lian's mother, home on weekend leave from re-education camp, persuades an official to allow her to take Lian back with her. Before our young narrator knows what's happening, she's in the middle of nowhere, sleeping in a dank, windowless dormitory full of persecuted elders -- a group of ''undesirable human weeds,'' which in this case are some of the most important scholars in China. Between hours of forced labor, and under the prying eyes of the camp's informers, these prisoners take it upon themselves to give the girl an honest schooling. Soon Lian herself is giving impromptu soliloquies of politically condemned Chinese history to a lakeside audience of frogs and birds -- a peaceful, private place she calls ''The Lily Theater.''</p>
        <p>This first section -- roughly a third of the book -- is in many ways the richest. Wang, through the plucky and empathetic gaze of her alter ego, draws with considerable finesse the emotional and physical boundaries of a world within a world. Certainly, we understand, this re-education camp is a microcosm of Mao's born-again China. And yet -- populated as it is by society's outcast sages, by the tender and the wise and perceived by a girl who has not yet had her heart hardened by experience -- it is also unmistakably its own place; it is a world that despite the daily brutalities perpetrated against its (mostly) kindhearted inmates seems stubbornly innocent, marked by a sense of timelessness and, ultimately, nostalgia.</p>
        <p>And that is one of the most surprising and endearing aspects of ''The Lily Theater.'' We are witness to a great deal of cruelty, to the bitterness eating at decent people, scholars and peasants alike, for whom all real truth has been turned inside out and made dangerous; but cruelty and bitterness are not this novel's themes. Friendship and knowledge are the gifts offered up to Lian's trust, and we see that they not only sustain her through a time of unimaginable upheaval but also knit the very fabric of her identity. The unlikely, formative friendships Lian makes with two aging historians in the camp (one's cogent motto is ''Don't turn around, because behind you lies the dreadful past'') and especially with Kim, a schoolmate back in Beijing, constitute the soul of the book as well as the only real spine of its perhaps too linear plot.</p>
        <p>Released from the camp, Lian comes home to Kim and to school. The story of their friendship, its connections and disconnections -- which is in many ways a story about class in the classless fiction called Maoist China -- makes up the last two-thirds of the book. While Lian is of the highest, or first, caste -- she and her parents return to a big state-owned apartment with central heating -- Kim comes from the lowest, or third, caste, and lives with her peasant-laborer family in a mud house in the Beijing slums, far from the city center. It is one of the novel's most insistent ironies (irony not being the principal form of expression here) that the Cultural Revolution -- whose stated program was to return China to its revolutionary zeal through celebration of the peasants and suppression of the ''thinking elements'' -- should offer no relief at all from the staggering class divides that were the reality of Chinese life. Add to this the common cruelty of teenagers, the tendency of a group to attack or scapegoat its weakest member, and you have the makings of a tragedy. Wang is convincing in her depiction of the moral chaos at Lian and Kim's school, and of the remorseless shifting of political winds that becomes the cover under which people humiliate or ruin one another. And she is good, too, in her realization of Kim's ''mongrel existence,'' of ''the hooded caution that was the secret of her survival,'' and of her strange and squalid home life, which is the setting of some of the book's most memorable scenes.</p>
        <p>It is all the more disappointing, then, to reach the end of this fairly long novel -- too long, it must be said -- and discover in the place of tragedy a bizarre and rather hysterical denouement that reads like a cross between ''Lord of the Flies'' and ''The Siege.'' Whether or not this event is drawn from Wang's own life doesn't, alas, matter; it's neither credible nor interesting within the context of the characters we have come to believe we know. It is here -- late in the book, in her depiction of Kim as a kind of outlaw forged by society's cruelty and ignorance -- that the story, reaching for a big payoff, seems to shrink. The book's linguistic ''liberties'' begin to pop out of the prose, like the rusty springs of an old couch.</p>
        <p>But that's the end. Until then, ''The Lily Theater'' evokes its world with abundant and cleareyed sympathy.</p>
        <p>John Burnham Schwartz is the author of ''Bicycle Days'' and, most recently, ''Reservation Road.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Burnham Schwartz is the author of ''Bicycle Days'' and, most recently, ''Reservation Road.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
