<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Kennedy's Legacy, Lessons and Pitfalls For Hillary Clinton; Carpetbagger Issue Has Echoes of '64, But Differences Could Prove Crucial</title>
    <meta content="10RFK.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/politics/10RFK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Robert Francis (1925-68)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Lyndon Baines (1908-73)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DC1E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Kennedy's Legacy, Lessons and Pitfalls For Hillary Clinton; Carpetbagger Issue Has Echoes of '64, But Differences Could Prove Crucial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article compares Hillary Rodham Clinton's run for Senate seat from New York to Robert Kennedy's in 1964; cartpetbagger accusations that are hurled at Clinton were also used against Kennedy; even though Lyndon Johnson carried New York by 2.5 million votes, Kennedy's margin of victory was considerably less; among striking similarities between campaigns is deep hostility provoked by both Kennedy and Clinton, photo; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He stepped out of the shadows of another political era one morning last week, a familiar silhouette walking at the side of Hillary Rodham Clinton along the Hudson River in the Upper West Side neighborhood that had so rallied around his father, Robert F. Kennedy, when he ran for senator 36 years ago.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Kennedy Jr., the son of the 1964 Democratic candidate for the Senate, had been recruited by Mrs. Clinton's campaign to talk about the environment, but it soon became clear that that was not the only reason for this news conference. Without prompting, Mr. Kennedy began reminiscing about his father's campaign. He recalled his father's success in overcoming the accusations of carpetbagging and the ''hatred'' that the candidate found in New York in the summer of 1964.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He stepped out of the shadows of another political era one morning last week, a familiar silhouette walking at the side of Hillary Rodham Clinton along the Hudson River in the Upper West Side neighborhood that had so rallied around his father, Robert F. Kennedy, when he ran for senator 36 years ago.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Kennedy Jr., the son of the 1964 Democratic candidate for the Senate, had been recruited by Mrs. Clinton's campaign to talk about the environment, but it soon became clear that that was not the only reason for this news conference. Without prompting, Mr. Kennedy began reminiscing about his father's campaign. He recalled his father's success in overcoming the accusations of carpetbagging and the ''hatred'' that the candidate found in New York in the summer of 1964.</p>
        <p>It was a scene shimmering with history, and evocative of the battle Mrs. Clinton finds herself in today. Kennedy, like Mrs. Clinton, was a polarizing figure seeking to represent a state where he did not live, a first-time candidate for public office whose last name, more than anything else, accounted for the honor of his nomination to run for senator from New York.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's supporters routinely offer up the election of Robert Kennedy as the case study that demonstrates that she can overcome the difficulties that have arisen in her campaign. She has spent hours studying newspaper clips from the 1964 campaign, an aide said, and lessons drawn from the Kennedy candidacy have shaped much of what she has done these last 15 months.</p>
        <p>But for all the seeming symmetry between these two races, the candidacy of Robert F. Kennedy is arguably more a tale of caution than of comfort for Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>The characterizations of Kennedy as a carpetbagger emerged from the moment he announced his candidacy at Gracie Mansion -- demonstrators carried signs that said ''Bobby Go Home'' -- and they festered until the very end of the election.</p>
        <p>''Why should you represent a state where you cannot even vote?'' asked a full-page newspaper advertisement bought by Democrats supporting the Republican in the race, Senator Kenneth B. Keating. The editorial pages of the state's major newspapers, in particular those of The New York Times and The New York Herald Tribune, opposed Kennedy's march into New York every step of the way, dismissing him, in the words of one Times editorial, for ''attempting to use New York and the senatorial office in a relentless quest for greater political power.''</p>
        <p>For Robert Kennedy in 1964, and for Mrs. Clinton today, the label ''carpetbagger'' was really shorthand for a general condemnation, expressed in startlingly similar terms: they were, according to their critics, ambitious, opportunistic, ruthless (for Kennedy) and untrustworthy (for Mrs. Clinton).</p>
        <p>Yes, Kennedy won that race in 1964, but by 720,000 votes in a year when Lyndon B. Johnson carried New York by 2.5 million votes. In addition, Kennedy was running against a 64-year-old white-haired incumbent who, while respected and popular, ran a clumsy campaign in the critical final week. Without Johnson at the top of the ticket, Kennedy might very well have lost, or have won by even fewer votes, largely because of the attacks on his residency, according to his associates at the time.</p>
        <p>''It was a huge thing,'' the younger Mr. Kennedy said in an interview. ''As a 10-year-old, I knew what the word 'carpetbagger' meant, and where it came from. It was part of the conversation in our house every day. I remember for my father's birthday, people giving him carpetbags as presents. It was a constantly resounding theme during that campaign.''</p>
        <p>The chairman of Kennedy's Senate campaign, R. Peter Straus, said he came to view Kennedy's Massachusetts residence as perhaps the biggest obstacle to winning the election. ''It was a big issue, this carpetbagging thing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Straus sounded much like Mrs. Clinton's advisers, though he would not offer any direct comparisons with Mrs. Clinton's situation, noting his own particular relationship with the first family. (Mr. Straus is married to Marcia Lewis, the mother of Monica S. Lewinsky.)</p>
        <p>Many Democrats today, mindful of the lessons of Kennedy's 1964 victory, say they believe that the single most important factor in determining Mrs. Clinton's success in her race against Representative Rick A. Lazio will be how well Al Gore fares against George W. Bush in New York. While leaders in both major parties say it is highly likely that Mr. Gore will defeat Mr. Bush in the state, it seems improbable that he will come close to matching Johnson's 2.5 million-vote cushion of 1964.</p>
        <p>Even at that, it is doubtful that Mr. Gore can do for Mrs. Clinton what Johnson did for Kennedy. Voters these days are more independent, and a vote for Mr. Gore may not necessarily guarantee a vote for Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>What is more, although Mrs. Clinton is the wife of a sitting president popular in New York, Bobby Kennedy was the brother of a martyred president, running for office barely one year after John F. Kennedy was  killed. The trauma of that assassination shadowed Kennedy wherever he went in New York that fall. ''You couldn't vote against Robert Kennedy without seeing the presence of John Kennedy,'' said William J. vanden Heuvel, former deputy representative of the United States to the United Nations, who was deputy manager of the Kennedy campaign.</p>
        <p>More than anything else, it was the assassination of his brother that led Robert Kennedy to examine his own future.</p>
        <p>Like Mrs. Clinton today, Kennedy, who was the United States attorney general, was approaching the end of his time in Washington, and at the age of 38, he wanted to follow the path that his brothers had taken into elective politics. Some upstate Democratic leaders began floating Kennedy's name as a prospective opponent to Keating, who was a difficult target for Democrats.</p>
        <p>Kennedy's initial interest was not in running for the Senate, but in maneuvering to become Johnson's vice-presidential candidate. In June 1964, in what was seen in Washington as a signal to Johnson, Kennedy announced that he did not want to be considered for the Senate nomination from New York. But Johnson's dislike for the younger Kennedy was deep and well known, and at the end of July, he announced that would not consider any sitting cabinet member for vice president.</p>
        <p>It was now the middle of the summer, and Kennedy had to move fast. He could not realistically run for office in his home state, Massachusetts, because its voters had already elected Edward M. Kennedy senator. So Robert Kennedy flew to New York, met with Mayor Robert F. Wagner and won his support to enter the race, instantly eclipsing the Democrat who almost certainly would have won the nomination, Representative Samuel S. Stratton, from upstate.</p>
        <p>Kennedy found himself under immediate attack -- for much the same reason that Mrs. Clinton is criticized now. ''People have been standing in line at the World's Fair longer than my opponent has been a resident of New York,'' Keating declared.</p>
        <p>Kennedy set out to address the problem, with a kind of road map that Mrs. Clinton seems to be following 36 years later. He began a tireless schedule of travel across the state, seeking in 10 weeks to become a familiar fixture in New York, as she did over 15 months. He established a residence, though with so little time that he was forced to rent, rather than buy, a home on Long Island and a hotel suite in Manhattan. He had begun so late that he could not change his registration from Massachusetts to New York, and so could not vote for himself.</p>
        <p>Kennedy confronted the carpetbagger issue directly when he accepted the party's nomination, much the way Mrs. Clinton did in formally announcing her candidacy. ''For every citizen who is a New Yorker by birth, there is one who is a New Yorker by choice, or whose parents were,'' Kennedy said at the nominating convention. ''I am in the second category, but so was Thomas E. Dewey.''</p>
        <p>But Kennedy had one critical advantage over Mrs. Clinton: he had spent many of his first 20 years growing up in New York: in Riverdale, a Bronx neighborhood, and in Bronxville, in Westchester County. One early campaign stop was a visit to what had been the family home in Riverdale, with a young John F. Kennedy Jr. at his side.</p>
        <p>Both he and Mrs. Clinton faced other difficulties as newcomers in New York. Kennedy, like Mrs. Clinton, was frustrated by his difficulty capturing support from Jewish voters. That was a major reason, a Kennedy adviser said, that Mr. Straus, who is Jewish, was made campaign chairman, a highly visible job.</p>
        <p>Keating attacked Kennedy for not having a voting record, using some of the same language Mr. Lazio has used to try to discredit Mrs. Clinton's credentials. Kennedy responded by rummaging through his years at the Justice Department for accomplishments to cite, much the way Mrs. Clinton has engaged in a reclamation project from her years as first lady, although without the advantage of having Cabinet experience.</p>
        <p>Both candidates tried to undermine their opponents in nearly identical ways: Mrs. Clinton by tying Mr. Lazio to the conservative Republican policies of former House Speaker Newt Gingrich, Kennedy by linking Keating to the conservative policies of the Republican presidential candidate, Barry M. Goldwater, though Keating never endorsed Goldwater.</p>
        <p>And Kennedy, like Mrs. Clinton today, was a celebrity as much as he was a candidate, attracting swarms of New Yorkers -- though, Kennedy's aides would later acknowledge, not necessarily voters -- wherever he went.</p>
        <p>Upstate, people turned out in the middle of the night, some wearing pajamas, for a glimpse of Kennedy.  At the nominating convention, ''we had press tables perpendicular to the stage, and we're writing our stories and fans start jumping on the stage, running along this long table where all the press was, to get to him,'' recalled Milton Hoffman, a veteran New York political journalist and columnist who is a member of the editorial board at The Journal News in White Plains. Mr. Hoffman compared the scene to the night Judy Garland performed at the Westchester County Center.</p>
        <p>Through it all, Kennedy evoked the memory of what had happened the year before in Dallas. ''He looks and sounds just enough like his murdered brother to send a ghostly flutter through the New York crowds,'' James Reston wrote in The Times.  ''When he rode through the bustling traffic of Manhattan today, people stopped on the sidewalks as if they had suddenly seen an apparition.''</p>
        <p>Still, perhaps the most striking -- and the most curious -- similarity is the deep hostility stirred by both candidates, particularly among some voters who would presumably be their obvious supporters. Robert Kennedy Jr. struggled at length with that question in a telephone conversation, suggesting that Mrs. Clinton's difficulties in this race raised unresolved questions for him about the animosity his father had found in so many parts of New York.</p>
        <p>''The accusations against him are the same kind of accusations about Hillary: that he was opportunistic, a carpetbagger, that he is only running because he wants to run for president,'' Mr. Kennedy said. ''The intensity of feeling with my father's race, and the almost inexplicable intensity of feeling toward Hillary Clinton. People who ought to like Hillary Clinton, but don't, and can't really explain why, but just kind of have a visceral reaction to her -- that's the same kind of thing that I remember from my father.</p>
        <p>''People who should have liked him, but didn't. I remember reading The Village Voice when I was a kid and being horrified. The cartoons and that kind of stuff, and how vicious the attacks were.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy sighed. ''You explain it to me,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
