<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bookend; Drinking Gin With the Dead</title>
    <meta content="10BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Thorne (1892-1934)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Veale, Scott</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Topper (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Topper Takes a Trip (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Night of the Gods, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DF1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bookend; Drinking Gin With the Dead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Scott Veale</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Veale, Scott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Veale Bookend column recalls with fondness novels of Jazz Age humorist Thorne Smith, in light of Modern Library reprintings; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When do popular writers officially qualify as forgotten? It can't simply be when their books fall out of print, since plenty of authors exist in a kind of literary limbo, with their works slipping in and out of circulation depending on the whims of a fickle publishing industry. Perhaps the best gauge of forgottenness these days is the World Wide Web, where even the most arcane interests flourish among cells of true believers, and (thanks to Amazon.com) sweaty-palmed authors can track their daily ups and downs with the click of a mouse. It's fair to assume that if a writer's tree falls on the Internet and no one hears it crash, his existence has become an open question.</p>
        <p>Such is the case with Thorne Smith (1892-1934), the Jazz Age humorist whose fame is as evanescent as the sybaritic ghosts played by Cary Grant and Constance Bennett in the 1937 film version of his most famous book, ''Topper.'' Smith's works exist today as ancient dogeared paperbacks or as fond but fuzzy memories among those who grew up in America's postwar flush. A Web search turns up thousands of hits for the bodacious Courtney Thorne-Smith of ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Melrose Place'' but a mere handful for the nonbodacious writer -- and most of those thanks to the Modern Library, which recently restored to print three of his dozen or so novels: ''Topper'' (1926), ''Topper Takes a Trip'' (1932) and ''The Night Life of the Gods'' (1931).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When do popular writers officially qualify as forgotten? It can't simply be when their books fall out of print, since plenty of authors exist in a kind of literary limbo, with their works slipping in and out of circulation depending on the whims of a fickle publishing industry. Perhaps the best gauge of forgottenness these days is the World Wide Web, where even the most arcane interests flourish among cells of true believers, and (thanks to Amazon.com) sweaty-palmed authors can track their daily ups and downs with the click of a mouse. It's fair to assume that if a writer's tree falls on the Internet and no one hears it crash, his existence has become an open question.</p>
        <p>Such is the case with Thorne Smith (1892-1934), the Jazz Age humorist whose fame is as evanescent as the sybaritic ghosts played by Cary Grant and Constance Bennett in the 1937 film version of his most famous book, ''Topper.'' Smith's works exist today as ancient dogeared paperbacks or as fond but fuzzy memories among those who grew up in America's postwar flush. A Web search turns up thousands of hits for the bodacious Courtney Thorne-Smith of ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Melrose Place'' but a mere handful for the nonbodacious writer -- and most of those thanks to the Modern Library, which recently restored to print three of his dozen or so novels: ''Topper'' (1926), ''Topper Takes a Trip'' (1932) and ''The Night Life of the Gods'' (1931).</p>
        <p>Smith was overshadowed by higher-wattage comic writers of the time, like S. J. Perelman and James Thurber, but reading his whimsical, nearly plotless tales of human entanglements with blithe spirits cavorting in the material world, one suspects he may not have entertained terribly lofty ambitions anyway. Above all, he was an impassioned proselytizer for la dolce vita and a hearty champion of demon alcohol who uncorked his frothy fiction during the long, parched years of Prohibition. His books are steeped in unabashed hedonism and frivolity, and he was intoxicated with non sequiturs and aimless repartee.</p>
        <p>While there may not be much angst in the pages of Smith's novels, there are more than a few tortured souls -- like Cosmo Topper himself, a mild-mannered bank manager (played by Roland Young in the movie and Leo G. Carroll in the 1950's television sitcom) chained to a humdrum suburban life of rush-hour traffic and lamb dinners with his dyspeptic wife and taciturn cat, Scollops. But that tranquil existence is shattered when, acting on a dimly understood impulse, he buys a car haunted by the ghosts of its former owners, the sophisticated if hard-living George and Marion Kerby, who died after crashing into a tree. Before long, these ''low-plane spirits'' (who can materialize more or less at will) manage to rustle up some hooch and addle their reluctant new friend. The group is soon tooling about the countryside, invading roadhouses, drugstores and hotels, playing pranks on the locals and the constabulary and hooking up with another astral couple, the remarkably debauched Colonel and Mrs. Hart, and their dog, Oscar, whose corporeal presence is limited to his hind legs and tail. Cosmo's alarm at the rowdy shenanigans gradually disappears in the face of his growing infatuation with the beautiful, sharp-tongued Marion, with whom he takes an extended vacation. The rest of ''Topper'' is basically caught up with their mildly risque (but chastely portrayed) romance and the crew's misadventures.</p>
        <p>If the spectral goings-on seem a bit strained at times, the little pleasures more than compensate -- the Nick-and-Nora bantering, the sly but good-natured sniping at middle-class conformity, the featherlight narrative touch, the conjuring of a distant time when ''gay'' meant ''carefree'' and men wore hats and took walking sticks to the office.</p>
        <p>''Topper'' was an immediate hit for Smith, who was apparently a bit of a bon vivant himself. A Maryland native, he had previously written a popular series of comic stories for the service paper Broadside while in the Navy during World War I. He followed ''Topper'' with several more brittle fantasies about hidebound humans who learn to live with gusto thanks to the intervention of supernatural forces. The Cosmo who resurfaces in ''Topper Takes a Trip'' is truly a haunted man, having departed Glendale, U.S.A., with his wife and cat for the French Riviera. His drinking buddies, whose thinning ectoplasm had caused them to bid adieu at the end of the previous book, reappear with a vengeance. ''These spirits had evidently descended to even a lower plane,'' Cosmo moans. ''They were coarser than he had ever known them, and less restrained.'' This time Topper does not even try to resist their corrupting influence; early on he wanders the streets avoiding eye contact and informing everyone who gawks at the whirlwind of otherworldly activity around him, ''I neither speak nor understand French.''</p>
        <p>The boozing commences (at an ungodly early hour) and the party animals spend pages and pages terrorizing shopkeepers, beachgoers and casino frequenters by yanking off hats and clothes, stealing money and pilfering food and drink. Eventually Topper resumes his affair with his invisible paramour, whose jealous husband ''is forever insisting that death did not them part,'' but the book closes with Topper's bittersweet realization that ''a person can't live peacefully on one plane and associate with the denizens of another.''</p>
        <p>Smith's effervescent style and ribald japing (many ripostes have at least two entendres) are on ample display, and as usual he's in no hurry to get to the point, stopping abruptly, for example, to extol the virtues of the American breakfast or to grumble about the need for personal hygiene (to bathe ''is to admit that one is not all that one should be,'' Topper ponders at one point. ''And that is not at all a fragrant admission''). There's a particularly nutty scene, involving a dogless tail causing a near riot in a bar, in which Smith turns his gaze to a boorish patron: ''Mr. Harold Gay, in spite of his comfortable size, was not a comfortable companion. He had a penchant for bringing up subjects which neither he himself nor anyone else knew anything about. And yet these subjects were of such a disturbing nature that they demanded some sort of definite settlement -- even an erroneous one -- before anyone could return to that comfortable state of mental torpor which is germane to man.''</p>
        <p>That, in a martini shaker, is a Thorne Smith moment.</p>
        <p>Hunter Hawk, the hero of ''The Night Life of the Gods,'' is also at the mercy of forces he can't control, in this case a comely 900-year-old female leprechaun he encounters late one night in the woods. Hawk, a wealthy bachelor inventor who lives with his irritating relatives in New England, has discovered how to transform the living into stone, but Megaera can trump his sorcery: she can bring statues to life.</p>
        <p>After much carousing and mayhem in the countryside, the pair move their feast to New York. Fueled by flasks of whiskey, they wind up in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where they stay past closing time in a quest for drinking companions: ''We would like a small, congenial group,'' Hawk says. ''Not too large to handle.''</p>
        <p>Fat chance. Soon enough, Hawk and Meg have liberated Mercury, followed by Bacchus, Neptune, Apollo, Diana, Perseus, Hebe and the armless Venus. The joke is that the gods are really overgrown children: guileless, bickering and relentless in pursuit of their appetites. After a madcap search for clothes (there's lots of silliness about ladies' slip-ons in all these books, a kind of mild fetish that must have raised eyebrows way back when), the band embarks on a prowl through Prohibition-era Manhattan, swilling highballs and getting into all kinds of trouble with saloonkeepers, the police and hotel employees. Venus and Diana are forever sniping, Perseus insists on toting around Medusa's snaky head despite the pleas of his comrades (he even gets the tart-tongued noggin drunk), Venus manages to acquire a pair of plaster of Paris arms, Mercury steals everything in sight, Neptune starts a fish-hurling riot in a waterfront market and later takes to poking swimmers with his trident from the bottom of a hotel pool -- you get the idea.</p>
        <p>Smith died of a heart attack in 1934 while vacationing with his wife and two young daughters in Florida. An unfinished novel, ''The Passionate Witch,'' was published seven years later and inspired the Veronica Lake-Fredric March movie ''I Married a Witch'' and later the hit television series ''Bewitched.''</p>
        <p>It may be that the insouciant pleasures of Smith's fiction verge on the sinfully quaint in this irony-drenched postmodern era. But one suspects that more than a few readers would find his mischievous spirits and hapless humans awfully good company. Here's to you, Thorne. Bottoms up.</p>
        <p>Scott Veale, an editor at the Week in Review of The Times, writes the New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks column for the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Scott Veale, an editor at the Week in Review of The Times, writes the New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks column for the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
