<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime</title>
    <meta content="10CRIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Francis, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdermid, Val</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harstad, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoag, Tami</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henderson, Lauren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stasio, Marilyn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shattered (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Place of Execution, A (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Thaw, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dust to Dust (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Strawberry Tattoo (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DF1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stasio, Marilyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marilyn Stasio reviews books Shattered by Dick Francis, A Place of Execution by Val McDermid, The Big Thaw by Donald Harstad, Dust to Dust by Tami Hoag and Strawberry Tattoo by Lauren Henderson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The youthful spring in Dick Francis' literary step has a lot to do with his relish for depicting physical punishment. You can almost see the gleam in his 80-year-old eye as he dispatches four thugs, led by an Amazonian sadist named Rose, to break the wrists of a young glass blower who runs afoul of a rough racetrack crowd in SHATTERED (Putnam, $25.95). As the latest in a long line of decent and honorable (and virtually indistinguishable) heroes who achieve their moral majority by standing up to bullies, Gerard Logan eludes the wrist snappers, but only because Francis has more tortuous tests in store for him.</p>
        <p>How did a sensitive guy like Logan, whose creative impulses express themselves in delicate glass objects like winged birds and sailing ships, get mixed up with such nasty people in the first place? It was just his misfortune to have been entrusted with the videotape of a valuable medical secret by his best friend, a jockey who dies in a dreadful racing accident at Cheltenham. Not having the slightest clue as to the contents of the tape, which is stolen before he can blink, Logan enlists the aid of some brave and burly friends to trace the tape and dump some manure on the prickly Rose. Francis' formula is made for excitement, not subtlety, so the eerie serenity of the glass blower's studio provides a nice breather from the choreographed displays of bruising action that keep the author on his toes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The youthful spring in Dick Francis' literary step has a lot to do with his relish for depicting physical punishment. You can almost see the gleam in his 80-year-old eye as he dispatches four thugs, led by an Amazonian sadist named Rose, to break the wrists of a young glass blower who runs afoul of a rough racetrack crowd in SHATTERED (Putnam, $25.95). As the latest in a long line of decent and honorable (and virtually indistinguishable) heroes who achieve their moral majority by standing up to bullies, Gerard Logan eludes the wrist snappers, but only because Francis has more tortuous tests in store for him.</p>
        <p>How did a sensitive guy like Logan, whose creative impulses express themselves in delicate glass objects like winged birds and sailing ships, get mixed up with such nasty people in the first place? It was just his misfortune to have been entrusted with the videotape of a valuable medical secret by his best friend, a jockey who dies in a dreadful racing accident at Cheltenham. Not having the slightest clue as to the contents of the tape, which is stolen before he can blink, Logan enlists the aid of some brave and burly friends to trace the tape and dump some manure on the prickly Rose. Francis' formula is made for excitement, not subtlety, so the eerie serenity of the glass blower's studio provides a nice breather from the choreographed displays of bruising action that keep the author on his toes.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the ''very disciplined form'' of the murder mystery, whose formulaic rituals put her in mind of ''a modern morality play,'' P. D. James once said, ''These rather strict conventions liberate my creative imagination.'' Val McDermid's elegiac study of a heinous crime and its aftermath, A PLACE OF EXECUTION (St. Martin's Minotaur, $24.95), is very much in the Jamesian mode, both in its inventive use of the devices of detection and its mournful view of murder as a moral reckoning.</p>
        <p>When a 13-year-old English schoolgirl goes missing from her Derbyshire village in the winter of 1963, George Bennett, the police inspector in charge of the case, quickly realizes that the secrets of the child's life and possible death are locked in the collective mind of Scardale, an isolated hamlet of inbred families united by their common surnames and their hostility to strangers. Through Bennett's exhaustive efforts, the likely villain is caught and hanged -- or so it seems, until the story reaches 35 years into the future for its chilling resolution. At this point, McDermid tosses convention aside and gets to the heart of the issues that really concern her: the feudal mentality of insular societies like Scardale, tribal definitions of guilt and punishment, and the expiation of sin through the almost priestly functions of a conscience-driven hero.</p>
        <p>It's a cold, starry night in deep winter when Donald Harstad opens THE BIG THAW (Doubleday, $23.95) with a thrilling car chase through the snow-crusted backroads of Nation County, Iowa. At minus 44 degrees, it's so cold you could toss a cup of hot water into the air and hear it shatter into ice crystals. So cold that two enterprising burglars who have been raiding the houses of rich farmers off sunning themselves in Florida could freeze into solid blocks -- after being shot to death with a rare-caliber Soviet military handgun.</p>
        <p>Carl Houseman, the plain-spoken sheriff's deputy who narrates this, the third in a series with an irresistible blend of no-nonsense cop wisdom and dry heartland humor, does an outstanding job taking us through the lively moves of this case. Although Houseman lays on the good-old-boy folksiness with a spreader, he's a stickler for the details of rural police work (just watch him secure a crime scene in subzero weather) and his ''great leaps of intuition'' are actually solid feats of deduction (just watch him analyze the behavior of an abused wife).</p>
        <p>Harstad, a 26-year veteran of a county sheriff's department in Iowa, has a canny way of using his home-grown knowledge of citizen militia groups and Mississippi riverboat casinos to make us swallow the more fanciful elements of his well-imagined but well-grounded plot.</p>
        <p>Tami Hoag must have raided a recycling station for the stock characters and familiar plot elements of her first police procedural, DUST TO DUST (Bantam, $25.95). Michael Fallon was a legend on the Minneapolis police force until he was shot down and became a broken-down drunk in a wheelchair. Having disowned one son for being homosexual and dismissed the other for being a loser, Fallon blows his brains out when his gay son, an Internal Affairs cop, commits suicide. Although the Fallon affair is an embarrassment to the big brass, it raises the suspicions of two homicide detectives, Sam Kovac and Nikki Liska, as cliched a pair as you're likely to find in a stack of remaindered paperbacks. With her ''maniacal pixie look,'' his broodiness (''I'm not morose, I'm bitter'') and the mannered dialogue that is supposed to pass for their station-house banter, these two are the real criminals.</p>
        <p>I sympathize with amateur sleuths. I really do. Lacking the resources of the law, they can't haul suspects down to the cop shop or play with the high-tech gadgets in the crime lab. Without a private eye's license and retainer, it's awkward for them to buy information or beat it out of their informants. When amateurs snoop around a murder they have to be very clever -- or very cute. Sam Jones, the sexually adventurous young avant-garde British sculptor who is the heroine of Lauren Henderson's saucy whodunits, usually manages to be a bit of both. But Sam isn't quite herself in STRAWBERRY TATTOO (Crown, paper, $12.95), which finds her in New York for a group show at a trendy SoHo gallery. Although she isn't cowed by the art vandalism and murder she encounters, she is so awed by the downtown crowd that she loses her edge. Oh, there are still flashes of the exuberant dominatrix who stomped her boot heels in ''Black Rubber Dress'' and ''Freeze My Margarita,'' but Sam is too busy making friends to put any real kick into this case.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
