<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia's Troubled Schools Reopen as a Showdown With Teachers Nears</title>
    <meta content="10TEAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/education/10TEAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Federation of Teachers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFD71139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia's Troubled Schools Reopen as a Showdown With Teachers Nears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelpha's troubled schools reopen as teachers union authorizes strike in face of powferul new bargaining-table coalition of state and city political leaders determined to overhaul system; 21-member Philadelphia Federation of Teachers is fighting demands for contract concessions, including introduction of pay-for-performance teacher rating similar to that increasingly invoked by politicians nationwide to improve schools; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This city's deeply troubled public schools reopened near cliff's edge this week as the teachers union authorized a strike in the face of a powerful new bargaining-table coalition of state and city political leaders determined to overhaul the system.</p>
        <p>The 21,000-member union is fighting demands for contract concessions, including the introduction of a pay-for-performance teacher rating like those increasingly being invoked by politicians across the nation to improve schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This city's deeply troubled public schools reopened near cliff's edge this week as the teachers union authorized a strike in the face of a powerful new bargaining-table coalition of state and city political leaders determined to overhaul the system.</p>
        <p>The 21,000-member union is fighting demands for contract concessions, including the introduction of a pay-for-performance teacher rating like those increasingly being invoked by politicians across the nation to improve schools.</p>
        <p>For the first time, the School District of Philadelphia, acting under crisis-driven changes in city and state law, is negotiating with the explicit backing of Mayor John F. Street and Gov. Tom Ridge. In the past, ranking elected officials played a sideline role.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly a big stick,'' said David L. Cohen, a chief strategist of the city-state bargaining initiative, referring to a new state law, Act 46, designed to shake up the balance of power of traditional contract bargaining in the 210,000-student system.</p>
        <p>With the contract deadline past, an emergency court order has kept the parties bargaining, but only on a day-to-day basis as the city's anxieties mount. The order runs out on Monday night, with no certainty that it will be extended as the union argues that Act 46 violates the state constitution.</p>
        <p>The act, designed to narrow the union's bargaining room, prohibits the temporary extension of the old teacher contract provisions and benefits. It empowers the governor to take over the city system if necessary to keep the schools open and to pursue reforms in the event of a strike.</p>
        <p>The law was enacted by the state Legislature in 1998, after a school-aid fight with the city, in the name of improving plummeting reading and math scores here and in 10 smaller districts in the state.</p>
        <p>But the Philadelphia Federation of Teachers maintains that the act was passed by the Republican legislature without fair public debate to bust the power of the teachers union in this Democratic city. Other city union leaders have expressed support for the teachers, who last struck in 1981 for 51 days.</p>
        <p>''We're ready to strike; the picket signs are in the schools,'' said Ted Kirsch, the union president who heard thousands of members roar approval for a strike rather than surrender prerogatives of their old contract.</p>
        <p>''This is about survival of the union, sure, but also survival of public education in this city,'' Mr. Kirsch said in an interview. ''A state takeover could mean the charterizing of schools and the dismantling of the public system.''</p>
        <p>While fighting the Republican governor and Statehouse, the union must also confront Mayor Street, a Democrat who won City Hall last November after vowing to address the public's deep frustration with the school system. At that time, voters also approved a city charter change that gave the mayor far greater power over the schools by allowing him to appoint the nine-member school board in charge of the system.</p>
        <p>''If this goes down, Mayor Street takes the hit,'' Mr. Kirsch said of the political responsibility for a strike and potential state takeover.</p>
        <p>Beyond the as yet unspecified performance-pay innovation, the state, city and school district are also challenging current seniority protections by allowing principals and supervisors a stronger say in where teachers are assigned. The city also wants to increase the teachers' work day by 1 hour and 15 minutes, to 7 hours and 45 minutes, while adding five work days to the 190 in the school year.</p>
        <p>But the pay-for-performance proposal clearly upsets the union the most.</p>
        <p>''We could settle a contract a lot more easily if that wasn't on the table,'' said Jerry Jordan, the chief union negotiator. He noted that the performance idea, while increasingly popular among critics of public schools, is in only the experimental stage in a few places like Cincinnati, Milwaukee and Colorado, and so has no track record.</p>
        <p>''I will not make our teachers guinea pigs,'' Mr. Jordan said. He  noted that the old contract permitted principals to deny raises to teachers considered subpar.</p>
        <p>But district negotiators say the old contract had frozen too many dated teacher protections in place, to the city taxpayers' disadvantage.</p>
        <p>''This is all about a sea change,'' Mr. Cohen declared, maintaining that the goal was not to destroy the union but to bring the city in line with changes enacted by other urban systems over the past 15 years.</p>
        <p>In the unusual bargaining alliance between the governor and mayor, Mr. Ridge has emphasized that he is not eager to take over the city schools, but said he would do so under the mandate of the new law. At the same time, he expressed a willingness, if a satisfactory contract is negotiated, to seek help for the schools, which have an $80 million budget deficit.</p>
        <p>''We are collaborating more productively on education in Philadelphia than we ever have in the past,'' said Tim Reeves, Mr. Ridge's spokesman.</p>
        <p>Out in the district, students began classes on Thursday even as their teachers monitored contract talks that continued into the weekend.</p>
        <p>Outside Benjamin Franklin High School, Arlene Fields, a mother of a student and a nonunion consultant on parent involvement in school affairs, pointed to the building and said, ''Don't worry, they're still teaching and learning in there.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fields, a proud city native, said the heightened city and state involvement ''makes this year's contract talks a pretty potent mix,'' but a promising one, too. She praised Mayor Street for daring to get involved in the complex issue.</p>
        <p>''But everybody needs to give a little for this to work out for the kids,'' she said as a student politely volunteered to carry her briefcase into the busy school.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
