<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strike Ends at the Modern In a Spirit of Compromise</title>
    <meta content="10MOMA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/nyregion/10MOMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DB1E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strike Ends at the Modern In a Spirit of Compromise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Union representing 250 striking workers at Museum of Modern Art votes to end 134-day walkout after reaching agreement in which both sides made significant concessions; workers will get wage increase of more than 18 percent over five years; all new professional and administrative workers will be required to join union or pay dues; museum gained right to unilaterally impose changes in health coverage if it cannot reach agreement with union (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The union representing 250 striking workers at the Museum of Modern Art voted to end its 134-day walkout yesterday, just hours after reaching an agreement in which both sides made significant concessions.</p>
        <p>The museum's workers applauded the contract, which awards a wage increase of more than 18 percent over five years and promises to give jobs back to any union members who are furloughed when much of the museum is closed during a five-year, $650 million expansion and renovation. During the project, some employees will be assigned to a temporary museum to be set up in Long Island City, Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The union representing 250 striking workers at the Museum of Modern Art voted to end its 134-day walkout yesterday, just hours after reaching an agreement in which both sides made significant concessions.</p>
        <p>The museum's workers applauded the contract, which awards a wage increase of more than 18 percent over five years and promises to give jobs back to any union members who are furloughed when much of the museum is closed during a five-year, $650 million expansion and renovation. During the project, some employees will be assigned to a temporary museum to be set up in Long Island City, Queens.</p>
        <p>The museum also agreed to require all new professional and administrative workers to join the union or pay union dues, a change the union had sought in an effort to increase its strength.</p>
        <p>''I'm elated,'' said Michael Cinquina, a buyer for the museum's bookstore and a member of the negotiating team for the union. ''It's all that I hoped for. It made every day we stayed out worthwhile.''</p>
        <p>The union, Local 2110 of the United Automobile Workers, represents 250 archivists, assistant curators, librarians, bookshop workers and others at the museum.</p>
        <p>The agreement, reached at 3 a.m. yesterday after a 15-hour negotiating session, ends a bitter dispute in which half the workers crossed the picket line and the museum canceled numerous fund-raisers, concerts and screenings. Museum officials said the walkout did not hurt attendance.</p>
        <p>The museum's chief negotiator, Robert Batterman, said the agreement was very much a compromise. ''I think it's a fair settlement,'' he said. ''There were no winners.''</p>
        <p>He said the museum achieved its goal of greater flexibility in administering a health plan for management employees and union members. He said the museum gained the right to unilaterally impose changes in health coverage if it cannot reach agreement with the union on proposed changes. One caveat is that any changes made to union members' coverage would also apply to management employees.</p>
        <p>Union officials also claimed a victory in health coverage, saying that management had altered its stance and acknowledged the union's right to bargain collectively about changes in the plan.</p>
        <p>The union leaders said they pressured the museum into showing more flexibility at the bargaining table by enlisting the support of 150 prominent artists, and by lining up City Council members to delay, and perhaps block, a zoning variance the museum was seeking for its expansion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman contended that the union had been hurt by the decision of many construction unions to allow their members to do demolition work for the museum's expansion despite the picket line.</p>
        <p>Phil Wheeler, the director of the United Auto Workers in New York, said some strikers grew dispirited when workers crossed the picket line, but were buoyed by support from other unions.</p>
        <p>The president of Local 2110, Maida Rosenstein, said, ''I don't think the museum anticipated that this group would stay out and be as steadfast as they were.''</p>
        <p>She said the museum was eager to settle the strike this month because several new exhibits were opening and it would be harder to mount them without all the workers.</p>
        <p>The negotiating session, which began at noon on Friday, was the first face-to-face meeting of the two sides since the strike began on April 28.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman said the museum was so frustrated by the deadlocked talks that he took an unusual step: he asked a union official to mediate, an idea welcomed by museum workers.</p>
        <p>That official, Bruce Raynor, secretary-treasurer of the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, worked with federal mediators on Friday to settle the dispute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman denied that the museum was affected by a letter in which 150 prominent artists, including Robert Rauschenberg and Steven Spielberg, voiced support for the strikers. He also insisted that the museum was not worried that the City Council would block the zoning variance.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the museum's union, working with the New York City Central Labor Council and the New York State A.F.L.-C.I.O., had gotten a majority of the City Council's Manhattan members to hold off on recommending the variance. Typically, the full City Council does not grant variances unless the members from the affected borough recommend it.</p>
        <p>In the last proposal before the strike, the museum offered a 3 percent raise for each of three years. The union sought a 5 percent raise for the first year, and a 4 percent raise for each of the next four years.</p>
        <p>The new agreement calls for a 3 percent raise in the first year, and 4 percent, or $1,100, in the second year, whichever is greater. In the third, fourth and fifth years, there will be a 3.5 percent wage increase. Workers' salaries range from $17,000 to more than $50,000.</p>
        <p>The agreement could run for longer than five years if the expansion project takes longer than that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
