<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ski Resorts Pledge To Protect Natural Areas</title>
    <meta content="10REP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Ski Areas Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ski Resorts Pledge To Protect Natural Areas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Ski Areas Assn opens campaign called Sustainable Slopes, aimed at protecting natural areas; critics say standards are vague and do not go far enough to shield wild areas from damage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the nation's biggest ski resorts, trail maps this season will be emblazoned with a proclamation of environmental good will. ''Sustainable Slopes,'' the new program, is the product of a ski industry association campaign to quiet critics and to reassure visitors that its members are committed to protecting natural areas.</p>
        <p>At least 165 ski resorts around the country, including the 20 largest, will be entitled to display the logo, having signed off in June on a set of standards drafted by the association with help from government agencies and some environmental groups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the nation's biggest ski resorts, trail maps this season will be emblazoned with a proclamation of environmental good will. ''Sustainable Slopes,'' the new program, is the product of a ski industry association campaign to quiet critics and to reassure visitors that its members are committed to protecting natural areas.</p>
        <p>At least 165 ski resorts around the country, including the 20 largest, will be entitled to display the logo, having signed off in June on a set of standards drafted by the association with help from government agencies and some environmental groups.</p>
        <p>But the standards are often vague, leading many critics to complain that they do not go far enough to shield forests, rivers and other wild areas from the damage that ski areas can cause.</p>
        <p>The charter calls for voluntary commitment to follow ''best practices'' in several areas, including ''to use the natural surroundings as a means to increase environmental awareness'' and ''to conserve natural resources'' in dealing with water, energy, waste management, fish and wildlife, forests and wetlands. It also calls on signatories ''to engage surrounding communities and interest groups in a dialogue on development plans.''</p>
        <p>The effort has already kindled debate between an industry trying to show itself as ecologically sensitive and skeptical activists who have now vowed to develop a rating system of their own in order to grade ski areas on their environmental conduct.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, we feel that this so-called charter is being used as a public relations ploy rather than a genuine attempt to improve their environmental performance,'' said Jeff Berman, executive director of Colorado Wild of Durango, Colo., one of the organizations trying to develop the report card by the time the ski season begins.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups and the ski industry have long been at odds, wrangling in the courts and other arenas over issues like the development of ski areas in the national forests and the tapping of mountain streams for snowmaking.</p>
        <p>One of the angriest battles, over the proposed expansion at Vail Mountain in Colorado, was fought through the mid 1990's. After a federal court upheld the development plan, arsonists destroyed a mountaintop restaurant and four ski lifts at Vail in October 1998, causing $12 million in damage.</p>
        <p>The attack was condemned by mainstream environmental groups, but an organization calling itself the Earth Liberation Front took responsibility, saying it was protesting destruction of habitat for the lynx.</p>
        <p>In drafting the new charter, the industry group, the National Ski Areas Association, has not tried to hide its determination to put forth a greener image.</p>
        <p>The resorts that make up the ski industry ''are operated or owned by individuals who have a strong environmental ethic,'' Geraldine Hughes, the group's director of public policy, said in a telephone interview from Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>Among other things, the document, issued as a 22-page book on recycled paper, calls for voluntary commitment to protecting nature through more efficient use of energy, safer waste disposal and water conservation. Ms. Hughes said the association would issue a report next spring assessing progress toward meeting those goals.</p>
        <p>The signatories include virtually every major ski resort, including Vail, Aspen, Park City, Jackson Hole and Sugarloaf, with the total number accounting for about 70 percent of skier visits. Half the group's 330 members have not yet agreed to the plan, but Ms. Hughes said most of these were small operators with limited resources.</p>
        <p>Among 12 outside organizations that have endorsed the plan as partners (including the Environmental Protection Agency and the Forest Service), two were environmental groups: Leave No Trace, of Boulder, and the Conservation Law Foundation of New England, which has filed numerous lawsuits against ski resorts in the past.</p>
        <p>In a June announcement, Mark Sinclair,  vice president of the Conservation Law Foundation, said he believed that the charter would ''allow resort owners and environmental groups to work more closely together to improve the sustainability of the ski industry.''</p>
        <p>But many other environmental groups chose not to endorse the plan, including Trout Unlimited, which objected to the absence of a clear commitment to protect fish habitats from increasingly extensive snowmaking operations.</p>
        <p>''When I grew up, skiing started at Christmas or, if you were lucky, at Thanksgiving,'' said Melinda Kassen, a Colorado-based expert for the organization. ''With snowmaking, ski areas open in mid-  to late-October, the low-flow season for the streams and creeks, and so that means they're sucking water when the fish are most vulnerable.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes, the ski industry official, said the resort operators had been careful not to promise too much.</p>
        <p>''We do create great recreation opportunities,'' Ms. Hughes said. ''But with those opportunities come impacts, and we're not going to agree to something we cannot do.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
