<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blood Money</title>
    <meta content="10IGNA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ignatieff, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barkan, Elazar</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Guilt of Nations, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DF1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blood Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Ignatieff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ignatieff, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Ignatieff reviews book The Guilt of Nations: Restitution and Negotiating Historical Injustices by Elazar Barkan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Guilt of Nations</p>
        <p>Restitution and Negotiating</p>
        <p>Historical Injustices.</p>
        <p>By Elazar Barkan.</p>
        <p>418 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Guilt of Nations</p>
        <p>Restitution and Negotiating</p>
        <p>Historical Injustices.</p>
        <p>By Elazar Barkan.</p>
        <p>418 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton. $29.95.</p>
        <p>A troubling question for any society, but especially a capitalist one, is what money can and cannot buy. We are all supposed to know that money can buy you sex but not love, power but not respect and flattery but not self-esteem. Even in capitalist societies -- which are supposed to know the price of everything and the value of nothing -- it turns out that the most important things in life are still understood as goods that cannot be bought and sold without reducing their value to zero.</p>
        <p>If this is true, then what are we to think when a community or an individual has lost honor, dignity and respect as a result of some crime or injustice, and the offending community or individual offers money by way of restitution? If honor and dignity cannot be bought and sold, can their loss be compensated with money? At first sight, most people would answer no. And more than no. If you were a victim you would think: they have persecuted, abused and dispossessed me. Now they offer me money. Who do they think I am? And who do they think they are?</p>
        <p>Financial restitution runs up against the idea that honor and dignity are beyond price and that once they are taken away, they cannot be restored by mere money. But if such things have no price, it is hard to undo the harm done when they are lost. The perpetrators can always say they are sorry, but that is too easy. They must be made to pay. So money becomes the sorry center of the whole restitution business.</p>
        <p>Despite the fact that it never fully satisfies either party, financial restitution has become a central ritual of atonement and expiation in modern societies. The resentful Swiss are paying for the way their banks stored Nazi gold and robbed concentration camp victims of their deposits. The survivors and their families feel the money is too little, too late. The Japanese have offered limited restitution to the Korean women who were forced to work as prostitutes for Japanese soldiers, and the Korean women have to decide whether accepting the money makes them feel better or worse. The Australian, Canadian and New Zealand governments have negotiated restitution with their indigenous peoples, only to discover that these agreements seem only to breed further claims. At the center of all these restitution cases -- surveyed by Elazar Barkan in his well-researched and discriminating study, ''The Guilt of Nations'' -- is an enduring uneasiness on both sides about the very nature of the transaction.</p>
        <p>Each side wants very different things. Perpetrators want the money to buy closure -- an end to claims and recriminations -- while victims want recognition and acknowledgment of their sufferings. One side wants the money to wash away the stain. The other side wants the stain to remain forever.</p>
        <p>Now that reparations, especially to Holocaust victims or their families, have become an industry involving lawyers and State Department officials, the possibility that there is no adequate restitution for certain crimes has been quietly forgotten. Barkan reminds us that after World War II, many survivors wanted to spurn restitution altogether. In January 1952, when Nahum Goldman of the World Jewish Congress and Konrad Adenauer of West Germany negotiated their restitution agreement, protesters outside the Israeli Parliament denounced compensation as blood money. To this day, many Holocaust survivors continue to feel that accepting restitution is a betrayal of the dead.</p>
        <p>This position of dignified refusal has had virtue on its side, but there were other survivors who believed that such virtue lacked moral realism. Restitution committed West Germany to a new identity, while enabling the new Israeli state to settle a tide of new immigrants, including many Holocaust survivors. The moral character of the transaction may have been questionable, but the consequences have been good for both sides.</p>
        <p>It is Barkan's argument that for all their ambiguities, restitution agreements validate victims and perpetrators alike. Perpetrators atone for guilt and hope to emerge cleansed, while victims acquire the power that comes when victimhood is recognized and given the legitimacy of financial compensation. Native Americans -- who have seen their ancestral bones shipped off to the Smithsonian as specimens for study, who have watched their sacred sites stripped by mining and petroleum companies, who have been cheated by 19th-century treaties -- are now using class-action suits and restitution claims to rebuild tribal identities.</p>
        <p>But, as Barkan also points out, restitution is no panacea. It is one thing to return aboriginal bones and sacred relics from museums, and quite another to overturn the economic and social disadvantage of aboriginal peoples as a whole. There is a risk that restitution may become a substitute for social reform. The other problem is that restitution tends to perpetuate victim identities. It is right and proper, for example, to compensate Japanese-Americans for their internment during World War II, but it is not necessarily a good thing if new generations, born long since, continue to define their relation to American society in terms of that trauma.</p>
        <p>Moreover, once one group secures restitution, others follow suit. If the Japanese-Americans can be compensated for internment, why shouldn't African-Americans be compensated for slavery? Here the injustice is both so large and so distant in time that the mechanics of compensation become nearly impossible. As some black activists set the restitution claim for slavery at $1.6 trillion, it becomes obvious that restitution is both an unwise and an impractical substitute for basic social justice. Moreover, many African-Americans resent being type-cast as victims of an institution abolished more than a century ago.</p>
        <p>Yet the past, however painful, must be faced, and wrongs must be paid for. And societies that do so -- and pay the price -- are healthier and more decent places for doing so. Victims who have received the formal recognition and acknowledgment provided by restitution can look themselves in the mirror. And the money can do good things, as anyone can see when aboriginal land claims are settled and provide native communities with the capacity to look after themselves. As Barkan suggests, restitution works best when everybody understands what money can and cannot buy. Money's alchemy is much more limited than its power over our lives leads us to suppose. Financial restitution can serve to acknowledge and recognize suffering. What it cannot buy is either forgiving or forgetting.</p>
        <p>Michael Ignatieff's most recent book is ''Virtual War: Kosovo and Beyond.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Ignatieff's most recent book is ''Virtual War: Kosovo and Beyond.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
