<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bulbs Here, Bulbs There, Bulbs Everywhere</title>
    <meta content="CNGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DA1139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bulbs Here, Bulbs There, Bulbs Everywhere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRADITION has it that the sight of the first robin means that spring is on its way. Yet so many of these friendly birds stay around all through the  winter months, they have lost their springtime significance.</p>
        <p>More reliable for me are the first bulb blooms. My harbinger is winter aconite (Eranthis). These delightful buttercups that appear in the the earliest spring grow from tiny bulbs. The blooms are so tiny, they are easily missed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRADITION has it that the sight of the first robin means that spring is on its way. Yet so many of these friendly birds stay around all through the  winter months, they have lost their springtime significance.</p>
        <p>More reliable for me are the first bulb blooms. My harbinger is winter aconite (Eranthis). These delightful buttercups that appear in the the earliest spring grow from tiny bulbs. The blooms are so tiny, they are easily missed.</p>
        <p>The secret to planting these bulbs is to plant plenty of them, not just 5 or 10 bulbs, but 50 or even 100. They will surely make a show. These dainty yellow buttercups sit on a ruff collar of green foliage. They always make me think of historical pictures I've seen of the first Queen Elizabeth who always wore a high ruff collar.</p>
        <p>Another early sign of the new season is the charming snowdrop.</p>
        <p>It blooms almost at the same time as the winter aconite and the two can be set near each other.</p>
        <p>One thing rather amazing about snowdrops (Galanthus): bulbs can be transplanted when they are in full bloom. It is easy to see where they are, of course, and as with most of these little bulbs, the snowdrops multiply quite generously and bare places in the early spring garden can be spiced up with these blooms.</p>
        <p>There is a larger and later bulb, the snowflake, that blooms about a month after the snowdrops. These snowflakes (Leucojum) are taller than the early snowdrops, but the blooms are quite similar. They are clean, white nodding bells that seem to last for several days. Be sure to take the time to turn these flowers upward to see the collar of green petals inside.</p>
        <p>Of all the so-called little bulbs, perhaps the most unusual is windflower. The blooms are handsome little daisies, so unlike the rest of the bulb clan. The daisies are in wonderful colors: blue, white and rose-pink. Mixtures of all these colors are available. These anemones must be planted in large numbers to make any kind of a statement. They are dramatic on a sloppy hillside that has well-drained soil and receives some of the early spring sun's rays.</p>
        <p>When planting anemones, here is a good trick. The bulbs are not really bulblike structures, the sort of onionlike forms that gardeners come to expect. Rather, they look more like small dark-brown twigs. I like to soak them for an hour or so before planting since they do dry out in storage. Be sure to plant them just under the surface of the soil, not too deeply or they won't appear the following year. Also, these anemones are excellent spreaders so choose a place where they can show off.</p>
        <p>If the wind flowers appeal (Anemone blanda), then there is another sort of anemone that might click. This one is the wood anemone (A. nemorosa). It. too, spreads. The blooms are upright. The foliage is particularly handsome and remains around for sometime as a decorative asset.</p>
        <p>One of the wood anemones that is particularly appealing is the one with lavender-blue flowers. The foliage even has a lavender-blue tinge. This particular favorite was introduced many years ago about 1870.  Another little bulb that deserves much more garden space is the pretty little bulb, Puschkinia that is sometimes called Siberian squill.</p>
        <p>The flowers are pale blue, a rare color in spring, with darker deep-blue lines down each petal. The display are short-lived, so I would suggest placing these bulbs where they are easily seen. For the longest time, I assumed this bulb was named for the famed Russian writer, Pushkin. But I have since learned that the bulb was named for Count Puschkin who collected unusual plants in the Caucasus. This one, too, is a spreader, especially if the flowers are allowed to set seed.</p>
        <p>No spring lawn would be complete without a few chionodoxa coming up for an early show. These glory of the snow come in two colors: dark blue or pink.</p>
        <p>There is also a white form, but it doesn't seem to have as much drama as the darker blue. These are also spreaders and thrive in lawns or rock gardens. Many gardeners like to toss the bulbs along the edges of woodlands and plant the tiny bulbs where they fall.</p>
        <p>Both Ipheion and Muscari have what I call foliage problems. Ipheion has been black-balled in my garden  because the foliage persists too long in the spring. It seems to smother  everything else nearby. Muscari foliage not only appears with the blooms in spring, but again in late summer.</p>
        <p>These are just a few of the little bulbs that deserve better use. The  bulb brokers, McClure &amp; Zimmerman, 108 West Winnebago Street, Friesland, Wis. 53935 offer an amazing selection of these unusual bulbs in a catalog.</p>
        <p>The company's Web site is www.mzbulb.com.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
