<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vintage Washington</title>
    <meta content="10WASHINT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFD91631F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vintage Washington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Timothy Egan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Timothy Egan describes trip through Washington state vineyards; photos; map (The Sophisticated Traveler, part 2 of 2-part section)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A two hours' drive east of Seattle, the land turns from green to beige, the coffee from cappuccino to cup of joe and a most curious sign appears, welcoming visitors to ''The Palm Springs of Washington.'' But I couldn't find any palm trees in the Yakima Valley, and certainly nothing approaching the ubiquity of golf courses and streets named for celebrities that define the Palm Springs of Southern California.</p>
        <p>Giant sprinklers spit irrigation water on orchards crowded with apple, peach, apricot and cherry trees. The glaciers of Mount Adams gleam in the midday sun, just a magpie flight from desert sage. And then, deeper into the valley, appears the first of what will become a signature sight: a vineyard sloping to the Yakima River. The valley is the gateway to Washington's wine country, bigger in size and production than that of any state but California, yet somewhat bashful, hard to find and as down-home as a county garlic festival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A two hours' drive east of Seattle, the land turns from green to beige, the coffee from cappuccino to cup of joe and a most curious sign appears, welcoming visitors to ''The Palm Springs of Washington.'' But I couldn't find any palm trees in the Yakima Valley, and certainly nothing approaching the ubiquity of golf courses and streets named for celebrities that define the Palm Springs of Southern California.</p>
        <p>Giant sprinklers spit irrigation water on orchards crowded with apple, peach, apricot and cherry trees. The glaciers of Mount Adams gleam in the midday sun, just a magpie flight from desert sage. And then, deeper into the valley, appears the first of what will become a signature sight: a vineyard sloping to the Yakima River. The valley is the gateway to Washington's wine country, bigger in size and production than that of any state but California, yet somewhat bashful, hard to find and as down-home as a county garlic festival.</p>
        <p>The wines that come from this arid land are no longer secrets, of course. When a private jet shows up at the tiny airport outside of Walla Walla these days, it is not because the owner is seeking the sweet onions for which the region has long been famous. More likely, he is trying to persuade Leonetti Cellar to give up a case of its coveted cabernet sauvignon or merlot. (Forget about it: there's a waiting list to get on the waiting list.)</p>
        <p>The red wines from Walla Walla have found themselves in the rarefied air of the better Bordeaux in ratings by wine publications over the last decade. The chardonnays and sauvignon blancs from other parts of the Columbia Valley are as crisp as the countryside at night. And in blind taste tests a handful of the local merlots, syrahs and cabernet sauvignons have even bested some of the premier red wines of California's Napa Valley. But there the resemblance to any other wine region ends.</p>
        <p>In the Napa Valley, the roads are full of limousines driving in and out of chateau-style wineries. Sunday afternoon is a traffic jam. In Washington, a lonely pickup or two and the stray S.U.V. from Seattle are the only vehicles likely to be seen. Tastings are free. And more often than not the person pouring the samples is the winemaker, or chief assistant, spouse, cousin or well-versed hanger-on.</p>
        <p>In this sense, a journey in search of vinicultural aesthetics in Washington is like touring the Umbrian countryside in Italy, or an out-of-the-way appellation in France. The wine pilgrim follows a distant path, knocks on a door and ends up sharing baby pictures with somebody whose hands are stained by grapes.</p>
        <p>And there are some bows to the castle-and-garden settings of European wineries: Columbia Crest's vast chateau on a hill above the Columbia River near the tiny town of Paterson could have been shipped from the Continent.</p>
        <p>Washington's wine country is unique to the American West. The grapes are tended by Latinos, Indians or Anglo farmhands whose fathers and grandfathers made beer, grew potatoes and certainly fished for the legendary Columbia River chinook salmon, now making something of a comeback. Roadside stands offer espresso, fresh fruit and fine wines.</p>
        <p>The ground bakes at temperatures above 100 degrees in the hottest days of summer, while just to the west are walls of high ice in the Cascade Mountains. This is new land for Vitis vinifera, and it is growing at an extraordinary rate.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago, Washington had just 19 wineries and fewer than 5,000 acres of wine grapes. Today, there are at least 145 wineries -- a new one appears nearly every month -- and a fivefold increase in grape production from 1980, to 25,000 acres. Once known for white wine, Washington is now better known for its reds -- merlot, cabernet sauvignon and, most recently, syrah, cabernet franc and sangiovese. Even nebbiolo, the northern Italian grape used in making the celebrated Barolo and Barberesco of Piedmont, has gained a foothold in this state that is farther north, in latitude, than Maine.</p>
        <p>''We are the new frontier,'' said Allen Shoup, chief executive officer of Stimson Lane, the biggest Washington winemaker, owner of Chateau Ste. Michelle and Columbia Crest. ''There are places where you can lie in the middle of the road for half a day before you'd see a car.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoup, like other evangelists of Washington wine, notes that the grapes are grown in the same latitude as the Bordeaux, Loire and Burgundy regions of France, between the 46th and 48th parallels. ''That means two hours a day of more sunshine than California,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As travelers to the Pacific Northwest know, the region has two distinct climates: the wet, temperate western side of the Cascade Mountains, where rainfall, particularly in the Puget Sound area, averages about 40 inches a year, and the near-desert eastern side that receives about 8 inches annually. The westerly storms are blocked by the Cascade curtain.</p>
        <p>Until recently, the food and wine culture that blossomed with the wealth of high-tech Washington had been mostly around Seattle. And people who wanted to tour wineries would usually visit those in the Seattle area, like Chateau Ste. Michelle in Woodinville or Hedges in Issaquah.</p>
        <p>For a tour of the terroir, as the French call the land and climate unique to a grape, a visitor has to drive over the Cascades and into the dry country. In these valleys, dozens of wineries are open for tastings every day. And new restaurants -- though only a handful of quality ones -- are beginning to appear. At the same time, established restaurants are starting to make use of fresh local food with wine from neighboring vintners. It is all in the dawning phase, which is part of what makes a Washington wine country visit stand out in the age of packaged tours.</p>
        <p>Virtually all of Washington's premium wine comes from grapes grown in one of three officially designated viticultural regions, or appellations: the Yakima Valley, the Walla Walla Valley and the Columbia Valley, which overlaps the two smaller regions.</p>
        <p>The Yakima Valley is the easiest to reach from Seattle, about two hours east on Interstate 90 and then south on Interstate 82. Restaurants, visitor centers and kiosks in some of the roadside convenience stores offer free tour brochures of the wine country. The highway passes strip malls, yards stacked with logs and other bits of commerce and industry that bear no resemblance to the pastoral charm of a grape-growing area.</p>
        <p>But all that changes if you leave the freeway near the town of Zillah, southeast of Yakima. Grapes are planted on south and west-facing slopes, near prodigious orchards of apples and cherries. At Covey Run Winery, on the outskirts of Zillah, the owners encourage picnics on the big lawn or the deck that overlooks the vineyards and mountains. This vintner makes a much-praised dry white wine, a fume blanc, and a red wine, lemberger, rarely produced in the United States.</p>
        <p>Nearby, at Horizon's Edge, I found a tractor in the parking lot, a stray dog roaming around and a little upstairs sampling room in a refurbished barn. A winemaker was pouring a reserve merlot, 1997, while talking about what to name a baby on the way.</p>
        <p>The main passage through the Yakima grape-growing region is Highway 12, which becomes the Wine Country Road. Along it are some of the better-known wineries, like Hogue Cellars, and smaller ones just gaining prominence, like Thurston Wolfe, Chinook and Kestrel. The Wine Country Road ends near the town of Prosser, home of an established restaurant, the Blue Goose, that has an exhaustive Washington wine list, but is a bit hard to find. It looks like a roadside diner from an outtake of American Gothic, but serves dishes like spaghetti carbonara, veal marsala and New York steak to go with robust reds made within miles of the restaurant.</p>
        <p>Throughout the Yakima Valley, where big cottonwoods grow along the river and Indian fishermen still net chinook salmon from the occasional wood platform, the well-tended vineyards are a striking contrast to the potato-skin-colored expanse of the native desert, with its sage and shrubs of greasewood.</p>
        <p>Farther east, near the Tri-Cities region in the heart of the Columbia Valley, the desert looks like parts of Arizona. This is the hottest section of the wine country, home of the syrah grape from southern France, which is being planted at a frantic rate. But it is also cluttered with sprawl from the three cities: Pasco, Richland and Kennewick. Convenience store signs read: Food, Gas, Wine. Among the wineries in the area with year-round tasting rooms are Bookwalter, Barnard Griffin and Gordon Brothers Cellars.</p>
        <p>As a diversion, two wineries stand out. To the south, in the National Scenic Area of the Columbia Gorge, is Cascade Cliffs, set on a bluff above the river next to towering basalt walls, one of the most dramatic winery settings anywhere. It also makes a nebbiolo that is hard to find outside the winery.</p>
        <p>Up the Columbia River another 80 miles or so is Columbia Crest. It is big and corporate, but the wines get consistently good reviews, are moderately priced and the setting is pleasant for visitors. There is a big tasting room and large picnic grounds amid manicured gardens around the chateau and its 2,150-acre vineyard.</p>
        <p>East of the big bend of the Columbia River, Highway 12 leads to Walla Walla, the most remote part of Washington wine country, but also the region that is generating the most excitement now. Wines from Walla Walla -- among them, Leonetti Cellar and Woodward Canyon -- have put this little valley on the map of the world's great wines. Money, French chefs and oenophiles have followed. But it is just now gearing up to welcome visitors on a mission of taste and discovery.</p>
        <p>Walla Walla is an oasis of about 30,000 people in the desert that rolls up against the Blue Mountains. It is the home of a well-regarded, 117-year-old liberal arts school, Whitman College, but is perhaps best known as the area that produces a sweet onion of some renown. Its nearly two-dozen wineries may soon eclipse both the school and the onion. The town has an airport, with regular flights from Seattle, and a strip long enough to accommodate those private jets of the dot-com class.</p>
        <p>A lazy river winds through the arid hills; llamas and sheep graze on alfalfa. Driving east, you come to the hamlet of Lowden. Blink and you miss it. Slow down, since the police are always busy filling the public coffers through speeding tickets. Woodward Canyon is the first stop. When my wife, Joni, and I were there recently, a county sheriff was writing a ticket in the parking lot while we strolled to an old shed. Inside, the Wine Spectator was open to a page rating Woodward Canyon's reds among the top 100 wines in the world, and we sat on boxes testing the article's premise. The winery had a funky charm typical of the Northwest. An old farmhouse, next door, has since opened as a tasting room. A few hundred yards east is L'Ecole No. 41, an extensively remodeled old schoolhouse. The wines for sampling are written on school chalkboards in a big-windowed room looking out at the countryside. L'Ecole's outdoor deck and dining room are available for large dinners arranged through the winery or private caterers. The schoolhouse has an elaborate cellar, as well. Its cabernets and merlots -- particularly the 1990 and the 1994 vintages -- are much in demand.</p>
        <p>In Walla Walla itself, a number of the historic buildings that date from the days when this town dreamed of being a major city have been reborn as wineries. Canoe Ridge, Waterbrook, Seven Hills and Cayuse are all open for tastings in downtown Walla Walla. Alas, the best-known winery, Leonetti Cellar, is not open to the public.</p>
        <p>On a visit last year, everyone told us there was no restaurant in Walla Walla that lived up to the quality of the local wines. We were steered to the town of Dayton, 30 miles to the north, tucked in a fold of wheat farms in the rolling Palouse hills, where there is an extraordinary French-style bistro, Patit Creek. The limousines in the parking lot should have been a tipoff. We ate lamb chops with asparagus and other local vegetables, accompanied by a wine from the heretofore impossible-to-find Leonetti Cellar -- the great 1994 cabernet sauvignon -- at a reasonable price.</p>
        <p>This past spring we found a fine new restaurant in Walla Walla, Whitehouse-Crawford, set in an old planing mill downtown. It has replaned fir floors and high ceilings, and is listed in the National Register of Historic Places. We enjoyed studying the exhaustive list of local wines to find the appropriate complement to our ravioli in garlic sauce with morels and grilled Chinook salmon.</p>
        <p>There are several new chain hotels in Walla Walla, and a number of bed-and-breakfasts, including the Green Gables Inn, in a leafy old neighborhood, and, just outside the city, Mill Creek Inn, where we stayed.</p>
        <p>One morning we went for a run through the nearby woods, where we saw herons, a bald eagle and lots of deer. Wandering around the property after a big breakfast, we were surprised when the doors of an old carriage house opened to reveal a small tasting room. Rusty Figgins, younger brother of Gary Figgins, the winemaker at Leonetti, offered to pour samples of his Glen Fiona syrah. It was early, and I resisted. But he was persistent, and I'm glad he was.</p>
        <p>VINEYARDS AND BEYOND  The WASHINGTON WINE COMMISSION (telephone: 206-667-9463; e-mail: jdoak@  washingtonwine.org) has a free brochure on the wine country, with maps and extensive listings.  RIVER'S EDGE BED AND BREAKFAST, North River Road (telephone and fax: 509-786-3060), is three miles west of Prosser, right on the Yakima River. Built 15 years ago, it has one room and two suites, all facing the river, with private entrances and patios. Rates range from $89 for a double room, to $98 for a suite with bedroom and living room, to $110 for a suite with a full kitchen; prices include breakfast. Open all year. Credit cards not accepted. Smoking is restricted to the patios. No small children.  GREEN GABLES INN, 922 Bonsella (509-525-5501; e-mail: greengables@wwics.com), is near the Whitman College campus in Walla Walla. Built in 1909, it has five bedrooms, with names -- among them ''Willowmere'' and ''Dryad's Bubble'' -- taken from L. M. Montgomery's ''Anne of Green Gables.'' There is a sixth bedroom in a separate carriage house. All have bath, refrigerator, cable TV and VCR. Prices range from $95 to $125, including breakfast. Open all year. No smoking. Children under 12 welcome in the carriage house.  MILL CREEK INN, Mill Creek Road, a few miles outside of Walla Walla (telephone and fax: 509-522-1234), is on the site of what was a big farm, 22 acres including gardens, vineyards and a wildlife habitat. There are three cottages in restored farm buildings (bunkhouse, creamery) and two suites in a restored barn; all have baths. Prices, which range from $85 to $150 depending on the day of the week, include breakfast, which might consist of seasonal fruits, sweet onion and zucchini quiche, cinnamon buns or raspberry scones. Open all year. No smoking. Children and pets welcome.  THE BLUE GOOSE, 306 Seventh Street, Prosser (509-786-1774), serves local wines, microbrews and German beer to accompany salads, hamburgers, pasta dishes and such main courses as blackened halibut, chicken piccata and New York steak. Desserts include a four-layer chocolate ''suicide'' cake and ''bumbleberry'' pie, with blackberries, red raspberries, strawberries, rhubarb and apples. Dinner for two, with a bottle of wine, is about $60. Open daily for breakfast, lunch, dinner and for Sunday brunch.  PATIT CREEK RESTAURANT, 725 East Dayton Avenue , Dayton (509-382-2625), is a fine French-style bistro, offering such dishes as avocado-cream cheese omelet with sour cream and salsa; poached Australian lobster tail with grapefruit and white wine beurre blanc, and center-cut New York black peppercorn steak with a Scotch whiskey and red wine sauce. Desserts include an assortment of homemade pies and tortes. The reasonably priced wine list includes some rarities; wines range from $20 to $70. Dinner for two, with a bottle of wine, is about $90. Open Wednesday through Friday for lunch, Wednesday through Saturday for dinner.  WHITEHOUSE-CRAWFORD, 55 West Cherry Street, Walla Walla (509-525-2222), opened in May, housed in an old planing mill that is on the National Register of Historic Places. Specialties include roasted clams in coconut milk; Chilean sea bass served with a warm salad of potatoes, mushrooms and asparagus; roast duck with port, plums and spaetzle; and, for dessert, profiteroles with homemade coffee ice cream. The large wine list includes some 60 local wines; dinner for two, with a bottle of wine, is about $110. Open Tuesday through Saturday: wine and appetizers, 4 p.m. to 10 p.m., dinner, 5 p.m. to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Timothy Egan, who writes for The Times from Seattle, is the author of ''Lasso the Wind: Away to the New West''(Knopf).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Timothy Egan, who writes for The Times from Seattle, is the author of ''Lasso the Wind: Away to the New West''(Knopf).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
