<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making More Air Time for Water Polo, Archery, Team Handball and Canoeing</title>
    <meta content="10COV4RS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MSNBC (cable network)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cnbc (Cable Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4D91E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making More Air Time for Water Polo, Archery, Team Handball and Canoeing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>CNBC and MSNBC plan to render broad coverage of variety of sporting events at Summer, 2000, Olympic Games; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Devoted CNBC and MSNBC viewers may be surprised when soccer players, boxers, weight lifters, kayakers and wrestlers start to replace Ron Insana, Chris Matthews, Matt Lauer, and Maria Bartiromo at strategic intervals during the next few weeks. But the NBC mother ship doesn't mind shoving aside some of its cable mainstays for two weeks to broaden its Summer Olympics coverage from Sydney.</p>
        <p>So what if NBC is playing its own version of ''Hardball''? The Summer Games cost the network $705 million. Why not spread out the sports and amortize a little?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Devoted CNBC and MSNBC viewers may be surprised when soccer players, boxers, weight lifters, kayakers and wrestlers start to replace Ron Insana, Chris Matthews, Matt Lauer, and Maria Bartiromo at strategic intervals during the next few weeks. But the NBC mother ship doesn't mind shoving aside some of its cable mainstays for two weeks to broaden its Summer Olympics coverage from Sydney.</p>
        <p>So what if NBC is playing its own version of ''Hardball''? The Summer Games cost the network $705 million. Why not spread out the sports and amortize a little?</p>
        <p>Five years ago, NBC staged a television coup by snaring the rights to five Olympics, from 2000 to 2008, for $3.5 billion. As part of its plan, NBC chose to augment its broadcast-only coverage with two cable channels. CNBC was in place, but America's Talking had not yet become MSNBC.</p>
        <p>This year, besides NBC's 162.5 morning, prime time and late night hours, CNBC and MSNBC will together carry 172 more, with MSNBC replaying its daily coverage at midnight. On weekdays, CNBC will carry the Olympics from 5 p.m. to 9 p.m., and MSNBC from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. On weekends, CNBC stretches to a 4 p.m. to 9 p.m. block, with MSNBC contracting for 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>Pat O'Brien of ''Access Hollywood'' will be the host of CNBC's coverage; Jim Lampley, on his 10th Olympic assignment, will be MSNBC's host. Everything will be on tape because of the 15-hour difference between Sydney and Eastern Daylight Time. Results will be known, but executives at NBC believe Olympic viewers care more about the pictures than about who won or lost.</p>
        <p>''It's been like working for a start-up,'' said Molly Solomon, the coordinator-producer of NBC's Olympic cable coverage. ''We had to define the vision in 1996 when I got here. We had to define what to put in our 11 hours a day. At the beginning, we said, 'If there's a great dream-team basketball game that was on NBC, we'll carry it all the next day.' Now we're saying, 'Let's not carry any redundant programming, only what's original and dramatic.' ''</p>
        <p>The cable strategy will enable NBC to give time to sports that were ignored or received minuscule coverage four years ago during the Atlanta Summer Games.</p>
        <p>Now, for example, boxing will be the first sport on CNBC's daily schedule. Four years ago, a boxing fan with long memories of how ABC Sports featured Sugar Ray Leonard or George Foreman in the past, would have needed a jeweler's loupe to find the sweet science on NBC.</p>
        <p>In all, CNBC and MSNBC are scheduled to carry 30 gold medal finals -- from tennis and water polo to baseball and the three-day equestrian For the first time, team handball, archery and field hockey finals will be seen.</p>
        <p>The cable complement will let NBC avoid the major faux pas of the 1996 Atlanta Summer Games -- missing all but the final minute of the U.S. women's gold-medal-winning soccer game. Games that require nearly two hours would never make it on NBC but can find room on cable.</p>
        <p>Mostly, when an event starts on MSNBC or CNBC, it will finish. End-to-end coverage of men's and women's soccer, baseball, women's softball and women's basketball is a vast change from NBC's approach -- in which mass-appeal sports like, track and field, swimming, diving and gymnastics are packaged into emotional soap operas laden with profiles and features that are planned to build to a climax at midnight.</p>
        <p>The Olympics will actually begin on MSNBC before Friday night's opening ceremony: the first United States men's soccer match will be carried Wednesday night, followed Thursday night by the first U.S. women's soccer game.</p>
        <p>''We're putting games into time slots that fit,'' Ms. Solomon said. ''We're not trying to put a soccer game into a 30-minute time slot. When we put in a volleyball game, we're putting it into an hour slot to show virtually the whole thing. On the network, you're hopscotching all the time, so you can't do that.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''On cable, we're saying this is going to be more like watching a traditional sports program, where we go there and stay there. In 1996, there was a triple overtime basketball game between Lithuania and Croatia, and I was frustrated that there was no room for it. Now our commitment on the cable side is that we will alter our schedule to accommodate things that happen.''</p>
        <p>Inevitably, those alterations may mean that some events will not be shown to their conclusion. And events like weight lifting and archery -- which have significant downtime between competitors -- will not be seen continuously, but in pieces.</p>
        <p>''But it will be long-form television,'' Ms. Solomon said.</p>
        <p>For first-time analysts like Jon Lugbill (canoeing and kayaking) and Sam Maxwell (weight lifting), the CNBC-MSNBC plans make their work worthwhile. Without cable, their events would be relegated to morning or late-night shows or condensed into brief recaps.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell thought NBC's weight lifting coverage in 1996 suffered for having a football analyst, Phil Simms, as the analyst. ''For some reason, lifting got someone who didn't know the sport,'' said Maxwell. '</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell, who has appeared on television as a financial analyst, made his debut as a sports analyst at the Olympic weight lifting trials, which were carried on PXN. ''Weight lifting has been made into a freak show, of a 350-pound guy lifting the combined weight of three refrigerators,'' he said. ''It's not just about the weight but an appreciation of the movement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell will now have the time to convey his passion on cable -- as will Mr. Lugbill, a 1992 U.S. Olympic canoer who remembers how NBC highlighted Greg Barton, a gold-medal-winning U.S. kayaker, at the 1988 Summer Games in Seoul. ''But in 1996, no American was doing well in a final, so they only did an overview, maybe in two-minute segments,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''To have kayaking on MSNBC is huge,'' he said. ''It gives the sport tremendous visibility and the exposure you'd never get.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
