<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Must-Sees: Everybody Has an A-List</title>
    <meta content="10GERS$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10GERS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LOOKING AHEAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFDA1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Must-Sees: Everybody Has an A-List</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jill Gerston.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several actors, producers, directors, progammers, screenwriters and cinematographers comment on upcoming television season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROB MORROW  Actor</p>
        <p>CASTAWAY'' looks cool. I like the director, Robert Zemeckis, a lot. From an actor's point of view, the idea that they shut down the film for Tom Hanks to lose weight and grow a true beard is fantastic. To give such attention to detail on every level is amazing. I can't wait to see ''The Legend of Bagger Vance.'' I love golf. I believe the story is that Bagger Vance shows up out of nowhere and shows Matt Damon how to find the inner strength to win. In a way, it reminds me of the mysticism in ''The Natural.'' I'm excited about the Coen brothers'  ''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' I don't know how the title informs the movie, but it's the same one that the filmmaker Sullivan, in Preston Sturges's classic ''Sullivan's Travels,'' wanted to make. That was a wonderful film, and I assume there is some kind of link. Just the title and the Coen brothers are enough for me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROB MORROW  Actor</p>
        <p>CASTAWAY'' looks cool. I like the director, Robert Zemeckis, a lot. From an actor's point of view, the idea that they shut down the film for Tom Hanks to lose weight and grow a true beard is fantastic. To give such attention to detail on every level is amazing. I can't wait to see ''The Legend of Bagger Vance.'' I love golf. I believe the story is that Bagger Vance shows up out of nowhere and shows Matt Damon how to find the inner strength to win. In a way, it reminds me of the mysticism in ''The Natural.'' I'm excited about the Coen brothers'  ''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' I don't know how the title informs the movie, but it's the same one that the filmmaker Sullivan, in Preston Sturges's classic ''Sullivan's Travels,'' wanted to make. That was a wonderful film, and I assume there is some kind of link. Just the title and the Coen brothers are enough for me.</p>
        <p>RENNY HARLIN  Director</p>
        <p>THE ''Remember the Titans'' trailer looks great, and Denzel is always good. Kip Pardue will be the next superstar. ''Unbreakable'' -- the director, M. Night Shyamalan, is talented and able to mix art with commerciality. ''Men of Honor'' has a powerful trailer, and De Niro is always great. Cuba Gooding Jr. deserves a great part because he is so talented. The original ''Get Carter'' was a classic. Stallone looks great and the film looks stylish and cool.</p>
        <p>JOHN WATERS  Director</p>
        <p>I'M very eager to see ''Shadow of the Vampire,'' with Willem Dafoe. I'm a huge Willem Dafoe fan, and I heard the best buzz about this movie when I was in Cannes. Then there is Lars von Trier's new movie, ''Dancer in the Dark,'' which won best picture in Cannes. It's a musical, tearjerker, melodrama, lunatic masterpiece with Bjork and Catherine Deneuve. Von Trier is a director who certainly makes people nervous. He is a love-him-or-hate-him director, which is always my kind of guy. I'm very much looking forward to Steve Buscemi's new film, ''Animal Factory.'' I really liked his first movie, ''Trees Lounge.'' He directed this one, and Edward Furlong and Willem Dafoe are in it. So I guess I'm looking forward to a Willem Dafoe fall. There is no Chucky movie coming out, is there? Because that is the main thing I want to see.</p>
        <p>ISMAIL MERCHANT  Producer, director</p>
        <p>I'M looking forward to Ang Lee's ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon.'' Ang Lee is such a distinguished director. He is working in a new territory, China, and he himself is Chinese, so in a sense he is going back to his roots. The star, Chow Yun Fat, is a wonderful actor. I believe the film is almost like a grand ballet. I'm also interested in seeing ''Billy Elliot,'' Stephen Daldry's film with Julie Walters, both of whom I admire. I gather it is a very heartwarming movie about this young, struggling kid who wants to be a dancer. My focus is on films like these that stimulate you and challenge your intelligence.</p>
        <p>WARRINGTON HUDLIN  Director-producer</p>
        <p>I CAN'T wait to see ''Ladies' Man,'' the spinoff movie from ''Saturday Night Live.'' I'm fascinated by the phenomenon of ''Saturday Night Live'' as a fixture in American comedy and its ability to introduce characters whom we embrace first on the small screen and then on the large screen. ''Ladies' Man'' is the first African-American character to come out of the stable that gave us ''Wayne's World'' and ''The Coneheads.'' He is a sort of old-school player with this 70's sensibility. Without question, this will be a big break for Tim Meadows. The producer is Lorne Michaels. And I must confess that I happen to be genetically linked to the director, Reginald Hudlin, who is my brother.</p>
        <p>MIKE NICHOLS  Director</p>
        <p>I'M looking forward to Steven Soderbergh's ''Traffic.'' Soderbergh moves us forward.</p>
        <p>LILI FINI ZANUCK  Producer</p>
        <p>I'M anxious to see ''Quills,'' the Marquis de Sade film with Geoffrey Rush and Kate Winslet. You say ''Marquis de Sade'' and people go, ''Oh, a sex movie.'' But in fact, I've read a couple of books about him, and it's a fascinating story about the marquis, his wife and his mother-in-law. Phil Kaufman had been trying for a while to get the movie made, and I find it incredible that he did. ''The Legend of Bagger Vance'' is also something I want to see. Robert Redford is a wonderful filmmaker who is very sensitive to story and performance. And I want to see Will Smith in a dramatic role. I'm really interested in seeing ''Moulin Rouge.'' Baz Luhrmann is such a smart filmmaker who always does things that redefine the medium. And then there is ''Bounce.'' I read the script. It was a good story and very romantic. When I heard that Gwyneth Paltrow and Ben Affleck were going to do it, I thought, I really want to see this movie.</p>
        <p>JON AVNET  Director</p>
        <p>I'D like to see Robert Redford's movie, ''The Legend of Bagger Vance.'' I hate golf, but I love Redford. Bob is such a smart guy that whatever he deals with makes an interesting film. And the cast, with Matt Damon and Will Smith, is very good. I'm also interested in ''All the Pretty Horses.'' I optioned Cormac McCarthy's first novel a long time ago, so I'm curious to see how his book has been adapted for the screen. I'm also interested in ''Castaway.'' I want to see Tom Hanks looking skinny.</p>
        <p>SCOTT RUDIN  Producer</p>
        <p>STEPHEN DALDRY'S movie, ''Billy Elliot,'' is about a kid from a working-class town in England who wants to be a dancer. I'm a huge fan of Stephen Daldry, who is a complete original. If he is 10 percent as talented a movie director as he is a theater director, he is a major force to be reckoned with. I'm also eager to see ''Moulin Rouge,'' because anything Baz Luhrmann does, I'm there on Friday at 11 a.m. I think ''Moulin Rouge'' is going to be a singular piece of filmmaking. If you look at the leap Luhrmann made from ''Strictly Ballroom'' to ''Romeo and Juliet'' and assume he does the same thing in this movie, it should be remarkable. He is a gifted filmmaker.</p>
        <p>JANUSZ KAMINSKI  Cinematographer-director</p>
        <p>I HAVE seen clips of ''Pollock,'' and I can't wait to see the movie in its entirety. Ed Harris, who plays Jackson Pollock and directed the film, is amazing. He became Pollock. He has been learning how to paint for several years and he can virtually imitate Pollock's painting style. The next movie that I want to see is Cameron Crowe's ''Almost Famous.'' This one is supposed to be semiautobiographical, which intrigues me because I would like to learn more about him. Unlike some directors who just want to entertain, Cameron is curious about the world. He throws questions at us and examines moral issues, but he does it in an old-fashioned kind of Billy Wilder way. And then there is the Coen brothers' movie, ''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' I saw it at the Cannes Film Festival, but I want to see it with an audience that actually goes to the movie theater and pays for the ticket. It would be great to see how they respond. I like the cinematographer Harris Savides, who shot ''Illuminata'' and whose next movie is ''The Yards.'' I love his simple way of lighting a scene, no tricks, no funny stuff. I'm always interested in seeing his work.</p>
        <p>JEAN DOUMANIAN  Producer</p>
        <p>I READ the script of Ang Lee's ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon,'' and I loved it. It's an epic that takes place in China. When it's an Ang Lee movie, you know, regardless of whether you like it or not, that you will be entertained. There is a movie coming out by Darren Aronofsky called ''Requiem for a Dream.'' He showed so much promise with ''Pi'' that I'm really curious to see what he is doing. And everyone is talking about ''Dancer in the Dark,'' the Lars von Trier movie with Bjork. I hear Bjork is just wonderful, and it's a magnificent movie. It's not going to be ''Scary Movie,'' but it is a movie about relationships that stirs your emotions.</p>
        <p>LYNDA OBST  Producer</p>
        <p>I DEFINITELY want to see ''Bounce,'' Don Roos's movie. I love him and I loved the script. I tried to buy it -- you always want to see how a movie you almost bought turns out. It's not a romantic comedy or a straight drama, and I like it when you can't categorize a film. It's very exciting for a producer when that type of movie works, because it gives you license the next time around. And one wants to see if Gwyneth Paltrow and Ben Affleck are Tracy and Hepburn, right? I'm also excited about ''Lucky Numbers,'' with John Travolta and Lisa Kudrow. It's a very offbeat Nora Ephron movie about the lottery. It's quirky and something different from Nora, so I'm intrigued. I've heard really good things about ''Quills,'' Phil Kaufman's movie about the Marquis de Sade. It's racy. And I understand that ''Men of Honor,'' with Cuba Gooding Jr. and Robert De Niro, about the first black Navy diver, is really good. People were crying at the screening. Cuba is such a good actor.</p>
        <p>SAM MASER  Film series programmer</p>
        <p>AS a program director, I always look for films with a unique visual sense that tell an engrossing story cinematically. I think that describes ''Nurse Betty,'' which is at the top of my list. I loved Neil LaBute's first two movies, so I'm looking forward to this. I really want to see ''Bounce,'' directed by Don Roos, who did ''The Opposite of Sex.'' I've heard that the script is really great, and to me the script is where it all starts. The other film I'm curious to see is Chris Guest's new movie, ''Best in Show.'' It is a mockumentary set at a dog show. I'm nuts about dogs and I love the humor of Chris Guest -- ''Spinal Tap'' is one of the funniest movies I've seen -- so I think this should be hilarious. I also want to see ''Traffic,'' Steven Soderbergh's movie. He got an amazing performance out of Julia Roberts in ''Erin Brockovich.'' He is a genius who has a unique way of telling a story.</p>
        <p>ROBERT NELSON JACOBS  Screenwriter</p>
        <p>ONE of the things I look for is an interesting collaboration between a writer and a director, which is the case with ''Dr. T and the Women,'' Robert Altman's new movie, which was written by Anne Rapp. She is the screenwriter who did ''Cookie's Fortune,'' which I thought was an unsung gem. This new movie has the potential to be one of those great Altman ensemble pieces with quirky, specific characters with intertwining stories. I also like when filmmakers aren't afraid to mix comedy with drama so a movie isn't pigeonholed into a particular genre. Which brings me to my next choice, the Coen brothers' movie, ''O Brother, Where Art Thou?'' It's about escaped chain-gang members in the south in the 1930's. Apparently, it is based on Homer's ''Odyssey,'' so it's a natural fit, Homer and the Coen brothers. Another film that intrigues me is the Giuseppe Tornatore movie, ''Malena.'' He did ''Cinema Paradiso.'' It is set in World War II and is a rite-of-passage story about a young boy in love with the town beauty. I'm a total sucker for that dreamy, bittersweet film drenched in Italian sentiment.</p>
        <p>DEBRA ZANE  Casting director</p>
        <p>FROM my perspective, it's always about the cast. It's always good to see what people can do, to get an idea of their ability and to see what else they might be right for. I'm looking forward to Cameron Crowe's movie, ''Almost Famous,'' starring Billy Crudup and Frances McDormand. I'm always anxious to see Billy Crudup. I love his work. And there is a brand new kid in it named Patrick Fugit, and I want to see him. I also heard that Crowe has dug up a lot of songs from the 70's that are atypical, so I'm curious to hear them. I'm looking forward to seeing ''Remember the Titans,'' about a high school football team. It has a young cast with a lot of newcomers. And I love Denzel Washington, who plays the coach. I also want to see ''All the Pretty Horses.'' I think Matt Damon is a terrific actor, unlike a lot of others of his age group who call themselves actors. And Lucas Black, who played the boy in ''Sling Blade,'' is a teenager now, and I'm curious to see his work.</p>
        <p>RUTH CHARNY  Producer</p>
        <p>ANG LEE'S ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon'' got wonderful press coming out of Cannes, and it sounds like it's going to be a cinematic tour de force. I would love to see Wong Kar-wai's new movie, ''In the Mood for Love.'' He is a groundbreaking director who has a huge following because his cinematic work is so unusual. He did ''Chungking Express,'' so I'm anxious to see what he is up to. I'm also looking forward to ''Nurse Betty,'' Neil LaBute's film. I loved ''In the Company of Men,'' but I was disappointed in ''Your Friends and Neighbors,'' so I'm curious to see where he is going. He is also working with an extraordinary cinematographer, Jean-Yves Escoffier. I want to see Lars von Trier's ''Dancer in the Dark.'' The movie is shot on digital video, and he uses dozens of cameras to cover his musical numbers. He is a very filmic filmmaker who really uses the medium to tell a story.</p>
        <p>GEORGE TILLMAN JR.  Director</p>
        <p>AT the top of my list is Spike Lee's ''Bamboozled.'' I remember watching Spike Lee in film school, and he is an inspiration to me. He's a very strong filmmaker who is very influential on a lot of young filmmakers coming up. I'm also looking forward to ''The Legend of Bagger Vance.'' I'm a big fan of Robert Redford, and Will Smith is just great. I heard it's ''The Natural'' in golf. The Steven Soderbergh movie ''Traffic'' really interests me. There is not one film that he made that I didn't like. He gets behind the camera and does his own operating and does his own editing. As a technician, he is amazing. I usually see a film two times -- the first time I watch it as entertainment, the second as a director, to see what is going on. I think we should make films to entertain and have a message, and all these films are great stories and have a message behind them.</p>
        <p>JOHN RIDLEY  Screenwriter</p>
        <p>ABOUT the only movie I'm looking forward to seeing is ''Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon.'' The trailer is amazing. I'm a huge fan of Hong Kong cinema, and having Chow Yun Fat and Michelle Yeoh in the same film is monumental. Ang Lee is an interesting director who has done a lot of different work. The story is about love and honor and betrayal, and to have a tragic romance with a lot of action is challenging. It could be a real breakthrough for Asian cinema.</p>
        <p>LOOKING AHEAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
