<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Doesn't Look A Day Over 30</title>
    <meta content="10COUN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/living/10COUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTERINTELLIGENCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Caravelle (Nyc Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DF1039F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Doesn't Look A Day Over 30</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Witchel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex Witchell article on La Caravelle, New York City restaurant that is celebrating its 40th anniversary; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I invited friends to dinner recently at La Caravelle, one asked plaintively: Was she allowed to wear pants?</p>
        <p>I laughed, until I spent a morning with the scrapbooks the restaurant's original owners, Robert L. Meyzen and Fred Decre, had kept since its debut on Sept. 21, 1960. I realized then that my friend has a long memory. An article in The New York Times on Oct. 7, 1968, titled ''Even the Restaurateurs Concede That Pants Are Fashionable,'' read in part: ''Robert Meyzen of La Caravelle, who has long frowned on pants 'because very few women wear them handsomely,' said with resignation: ''This is going to be the fashion this winter. You can't avoid it. If the woman is young, elegant and well-groomed, personally, I don't feel there's anything wrong with it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I invited friends to dinner recently at La Caravelle, one asked plaintively: Was she allowed to wear pants?</p>
        <p>I laughed, until I spent a morning with the scrapbooks the restaurant's original owners, Robert L. Meyzen and Fred Decre, had kept since its debut on Sept. 21, 1960. I realized then that my friend has a long memory. An article in The New York Times on Oct. 7, 1968, titled ''Even the Restaurateurs Concede That Pants Are Fashionable,'' read in part: ''Robert Meyzen of La Caravelle, who has long frowned on pants 'because very few women wear them handsomely,' said with resignation: ''This is going to be the fashion this winter. You can't avoid it. If the woman is young, elegant and well-groomed, personally, I don't feel there's anything wrong with it.''</p>
        <p>A year later Mr. Meyzen officially surrendered on the issue of pants, telling The Times, ''At first we didn't allow them, but we are here to serve food, not to buck the trend of fashion,'' though he added sternly, ''We don't allow turtlenecks.''</p>
        <p>That contretemps was second only to another revolutionary moment, in 1963, when The New York Journal-American published an article called ''Missing Millinery,'' which recorded sightings of Pauline Trigere and Elizabeth Arden daring to go hatless at Pavillon, while at La Caravelle, ''the same hatlessness prevailed'' among editors from Harper's Bazaar and Vogue. Mon Dieu!</p>
        <p>La Caravelle, which opened with a $5.50 prix fixe lunch and $7.50 dinner, celebrates its 40th anniversary this month. A New York institution, it has stood as a marker of a bygone era of glamour. But rather than settling into dinosaur status, it has actually hung around long enough to be back in style again. While the older crowd continues its patronage (Brooke Astor, Geoffrey Beene and Oscar de la Renta among them), the next generations are booking tables, too. In a fashion season smitten with the trappings of uptown chic, the younger set is seeing La Caravelle not as stiff but as Old World charming. They are happy to dress up and play Paris for an evening out.</p>
        <p>Or an afternoon. At lunch recently, I watched Alexandra Lind, a 30-year-old fashion designer whose cocktail dresses sell at Searle and whose bridal gowns sell at Bergdorf Goodman, with three other women, bringing the median age in the room down by half. Honoring the tradition of the fashionable women who have always frequented La Caravelle -- Babe Paley and the Duchess of Windsor among them -- they were dressed to the teeth, complete with the new bowling-ball bags, barely in stores yet. It was the first time Ms. Lind had been back since she was 15. ''I was pleasantly surprised,'' she said. ''It was a really warm atmosphere and felt very youthful, not overly formal at all. I liked the intimacy of it. You can really talk to people. And hear them.''</p>
        <p>Rita Jammet, who with her husband, Andre, became owner of La Caravelle in 1988, says they have attracted younger diners by steering away from stuffiness with an attitude they call ''friendly formality.''</p>
        <p>''We were out of favor at some point, but the pendulum swings again, and the next generation is attracted to us,'' Mrs. Jammet (pronounced jah-MAY) said. ''We are trying to bring back the idea of hospitality, not give the feeling, 'Are you good enough to come in here?' ''</p>
        <p>Though the phrase friendly formality sounds lifted from a marketing textbook, I did see it in practice at two recent meals. Women were stylishly dressed (even in pants), with the exception of one who dashed in at lunch wearing khakis and a black tank top, took one look around her and seemed sorry she had. Jackets are required for men, though ties are optional, and also required is a decorum that disqualifies the packs of marauding traders who seem to frequent steakhouses -- at least every time I'm eating at one. As Mrs. Jammet put it: ''We try to maintain a civility here. Yes, it's wonderful to be young and social and up-and-coming, but you still have to maintain a certain gentleness with yourself.''</p>
        <p>On the Friday night of Labor Day weekend, the restaurant was surprisingly full, with a wine-tasting dinner under way in a private room. The few cell phone users didn't shout; a man escorting a Catherine Zeta-Jones look-alike looked askance at something on his plate, and it was immediately whisked away; and if I ever raised my glance, a waiter was instantly at my side. I admit it: I liked being taken care of. My oysters came accompanied by small pieces of bread that had already been buttered. I started to feel my shoulders come down from around my ears and settle back where they belong.</p>
        <p>That the restaurant looks good helps. It is lauded for its pastoral murals, painted by Jean Pages, a student of Raoul Dufy; the Jammets replaced the original red velvet banquettes with peach, to highlight them further. This ensures that what Holiday Magazine wrote in 1964 still holds: La Caravelle ''is so flatteringly lit that it turns aunts into nieces and sugar daddies into gigolos.'' Certainly, by the time our dinner ended, we felt as if we had been on vacation.</p>
        <p>Part of that feeling comes from the sense of time travel. The Jammets have divided the menu between classic (quenelles, Dover sole) and contemporary (tuna carpaccio), and it's a flashback to childhood (the good parts) watching someone carving a roast duck tableside.</p>
        <p>The other lift is dining surrounded by history. For starters, the bar, tucked away in the back, heralds the room's early days as a speak-easy. Then there are the ghosts of diners past. For its inaugural year alone, the restaurant's reservation book included Joseph Kennedy, Cecil Beaton, Mainbocher, Otto Preminger and Harry Winston. When President Kennedy was elected, the White House chef, Rene Verdon, was selected and trained by La Caravelle's chef, Roger Fessaguet.</p>
        <p>But there were bad times, too. The recession of the early 1970's hurt the restaurant, as did the switch in Broadway curtain times to 8 from 8:30, cutting into the traditional dinner hour. By 1978, Mimi Sheraton demoted La Caravelle to two stars in The New York Times, down from Craig Claiborne's four.</p>
        <p>''There was a period before Andre and Rita took over where you didn't know if the restaurant would survive,'' said Tim Zagat, publisher of the Zagat Surveys. ''Our survey has measured that the demographic is younger than it used to be, and the restaurant is definitely more popular.'' (As chef, Cyril Renaud earned three stars from The Times in 1998. He left in April; his sous-chef, Eric Di Domenico, who trained at Taillevent, has taken over.)</p>
        <p>While the food is still wonderful, customers rave about the Jammets' particular brand of hospitality. Mr. Jammet, whose father founded the Bristol Hotel in Paris, worked here as an assistant manager at the Regency; Mrs. Jammet was at the French Embassy. They bought La Caravelle just as a recession hit.</p>
        <p>''Talk about our bubble bursting,'' Mrs. Jammet said. They hired a public relations firm that mandated modernization, designing a (short-lived) corporate-looking logo. ''It took away all the charm,'' Mrs. Jammet said. The changes they did make included hiring the Japanese chef Tadashi Ono. ''Even though he had French training, that was considered revolutionary,'' Mrs. Jammet said. He is now at Sono on East 57th Street, which the Jammets own with Larry Goldenberg of Gramercy Tavern.</p>
        <p>So, they know what modern is. But when it comes to La Caravelle, they still will go only so far in forsaking anything that might be considered old-fashioned. ''If we decide tomorrow to be hip and downtown,'' Mrs. Jammet said, ''the new people wouldn't know us. And the older ones wouldn't want to.''</p>
        <p>COUNTERINTELLIGENCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
