<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Portrait of a Turnip</title>
    <meta content="10BROW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Terence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frazier, Adrian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, George (1852-1933)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">George Moore, 1852-1933 (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DF1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Portrait of a Turnip</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Brown</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Terence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terence Brown reviews book George Moore, 1852-1933 by Adrian Frazier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEORGE MOORE, 1852-1933.</p>
        <p>By Adrian Frazier.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 604 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEORGE MOORE, 1852-1933.</p>
        <p>By Adrian Frazier.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 604 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $35.</p>
        <p>In 1935 the poet W. B. Yeats recollected how George Moore, who had died in 1933, had as a young man left his County Mayo home for Paris, where he sat ''among art students, young writers about to become famous, in some cafe, a man carved out of a turnip, looking out of astonished eyes.'' In focusing on Moore's appearance Yeats was of course taking sweet revenge on the man who had once caught him memorably at Lady Gregory's Coole Park ''standing lost in meditation before a white congregation of swans assembled on the lake, looking himself in his old cloak like a huge umbrella left behind by some picnic party.''</p>
        <p>However, Yeats was also responding to something essentially strange and disconcerting in Moore's appearance that friends and enemies noted throughout his life. His own mother had thought him the ugly duckling of her brood and even some of his many lovers found him an odd enough specimen. Adrian Frazier in his revealing biography deploys throughout his text brief verbal snapshots of his subject supplied by Moore's contemporaries, as if to confirm what the novelist himself told his mother in a sadly brave letter: ''I was born, I live and I shall die a peculiar man -- I could not be be commonplace were I to try.'' One former lover in a roman  clef had him with ''narrow chest and sloping shoulders'' and ''boneless, fat, soft and white hands.'' Another woman described him as possessing ''a long colorless face that looked like a codfish crossed by a satyr.'' Oscar Wilde noted his ''vague, formless, obscene face,'' while the Irish poetaster James Cousins saw a ''pasty face and vague eyes . . . straw-colored hair that looked as if it had been pitchforked on.''</p>
        <p>Given such unprepossessing physical attributes (and portraits or caricatures by, among others, Manet, Sickert and Beerbohm, as well as the photographic record, confirm that Moore was a ready target for the verbal lampoon), it is initially surprising that Moore enjoyed so many amorous conquests. In his lifetime many assumed that most of these were of the literary variety -- all talk and little action. The Irish painter Sarah Purser's quip that ''some men kiss and tell; Moore tells but doesn't kiss'' (recycled by Susan Mitchell, author of the first book on Moore) was in fact, as Frazier suggests, doubly wrong. For Moore was by no means sexually inactive, and in his many liaisons he was an advocate of the joys of oral sex when pregnancy was an inhibition. Frazier puts definitively to rest any suspicion that Moore merely posed as a roue for scandalous effect. For upon discovering that he could be attractive to women he made the most of the opportunities bohemian and literary fame afforded until in a goatish, impotent old age, he became, as Frazier euphemistically has it, a ''tactilist,'' with a notable penchant for bottom-pinching.</p>
        <p>Frazier, who teaches English at Union College in Schenectady, N.Y., deals interestingly with the matter of Moore's peculiar sexual nature, which constitutes one of the mysteries of his career. His conclusion that Moore was ''a homosexual man who loved to make love to women'' rings a little too confidently, however, in view of the story he tells. For at its heart is material Moore's first biographer, Joseph Hone, could not include -- the long, intense, bittersweet affair with Maud Cunard that lasted from before Maud's marriage to the shipping magnate until Maud forsook Moore for the younger Thomas Beecham. And most poignantly, both Moore and Cunard's daughter, Nancy, suspected that they were father and daughter and, although neither was certain, deeply felt this to be the case. Moore's relationship with mother and daughter Cunard, as Frazier recounts it, does much to humanize a figure who might otherwise have become an increasingly tiresome sexual conundrum.</p>
        <p>If Frazier finds Moore's sexual nature a constant fascination, he is troubled by another mystery -- the current literary status of his subject. In his final chapter he acknowledges that Moore himself spent his last 15 years fretting that ''the canon of English fiction for his era would have room for no more than three novelists, and the three most likely to end up there would be James, Hardy and Conrad. . . . The door would shut on Moore.'' And one senses that Frazier knows the door has in fact shut pretty firmly on his subject, for all that he admires Moore's work and is interested by the man. His strategy to rescue Moore from the comparative obscurity into which he has sunk is to write a biography that sets him firmly in the three contexts in which he flourished -- the Paris of Manet, Zola, Mallarme and Degas; the London of the 1880's and 90's; and turn-of-the-century Dublin when the Irish literary revival was at its height, before Moore's protracted decline in London when the literary limelight fell on a new generation. Moore knew everybody worth knowing in these years: his relationships with Zola, Mallarme and Manet; his defense of progressive literary values against the circulating libraries and Mrs. Grundy in Victorian London, when a publisher went to jail for publishing Zola entire and Wilde was destroyed; his battles with Yeats and Lady Gregory in Dublin on the future of Irish theater -- these make for compelling and often entertaining reading. Frazier writes with a genially mordant, even worldly tone about the many excesses and absurdities of Moore's public and private dealings, with a character list that constitutes a cultural history of the period (Moore emerges as the principal champion of Impressionism in England, when he had graduated from being ''Zola's ricochet'').</p>
        <p>And behind all the journalistic, literary and aesthetic maneuvering, the outrageous and hilarious episodes that made Moore notorious in his time, the history of Ireland rumbles threateningly on, like a bass theme in a symphony -- the estate in County Mayo that he had inherited on his father's death in 1870 became more and more of a burden in an era of land wars and rising republicanism; Moore quarreled irrevocably about religion and family with a brother who resided there by his leave; finally Moore Hall itself was torched by the Irish Republican Army in 1923, during the Civil War, a symbol of the fall of feudalism.</p>
        <p>Yet for all its strengths, Frazier's book still leaves one wondering about the reputation. It may be that Moore's fiction (his primary claim on posterity, though he recurrently tried for a dramatic success) is crippled by what Jorge Luis Borges identified as the fault of the imaginary Herbert Quain: ''His books are over-anxious to astonish.'' For the writer who took as his creed Manet's injunction to be ashamed of nothing but shame itself relished shocking his public with a fiction of disturbing realism and candid self-revelation to the point that the reader is no longer surprised and can weary of a species of literary exhibitionism (''astonishment by rote'' was Borges's damning phrase for Quain).</p>
        <p>Or perhaps Moore's reputation in his lifetime was too dependent on what Frazier, in a term derived from the theory seminar, identifies as the ''author function.'' This was a ''life-long project of constructing . . . 'George Moore' as his chief creation,'' which involved studiously elaborating ''a complex and developing identity for public consumption'' and not only the publication of books but a self-advertising campaign in the newspapers and ''public enactment of a studied role.'' With the actual death of the author the ''author function'' inevitably lost some of its power and the reputation was a matter of the texts alone and could not, it seems, be sustained.</p>
        <p>This indeed may be the metaphorical significance of the announcement of sexual impotence in the three-volume ''Hail and Farewell'' (the one work by Moore, along with the realist fiction ''Esther Waters'' and a handful of short stories that will probably resist time's revenges), where ''George Moore'' in a brilliant semi- fictional autobiography is revealed as treacherous friend, self-mocking comedian of the Irish literary revival, lampoonist of genius. Oddly Frazier, so interested in Moore's strange masculinity, makes little critically of this extraordinary confession, which may, as Moore displays himself at the height of his powers, prefigure a time when he knows he will no longer be in control of the reception of the astonishing works of that irresistible fellow, ''George Moore,'' whom he had sedulously fashioned from unlikely materials.</p>
        <p>Terence Brown is professor of Anglo-Irish literature in Trinity College, Dublin. He is the author of ''The Life of W. B. Yeats: A Critical Biography.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Terence Brown is professor of Anglo-Irish literature in Trinity College, Dublin. He is the author of ''The Life of W. B. Yeats: A Critical Biography.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
