<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lava Lamp Goes Here, Near The Fridge</title>
    <meta content="10BLAI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/weekinreview/10BLAIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dormitories</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DE1139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lava Lamp Goes Here, Near The Fridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>College students are taking as much stuff from home as they can when they move into their dormitories; college housing authorities say it has become an increasing challenge to fit the computers, stereo systems, refrigerators and other belongings into dorm rooms that were often built to hold two suitcases and a trunk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOSEPHINA FINAMORE, an 18-year-old sophomore from Wilmington, Del., thinks she has done a good job of making her small dormitory room at the University of Maryland in College Park feel like home. When the family's metallic gold Plymouth  Voyager was unpacked two weeks ago, she and her parents unloaded, among other things: a computer, two suitcases of clothes, a box of sweaters, a plastic storage bin full of running clothes and a trash bag full of shoes. She also brought items for the kitchen and bathroom, a CD player, photo albums, framed pictures and a light brown teddy bear that sits atop her blue, pink, yellow and green plaid sheets.</p>
        <p>Ms. Finamore and her roommates share, with others in a suite of rooms, several televisions, a microwave, a toaster, a large refrigerator for food and a smaller one reserved for beer. Then there's the Mardi Gras beads, the book of drinking games and the cup full of condoms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOSEPHINA FINAMORE, an 18-year-old sophomore from Wilmington, Del., thinks she has done a good job of making her small dormitory room at the University of Maryland in College Park feel like home. When the family's metallic gold Plymouth  Voyager was unpacked two weeks ago, she and her parents unloaded, among other things: a computer, two suitcases of clothes, a box of sweaters, a plastic storage bin full of running clothes and a trash bag full of shoes. She also brought items for the kitchen and bathroom, a CD player, photo albums, framed pictures and a light brown teddy bear that sits atop her blue, pink, yellow and green plaid sheets.</p>
        <p>Ms. Finamore and her roommates share, with others in a suite of rooms, several televisions, a microwave, a toaster, a large refrigerator for food and a smaller one reserved for beer. Then there's the Mardi Gras beads, the book of drinking games and the cup full of condoms.</p>
        <p>The days when students would show up at the end of summer with a trunk, a suitcase or two and a tennis racquet are long gone, say college administrators. Today, students have become hermit crabs and simply take everything with them when they move into dorms. The ideal seems to be as much stuff as it is possible to cram into their rooms.</p>
        <p>In interviews, college housing administrators say it has become an increasing challenge to accommodate the computers, bean bag chairs, stereo systems and futons that students are trying to pack into dorm rooms that were often built to hold two suitcases and a trunk. Meanwhile, from Pearson Hall at the University of Miami to the Oxford House at the University of Michigan, parents say they will need time to recover from helping their children move in.</p>
        <p>According to surveys by the Association of College and University Housing Officers International, based in Columbus, Ohio, students are bringing more than ever to campus. In many cases, they are trying to pack a U-Haul's worth of effects into half of a 12-by-15 room.</p>
        <p>In the early 1980's, administrators say, students began bringing electric typewriters to school. Later in the decade, small television sets and stereo systems began to appear. These days, as consumer electronics are increasingly seen by students as academic and social necessities, everything from CD players, bubble jet printers and computers to portable DVD's, large-screen televisions and electronic keyboards are finding their way into dorms.</p>
        <p>In addition, the introduction of computers into classrooms and Ethernet network connections in dorm rooms have made personal computers (and 24-hour access to e-mail and AOL Instant Messenger) the norm in college dorms, officials say.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL DeMAYO, a sophomore at the University of Miami, brought so much stuff this year that he uses a loft bed, which allows him to sleep up high and store lots of stuff under his bed.</p>
        <p>''I know a lot of people who have made their dorm rooms into mini-nightclubs,'' he said. ''They brought Christmas lights to put around their windows, strobe lights, black lights, disco balls, lava lamps.'' One person, he said, brought at 20-gallon fish tank.</p>
        <p>''With all the other stuff, it's sometimes hard to remember to bring notebooks for class,'' acknowledged one of Ms. Finamore's roommates, Emily Dammeyer, who brought an equally impressive collection of items to school with her.</p>
        <p>Allan J. Levy, an assistant housing director at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, which has not built a new dorm since 1968, says the fact that students are loading more into their rooms has caused a ''storage nightmare'' and that the vogue for electronics has created a significantly increased risk of fire. Moving in or out, which might have taken half an hour 25 years ago, can now take hours, he said. So great has the increase in baggage volume been over the years that the university has been forced to raise the number of days it allots for student moving to five. It was two in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>On the bright side, said Mr. Levy, who attended the university from 1970 to 1974, while technology may have created this problem, it seems to be solving it. ''I guess the saving grace is that certain parts of electronics are getting smaller rather than larger.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
