<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Designer Who Lives Like Her Clients</title>
    <meta content="10FISH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Eileen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Merri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DE1439F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Designer Who Lives Like Her Clients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Merri</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on fashion designer Eileen Fisher, suburban mother who lives in Irvington, NY, and creates simple clothing from style based on school uniforms; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a fashion cliche for designers to say they design for themselves, but in Eileen Fisher's case, it's true.</p>
        <p>As a working mother of two -- an 11-year-old son and a 7-year-old daughter -- who does the afternoon car pool, works from home to be with her children and takes part in charities and fund-raisers, Ms. Fisher really does live her clients' lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a fashion cliche for designers to say they design for themselves, but in Eileen Fisher's case, it's true.</p>
        <p>As a working mother of two -- an 11-year-old son and a 7-year-old daughter -- who does the afternoon car pool, works from home to be with her children and takes part in charities and fund-raisers, Ms. Fisher really does live her clients' lives.</p>
        <p>Small wonder, then, that her spare designs, expressed in simple shapes like kimono jackets, sleeveless shells, loose tunics and elastic waist skirts and slacks, which are made from fabrics like Irish linen, silk crepe or velvets, have become a uniform of sorts for Ms. Fisher's peers.</p>
        <p>It is not uncommon for stylish women here to check with one another to find out which ''Eileen'' has been selected for the coming wedding, bar mitzvah or charity event, so they don't duplicate outfits. In fact, Ms. Fisher, who recently turned 50, said, ''We have parties where the staff shows up in the same clothes.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's not surprising that Ms. Fisher has developed such an identifiable look.</p>
        <p>As a child growing up in suburban Chicago, she attended parochial schools, where a uniform was required. She never thought she would actually be a clothes designer: she began her college career as a math major. Her roommate was in visual design, and as Ms. Fisher became more disenchanted with higher mathematics, design seemed more and more appealing. By the time she reached New York City, the daily routine of getting dressed for work proved the impetus to a new career.</p>
        <p>''Just getting dressed in the morning was overwhelming,'' said Ms. Fisher, who admitted that she can't really draw and relied on someone else to help sew her clothes when she started to make her own designs.</p>
        <p>''Shopping would turn my stomach,'' she said. ''I felt a longing for my school uniform, a tweed jacket and textured skirt -- even though I hated it because my uniform didn't make me feel special.''</p>
        <p>Pared down to essentials, Ms. Fisher observed, the story of her company is ''a school uniform story.''</p>
        <p>''What we do is keep what's good about the school uniform, but not that limited,'' she said. ''It's a simplified system, like a Lego system, where it's simple pieces used in different ways.''</p>
        <p>From a sleek building between the Irvington train station and the Hudson River, Ms. Fisher presides over a company that generated $100 million in revenue last year. Ms. Fisher, who owns more than 80 percent of the company, started it in 1984 by borrowing money from friends.</p>
        <p>The decision to move here reflected Ms. Fisher's philosophy not only as a designer but also as a parent and an executive.</p>
        <p>''I had lived in TriBeCa and SoHo for 12 years,'' she said. ''I had had a loft space in a renovated warehouse and liked the idea of being in a warehouse by the river. I've always loved water and loved sunsets.</p>
        <p>''When we moved from the city, we wanted to keep the people we had, and I liked Irvington because people could come into the community, and they didn't need a car. Being here, people could have a little fuller life. We're close enough to the city, and I go to the showroom there once a week. I pick my kids up from school three days a week, and I can work from home, so I can spend time with them.''</p>
        <p>Her employees, too, are encouraged to balance family responsibility with community involvement. Even some employees who live in Manhattan are members of the Irvington volunteer ambulance corps, going out on calls during the work day.</p>
        <p>In many ways, the Eileen Fisher company reflects Ms. Fisher's beliefs and values. Her designs mirror Ms. Fisher's attitudes toward life.</p>
        <p>''It's not about money,'' she said. ''It's about people, friends, family and community and how people treat each other. There has to be natural growth. It can't be something you force.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the company's latest advertising campaign features employees who are self-described in their various roles (bookkeeper, wife, illustrator, mother) wearing Eileen Fisher designs.</p>
        <p>Community matters to Ms. Fisher. In 1999, the company donated 3 percent of pretax profits to charitable organizations, of which one-third are based in Westchester.</p>
        <p>For several years, the company's annual warehouse sale was a major charitable event, with 25 percent of the sales going to local projects, including the public schools and a women's shelter. Most years, there was a surplus of volunteers, lured by the chance to get first crack at the clothing.</p>
        <p>With the arrival of its own outlet stores, the company no longer holds a warehouse sale, though its donations continue.</p>
        <p>The company even has a manager of social accountability, Amy Hall, who had previously spent six years in public relations and community relations.</p>
        <p>''This position didn't even exist two years ago,'' Ms. Hall said. ''It grew out of the desire to address human rights issues in our factories.</p>
        <p>''One of Eileen's fundamental philosophies is that clothing should simplify women's lives. It felt natural to extend that to how we work with the community. It encompasses women who are facing crises in their lives, dealing with economic independence, domestic violence and health crises. We get about 40 requests a week and meet every eight weeks to discuss the requests.''</p>
        <p>As Ms. Fisher explained: ''What we do with trying to help women get dressed is bigger than their clothes. It's not about dictating, and it's not about just a business to sell fashion. It grew out of what I was looking for. I have no time, so I want to make it simple.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
