<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Moves From a Land Beyond Category</title>
    <meta content="10KISS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10KISS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1DA1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Moves From a Land Beyond Category</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff on France Moves, major festival of French contemporary dance that will include performances by ten experimental troupes in New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DIVERSITY, thy name is individuality. That may well be the message of ''France Moves,'' a major festival of French contemporary dance that will spread some 10 experimental troupes over three boroughs in New York from April 24 to May 6.</p>
        <p>Final programs (including film screenings and panel discussions) still have to be worked out. But the choreographers chosen by Yorgos Loukos, the artistic director of the Lyon Opera Ballet and of the new showcase, include Maguy Marin and Angelin Preljocaj, both well known from previous appearances here; Jose Montalvo and the hip-hop collective Kafig, both part of the New Europe Festival last year; and Fred Bendongue, seen at the American Dance Festival this summer and earlier at 651, the black arts center associated with the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DIVERSITY, thy name is individuality. That may well be the message of ''France Moves,'' a major festival of French contemporary dance that will spread some 10 experimental troupes over three boroughs in New York from April 24 to May 6.</p>
        <p>Final programs (including film screenings and panel discussions) still have to be worked out. But the choreographers chosen by Yorgos Loukos, the artistic director of the Lyon Opera Ballet and of the new showcase, include Maguy Marin and Angelin Preljocaj, both well known from previous appearances here; Jose Montalvo and the hip-hop collective Kafig, both part of the New Europe Festival last year; and Fred Bendongue, seen at the American Dance Festival this summer and earlier at 651, the black arts center associated with the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>Making their United States debut will be Philippe Decoufle, a mixed-media wizard who choreographed the ceremonies for the 1992 Winter Olympics, complete with bungee jumpers; Joseph Nadj, who favors Kafkaesque images; Dominique Boivin, whose solos suggest a gentle clown; and Boris Charmatz, whose mix of brain and brawn has made him French experimental dance's young golden boy.</p>
        <p>It seems only yesterday that Ms. Marin was part of the historic debut in 1983 by five young French companies at the American Dance Festival in Durham, N.C. -- a series of performances that revealed a nascent modern-dance boom in a country once dominated by ballet.</p>
        <p>Although sent over as a group by Association Francaise d'Action Artistique, the cultural arm of the French foreign ministry (which is also behind ''France Moves''), the choreographers in 1983 were unanimous on one point: They were making their United States debut not as representatives of France but as themselves.</p>
        <p>Indeed, to place the French in a category is to do so at one's peril. Certainly the choreographers who have emerged since 1980 have not lacked separate signatures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Preljocaj's work is even distinctive enough to have attracted the ire of an American presidential candidate. Typical of his exploration of instinct and gesture, his mesmerizing ''Annonciation'' depicted a tender encounter between the Virgin Mary and an angel portrayed by an androgynous woman. Patrick J. Buchanan did not see this female duet at the Joyce Theater in 1997, but denounced it nonetheless in his syndicated column as an assault on religious beliefs.</p>
        <p>The French government, for its part, rewarded Mr. Preljocaj that year with the Legion of Honor. Perhaps it knew more about how religious ecstasy has been depicted in the history of art. After all, it was a Frenchman, Charles de Brosse, who had this to say in 1739 about Bernini's famous sculpture of an angel hovering over St. Teresa's contracted body: ''If this is divine love, I know all about it.''</p>
        <p>It is not surprising that the inspiration for experimental choreographers in France often comes from art, literature and film. These reference points come from a major part of their culture.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the three generations of companies that will appear in Manhattan theaters (the Joyce, the New Victory, St. Mark's Church, the Kitchen and Florence Gould Hall), Brooklyn (the Academy of Music) and the Bronx (Hostos College) next spring will show a shift in focus since Ms. Marin, the group's senior choreographer, came to notice in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>For all their individuality, the 1983 choreographers had common themes. ''May B,'' Ms. Marin's poignant tribute to Samuel Beckett, was typical of a shared concern with the human condition. The 1983 choreographers (Ms. Marin, Karine Saporta, Dominique Bagouet, Caroline Marcade, Joelle Bouvier and Regis Obadia) were not alike. But most had a sensibility aligned with existentialist and absurdist theater. More often than not, their dancers failed to make connections, fell repeatedly and were hemmed in by darkness or closed doors.</p>
        <p>ALIENATION is not entirely absent from ''France Moves.'' Mr. Nadj, an ethnic Hungarian from Yugoslavia (think Monica Seles), will present ''Les Veilleurs,'' inspired by Kafka, with a cast of Hungarian-trained actors and French dancers. Expect his hallucinatory brand of relentless nightmares. Mr. Preljocaj's new ''Paysage Apres la Bataille'' draws upon the aesthetics of Joseph Conrad and Marcel Duchamp, a contrast that already sets up a picture of tension between instinct and intellect.</p>
        <p>Most of the choreographers opt for lighter, more playful imagery. But beneath the entertaining surface, there is a change from a pondering of the absurd to a concern with new reality and a celebration of cross-cultural differences.</p>
        <p>Modern dance in France is visibly reacting to a change in politics and in society. France is now a multicultural country, with an immigrant population that is the target of extreme right-wing propaganda.</p>
        <p>The new theme of most choreographers today is reconciliation within diversity. Mr. Montalvo and his co-choreographer, Dominique Hervieu, have recruited dancers from Guadeloupe to Africa to preach an antixenophobic message in their high-tech blend of video and live images. Their hip-hop virtuosos, as in other troupes, are often of North African and sub-Saharan African descent. Kafig uses the break-dance idiom with ultimate sophistication. Mr. Bendongue worked for many years with a hip-hop troupe. ''D'une Rive a l'Autre,'' his new piece, is concerned with identity in a multiracial world.</p>
        <p>That politics impinge directly on choreographers was obvious in 1995 when Mr. Preljocaj rejected a post at an arts center in protest of a victory by the extreme right in nearby Toulon. Ms. Marin, who will present a new trio, ''Pour Ainsi Dire,'' has chosen to work in a tough immigrant suburb of Lyon.</p>
        <p>Although some of the choreographers are children of foreign political exiles, it is hard to think of them as anything but French. By extension, Mr. Decoufle, Mr. Boivin and Mr. Preljocaj have studied in France and New York with Americans including Alwin Nikolais, Merce Cunningham, Viola Farber, Carolyn Carlson and Douglas Dunn. Yet their choreography does not have the formal look of American experimental dance.</p>
        <p>Rooted in different experiences, these choreographers could be compared to the painters of the School of Paris between the two world wars: their origins are varied, and France has allowed them to be themselves.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
