<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rockville Centre Landmark's New Role</title>
    <meta content="10DINE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rockville Centre (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Monte's (Restaurant) (Rockville Centre, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DE1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rockville Centre Landmark's New Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Monte's restaurant in Rockville Centre, New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN recent years, steakhouses have popped up across the Island like fall mushrooms after a rainy summer. Monte's, which opened in mid-July, has emerged as the best of this year's crop.</p>
        <p>Its location is a familiar one to Rockville Centre residents. Generations knew it as the Lincoln Inn. Monte's has turned the landmark building into an old-fashioned, masculine steakhouse. The main dining room makes a bold statement with dark wood breakfronts, shining wood floors and massive chandeliers. Other rooms are wood-paneled but carpeted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN recent years, steakhouses have popped up across the Island like fall mushrooms after a rainy summer. Monte's, which opened in mid-July, has emerged as the best of this year's crop.</p>
        <p>Its location is a familiar one to Rockville Centre residents. Generations knew it as the Lincoln Inn. Monte's has turned the landmark building into an old-fashioned, masculine steakhouse. The main dining room makes a bold statement with dark wood breakfronts, shining wood floors and massive chandeliers. Other rooms are wood-paneled but carpeted.</p>
        <p>Local residents will also know the restaurateurs. Raymond and Margaret Montemurro have won fans at Dodici and Blue Moon, two popular Italian spots just a few blocks away.  Their experience shows in the well-trained dining room staff. The meal flows smoothly: bread and butter are delivered and menus presented before patrons are even settled into their chairs.</p>
        <p>Steak is the big story here, and the good news is that it's great. The porterhouse for two, the sirloin and the sliced sirloin atop a bed of sauteed mushrooms, onions and peppers all drew raves. So did a trio of thick cooked-to-order lamb chops.</p>
        <p>Waiters are not the curmudgeons diners have come to expect at steakhouses. These fellows do not slam down platters and bark at customers. They explain the specials, know the menu and serve the food with finesse. Crunchy asparagus sauteed in oil with garlic was expertly served to each diner and so was the creamed spinach, which arrived at the table in a large bowl. (Both of these a la carte vegetables were selections I'd definitely order again, by the way.)</p>
        <p>Two minor service flaws should be mentioned. Water is not served automatically. We had to ask, but then it was promptly poured. The other slip-up concerned the description of the Park Avenue salad. It is essentially a chopped salad, but our waiter never mentioned anchovies when itemizing the ingredients. That assertive flavor is not a universal favorite, and diners should be warned.</p>
        <p>But anchovy fans will find the salad a stellar opener. Monte's salad of crisp cut green beans, chopped tomatoes, onions, shrimp and bacon is another crowd pleaser. And the large classic Caesar will delight those who demand the real thing.</p>
        <p>The list of cold appetizers contains a trio of spectacular, though pricey ($11.95 to $13.95) seafood choices: shrimp cocktail (four firm jumbos), a mountain of lump crab meat and a one-pound lobster, split and served on a bed of ice. All three arrive with ramekins of cocktail and Dijon sauces. Another worthy cold starter is the plate of paper-thin carpaccio topped with an arugula salad, shaved Parmesan and tiny black olives.</p>
        <p>The only letdown among the appetizers was the hot shrimp Dijon. Its breading quickly turned soggy in the tangy mustard sauce.</p>
        <p>A soup of the day, cream of beefsteak tomato with basil and tender shelled clams, gets a thumbs-up. It also gave the chef a chance to be creative.</p>
        <p>He gets another chance to shine with the daily specials. Unlike the menu listings, these entrees arrive fully decked out with sauces, vegetables and potatoes. Especially appealing were two marinated grilled pork loin chops atop a mound of cheese-laced mashed potatoes, the plate decorated with a sprinkling of diced apple and long, slim slices of carrot. A special of two veal chops over garlic mashed potatoes in a tasty brown sauce, served with crisp asparagus spears, was its equal.</p>
        <p>Good seafood choices were the sweet steamed lobsters (two one-pounders for $35) and the moist broiled swordfish presented under a mantle of yellow and red tomatoes and basil.</p>
        <p>The half-and-half platter of cottage fries (crisp homemade potato chips) and thin, wispy onion rings is the side dish to order. The hash browns and thick, wedgelike French fries were ordinary.</p>
        <p>Desserts are a combination of homemade and commercial treats. The homemade creme brulee with its crackling surface of caramelized sugar is the top pick. The cheesecake and tiramisu are acceptable, but I've had richer, creamier versions. Among the brought-in sweets, the silken chocolate mousse cake and the warm apple strudel are the best bets.</p>
        <p>Monte's  54 Lincoln Avenue, Rockville Centre (516) 536-1500.</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Bold, woody, turn-of-the-century steakhouse.  SERVICE -- Friendly, competent waiters.  SOUND LEVEL -- Average. Despite bare wood floors in the main dining room, it is not as loud as one might expect.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Tomato soup with clams, Monte salad, Park Avenue salad, Caesar salad, shrimp cocktail, crab meat cocktail, lobster cocktail, carpaccio, all steaks, lamb chops, lobsters, swordfish, marinated pork loin, veal chop special, half-and-half platter, asparagus, creamed spinach, creme brulee, chocolate mousse cake, apple strudel.  WINE LIST -- A California-skewed list (Italy is a distant second) with more than 150 selections starting at $20 and going to $400.  PRICE RANGE -- The dinner menu is available at lunch, along with an $8.95 hamburger, two steak specials (soup or salad plus potato and vegetable) for $14.95 each and a list of daily specials.  At dinner, appetizers $4.95 to $13.95, entrees $12.95 to $31.95 (lobsters higher).  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  HOURS -- Lunch noon to 4 p.m. Monday through Friday, dinner 5 to 10 p.m. Monday through Thursday, to 10:30 p.m. Friday and Saturday and 3 to 10 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Two steps at entrance.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT E-mail: lidining@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lidining@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
