<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books In Brief: Nonfiction</title>
    <meta content="RV101531" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Dagens, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsberg, Debra</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Waiting: The True Confessions of a Waitress (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3DA1230F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books In Brief: Nonfiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margaret Van Dagens</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Dagens, Margaret</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margaret Van Dagens reviews book Waiting: The True Confessions of a Waitress by Debra Ginsberg (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WAITING</p>
        <p>The True Confessions of a Waitress.</p>
        <p>By Debra Ginsberg.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WAITING</p>
        <p>The True Confessions of a Waitress.</p>
        <p>By Debra Ginsberg.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins. $22.</p>
        <p>At the age of 16, Debra Ginsberg thought waitressing in her father's Catskills luncheonette was an adventure but did not see it as a way of life. Yet, almost without planning, that is what it became. In ''Waiting,'' she writes about the work she does and people she has met as a waitress. Her first job at the luncheonette was ''irresistible'' because of Steve, a bold, good-looking guy who sat at the counter drinking soda. Ginsberg captures all the promise of warm summer nights and teenage romances when she writes about Steve, in the first of her candid but lean accounts of personal experiences. Through high school and college waitressing kept its ''glitzy appeal'' and provided spending money. After graduation, she had vague ideas about becoming a novelist, but she needed to earn a living. So back to waitressing -- temporarily, she thought. Instead, she found every new table was an adventure, collecting stories about customers and people she has worked with: Leo, the chef from Colorado, who talked about planning a life with her but never mentioned his wife; Belinda, who taught her skills like opening wine bottles without putting them down; John, who fathered her son during a relationship that ''came apart so rapidly.'' Ginsberg believes waitressing is not seen as a desirable career and is considered low-class. She defends her work by discussing the mental, physical and social skills needed for ''short, intense periods of time.'' Ginsberg finds it satisfying to be part of ''one of the last customer service industries to flourish.'' She writes positively but not Pollyannaishly and has told an attractive story about coping with a life that has been different than what she expected.</p>
        <p>Margaret Van Dagens</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
