<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old Southern Strategy Faces Test in Selma Vote</title>
    <meta content="Y10SELM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/politics/10SELM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Selma (Ala)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smitherman, Joe (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perkins, James Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5DE1139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old Southern Strategy Faces Test in Selma Vote</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <dateline>SELMA, Ala., Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph T Smitherman, former segregationist who has been mayor of Selma, Ala, for past 35 years is locked in political fight of his life; has been forced for first time into runoff election against black candidate James Perkins Jr and has made race an issue; is promoting himself as candidate of diversity, preventing city government from being engulfed by blacks; is appealing to black fear of ruined economy, by citing several examples of black-run towns that have gone bankrupt; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 35 years, Mayor Joseph T. Smitherman's high-wire act above the city's churning racial politics had begun to settle into routine. Every four years, he would hold barbecues in black neighborhoods, boasting about the number of black department heads he had appointed, while reminding white voters that he would be ''the last white mayor of Selma,'' hinting that the racial deluge was around the corner.</p>
        <p>But this year, Mr. Smitherman has found himself in the fight of his life, forced for the first time into a runoff election -- on Tuesday -- against a black candidate, and the hints have become a bit less subtle. Now, in the city that became the blood-stained symbol of the fight for voting rights, the former segregationist is promoting himself as the candidate of diversity, preventing city government from being engulfed by blacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 35 years, Mayor Joseph T. Smitherman's high-wire act above the city's churning racial politics had begun to settle into routine. Every four years, he would hold barbecues in black neighborhoods, boasting about the number of black department heads he had appointed, while reminding white voters that he would be ''the last white mayor of Selma,'' hinting that the racial deluge was around the corner.</p>
        <p>But this year, Mr. Smitherman has found himself in the fight of his life, forced for the first time into a runoff election -- on Tuesday -- against a black candidate, and the hints have become a bit less subtle. Now, in the city that became the blood-stained symbol of the fight for voting rights, the former segregationist is promoting himself as the candidate of diversity, preventing city government from being engulfed by blacks.</p>
        <p>''Everywhere that you've gone all black, the towns have gone down,'' he said between cigarettes in his office, citing several examples of black-run towns that have gone bankrupt. ''You need white inclusion, you need diversity in the city government. Let's face it, the whites have the money, the white business people. They tend to pull back when it goes all black. So that's what I'm trying to get across to the blacks.''</p>
        <p>Unfiltered and raw, appealing even to black fear of a ruined economy, this is hardly the velvety approach of the typical New South white politician. But racial politics in Selma has always been a few degrees more blunt than average. Many of the city's white business leaders -- the ones supposedly heading for the door -- shake their heads at Mr. Smitherman's argument.</p>
        <p>''Joe Smitherman can call up Armageddon as well as any Southern preacher, and that's what he's doing,'' said Richard P. Morthland, chairman and chief executive of The Peoples Bank and Trust Company, the city's largest locally owned bank. ''I don't know of any business that would leave town just because we have a black mayor.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the mayor's arguments have proved remarkably effective over the years. Though he was mayor on that bloody March Sunday in 1965 when sheriff's deputies and state troopers attacked hundreds of people marching across the Edmund Pettus Bridge for voting rights, he argued persuasively that he and his police had nothing to do with the beatings. He has made a career out of renouncing his former support for segregation, making sure he spread city services evenly in black and white neighborhoods. Now 70 years old, he has been re-elected nine times since 1964, despite repeated efforts to unseat him by black candidates in a city of 21,000 that is now 65 percent black.</p>
        <p>But last month, James Perkins Jr., a former computer consultant, came as close as anyone ever has to defeating him. Mr. Perkins won 43 percent of the vote, just 276 votes behind Mr. Smitherman at 46 percent. A second black candidate, City Councilman Yusuf Abdus-Salaam, won 10 percent of the vote, forcing the two leading candidates into a runoff on Tuesday.  Mr. Salaam, who leads the city's Muslim community, has accused Mr. Perkins of ''religious bigotry'' and appears to be siding with the mayor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perkins, 47, who has run against Mr. Smitherman twice before, contends this effort will turn out differently. While black voters are increasingly put off by the mayor's condescension, he said, white voters are also disenchanted by Mr. Smitherman's performance. Last year, the city's former police chief and former city clerk, along with Mr. Smitherman's nephew, pleaded guilty to embezzling more than $700,000 from the city through fraudulent billings. The mayor said he knew nothing about the theft.</p>
        <p>''It's his job to know what's going on,'' Mr. Perkins said. ''And at the same time, he's allowing a huge disparity in the quality of life between black and white neighborhoods, and now he's trying to divide the city by saying industry will leave if I'm elected. This is obviously a mayor who's panicking.''</p>
        <p>Many residents say the mayor has not done enough to improve the city's economy, which has suffered like much of the rural South from a continuing drain of manufacturing jobs. (The county's unemployment rate in July was 10.7 percent, compared with Alabama's rate of 4.4 percent.) Racial tensions continued to bubble in Selma long after the marches ended, particularly in 1990 when the city's first black schools superintendent was dismissed and protests closed the city schools.</p>
        <p>Although black officials now dominate the City Council and the County Commission, there has long been an outspoken faction of blacks, led by State Senator Hank Sanders and his wife, Rose Sanders, that has worked to remove Mr. Smitherman. The group has plastered the city with posters saying ''Joe's Gotta Go,'' although the Sanderses say they are not working directly for Mr. Perkins.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Perkins and his supporters point to a few criticisms of Mr. Smitherman's administration, their main argument against him is that he has never really left his segregationist core. They liken him to the former Gov. George C. Wallace as one who changed his language to suit the times, but could never escape his past.</p>
        <p>As often as he has heard it, this argument still infuriates the mayor. Rummaging furiously through his office, he pulls out a campaign flier showing that 9 of 13 department heads are black, and digs through drawers to unearth tributes he has received over the years from black leaders.</p>
        <p>''They know I'm not the devil they say I am, but Selma's their mecca,'' Mr. Smitherman said. ''They want Selma because this is where it all happened, where people got the right to vote. What really bothers them is that this place of all places has a white mayor, but I still keep getting elected, don't I?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
