<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scott Simon and Caroline Richard</title>
    <meta content="10VOWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/living/10VOWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARD, CAROLINE (CAROLINE SIMON)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMON, SCOTT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richard, Caroline</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Lois Smith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Julian, Alexander</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DA1339F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scott Simon and Caroline Richard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOIS SMITH BRADY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Simon, National Public Radio host, and Caroline Richard, documentary filmmmaker, wed at home of designer Alexander Julian in Ridgefield, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE host of ''Weekend Edition With Scott Simon'' on National Public Radio has a voice that's just right for reading a bedtime story to a child. Yet Mr. Simon's observations and questions never put you to sleep, whether he is reporting on Al Gore, a hospital in Kosovo, surfing or the death of his cat. (He did an obituary for her on the air.)</p>
        <p>''I once heard Scott interviewing a steelworker, and he said, 'If you could make pink plastic flamingos and earn as much money as you do making steel, would you make pink plastic flamingos?' '' said Jacki Lyden, a host for ''All Things Considered'' on NPR. ''Unlike so many people, men especially, Scott sees that whimsy is a necessary part of life. It's a huge part of his life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE host of ''Weekend Edition With Scott Simon'' on National Public Radio has a voice that's just right for reading a bedtime story to a child. Yet Mr. Simon's observations and questions never put you to sleep, whether he is reporting on Al Gore, a hospital in Kosovo, surfing or the death of his cat. (He did an obituary for her on the air.)</p>
        <p>''I once heard Scott interviewing a steelworker, and he said, 'If you could make pink plastic flamingos and earn as much money as you do making steel, would you make pink plastic flamingos?' '' said Jacki Lyden, a host for ''All Things Considered'' on NPR. ''Unlike so many people, men especially, Scott sees that whimsy is a necessary part of life. It's a huge part of his life.''</p>
        <p>At NPR's offices in Washington, Mr. Simon, 48, is known for his dapper clothes and for broadcasting in suits with pocket handkerchiefs to match his (sometimes red) socks. He was also known as a longtime and not unhappy bachelor. Robert Siegel, another ''All Things Considered'' host, said Mr. Simon once remarked, ''I've led the best life one could lead, and I'm not forgetting Warren Beatty when I say that.''</p>
        <p>Then, in April, Caroline Richard, 33, visited NPR to talk about a documentary film she was working on. (She had been an intern at NPR in the early 1990's, when Mr. Simon was away covering the Persian Gulf war.) She was introduced to Mr. Simon, who liked her right away. ''She has a very quick and a wide-ranging, probing, searching mind,'' he said. ''It is always interesting to pay a visit to it. And her beauty is breathtaking. Before I met her, I'd hardly been lonely, but this was the first time I'd been hit over the head by a two-by-four.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Simon, Ms. Richard loves Coney Island, Graham Greene novels and riding the subway for whole weekend afternoons. She grew up in San Francisco in a household of European tradition. ''My mother, who is French, made all of our clothes, and we wore braids and clogs,'' she said. ''We got teased endlessly. I was voted most unique in high school, and it was not a compliment.''</p>
        <p>She went to the University of California at Berkeley, studied international politics in Paris and wound up in New York at Gabriel Films, which specializes in prison documentaries. When she met Mr. Simon, she lived in a tiny Chinatown apartment in Manhattan, furnished with a futon, flowering plants and piles of books. ''She's the brilliant one,'' said Muriel Price, one of Ms. Richard's sisters. ''She goes over our heads a lot.''</p>
        <p>A few weeks after they met, Mr. Simon invited her to a party at Ms. Lyden's apartment in Brooklyn to celebrate the publication of his memoir, ''Home and Away.'' As Mr. Simon arrived, he hit his head on the taxi door and walked into the party bleeding. ''He always knows how to make an entrance,'' Ms. Lyden said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simon added: ''I had what amounted to a war wound. While I talked to Caroline, I had to hold a cold compress on my head, alternating between my right hand and my left.''</p>
        <p>She was nevertheless charmed. ''I realized he was human and full of a great sense of humor about the world and also about himself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Days later, they had their first real date, at a tiny downtown bistro, talking in the back garden until closing time. ''At that moment, I knew I was going to spend the rest of my life with him,'' Ms. Richard said. ''We both felt it, and we acted on it.''</p>
        <p>In July, she moved into his apartment at the Watergate in Washington.</p>
        <p>Last Sunday, they were married in a Methodist, Quaker, Jewish service in Ridgefield, Conn., at the home of Alexander Julian, the men's wear designer, a family friend of the bride. There was a traditional Quaker period of silence during the service, and although the bride was clearly trying to stay quiet, little laughs kept escaping from her like bubbles.</p>
        <p>''When Caroline began to giggle during the two minutes of silence, it confirmed everything for me,'' Mr. Simon said afterward. ''That's exactly the reaction I want from my life's companion.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
