<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Samaranch's Legacy: An Olympic Savior or a Spoiler?</title>
    <meta content="10SAMA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/sports/10SAMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Salt Lake City (Utah)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Samaranch, Juan Antonio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MacAloon, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Honecker, Erich</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah/Salt Lake City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3D61139F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Samaranch's Legacy: An Olympic Savior or a Spoiler?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International Olympic Committee President Juan Antonio Samaranch prepares to retire after 20 years, having transformed Olympic movement to where it has never been more successful, or more threatened; under his leadership, nearly bankrupt IOC that he took over now generates more than $900 million in annual revenues, mostly from television and corporate sponsorships; women are involved in large numbers as atheletes and administrators; called most significant leader in modern Olympic history by Olympic historian John MacAloon; corruption, especially bidding for Salt Lake City games, tarnishes his legacy, as does award of Olympic Order to East German President Erich Honecker, move that is criticized as giving tacit approval to state-sponsored doping; opening Olympics to professional athletes is thought to have created tedium in some sports; photo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Summer Games begin here on Friday, Juan Antonio Samaranch will preside over his final Olympiad before retiring next year, having transformed the modern Olympic movement to where it has never been more successful, or more threatened.</p>
        <p>When Samaranch, the former Spanish ambassador to the Soviet Union, became president of the International Olympic Committee in 1980, the organization was nearly bankrupt and was caught in a maelstrom of boycotts that continued through the 1984 Summer Games in Los Angeles. Now, as Samaranch prepares to step down next July at age 81, the I.O.C. generates $900 million a year in revenues, mostly from television and corporate sponsorship. NBC television alone will pay $3.5 billion to broadcast the five Games between now and 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Summer Games begin here on Friday, Juan Antonio Samaranch will preside over his final Olympiad before retiring next year, having transformed the modern Olympic movement to where it has never been more successful, or more threatened.</p>
        <p>When Samaranch, the former Spanish ambassador to the Soviet Union, became president of the International Olympic Committee in 1980, the organization was nearly bankrupt and was caught in a maelstrom of boycotts that continued through the 1984 Summer Games in Los Angeles. Now, as Samaranch prepares to step down next July at age 81, the I.O.C. generates $900 million a year in revenues, mostly from television and corporate sponsorship. NBC television alone will pay $3.5 billion to broadcast the five Games between now and 2008.</p>
        <p>Boycotts are no longer a serious threat; cities are eagerly bidding to play host to the Games; corporations are shelling out $50 million apiece to become official Olympic sponsors; athletes can build long, lucrative careers as professionals; and women are involved in larger numbers than ever as administrators and participants. During his presidency, Samaranch has increased the number of female I.O.C. members from zero to 13 and the percentage of female Olympians from 21 percent to 42 percent. Athletes from 199 nations will participate in Sydney, compared with 80 at the 1980 Summer Games in Moscow, which more than 50 countries, including the United States, boycotted.</p>
        <p>With the exception of Pierre de Coubertin, the French baron who founded the modern Games in 1896, Samaranch ''has been the most significant leader in modern Olympic history,'' said John MacAloon, an Olympic historian and professor of social sciences at the University of Chicago. ''The greatest single accomplishment has been a kind of political maturity, an ability to deal with political elites, heads of state, industrial elites. That was something the movement never really had.''</p>
        <p>According to the I.O.C., the Sydney Games will reach a record audience, about 3.7 billion of the 3.9 billion people worldwide who have access to television. Even David D'Alessandro, the president and chief executive officer of John Hancock and Samaranch's most vocal corporate critic in the wake of the Salt Lake City bribery scandal, has signed on for another four years of Olympic sponsorship.</p>
        <p>''My feeling in the end was that the Games were going to emerge hurt, but not fatally wounded,'' D'Alessandro said. ''I'm encouraged that what the Olympics stand for continues to grow. No one really believes in the efficacy of professional sports. There are an awful lot of clouds around college sports. The Olympics are the last kind of major sport people can believe in the purity of.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Olympics have been devalued by scandal and the pervasive use of performance-enhancing drugs, and they have grown so big that they have become in some ways unmanageable for the host cities. Sydney, which will welcome 700,000 visitors, 10,438 athletes and 21,046 media representatives, struggled with its train service and airport baggage handling system even before the crush of arrivals began. And the New South Wales state government, which is underwriting the Games, had to issue bailouts of $56.7 million in May and $84.8 million in June to organizers because the cost of the Sydney Games had escalated to $1.8 billion.</p>
        <p>While almost no one believes the Olympics will end any time soon, Olympic officials, sponsors and independent experts cautioned that a failure to address these threats could affect the survival of the Games in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there will ever be again a golden age of the Olympic movement as existed between the Games of Los Angeles in 1984 and Atlanta in '96,'' said John Krimsky, a former executive director of the United States Olympic Committee.</p>
        <p>Donna de Varona, a gold medalist in swimming in 1964, has long been an activist for women's sports and a prominent figure in the fight against doping. She said she sees troubling similarities between the current Games and the ancient ones, which had problems with professionalism, corruption, cheating and bribery before collapsing after a millennium in 393 A.D. It was 1,500 years before the Games were revived.</p>
        <p>''I think we are on parallel tracks,'' de Varona said. ''I think the Games are coming to an important crossroads.''</p>
        <p>Corruption Uncovered</p>
        <p>Corruption, drugs and the unwieldy size of the Games can be attributed to two things, Samaranch's supporters and detractors say. First, in his attempt to return the whole world to the Olympics after crippling boycotts in the 1970's and 1980's, Samaranch made a number of decisions based on strategy or expediency rather than principle. Second, he seldom said no.</p>
        <p>Samaranch also made a habit of co-opting his enemies, saying, ''It is better to have them inside than outside.'' But sometimes that strategy came back to embarrass him.</p>
        <p>Jean-Claude Ganga of Congo Republic had been an anti-apartheid activist who led the African boycott of the 1976 Summer Games in Montreal. In 1986, Samaranch made him a member of the I.O.C., and problems with African participation dissolved. But last year, Ganga came to represent the most brazen example of the corrupted bidding process.</p>
        <p>Ganga, an investigation revealed, accepted more than $300,000 in cash payments, medical treatment, travel expenses and even doorknobs and knee-replacement surgery for his mother-in-law while Salt Lake City was trying to win the bidding for the 2002 Winter Games.</p>
        <p>How did Samaranch, a man of such political savvy, allow the bidding process to become so corrupted, leading to the resignation or dismissal of Ganga and nine other of the I.O.C.'s 113 members?</p>
        <p>There are several reasons, say those who have studied the Olympic movement or who know Samaranch. Samaranch is an imperial man who likes to be pampered, said John Lucas, an Olympic historian and retired professor at Penn State University. Sam Ramsamy, an I.O.C. member from South Africa, said Samaranch has longed for a Nobel Peace Prize and perhaps in the final years of his presidency he did not want to ''rock the boat'' and threaten his legacy.  Samaranch was a sports bureaucrat and a parliamentary leader in Spain during Franco's dictatorship, D'Alessandro noted, when a good deal of corruption was tolerated.</p>
        <p>''If Samaranch had snapped his fingers, this wouldn't have happened,'' Lucas said. ''He either was unaware, looked the other way or thought it was harmless. What we need is an I.O.C. that is incorruptible, like Eliot Ness made the F.B.I. We need a group of individuals wedded to the Olympic principles, nonpolitical individuals who cannot be bought.''</p>
        <p>Samaranch said in a recent interview that he should probably have retired after the 1992 Summer Games in Barcelona, Spain. Yet in 1995, he pushed through a rule change that raised the age limit for president so that he could continue. It was also Samaranch, having realized the seriousness of the Salt Lake City scandal, who pushed through a number of reforms. The leader who in the past had been secretive and autocratic  threw open the I.O.C.'s books, pushed through term limits and persuaded members to vote against visiting the cities that are bidding on the Games.</p>
        <p>''Our organization was hurt, but not the Olympic Games,'' Samaranch said.</p>
        <p>Polling done by the I.O.C. and the U.S.O.C. shows that people have made a separation between corrupt officials and the Games themselves. Mitt Romney, the venture capitalist brought in to save the Salt Lake City Games, said that the scandal, construction noise and traffic problems had made him uncertain whether he would vote to hold the 2002 Winter Games in Utah if he had to make the choice now. But he also said that Salt Lake City was obligated to put on the best Games possible.</p>
        <p>''I see the Olympics as the last great demonstration of peace in the world,'' Romney said.</p>
        <p>The Sydney Games carry some of the same tarnish as Salt Lake City. Sydney won the 2000 Summer Games by two votes over Beijing; the night before the vote, Sydney officials promised $35,000 apiece to I.O.C. members from Kenya and Uganda. And both Australian I.O.C. members were implicated during the recent scandal investigations, one for excessive travel in the Salt Lake City case and for helping to write dossiers about his fellow members; the other for giving his daughter a preferred place in the Olympic torch relay.</p>
        <p>The Salt Lake City scandal also confirmed for a number of athletes and their representatives what they had believed all along, that they were a low priority with the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>''The Olympics could end as far as I'm concerned,'' said Jos Hermens, a distance runner for the Netherlands at the 1972 Munich Games who is now a sports agent. ''They have no meaning. It's a false dream. They build the illusion of brotherhood, but it's just a commercial venture. It's a bunch of old people misusing old-fashioned dreams for their own purposes. It's like a cult. These people are addicted to power.''</p>
        <p>How the power shifts after Samaranch's retirement will be of great interest to American corporate sponsors, which account for about 70 percent of the I.O.C.'s commercial income. D'Alessandro, of John Hancock, said that given the scrutiny of the Salt Lake City scandal by the American sponsors, Congress and the media, anti-American sentiment within the I.O.C. has never been higher. If this sentiment keeps the Games from returning to the United States soon, he said, American sponsors will drop out.</p>
        <p>''They've got to be careful not to have the American public turn on them,'' D'Alessandro said. ''When you enter a Faustian bargain with sponsors, you better have people around who understand Faustian bargains.''</p>
        <p>Drug Problems</p>
        <p>At an I.O.C. meeting in East Berlin in 1985, Samaranch presented Erich Honecker, the East German president, with the highest honor he could bestow, the Olympic Order. It was another pragmatic move by Samaranch, who, a year after the Eastern bloc boycott of the 1984 Games in Los Angeles, was seeking to head off further boycotts at the 1988 Summer Games in Seoul, South Korea. It worked. East Germany competed in Seoul the year before the Berlin Wall fell.</p>
        <p>But awarding the Olympic Order to Honecker, an honor that had also been bestowed on Manfred Ewald, who was president of the East German Olympic Committee, was roundly criticized as giving at least tacit approval to state-sponsored doping -- a system that was long suspected and has since been revealed in courts and in released documents.</p>
        <p>In July, Ewald was convicted of masterminding the doping program in East Germany and was given a 22-month suspended jail sentence. In a country where sport was used to validate Communist ideology, the doping system affected as many as 10,000 athletes, many without their knowledge. A number of the athletes now have heart, kidney and liver problems.</p>
        <p>The failure to curb the East German doping program, which was an open secret, ''is the Olympic movement's biggest failure,'' said Rob Housman, an associate of Gen. Barry R. McCaffrey in the White House drug policy office. ''They knew this stuff was going on. For years, it was willful blindness.''</p>
        <p>Only after the French police uncovered widespread doping at the 1998 Tour de France did an embarrassed I.O.C. rededicate itself to the problem of performance-enhancing drugs. For too long, the I.O.C. treated the issue as a public relations problem instead of a drug problem, said Frank Shorter, the 1972 Olympic marathon champion, who will head an independent drug-testing agency in the United States after the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>''Every 14-year-old kid knows that to be in strength and endurance sports, if he wants to go on with his career, 'I have to go on these drugs,' '' Shorter said.</p>
        <p>Drug use has become so pervasive that cheaters have been caught recently even in table tennis, badminton and synchronized swimming. Samaranch suggested last year that only drugs that are considered harmful to an athlete's health should be banned. An uproar followed, and he backed down. He created the World Anti-Doping Agency, meant to be independent of the I.O.C., then decided he wanted to head the agency. Governments around the world, however, rebuffed his attempt.</p>
        <p>The I.O.C. did make one significant change for the Sydney Games, approving a blood test for the endurance drug known by its initials as EPO, which is believed to be widely used in distance running, cycling and swimming. Independent monitors will also try to make sure positive results are not covered up, which had been widely suspected in the past. ''We've come a long way, but we've got a long way to go,'' said McCaffrey, the White House drug policy director.</p>
        <p>Drug tests will not be available in Sydney for human growth hormone, insulin growth factor and products that serve as a kind of artificial blood. Testing still remains so deficient that athletes cannot prove their innocence, and athletes at the Sydney Olympics will have to live with the suspicion that accompanies successful performances.</p>
        <p>''The fact is, the I.O.C. is scared about what could happen if a large number of great athletes were caught,'' said Ian Thorpe, the Australian teenage swimming sensation and an anti-drug advocate. ''What would their image be? I think something has to be done in the long term or the Olympics will be absolutely ruined.''</p>
        <p>Samaranch's resolve on the drug issue was again called into question last month when the International Amateur Athletic  Federation, track and field's world governing body, cut in half the two-year ban on Javier Sotomayor, the Cuban world record-holder and 1992 Olympic champion in the high jump. Sotomayor tested positive for cocaine at the 1999 Pan American Games. Cocaine can serve as a stimulant during competition. Samaranch kept quiet, allowing a known drug user into the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>''It would have been helpful to say, 'I won't allow this athlete into my Games,' '' said de Varona, the 1964 swimming champion and a member of the World Anti-Doping Agency's ethics committee. ''Instead, he turned his head and compromised himself.''</p>
        <p>Matters of Size</p>
        <p>Samaranch has lobbied the presidents of North and South Korea to march as one country during the opening ceremonies on Friday in Sydney. Iran and Iraq, also mortal enemies, will file into the stadium, one behind the other. More than any other moment in sport, the opening ceremonies of the Olympic Games demonstrate the possibility of an international community. The growing size of the Games, however, has threatened their ability to be well organized.</p>
        <p>Four years ago in Atlanta, bus drivers frequently got lost and the I.B.M. computer system could not deliver results in a timely manner. Anita DeFrantz, an American I.O.C. member, suggested that Sydney residents avoid using the city's buses and trains for non-Games activity.</p>
        <p>The problem, known as ''gigantism'' among Olympic officials, has limited the number of cities that can afford to be host of the Games and has become so acute that significant changes in the organization of the Games are being proposed. Princess Anne, an I.O.C. member from Britain, has called for the removal of all team sports. A number of people have suggested rotating the Games among a few cities or establishing a permanent site.</p>
        <p>Samaranch opened the Olympics to professionals after the 1988 Seoul Games as a way to bring the world's best athletes to the Games. This ended what many believed was the hypocrisy of amateurism and allowed athletes to build careers over several Games. But it also made athletes less dependent on the Olympics; they can now earn a living in their sports, which have yearly competitions and world championships that offer prize money.</p>
        <p>Professionalism also has created tedium in some sports; in basketball, for example, the American men's Dream Teams have gone unchallenged. The end of the cold war, too, has eliminated the supercharged political drama that once accompanied competitions between the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>''To see the Dream Team there, the N.H.L. players, I think the Olympics has lost its purpose, perhaps,'' said Bruce Arena, coach of the American men's national soccer team, who was the Olympic coach in 1996. ''When millionaires are winning gold medals all the time, it takes away from the Olympics I remember 40 years ago.''</p>
        <p>Because the Olympics were growing so large and unmanageable, the I.O.C. separated the years in which the Winter and Summer Games took place after 1992. Sponsors and various national Olympic committees were finding it prohibitive to spend so much money in one year. Now, there is a Winter or Summer Games every two years.</p>
        <p>But the increased frequency has cost the Olympics their novelty, and they must compete for attention on crowded sports calendars. This is especially true this month, when the Games coincide with baseball's pennant races and football in the United States and soccer in Europe.</p>
        <p>''They've lost the symbolism that this is a powerful event, held once and only once every four years, and an important connection with a kind of Greek and calendar model in which people live their lives in four-year increments,'' said MacAloon, the Olympic historian.</p>
        <p>A year from now, none of this will be Samaranch's problem. It will be up to the next generation of leaders to combat the problems of corruption, drugs and size. Relevancy could also become an issue.</p>
        <p>''One thing one has to guard against is that over time, professional events, or events that have commercialism, have run their course,'' D'Alessandro, of John Hancock, said. ''We've seen it happen in the N.F.L. and the N.B.A. They wax and wane. The Olympics have been on the rise. There's going to be a trough period where there may not be as much interest. That's a challenge for the new players.''</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
