<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Capture the Poignancy of the Period</title>
    <meta content="10PSIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haddonfield (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolodi, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D81539F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Capture the Poignancy of the Period</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <dateline>HADDONFIELD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes how Haddonfield, New Jersey, Memorial High School teacker Patricia Kolodi injects poignancy into her history course on Vietnam War (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When you ask students at Haddonfield Memorial High School what they remember most about Patricia Kolodi's course on Vietnam, the answer comes in a quick volley: the speakers and the trip to the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in Washington.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Kolodi says the trip as well as the poignant speeches by veterans and conscientious objectors would not have the same meaning without knowing the history of Vietnam and having a clear picture of America in the 1950's, 60's and early 70's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When you ask students at Haddonfield Memorial High School what they remember most about Patricia Kolodi's course on Vietnam, the answer comes in a quick volley: the speakers and the trip to the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in Washington.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Kolodi says the trip as well as the poignant speeches by veterans and conscientious objectors would not have the same meaning without knowing the history of Vietnam and having a clear picture of America in the 1950's, 60's and early 70's.</p>
        <p>''They have no understanding of the fear of communism in the United States and of how no president wanted to appear weak on communism,'' she said. ''They need a solid foundation and understanding before any speaker comes in.''</p>
        <p>At the first class, Mrs. Kolodi shows a video from a public television series on Vietnam while playing Billy Joel's song, ''Good Night Saigon.'' Even though ''they really don't understand it,'' she said, they watch.</p>
        <p>From there, the course goes back more than 2,000 years as Mrs. Kolodi talks about the various occupiers of Vietnam -- the Chinese, the French, the Japanese and the French again after World War II. They also learn about the lifestyle and culture of the country, which is 85 percent Buddhist and 15 percent Roman Catholic.</p>
        <p>The class also learns about the North Vietnamese leader, Ho Chi Minh, and the South Vietnamese president , Ngo Dnh Diem. It was in the 1950's, when President Dwight D. Eisenhower sent advisors to Vietnam and started America's involvement began. They discuss President Lyndon Johnson's role in widely escalating the war and the subsequent anti-war movement along with the role of the media in questioning the war.</p>
        <p>On week nine of the class, speakers begin to come in and tell their stories. They include infantry soldiers, nurses, helicopter pilots, protesters, conscientious objectors and the relatives of any student who was a veteran, resister, just wants to address the class.</p>
        <p>''When they bring in their fathers and uncles, you see how proud they are,'' she said. Afterward, each student must write a letter to the speaker thanking him or her and talking about what the speech meant to them.</p>
        <p>The students have a chance to question each speaker, though they are not allowed to challenge or argue with the guests. Some years, the class has given dinners for the speakers with red, white and blue decorations.</p>
        <p>While Mrs. Kolodi said she was very careful not to take a stand on American involvement in the war, she makes it clear that the veterans were not welcomed back with open arms.</p>
        <p>When the course is finished, Mrs. Kolodi said, she hopes her students want to work for peace and ''do the right thing for the men and women who served.''</p>
        <p>After one dinner, a veteran wrote a letter about the experience: ''Our future is in good hands with the likes of these young people, it was a magical, poignant night . . . I have often said that there was nothing that the American people or the American government could do to make up for what was done to us all those years ago . . . some things just can't be undone . . . but I have to tell you that it might just be young people like these students . . . who weren't even alive during those turbulent years . . . well, they might just be able to heal the wounds inflicted by those who went before them.''</p>
        <p>On the last day of class, students listen to the Billy Joel song again and watch the same video, but this time, they nod their heads and say the names of the people and places they see projected on the classroom wall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
