<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Boom Market In Travel Scams</title>
    <meta content="10PRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/travel/10PRAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1D71230F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Boom Market In Travel Scams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Cay Johnston Practical Traveler column on travel frauds, in light of Federal Trade Commission's announcement of third round of enforcement actions since 1997 against deceptive travel industry practices; describes some popular ruses and tips on how to spot them; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE vacation swindle business is booming, according to law enforcement agencies, consumer advocates and travel industry organizations. The bait for unsuspecting victims ranges from nonexistent trips to identification cards offering anyone the kind of discounts only travel agents can get legitimately.</p>
        <p>''Every time we go out there looking, we find there are people running travel scams,'' said Mitchell J. Katz, a spokesman for the Federal Trade Commission, which last month announced its third round of enforcement actions against deceptive travel industry practices since 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE vacation swindle business is booming, according to law enforcement agencies, consumer advocates and travel industry organizations. The bait for unsuspecting victims ranges from nonexistent trips to identification cards offering anyone the kind of discounts only travel agents can get legitimately.</p>
        <p>''Every time we go out there looking, we find there are people running travel scams,'' said Mitchell J. Katz, a spokesman for the Federal Trade Commission, which last month announced its third round of enforcement actions against deceptive travel industry practices since 1997.</p>
        <p>The commission and 19 state agencies filed 85 actions against travel promoters, who were accused of actions ranging from falsely telling people they had won a free trip to concealing costs to refusing to make refunds.</p>
        <p>In addition, the commission reached an agreement under which American International Travel Services Inc., of Deerfield Beach, Fla.,  paid $1 million to the F.T.C. for refunds to people who say they were improperly charged for what they thought were free trips to Florida. The firm did not admit wrongdoing in the settlement, which was approved by a federal judge in Miami.</p>
        <p>Travel schemes consistently rank among the top 10 complaints to the F.T.C., Mr. Katz said. This year,  faxed offers of free trips have prompted a surge of complaints from consumers, he said.</p>
        <p>Barbara Davis, 28, of Dubuque, Iowa, was one of those who complained about deceptive practices.</p>
        <p>''I filled out this card at the Dubuque County Fair in 1999 and then I was notified that I had won a free trip,'' Miss Davis said. She paid $598 to ''reserve'' her trip for four to Florida. She said the vendor, Epic Travel, of King of Prussia, Pa., one of the firms the commission has filed charges against, never returned her calls until she wrote that she had retained a lawyer; then, she said, the firm called only to say that it had no record of her calls and that it was too late to get a refund.</p>
        <p>''So far I haven't gotten anything back and I never got a trip anywhere,'' she said. ''But I did learn to never again fill out a slip for a free trip.''</p>
        <p>Pat Semegen, general counsel for Epic Resorts, said Miss Davis's remarks were ''not anywhere close to factual.'' He said that the company issues refunds if requested within 30 days, and that it sells time-share packages and does not promise free trips.</p>
        <p>Some Popular Ruses</p>
        <p>Here are a few of the fraud techniques currently in vogue and some tips on how to spot them.</p>
        <p>The Internet has provided a lucrative new venue for a variety of travel swindles. Travel scams are the ninth most common swindles reported to Internet Fraud Watch at the Web site www.fraud.org, said Philip McKee, assistant director of the project, a service of the National Consumers League, a nonprofit organization.</p>
        <p>Consumers should ignore ads on Internet auction sites from people who say they have frequent-flier miles expiring or a ticket in their own name, said Kristina Rundquist, a spokeswoman for the American Society of Travel Agents.</p>
        <p>''You cannot transfer frequent-flier miles for money and you cannot use a ticket made out to someone else.'' she said.</p>
        <p>According to Stan Bosco, the society's assistant director for consumer affairs, one common scheme is to offer a trip that, if paid for immediately, can be taken any time in the next 18 months. The extended time period, as well as any efforts to stall the making of reservations, are signs that the promoters intend to close the business and flee with the money before any trips are taken.</p>
        <p>The American Society of Travel Agents said it has been receiving a growing number of complaints about phony travel-agent identification swindles, which it calls ''card mill scams.'' Consumers are told they can buy credentials that make it possible to pose as a travel agent and obtain the deep discounts on air fares, hotel rooms and other services that are available to travel agents on trips that are meant to familiarize them with a destination.</p>
        <p>Travel agents do get such discounts. But Mr. Bosco said that as this swindle has spread, at a time when demand has pushed up rates, both airlines and hotels have begun to tighten up on the availability of such discounts for legitimate travel agents while training their employees to weed out fake travel agents.</p>
        <p>Another dubious deal offers free travel as an inducement to take out a credit card. William J. McGee, editor of Consumer Reports Travel Letter, published by the same company that puts out the magazine, said one such offer it investigated required customers to join a travel club with a membership fee so high that it offset any potential travel benefit.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGee also advises consumers not to deal with any travel company that will not allow them to pay by credit card or will not conduct business through the mail. Sales made by credit card can be contested. Refusal to send through the mail can be a sign of fraud by people trying to avoid mail-fraud statutes, he said.</p>
        <p>Checking the Charters</p>
        <p>Trips on chartered aircraft are one area that can easily be checked out. Federal consumer protection rules require charter companies to specify the airline whose planes are being chartered in all advertisements and promotional materials.</p>
        <p>To check out charter operators, call the Department of Transportation at (202) 366-1037 and give the name of the tour operator and travel dates; the department will tell you whether the company has posted a P.C. number as a public charter operator, meaning it has met minimum financial-stability requirements. Even if the operator volunteers its P.C. number, check with the government, Mr. McGee said.</p>
        <p>Tour operators can cancel up to 10 days before a trip if they refund all money. Customers have the right to cancel if the tour operator changes the departure or destination, raises prices more than 10 percent or moves departure and return times by more than 48 hours.</p>
        <p>When you are already at your destination and ready to return home, tour operators have the right to delay you by up to two days. And if you refuse the delayed return, all the charter operator owes you is the return air fare at the charter rate, which typically is a fraction of the cost of buying a one-way ticket home or two extra nights in most resorts, assuming you can even get a room.</p>
        <p>The F.T.C. has two advisories for travelers on its Web site, at www.ftc.gov, one about telemarketing fraud and the other about travel scams in general (click first on ''consumer protection'' and then on ''telemarketing'').</p>
        <p>There is one simple rule that, if followed, pretty much eliminates the risk of being taken by even the slickest travel con artists.</p>
        <p>''Remember that nothing comes free,'' Mr. McGee said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bosco of the American Society of Travel Agents echoed his sentiments. ''An offer of a week at a beachfront hotel in Hawaii for $299 is likely to leave nothing but memories of money spent for a trip that was never made,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER DAVID CAY JOHNSTON is a business reporter for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">DAVID CAY JOHNSTON is a business reporter for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
