<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How an Unpretentious Family Car, the Passat, Got So Hot</title>
    <meta content="10PASS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Volkswagen Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFDF1039F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How an Unpretentious Family Car, the Passat, Got So Hot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Positive customer response, glowing press and high ratings from consumer publications propel Volkswagen Passat to extremely strong sales; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FAMILY sedans generate big sales, but seldom do they create a buzz. The Volkswagen Passat, however, has gained most-wanted status, thanks to glowing reviews from automotive writers, high ratings from consumer publications and positive word-of-mouth among owners.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Consumer Reports has given high ratings to the Passat. In its July issue, the magazine rated the Passat GLS  V-6 first among midsized sedans, over the Toyota Camry, Nissan Maxima and Honda Accord. The magazine had previously ranked the four-cylinder Passat above comparable models.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FAMILY sedans generate big sales, but seldom do they create a buzz. The Volkswagen Passat, however, has gained most-wanted status, thanks to glowing reviews from automotive writers, high ratings from consumer publications and positive word-of-mouth among owners.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Consumer Reports has given high ratings to the Passat. In its July issue, the magazine rated the Passat GLS  V-6 first among midsized sedans, over the Toyota Camry, Nissan Maxima and Honda Accord. The magazine had previously ranked the four-cylinder Passat above comparable models.</p>
        <p>A top ranking from Consumer Reports, or even its more common ''recommended'' rating, is coveted, given that many car shoppers come to dealerships clutching copies of the magazine's reports, which some regard as gospel; some auto marketing executives have estimated that its recommendation can result in 25,000 added sales.</p>
        <p>The Passat has also received uniformly favorable notices in enthusiast magazines and newspaper reviews, and it has won industry awards. This summer, for instance, J. D. Power &amp; Associates named it the ''most appealing family car.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Passat sales are soaring, setting records for much of the year. And if sales continue at the torrid first-half pace, VW is likely to sell nearly 90,000 Passats in 2000, well above last year's record of 68,151, said Tony Fouladpour, a spokesman for VW. The Northeast is a particularly hot market, accounting for 15 percent of Passat sales nationwide, Mr. Fouladpour said.</p>
        <p>The car is attracting interest among consumers who might never have considered VW's lineup before. In Grand Rapids, Mich., buyers often arrived at Betten Imports with copies of Consumer Reports in hand, said the former sales manager, Jeff Leckta. Used to selling Volkswagens to repeat customers, he said, ''I've seen people in here that I've never seen before.'' Several recent buyers traded Camrys for Passats.</p>
        <p>He and other salespeople complain about a lack of cars to sell. As early as May, some dealers were telling shoppers that if they wanted a Passat, they would have to order a 2001 model, due in October.</p>
        <p>The car's popularity means that VW has not offered special lease deals, discount financing or rebates, although the Passat is priced above its rivals. The base GLS is $21,725, compared with $18,980 for a Honda Accord LX and $20,843 for a Toyota Camry LE. The Passat GLS V-6 starts at $24,325 versus the Honda Accord LX V-6 at $22,390 and the Toyota Camry LE V-6 at $22,813.</p>
        <p>The success of the Passat, a descendent of past VW models like the Quantum and Dasher, is quite recent. The previous-generation car suffered from quality problems and boxy styling. ''You had to have a real appreciation for Teutonic German design,'' Mr. Fouladpour said of the 1990-97 model. Sales slipped as low as 11,021 in 1994.</p>
        <p>Everything changed with the redesigned 1998 model, whose roofline is a graceful arc that mimics the look of the New Beetle. The restyled Passat has won praise for its interior comfort, adept handling and responsive engine. Many of its parts are shared with the more expensive Audi A4 and A6.</p>
        <p>Fans include Ron Pinelli, founder of the Autodata Corporation, a statistics and marketing firm in Woodcliff Lake, N.J. This year, he bought a silver GLS with a turbocharged four-cylinder engine and promptly spent another $3,000 for custom wheels.</p>
        <p>''Accord and Camry are wonderful products, but the Passat has more passion behind it,'' Mr. Pinelli said. He said the Passat's popularity was a symbol of VW's sales comeback in the United States. ''It wasn't many years ago that VW was basically out of business in this country.''</p>
        <p>Passat has brought Volkswagen a sought-after group of buyers. Their average age is 38, compared with 43 for the last Passat. More are women: 43 percent, compared with 38 percent previously. And their household income tops $83,000, up $13,000. Three-quarters are college-educated, compared with two-thirds for the previous car.</p>
        <p>Many auto companies would put on a full press to attract additional buyers, but VW's goal is eventually to sell 100,000 Passats a year in the United States. Mr. Fouladpour said VW could not hope to steal more business from the Accord and Camry, which each have more than 400,000 sales annually, because of production constraints and a relatively small network of dealers.</p>
        <p>And VW insists that the Passat, with its decidedly German ride and handling characteristics, was never intended to appeal to the mass American market.</p>
        <p>''It's still not a car for everybody,'' Mr. Fouladpour said. ''It has a personality that attracts a certain type of buyer. Toyota and Honda do vanilla and bland better than everyone else. We intend to be a wakeup call.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
