<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nantucket, Aglow In Shades Of Gray</title>
    <meta content="10NANTUCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nantucket (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fugard, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Nantucket</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D91631F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nantucket, Aglow In Shades Of Gray</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Fugard</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fugard, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Fugard describes trip to Nantucket, Mass; photos; map; charts (The Sophisticated Traveler, part 2 of 2-part section)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The roses and foxgloves were muted splashes of color in the evening's last light, and I wandered through the town of Nantucket a little in awe. I'd never seen so many gray houses. The term ''weathered gray siding,'' frequently used to describe their restrained beauty, doesn't do them justice. Nantucket houses seem to know weather: they've been intimate with rain squalls gusting off the Atlantic and the fog that periodically enshrouds the island, with winter's northeasters and, of course, resplendent sunny summer days.</p>
        <p>Winding lanes led me past traditional saltboxes and handsome early Federal-style homes crowned with austere roof walks. On the cobblestone streets I saw elegant brick mansions with delicate balustrade trim on their roofs, grand Greek Revival houses with pillars and porticoes and a few flamboyant Victorians. There are hundreds of authentic 18th- and 19th-century houses in the town, but the one I fell in love with, on reaching the top of Sunset Hill Lane, predates all of them. The Oldest House, as it's called, was built in 1686, just 27 years after Nantucket Island was settled. With its tiny diamond-pane windows and huge sloping roof, it looked more like a landlocked ark than a house, and on my first evening on Nantucket it stood stoic on its hillock as a light rain nuzzled its shingles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The roses and foxgloves were muted splashes of color in the evening's last light, and I wandered through the town of Nantucket a little in awe. I'd never seen so many gray houses. The term ''weathered gray siding,'' frequently used to describe their restrained beauty, doesn't do them justice. Nantucket houses seem to know weather: they've been intimate with rain squalls gusting off the Atlantic and the fog that periodically enshrouds the island, with winter's northeasters and, of course, resplendent sunny summer days.</p>
        <p>Winding lanes led me past traditional saltboxes and handsome early Federal-style homes crowned with austere roof walks. On the cobblestone streets I saw elegant brick mansions with delicate balustrade trim on their roofs, grand Greek Revival houses with pillars and porticoes and a few flamboyant Victorians. There are hundreds of authentic 18th- and 19th-century houses in the town, but the one I fell in love with, on reaching the top of Sunset Hill Lane, predates all of them. The Oldest House, as it's called, was built in 1686, just 27 years after Nantucket Island was settled. With its tiny diamond-pane windows and huge sloping roof, it looked more like a landlocked ark than a house, and on my first evening on Nantucket it stood stoic on its hillock as a light rain nuzzled its shingles.</p>
        <p>I visited Nantucket, Mass., in late June of this year, but my initial encounter with the island -- which lies 30 miles at sea from the south shore of Cape Cod -- happened several years ago, through literature.</p>
        <p>''Be it distinctly recorded here,'' wrote Herman Melville in ''Moby-Dick,'' ''that the Nantucketers were the first among mankind to harpoon with civilized steel the great Sperm Whale; and that for half a century they were the only people of the whole globe who so harpooned him.''</p>
        <p>My new understanding of how whaling is woven into the island's history began when I checked into the Anchor Inn for my five-day visit. The house was built for Archibald Hammond, a ship's captain. The rooms are named after Nantucket whaling ships, and I fell asleep to the two-toned bleat of a foghorn.</p>
        <p>The first settlers on Nantucket had planned to raise sheep but eventually began hunting whales, first from the shore and then from whaling boats. When Nantucketers invented the tryworks, a brick furnace built on deck that turned whaling ships into small factories capable of processing blubber, the oceans of the world opened up to them.</p>
        <p>Ocean voyages that lasted for years? Women pacing roof walks, searching for signs of their husbands' ships? It seemed rather romantic to me, until I set foot in the Whaling Museum on Broad Street, one block away from the harbor. Doug Burch, a staff member at the museum, was giving a talk on the gruesome business of whaling, and I took a seat in the back of Sanderson Hall, the walls of which are lined with a fierce array of harpoons, lances and flensing knives.</p>
        <p>''Thar she blows!'' Mr. Burch cried, and he strode over to an authentic 30-foot whaleboat in which six men once pursued sperm whales that could reach 100 feet in length. For the next 45 minutes he took me on a heart-thumping journey, peppering his talk with evocative whaling terminology such as ''Nantucket sleigh ride'' -- once harpooned, the enraged whale often surged across the ocean for hours, dragging the men on a wild, bucking ride.</p>
        <p>The museum's collections include dramatic oil paintings of anatomically dubious whales flipping boats into the air, the skeleton of a 43-foot finback whale and intriguing artifacts like the harpoon head that once belonged to Peter Paddock. While captain of the Lion he harpooned a whale that got away; 13 years later, he successfully harpooned the same whale and found his harpoon head buried in the animal's flesh. The scrimshaw collection conjures up images of more tender moments at sea. On the days when they weren't being dragged across the ocean by furious sperm whales, the sailors carved whale ivory. These men were homesick. How else can one explain the rolling pins and pie crimpers that they fashioned? My favorite display was of pictures of women etched on sperm whale teeth. Were they wives? Fiancees? Was the half-naked woman reclining on a sofa someone's fantasy?</p>
        <p>Leaving the museum, I found myself in a crowd of people with suitcases and bicycles and dogs and babies. To my left was the harbor where the last whaling ship docked in 1870 to unload its barrels of rendered oil. Now, almost hourly, ferryboats arrive from Hyannis and unload visitors. Nantucket's year-round population of more than 9,000 swells to more than 50,000 in July and August.</p>
        <p>I suppose we visitors are as valuable to Nantucket's economy as sperm whales used to be, I thought ruefully. The cobblestone streets and lanes leading away from the harbor are lined with shops filled with fine merchandise, and though I tried to be the noble tourist interested only in history -- surely I shouldn't be shopping on my first day? -- I succumbed.</p>
        <p>Besides, I had a mission. My father, Athol, wanted a scrimshaw pocketknife. When he was 20 he worked for a year on a merchant ship, the S.S. Graigaur. He was the captain's personal steward, or ''tiger,'' and the only thing he managed to carve for himself was an extremely uncomfortable pair of wooden sandals.</p>
        <p>I visited several antiques shops, two of my favorites being Nina Hellman Marine Antiques and Leonards Antiques, with its inviting four-posters. I bought my father a beautiful knife at another shop, Craftmasters, and then spent the rest of the afternoon traipsing in and out of nearly every boutique. I now own a pair of fancy Japanese-looking flip-flops that just might be as uncomfortable as the sandals my father carved out of wood.</p>
        <p>As wonderful as the shops were, something quite magical happened at dusk when most of them closed and the day visitors departed. The town seemed to wobble in time, and I experienced a delicious sense of dislocation. I was a 21st-century woman strolling through the 18th century, as long as no S.U.V.'s and Jeeps rumbled past. I wandered from one narrow lane to the next, peeping into the riotous flower gardens of the grand gray houses, billowing with hydrangeas and cosmos, with lilies and brilliant yellow coreopsis and, of course, roses.</p>
        <p>Eventually I returned to the harbor. During the day, it's bustling with people visiting the galleries and restaurants on the wharves, but in the evening hours it quiets down. Reflections from the lights of the gray-shingled rental cottages on the piers winked in the dark water as a few boats glided into the bay for moonlight cruises. Nantucket is often referred to as ''the little gray lady,'' and on this early summer evening I had found her to be particularly beautiful.</p>
        <p>Was this what those homesick, rolling-pin-carving sailors pined for, I wondered. I had a vivid impression of the life of a Nantucket whaler; now I wanted to know about the women of the island, those wives and fiancees and lovers so tenderly etched on the teeth of sperm whales. What were they doing while their men were at sea?</p>
        <p>Women shaped Nantucket's history as much as the men, starting with Mary Coffin Starbuck, who, around 1702, was instrumental in introducing Quakerism, with its belief in the equality of the sexes, to the island. While their husbands were at sea -- the longest whaling voyage lasted 11 years -- many Quaker women in coal-scuttle bonnets and homespun dresses took care of their children, launched themselves as independent businesswomen and participated in town government.</p>
        <p>The woman who intrigued me the most was unmarried, the astronomer Maria Mitchell. On the night of Oct. 1, 1847, she excused herself from a dinner party being held in the Pacific Bank building, where she lived with her family; her father, who was an amateur astronomer, worked at the bank. She climbed to the roof and, using a Dolland telescope, became the first American and the first woman to plot the course of an unknown comet. The following year, she was the first woman elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (it took the academy almost a century to elect another woman). In 1865, when she was hired by the newly founded Vassar College, she became the first woman professor of astronomy in the United States.</p>
        <p>En route to her birthplace on Vestal Street, I walked up the shady reaches of upper Main Street past some of Nantucket's finest 19th-century mansions: the John Wendell Barrett house, white clapboard with looming chimneys and an enclosed cupola; the Three Bricks, three identical houses with handsome porticoes built by the whaling patriarch Joseph Starbuck for his three sons. The Hadwen House, an imposing Greek Revival mansion built in 1844 for William Hadwen, a candle manufacturer, is open to the public. Its large, impeccably furnished parlors feature carved Italian marble fireplaces and gilded chandeliers, while upstairs the Chinese grass mat in Eunice Hadwen's bedroom whispers of the China trade and ships docking in exotic ports.</p>
        <p>The house in which Maria Mitchell was born and lived until she was 18 is a fine example of late 18th- to early 19th-century Quaker design and reveals how people of more moderate means lived. While the Hadwen House has carpeted floors, here two of the floors feature the original floor painting. No brilliantly colored wallpaper brightens the small parlor, and the kitchen walls, constructed from various pieces of wood -- maybe even a few boards from a shipwreck -- and plaster, are grain-painted to resemble knotty pine. Most moving to me, and atypical for a Quaker house, was the tiny study, no larger than a broom closet, that William Mitchell created for his 10 children. When Maria, the third oldest, closed the door on her siblings and worked at her mathematical calculations it became her ''room of one's own'' in miniature.</p>
        <p>Maria was as passionate about the earth as she was about the cosmos, and the Maria Mitchell Association continues her work in science education. The Loines Observatory, on Milk Street Extension, offers lectures and public telescope viewing.</p>
        <p>The Hinchman House, on Milk Street, is a small natural science museum that includes displays of whale and dolphin bones, wildflowers, tropical drift seeds that wash up on Nantucket's beaches and a unique hands-on exhibit: an owl-pellet dig. ''Is this for kids?'' I asked the young volunteer. ''No-o, not really,'' he said with a smile that made me think I wasn't the first adult to ask this question. Owl pellets are composed of regurgitated hair, feathers and bits of bone that the owl couldn't digest. Using tweezers, forceps and probes I carefully took apart a barn owl pellet that resembled a tightly packed gray oval dust ball and found at least a dozen tiny bones. A bone-sorting chart helped me identify a rodent's jawbone and several small vertebrae .</p>
        <p>That evening, I ate in one of the island's fine restaurants, Black-Eyed Susan's. It used to be a diner and is now adorned with three Italian glass chandeliers. The Afghan jerked chicken was delicious.</p>
        <p>I felt satiated in more ways than one. Not only had I dined well but I was also fat with history -- whaling ships and mansions and a bold woman staring at the heavens. Of course, there were historical sites that I hadn't visited: the old jail; the Atheneum, the Greek Revival building that houses Nantucket's library, where Maria Mitchell worked as the first librarian and, rumor has it, read every book; and the Quaker Meeting House. But I decided that on the following day I would plunge into the natural world.</p>
        <p>Beautiful beaches rim Nantucket. More than 40 percent of the island is protected conservation land, and there are several nature preserves in which to hike or go birding. (Sadly, the rest of the island is being developed at a brisk pace, and huge summer homes are sprouting on the bluffs and moors.) Six bike paths, totaling approximately 25 miles, fan out across the island, and in a day one can easily cycle from the beaches of Madaket at its western tip to the village of Sconset at the eastern end. I wanted to do something a little more adventurous, and so I visited the scalloped barrier beach that forms the western flank of Nantucket's natural harbor. The Coskata-Coatue area, as it's known, consists of several adjoining wildlife refuges and encompasses sand dunes, pristine beaches, salt marshes and an old maritime red cedar forest. It is accessible only by four-wheel drive or by boat. I went in a raspberry-colored fiberglass kayak rented from Sea Nantucket on Francis Street Beach.</p>
        <p>I felt like a poor relative as I made my way past the fancy yachts and speedboats bobbing in the choppy waters of the harbor. From a distance, the barrier beach didn't look like much more than a spit of sand, and I girded myself for disappointment. Half an hour later, as I paddled closer -- glided really, because the headwind had died down and the water was limpid and glasslike -- my heart quickened. There wasn't a soul around. For the next three hours I kayaked from one beguiling bay beach to the next. I had several swims, walked inland to view a colony of nesting egrets and dodged an enormous horseshoe crab. Rosa rugosa, the salt-spray rose, was in bloom, and I decided that there is nothing, absolutely nothing, more sublime than roses on a deserted beach.</p>
        <p>Except, perhaps, the roses at Sconset. The heart of this village, perched on a bluff overlooking the ocean, was settled in the 17th century and has many enchanting seaside cottages. They began as one-room shacks built by fishermen from Nantucket town who came to the village for cod-fishing season. Soon enough, their wives wanted to join them and tiny bedrooms or ''warts'' -- was it a disgruntled husband who came up with this name? -- were added to the shacks, creating the higgledy-piggledy look of the some of the oldest ones. And the rambler roses adore them, up and over the cottages they clamber as if in competition with the giant hollyhocks to see which species can put on the most impressive display.</p>
        <p>On my last afternoon on the island I stood in one of Sconset's sheltered narrow lanes until a most bewitching sense of stillness came over me. Surely I had entered a fairy tale. I was almost as tall as some of the cottages, yet some of the flowers were taller than I. I wanted to curl up on the nearest wooden doorstep like a cat. Not acceptable behavior for a visitor, so I strolled down to the beach known as Codfish Park and napped on the sand. The Atlantic was restless when I awoke, and the least terns were fishing close to shore, folding their wings until they resembled origami birds and plummeting into the waves. Sconset is short for Siasconset, an Indian word meaning ''place of bones,'' and thought to be a reference to the bones of right whales that used to wash ashore. As I watched the whitecaps tearing off the indigo swells, it pleased me deeply to know that I was looking at whale country. Their numbers have greatly diminished, but they're still out there -- humpbacks and finbacks, sei and pilot whales and a few hundred right whales. Breaching and sounding and filling the waters with their songs, they migrate from ocean to ocean on journeys as epic as those of the Nantucket whaling ships that pursued them hundreds of years ago.</p>
        <p>PORT OF CALL  I made calls for accommodations a week before I visited Nantucket in June and almost didn't find a room. It's wise, particularly in summer, to book well in advance.  ANCHOR INN, 66 Center Street (telephone: 508-228-0072; e-mail: anchorin@nantucket.net), was built in 1806. Its 11 rooms, with private baths and air-conditioners, are named after Nantucket whaling ships. ''Cyrus,'' my room on the third floor, was a little small; those on the first and second floors are larger. Ann and Charles Balas, the owners, went out of their way to help me during my visit. In late September and October, midweek prices range from about $115 to $125, $165 to $175 on weekends, with Continental breakfast. No smoking. Children old enough to stay in their own room are welcome. Usually closed for six to eight weeks in the winter.  SHERBURNE INN, 10 Gay Street (508-228-4425; fax: 508-228-8114), a quiet place just a few minutes' walk from the center of town, is where I shall stay when I return to Nantucket. Built in 1835 as the headquarters for the Atlantic Silk Company, its rooms tend to be a little larger than those in the private houses that have been converted into inns. Eight exquisitely appointed bedrooms all have private baths and air-conditioning. Rates range from $150 to $250 until Columbus Day, after which they drop to around $95 to $150, Continental breakfast included. Special packages are offered from mid-October through mid-May. No smoking. Children older than 6 are welcome. Open all year.  I loved dining in BLACK-EYED SUSAN'S, 10 India Street (508-325-0308), with its funky decor. The menu changes almost weekly, and tuna tartare and Malaysian barbecued pork are popular dishes. They have no liquor license and do not take credit cards. Open for dinner every night except Sunday; reservations accepted only for the 6 p.m. seating. A two-course dinner for two averages around $80. Also open daily from 7 a.m. to 1 p.m. for breakfast.  AMERICAN SEASONS, 80 Center Street (508-228-7111), is a lovely, rather romantic restaurant with a terrace. Open for dinner seven nights a week, its  menu changes every six weeks and features American regional cuisines: pan-roasted wild striped bass in saffron butter from New England, perhaps, while the South might be represented by applewood-smoked sweetbreads. A two-course dinner for two, with a bottle of wine, costs about $130.  TOPPER'S AT THE WAUWINET, 120 Wauwinet Road (508-228-8768), is in a restored old inn at the western end of Nantucket harbor. A tasting menu is served on the terrace, and I feasted on scallops, grilled calamari, yellow-fin tuna tartare and a lobster club sandwich. The tasting lunch averages $25 a person. During the spring and fall, a six-course wine-tasting dinner, with each course accompanied by a wine, is $175 a person. Topper's provides a complementary launch service to and from town; if you miss the boat you can always take a taxi from town. Open daily for dinner, Monday through Saturday for lunch, Sunday for brunch.  I rented something called a sit-on-top kayak from SEA NANTUCKET, at Francis Street Beach at the end of Washington Street Extension, about a five-minute walk from the harbor (508-228-7499). Expect to get wet. If you take a camera or a picnic lunch, wrap it securely in plastic. The kayaks have drainage holes in the bottom, which also let in water, and you will spend your time sitting in about half an inch of water. It's worth it. The rates are $15 an hour for a single, $30 for a half-day; $30 an hour for a double, $50 for a half-day. Only cash and checks accepted. Open from May through October.</p>
        <p>Lisa Fugard</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND SHOPS  MARIA MITCHELL BIRTHPLACE HOUSE, 1 Vestal Street (telephone: 508-228-2896), is open from mid-June through mid-September, Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; call for fall and winter hours. Admission: $3.  NANTUCKET WHALING MUSEUM, 13 Broad Street (508-228-1736), is open daily from Memorial Day to around Labor Day, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m; from then until Columbus Day, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; limited hours in winter. Admission: $5; visitor pass for museums and sites operated by the Nantucket Historical Association, $10.  HADWEN HOUSE, 96 Main Street, run by the Nantucket Historical Association (508-228-1894), is open daily from Memorial Day to around Labor Day, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; from then until Columbus Day, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; closed in winter. Admission: $5; visitor pass, $10.  HINCHMAN HOUSE NATURAL SCIENCE MUSEUM, 7 Milk Street (508-228-0898), is open from June 15 through Labor Day, Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; reduced hours in September and October; closed in winter. Admission: $3.  NINA HELLMAN MARINE ANTIQUES, 48 Center Street (508-228-4677), is open June through the end of September, Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m, Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m; call for fall and winter hours.  LEONARDS ANTIQUES, 31 Washington Street (508-228-0620), is open from the end of April until mid-December; in summer, Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., Sunday, 1 to 5 p.m.; call for fall hours.  CRAFTMASTERS OF NANTUCKET, 7 India Street (508-228-0322), is open daily, April through October, 10 a.m. to 11 p.m., November through March, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>Lisa Fugard is a fiction writer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lisa Fugard is a fiction writer.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
