<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In 2 Nassau Races, It's a Family Affair</title>
    <meta content="10ELEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuriloff, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuriloff, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Todd, Russell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Todd, Samantha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7DF1439F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In 2 Nassau Races, It's a Family Affair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Green Party voters in Nassau County, NY, because of confusion over state's arcane election laws, will be forced to choose between Ronald Kuriloff and wife, Maria, who are running for state committee posts in primary; same is true in 16th Assembly District, where Russell and Samantha Todd are competing for Green Party state committee seat (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>USUALLY, the job of a candidate's spouse is to be supportive. That may be a tricky task for two Nassau County couples who have found themselves running husband against wife in Tuesday's primaries.</p>
        <p>The mixup, involving the election of state committee members for the Green Party, began amid confusion over New York's arcane election laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>USUALLY, the job of a candidate's spouse is to be supportive. That may be a tricky task for two Nassau County couples who have found themselves running husband against wife in Tuesday's primaries.</p>
        <p>The mixup, involving the election of state committee members for the Green Party, began amid confusion over New York's arcane election laws.</p>
        <p>''We were under the impression we could have a male and a female on the ballot,'' explained Ronald Kuriloff of Malverne. ''We did not realize that we didn't have enough registered Green Party enrollees to warrant two committee members.''</p>
        <p>So on Tuesday, voters in the 22nd Assembly District will have to choose between Mr. Kuriloff, a commercial artist, and his wife, Maria, an acupuncturist</p>
        <p>''It's kind of amusing,'' Mr. Kuriloff said, ''but it's true.''</p>
        <p>The same thing is true in the 16th Assembly District, where Russell and Samantha Todd of Roslyn Heights are going head to head in another race for the Green Party state committee.</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Galante, a deputy commissioner at the Nassau County Board of Elections, said that ''after a certain period of time, people can't decline from the ballot. By the time we were told of this mistake by the Green Party, it was too late to get them off the ballot.''</p>
        <p>Turnout is guaranteed to be low. There are only 12 registered members of the Green Party in the 22nd Assembly District and 20 in the 16th.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuriloff said he knows that few voters bother to go to the polls in primaries. To ensure a winner and for the sake of ''domestic tranquility,'' Mr. Kuriloff said that he and his wife plan to decide which one of them would ''drop out of the race by voting for the other.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kuriloff, 50, said she wants her husband to win. ''I was once active in the Democratic Party; I've had my 15 minutes of fame,'' she said. ''And he is the one who got me interested in the Green Party.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to hold my nose and vote for him,'' she quipped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Todd, 49, said that running against his wife is ''a little weird.''</p>
        <p>''We had no political ambitions other than to make sure the Green Party could exist by having committee members in each assembly district,'' he said. ''They told us that there needed to be a male and female running in this district and, although we are not competitive type people, we said we would do it if it was needed.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Todd, 35, added, ''They had no other people to put on.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Todd, a computer programmer, was asked how his campaign was going against his wife, a data entry employee.</p>
        <p>''We're not debating each other,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Green Party first surfaced in Nassau County in 1996, when the consumer activist Ralph Nader ran for president, a post he is seeking again this year.</p>
        <p>''The Green Party became an official party two years later when we petitioned to get Al Lewis on the ballot for governor and he got more than 50,000 votes,'' Mr. Todd said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Todd said the Greens in Nassau are running candidates in the Third Congressional District and in three assembly races. The party, which was founded in the early 1970's in Europe as an environmental, anti-nuclear and social justice grassroots movement, is also fielding a short list of candidates in Suffolk.</p>
        <p>Does he plan to campaign?</p>
        <p>''No, not really,'' said Mr. Todd. ''You'll see bumper stickers, but they will be for Nader.''</p>
        <p>Did he care to predict the outcome of his election against his wife?</p>
        <p>''We'll vote for ourselves,'' he said, ''and if a third person shows up, he will decide the winner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
