<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Long Road From Whoville to Broadway</title>
    <meta content="10MARK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/arts/10MARK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Costumes, Theatrical</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seussical (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DB1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Long Road From Whoville to Broadway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Marks report on costume design troubles in Boston tryouts of Broadway-bound musical Seussical; believes Broadway has become more preoccupied with needs of children, who were rarely catered to in past; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the Broadway of right now, the notion seemed irresistible: an original musical out of the pages of Dr. Seuss that would turn Horton the Elephant and the Cat in the Hat into theater animals.</p>
        <p>But one look at the characters onstage in Boston and the creators of ''Seussical'' knew the show had identity problems. Catherine Zuber's costumes for the eagerly anticipated production, based on the work of one of the world's most popular children's writers, were simply too stylized, too whimsical -- too, of all things, Seussian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the Broadway of right now, the notion seemed irresistible: an original musical out of the pages of Dr. Seuss that would turn Horton the Elephant and the Cat in the Hat into theater animals.</p>
        <p>But one look at the characters onstage in Boston and the creators of ''Seussical'' knew the show had identity problems. Catherine Zuber's costumes for the eagerly anticipated production, based on the work of one of the world's most popular children's writers, were simply too stylized, too whimsical -- too, of all things, Seussian.</p>
        <p>It was not that Ms. Zuber, a highly regarded designer in her own right, had failed her aesthetic mandate. It was just that the producers, authors and director of the $8.5 million production, a show blessed with some of the best pre-Broadway buzz in years, were worried. If taste-setting early audiences sensed too much fluff and preciousness, would the musical be categorized -- and marginalized -- as kids' stuff?</p>
        <p>''We had beautiful costumes individually, but as soon as we put more than half a dozen out there it became such a feast for the eyes that we lost focus on the people and the storytelling,'' said Gary Gunas, who is producing ''Seussical'' along with such Broadway and Hollywood powerhouses as SFX Theatrical Group, Barry and Fran Weissler and Universal Studios. ''Catherine and the rest of us just sort of stared up there and said, 'O.K., we've gone astray.' ''</p>
        <p>So, mere days before performances were to begin late last month for the show's Boston tryout, Ms. Zuber and her designs were out. William Ivey Long was brought in to replace her, with the idea of dressing the Seuss characters more realistically. Such substitutions are not unheard of in a show's trial-and-error phase out of town. But the last-minute turmoil was more than a struggle over how Dr. Seuss' exotic creations should look. It reflected the serious artistic and commercial conflicts arising ever more frequently these days as Broadway becomes more preoccupied with the needs of an age group that in the past it rarely catered to -- children -- while holding on for dear life to the adult audience that has sustained it.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, George Bernard Shaw or Thornton Wilder served as the inspiration for a season's major Broadway musical. Today, that role has shifted to the likes of Disney cartoon animators -- and the creator of ''Green Eggs and Ham.'' From the New Amsterdam Theater on 42nd Street, where ''The Lion King'' reigns as the biggest Broadway hit in years, to the Royal National Theater in London, where ''Honk!,'' a show based on ''The Ugly Duckling,'' snared the Olivier Award for best musical this year, it is the fantasy world of the youngest theatergoers that has captured the imagination of the conceptualizers and bankrollers of lavish entertainments.</p>
        <p>The evolution can be traced through shows like ''Cats.'' When it began life on Broadway 18 years ago, it was touted as an innovative grown-up musical. But over the years, the marketing seemed to shift. Where once the show's dominant image was of that lithe dancer framed by a pair of cat's eyes, the television commercials became filled with the images of children having their faces painted to resemble the characters onstage.</p>
        <p>''When I was a child in the suburbs of New York, the big event was to go to the theater and see the thing that all the adults were excited about,'' said Leonard Marcus, a children's book historian and critic. ''I went to see 'My Fair Lady' and 'The Music Man' and 'Bye Bye Birdie': that's a reflection of how child-adult relationships were in those days. These days, there's a lot more interest in what the child wants to do. Doing things for the child's sake.''</p>
        <p>''Seussical,'' scheduled to open Nov. 9 at the Richard Rodgers Theater, was clearly created with the hope of tapping into the changing demographics of Broadway, a shift mainly brought about by three factors: the culture's obsession with youth, a nostalgia craze among baby boomers with children and an appetite for pricier family entertainment fueled by the robust economy.</p>
        <p>But in engaging such known Broadway quantities as the lyricist Lynn Ahrens, the composer Stephen Flaherty and the director Frank Galati, all of ''Ragtime'' fame, along with the choreographer Kathleen Marshall (''Kiss Me, Kate''), the producers of ''Seussical'' found themselves faced with a difficult question: could an ambitious show that tells the story of an elephant who hatches an egg and a microscopic boy who lives on a speck of dust and a homely bird who just wants to be loved add up to something that grown-ups would buy tickets to, even if they didn't have children?</p>
        <p>Barry Weissler, a co-producer of ''Chicago'' and ''Annie Get Your Gun,'' joined the production team with his wife after he saw a workshop version last summer in Toronto that witnesses report had many a hard-bitten producing type in tears.  Mr. Weissler said the success or failure of ''Seussical'' at overcoming preconceptions of how adult a show about Seuss could possibly be might be the ultimate test of its theatrical power.</p>
        <p>THE magic numbers, say the producers of ''Seussical,'' are 7 and 77. That is the age range they are seeking to attract; indeed, it is the range they believe they have to draw to approach the success of the show that radically changed perceptions of children's musical theater, ''The Lion King.'' With its heart-stopping masks and visual effects, overseen by the avant-garde theater director Julie Taymor, on whom the Walt Disney Company took a chance, ''The Lion King'' demonstrated that a big, commercial family show could have artistic aspirations: that it could be more than a cartoon with Equity actors cast as dessert plates (Disney's ''Beauty and the Beast'') or the kind of clunky spectacle doomed to be made sport of by critics (Frank Wildhorn's ''Jekyll and Hyde'').</p>
        <p>The powers behind ''Seussical'' believe that some of its strengths -- a melodic Ahrens-Flaherty score; an emotional narrative; a potential star in Kevin Chamberlin (a Tony nominee last season for his role in ''Dirty Blonde''), who plays the hapless Horton -- make it a worthy example of old-style Broadway values, and thus perhaps an even likelier candidate than ''The Lion King'' for crossover appeal. Though Ms. Taymor's production received generally glowing notices, some critics, like Ben Brantley of The New York Times, pointed to the show's weaker elements -- for example, a book that seemed undramatic and characters that were essentially opaque.</p>
        <p>Indeed, ''Seussical'' strives to be unlike ''The Lion King'' everywhere but at the box office. ''We are a different animal,'' Mr. Weissler said, the pun unintentional. ''Julie Taymor is a genius at what she does with masks and costumes. But that's the opposite of what we're doing. That's why the costumes had to go. Because they weren't allowing us to be the opposite.''</p>
        <p>Six weeks ago, in a fourth-floor studio at 890 Broadway, rehearsal central for musical theater in New York, Mr. Galati and Ms. Marshall watched as the company ran through the ensemble number ''Here on Who.'' Whoville is an important destination in the nearly sung-through ''Seussical.'' The inhabitants of ''the tiniest planet in the sky'' are beset by war and environmental disaster: some of the books by Dr. Seuss, a k a Theodor Geisel, are virtual parables of modern human perils. But the most affecting problem facing the Whos is that no one knows they are alive.</p>
        <p>When the number was over, Mr. Galati seemed pleased. ''There's no sense of cartoon,'' he told the company, and he meant it as a compliment. ''It's absolutely real and specific. Just as long as it stays that way, the arc of the number will work.''</p>
        <p>That adult sensibility is intended to inform every movement. For example, when the denizens of Who, hoping that Horton will protect their little planet, end their serenade of him with ''We're tiny little people/  Saying thanks in advance,'' Ms. Marshall devised a tip-o'-the-hat gesture on ''thanks in advance'' that is an homage to Broadway choruses of the past.</p>
        <p>''Like any good theater, the theme reveals itself,'' she said. ''The universality comes from the specifics.''</p>
        <p>The interwoven tales of ''Seussical'' amount to a musical convention of Seuss characters, presided over by the Cat in the Hat (played by David Shiner, half the mime team of ''Fool Moon,'' in his first professional speaking role). It is Horton alone, as the famous story goes, who hears the Whos, and in particular one of the littlest Whos, a boy named JoJo (Andrew Keenan-Bolger and Anthony Blair Hall alternate in the role) with a vivid imagination and a feeling of being all alone in the universe.</p>
        <p>It becomes Horton's humanitarian (elephantarian?) mission to have their innocent voices heard in the brutally cynical Jungle of Nool, where Horton himself is an outcast, a lonely figure of fun. He too has his blind spots, though; he is oblivious to the attentions of Gertrude McFuzz (Janine LaManna), a sorry-looking bird with only one pathetic tail feather.</p>
        <p>With its deep investment in the rhyming nonsense of Seussian language -- ''Think a Trip on a Ship/ To the Vipper of Vipp/ Or to Solla Sollew,'' the cast sings in the opening, ''Oh, the Thinks You Can Think!'' -- the musical is a manifesto on the liberation of the mind. It is also about the dignity of individual expression, the struggle to be noticed -- and accepted -- for who you are.</p>
        <p>''It's really been Lynn's and my vision of Dr. Seuss,'' said Mr. Flaherty, who has been writing musicals with Ms. Ahrens for nearly 20 years. In addition to ''Ragtime,'' their Broadway collaborations include ''My Favorite Year'' and ''Once on This Island.''</p>
        <p>''Stephen forced me to read the books,'' Ms. Ahrens added. ''The little Whos are like Earth: we're adrift, looking to save ourselves. We tried to be truthful to the innocent anarchy in the books. There is a deep concern in them for the planet, for human beings and how we should behave toward one another, and it plays out in all this zany stuff.''</p>
        <p>The songwriting team was recruited for the project by Livent, the Canadian theatrical production house founded by Garth Drabinsky, which produced ''Ragtime'' and obtained the rights to the Seuss anthology from Geisel's widow, Audrey. Following Mr. Drabinsky's dismissal after questions about Livent's bookkeeping practices, the shepherding of ''Seussical'' became the responsibility of SFX, the entertainment giant that had acquired Livent. Signing on as co-producers were Universal -- which is bringing out a big-screen version of ''How the Grinch Stole Christmas'' starring Jim Carrey, scheduled to open the week after ''Seussical'' -- and the Weisslers.</p>
        <p>Initially, Eric Idle, a member of the Monty Python comedy team, was to write the book, but he dropped out well before last summer's Toronto workshop, the event that kicked ''Seussical'' into high gear. Even Audrey Geisel was there. ''I was completely captivated,'' Mrs. Geisel said in a recent interview. ''And if I had to be narrowed to one single word about the production it would have to be 'seamless.' '' Though she had been wooed ''many, many times'' for the rights to musicalize her husband's works, she said, what persuaded her to yield on this occasion was the run-the-gamut approach.</p>
        <p>''No one had ever hit on that bouquet of all the characters, and said 'I want to take all of them,' '' she continued. ''And before, none of it was enchanting enough that I wanted to give the critters up.''</p>
        <p>From that successful workshop, many actors were retained for Broadway. None are household names, but the most troubling loss was that of Andrea Martin, who won a Tony Award for ''My Favorite Year'' and was to play the Cat in the Hat, until she decided, the producers said, that she could not be away from her family in California for the length of a Broadway run. It was then that the producers approached Mr. Shiner, whose skills as a clown with a mean streak were thought to encompass just the sort of danger required for the major-domo-like role of the Cat.</p>
        <p>Even more dangerously, though, the Cat in the Hat is ubiquitous in ''Seussical,'' assuming various personalities, commenting on the action and, gulp, singing his heart out. And Mr. Shiner has absolutely no professional experience in a musical.</p>
        <p>''I've never sung a note onstage in my life,'' he said. In fact, the thought of singing for the cast, let alone an audience, terrified him. ''I just kept getting in a room and singing and singing and singing until I started feeling comfortable with it,'' Mr. Shiner added. ''I started taking voice lessons, learning ways to deepen my voice and to relax, and I slowly discovered that my voice wasn't that bad.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, Mr. Shiner has become the embodiment of the show's attempt to defy expectations, the clown who is not just for children in a musical that is not meant just for them, either.</p>
        <p>What he and everyone else associated with ''Seussical'' are banking on is Dr. Seuss's uncommon common touch.</p>
        <p>''The essence of this piece is very universal and it connects in a deeply emotional way,'' Mr. Shiner said. ''Horton and JoJo sing of being alone in the universe, of the notion that 'I have wings and I can fly.' There is a part of everyone that feels alone -- and the feeling we all have of something in us that is much, much deeper, that feeling that we can fly.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
