<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sept. 3-9; If It Moves, Impale It</title>
    <meta content="10BOXB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DB1039F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="342" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sept. 3-9; If It Moves, Impale It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Lee Myers</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pentagon is struggling with all sorts of technological challenges -- from designing a national missile defense that works to perfecting new aircraft like the F-22. But its most embarrassing technological failure these days is popping up right outside its front door.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a heavy steel security barricade misfired, striking a car carrying Germany's defense minister, Rudolf Scharping, moments before a full-dress honors ceremony on the Pentagon's steps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pentagon is struggling with all sorts of technological challenges -- from designing a national missile defense that works to perfecting new aircraft like the F-22. But its most embarrassing technological failure these days is popping up right outside its front door.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a heavy steel security barricade misfired, striking a car carrying Germany's defense minister, Rudolf Scharping, moments before a full-dress honors ceremony on the Pentagon's steps.</p>
        <p>The freak accident wrecked the car, slightly injured Mr. Scharping, the German defense attache and an American security guard, and left Secretary of Defense William S. Cohen, who rushed to Mr. Scharping's aid, fuming.</p>
        <p>Only it was no freak accident.</p>
        <p>Two years ago the same barricade sprang up beneath the car of Japan's defense minister, Fukushiro Nukaga, injuring him and five others. In 1995, another gate struck a car carrying the former secretary of defense, William J. Perry.</p>
        <p>Evidently the system, built in the early 1990's to keep terrorists out, has a sentry's worst nightmare built in. It has difficulty distinguishing between friend and foe.</p>
        <p>What made last week's accident even more infuriating was that the Pentagon believed it had fixed the problem by replacing manual switches with electronic controls meant to keep the barricades open long enough for motorcades to pass through. (The redesigned barricade struck a car carrying Chinese military officers last January, but officials blamed tailgating and insisted the system worked.)</p>
        <p>The Pentagon vowed to conduct a new investigation into what is being called ''Gategate.'' Asked if human error, not technology, was to blame, the Pentagon's spokesman, Kenneth H. Bacon, said simply, ''I don't think we fully understand yet.''</p>
        <p>Steven Lee Myers</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
