<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Symphony Looks Back and Ahead</title>
    <meta content="10NJSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Danielpour, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Thomas Oboe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lam, Bun-Ching</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kandell, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macal, Zdenek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DC1239F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Symphony Looks Back and Ahead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KANDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kandell, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Symphony Orchestra music director Zdenek Macal comments on season's opening night, which will include premieres of works by Richard Danielpour, Thomas Oboe Lee and Bun-Ching Lam; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 20th century has passed into history. From now on, its musical works -- serialism, minimalism, warts and all -- will have to be excavated or exhumed, unless their beauty and worth float them to the surface. Picking his way through the rubble, the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra's music director, Zdenek Macal, has pulled up a season of nuggets and curiosities, combined with far-off 19th-century repertory of solid gold.</p>
        <p>The immediate past is displayed in the New Jersey premiere of Richard Danielpour's ''Toward the Splendid City'' from 1996, which opens the orchestra's first concert Sept. 14, and is to be repeated in Trenton and Newark. Mr. Macal's recording of the vibrant, rhythmic work is on Sony Classical, along with Mr. Danielpour's ''Celestial Night,'' commissioned by the orchestra for the opening of the New Jersey Performing Arts Center. Named for a Nobel Prize address by the poet Pablo Neruda, the piece portrays struggles of city life and dreams of what might be an ideal place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 20th century has passed into history. From now on, its musical works -- serialism, minimalism, warts and all -- will have to be excavated or exhumed, unless their beauty and worth float them to the surface. Picking his way through the rubble, the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra's music director, Zdenek Macal, has pulled up a season of nuggets and curiosities, combined with far-off 19th-century repertory of solid gold.</p>
        <p>The immediate past is displayed in the New Jersey premiere of Richard Danielpour's ''Toward the Splendid City'' from 1996, which opens the orchestra's first concert Sept. 14, and is to be repeated in Trenton and Newark. Mr. Macal's recording of the vibrant, rhythmic work is on Sony Classical, along with Mr. Danielpour's ''Celestial Night,'' commissioned by the orchestra for the opening of the New Jersey Performing Arts Center. Named for a Nobel Prize address by the poet Pablo Neruda, the piece portrays struggles of city life and dreams of what might be an ideal place.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Macal, ''The program is about the way composers look at cities and towns.'' The troubled splendid city is New York, he points out: the next piece, Beethoven's Pastoral Symphony, is centered in a village, and Respighi's ''Pines of Rome'' are in Rome.</p>
        <p>After ''Celestial Night,'' the orchestra won an Ascap prize for programming works composed after 1970, but Mr. Macal is wary of giving the impression that the orchestra comes up short on favorites and standards. ''It's important we play enough new music to get the prize,'' he said then, ''but the audience should not be worried that we will overload them.''</p>
        <p>Another prize -- the Pulitzer -- was awarded to Aaron Jay Kernis, whose ''Overture in Feet and Meters'' is to have its New Jersey premiere when Hugh Wolff, the orchestra's former director, returns to New Jersey after Christmas.</p>
        <p>The immediate future is represented by two orchestra commissions: ''Flauta Carioca,'' by Thomas Oboe Lee, has family ties. Mr. Lee, a college band chum of the orchestra's executive director, Lawrence Tamburri, has composed a jazzy piece, to be performed by Bart Feller, the principal flutist.</p>
        <p>''Song of Pipa,'' the other world premiere, is part of a project called ''Music Alive.'' Bun-Ching Lam, its Macao-born composer, is to be in residence at the Newark Museum. Another mini-residency is planned around the first performance. Samuel Wong, music director of the Honolulu Symphony, and the Hong Kong Philharmonic, is guest conductor.</p>
        <p>The title of Ms. Lam's concerto for pipa and symphony orchestra is from a famous eighth-century Tang Dynasty poem, she says, ''about a poet in the middle of nowhere, who has a human encounter with a girl playing the pipa,'' a Chinese lute played with picks. Wu Man, a pipa virtuoso, is to play.</p>
        <p>A recent article in The Los Angeles Times lamented that ''the American orchestra is, and always has been, a profoundly un-American institution.'' American composers are described as foreigners in their own concert halls. The American whose work is best positioned to improve that situation is Aaron Copland, whose centenary culminates in his November birthday.</p>
        <p>Surveys of Copland's music around the country suggest that his tonal orchestral pieces, with their exhilarating concoction of folk idioms, outrank his other forms. Mr. Macal is to lead an all-Copland concert: the suite from ''Appalachian Spring,'' ''A Lincoln Portrait'' and the Third Symphony, from which Copland drew the piece, ''Fanfare for the Common Man.''</p>
        <p>Mindful that last year's Pulitzer Prize in music went to a New Jersey resident, Melinda Wagner, the orchestra's chamber players are to perform new works of five New Jersey women, at the Newark Museum, with composers in attendance.</p>
        <p>The annual three-week winter festival spotlights Tchaikovsky. Concerts and seminars will focus on his fevered, misunderstood symphonies, his universally beloved ballets and his seething personal torments.</p>
        <p>Joseph Horowitz, the festival consultant, has planned events similar to those in last winter's Rachmaninoff festival: the Newark Museum commentary and recital, three concert programs of symphonies and concertos, and a choral evening of church music, called ''The Spiritual Tchaikovsky.'' Other talks link the composer to the poets Byron, Goethe, Shakespeare. There will also be a showing of ''The Music Lovers,'' Ken Russell's film about Tchaikovsky, and a separate autobiographical talk by Mr. Russell.</p>
        <p>Recognizing that movies are a great 20th-century contribution to culture, an October concert showcasing Hollywood composers who scored Hitchcock films has been designed. The orchestra is to accompany film clips from ''North by Northwest,'' composed by Bernard Herrmann, ''Dial M for Murder'' and ''Strangers on a Train,'' by Dmitri Tiomkin and ''To Catch a Thief'' by Lyn Murray. As part of the orchestra's circuit-riding tradition, subscription concerts are repeated in cities like Newark, New Brunswick, Englewood, Red Bank, Morristown, Princeton and Trenton.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SYMPHONY  ORCHESTRA OPENING NIGHT GALA</p>
        <p>New Jersey Performing Arts Center,  1 Center Street Newark.  Thursday at 7 p.m.  (800) 255-3476.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
