<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenport Painter's Art Spared From Obscurity</title>
    <meta content="10ART.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museums at Stony Brook</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Islip Art Museum</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">City Artists In Response to Nature (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dowling College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Helen A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubbard, Whitney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DF1639F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenport Painter's Art Spared From Obscurity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Helen A. Harrison</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harrison, Helen A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Helen Harrison reviews retrospective of painter Whitney Hubbard of Greenport, NY, at Museums at Stony Brook, site-specific installations by eleven artists at Carriage House, Islip Art Museum, East Islip, and show organized by City Artists In Response to Nature at Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Oakdale; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whitney M. Hubbard  The Museums at Stony Brook, 1208 Route 25A, Stony Brook. Through Sept. 24. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>In 1951, the residents of Greenport celebrated ''Hubbard Appreciation Day,'' honoring the painter Whitney Hubbard with a retrospective exhibition of his work. This past June, the village again recognized Hubbard's art with a large, wide-ranging exhibition. The current show is a condensed version of that tribute, and includes several pieces from the permanent collection of the Museums at Stony Brook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whitney M. Hubbard  The Museums at Stony Brook, 1208 Route 25A, Stony Brook. Through Sept. 24. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>In 1951, the residents of Greenport celebrated ''Hubbard Appreciation Day,'' honoring the painter Whitney Hubbard with a retrospective exhibition of his work. This past June, the village again recognized Hubbard's art with a large, wide-ranging exhibition. The current show is a condensed version of that tribute, and includes several pieces from the permanent collection of the Museums at Stony Brook.</p>
        <p>Although he also painted in New England and New York City, Hubbard's primary subject was the area around his Greenport home. His father managed the local brickworks, where Hubbard set up his easel on more than one occasion. The port itself, the surrounding coastline, and the neighborhood homes and gardens are his dominant themes. Hubbard's paintings are seldom titled and, with the exception of one canvas, ''The Harbor at Greenport,'' which won a prize in 1924, none can be confidently dated. Therefore, while he evidently went through various phases, it is more or less fruitless to try tracing his stylistic development.</p>
        <p>At different times -- or perhaps simultaneously -- his work reflects the principles of Frank Vincent DuMond, his teacher at the Art Students League; the influence of American Impressionism and Tonalism; and the more progressive post-Impressionist trends to which even conservatives like Hubbard responded in the early 20th century.</p>
        <p>What little reliable documentation exists has been summarized by Ronald G. Pisano in a catalogue essay that sheds considerable light on Hubbard's life and career. In many ways, he was a fairly typical regional artist who had some wider recognition but ultimately was all but forgotten beyond his immediate area. If it had not been for the efforts of an enthusiastic collector, whose research files were donated to the museums, Hubbard might now be entirely unknown outside Greenport.</p>
        <p>Such obscurity would be undeserved. The work certainly justifies recognition, especially the lively, freely brushed oil sketches of shoreline scenery and the dramatic landscape set pieces, like ''Long Island Farms'' and ''North Fork, Long Island Landscape,'' with their stylized compositions and vivid tonal contrasts.</p>
        <p>'Projects 2000'  Carriage House, Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane, East Islip. Through Oct. 1. (631) 244-5402.</p>
        <p>Eleven artists have contributed to the latest series of site-specific installations in the raw spaces of the museum's carriage house, where individual rooms are temporarily transformed into concentrated environments.</p>
        <p>At one entrance, Adam Shreckhise's ''The Play of Lenses and Lights'' focuses attention on building details, like the corner of a step and an edge of molding, that one would normally pass without noticing. This close observation is surprisingly intriguing, bringing out shapes, textures and patterns of things routinely taken for granted. The ordinary is also accorded elevated status in ''Spheres,'' Barbara Andrus's pair of wood balls, eight feet in diameter, crammed into a low-ceilinged room. Radiating out from boxy cores, the balls are made of interwoven twigs that appear to grow organically from the rectangular frameworks. Like oversize seed pods, they seem ready to burst the confines of their allotted space.</p>
        <p>Geraldine Erman's untitled soft sculptures are similarly expansive, apparently escaping from a closet and oozing from exposed pipes in a hallway. Made of printed fabric, woven yarn and cozy cotton blankets, the forms exploit the contrast between benign softness and assertive aggression, as if cushions and bedding had become alien life forms bent on domination.</p>
        <p>A similar feeling is intensified in ''Lust,'' an installation by an artist known as D. B. Lampman, who has filled the building's lavatory with clusters of light bulbs. Most are dormant, but each cluster contains one that glows red, while a visitor's movement activates a motor that rattles them ominously. The effect is eerily like a hothouse hatchery, with the bulbs suggesting the germinating eggs of yet another alien species.</p>
        <p>''Happy Hour,'' a collaboration by Nora Ligorano and Marshall Reese, uses video portraits and clock-face formats to critique the emotional ambiguity of laughter. Ranging from subdued chuckles to hysteria bordering on tears, the four-minute dialogue between male and female subjects provokes the observer to question what emotions are being expressed and how to recognize their meaning.</p>
        <p>Technical problems detract from the effectiveness of Teresa Jaynes's ''Gossip Manual,'' a series of disembodied mouths that satirizes idle chatter, and Charles Browning's ''A Year and a Day,'' harking back to the ancient lunar calendar of 13 months. Both pieces have animated components that were not operating when this viewer visited.</p>
        <p>'Urban Nature'  Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Idle Hour Boulevard, Oakdale. Through Sept. 17. (631) 244-3016.</p>
        <p>Organized by a New York City-based group called City Artists In Response to Nature, the show examines the interrelationship of natural and man-made environments. Urban settings often seem antithetical to nature, yet buildings, pavements and other imposed structures are surrounded and punctuated by natural phenomena.</p>
        <p>Janet Soderberg uses the city skyline as an abstract motif in ''Moonrise Over Manhattan,'' a composite photograph that turns its grid into a crystalline structure that mimics a natural formation, its warm internal glow contrasted with the moon's cool radiance. This complementary interplay takes on sinister implications in Ms. Soderberg's two ''Skystack'' pieces, in which the city's pollution subtly interacts with natural weather effects. Such cross-references are also found in Kathy Levine's mixed media works, like ''Radiali,'' where a skyline becomes the framework for a sectioned tree trunk, and ''Ascension,'' with a weedy sumac branch struggling against an artificial barrier.</p>
        <p>True to her name, Ilene Sunshine injects a lighthearted note with her star-shaped sculptures made of discarded Christmas trees. Scavenged from sidewalks, the derelict trees are cut, painted and wired to create, in the artist's words, ''a poetic synthesis of the cultivated and the constructed.''</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
