<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Champion From the 1928 Games</title>
    <meta content="10OLYM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="UP FRONT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1928)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">George Baird</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baird, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DC1439F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Champion From the 1928 Games</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <dateline>ARMONK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on George Baird, 93, relay runner in 1928 Olympics who is now second oldest living US gold medalist; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Olympics begin in Sydney, Australia, this week, George Baird will be watching as the athletes confront the blend of nerves, international attention and world-class competition that is the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>He knows the feeling. In 1928, he was a gold-medal winner in Amsterdam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Olympics begin in Sydney, Australia, this week, George Baird will be watching as the athletes confront the blend of nerves, international attention and world-class competition that is the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>He knows the feeling. In 1928, he was a gold-medal winner in Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>Baird, 93, the leadoff leg on a world-record-setting 4 by 400-meter relay team, is the second oldest living United States gold-medal winner. ''James Quinn has me by a few months,'' he said of a teammate who ran on the 4 by 100-meter relay in Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>The oldest living American Olympian is Hal Prieste of Wildwood Crest, N.J., 103, who took a bronze medal in platform diving in 1920 in Antwerp, Belgium. ''But,'' Baird said softly, ''Mr. Prieste was not a gold medalist.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, there is something special about the gold medal, and Mr. Baird keeps his in a bank vault.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing like being an Olympic champion,'' he said. ''I don't talk about it often, but sometimes youngsters whom I tell or who know about me just look at me.''</p>
        <p>What they see is a slender, wiry man with wisps of white hair. It is hard for them to picture that 72 years ago he was a college flash who got the last event of the 1928 Olympics off to a rousing start, then ran a personal-best 47.4-second 400 meters for the University of Iowa the next year.</p>
        <p>''I don't run anymore,'' Baird said. ''I gave that up in my 80's.''</p>
        <p>Even in a bank vault, his medal can work its magic, said Dorothea Baird, who shared a 48th wedding anniversary with her husband last Thursday.</p>
        <p>''When we go to a track meet, all the spectators have to park far away,'' she said, ''except for the V.I.P.'s. We show them an Amsterdam '28 pin George has, I say 'Who's more a V.I.P. than an Olympic champion?' and they let us park in the front.''</p>
        <p>In his day the Olympics, Baird said, were not the global event they are now. ''The 1928 Olympics were the start of the modern era,'' he said. ''But they had nobody from the Far East, Africa or Russia.</p>
        <p>''They didn't allow girls to run distance races, either. They didn't think they could do that. They should see them now. And it was quite different from today in another way. Money. There was none then. I liked it better that way.''</p>
        <p>The way to Amsterdam in those days was by ship.</p>
        <p>''In those days you could sail right into the city,'' Baird said. ''It was before they built all those dams. We came in on the boat, and we lived on the boat.</p>
        <p>''Shell Oil offered us the use of their facilities, so we had to be driven to their track in The Hague each day to train. I never did get to see much of the Olympics because I was in the last race.''</p>
        <p>It was a race that the United States had won by the time Baird passed the baton to the second runner. ''I had a lead of a good four yards,'' he said, then added: ''Oh, make it five; who's there to contradict me?''</p>
        <p>After a dual meet in London, it was time to relax. ''I went to Paris for a week,'' Baird recalled. ''Try ordering breakfast there in your high school French. But there was other stuff -- oh, I better not tell you about that.''</p>
        <p>Nor was there much to tell when he returned. ''I lived it then and moved on,'' he said. ''In 1929, as you've probably heard, we had the Depression. I would have liked to return to the 1932 Olympics, but there was no way to continue. Everybody had to scrounge.''</p>
        <p>Baird, born in Grand Island, Neb., but raised in Mason City, Iowa, scrounged instead of sprinting. ''I went broke somewhere in Minnesota and had to join a carnival troupe,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also spent several years working with Bill Baird's Marionettes, his late brother's puppet act. ''They were the best marionettes ever,'' he said. ''The library in Mason City built a museum wing for his puppets.</p>
        <p>''I worked with my brother for about eight years, sort of as a stage manager,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While touring in California, Baird became fascinated with education, and a graduate degree at New York University led to a lifetime of teaching. He and his wife still offer two philosophy correspondence courses, and he teaches at the theosophy center in Manhattan three or four times a week.</p>
        <p>Theosophy, he explained, ''is a very ancient science of life.</p>
        <p>''It is strictly nonsectarian, and it is probably the basis for all of the great religions down through the ages, including Hinduism, Buddhism, Plato and even Emerson.''</p>
        <p>For a long time, Baird moved away from the sport he had loved. His wife said someone else had to tell her she was married to an Olympic champion.</p>
        <p>''I got interested in the Olympics in Mexico City,'' Baird said, referring to the 1968 Games. ''I got hopped up again. Now we go on a lot of the tours offered by the Track and Field news magazine. We went to Atlanta on one in 1996. Being at the Olympics again was really great.''</p>
        <p>The Bairds still travel a lot.</p>
        <p>''Dorothy and I went to the stadium in Amsterdam a few years ago,'' he said. ''The old stadium was a mess. I've heard they've since brought it back to its original form. I'd like to see it again.''</p>
        <p>The Bairds' home, in a comfortable neighborhood here, features a long, uphill climb on a driveway to the house, where there are stairs to take one to the first level. Inside, there are family pictures and one framed Amsterdam '28 poster. The only visible concession to their years is a proliferation of magnifying glasses, and those are for Dorothea to use.</p>
        <p>''George was in very good health until last January,'' she said. ''Then he fell on some black ice going down our driveway. The medics said it was a miracle he didn't break anything. But he dislocated a hip, and his back still hurts. It's slowed him down a bit.''</p>
        <p>Baird disagreed. ''Am I slowing down? Nope,'' he said. ''I've got a lot to do yet.''</p>
        <p>UP FRONT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
