<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leader Moves To Dominate Civic Groups In Venezuela</title>
    <meta content="Y10VEN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/10/world/10VENE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Venezuelan Workers' Confederation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1DD1E39F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leader Moves To Dominate Civic Groups In Venezuela</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venezuela's Pres Hugo Chavez, whose control of government is assured by landslide victory in recent election, moves to replace independent civic and labor groups with equivalents under control of 'revolutionary' movement he heads; his immediate target is main labor coalition, Venezuelan Workers' Confederation, which he threatens to demolish; accuses its leaders of being elites who have betrayed working class; organization is sympathetic to opposition Democratic Action Party and has organized numerous strikes and protests against Chavez (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his control of the Venezuelan government assured in a landslide election five weeks ago, President Hugo Chavez is now moving to replace independent civic and labor groups with equivalents under the control of the ''revolutionary'' movement he leads.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez's immediate target is the country's main labor union coalition, the Venezuelan Workers' Confederation, or C.T.V. Accusing the group's leaders of being ''an elite that has betrayed the working class'' he warned this week that ''we are going to demolish the C.T.V.,'' which is sympathetic to the opposition Democratic Action Party and has organized numerous strikes and protests against Mr. Chavez.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his control of the Venezuelan government assured in a landslide election five weeks ago, President Hugo Chavez is now moving to replace independent civic and labor groups with equivalents under the control of the ''revolutionary'' movement he leads.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez's immediate target is the country's main labor union coalition, the Venezuelan Workers' Confederation, or C.T.V. Accusing the group's leaders of being ''an elite that has betrayed the working class'' he warned this week that ''we are going to demolish the C.T.V.,'' which is sympathetic to the opposition Democratic Action Party and has organized numerous strikes and protests against Mr. Chavez.</p>
        <p>In place of the current labor union, Mr. Chavez, a former Army paratrooper who in 1992 led an unsuccessful coup, has proposed that a referendum be held along with local elections in December to establish a single government-dominated union. The country currently has more than 9,000 unions, but Mr. Chavez has brushed aside suggestions that he allow the labor movement to clean its own house.</p>
        <p>Federico Ramirez Leon, president of the Workers' Confederation, responded to the initiative by accusing Mr. Chavez of adopting ''a policy of intimidation'' in violation of international treaties. ''The only war the president ought to win, and hasn't been able to, is the war against unemployment, crime, hunger and misery,'' he added.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Chavez's government has sought to exclude civic groups not affiliated with his movement from involvement in ''participatory democracy'' mechanisms established by the country's new Constitution, which was drawn up last year by a special assembly in which Mr. Chavez's supporters held 90 percent of the seats.</p>
        <p>Under the charter, civic groups are supposed to have a voice in designating nominees for the Supreme Court, ombudsman and other major posts. But the Supreme Court recently ruled that no organization that accepts foreign donations can take part in the process, thereby disqualifying several established human rights, religious and civic groups.</p>
        <p>''This government has a tendency to try to tailor civil society to its own measure, financing groups it likes with the objective of excluding the others from the process,'' said Liliana Ortega, a leading human rights lawyer here and a member of Queremos Elegir -- which translates ''we want to choose'' or ''we want to vote,'' -- a new, nonpartisan civic organization. ''The president thinks that he alone is civil society and that the rest of us represent nothing, and that worries me.''</p>
        <p>The court ruling is also important because Mr. Chavez's government has indicated that in order to ''decentralize'' power it intends to funnel money for community development and other projects directly to ''popular organizations'' instead of relying on state and municipal governments, some of which continue in the hands of opposition parties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez is directly involved in another dispute with Queremos Elegir and other independent civic groups that he has criticized on his weekly program broadcast by state radio, ''Hello President.'' Citing a provision in the new Constitution that requires media organizations to provide news in a ''timely and objective'' fashion, leaders of Queremos Elegir have demanded a right to reply to him on the air.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez has invoked his right to reply on several occasions. But in this case, he has refused to concede his space, with his chief adviser, Luis Miquilena, arguing that the provision does not apply to Mr. Chavez's radio program because ''it is a space that belongs to the president, who is acting as president in accordance with the hierarchy granted by the majesty of the presidency.''</p>
        <p>The controversy occurs at the same time as there are complaints the Chavez camp has clandestinely altered the country's new Constitution, which voters approved last December. Comparing that document with the version that was later published officially, Alan Brewer Carias, a constitutional lawyer who was a member of the assembly that drew up the charter, discovered 74 textual differences.</p>
        <p>Many of the changes are simply cosmetic. But some are substantive and appear either to extend or undermine the meaning of specific articles, including a phrase that deprives all Venezuelans who have double nationality through their parents from running for president, one of the Chavez team's pet causes.</p>
        <p>Facing opposition charges that ''when things are not convenient, they just change them,'' the pro-Chavez National Assembly agreed this week to have the text reviewed by the Supreme Court. But the Chief Justice, Ivan Rincon, also a Chavez loyalist, has already said that he sees ''no obstacle'' and considers the charter to be ''the most democratic'' that Venezuela has ever had.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
