<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apprehension and Hope For Stability in Mideast</title>
    <meta content="11REAX$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRANSITION IN SYRIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Hafez Al- (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D7163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apprehension and Hope For Stability in Mideast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Death of Pres Hafez al-Assad, who managed to keep Syria a political power in Middle East, brings expressions of apprehension and cautious hope for stability from regional and world leaders; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death of Hafez al-Assad, the Syrian strongman who skillfully managed to keep his insular nation a pivot of political power in the Middle East, brought expressions of both apprehension and cautious hope for stability from regional and world leaders.</p>
        <p>In Lebanon, where Mr. Assad exercised complete power, government leaders praised him effusively as the guardian of Arab pride and the man who helped Lebanon emerge from its long civil war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death of Hafez al-Assad, the Syrian strongman who skillfully managed to keep his insular nation a pivot of political power in the Middle East, brought expressions of both apprehension and cautious hope for stability from regional and world leaders.</p>
        <p>In Lebanon, where Mr. Assad exercised complete power, government leaders praised him effusively as the guardian of Arab pride and the man who helped Lebanon emerge from its long civil war.</p>
        <p>''Faced with the terrible catastrophe that strikes Lebanon at its heart, because of what the late leader gave through his efforts, his thinking, his reason and his heart, we decree a week of official mourning starting today,'' said Lebanon's prime minister, Selim al-Hoss.</p>
        <p>Syria maintains about 30,000 soldiers in neighboring Lebanon, which it treats as a satellite state. Mr. Assad's son Bashar, who appears poised to take over his father's post, has overseen Syrian activities in Lebanon for the past year.</p>
        <p>One of the most visible signs of the grief, and perhaps anxiety, over Mr. Assad's death was the reported exodus of thousands of Syrians who live and work in Lebanon but headed home today. Officials at Beirut's main bus station told Agence France-Presse that some 3,000 people had left in the space of two hours, and there were similar scenes in the northern city of Tripoli.</p>
        <p>In Jerusalem, the office of Prime Minister Ehud Barak issued a measured statement that underlined Israeli hopes that Mr. Assad's heir will exercise authority to make decisions and, if possible, sign a treaty.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, in a statement issued in Northfield, Minn., where he was speaking at a commencement, also added his hope for a renewed peace effort. ''Over the past seven years, I have met him many times and gotten to know him very well,'' Mr. Clinton said of Mr. Assad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad had calculating and often rancorous relations with his fellow Arab leaders. But after his death, the decades of bitterness were not mentioned.</p>
        <p>Yasir Arafat, who was alternately embraced and undercut by Mr. Assad, declared three days of mourning in the Palestinian-controlled territories.</p>
        <p>In Cairo, Esmat Abdel-Maguid, the secretary general of the Arab League, predicted that Syrian policy for the moment would continue along the same lines.</p>
        <p>''I believe that Syria will proceed along the same path chosen by the departed president with strength and might,'' he told the Al-Jazeera pan-Arab television station. ''I am certain the Syrian leadership will complete this process.''</p>
        <p>Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak ordered three days of mourning for Mr. Assad and praised him as a leader who ''rendered tremendous and valuable services not only to his country but also to the Arab and Islamic nations.''</p>
        <p>A presidential statement said Mr. Mubarak would ''always cherish his close friendship with the Syrian leader.''</p>
        <p>Egypt and Syria launched a surprise attack on Israel in October 1973, which was rolled back after initial gains that included an Egyptian crossing of the Suez Canal.</p>
        <p>In Russia, Mr. Assad was remembered as a crafty leader by Yevgeny M. Primakov, a former prime minister and intelligence chief who knew the Syrian president well. Syria, under President Assad, was a major client and recipient of military aid from the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>''I have known Hafez al-Assad since 1966,'' Mr. Primakov said. ''I had great respect for him. He was a wise statesman who ran his country under the difficult conditions of confrontation with Israel and the West.''</p>
        <p>But other Russian analysts, looking ahead, said Mr. Assad's death could open a window to a more confident search for peace.</p>
        <p>''An entire epoch in the Middle East is coming to an end,'' Andrei Kozyrev, the first foreign minister of Russia after the collapse of the Soviet Union, told the Echo of Moscow radio station.</p>
        <p>TRANSITION IN SYRIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
