<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gay Teacher's Disclosure Spurs a Debate</title>
    <meta content="11GAY.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newton (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaita, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDF163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gay Teacher's Disclosure Spurs a Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>NEWTON, Mass., June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Gaita, first-grade teacher who told his students that he is gay, has provoked debate among parents and educators in Newton, Mass, about when to talk to young children about sexual orientation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A first-grade teacher who told his students that he is gay has provoked a debate among parents and educators here about how soon is too soon to talk about sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>The teacher, David Gaita, who has worked at Burr Elementary School in this suburb of Boston for five years, apparently did not plan to ''come out'' to his students on May 17, when he was teaching about biographies. But when students asked about his family and who he lived with, he is said to have told his class that if he had a partner, ''someone you love the way your mom and dad love each other,'' it would be a man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A first-grade teacher who told his students that he is gay has provoked a debate among parents and educators here about how soon is too soon to talk about sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>The teacher, David Gaita, who has worked at Burr Elementary School in this suburb of Boston for five years, apparently did not plan to ''come out'' to his students on May 17, when he was teaching about biographies. But when students asked about his family and who he lived with, he is said to have told his class that if he had a partner, ''someone you love the way your mom and dad love each other,'' it would be a man.</p>
        <p>The out-of-curriculum lesson led some parents to question whether Mr. Gaita should have told his students he was gay without first informing parents. At a Parent-Teacher Organization meeting late last month, some parents said they thought it was their place to teach -- or not teach -- their children about homosexuality. Brian Camenker, director of a conservative parents' group and the father of a Burr student, told The Boston Globe that ''a child's psychology isn't put together for any of this stuff.''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Young, the Newton public schools superintendent, said he supported the way Mr. Gaita answered the students' questions. Mr. Gaita has declined to comment publicly.</p>
        <p>''Had the teacher at that point said, 'I'm married and have two kids,' no one would have blinked an eye,'' Mr. Young said. ''There should not be a double standard for heterosexual and homosexual teachers.''</p>
        <p>Mayor David Cohen of Newton said he would have been pleased to have Mr. Gaita as the teacher of his own children. ''It's quite clear he handled the situation with sensitivity and discretion,'' Mr. Cohen said.</p>
        <p>After the class, Mr. Gaita sent a letter to his students' parents explaining what had happened. But as accounts of the incident began to spread, Cynthia Bencal, the principal, sent a note to all parents on May 22 explaining the context of Mr. Gaita's statement. It read in part: ''One student asked him if he liked being gay and he said that that was a hard question to answer. He said that he was proud of who he was and that he knew he was a good person.''</p>
        <p>Pam Swift, whose children attend the Burr school, said she was unperturbed when she asked her daughter how school went and heard: ''Good. Mr. Gaita told us he was gay.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Swift sympathized with parents who want to control what their children learn, but, from what they see on television to what they hear on the playground, ''there are many things we can't shelter our kids from,'' she said. ''I'm grateful that my child can learn about this in a natural, relaxed manner.''</p>
        <p>The role of educators in explaining homosexuality has been under scrutiny here recently. On May 19, the state education commissioner fired an H.I.V. and AIDS education coordinator who conducted a talk with teenagers on ''queer sex'' as part of a gay and lesbian conference at Tufts University. The commission called the discussion prurient and not for the high school students who attended.</p>
        <p>Kathy Glennon, who heads a lesbian and gay civil rights committee for the Massachusetts Teachers Association, said Mr. Gaita was not the first first-grade teacher to have told his class he was gay, and in this context, it was more a lesson in relationships than in sexuality.</p>
        <p>''If you're a first-grade teacher and you talk about your husband or your wife, you're not talking about sex either,'' Ms. Glennon said. ''You're talking about your family.''</p>
        <p>''Unless people are willing to be out -- just be who they are -- then we send the message to students that all families are supposed to look a certain way,'' Ms. Glennon said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
