<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="11GUID$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2D6133FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>River Race</p>
        <p>The most outrageous craft ever to float, flounder or sink, and some that will sail to victory and a portion of the $2,500 prize money, will be in the Saugatuck River on Saturday at noon in Westport's Annual Great Race.</p>
        <p>Ashore on Jessup Green, from 10 a.m.to 4 p.m., boosters and booers -- and even some polite spectators -- will watch the nautical goings on and enjoy games, foot races, entertainment, ice cream and soft drinks, hot dogs. Fresh strawberries and cream will be provided by the Daughters of the British Empire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>River Race</p>
        <p>The most outrageous craft ever to float, flounder or sink, and some that will sail to victory and a portion of the $2,500 prize money, will be in the Saugatuck River on Saturday at noon in Westport's Annual Great Race.</p>
        <p>Ashore on Jessup Green, from 10 a.m.to 4 p.m., boosters and booers -- and even some polite spectators -- will watch the nautical goings on and enjoy games, foot races, entertainment, ice cream and soft drinks, hot dogs. Fresh strawberries and cream will be provided by the Daughters of the British Empire.</p>
        <p>There is no entry fee for participants in the race. They may launch themselves in canoes, kayaks, rowboats, catamarans or their own creations. The only restriction is no motors, only manual or sail power. In past years, boats have appeared as a great white shark, a pirate ship and a large yellow duck, while propulsion in one instance was provided by a gerbil running on a wheel. Three $500 prizes will be awarded for best theme, best costumes and best propulsion-flotation, plus a grand prize of $1,000 for best in show.</p>
        <p>The number to call for more information or to register for the race is (203) 454-6469.</p>
        <p>Tanzanian Inspiration</p>
        <p>An exhibition of paintings and drawings by an 18-year-old Weston High School senior, Jared Cohen, may be seen in the Weston library through July 10. Inspired by a trip to Tanzania two years ago on a five-week community service program, Mr. Cohen interpreted his experiences there in drawings and paintings. Among them are graphite pencil portraits of members of the Zulu, Masai, Wa Arusha, Ndebele and other tribes.</p>
        <p>A reception will be held on Tuesday from 6 to 8 p.m. at the library, 58 Norfield Road. Visiting hours are Monday, Tuesday, Thursday and Friday from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., Wednesday from 9 to 8 and Saturday from 10 to 4. The number to call for more information is (203) 222-2656.</p>
        <p>Impact of the Sea</p>
        <p>''Voyages: Stories of America and the Sea,'' opening at Mystic Seaport on Saturday, is described by the staff as the most ambitious exhibition ever undertaken by the 71-year-old living museum. For anyone not familiar with it, Mystic Seaport is a 40-acre re-creation of an early American fishing village and shipyard on the banks of the Mystic River.</p>
        <p>''Voyages,'' housed in the Stillman Building (a large, two-story exhibition hall at the north end of the grounds), will remain on view for 10 years, each year focusing on a different theme, with new material and special events.</p>
        <p>Its purpose is to provide visitors with a newly profound understanding of the impact of the sea on the development of the United States and each individual within its borders, no matter his or her race, age or cultural background.</p>
        <p>Seven sections of the exhibition contain rare objects and artifacts including maps, paintings, boats, clothing, tools and weapons, but there are also things to do. Interactive computer stations, hands-on art activities, audio and visual programs, and dramatic performances give life and meaning to the inanimate objects. As indicated in the exhibition title, the subject matter is revealed through the stories of people whose lives revolved around the maritime, not simply artifacts, documents and text. A perilous voyage for a Cuban family to America in 1944, memories of a young girl traveling with her family on a trade mission to Asia in 1872, and an Alaskan woman making a living by fishing are examples.</p>
        <p>The site is just off Exit 90 of Interstate 95 at 75 Greenmanville Avenue, open daily from 9 to 5. Admission is $16, $8 for children 6 through 12, free for children under 6. The number to call for more information is (888) 973-2767, the Web site address is www.mysticseaport.org.</p>
        <p>Ox Ridge Horse Show</p>
        <p>More than $125,000 in prize money will be awarded during the Ox Ridge Charity Horse Show in Darien, opening tomorrow and closing next Sunday. Begun 71 years ago, it is one of the oldest and largest horse shows in New England, attracting more than 1,500 professional and amateur riders and their mounts competing in 125 individual classes.</p>
        <p>The annual highlight, established in 1973, is the $35,000 Grand Prix, a United States Equestrian Team Regional Show Jumping Championship scheduled next Sunday at 2 p.m. Last year's winner was two-time Olympian Leslie Howard, who is expected to return this year to defend her title. Her competitors will include 1996 Olympic silver medalists Anne Kursinski, Peter Peone and Chrisy Kappler.</p>
        <p>Among other events are the $13,000 Open Jumper Division, the $5,000 Adams Futures Class, Liz Claiborne Inc. Junior Hunter division, $2,500 Junior Amateur-Owner Classic and $2,500 Howard Johnson Pony Hunter Classic. A fashion show lunch and ringside boutique shopping are also annual features of the event.</p>
        <p>Admission on Monday at 11 a.m. is free. Hours for the rest of the week are 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission from Tuesday through Friday will be $5 a car; on Saturday it will be $5, $3 for children over 5 and adults over 64; Sunday $7, $5 for children over 5 and adults over 64.</p>
        <p>The Ox Ridge Hunt Club is at 512 Middlesex Avenue in Darien. The number to call for directions or more information is (203) 656-1743.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
