<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/130 West 57th Street; A Building and a Family With Intertwined Histories</title>
    <meta content="11SCAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000618T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jedwabnik Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/130 West 57th Street; A Building and a Family With Intertwined Histories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on history of apartment building at 130 West 57th Street in Manhattan, which has been owned by Jedwabnik family for more than half century; photos (Streetscapes column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN August 1939, Mira Jedwabnik, 10, and her parents sailed from Poland to New York for a six-week vacation to see the World's Fair. But by the time they docked, the German Army was rampaging through Poland, and they were trapped in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Jedwabniks moved into an old studio building at 130 West 57th Street, and for  more than half a century it's been their home and business, for four generations of a family just as involved in art as in commerce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN August 1939, Mira Jedwabnik, 10, and her parents sailed from Poland to New York for a six-week vacation to see the World's Fair. But by the time they docked, the German Army was rampaging through Poland, and they were trapped in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Jedwabniks moved into an old studio building at 130 West 57th Street, and for  more than half a century it's been their home and business, for four generations of a family just as involved in art as in commerce.</p>
        <p>Before the start of the Second World War, Lydia and David Jedwabnik led a prosperous life in Vilna, Poland (now Vilnius, Lithuania). The Jedwabniks lived in a Baroque-style apartment house. Mrs. Jedwabnik, now 92, was a painter, and Dr. Jedwabnik ran a hospital.</p>
        <p>The Germans invaded Poland on Sept. 1, 1939, and the Jedwabnik's homeland collapsed within weeks. The Nazis killed most of their family, along with almost all the other Jews in Vilna. In New York, the Jedwabniks first settled on the Upper West Side, but after Dr. Jedwabnik was recertified to practice medicine, they looked for something that recalled the elegant quarters they had left.</p>
        <p>Guided in part by young Mira, whose command of English was the best in the family, they settled at 130 West 57th Street, a co-op studio building built in 1908 as a twin to 140. The co-op failed in the 1930's, and the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, which took over the building, was renting the apartments as best it could, although they were far from the clean, modern designs that were becoming popular.</p>
        <p>The Jedwabniks took an apartment with a giant, double-height studio facing 57th Street with flanking regular-height bedrooms, dining room and kitchen. Lydia Jedwabnik decorated the apartment with red velvet wall hangings, antique furniture and artwork. She painted the neo-Classical fireplace with Chagall-like colors, and painted figures of Russian folk dancers on the panes of the windows. She was born in Odessa and educated in Moscow and Berlin, and speaks German, Polish, Russian, French and English.</p>
        <p>During the war, Dr. Jedwabnik's brother, Abram, arrived from Paris and bought 130 West 57th Street from Metropolitan Life in 1945. He died in 1949 and left it to his brother.  The family ran it themselves. ''My father had run a hospital, he didn't think it was such a big deal to run a building,'' says his daughter, now Mira Jedwabnik Van Doren.</p>
        <p>What they got was a building with a distinguished history of tenants who included the novelist William Dean Howells and the artist Childe Hassam; the distinctive trapezoidal windows of 130 West 57th appear in several of his paintings.</p>
        <p>Later tenants included Joseph Heller and  Jose Ferrer, who often came to the Jedwabniks' New Year's Eve parties. Lydia Jedwabnik painted the dancers on her windows in honor of a visit by the Moiseyev ballet company.</p>
        <p>After the war, Mira Jedwabnik embarked on a career as a mural and vitreous enamel artist, taking commissions like tables for the luxury liner United States and the powdery, highly colored elevator doors of 130 West 57th. Thumping the panels, which still look fresh after 30 years she said: ''See?  Vandal-proof.''</p>
        <p>In 1955 she married the professor and editor John Van Doren, son of Mark Van Doren, the late critic, poet and professor of English at Columbia University, in her parents' apartment. She took over management of the building in the 1980's. She and her son Daniel, a lawyer, now run it with an Old World approach. ''We come from a family of artists and writers, and this has always been a place for them,'' Mrs. Van Doren said.</p>
        <p>Daniel's brother, Adam, an artist, architect and filmmaker, has his office in the building. He does the historical research for a growing lobby display, one of the most ambitious in New York.</p>
        <p>About 10 years ago, he began researching census and other records to determine the earlier tenants. Buying through Web vendors like eBay and Bibliofind, he has collated photographs, Playbills, book covers and reproductions of paintings and letters, creating a series of framed collages. These include a lease with Joseph Heller; a letter to Mark Twain from William Dean Howells (on 130 West 57th Street letterhead); reproductions of Childe Hassam's paintings showing the windows; and photographs of the painting studio of Irving Wiles. And, on one wall, a giant mural salvaged from the old Russian Tea Room.</p>
        <p>The Van Dorens have good lease records back to 1947, so they can document exactly which space Ray Charles rented, where the Rolling Stones practiced, and where Woody Allen's production company rented from the 1960's to the 1990's. But Adam Van Doren says he is frustrated by the earlier period, from 1908 to 1947; although early directories often list room numbers, only Polk's New York City Directory of 1933 lists apartment numbers.</p>
        <p>So they have to fill in from occasional clues as best they can. They know that  Hassam's studio was on the ninth floor west. That means the society figure Grace Wilson lived just below him, because in 1921 Hassam testified in court that he frequently had to jump up and down on the floor to complain about ragtime concerts at Mrs. Wilson's apartment. ''Discords, yelling, catcalling,'' the painter described them to The New York Times. ''It's an absolute riot.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Van Doren was excited when he recently spotted the filmmaker D. W. Griffith listed as a resident in the 1925 census, although how they will determine his apartment number is difficult to say. The Van Dorens have only seven residential tenants left -- the rest of the 55 units are commercial -- and the increase in rental income has permitted them to maintain the building in the way they would like.</p>
        <p>THEY cleaned the front a few years ago, and redid the hallways by exposing the mosaic tile and polishing the original mail chute. They salvage old flooring from one space and use it in another, they keep an eye out for more vintage doors and battle with the cable installers who ''have no regard for architectural integrity,'' Daniel Van Doren said.</p>
        <p>''Accountants come in and they want to divide up the space,'' he said, waving at one of the high-ceilinged studios. ''We just say,  This building is not for you.' '' This summer, the Van Dorens are putting up a new $30,000 metal and glass canopy on the street.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jedwabnik died in 1972, but Lydia Jedwabnik still occupies the family's original apartment. Asked if she ever considered leaving the city or moving to a more residential neighborhood, she exclaimed: ''No!  I like New York, and 57th Street, with Carnegie Hall and the Russian Tea Room.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Van Doren lives two floors above her mother, but her sons don't live at 130 West 57th Street, although Adam said, ''One day everybody will be living here.'' Both sons have young children who frequently visit.</p>
        <p>At the same time that the Van Dorens began researching the history of their tenants, Mira Jedwabnik Van Doren began researching the history of the Jewish community of Vilna, and is now close to completing a documentary film. From a duplex office, she is searching for financing for the film's final editing. ''I've had such good fortune,'' she said.''If I can finish it, it will be my thank you to God.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 18, 2000, Sunday  The Streetscapes column last Sunday, about the building at 130 West 57th Street, misstated the floor on which the artist Childe Hassam had a studio. It was the 13th, not the 9th.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 11, 2001, Sunday  The Streetscapes column last June 11, about the history of an apartment building at 130 West 57th Street, misstated the name of the defendant in a 1921 Police Court case that heard a nuisance complaint that included testimony by the painter Childe Hassam. A reader's letter received on Feb. 26 pointed out that according to contemporary news accounts the downstairs neighbor against whom Hassam testified in support of a neighbor's complaint about noise from dinner parties and musicales was Marion Wilson, not Grace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 18, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Streetscapes column last Sunday, about the building at 130 West 57th Street, misstated the floor on which the artist Childe Hassam had a studio. It was the 13th, not the 9th.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: March 11, 2001, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Streetscapes column last June 11, about the history of an apartment building at 130 West 57th Street, misstated the name of the defendant in a 1921 Police Court case that heard a nuisance complaint that included testimony by the painter Childe Hassam. A reader's letter received on Feb. 26 pointed out that according to contemporary news accounts the downstairs neighbor against whom Hassam testified in support of a neighbor's complaint about noise from dinner parties and musicales was Marion Wilson, not Grace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
