<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Miami Native Makes Nature Lush and Threatening</title>
    <meta content="11SCHW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, NAOMI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHWABSKY, BARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DA143FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Miami Native Makes Nature Lush and Threatening</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY SCHWABSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHWABSKY, BARRY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Schwabsky article on photographer Naomi Fisher, 23, Miami native whose first exhibition in New York is at Lombard-Freid Fine Arts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NAOMI FISHER makes Cibachrome photographs that are at once beautiful, disturbing and absurd. Amid lush tropical foliage, viewers glimpse isolated, partly clothed figures, often faceless, usually female. Are they victims of violence, perhaps even corpses that have been dumped in some forsaken terrain where they may never be recovered? Or are they participating in a clandestine sexual encounter with a partner just off-camera? In some of the images, gorgeous exotic flowers emerge from the figures' pulled-down panties as though they had been placed there as part of some bizarre ritual.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher is having her first exhibition in New York (at Lombard-Freid Fine Arts through June 24), a formidable accomplishment for someone who is 23 and who graduated from art school only two years ago. But the exhibition is more than the introduction of a young artist. It also represents broadening recognition for the newly energized Miami art scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NAOMI FISHER makes Cibachrome photographs that are at once beautiful, disturbing and absurd. Amid lush tropical foliage, viewers glimpse isolated, partly clothed figures, often faceless, usually female. Are they victims of violence, perhaps even corpses that have been dumped in some forsaken terrain where they may never be recovered? Or are they participating in a clandestine sexual encounter with a partner just off-camera? In some of the images, gorgeous exotic flowers emerge from the figures' pulled-down panties as though they had been placed there as part of some bizarre ritual.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher is having her first exhibition in New York (at Lombard-Freid Fine Arts through June 24), a formidable accomplishment for someone who is 23 and who graduated from art school only two years ago. But the exhibition is more than the introduction of a young artist. It also represents broadening recognition for the newly energized Miami art scene.</p>
        <p>Born and raised in Miami, Ms. Fisher could be the symbol for the city's commitment to arts education. ''I've been in art programs since I was in third grade,'' she says, and she must be one of the only artists around whose bio includes a high school degree (from Miami's New World School of the Arts, which includes both a magnet high school and a college). She went on to earn a bachelor of fine arts degree from the Maryland Institute College of Art in Baltimore before returning to her hometown in 1998.</p>
        <p>There, she supported herself until recently by working as a caretaker at the Rubell Family Collection, the showcase for the powerful, formerly New York-based art collectors. The Rubells went from being Ms. Fisher's employers to being patrons when they began buying her work last year.</p>
        <p>Bill Begert, the director of the Rubell Family Collection, says the interest of the Rubells and other Miami collectors in Ms. Fisher's work is something of a breakthrough. ''Local collectors who have traditionally looked outside Miami for direction -- to New York, to Los Angeles, to Europe -- have really followed Naomi's work and invested in it, and that's led collectors elsewhere to take an interest,'' he said. ''They're finally making a mark outside, acting on their own initiative.'' Other emerging Miami artists include Dara Friedman, whose work is in this year's Whitney Biennial, and Luis Gispert, whose work is included, along with Ms. Fisher's and others, in a group show called ''Young Miami'' at the Wooster Projects Gallery in SoHo through Friday.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher counts on the ambiguity of her images to be part of their power but also observes, ''Violence informs my way of working.''</p>
        <p>''Women get stereotyped as making art about repression or sexual politics,'' she says, ''and our work can be marginalized for that, but it's just part of our experience. I was in the eighth grade the first time a friend of mine was raped.''</p>
        <p>If people are seen as threatened and threatening in Ms. Fisher's images, her view of nature is no more comforting. With their flower-print clothing and underwear, the women in the photographs and her expressionistic drawings seem to have wanted to identify with nature, yet it turns out to be inhospitable.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Fisher, however, nature is also a family affair; her father is a prominent botanist. And though the photographs may look like they were taken in some isolated mangrove forest, she says, ''every single one of these was shot in my parents' backyard.''</p>
        <p>''My dad hates what my images look like, but he's totally supportive anyway,'' Ms. Fisher says. In general, she resists the suggestion that her work is autobiographical, and says that some viewers have made too much of the fact that the bodies in many of the photographs are her own or her sister's. ''That's why you rarely see any faces,'' she says. ''I don't want the photograph to be a portrait. In fact I just noticed, the only faces you can see are the boys'.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Barry Schwabsky is the author of ''The Widening Circle: Consequences of Modernism in Contemporary Art'' (Cambridge University Press).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Barry Schwabsky is the author of ''The Widening Circle: Consequences of Modernism in Contemporary Art'' (Cambridge University Press).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
