<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOLLOWING UP</title>
    <meta content="11FOLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Larson, Jonathan, Performing Arts Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mascara, Red</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Larson, Jonathan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rent (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Following Up</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFD9163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOLLOWING UP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Red Mascara of Phillipsburg, NJ, has spent last 40 years lobbying State Legislature, trying to get his song, I'm From New Jersey, adopted as official state song; photo; Jonathan Larson Performing Arts Foundation, created by family of creator of Broadway musical Rent has donated $55,000 in proceeds from show to struggling composers, lyricists, and other artists and nonprofit theater companies; Larson died night of show's final dress rehearsal, at age 35; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Song Remains the Same. Will New Jersey Listen?</p>
        <p>O, New Jersey! Not only are you the butt of tedious ''What exit?'' jokes, but you lack what most other states revel in: a song of your own. This is certainly not because of a lack of lyricism west of the Holland Tunnel (just ask any Bruce Springsteen fan), or because of a lack of efforts by Red Mascara of Phillipsburg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Song Remains the Same. Will New Jersey Listen?</p>
        <p>O, New Jersey! Not only are you the butt of tedious ''What exit?'' jokes, but you lack what most other states revel in: a song of your own. This is certainly not because of a lack of lyricism west of the Holland Tunnel (just ask any Bruce Springsteen fan), or because of a lack of efforts by Red Mascara of Phillipsburg.</p>
        <p>It is because of, dare we count, six decades of legislative inaction. Not since the state militia sang ''Jersey Blue'' in 1794 during the Whisky Rebellion has there been a consensus about a song for the Garden State. There was a contest for state song in 1939, but the Legislature didn't make the winner official. In 1956 the Department of Education reviewed many options, but found none of sufficient merit. In 1972 the Legislature cast its votes for the roisterous ''I'm From New Jersey,'' written in 1960 by Mr. Mascara. It goes something like this:</p>
        <p>I'm from New Jersey and I'm proud about it, I love the Garden State.</p>
        <p>I'm from New Jersey and I want to shout it, I think it's simply great.</p>
        <p>But Gov. William T. Cahill refused to sign the bill, reportedly saying, ''If there is one thing worse than the song 'I'm From New Jersey,' it is Red Mascara singing 'I'm From New Jersey.' ''</p>
        <p>Fast forward to 1996, when a law directed the New Jersey State Arts Council to come up with a list of favorites. Four years and 215 entries later, nothing. Rien de rien.</p>
        <p>It's all a little daunting for the tireless Mr. Mascara, 78, a retired chemical factory worker who for 40 years has lobbied the Legislature, schmoozing, passing out gumdrops, all for a song. He said the sponsor of one of the three current bills in favor of his song is Christopher Kip Bateman, whose father, Raymond, was Senate president back in 1972 when Governor Cahill rejected the Legislature's choice.</p>
        <p>But there is a move afoot, Mr. Mascara said, to create four state tunes: the top three choices of the 1996 contest, so the state would have a state song, a state anthem, a state pop song, and, be still, beating heart -- a state march. His.</p>
        <p>'Rent' Checks Go To Support Artists</p>
        <p>Jonathan Larson, creator of the Broadway musical ''Rent,'' died the night of the show's final dress rehearsal. But in the four years since, as his rock opera thrived, Mr. Larson, who was 35 when he died of a heart aneurysm, has continued to contribute to the theater world posthumously.</p>
        <p>The Jonathan Larson Performing Arts Foundation, created by his family using proceeds from the show, gave $55,000 in February to composers, lyricists, other artists and nonprofit theater companies.</p>
        <p>''He worked for 12 years as a waiter trying to support himself while he was trying to write shows,'' said Mr. Larson's father, Allan, who lives in New Mexico. ''We know he was not alone in that.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Kassak Diekmann, the foundation's executive director, said eight individuals received grants of $2,500 to $10,000 this year, and four organizations received aid.</p>
        <p>A 1998 grant winner, ''Bubbly Black Girl Sheds Her Chameleon Skin,'' a musical by  Kirsten Childs, is about to open at Playwright's Horizon. Other winners have included the composer-lyricist Paul Scott Goodman, whose ''Bright Lights, Big City'' played at the New York Theater Workshop.</p>
        <p>Allan Larson will travel to Dublin, the Netherlands, Copenhagen and Budapest in  coming months to see ''Rent'' openings. He is glad that his son's work can help more artists. ''That's what 'Rent' is all about, is community,'' he said, adding that his son would approve. ''He'd say, 'Where was it when I needed it?' ''</p>
        <p>TINA KELLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
