<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons in Body and Soul</title>
    <meta content="11CADA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDICINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Medical College (Valhalla, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2D6133FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons in Body and Soul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>VALHALLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at New York Medical College in Valhalla, NY, described as college holds Convocation of Thanks, 12th annual memorial service for those who donated their bodies to be studied there; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANTHONY ANZALONE stood in a crowded auditorium at New York Medical College here, speaking in a halting voice. Among those in the audience were students who had worked on the body of his wife in anatomy class.</p>
        <p>Before she died at 76, Annelise Anzalone had willed her remains to the school. Now her husband was at the Convocation of Thanks, the college's 12th-annual memorial service for those who had donated their bodies to be studied there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANTHONY ANZALONE stood in a crowded auditorium at New York Medical College here, speaking in a halting voice. Among those in the audience were students who had worked on the body of his wife in anatomy class.</p>
        <p>Before she died at 76, Annelise Anzalone had willed her remains to the school. Now her husband was at the Convocation of Thanks, the college's 12th-annual memorial service for those who had donated their bodies to be studied there.</p>
        <p>''My wife had a request for the students,'' he said, then read words he had written the way he imagined Mrs. Anzalone might have spoken them. ''I would be so grateful if you can let my living soul enter your hearts and always remember the anonymous little old lady on the laboratory table in New York Medical College. As you enter the world of medicine and are confronted with serious problems and need assistance, look for that little old woman, and I will be there in your hour of need.''</p>
        <p>As part of the ceremony, which drew 250 students and family members and friends of the dead, a dozen students spoke in the most respectful and grateful terms about the cadavers that they think of as their first patient. Each said that he or she would always be grateful to these people who, in death, had provided them with the means to learn the intricacies of the human body so that they could later heal the living.</p>
        <p>''What do we feel for the cadavers we study?'' Steve Fordan, a student, asked rhetorically. ''In a word, reverence.'' Mr. Fordan said that none of the students know the names of the deceased whose corpses they probe and analyze, but they recognize each as a once living, breathing, unique person. ''This was someone's body, the vessel of their soul,'' he said. ''This was someone's father, mother, son, daughter.''</p>
        <p>Others expressed similar feelings. In the laboratory, each cadaver is laid out on a stainless steel table and covered with a white plastic shroud. Students expose and dissect one section at a time, beginning with the chest, then the abdomen, and so forth, ending with the head. Seeing the facial features, probing the brain, they said, is nothing short of profound.</p>
        <p>''I was holding this brain, the essence of this person, in my hands,'' Ross Goldberg said. ''This person not only taught me about anatomy, but about life itself, and how precious, fragile and remarkable it is. The respect for human life is something we need to remember as we work so hard to be medical technicians.''</p>
        <p>This is a lesson that Dr. Matthew Pravetz, assistant professor of cell biology and anatomy, teaches repeatedly. Gone are the days, he said, when students were allowed to deflect their discomfort around the cadavers with gallows humor. From Day 1, Dr. Pravetz, who is also a Franciscan priest, reiterates that respect is paramount.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has annihilation anxiety, the fear of nonexistence,'' he said. Some students faint when they first see the bodies. Drained of blood, filled with embalming fluid, they are starkly pale. Stacked in an area called the cold room, they look almost unreal, until one sees wisps of hair or bits of nail polish that has occasionally not been removed from fingertips or toes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pravetz tells the students that they must never ignore these signs of humanity, never lose sight of the person that once was. Although they will be examining skin, muscle, organs and bone, all of these things will be replaced in proper order in the bodies. At the end of the year, the remains will be returned to families or cremated or buried by the school.</p>
        <p>And, at the end of each year, there is a convocation, with its speeches, poems and songs. Over and over, students express their thanks to the anonymous donors.</p>
        <p>''What I have learned from them will be with me always,'' Lea DeFrancicsi said. Brooke Wolvin called the cadaver on which she had worked ''my favorite teacher.'' Stuart Bentley-Hibbert added: ''My first patient valued our education so much as to give himself. Every life that I save will be influenced by that first patient.''</p>
        <p>For the relatives, the memorial is a way to receive these thanks, and to gain closure.</p>
        <p>Betty Duval, 79, was there to remember her mother, Marie Townsend Duval, who died at 102. ''She saw this as her last opportunity to give of herself,'' she said. There was even room for some humor. Nodding toward Ann Hayes, who helped care for her mother for nine years, Mrs. Duval said,  ''Mother used to tell me all the time: 'When it happens, when I go, don't start screaming. Just get busy and get me to the college.' ''</p>
        <p>MEDICINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
