<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Border-Hopping In Basque Country</title>
    <meta content="HONDA.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GIUPUZCOA (SPAIN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HONDARRIBIA (SPAIN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINBERGER, JILL KNIGHT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1D6163FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Border-Hopping In Basque Country</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL KNIGHT WEINBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINBERGER, JILL KNIGHT</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jill Knight Weinberger travel article on Hondarribia, coastal resort in Spain's Basque country, tiny province of Guipuzcoa and quick hops across border to France; photos (M)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was nothing remotely spooky about the sparkling August day on which my husband, G. J., and I checked into El Emperador, a parador in the  Basque town of Hondarribia in northern Spain. Even the severe 16th-century stone facade of this former castle-fortress seemed welcoming and golden, washed as it was by the afternoon sun. Nonetheless, near the end of our stay we were told about Celedonio, the parador's resident phantom. The congenial apparition is a nobleman who is thought to have once lived in what is now one of Spain's most popular historic hotels.  Neither G. J. nor I made his acquaintance during our four-day stay, but many other guests have, said the parador's director, Pilar de Miguel Hernando, who has herself seen him four times. Celedonio is a good ghost, she claimed, a smiling figure who usually appears in January and February, the parador's quietest months.</p>
        <p>Although the folklore of Spain's Basque country is rife with the supernatural, we experienced nothing disturbing during our stay in Hondarribia, one of the region's  principal coastal resorts, or during our explorations of the tiny province of Guipuzcoa.  The only spirits we encountered were those we imbibed, although Izarra, the Basque liqueur made from Pyrennean herbs, did taste to me more like witches' brew than magic potion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was nothing remotely spooky about the sparkling August day on which my husband, G. J., and I checked into El Emperador, a parador in the  Basque town of Hondarribia in northern Spain. Even the severe 16th-century stone facade of this former castle-fortress seemed welcoming and golden, washed as it was by the afternoon sun. Nonetheless, near the end of our stay we were told about Celedonio, the parador's resident phantom. The congenial apparition is a nobleman who is thought to have once lived in what is now one of Spain's most popular historic hotels.  Neither G. J. nor I made his acquaintance during our four-day stay, but many other guests have, said the parador's director, Pilar de Miguel Hernando, who has herself seen him four times. Celedonio is a good ghost, she claimed, a smiling figure who usually appears in January and February, the parador's quietest months.</p>
        <p>Although the folklore of Spain's Basque country is rife with the supernatural, we experienced nothing disturbing during our stay in Hondarribia, one of the region's  principal coastal resorts, or during our explorations of the tiny province of Guipuzcoa.  The only spirits we encountered were those we imbibed, although Izarra, the Basque liqueur made from Pyrennean herbs, did taste to me more like witches' brew than magic potion.</p>
        <p>Hondarribia proved an excellent base for our first foray into Basque country. Situated at the confluence of the Bay of Txingudi and the mouth of the Bidassoa River, the fishing port offered an agreeable combination of elements: a medieval quarter with cobblestone streets and Gothic church, a former fisherman's district of gaily colored townhouses, and a lively waterfront promenade.  France lies just across the Bidassoa, a five-minute ferry ride away (or a 15-minute drive overland to the border), so it was easy to hop between countries at our whim; to lunch, say, in Biarritz and drive back to Spain along the scenic corniche carved into the steep hills facing the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Still partly encircled by stone ramparts, Hondarribia's old town is perched above La Marina, the fishermen's quarter. Its hub is the Plaza de Armas, a broad square dominated by the castle-parador, where border troops once practiced their manual of arms.  From here one enjoys a fine view of the harbor and the French border town of Hendaye before descending the winding and uneven steps to the lower town.</p>
        <p>The castle, however, is Hondarribia's most notable monument. Built in the 10th century by the kings of Navarre, it provided strategic fortification against periodic incursions by the French. Nowadays, the only invaders are tourists and sailors. Looking out from the casement windows of our castle room, we witnessed the daily invasion of sailboats, fleets of them, as they plied the narrow waterway between Hondarribia and Hendaye.</p>
        <p>Still bearing a few battle scars, the castle's austere facade reflects both the 16th-century renovations undertaken in the reign of Emperor Charles V -- the first Spanish Hapsburg monarch, who visited from time to time -- and its former function as fortress, barracks and prison. In the 1920's, Queen Maria Cristina helped rescue the nearly ruined castle, which subsequently underwent decades of restoration work. General Franco presided over its opening as a parador in 1968.</p>
        <p>Inside, the castle is a marvel of modern comfort and royal, if somewhat martial, grandeur, with its stone-block walls, vaulted ceilings and profusion of weaponry that decorate its public spaces. Even a cannon can be found in the glass-roofed, light-flooded inner courtyard, one of our favorite haunts. G. J. and I took our breakfast here, helping ourselves to the delicious buffet in the adjacent dining room, then settling in to sip our cafe con leche and admire the courtyard's renaissance arches and moss-draped walls.</p>
        <p>A few steps away from the castle along the Calle Mayor is another historic gem of Hondarribia's old quarter. The small 15th-century Church of Santa Maria, formally known as Our Lady of the Assumption, was the site of the proxy wedding of French King Louis XIV and the Infanta of Spain, Maria Teresa, in 1660. This alliance -- more political than romantic -- is recalled throughout the region. The 1659 Treaty of the Pyrenees that decreed their marriage was signed on Pheasant Island (Isla de los Faisanes), situated in the Bidassoa, in the neighboring town of Irun.</p>
        <p>The narrow Calle Mayor is lined with old manor houses, many of them dating from the 18th century. Several of these are now art galleries, although one houses the Restaurante Sebastian, where G. J. and I dined at the recommendation of the parador staff. One of Hondarribia's finest Basque restaurants, Sebastian's has the atmosphere of a private home, with its series of small rooms (painted a rich rose and hung with an eclectic array of paintings).  We enjoyed a splendid meal of monkfish-stuffed ravioli, lubina (sea bass) and, for G. J., a tender fillet of ostrich (farm raised in Spain).</p>
        <p>Sampling the local cuisine, how ever, did not always require a reservation. Late one afternoon, while strolling in La Marina in the lower town we chanced upon a sardine festival. While a trio performed amplified Basque songs, local people lined up at stalls for freshly grilled sardines and draughts of hard cider or white wine.</p>
        <p>Even without the street fair, La Marina's pedestrian thoroughfares -- Calle Santiago and Calle San Pedro -- were always lively with cafe patrons and shoppers. Once home to Hondarribia's fishermen and now a small but thriving commercial district, these streets are lined with distinctive wooden three-story houses called arratzales. Their whitewashed exteriors are brightened by their red, blue and green trims and flower-laden balconies.</p>
        <p>Along Hondaribbia's waterfront promenade, G. J. and I often joined the crowds of families and couples on their evening paseo, pausing to watch the sailboats float by or stopping for a sherry in one of the myriad cafes.</p>
        <p>Early one evening we took a turn off the promenade and boarded the ferry for a quick hop over to France.  In the fading light, we strolled for an hour around Hendaye's beachfront and marina district, watching patrons stream into the many seafood restaurants. Soon, the elaborate plateaux de fruits de mer began to tower over tabletops, edible still lifes of local shellfish.</p>
        <p>Hondarribia's attractive half-mile wedge of sandy beach lies north of town, and beyond it lies Cape Higuer, which juts into the Bay of Biscay. The landscape and coastline to the west of town turn wilder, as we discovered on a morning's ride over the Jaizkibel Road to San Sebastian, the provincial capital of Guipuzcoa some 12 miles distant. This scenic route winds over the green hills lining the coast, past the 16th-century Chapel of Our Lady of Guadalupe, to whom an annual festival is dedicated in honor of the deliverance of Hondarribia from the French siege of 1638.  Although we took the route in the morning, shielding our eyes against the sparkling glare of the Atlantic waters, it is best driven in the late afternoon, when, we are told, the jagged coastline turns golden.</p>
        <p>Another excursion took us along the Corniche Basque, which hugs the French coastline between Hendaye and the resort town of St.-Jean-de-Luz, about 10 miles to the northeast of Hondarribia. We found the town in full summer swing, crowded but pleasant nonetheless. The local food and crafts are decidedly Basque:  pastry shops offer the delectable gateau basque filled with almond cream or black cherry preserves, and souvenir shops sell handmade espadrilles and linens embroidered with a geometrical pattern of seven stripes denoting the seven Basque provinces of France and Spain.</p>
        <p>But the town's historical and cultural ties to Hondarribia provided a focus for our visit. We toured the Maison Louis XIV, the 17th-century mansion where the bridegroom Louis resided for 40 days while awaiting his nuptials. The house is still privately owned by descendants of the Lohobiague family, whose ancestor, a wealthy shipowner, built the mansion in 1643. Nearby, a 17th-century Italianate villa now called Maison de l'Infante housed the bride, Maria Teresa, and her mother-in-law, Anne of Austria.</p>
        <p>The wedding took place on June 9, 1660, in the Eglise St.-Jean-Baptiste, situated in what is now the pedestrian shopping zone of the town. Its most remarkable feature is a mid-17th-century altarpiece mounted with 22 gilded statues of the saints.  The designer is unknown, but a local sculptor named Martin de Bidache is credited with its execution, carving the individual statues in his workshop and transporting them in an oxcart to the church.</p>
        <p>On our last morning in Hondarribia, a Sunday, G. J. and I awoke not to the pealing of church bells but to the muted, serene sounds of the txistularis. Racing down to the Plaza de Armas, we watched as the quartet of Basque musicians circled the plaza, playing their traditional instruments: the txistu, a flute, and the attabal, a small drum. It was not a call to worship but simply a reminder of a centuries-old musical heritage still cherished in this region. To G. J. and me, they were also the sounds of farewell.</p>
        <p>A handy base for Basque country</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>Travelers may fly to the San Sebastian-Hondarribia airport from Madrid on Iberia Airlines. Other regional airports are in Bilbao and Biarritz, France.</p>
        <p>The closest railway station to Hondarribia is in the neighboring town of Irun. Exploring the region is most easily done by car.</p>
        <p>Places to Stay</p>
        <p>Parador El Emperador, Plaza de Armas 14, Hondarribia; (34-943) 645 500, fax (34-943) 642 153. Doubles are around $90, including breakfast but not 7 percent tax, and go up to $104 in July and August (at 183 pesetas to the dollar). Reservations can be made in the United States through Marketing Ahead, (800) 223-1356, which quoted a rate of $125 including tax and breakfast until July 1, then $142. Information on paradores can be found at www.parador.es.</p>
        <p>The charming eight-room Pampinot Hotel, Calle Mayor 5, (34-943) 640 600, fax (34-943) 645 128, is in a 16th-century manor house. Doubles start at $90 plus 7 percent tax; breakfast is $7. On the Web: www  .hotelpampinot.com.</p>
        <p>Places to Eat</p>
        <p>Restaurante Sebastian, Calle Mayor 9-11, Hondarribia; (34-943) 640 167, housed in an old mansion, provides an intimate setting in a series of small dining rooms. Offerings include the Basque classic hake in green sauce, as well as traditional Spanish fare such as gazpacho. Dinner for two with wine, about $60.</p>
        <p>More casual in atmosphere is the Restaurant Arraunlari, on Hondarribia's waterfront promenade, the Paseo de Butron. Fresh fish is the specialty. A thoroughly enjoyable meal included cold melon soup garnished with Iberico ham, warm seafood salad and squid cooked in its own ink.  With a half-bottle of house red, our bill was about $50.</p>
        <p>Places to See</p>
        <p>Hondarribia's historic district and colorful fisherman's quarter are delightful to stroll. Historic highlights include the parador; Santa Maria de la Asuncion, and the 15th-century gate, Puerta de Santa Maria. Excursions to the elegant resort cities of San Sebastian and Biarritz can be made by car in well under an hour.</p>
        <p>The outstanding cultural attraction of Basque Spain, however, is the Guggenheim Museum, Abandoibarra Et. 2, Bilbao; (34-944) 359-080.  The museum, designed by Frank O. Gehry, is about an hour's drive west of Hondarribia. Open 10 a.m. to 8 p.m. from Tuesday to Sunday, as well as on Mondays in July and August. Admission, about $6.50.</p>
        <p>Across the French border, in St.-Jean-de-Luz, the Maison Louis XIV, (33-5) 59.26.01.56, is open from June through mid-October on Monday through Saturday from 10:30 a.m. to noon and 2:30 to 5:30 p.m.; afternoons only on Sundays and July 14 and Aug. 15, and until 6:30 in July and August. Closed the rest of the year. Tours of this 17th-century mansion, where the Sun King spent his last days of bachelorhood, are offered on the half-hour. Admission $4.</p>
        <p>More Information</p>
        <p>Tourist Office of Spain, 666 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10103; (212) 265-8822 fax (212) 265-8864; www  .okspain.org.</p>
        <p>French Government Tourist Office, 444 Madison Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022; (212) 838-7800, fax (212) 838-7855; www.francetourism.com.</p>
        <p>JILL KNIGHT WEINBERGER is a professor of English at Central Connecticut State University in New Britain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JILL KNIGHT WEINBERGER is a professor of English at Central Connecticut State University in New Britain.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
