<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newest Sporting Event: Beat the Clock, and EPO</title>
    <meta content="Y11DRU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BACKTALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Epo (Recombinant Erythropoietin) (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D71F3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newest Sporting Event: Beat the Clock, and EPO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers in France and Australia attempt to find effective and practical test to detect synthetic erythropoietin, hormone know as EPO, which boosts user's red blood cell count and therefore capacity to carry oxygen, before start of 2000 Olympic Games; use of EPO has tainted results in cycling and other endurance races; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Summer Olympics are still three months away, but in Australia and France a race with potentially huge implications for the Olympics is already well under way.</p>
        <p>It is the race to find an effective and practical method of detecting synthetic erythropoietin, the hormone known as EPO. Unauthorized use of the hormone, which boosts a user's red blood cell count and hence the capacity to carry oxygen, has tainted results and reputations in cycling and other endurance sports throughout the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Summer Olympics are still three months away, but in Australia and France a race with potentially huge implications for the Olympics is already well under way.</p>
        <p>It is the race to find an effective and practical method of detecting synthetic erythropoietin, the hormone known as EPO. Unauthorized use of the hormone, which boosts a user's red blood cell count and hence the capacity to carry oxygen, has tainted results and reputations in cycling and other endurance sports throughout the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Even though research teams in other countries are also attempting to develop a foolproof, lawsuit-proof test, the efforts based in France at the Laboratoire de Chatenay-Malabry and at the Australian Institute of Sport in Canberra are by far the most advanced.</p>
        <p>The French have developed a urine test, which the International Cycling Union hopes to use during the Tour de France, which begins on July 1. The test that has been developed at the Australian institute with the Sydney Games in mind is a blood test.</p>
        <p>Both methods have been published in scientific publications this month, an important step in the validation process and a first for prospective EPO tests. The French test's methodology has been published in the British magazine Nature, the Australians' in the scientific review journal Haematologica.</p>
        <p>''In the sense that some of the previous criticism has been that there has been no publication of an EPO study, this should help answer that,'' said Dr. Peter Davis, the EPO research project manager at the institute.</p>
        <p>The Canberra-based project has several advantages: adequate funding, a method it claims has worked on a small scale, and the motivation provided by a once-in-an-Australian-scientist's-lifetime deadline.</p>
        <p>Australians have been among the most vocal proponents of improved detection and stiffer penalties for performance-enhancing drug use. Developing a method to identify synthetic EPO would be both a blow against cheating and a coup for the country. But any test for EPO would have to be approved by the International Olympic Committee well before the Games begin on Sept. 15.</p>
        <p>''I'd say the chances of having a test in place are now 50-50,'' Dr. Jacques Rogge, vice chairman of the I.O.C. medical commission, said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Prince Alexandre de Merode, the medical commission chairman, said the I.O.C. usually required six months to validate a drug test, but the I.O.C. is prepared to work on a much tighter deadline in this instance. Though neither the Australians nor the French expect to have the test ready to present formally to the medical commission until late July or early August, officials are scrambling to make the procedural hurdles easier to clear.</p>
        <p>''We are on track and under the impression the test is coming,'' Davis said. ''But I also understand that it's not a simple matter of saying: 'Here's the test. Now do it.' There are a lot of other issues that go around taking blood: legal challenges and all the rest.''</p>
        <p>Rogge says that despite concerns about legal action or cultural sensibilities, Olympic athletes will be required to submit to blood tests if this test is ready. But Davis acknowledges that giving the athletes of the world the impression that an EPO test is imminent could be almost as effective a deterrent as actually completing the test. ''Just the threat of a test might be enough to discourage it,'' Davis said. ''But we are committed to providing a real test for Sydney. But it will be up to the I.O.C. how they implement it. And that's tricky, probably a lot trickier than coming up with the test. The test is easy.''</p>
        <p>The stumbling block with testing for EPO has been that it is a hormone that occurs naturally in the body. Distinguishing the injected hormone from what is already present has proved problematic, but Davis said that a study by the Australian institute last year, which involved about 30 subjects, produced a model for solving the riddle.</p>
        <p>On the basis of that effort, the I.O.C. has contributed $1 million and the Australian government approximately $1.5 million to finance the second phase of testing, which began on March 20 and involves about 100 recreational athletes in Canberra and Sydney. According to Davis, most of the subjects, all volunteers who are in no position to contend for the Australian Olympic team, have been administered either EPO or a placebo for a period of eight weeks. Davis said the preliminary results of the study had reinforced their faith in the test.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the institute's team, which is working in conjunction with the Australian Sports Drug Testing Laboratory in Sydney, is continuing to analyze and profile blood samples collected from about 1,200 elite athletes from 10 countries and disparate ethnic groups in order to make sure that all variations in blood type have been taken into account.</p>
        <p>EPO use became widespread in cycling in the early 1990's, but the extent of the problem did not become clear to the general public until the scandal-ridden 1998 Tour de France, when the French border police found a large supply of banned performance-enhancing drugs, including more than 200 doses of EPO, in an offical Tour de France car driven by a Belgian employee of one of the leading teams. The Frenchman Jerome Chiotti, the world mountain bike champion in 1996, recently admitted using it when he won his title.</p>
        <p>Though synthetic EPO, which was initially developed to help kidney transplant patients, remains undetectable for now, the International Cycling Union and International Ski Federation have attempted to combat its use by implementing limits on hematocrit, or red blood cell counts. If a tested athlete goes over a predetermined limit (50 percent in the case of cycling), he is not allowed to start a race. Even though both Davis and Arne Ljunqvist, an I.O.C. medical commission member, support the intent of such procedures, both argue against their validity.</p>
        <p>''The limits are, in my view, arbitrary; I think this is the wrong approach,'' Ljunqvist said. Davis added: ''At Canberra Hospital, the upper limit of normal is 54, and the normal range is 47 to 50, and that's why it's ridiculous. You take Mexican athletes at altitude from a place like Mexico City and they will be at 52 easily, and you can manipulate the level so easily. If it's 52, take a big dose of saline, and it's 49 tomorrow morning. The thing about our test is that it's impossible to manipulate.''</p>
        <p>Allan Hahn, the head of physiology at the Australian institute, said its test was based on probabilities and involved ''measuring a number of different parameters,'' including hematocrit levels and the characteristics of young red blood cells.</p>
        <p>''We believe there is a very low probability that someone could be abnormal on all those parameters unless they were taking EPO,'' he said, explaining that the initial phase of testing showed that the chance of a faulty test was one in 100,000.</p>
        <p>The urine test that has been developed in France can detect only very recent EPO use -- up to three days after the fact, according to Jacques de Ceaurriz, the director of the Chatenay-Malabry laboratory. The Australian blood test is designed to detect use three to four weeks later. There has been significant cooperation between the French and Australian researchers, with the Australians sending urine samples gathered in their study.</p>
        <p>The French are on an even tighter timetable than the Australians because of their desire to have the test ready for the Tour. The International Cycling Union has set a deadline of June 20 for validation, and the heads of the Tour cycling teams have agreed to cooperate if the test is ready. To increase the chances of meeting the deadline, the cycling union is relying on a less exhaustive validation procedure than the I.O.C. requires.</p>
        <p>But I.O.C. officials are not prepared to get ahead of the science. They do not want a repeat of what happened during the 1996 Atlanta Games, when five athletes tested positive for the banned substance Bromantan only to be exonerated by the Court of Arbitration for Sport. Rogge said the court ruled that the new test had not been through the customary validation process, which includes publication of the results in a scientific review journal and independent confirmation by outside experts.</p>
        <p>And even if the Olympic movement gains on EPO, that does not mean it is winning the fight to level the playing fields. Human growth hormone, another popular performance-enhancing drug, will likely remain undetectable in Sydney. And if Patrick Schamasch, the French orthopedic surgeon who is the director of the I.O.C.'s medical commission office, and other experts are correct, the I.O.C. will soon need to invest time and money in genetic research as well as hormone research.</p>
        <p>''The next challenge will be genetic,'' Schamasch said. ''We were laughing as kids about the bionic man or the bionic woman, but we're going to be there.''</p>
        <p>In this brave new world, EPO injections would no longer be required: cells could be modified to produce more of it internally.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the history of nearly all the illegal substances in sport, they were first used for legitimate medical purposes,'' Davis said. ''I think it's only logical to think that if there is already genetic manipulation of cells for beneficial purposes to fight disease or eliminate disease, someone will manipulate cells so they can carry more oxygen or recover from stress.''</p>
        <p>For now, experts are manipulating performance in other ways, even at the Australian institute. In the room next to the EPO research laboratory is an ''altitude house.'' It is a self-contained apartment with a dozen beds where top Australian athletes can legally -- if not ethically -- spend several days and nights in artificially thin air in order to increase their endurance (and red blood cell count). Altitude chambers are widespread around the world.</p>
        <p>''There are so many things that athletes can do, so many ways they can cheat,'' Davis said. ''Certainly, if we get a test for EPO, it would be one less, but I'm also not naive enough to think this will clean it up.</p>
        <p>''Because there are other things, and while there are 75 people here at the A.I.S. working their hardest to improve performance under any legal means possible, there will be other places with 175 people who will come up with whatever works no matter whether it's legal or not.''</p>
        <p>BACKTALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
