<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin Seeks Allies in Quest To Fight U.S. Missile Plan</title>
    <meta content="11RUS.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D8163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin Seeks Allies in Quest To Fight U.S. Missile Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin seeks allies in his campaign against US plans for national missile defense system; recently visited Brussels and Rome and plans to visit North Korea; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin had barely said farewell to President Clinton this week before the Russian leader and top aides fanned out across Europe to campaign against American plans for a national missile defense.</p>
        <p>On whirlwind trips to Brussels and Rome, the Russians sought to persuade the Europeans that a blend of diplomacy, vigilance and Russian technology is a better way to cope with the emerging missile threat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin had barely said farewell to President Clinton this week before the Russian leader and top aides fanned out across Europe to campaign against American plans for a national missile defense.</p>
        <p>On whirlwind trips to Brussels and Rome, the Russians sought to persuade the Europeans that a blend of diplomacy, vigilance and Russian technology is a better way to cope with the emerging missile threat.</p>
        <p>Then the Kremlin announced that Mr. Putin would be undertaking a diplomatic mission to North Korea, the very ''rogue nation'' Washington has cited to justify its plan.</p>
        <p>Given Russia's economic weakness, the new Russian president is not looking for a confrontation with the United States. But neither is he very pliable.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it seems as if Mr. Putin, the former K.G.B. agent who spent the waning days of the cold war in East Germany, is trying to split the Europeans from the Americans. It is a classic Kremlin tactic, wielded with a heavy hand in Soviet times.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Putin is more gentle, insisting only that Russia is a fellow European power and as such more concerned with preserving the framework of arms control than what many Europeans see as the go-it-alone Americans.</p>
        <p>''There is a public relations war over missile defense, and all's fair in P.R. wars,'' a Clinton administration official said of the new Russian stand. ''Some of it has been sophisticated. Some has been crude. But we have really seen an activist Russian foreign policy.''</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration had been accustomed to dealing with Boris N. Yeltsin, a sickly president who nonetheless had a rapport with leaders like Mr. Clinton and Helmut Kohl, the former German Chancellor. But while Mr. Putin's relations with Western leaders are more correct than close, he has engaged in a surprising burst of diplomacy.</p>
        <p>Since his election two months ago, Mr. Putin has visited Britain, Italy, Belarus, Ukraine, Uzbekistan and Turkmenistan. Over the next six weeks, he is headed to Spain, Germany, Moldova, Tajikistan, China, North Korea and Japan, where he plans to attend the summit meeting of the major industrialized nations, and possibly to South Korea. Visits to the United States, India and Brunei, the site of an Asian summit meeting, are also planned for the rest of the year -- but so far not to France, which has been fiercely critical of Russia's war in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>A principal goal of the globe-trotting Russian leader is to lure Western investment, an important element of his plan to strengthen his country's economy and restore Russia as a world power. He is also looking for relief from his nation's mammoth debts, which is a major purpose of his coming German trip.</p>
        <p>Countering the administration's missile defense plan and its insistence that the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty be amended to accommodate it, however, is clearly a top priority.</p>
        <p>The Russians understand that the first phase of the American plan would have little effect on their nuclear forces. But they fear that it would lay the basis for still grander plans, which would give the United States a strategic advantage. Having failed to persuade Washington to abandon its push to build an antimissile system, the Kremlin is doing the next best thing: It is working on America's allies.</p>
        <p>The Europeans, for example, not only fear that the American plan to place 100 interceptors in Alaska and to build a battle-management radar system would undermine the framework of arms control accords and ignite an arms race. They are also not entirely convinced that there is a new missile threat, and they are keenly aware that the administration's missile defense plan is not intended to protect them.</p>
        <p>The Russian diplomacy is intended to exploit all of those fears. At a meeting on Friday at NATO headquarters, Marshal Igor D. Sergeyev, the Russian defense minister, presented a Russian alternative, which he dubbed a plan for ''European, nonstrategic defense.''</p>
        <p>The not-so-subtle message is that Russia, unlike the United States, has a plan that not only protects the European Continent from an evolving missile threat, but would be consistent with the ABM treaty, which is widely seen as the bulwark of arms control as pursued to date.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, Russian policy is trying to use the European skepticism for its own purposes,'' said Karl Kaiser, a German foreign policy analyst.</p>
        <p>Russia is also calculating that the Europeans view their Russian neighbor as more of a potential partner than the Americans. By casting himself as a philosophical ally, Mr. Putin is also trying to win friends and secure funds from Europe.</p>
        <p>''Instead of just saying no and saying that we do not see a threat, Putin is proposing a way to address it,'' said Aleksei Arbatov, a defense expert and member of the Russian Parliament. ''I think it is a very smart policy.''</p>
        <p>At the NATO meetings on Friday, Marshal Sergeyev presented a seven-step plan so vague in outline that it appeared more of a debating agenda than a blueprint.</p>
        <p>Under his proposal, NATO nations and Russia would first evaluate the missile threat and develop a joint European and Russian defense that would use theater antimissile systems. Those are systems that are designed to intercept shorter-range missiles, not long-range ballistic missiles, and as such are allowed under the ABM treaty.</p>
        <p>The Russians have suggested nonetheless that those systems might have some use against the emerging missile threat. Marshal Sergeyev did not say, however, whether the theater defense would be used to blow up third world missiles on their way up or to intercept warheads on their way down. Nor did he provide any detailed account of how the defense system would work.</p>
        <p>''At this stage we know very little about what, if anything, the Russians have in mind at a detailed technical level,'' Walter B. Slocombe, the United States under secretary of defense, said after the NATO session. Defense Secretary William S. Cohen and his aides will have a chance to investigate further at meetings in Moscow early next week.</p>
        <p>While the Europeans harbor doubts about the American missile defense scheme, they are unlikely to rally around the Russian plan. Western European nations are reluctant to spend their limited military funds on missile defense, regardless of whether the technology originates in the United States or Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin, however, is not counting only on the Europeans. He is also likely to encourage opposition to the American missile defense plan during his visit to Beijing. The Chinese are already strongly opposed to Washington's plan, and Mr. Putin is expected to encourage them to remain firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin is also expected to use his visit to North Korea, the first ever by a Russian president, to cast doubt on the rationale for the American missile defense plan. He will probably use the trip to portray North Korea as a rational government that is emerging from its isolation and to try to debunk the American notion that North Korea is an irrational ''rogue state'' that is likely to hurl a missile at the West at any moment.</p>
        <p>After the flurry of Russian moves this week, Mr. Putin called Mr. Clinton on Friday to express his appreciation for a workmanlike summit meeting and to state his commitment to deeper arms cuts. American officials said Mr. Putin's tone was polite but doubted it heralded a breakthrough on the missile issue.</p>
        <p>''Yeltsin might say no at first but it would eventually mean yes,'' a Clinton administration official said. ''Putin says yes when he means no. He says I agree with you and then elaborates. And after you examine his elaboration you discover there is almost no agreement there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
