<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Upgrade Means More Space For Mexico</title>
    <meta content="11VIEW$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Moody's Investors Service Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDA103FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Upgrade Means More Space For Mexico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony DePalma Economic View column notes Moody's Investors Service's upgrade of Mexico's sovereign foreign-currency debt rating to Baa3 elevates Mexico to elite club of Latin American countries that have achieved investment-grade credit rating; reads rating as affirmation of harsh policies imposed amid 1994 peso crisis; notes improved rating will lower cost of borrowing and open up larger pool of potential investors for Mexican bonds; upgrade also adds about $16 billion in Mexican debt to bench mark Lehman Brothers Aggregate Bond index; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the most exclusive clubs in Latin America is the select group of nations with the financial stability to earn investment-grade ratings for their bonds and notes. Just about every politician in the region dreams of joining.</p>
        <p>Consider Alejandro Toledo of Peru. Fighting to unseat President Alberto Fujimori, Mr. Toledo came to New York to denounce electoral fraud, and ultimately pulled out of a runoff widely thought to be rigged against him. Even so, he told reporters, he made time to visit Wall Street and to talk up Peru's prospects for a rating upgrade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the most exclusive clubs in Latin America is the select group of nations with the financial stability to earn investment-grade ratings for their bonds and notes. Just about every politician in the region dreams of joining.</p>
        <p>Consider Alejandro Toledo of Peru. Fighting to unseat President Alberto Fujimori, Mr. Toledo came to New York to denounce electoral fraud, and ultimately pulled out of a runoff widely thought to be rigged against him. Even so, he told reporters, he made time to visit Wall Street and to talk up Peru's prospects for a rating upgrade.</p>
        <p>In truth, few Latin American nations have ever had the economic or political credentials to qualify for admission. Chile is a member, along with Panama, Uruguay and postwar El Salvador. For a while, Colombia was, too, but shaky finances knocked it out last August.</p>
        <p>The small circle widened earlier this year, when Moody's Investors Service bumped up Mexico bonds to Baa3, its lowest investment grade, nearly 20 years after a government default sent tremors around the world. (Standard &amp; Poor's still ranks Mexico a step lower.)</p>
        <p>''Baa3'' sounds discordant, but it is sweet music to politicians' ears. Mexican officials take it as affirmation of their harsh policies in the 1994 peso crisis, when the country's last flirtation with an investment-grade rating fell apart. Naturally, it has become campaign fodder for the presidential election in July.</p>
        <p>What does it really mean? By all accounts, more than enough to justify politicians' aspirations. ''Mexico, like the entire region, has always paid incredibly high prices for capital because of the volatility of the past,'' said Eduardo Cabrera, senior director of Latin America strategy at Merrill Lynch. ''Now the cost of capital will be decreasing, which gives Mexico an incredible competitive advantage.''</p>
        <p>With a smaller ''risk premium'' needed to compensate investors for the risk of default, the government can borrow more cheaply for new highways and hospitals. But more important, analysts say, the investment grade opens a much larger pool of potential investors. Many large pension and money management funds are required to hold only investment-grade instruments.</p>
        <p>And the new status means Mexican bonds are now represented in benchmarks like the Lehman Brothers Aggregate Bond index. Steven D. Berkley, Lehman's global index manager, said that as soon as Mexico's rating was upgraded, about $16 billion of Mexican paper was automatically added to the index, joining about $4 billion in notes from Pemex, the state-owned energy monopoly.</p>
        <p>The Moody's rating refers specifically to Mexican government debt payable in foreign currency, but the benefits extend to corporate borrowers, which are rarely able to win ratings higher than their home country's, a limit known as the sovereign ceiling.</p>
        <p>To Herminio Blanco, Mexico's secretary of commerce and industrial development, the re-evaluation by Wall Street represents ''thousands more jobs in Mexico in the near future.'' It did not contribute to the country's blistering 7.9 percent economic growth rate in the first quarter, he said, but it will help President Ernesto Zedillo end his administration as he has promised, ''with no crisis'' -- a far cry from its start in 1994.</p>
        <p>Moody's based its decision on the perceived success of many Zedillo initiatives: a more manageable debt load, a flexible exchange rate policy and a dynamic export sector that is ''well integrated into the North American economy,'' said Luis Ernesto Martinez-Alas, a vice president at Moody's.</p>
        <p>THE agency did see a few areas of Mexico's economy that still need attention and called for additional spending cuts and a broadening of the tax base, leaving  some economists grumbling that perhaps Mexico didn't deserve the upgrade just yet.</p>
        <p>''It really should be called a confusion-grade rating,'' said Roberto Salinas Leon, a Mexican economist. He said too much work remained to be done in opening competition in the state-run oil and electricity sectors, updating labor laws and fortifying a rickety banking system. ''The investment grade was premature,'' he said, ''and the explanations given are exceedingly rosy, unreflective of a far more problematical situation.''</p>
        <p>Inevitably, investment-grade ratings also bring negatives. The same interest-rate decrease that helps Mexico's finances drives  away risk-tolerant investors seeking higher returns. Joyce Chang, global head of international fixed-income research at Chase Securities, said some high-stakes players she surveyed were planning to swap out of Mexico for countries whose bonds yielded more. Two-thirds of them said Brazil was their top choice. Mr. Toledo would be disappointed to know that Peru, now rated two notches below Mexico, was on no one's list.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
