<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tech 2010: #01 The Plush Life; The Teddy Bear That Knows Your Name</title>
    <meta content="611LAWNT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Fernanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D7163FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tech 2010: #01 The Plush Life; The Teddy Bear That Knows Your Name</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Fernanda Moore</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moore, Fernanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fernanda Moore comment on high-tech toys and teddy bears; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The noble and understanding teddy bear is a longstanding cliche; bears and their stuffed counterparts have served as children's sidekicks and confessors for generations. But the teddy bear of tomorrow is a frightfully evolved beast. Picture a stuffed animal that not only tells stories and learns the names of its human pals but also tailors its personality to them and becomes more complex and mature as they grow up.</p>
        <p>Such bears are a few years off, but there are plenty of high-tech playthings that point in their direction. The talk of the toy industry is Smart Alex, who isn't a bear at all but does a lot of the things interactive teddy bears will eventually do. So I called Alex's inventors, and they kindly offered to send over the lone prototype (with a human attendant) and allow my 4-year-old son, Zander, and his friends Avery, Tim and Charlotte to give it a test drive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The noble and understanding teddy bear is a longstanding cliche; bears and their stuffed counterparts have served as children's sidekicks and confessors for generations. But the teddy bear of tomorrow is a frightfully evolved beast. Picture a stuffed animal that not only tells stories and learns the names of its human pals but also tailors its personality to them and becomes more complex and mature as they grow up.</p>
        <p>Such bears are a few years off, but there are plenty of high-tech playthings that point in their direction. The talk of the toy industry is Smart Alex, who isn't a bear at all but does a lot of the things interactive teddy bears will eventually do. So I called Alex's inventors, and they kindly offered to send over the lone prototype (with a human attendant) and allow my 4-year-old son, Zander, and his friends Avery, Tim and Charlotte to give it a test drive.</p>
        <p>Smart Alex is the brainchild of Team Concepts, a company that also designs laptop computers for kids. Like many new toys, Alex has animatronic facial features and speaks in a human voice; unlike them, he has advanced voice-recognition abilities and uses a 900-megahertz wireless receiver to communicate with the powerful PC necessary to run his software. He plays games, tells jokes and recites stories, and he can download various ''scripts'' tailored to a child's tastes, provided a parent enters the proper information ahead of time. Eventually, Alex will be programmed to teach foreign languages. Visions of Zander prattling in accentless French -- without the expense and bother of an au pair! -- swam in my head.</p>
        <p>We unwound Smart Alex's Bubble Wrap, and four rapt preschoolers confronted a strangely proportioned soft yellow plastic book with long arms and legs and a pair of googly eyes that suddenly opened as the toy began to speak. My dog barked. The kids backed away. ''Do you want to play a game?'' Smart Alex cheerfully asked. ''Or hear a story? Say 'game' or 'story.' ''The kids stared at the toy, then at one another. ''Say 'game' or 'story,' ''Alex warbled, with no trace of the rancor that often accompanies repeated parental requests. Finally Avery took the bait. ''Story,'' she murmured. Instantly, the toy launched into a plausible and only slightly cloying version of ''Goldilocks and the Three Bears.''</p>
        <p>The only problem was, before Goldilocks had even finished sampling the bears' porridge, Zander and Tim had wandered off. A moment later Avery followed, and soon all three were busy playing with a marble game I bought for 75 cents at a garage sale. Charlotte stuck around a little longer, poking Alex's moving plastic lips and giggling. But by the time Baby Bear found Goldilocks sleeping in his bed, Smart Alex was alone in the middle of the room, still talking, like an overzealous host whose weary guests have all gone home.</p>
        <p>I felt sorry for Alex and his crestfallen chaperon, but the kids just weren't interested. Perhaps they were too young to appreciate the wonders of voice recognition; perhaps they saw through Alex in a way we could not. It seems that the developers of the new tech toys, in their excitement at creating talking, moving creatures, forgot to ask whether something that basically acts like a synthetic grown-up is a welcome companion, and whether a chatty stuffed animal offers anything kids can't better summon from their own imaginations.</p>
        <p>Bruce Blumberg, an M.I.T. assistant professor whose Synthetic Characters Group designs animated creatures as a way of understanding the nature of intelligent behavior, shared my misgivings. ''When I was a kid, I was pretty sure my teddy bear already knew how to talk,'' he said. ''If the toy companies are trying to create the illusion of life in inanimate objects, the moment they step into the world of language they run up against a serious wall. When the toy falters, when it misinterprets a cue or answers a question wrong, the whole illusion is shattered.''</p>
        <p>I asked Blumberg to suggest a better way for technology and toys to team up. ''I've always wanted to design a beaver colony,'' he told me. ''There could be animated beavers on the screen building dams and doing what beavers do, and the kid could use a stuffed beaver with special sensors to direct her own character in the scene. It would be a whole new adventure, life as a beaver, and then maybe later she'd wander down to the creek to get a closer look at what the real beavers were doing.'' Blumberg's game struck me as a revelation; like the old teddy bear, it's a portal into a wonderfully alien world.</p>
        <p>Hours after Smart Alex and his escort left for the airport, Zander climbed into my lap. ''O.K., Mom, which one do you want?'' he asked. ''Story, song or game? Say 'story,' ''he added helpfully. I found out later that Tim and Avery had both gone home and done the same thing. Twenty minutes with a talking book obviously made a powerful impression; at the very least, it turned three normal children into walking multiple-choice tests. My only regret is that Alex wasn't speaking French.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
