<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happy Families Are Not All Alike</title>
    <meta content="11KIRNGT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Earley, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirn, Walter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jim the Boy (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5D6123CF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happy Families Are Not All Alike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Kirn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirn, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Kirn reviews book Jim the Boy by Tony Earley; drawing (M)6</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim The Boy</p>
        <p>By Tony Earley.</p>
        <p>227 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jim The Boy</p>
        <p>By Tony Earley.</p>
        <p>227 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>THE rap against minimalist fiction was always nonsense -- the charge that it lacked ambition, imagination. Size has nothing to do with literature. All legs are long enough to touch the ground, and all books are big enough to fill their covers. Lately, though, this truth has been easy to forget. Serious novels (such a dreary term) seem to grow thicker every year, as if weight were a simple function of mass. Complexity -- the grand vocabulary, the page-long paragraph, the jointed sentence -- has come to be valued as an outright virtue instead of a choice that is often not a good one. It's an odd development. However old-fashioned and right-wing this may sound, the American genius for language lies in understatement, in saying things simply, pointedly and quickly, and in making new and clean and swift what otherwise might be ponderous, round and slow.</p>
        <p>From its title to its closing sentence, Tony Earley's first novel returns to basics, back to modernness in the old sense of the word. It's not a big book, just a good one -- and in this instance ''good'' is higher praise than ''great.'' At a time when the latest, most souped-up version of something, a car or a computer program, say, is by reflex regarded as the best, Earley has had the courage to return to artistic first principles: clarity, balance, ease. Set in Depression-era North Carolina, his year-in-the-life story of a rural boyhood unmarked by parental abuse, erotic turmoil or domestic dysfunction seems strangely brave and new. ''Jim the Boy'' is a novel that does one thing memorably instead of many things forgettably.</p>
        <p>Jim is 10. His mother is a widow. They live in the small town of Aliceville with Jim's three uncles, Zeno, Coran and Al. And they're content. The family disproves the old Tolstoyan epigram about all happy families being alike and thus, by implication, boring. That may have been true in 19th-century Russia, but in 20th-century America -- at least as depicted in works of fiction -- future scholars will note that happy families were rare indeed, if not absent altogether.</p>
        <p>The story begins on Jim's birthday, no more a turning point than any other arbitrary date and yet mysteriously important to Jim, as 10-year-olds' birthdays tend to be. Earley remembers what most adults forget: how American children mature not through trials by fire or tribal ceremonies, but by finding meaning in X's on a calendar. I'm 10, therefore I am. At least that's Jim's thought. It's an awakening made no less profound for being thoroughly conventional.</p>
        <p>The same might be said for the novel as a whole. Earley isn't into genre-bending; he tells his coming-of-age story straight, making all the familiar stops in a way that reminds us, paradoxically, just how unfamiliar they've become. The first baseball glove. The first brush with the local bully. The first best friend. The first glimpse of death and nothingness. This last discovery happens inside a hole dug by a convict for a power pole, and it's characteristic of Earley's method, which is not to appear to have a method: ''When Uncle Zeno let go, Jim thought he was going to fall a long way, but his feet hit the ground after only a few inches. He found himself crouched in the bottom of the hole, his heart racing, both of his arms held over his head, his mouth open to yell -- a position that made him feel a little silly once he realized he wasn't falling. He lowered his arms to his side and slowly realized there was no reason to be afraid. The hole had more room than he had thought.''</p>
        <p>Such pared-down, ''Elements of Style'' prose verges, at times, on the precious. But that's its magic. Such is Earley's control over his tone that it never quite lapses into cuteness. The risk that it might, at almost any moment, creates a curious sort of suspense. What makes the style interesting, and even daring, is how close it keeps coming to going soft and maudlin without ever crossing the line. When Jim inhales the scent of his new glove, sizes up his schoolyard playmates or gawks at the new express train roaring through town, there's the threat of a free fall into pure nostalgia. When the threat passes, though, as it always does, beaten back by a saving precision in the language and a remarkable purity of attention, what remains is admiration for Earley's sure footing.</p>
        <p>The novel is a period piece, technically, but the period lives mostly inside the characters, in their habits, attitudes and mores, instead of in their physical surroundings. Jim's mortal shame over slighting his buddy, Penn, by refusing to let him wear his baseball glove during a certain crucial game of catch is at least as evocative of the 1930's as the new electric lines being strung up on the highway into town. When Jim's mother rejects an earnest suitor rather than be untrue to her dead husband, the past becomes spiritually palpable in a way that can't be achieved by strewing around antiques and references to historical events.</p>
        <p>Jim and his family aren't conscious, for the most part, of living in a specific time and place -- the attitude that dates them most of all. Television and the media haven't yet turned America into a culture of itchy, restless escapists, ceaselessly comparing what's over there with what's right here, what's coming with what's happening. Their small town is still their universe, and they live in the present because the past is gone and the future is not to be depended upon. They exist in a little eternity, like the book. Their horizons are tiny, but their perspective is long.</p>
        <p>Anxiety doesn't pay in Jim's world; nor does excessive self-awareness. Though his father dropped dead in a cotton field the week before he was born, Jim doesn't waste time considering what might have been. His uncles and his mother are his circle, a circle he finds little reason to look beyond -- although, eventually, the family forces him to (if only for one brief, disorienting moment). Like the farmhands in ''The Wizard of Oz,'' the uncles are less distinct individuals than a single guardian split three ways. Jim's innocence is made possible by their care, and they lead him out into the world in measured steps, doling out experience in modest portions sized to his ability to digest them. They rein in Jim's high spirits with a light touch, and we sense that they've seen enough trouble to know, instinctively, when to loosen and tighten their control. Family love, in the book, is nothing so contemporary as unconditional approval. It's constricting but warm, like a tautly made-up bed that forces its occupant to lie down straight.</p>
        <p>The protection the uncles offer isn't perfect, of course. More than once, Jim wanders off alone, but such is the ironclad nature of the social contract obtaining in his corner of the world that someone older and wiser always shows up to keep him from harm's way. The world itself is Jim's parent -- a cozy notion -- and Earley's anachronistic fondness for personification underscores this. His objects have intentions, even moods. A mountain road climbs ''at a desperate clip.'' A nail in a ceiling joist pokes up ''angrily.'' Such old tricks can be grating, let's face it -- they smack of a storybook on pappy's lap -- but Earley doesn't push them, thankfully. It's because he's so thoroughly caught up in his playing that he sometimes strikes a tinny note.</p>
        <p>The novel's determination to be lovable is its only, minor flaw. A soulful old black man who may as well be Uncle Remus pops up once or twice, usually peeling an apple and quoting the Bible. The folksy scoldings of Jim's mother and uncles begin to sound alike after a while, like tributes to the dialogue of ''Old Yeller'' rather than authentic emotional utterances.</p>
        <p>One can't charm all the people all the time, though Earley comes close. In a way, his novel is fantasy, an updating of classic boyhood tales that's somehow more loyal to literature than to life. Then again, happy families do exist -- in obscurity, granted, but they're out there. What the story of Jim's happy family accomplishes is to remind the reader how much was lost when contentment became illegal as a theme and ambivalence mandatory. Young Jim may be easygoing and nave, but he's not entirely unworldly. Just below the level of awareness, he knows full well he's living a fairy tale, and he's wise enough to cling to it. He'll have plenty of time to be miserable when he's older.</p>
        <p>Walter Kirn's latest book is ''Thumbsucker,'' a novel. He is the literary editor of GQ magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Kirn's latest book is ''Thumbsucker,'' a novel. He is the literary editor of GQ magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
