<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Britain in Africa; Colonialism's Legacy Becomes a Burden</title>
    <meta content="11COWE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DC163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Britain in Africa; Colonialism's Legacy Becomes a Burden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Great Britain is currently confronting two conflicting responses to its colonial legacy in Africa in Sierra Leone, where government is pleading for British intervention force to stay on, and Zimbabwe, where government holds Britain responsible for country's current woes; divergent signals are reminder that imperial power, once extended, creates stubborn, messy and enduring legacy and leaves behind tangle of obligation, expectations and resentment even when it recedes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN recent weeks, Britons have been treated to two conflicting, almost puzzling, sets of images. In Sierra Leone, an African leader pleads with British troops to stay on, after they arrive there to protect the capital from rebel forces who had kidnapped hundreds of United Nations peacekeepers. Across the continent in Zimbabwe, another African president reviles just about everything that smacks of the British and tells them to be gone.</p>
        <p>Binding the two images is Britain's colonial past and, with it, a message that has some resonance for the United States in its own new imperial age: Once power is extended, it creates a stubborn, messy and enduring legacy. And even when influence recedes, the tangle of obligation, expectation and resentment survives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN recent weeks, Britons have been treated to two conflicting, almost puzzling, sets of images. In Sierra Leone, an African leader pleads with British troops to stay on, after they arrive there to protect the capital from rebel forces who had kidnapped hundreds of United Nations peacekeepers. Across the continent in Zimbabwe, another African president reviles just about everything that smacks of the British and tells them to be gone.</p>
        <p>Binding the two images is Britain's colonial past and, with it, a message that has some resonance for the United States in its own new imperial age: Once power is extended, it creates a stubborn, messy and enduring legacy. And even when influence recedes, the tangle of obligation, expectation and resentment survives.</p>
        <p>''What's left after you've gone is a very deep imprint,'' said David Anderson, chairman of the Center for African Studies at the School for Oriental and African Studies here. ''And it dictates cultural links, investment flows. All these things have substantive meaning in the way things are done.''</p>
        <p>The circumstances that motivated Presidents Ahmed Tejan Kabbah of Sierra Leone and Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe could hardly have been more different, and neither could Britain's responses.</p>
        <p>In Sierra Leone, a chaotic assemblage of rebel and pro-government forces has turned the nation into a patchwork of armed fiefs competing for the country's diamond riches. A United Nations mission to make peace had collapsed, leaving a dangerous vacuum. This threatened to propel the war-weary nation into further mayhem -- mayhem that had already caught the world's eye through  the singular cruelty of rebels who hacked off the limbs of innocents.</p>
        <p>But Britain's sense of post-colonial obligation went further. Its gunboat diplomacy in Sierra Leone also reflected a broader readiness by Tony Blair's government to pursue the same ethical -- if somewhat selective -- crusade as had led it to promote last year's NATO bombing of Kosovo.</p>
        <p>In Zimbabwe the fight is different: After 20 unchallenged years in power, Mr. Mugabe is facing elections this month that he is afraid of losing. And he has seized on the emotional issue of racial discrimination left over from colonial days -- in this case, unfair patterns of land distribution -- as a pretext to order a campaign of bloody intimidation of his principal opponents. These include white farmers and workers on the farmers' land. Hundreds of white-owned farms have been occupied by so-called veterans of Zimbabwe's liberation war in the 1970, and at least 25 people have died.</p>
        <p>In other words, Mr. Mugabe is assailing the very legacy that Britons feel links them to the land. And Britain's choices are circumscribed, illuminating both the ambiguities of its colonial history and the limits on its modern influence.</p>
        <p>While Sierra Leone was established in 1787 as a coastal settlement for freed black slaves, white British settlers were encouraged to migrate to Rhodesia -- as Zimbabwe was then known -- in the late 19th and early 20th century, simply seizing vast tracts of land from the indigenous people.</p>
        <p>When British officials started to protest Mr. Mugabe's behavior, that inescapable history clouded the moral issue and gave Mr. Mugabe the ammunition to defy the onetime colonial ruler. The collision left Britain's standing in Zimbabwe at its lowest in decades, even as its star rose ever higher in Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>So what drives a small nation with shrunken influence to project its influence with such Victorian zeal?</p>
        <p>WHILE Britain's initial intervention in Sierra Leone was depicted as a mission to rescue British passport-holders, it was quickly seen here by a broad swath of the populace as something more: an opportunity to unravel chaos that has at least some roots in earlier British initiatives.</p>
        <p>In Zimbabwe, by contrast, the presence of some 15,000 white Zimbabweans entitled to British citizenship revived a far more ambiguous legacy. Successive British governments may have voiced support for the aspirations of Zimbabwe's black majority, but, on the right wing of British politics, there remains an insistence that Britain should look after its so-called kith-and-kin in Africa -- a view that invariably leads Zimbabweans, and some Britons, to argue that British policy is racially biased.</p>
        <p>The deeper reality in both Zimbabwe and Sierra Leone is that colonialism does not have an easy cut-off point, or a simple close-of-sale date. When the flags are furled, the colonial power maintains a vast array of commercial and other involvements.</p>
        <p>Just as colonialism itself was propelled by the economics of Europe's industrial revolution with its need for raw materials and markets, so the post-colonial era has been driven by Lord Palmerston's 19th-century dictum that nations do not have eternal allies, but they do have eternal interests.</p>
        <p>In Zimbabwe, for instance, by insisting that this month's elections be free and fair and by offering increased financial aid for land redistribution, Britain is signaling its broader interest in the stability of a region that encompasses vast British investment, particularly in South Africa.</p>
        <p>Of course, the same self-interest also creates a web of commitment and expectation, as Americans know well from their nexus of relationships from Latin America to the Middle East, from the rim of Asia to the heart of Europe.</p>
        <p>Britain's military intervention in Sierra Leone, moreover, has led to the same worries as dogged American forces in Vietnam, Beirut and Somalia : Once committed, troops may well have to stand their ground  at the risk of unwelcome casualties -- or contemplate withdrawal in humiliation.</p>
        <p>That is why Britain has given clear notice that its 600 combat troops in Sierra Leone will be withdrawn by mid-June. But, already, the potential for bloody chaos has obliged Britain to station 200 military advisers there when the combat troops leave --  an eerie echo of the beginnings of American embroilment in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea of mission creep is inevitable,'' Dr. Anderson said. ''It isn't a problem as long as you draw a line in the sand.'' But those lines in the sand, of course, are what the players of the post-colonial era have found so elusive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
