<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tech 2010: #30 Healthy Living; The French Fry That Will Save Your Life</title>
    <meta content="611BODT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="100" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patchett, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D7163FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tech 2010: #30 Healthy Living; The French Fry That Will Save Your Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ann Patchett</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Patchett, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Patchett report on nutraceuticals or functional foods, from breakfast cereals pumped up with vitamins to margarine spreads that can lower cholesterol to bananas containing vaccines (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consider dinner a cowboy movie. Broccoli and Broiled Fish: the good guys. Ice Cream with his trusty sidekick, Fudge Sauce: the bad guys. Except, as so often happens in cowboy movies, the heroes are bland in their tireless sense of duty, and the villains, well, there's just something bewitching about those two. The next thing we know, we're longing for what's bad for us while slipping what's good to the dog beneath the table.</p>
        <p>Enter ''nutraceuticals,'' a made-up word for made-up food. Also known as functional foods, nutraceuticals cover everything from breakfast cereal that has been pumped full of vitamins (Special K Plus) to Johnson &amp; Johnson's Benecol, a margarinesque spread that actually lowers the L.D.L cholesterol -- if you're willing to eat it three times a day. According to Novartis Consumer Health, a division of a Swiss pharmaceutical company, the U.S. market for functional foods is estimated to be between $10 billion and $20 billion, and it is expected to grow at the rate of 10 percent annually. Altus, Unilever and other food giants are working to come up with ways of getting the vitamins, nutrients and health benefits into foods that we'd be eating anyway. Among the many products in development at Monsanto, for example, are an improved-solids potato, which absorbs less moisture and so will take on less oil in cooking, and a low-calorie, low- (and possibly no-) saturated-fat oil in which to cook those potatoes. When these products of the future merge, you suddenly have a French fry that's not bad for you. Or, if you choose to use Monsanto's high-beta-carotene oil to fry your improved-solids potato, you get a French fry that is actively good for you. With all this progress, is it only a matter of time before fortified ice-cream nudges broccoli completely off the plate?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consider dinner a cowboy movie. Broccoli and Broiled Fish: the good guys. Ice Cream with his trusty sidekick, Fudge Sauce: the bad guys. Except, as so often happens in cowboy movies, the heroes are bland in their tireless sense of duty, and the villains, well, there's just something bewitching about those two. The next thing we know, we're longing for what's bad for us while slipping what's good to the dog beneath the table.</p>
        <p>Enter ''nutraceuticals,'' a made-up word for made-up food. Also known as functional foods, nutraceuticals cover everything from breakfast cereal that has been pumped full of vitamins (Special K Plus) to Johnson &amp; Johnson's Benecol, a margarinesque spread that actually lowers the L.D.L cholesterol -- if you're willing to eat it three times a day. According to Novartis Consumer Health, a division of a Swiss pharmaceutical company, the U.S. market for functional foods is estimated to be between $10 billion and $20 billion, and it is expected to grow at the rate of 10 percent annually. Altus, Unilever and other food giants are working to come up with ways of getting the vitamins, nutrients and health benefits into foods that we'd be eating anyway. Among the many products in development at Monsanto, for example, are an improved-solids potato, which absorbs less moisture and so will take on less oil in cooking, and a low-calorie, low- (and possibly no-) saturated-fat oil in which to cook those potatoes. When these products of the future merge, you suddenly have a French fry that's not bad for you. Or, if you choose to use Monsanto's high-beta-carotene oil to fry your improved-solids potato, you get a French fry that is actively good for you. With all this progress, is it only a matter of time before fortified ice-cream nudges broccoli completely off the plate?</p>
        <p>Not everyone thinks this is such a terrific idea. ''Food, drugs and supplements should be separate,'' says Marion Nestle, the chairwoman of the department of nutrition and food studies at New York University. ''This is really not a good idea, except for marketing purposes. The assumption is, the more vitamins, the better, but I'm not sure that's true. Medicine is medicine and food is food. I think we should keep the two separate.''</p>
        <p>Not to mention that there is pleasure in eating food that isn't supposed to be good for you. A huge part of the joy of the villains, Ice Cream and Fudge Sauce, is that they have no intention of improving the quality of our lives; they represent unrepentant decadence. In what can only be described as a radical step backward, Nestle suggests forgoing, say, the evil-tasting power bars (the doyenne of nutraceutical food), which are often loaded with sugar and calories along with vitamins, in favor of a really tasty plain old candy bar with a vitamin pill on the side. Despite her personal logic, she believes the day is coming when virtually every food on the market will be fortified. ''This food is very expensive,'' she says. ''Which is the point.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, scientists are off in the lab trying to do the world a good turn with a banana. At the Boyce Thompson Institute, Charles J. Arntzen and Hugh Mason are developing plants that contain vaccines. The point is to someday eliminate the need for refrigeration so that these drugs can be easily and safely distributed to third-world countries. Some of the vaccines currently being worked into bananas include those for hepatitis B, Norwalk virus and enterotoxic E. coli.</p>
        <p>But don't expect to be slicing such a banana on your Special K Plus any time soon. In fact, don't expect to be able to buy one at all. In the same way you wouldn't hand out bottles of vaccine and tell people to help themselves, you can't send a bunch of bananas containing vaccines into a country and just tell people to eat up. Joyce Frank, the director of licensing and development at the Boyce Thompson Institute, explains that when the product is ready, it will be distributed through clinics, not sold in supermarkets. ''There won't ever be a time when people will be growing their own bananas with vaccines in them.''</p>
        <p>Other scientists at the institute are doing research on food projects as well, including Patricia Conklin, who is working to develop plants with higher amounts of vitamin C and folic acid, which is especially important for prenatal health. In the future, the spinach that was always good for you will be great for you.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, back at the grocery store, expect the future to look like a can of Ultra Slim-Fast -- food that is low in fat and calories, packed full of vitamins and minerals and not exactly food at all. While you're drinking that frothy whip that reminds you of a milkshake the same way a light bulb reminds you of summer, remember the Ben &amp; Jerry's you may have left behind.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
