<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will a Onetime Jazz Mecca Make Room for a Pancake House?</title>
    <meta content="11SMAL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International House of Pancakes (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abyssinian Development Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smalls's Paradise (Defunct Nyc Nightclub)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6D91E3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will a Onetime Jazz Mecca Make Room for a Pancake House?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abyssinian Development Corp, which controls site of legendary Smalls's Paradise, Jazz Age club in Harlem, is considering leasing part of space to International House of Pancakes; timeline; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1925, when Ed Smalls opened Smalls's Paradise, a nighclub for black and white patrons that offered jazz, Chinese food and waitresses on roller skates, it was quickly called ''the hottest spot in Harlem.''</p>
        <p>Though the legendary Jazz Age club is long gone, the building in which it was once located, on a corner of 135th Street and Seventh Avenue, still stands. In recent years, the Abyssinian Development Corporation, the local development arm of the Abyssinian Baptist Church, which controls the site, has explored a variety of possible uses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1925, when Ed Smalls opened Smalls's Paradise, a nighclub for black and white patrons that offered jazz, Chinese food and waitresses on roller skates, it was quickly called ''the hottest spot in Harlem.''</p>
        <p>Though the legendary Jazz Age club is long gone, the building in which it was once located, on a corner of 135th Street and Seventh Avenue, still stands. In recent years, the Abyssinian Development Corporation, the local development arm of the Abyssinian Baptist Church, which controls the site, has explored a variety of possible uses.</p>
        <p>One plan currently in negotiations, according to Karen A. Phillips, president and chief executive of the development group, is to lease part of the space to the International House of Pancakes.</p>
        <p>And at least one neighborhood preservationist, Michael Henry Adams, is appalled.</p>
        <p>''When you're talking about attracting people from all over the world to see the landmarks here, you'd think they could come up with something a little more special,'' he said. ''You can go to an IHOP anywhere, but there's only one Smalls's.''</p>
        <p>Abyssinian became the managing shareholder of the building in 1993, when a group of Harlem business leaders bought the  building that housed Smalls's and formed the Community Paradise Corporation.</p>
        <p>Since 1997, when the corporation secured the deed to the property, various plans have been explored for it, including using the space for a jazz museum, a restaurant and a beauty parlor. But potential operators of such proposals have had difficulty getting investors.</p>
        <p>Ms. Phillips said her group would lease only 5,000 of the building's 75,000 square feet to IHOP, as part of the Neighborhood Franchise Program, which promotes local franchise ownership in minority neighborhoods and brought the first Sterling Optical store to Harlem.</p>
        <p>''Whatever is ultimately the plan, it's going to be consistent with the process of community revitalization, job creation, education and service to the local community,'' said Darren Walker, chief operating officer for Abyssinian.</p>
        <p>Other preservationists support the idea of adding IHOP to the mix.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing in dealing with historic structures is to protect the building, and the worst thing is for it to be vacant,'' said one, Ron Melichar. ''If this plan allows us to use it and preserve it for future use, I'm in favor of it.''</p>
        <p>NINA SIEGAL</p>
        <p>RIFFS  Once a Paradise</p>
        <p>Smalls's Paradise has been shuttered since the mid-1980's, but it has had a vibrant history:</p>
        <p>1925 -- Ed Smalls opens ''Harlem's House of Mirth and Music.''</p>
        <p>1930's -- Smalls's features musicians like Cab Calloway and Fletcher Henderson. The largest and most popular black-owned nightclub in Harlem, it is one of few that are racially integrated.</p>
        <p>1940's -- As downtown clubs integrate, Smalls's loses customers and eventually closes.</p>
        <p>1960's -- The basketball great Wilt Chamberlain buys the place and reopens it as ''Big Wilt's Smalls's Paradise.'' It revives briefly.</p>
        <p>1990's -- Greater Harlem Chamber of Commerce considers turning the closed Smalls's into a jazz museum</p>
        <p>1997 -- The Community Paradise Corporation, formed by Harlem business leaders, secures the deed to the property.</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
