<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Stick, a Spaldeen, and 'Boys' Are Back to a 60's Summer</title>
    <meta content="11STIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: PARK SLOPE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stickball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bahrampour, Tara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD9103FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Stick, a Spaldeen, and 'Boys' Are Back to a 60's Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARA BAHRAMPOUR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bahrampour, Tara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene on Garfield Place in Park Slope section of Brooklyn, NYC, described as annual stickball game gets underway; for past eight years, on first Sunday of June, former residents join those who never left neighborhood to play game and reminisce about summer boyhood days; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobody plays Buck-Buck anymore. Or Johnny-on-the-Pony. Or most of the street games Mike Lamanno played growing up on Garfield Place 40 years ago.</p>
        <p>But one Sunday a year, it's just like the old days. Mr. Lamanno's mother, Millie, sits out by the stoop to watch her son and his friends draw up bases and swing a painted red stick behind their heads. With a crack, the wood connects with a pink rubber ball, and the neighborhood's annual stickball game is under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nobody plays Buck-Buck anymore. Or Johnny-on-the-Pony. Or most of the street games Mike Lamanno played growing up on Garfield Place 40 years ago.</p>
        <p>But one Sunday a year, it's just like the old days. Mr. Lamanno's mother, Millie, sits out by the stoop to watch her son and his friends draw up bases and swing a painted red stick behind their heads. With a crack, the wood connects with a pink rubber ball, and the neighborhood's annual stickball game is under way.</p>
        <p>''This is like a lost art,'' Mr. Lamanno said, as two dozen middle-aged men positioned themselves along the tree-lined street. Most of the Garfield Boys, as they were called, left the area long ago. But from Staten Island to New Jersey they have kept in touch, and for eight years, on the first Sunday of June, they have returned to play the game that enlivened so many summer days and annoyed some neighbors.</p>
        <p>''It gives me a good feeling to play,'' said Gregory Garra, as a gray-haired man sucking on a cigar pitched the ball to a potbellied fellow in Bermuda shorts. ''It brings back your youth.''</p>
        <p>Frank Tedesco, who brought along his 12-year-old son, Joe, recalled the days when Park Slope housed working-class Irish and Italian families and was simply South Brooklyn. The men marveled at a brownstone on their block that recently sold for $800,000, 100 times what some of their parents paid in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>''The neighborhood changed,'' Mr. Tedesco said. ''Everybody was trying to improve their lives, parents moving away so they could buy houses. Now they couldn't come back if they wanted to.''</p>
        <p>Some never left. Millie Lamanno, 82, recalled the stickball players coming in to use her bathroom and being waylaid by the smell of her eggplant Parmesan. ''They did more hollering than playing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Tom Callahan, whose mother was also out watching in her chair, provided a sociological history of the game, invented at the turn of the century ''by kids who weren't able to buy their own gloves and baseball uniforms'' but could afford 25 cents for a spaldeen, the small pink ball.</p>
        <p>As for the stick, he said, ''many a mother would find her good broom handle gone during the summer months because her son would have taken it and sawed the stick part off.''</p>
        <p>Although on this day a couple of neighborhood girls took a turn, in the old days girls didn't play stickball. But they didn't ignore it.</p>
        <p>''That's how I met my husband,'' said Annette Ferraioli, visiting from Staten Island. ''I was 13, and I used to watch him and root for him.''</p>
        <p>Garfield Place was the designated stickball street, John Fischetti said, because ''there were no trees in those days.'' (The trees didn't arrive until the 70's.)</p>
        <p>''The camaraderie that we had was amazing,'' Mr. Tedesco said. ''The way it used to be on this block, my kids, they can't picture it.''</p>
        <p>But one thing hadn't changed. As the men cheered, an irate woman pushed open an upstairs window.</p>
        <p>''Where do you guys live?'' she yelled. ''I'm going to come to your house and play stickball in your street!''</p>
        <p>Odds are, they'd be happy to join her.</p>
        <p>TARA BAHRAMPOUR</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: PARK SLOPE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
