<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big-Family Feeling Behind a Solo Performer</title>
    <meta content="11MUSI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lavin, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D8123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big-Family Feeling Behind a Solo Performer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of folk singer-songwriter Christine Lavin, who comments on her Stealth Project Tour, which includes stop at Bearsley Zoo in Bridgeport, Conn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OF all the solo acts in the contemporary music scene, the singer-songwriter  Christine Lavin seems the least alone.</p>
        <p>In 1992 she founded the Annual Singer-Songwriter Retreat on Martha's Vineyard, where she surrounded herself with dozens of musicians. A few years later she joined Cliff Eberhardt and Cheryl Wheeler on a successful tour called ''On a Winter's Night.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OF all the solo acts in the contemporary music scene, the singer-songwriter  Christine Lavin seems the least alone.</p>
        <p>In 1992 she founded the Annual Singer-Songwriter Retreat on Martha's Vineyard, where she surrounded herself with dozens of musicians. A few years later she joined Cliff Eberhardt and Cheryl Wheeler on a successful tour called ''On a Winter's Night.''</p>
        <p>Most famously, Ms. Lavin started the Four Bitchin' Babes tour, whose floating roster included Sally Fingerhut, Julie Gold, Megon McDonough, among many.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lavin's current excuse not to perform alone is her Stealth Project Tour, which stops at the Beardsley Zoo in Bridgeport on Saturday. Diane Zeigler, Jackie Tice and Ron Renniger join Ms. Lavin at the 7 p.m. concert. All three singer-songwriters are among the 16 artists represented on the new CD ''The Stealth Project Tour: Music Under the Radar,'' which is sold through Ms. Lavin's Web site (www.christinelavin.com).</p>
        <p>''I come from a big family so I try to recreate that atmosphere,'' said Ms. Lavin, the fourth of nine children, originally from Peekskill, N.Y. ''Music can be a lonely profession, so it's fun to play with friends now and then.''</p>
        <p>Whether Ms. Lavin performs with friends or alone, she is known for her ebullient wit and self-deprecating humor in performance. Some of her better-known titles include ''Sensitive New Age Guys,'' ''Prisoners of Their Hairdos'' and ''Bald-Headed Men.''</p>
        <p>She is known to break into an impromptu version of ''Jeopardy'' with the audience, and finish with a two-fisted baton-twirling exhibition. Before making music her full-time occupation, Ms. Lavin worked at jobs including selling Cracker Jacks at Miami Dolphins football games and being an aide at Bellevue Hospital Center in New York, which, she said, greatly informed her writing. ''I don't know why these things happen to me, or how I get into these situations, but I do,'' said Ms. Lavin from her New York City home.</p>
        <p>''I only made about 7 cents a box. Trouble was that I'd get into the game so much that I wouldn't sell anything after the first quarter. But I cheered hard for the Dolphins.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lavin has helped pioneer the New Folk movement since her 1984 album ''Future Fossils'' hit the streets. She grew up listening to WNEW-FM (102.7), New York's first progressive rock station in the 60's (''I had no record collection,'' she said) and learned to play guitar from televised lessons on PBS. On her first public performance at a Girl Scout function, Ms. Lavin, then 13, showed a precocious quirkiness by introducing her own song ''The World Is Going To End.'' (''Kind of brought the parents down,'' she said.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lavin continued to improve her musical and songwriting skills through high school and college (''I declared about seven majors at Brockport State College before settling on English.'') After her sojourn in Miami, she returned to upstate New York to work for Lena Spencer, proprietor of Cafe Lena, the well-known folk club in Saratoga Springs, N.Y. The folk icon Dave Von Ronk saw Ms. Lavin's performance and helped her land work back in New York City.</p>
        <p>''I guess that's why I've tried to help out other musicians,'' said Ms. Lavin, who promoted an unknown Suzanne Vega back in the early 80's, as well as the songwriter Julie (''From a Distance'') Gold.</p>
        <p>Besides music, Ms. Lavin's passion these days is Dame Edna, the loveable cross-dressed creation of the Australian actor Barry Humphries that earned a special Tony Award last week. A self-confirmed Dame Edna-holic, Ms. Lavin, who has seen the Broadway show (''Dame Edna: The Royal Tour'') 22 times, even wrote an article, ''Stop Me Before I Edna Again'' published in The St. Petersburg Times last month.</p>
        <p>''My fascination with Dame Edna started in 1989 when I toured Australia,'' said Ms. Lavin. ''I saw her on her television show. I was transfixed. It wasn't until 11 years later that I saw her live. It's like going to school, watching Barry work the audience.''</p>
        <p>Should Mr. Humphries ever catch Ms. Lavin's act, he may very well say the same of her.</p>
        <p>Christine Lavin performs at the Beardsley Zoo in Bridgeport with her Stealth Project Tour (Diane Zeigler, Jacky Tice) at 7 p.m. on Saturday. Gates open at 6:15 p.m. Tickets are $15 in advance, $17.50 at the door. The number to call for directions and reservations is (203) 394-6565.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
