<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Test Scores Are Up. From This We Can Conclude that the schools are doing:</title>
    <meta content="11TEST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6D8163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Test Scores Are Up. From This We Can Conclude that the schools are doing:</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's new schools chancellor, Harold O Levy, greets two successive waves of good news on student testing--nine-point rise on statewide test and five-point rise on citywide test--by urging caution; experts say it is almost impossible to attribute real meaning to one-year gain in scores; Levy defends testing as crude, if necessary, check on system, yet sides with skeptics in suggesting that one-yar gain reveals little about condition of schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this era of standardized student testing, it has become an all-too-familiar ritual in New York City and across the country: the leader of the school system calls a news conference and holds a wedding or a funeral, crowing if scores are up, grieving and accepting blame if they are down.</p>
        <p>Historically, most New York City chancellors have been able to do a bit of both. Test results can be relied on to rise in some years and fall in others. For parents and many teachers, the constant ratcheting up and down of scores -- testing experts call it the sawtooth effect -- is confusing and exhausting, if not dispiriting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this era of standardized student testing, it has become an all-too-familiar ritual in New York City and across the country: the leader of the school system calls a news conference and holds a wedding or a funeral, crowing if scores are up, grieving and accepting blame if they are down.</p>
        <p>Historically, most New York City chancellors have been able to do a bit of both. Test results can be relied on to rise in some years and fall in others. For parents and many teachers, the constant ratcheting up and down of scores -- testing experts call it the sawtooth effect -- is confusing and exhausting, if not dispiriting.</p>
        <p>So it was a reality test last week when Harold O. Levy, New York's new chancellor, greeted two successive waves of good news on testing -- a nine-point rise on a statewide test and a five-point rise on a citywide test -- by urging caution. Mr. Levy half-joked that he would post bar charts in the lobby of 110 Livingston Street in Brooklyn, headquarters of the Board of Education, where, like a corporation reporting to stockholders, the school system would be forced to expose its long-term gains and losses.</p>
        <p>In the war of perception against reality, almost nothing can be harder to gauge than the meaning of test scores. It seems only common sense that a system of 78,000 teachers and 1.1 million schoolchildren -- or, as Mr. Levy likes to point out, one out of 43 schoolchildren in America -- is too big an ocean liner to turn around in just a year. Is the curriculum new and wonderful? Did the quality of teachers improve? There is no systemic evidence of either. Yet parents and teachers are encouraged to judge their children and schools the way investors watch the Dow industrials.</p>
        <p>''There's a quantifiable aspect to testing that is so seductive,'' said Gary Lincoff, the father of a fifth grader in Manhattan. ''If a kid does well and scores high, you can dismiss the tests as meaningless, because you're happy. But if your kid gets a low score, you suspect he isn't getting it and blame yourself, your child, or go the other way and blame the system.</p>
        <p>''Success in America is like a quiz show. It's how to be a millionaire, and there's usually a number in there.''</p>
        <p>But the more sophisticated view, experts say, is that it is almost impossible to attribute real meaning to a one-year gain in scores.</p>
        <p>The New York City reading test seems a particularly clear case in point. The city and the state are now in their second year of a new reading test, and experts say it is almost axiomatic that scores go up in the second year of a test.</p>
        <p>Last spring, in the first year of the new state test, 32.8 percent of New York City's fourth graders and 56.8 percent of the fourth graders in the rest of the state met state standards for reading and writing. This year's results showed that 41.7 percent of fourth graders in New York City met the standards, a gain of nine percentage points, as did 68.2 percent in the rest of the state.</p>
        <p>Then, last week, the results of the city's separate reading test for grades three, five, six and seven came out, offering some corroboration of the rise in performance. On the test, 40.8 percent of students met the standards, up from 35.7 percent last year.  Every district and almost every school in the city improved. But despite the overall improvement, schools at the bottom stayed at the bottom and schools at the top remained there.</p>
        <p>Pessimists point out that the scores still mean that 6 out of 10 students in New York City, mostly poor black and Hispanic students, are not meeting city and state standards for reading and writing.</p>
        <p>''Some schools, what I call the dead zone schools, just seem stuck at the bottom,'' said Raymond J. Domanico, an education consultant to the Metro Industrial Areas Foundation, a coalition of New York civic and church groups. ''They were dysfunctional, they continue to be dysfunctional, and they won't reap the benefits of any of these systemic efforts until we get more highly qualified teachers and principals.''</p>
        <p>The Board of Education, in its press release, ascribed the rise in scores to a variety of causes: more diagnostic reading tests, expanded prekindergarten, reduced class size and after-school reading classes. But as David Liben, principal of the Family Academy in Harlem, pointed out, ''you have to look at this like Sherlock Holmes.''</p>
        <p>Many steps, including reducing class size and expanding prekindergarten, are new and have affected only a small fraction of the city's very youngest students. They seem only remotely connected, if at all, to sixth and seventh grade, where scores rose the most.</p>
        <p>While children who failed the test last year and were held back in the same grade showed large gains in test scores this year, experts say such results are the norm the year after schools stop promoting failing students. Those students, said Lorrie A. Shepard, a professor of education at the University of Colorado at Boulder, are reviewing the same material and taking roughly the same test, so their performance can be expected to go up. The more critical question, she said, is whether their gains will be maintained in future years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy defended testing as a crude, if necessary, check on the system, yet sided with the skeptics in suggesting that a one-year gain revealed little about the condition of the schools.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard to identify causality with any certainty,'' he said. Once other exams also show positive trends, ''the more comfort one can have that we're moving in the right direction,'' he said. ''But in judging whether the system is performing, someone in my position needs to be properly skeptical about test scores and constantly questioning what are the alternative explanations, so that you don't put on rose-colored glasses.''</p>
        <p>A further complication is the completely different way of scoring reading tests. Percentile scores, based on a national norm, were replaced with performance scores, based on an absolute standard for what children should know. The performance standards were developed by a committee of teachers and test company officials. They rank students within four levels, from lowest to highest, and by what is called a scale score, much like an SAT score, from 427 to 810. The state also uses performance standards.</p>
        <p>Many experts say performance standards are a better measure of what students know than percentile scores, but they caution that the standards are also somewhat arbitrary, and subject to the caprices, judgment and manipulation of the officials who establish the cutoff points. ''There's no precise science for deciding what meets standards and what doesn't,'' Dr. Shepard said.</p>
        <p>The New York City results are also puzzling because they show striking variations from grade to grade, with scores stable in third grade, rising 12.4 points on the performance scale in sixth grade and dropping 4.1 points in fifth grade.</p>
        <p>Given the fluctuations, Sylvia Wertheimer, whose daughter Laura is a fifth grader, said she found it hard to put too much emphasis on the five-point gain. ''It doesn't make me feel better about the school system,'' she said. ''It makes me concerned that there's too much emphasis on tests.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of standardized testing use such fluctuations to argue that tests are meaningless and should be abolished.</p>
        <p>But others, echoing Mr. Levy, warn that test results matter most in the long term. From the 1960's to the 90's, performance on standardized tests declined in New York City as schoolchildren became poorer and dropout rates went up. Though the dropout rates and test scores have both shown a slight improvement in recent years, as the economy has improved, it is too early, experts say, to conclude that the change reflects real progress in the school system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that rather than focusing on test results, he wanted to focus on hiring, encouraging and retaining good teachers, principals and superintendents.</p>
        <p>Some experts suggested that the increased emphasis in the last two years on tests -- and on using them as a standard for promotion and graduation -- was enough to raise test scores in the beginning.</p>
        <p>''One common denominator is that we are now involved in high-stakes testing,'' said Joseph Viteritti, a research professor at New York University. ''And that's a motivator.''</p>
        <p>Diane Ravitch, the education historian, said studies showed that children who benefit most from testing were those just below the middle, ''who understand that with a little bit more effort they can reach the goal.'' That is why, she said, the outcry against more testing and higher standards ''never comes from poor districts, it comes from superadvantaged districts, like Scarsdale, which say, 'We don't want this, we're too good for this.' Those kids will do well, no matter what.''</p>
        <p>Jennette Williams, whose daughter Shauntay is in the eighth grade at Intermediate School 311 in the East New York section of Brooklyn, said tests had given her daughter a sense of mastery and pride. ''All children should know how far they are in life,'' Ms. Williams said, ''so they know where to go to move on.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
