<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Countdown to the Parade, With Pride and Profit</title>
    <meta content="11BRON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vendors, Street</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFD9163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Countdown to the Parade, With Pride and Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds, perhaps thousands, of vendors and hawkers take to streets of Bronx to sell hats, T-shirts, key chains and flags bearing colors or name of Puerto Rico in weeks before annual Puerto Rican Day Parade in Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each spring for the last 20 years, Nestor Rantas has traveled to the Bronx from Juana Diaz, P.R., to sell hats, T-shirts, key chains and anything else bearing the colors or name of his native land.</p>
        <p>So it was no surprise that early yesterday, the day before the annual Puerto Rican Day Parade in Manhattan, Mr. Rantas, 44, was standing near Southern Boulevard with a bundle of flags in his hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each spring for the last 20 years, Nestor Rantas has traveled to the Bronx from Juana Diaz, P.R., to sell hats, T-shirts, key chains and anything else bearing the colors or name of his native land.</p>
        <p>So it was no surprise that early yesterday, the day before the annual Puerto Rican Day Parade in Manhattan, Mr. Rantas, 44, was standing near Southern Boulevard with a bundle of flags in his hands.</p>
        <p>He was a small dot in a sea of red, white and blue flags on East Tremont Avenue. Men carrying their own collections of flags and hats came by and asked what he still had in stock. Some were looking for flags to place on their cars or to drape around themselves during the parade; others were sellers trying to stock up.</p>
        <p>Each year in the weeks before the parade, hundreds, perhaps thousands of vendors and hawkers take to the streets of the Bronx to sell the symbols that unite proud Puerto Ricans, many of whom travel across the country for the event.</p>
        <p>And the East Tremont neighborhood, where Mr. Rantas also owns the Borinquen Records store, is at the center of that industry.</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Rantas said, he sold the apparel ''for the people of Puerto Rico.'' But his next comment, which came after the driver of a flatbed truck stopped to pick up a flag and hoist it, suggested a motive somewhat less altruistic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rantas said he made tens of thousands of dollars each spring selling the items on the street and in his nearby store. But he does think that the economic returns show another type of pride.</p>
        <p>''For Puerto Rico, everything,'' he said. ''It is also good for the community because so many people are buying flags and selling them on the streets, and that helps the community.''</p>
        <p>Among New York City's many annual parades, the Puerto Rican Day Parade is particularly merchandise-rich. In the weeks before the event, flags begin popping up in windows all over heavily Puerto Rican sections of East Tremont and Mott Haven in the Bronx, East Williamsburg in Brooklyn and the Lower East Side and East Village in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>People also drape flags on the hoods of their cars or use them as shawls, hang trinkets in their cars and wear T-shirts emblazoned with phrases like ''I love you Puerto Rico.''</p>
        <p>The vendors are the economic engine of the annual rite.</p>
        <p>There are no official city estimates on the revenue generated by the hundreds of thousands of people drawn into New York City by the parade, or ''el desfile,'' as it is more commonly known in the East Bronx. But businesspeople in the neighborhood said the economic windfall was essential.</p>
        <p>Ramy Khalif, 28, the owner of Mak 99 Cents store at East Tremont and Marmion Avenues, said he purchased 40,000 Puerto Rican flags about three weeks ago to sell -- at $1 to $8 -- before the parade. There were only 2,000 flags left yesterday morning. He had already run out of towels and caps.</p>
        <p>The merchandise cost Mr. Khalif about $70,000 and he expects to make more than $100,000. He said yesterday that he expected to sell out in several hours. ''I don't think there will be anything left,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khalif, who was an employee in the store before buying it five years ago, added that the parade-related sales ''help bring people into the store.''</p>
        <p>At Mr. Rantas's music store, the rows of CD's and tapes that usually fill the store had been replaced by flags, T-shirts, clocks, coat racks, towels and key chains. There were even belts, plates and umbrellas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rantas would not say how much he expected to make from the parade, except that it would be in the tens of thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>But to many, he said, the merchandise sales are simply a symptom of pride. For Juan Nass, who is not Puerto Rican, it is less about pride and more about money. ''Tomorrow is going to be slow and back to normal, but in the week before the parade we make lots of money,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
