<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loggers Look at a Tree and See a Boat</title>
    <meta content="11LOG.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shipbuilding, Conversion and Repair</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oak Trees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Naval Timbers (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Besozzi, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monagan, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D6133FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loggers Look at a Tree and See a Boat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MONAGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Monagan, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on independent Connecticut logger Charles Besozzi, whose New England Naval Timbers in Cornwall deals exclusively with Connecticut white oak planks esteemed by shipwrights; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONNECTICUT'S 570 licensed loggers are an independent lot, mostly hewing an unseen living in one- or two-man bands from the forests that dot the two northern corners of the state. But the 70 million board feet of timber they harvest each year is thought by the state to contribute about $414 million to the economy, in large part because the state still holds many stands of prime hardwoods that are valued throughout the world.</p>
        <p>One of the most storied is the white oak, quercus alba, because it grows straight, hard, and clear grained, with superb rot and water resistance -- qualities all long esteemed by shipwrights. A Cornwall logger named Charles (Duke) Besozzi has found his way into the same market, supplying select timbers for the grand schooner restorations and one-of-a-kind wooden yachts that are being brought to life in boat yards up and down the New England coast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONNECTICUT'S 570 licensed loggers are an independent lot, mostly hewing an unseen living in one- or two-man bands from the forests that dot the two northern corners of the state. But the 70 million board feet of timber they harvest each year is thought by the state to contribute about $414 million to the economy, in large part because the state still holds many stands of prime hardwoods that are valued throughout the world.</p>
        <p>One of the most storied is the white oak, quercus alba, because it grows straight, hard, and clear grained, with superb rot and water resistance -- qualities all long esteemed by shipwrights. A Cornwall logger named Charles (Duke) Besozzi has found his way into the same market, supplying select timbers for the grand schooner restorations and one-of-a-kind wooden yachts that are being brought to life in boat yards up and down the New England coast.</p>
        <p>''Connecticut white oak was once known as the best white oak of all,'' said Mr. Besozzi, 50, of Collinsville, who looks more like a prep school English teacher than a logger with his tousled chestnut hair, clear blue eyes, and sleight but taut frame.</p>
        <p>''It is really good and slow-growing and especially free of dead knots in the Northwest Corner and just across the line in the Southern Berkshires and New York.''</p>
        <p>He was standing beside a 30-foot length of white oak from a tree whose first milling revealed hints of rose in its milky grain. The seven-inch thick timber, which Besozzi estimated was 175 years old, will soon be refined into the tapering contours of a yacht's keel by a seventh-generation Massachusetts shipwright.</p>
        <p>''Naval architects will fax me the dimensions of a keel or sternpost or whatever they need, and I'll go out to find the right tree. I can tell straight away if there's a keel in a tree from the trueness and height and upper edge defects, or a natural sweep waiting for deck planking. Other loggers will also set aside what they think I might like,'' Mr. Besozzi said, pointing towards some behemoths with the name Duke painted at the end, ''and I go around collecting the best stuff like truffles.''</p>
        <p>Jon Wilson, the founder and editor-in-chief of the Maine-based Woodenboat magazine, said there is strong demand among ship builders for the white oak of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''If boat builders had to depend on commercial lumber yards, they'd go out of business,'' he said. ''There is no question that Connecticut white oak is among the most highly prized stock.</p>
        <p>''Wooden boat builders are extraordinarily dependent on the eye of a timber harvester like this,'' he said. ''It's as if you were a gourmet cook and the ultimate meal depended on absolutely perfect ingredients; you'd soon realize that if you don't have those you cannot express your art.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Besozzi, who studied history at the University of Connecticut and spent his boyhood summers in Maine, first spotted the possibility of combining his love of water and wood after a mast hunting excursion to Cornwall by Mystic Seaport representatives in the early 1980's. At the time, he was harvesting upward of a half-million board feet per year -- typically, the more predominant red oak, cherry, ash, and sugar maple that are central to Connecticut's forest industry.</p>
        <p>''I was just going like a demon, cutting a huge volume and not really that satisfied. I could visualize this continuing forever, producing millions of board feet without a real point. I wanted to do something for myself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Gradually, he began to sell raw logs and then saw out fine lengths for keels and planking for schooners and cutters, yawls, dories and Chris Craft motor launches. For the last four years, he has concentrated solely on his business, New England Naval Timbers. Mr. Besozzi and his assistant, Alex Ware, a wood technology graduate of the University of Massachusetts, have since supplied major portions of the sterns, stems, gunwhales, planking and decking for numerous grand projects such as the United States Park Service's 104-foot reproduction of the Friendship, an 18th-century trading vessel out of Salem, Mass.; a 60-foot Maine schooner that will soon be transporting cargo to and from the Caribbean; and now the elaborate restoration of the 1885 schooner Coronet just beginning at the International Yacht Restoration School in Newport, R.I.</p>
        <p>''He may be the only guy I've ever seen restrict his business to naval white oak timbers,'' said Clark Poston, program director at the Newport school, who noted that some good oak can be found in Rhode Island and Pennsylvania. ''He's finding really large old trees that a lot of common sawyers are not necessarily going to locate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Besozzi spoke with love of the redolent timbers by his side. One piece was worth about $800, roughly three times more than its value at a mass production mill. Stacks of white oak trunks awaited his 50-foot band saw in a glen below Cornwall Village where he works.</p>
        <p>''When you steam white oak, you can bend it like a noodle. Then when it dries, it just retempers itself and is as strong as ever. It has stringy, interlocking fibers that make it flex beautifully, which is just perfect for wooden boats, because they are flexing and living things.''</p>
        <p>But trees do not always reward the logger's affection. Mr. Besozzi himself had the middle three fingers on his left hand severed into stubs eight years ago by a log ripping chain. Chronic shoulder and arm tendinitis have also come with the job. In April, the highly experienced Winchester logger, Richard Hayes, was killed by a falling tree. Recently, another logger with a spinal injury had to be evacuated by helicopter from a nearby forest on Cornwall's Cream Hill.</p>
        <p>''Logging is very dangerous,'' explained Douglas Emmerthal, who handles the state's certification and safety programs for the State Department of Environmental Protection. ''The only occupation more so is commercial fishing.''</p>
        <p>Increased safety is another reason Duke Besozzi is delighted to be cutting only a fraction of the trees he once did. ''Production logging wears you out. I am so much happier,'' he said, eyeing a massive trunk and seeing the shape of some ship to be.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
