<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Owners Discount Microsoft Uncertainty?</title>
    <meta content="11INSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisenstat, Melissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB1E3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Owners Discount Microsoft Uncertainty?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenneth N Gilpin Market Insight column interviews CIBC Work Markets senior software analyst Melissa Eisenstat concerning likely impact of Federal Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson's antitrust ruling against Microsoft and Microsoft's prospects for avoiding breakup on appeal; Eisenstat expresses concern that ruling could apply to other companies that have products that work together; foresees volatility ahead for Microsoft shares; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Micro. Soft.</p>
        <p>That is what the government wants. And Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson agreed. But Microsoft wants to remain one word, not two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Micro. Soft.</p>
        <p>That is what the government wants. And Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson agreed. But Microsoft wants to remain one word, not two.</p>
        <p>There has been endless debate about what a breakup would mean for investors, and there is much more ahead, because the legal wrangling is far from over.</p>
        <p>But the judge's decision last week has made the discussion a bit less abstract. Unless it can convince a federal appeals court to postpone the restraints the government is demanding in addition to the breakup, Microsoft is likely to experience real financial pain at some point in the next three months. And that pain may well be shared by those who own its stock.</p>
        <p>Melissa Eisenstat, senior software analyst at CIBC World Markets, took some time last week to talk about the case and its impact on Wall Street. Following are excerpts from the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. Could this decision hurt the potential profitability for all software manufacturers?</p>
        <p>A. It depends. If this case becomes a slippery slope, and suddenly we start judging other companies that have products that work together as monopolies, that could be a negative. Oracle, for example, sells applications that work with its database.</p>
        <p>If the case forces companies to separate operations and not create complementary products, that is a negative for profitability. And conceivably the pricing changes that the government wants Microsoft to follow could force pricing changes in the rest of the industry.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk about the pricing issue. What is the government demanding that Microsoft do?</p>
        <p>A. As part of the behavioral remedy, the government wants Microsoft to standardize the prices it charges to its largest personal computer customers, like Dell and Compaq. In the past, they have offered discounts on older models.</p>
        <p>Standardized pricing would be a negative for the company, because if Microsoft is not charging as much per software unit, Wall Street would have to revise earnings estimates.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the chances that a Microsoft appeal to stay this and the government's other behavioral remedies will be approved?</p>
        <p>A. It is nearly a tossup. There is no question that a breakup of the company will be stayed pending the appeal process. But I would put the odds on the remedies being stayed at about 55 percent to 45 percent.</p>
        <p>Q. If the behavioral remedies are put into effect, who benefits?</p>
        <p>A. Sun Microsystems, which has an operating system. Oracle would do very, very well, because it might get better access to the Windows 2000 operating system, assuming that is opened up. America Online, because of their Netscape browser. And tangentially, the Linux companies may do well, even though I am skeptical about their longevity.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's say the behavioral remedies are put in place, and then down the road the courts reject the government's case. Hasn't Microsoft lost out in the intervening period?</p>
        <p>A. Undoing behavioral patterns is relatively easier than undoing a structural change. But some of their knowledge would be in the hands of third parties.</p>
        <p>But this industry moves rather quickly. The products that are critical today are not necessarily going to be critical tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Q. What's your opinion on the ultimate outcome of this case?</p>
        <p>A. I don't think the company will be broken up, but this appeals process could go on for a long time. I think the higher courts will agree with some elements and disagree with others. A mixed decision like that would send the matter back to Judge Jackson.</p>
        <p>Q. So what is your take on the stock?</p>
        <p>A. I downgraded the stock in early April, when the mediation talks broke down, and we have had a hold rating on the shares ever since. We thought then that the company would lose the case, that the appeal would take a long time and that some of the behavioral remedies would be harsh. The risk of those remedies being implemented is one I am not willing to recommend that investors take.</p>
        <p>Aside from the case, the company also faces questions related to the Internet and their product strategy. People owned Microsoft over the past two decades because of its dominance of the computing world. But nobody is going to own the Internet or wireless world the way Microsoft owned the desktop. And so far I don't think Microsoft has done a really good job showing investors how it is going to take a leading role in those worlds. We will get a better idea of what their strategy is later this month.</p>
        <p>I don't hate the company. It is a great company with a lot of talented technologists and marketers. But not all of the bad news is behind them. Going forward, there is going to be a lot of volatility in the stock.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
