<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The N.B.A.'s Ratings Resemble an Air Ball</title>
    <meta content="11NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DB163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The N.B.A.'s Ratings Resemble an Air Ball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBA notebook column examines various reasons for dwindling television ratings for regular season NBA games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Stern will issue his annual finals address next week in Indianapolis, going over all that is right and amiss with his league and insisting that business is not as bad as perceived.</p>
        <p>Whether or not the commissioner's words reflect the genuine state of the National Basketball Association, Stern knows he is not presiding over the megapopular product whose growth once seemed to have no end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Stern will issue his annual finals address next week in Indianapolis, going over all that is right and amiss with his league and insisting that business is not as bad as perceived.</p>
        <p>Whether or not the commissioner's words reflect the genuine state of the National Basketball Association, Stern knows he is not presiding over the megapopular product whose growth once seemed to have no end.</p>
        <p>''We're going through change, but we're convinced things will pick up,'' he said last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Stern spoke before Game 1 between the Los Angeles Lakers and the Indiana Pacers drew a television rating of 10.5 -- the lowest rating in 14 years and down 9 percent from Game 1 of the San Antonio Spurs-Knicks series last June.</p>
        <p>Last week, the icons who propelled his league in the 1980's and 1990's have candidly spoken their minds about the N.B.A.'s quality of play and its interest level.</p>
        <p>Larry Bird: ''I don't think it's totally back. We played Milwaukee in a Game 4 there and they didn't sell out. It just seems like a lot of people aren't talking about the N.B.A. as much as they used to.</p>
        <p>''I think they're doing a good job promoting it. I'd like to see them get more teams on TV than just the Lakers and New York. I think it's coming back. But the only way it comes back is if you have great competition.''</p>
        <p>Magic Johnson: ''We have to establish our superstars. Who's going to be our stars now? Who's going to take this league? It's out there. Shaq is the most dominant. But we need a guy to be the man in terms of Michael Jordan. So who is that going to be?''</p>
        <p>After the Lakers' riveting Game 7 comeback against Portland last Sunday, even Jordan was not impressed. ''In all honesty, I don't think they won it,'' he said. ''I think Portland lost it.''</p>
        <p>Bird, Johnson and Jordan are not the only ones concerned about the health of the game. ''When you watch a player like Reggie Miller in the clutch, it's at its best,'' said Pat Riley, the Miami Heat coach and team president who coached the Lakers to their last championship in 1988. ''And you realize it will never not be an entity. But the evolution of the player and the mentality of the player -- caused by a number of extenuating circumstances -- has changed the games and how it is perceived by the public.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The public likes it, but they're going to like it on their own terms now -- because they don't get the game on the favorable terms they used to get it. There was more humility by the players. The money factor, too, is huge. It really is a business now, even for fans. When fans buy season tickets now, they sign contracts.''</p>
        <p>Riley said he had read an article about several hedge-fund billionaires from the 1980's who lost hundreds of millions during the stock market's recent downturn.</p>
        <p>''These were brilliant men,'' he said. ''And one simply said, 'I don't understand this market anymore.' He admitted, as a professional investment counselor, that he doesn't understand his market.</p>
        <p>''And if you equate back to the league, I don't think a lot of our fans really understand it right now. They will support it until they understand it again. But we've got to make them understand it. The players have to make them understand it. Otherwise, we're going to lose them.</p>
        <p>''We're losing a lot of viewers to other things.''</p>
        <p>Even though ratings plummeted during the regular season -- off 21 percent from last season's lockout-shortened year -- Stern is unfazed.</p>
        <p>''TV remains the dominant entertainment vehicle, but people forget everyone's numbers are off,'' Stern said. '' 'Monday Night Football' just experienced its worst-ever ratings. We live in a changing entertainment environment. The number of people who watched the final episode of 'Seinfeld' was lower than the number of people who watched the final episode of 'Cheers.' And that number was lower than the final episode of 'M*A*S*H.' That's where we are.''</p>
        <p>Stern blames several factors for the low ratings and the declining interest in the league. ''First, I think it has to do with the post-Michael era, something we expected to happen,'' he said. ''You throw in the lockout and an extraordinary amount of additional programming, and that's where the problems lie. Those are not insubstantial numbers we're talking about. Adding games on Saturdays all resulted in the fact a cumulative effect on the ratings.''</p>
        <p>Bird thinks there is another factor contributing to the league's interest problems: many of today's players, he said, do not resonate with fans as much as players from his era.</p>
        <p>''I believe the players got to do more in their communities,'' he said. ''And stay out of trouble. And when they play, they got to play hard. You read about all the negative stuff sometimes and we don't think about the positive. We got a lot of great players in our league that play hard every night. It's just that you have to have a majority do that.''</p>
        <p>Stern discounts the notion that players were more passionate about their jobs two decades ago.</p>
        <p>''Whether it's Vince Carter, Allen Iverson, the Latrell Sprewells or the Ray Allens and Kevin Garnetts, we see an intensity to our players equal to any intensity in the last 20 years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The notion was we needed New York, everyone was writing that,'' he said. ''It was never a concern: the ratings will be fine. We're going through a transition, but I fully expect things to improve.''</p>
        <p>But a wedge is growing, and it is not relegated to the league and fans. The kinship between coaches and players and the N.B.A. is not as strong as it once was. Controversies involving league directives over access and the use of microphones led to widespread criticism earlier this year and a threatened lawsuit by the coaches' association.</p>
        <p>''They're marketing just like high-tech stocks,'' Riley said. ''Market the business. Market the image even though there's no profits. The N.B.A. has marketed their sport extremely well.</p>
        <p>''But maybe they've gotten involved into the game too much, making these changes. And they made them the last time in a very arbitrary manner. They said: 'Well, you guys don't want to change, so we'll change them. We're changing the rules, so you get with it.' That was basically the message.</p>
        <p>''So they must feel very strongly about the direction they're going in.''</p>
        <p>Improving the Wizards</p>
        <p>As Michael Jordan's coaching-search odyssey comes to a close -- University of Miami Coach Leonard Hamilton seems primed to take the job -- the Wizards' head of basketball operations must now concentrate on finding creative ways to upgrade Washington's roster.</p>
        <p>According to Magic Johnson, it will not be easy. Salary-cap problems that prevent many of the Wizards' players with locked-in, long-term contracts from being traded for equal value are well documented. But Johnson said Jordan faced another hurdle, too.</p>
        <p>It's called payback.</p>
        <p>''I told people it would take him three to five years,'' Johnson said. ''He's in a tough situation. Nobody in this league wants to help him because he beat them most of the time. No one is going to say, 'I'll take Juwan or Rod or Ike Austin,' '' Johnson said of Juwan Howard and Rod Strickland.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wanted to help us, either. That's the way it is. Everybody wants to see him lose. They're smiling because he has no cap room. But he'll break through.''</p>
        <p>Jordan appeared close to working out a deal with Mike Jarvis, the St. John's coach, before negotiations broke down.</p>
        <p>Asked if Jordan is frustrated making the transition from player to part-owner and N.B.A. executive, Johnson said: ''I would be frustrated. From his side, it's the same thing. He went after the guy he wanted and it didn't happen. That has to frustrate him.''</p>
        <p>Johnson has a small percentage of ownership in the Lakers in addition to his outside business interests, which include a traveling team that plays in Europe. As his playing contemporaries like Jordan and Larry Bird attempt to make their mark in other areas of the game, Johnson also is contemplating a more prominent N.B.A. position.</p>
        <p>''I don't know whether it would be what Rod Thorn did or what Larry is doing,'' Johnson said of Thorn, the new Nets' team president. ''I'll have to wait. But I'm having fun at what I'm doing, and I'm committed. When I get back into basketball, I want to get back into it all the way. I have a goal set. I'm almost there.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
