<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="T11TES0AC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DA163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BETTE MIDLER is great and we wish her well with her coming CBS comedy series, but it's hard to watch her first film, THE ROSE (1979), without lamenting the dramatic acting career that might have been. As a drugged-out, alcoholic, emotionally fragile rock star headed for the hometown stop on her concert tour (and for disaster), Ms. Midler pays tribute to Janis Joplin (whose story this is said to be) but adds her own explosive stage presence to the character. And that makes Barbra Streisand's imitation of a rock singer in ''A Star is Born'' three years earlier look even sillier than before. Ms. Midler was nominated for a best actress Oscar, and the phone booth scene alone shows why. Mark Rydell directed - Saturday at 10:45 p.m. on the Romance Channel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BETTE MIDLER is great and we wish her well with her coming CBS comedy series, but it's hard to watch her first film, THE ROSE (1979), without lamenting the dramatic acting career that might have been. As a drugged-out, alcoholic, emotionally fragile rock star headed for the hometown stop on her concert tour (and for disaster), Ms. Midler pays tribute to Janis Joplin (whose story this is said to be) but adds her own explosive stage presence to the character. And that makes Barbra Streisand's imitation of a rock singer in ''A Star is Born'' three years earlier look even sillier than before. Ms. Midler was nominated for a best actress Oscar, and the phone booth scene alone shows why. Mark Rydell directed - Saturday at 10:45 p.m. on the Romance Channel.</p>
        <p>James Stewart is Scotty Ferguson, and ex-cop with a paralyzing fear of heights, and Kim Novak is Madeleine, a friend's beautifully dressed platinum blond wife who has been behaving very strangely in VERTIGO (1958), one of Alfred Hitchcock's most haunting mysteries. Scotty is hired to follow Madeleine (who goes to all the prettiest places in San Francisco) and, naturally, falls in love with her, but that's the least of his problems. He witnesses what can only be a suicide, lands in a mental hospital and is discharged only to meet a woman who could be Madeleine's twin. Scotty's idea of a beauty-fashion makeover for her is very scary - Saturday at 8 p.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Movie fans who wish they were in Paris get an invigorating tour of the Bastille neighborhood in WHEN THE CAT'S AWAY (1996), Cedric Klapisch's charmer of a comic drama. Chloe (Garance Clavel) is an attractive but lonely young makeup artist who takes a much-needed vacation, leaving her beloved cat, Gris-Gris, with an elderly neighbor. When the cat disappears, Chloe is forced to scour the neighborhood, talk to people she'd never even noticed before and generally wake up to the world around her - Sunday at 2 p.m. and Sunday/Early Monday at 3:30 a.m. on Bravo.</p>
        <p>The N.Y.U. Film School must be very proud of Ang Lee. Just before he directed ''Sense and Sensibility,'' he looked to his homeland in the seductive EAT DRINK MAN WOMAN (1994), the story of the greatest chef in Taipei and some tense Sunday dinners with his three lovely but romantically challenged daughters. Mr. Shu (Sihung Lung), a widower, has lost the use of his taste buds (his offspring consider this a metaphor for his emotional shortcomings), but that doesn't stop hm from creating gorgeous culinary masterpieces, which are delicious just to look at - Wednesday at 9:45 p.m., Thursday at 6 a.m. and 12:15 p.m. on IFC.</p>
        <p>Who remebered that THE ODD COUPLE (1968) began with a thwarted suicide attempt? Felix, distraught over the end of his marriage, couldn't get the ninth-floor window open at the hotel, so he went to his divorced friend's apartment instead. And just stayed. Gene Saks directed this Neil Simon comedy about the fastidious Felix Ungar (Jack Lemmon, who gives the character real depth), his happy slob of a friend, Oscar Madison (Walter Matthau), and everything that goes wrong when they become roommates. Mr. Simon was at his peak here, and the film includes a depiction of the world's most awkward double date. Also, who remembers that it was an eight-room apartment? - Tuesday at 8 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>- Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
