<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Doctor: Voices Of Patients in Poetry</title>
    <meta content="11POET$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Marc J (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelb, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DE103FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Doctor: Voices Of Patients in Poetry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN GELB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gelb, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Marc Strauss, oncologist and poet in White Plains, NY, who often writes from point of view of patients in cancer ward; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 1980's, Dr. Marc J. Straus's resume listed his medical degree, fellowships at the National Cancer Institute and his tenure as head of oncology in hospitals in Boston and New York.</p>
        <p>Then in 1990, he signed up for a poetry class at the 92nd Street Y, eager to express his feelings about cancer medicine. ''I knew after one two-hour poetry class that I'd be doing this the rest of my life,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 1980's, Dr. Marc J. Straus's resume listed his medical degree, fellowships at the National Cancer Institute and his tenure as head of oncology in hospitals in Boston and New York.</p>
        <p>Then in 1990, he signed up for a poetry class at the 92nd Street Y, eager to express his feelings about cancer medicine. ''I knew after one two-hour poetry class that I'd be doing this the rest of my life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Now more than half his resume is devoted to mentions of his poems in the Kenyon Review, his literary awards and his poetry books. Dr. Straus does still practice medicine in White Plains, but he also considers poetry much more than a hobby.</p>
        <p>A literary descendant of William Carlos Williams, Dr. Straus often writes about communication between doctors and patients. Using what he calls his ''inner ear,'' Dr. Straus writes from the point of view of people in the cancer ward, penetrating a confusing, emotional world; one of his books, ''The Bridge,'' which has not yet been published, is a collection of 25 poems written in the voice of a fictional female patient. In a recent interview, he talked about both of his callings, and his new book, ''Symmetry'' (Northwestern University Press, 2000).</p>
        <p>Q. Just what about medicine inspired you to write poetry?</p>
        <p>A. I'm really compelled by the nuances in patient-doctor communication -- what it is that a doctor says and how it is received and internalized by the patient. In my world, I've been in the situation for over 25 years of telling thousands of people for the very first time that they have cancer. I try my best to absorb some of their anxiety by working really hard to support them. You have to learn to hear your patients. It's not just the exact words you say. It's how you say it.</p>
        <p>In medical school, the professor would take a group of us around and stop in front of patients' beds to present cases. In front of one elderly patient, he said, ''There are no treatment options.'' My heart just sank. I asked him why not, and he said, ''Well, she's 65.'' I guess I was a troublemaker, because I just looked at him and said, ''You know, you're not that young yourself.''</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think other doctors have problems communicating with patients?</p>
        <p>A. When I was trained as a doctor, most people did. There was a large school of thought where doctors would not even tell their patients they had cancer. In the past 20 years, that has changed, and it has all been for the best.</p>
        <p>Q. Does being a doctor make you a better writer?</p>
        <p>A. The things I write about always have a certain amount of power personally. What I've been doing my whole adult life as a cancer doctor is very powerful. I look back and think how fortunate that I've been to be an oncologist. It's a very painful life, yet it has allowed me to do things of substance.</p>
        <p>Q. What is your ''inner ear''?</p>
        <p>A. When I was 9 years old, I began working on weekends at my dad's textile store on Grand Street. But I listened to customers come into the store, and they were people of all ages, races and nationalities. It didn't take long for me to understand such extraordinary subtle differences. I was trying to figure out, ''What were these people really like?'' Part of it was paying attention to some other language that, at the time, I could never articulate. Now that is the language of my poems.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the premise behind ''Sigh'' and ''Say Yes,'' two poems from your new book?</p>
        <p>A. In ''Sigh,'' what I hear the patient telling us is that her doctor may be a good clinician, but he is not a good communicator. He is competent at running tests and he has good medical judgment, but she's telling us there is a greater need of connection and communication. She's having difficulty getting her doctor to listen. She wants to connect with him, but she realizes she can't. For that reason, this poem is an expression of pessimism about her hospital stay. In general, some doctors only address the optimistic part of a patient's chart. But a real challenge is to deal with patients' pessimism. By dealing with it openly, a lot of pain can be alleviated.</p>
        <p>In some ways, ''Say Yes'' is a personal poem. Patients ply us with questions all the time. Sometimes, they expect certain answers. Patients always want to hear that what they have is 100 percent curable. They know that may not be correct, but they really want an absolute answer. I think doctors do a disservice to patients when we give them absolutes. So how you choose your words is very important.</p>
        <p>SIGH</p>
        <p>I sighed this morning, a slow deep inspiration</p>
        <p>that dragged the air into the recesses of my lungs,</p>
        <p>portions I imagine had been forgotten</p>
        <p>in the last few months. And then for a second</p>
        <p>or two I felt the life pass out of me.</p>
        <p>As if it were a prelude, a taste for the sake</p>
        <p>of recognition, to diminish my anger.</p>
        <p>As if it were a gift to make me more accepting,</p>
        <p>so that when the angel lifts my hand</p>
        <p>onto her atomless sleeve I will have no animosity.</p>
        <p>She is so like my physician. He has no tolerance</p>
        <p>for remonstration, his head is so cluttered</p>
        <p>with obligatory data. I might articulate my pain</p>
        <p>but he is filled with dying and I'm obliged</p>
        <p>to keep the sigh inside.</p>
        <p>SAY YES</p>
        <p>If I cut down on fatty foods, lose</p>
        <p>fifteen pounds, work out three times</p>
        <p>a week, will I avoid a heart attack?</p>
        <p>If only every question were that simple.</p>
        <p>It's an opportunity to answer unequivocally,</p>
        <p>to give patients a sense of purpose</p>
        <p>and hope, even if they've always been obese,</p>
        <p>refractory to treatment, unable to comply</p>
        <p>with a regimen. Still, just to say yes</p>
        <p>is palliative, even though they know</p>
        <p>the answer isn't accurate. They don't want</p>
        <p>to hear statistics and vacillation.</p>
        <p>Just to be like the surgeon who says,</p>
        <p>It's 100 % curable -- I got it all, omitting</p>
        <p>the possibility that a cell, a micro-</p>
        <p>metastasis, may already be elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Say yes -- a sliver of grace in an</p>
        <p>excoriated world. I must try it sometime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
