<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Your Toddler's Apple Cider</title>
    <meta content="11SEAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN SEARCH OF..."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Applejack (Liquor)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laird Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunn, Lisa Laird</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laird, Larrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'agnese, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0DE103FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Your Toddler's Apple Cider</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH D'AGNESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">D'agnese, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>SCOBEYVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Laird family of Scobeyville, NJ, America's oldest family of distillers, whose signature product is applejack, 80-proof blend of apple brandy and other neutral spirits; Lisa Laird Dunn and cousin John E Laird 3d represent ninth geneation of Lairds to produce apple-based spirits; photos; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW and again, Larrie Laird leads visitors back beyond his family's plant to a building where 55-gallon oak casks rise from floor to ceiling. Here they lie, biding their time, resting, waiting, aging.</p>
        <p>And the air around them is suffused with the aroma of apples.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW and again, Larrie Laird leads visitors back beyond his family's plant to a building where 55-gallon oak casks rise from floor to ceiling. Here they lie, biding their time, resting, waiting, aging.</p>
        <p>And the air around them is suffused with the aroma of apples.</p>
        <p>''Isn't that smell great?'' said Mr. Laird's daughter, Lisa Laird Dunn.</p>
        <p>''We get used to it,'' said Mr. Laird, the company president, with a chuckle.</p>
        <p>Of course they do. The Lairds, holders of federal liquor license No. 1, belong to the nation's oldest family of distillers. Mrs. Dunn, the company's vice president, and her cousin John E. Laird III, executive vice president, represent the ninth generation of Lairds to produce spirits in this Monmouth County hamlet dotted with fruit orchards and horse farms.</p>
        <p>Their signature product is applejack, an 80-proof amber product that's a blend of apple brandy and other neutral spirits. (The federal government gives applejack its own alcohol classification, just like whiskey, Scotch, brandy or Cognac.) A single sip tastes something between good whiskey and even better brandy, tinged with apple notes. ''I just love watching peoples' faces when they try it,'' said Mrs. Dunn. ''They're usually amazed how smooth it is.''</p>
        <p>One cannot help but be amazed as well by the family's history, which is packed with colorful characters, not to mention cameos by historic figures. The tale begins in 1698, when the Scotsman William Laird departed County Fyfe for New Jersey. Presumably the first American Laird had produced his own Scotch back in his native land. In his new home, lacking peat, lacking malt, lacking gloomy moors, he set about distilling his own version of apple cider.</p>
        <p>Back then the word ''cyder'' was used interchangeably with applejack. Today, there's a big, federally mandated difference: sweet cider sold at farm stands each autumn may contain up to 3 percent alcohol; hard cider is 3 to 7 percent; applejack is 40 percent (80 proof); and apple brandy is 50 percent (100 proof).</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Laird's ancestors, Robert Laird, served under General Washington in the Revolutionary War. When the troops were stationed in New Jersey, the Lairds supplied them with ''Jersey lightning.'' The general himself was certainly no stranger to  the drink; sometime before 1760, Washington had written the family asking for their recipe. Later he reciprocated by sending the Lairds a recipe Martha Washington had dreamed up for applejack walnut cake with an applejack-spiked glaze. The story and the  recipe appear in a cookbook of applejack recipes Mrs. Dunn researched and compiled with her mother, Rose Marie Laird, in 1992.</p>
        <p>Such tales are common knowledge around Laird's, where everyday office business is conducted from an elegant white 1740's  house with a second-story porch and yellow shutters. In the main conference room,  hand-hewn timbers decorate the ceiling and generations of amber-colored bottles grace the fireplace. ''We all know the old stories,'' said Mrs. Dunn. ''A lot of it is taken for granted.'' A special moment for Mrs. Dunn came only this past February, when her 4-year-old son was learning about George Washington in preparation for Presidents' Day. ''I said, ''Did you know he was a friend of the family?' ''</p>
        <p>Speaking of Presidents' Day, a young Abraham Lincoln sold applejack in a tavern he ran in the 1830's in Springfield, Ill. ''We still have a bill of fare that shows that he sold applejack at 12 cents a half pint,'' says Mrs. Dunn. ''It doesn't seem like much, but a night's lodging was 12 1/2 cents.'' William Henry Harrison served punches laced with applejack at Whig Party rallies, earning himself the nickname the Hard Cider Candidate. Franklin Delano Roosevelt's favorite drink was an applejack Manhattan: a dash of bitters, vermouth and applejack stirred in ice, strained and served with a cherry. In 1967, Lyndon Johnson presented Soviet Premier Alexei Kosygin with a case of Laird's. And American-style dinners with President Clinton as host have featured after-dinner drinks of Laird's Applejack.</p>
        <p>Today, Laird's produces more than 99 percent of the nation's apple brandy, and is the nation's only producer of blended applejack. Each year, the company buys three million pounds of apples -- eating varieties  like Golden Delicious, Red Delicious, Pippins and Winesaps -- from farmers in the Shenandoah Valley in Virginia. The apples are shipped to the Laird's distillery in North Garden, Va., where they're pressed into cider, allowed to ferment, and then distilled. (In the end, 7,000 pounds of apples must be crushed to fill a single 55-gallon barrel.) The distilled product is shipped north, where it is aged in charred oak barrels once used to age borboun. The applejack is aged six years and the special brandies seven and a half or 12 years.</p>
        <p>Before the 1970's, all the processing was done in Scobeyville with locally grown fruit. That the company has been forced to move  operations south after more than 270 years speaks volumes about the changing agricultural climate in the Garden State. ''You can see what's happening to apple farming in e New Jersey,'' said Mrs. Dunn. ''It's all housing developments.''</p>
        <p>More than the source of apples has changed. These days, Laird's seven apple products -- among them the classic Laird's Blended Applejack, and a premium 12-year-old brandy unveiled only last fall -- account for only 3 percent of the entire business. Last year, the company imported 65,000 cases of Italian, French and German wines, and marketed 900,000 cases of domestic and imported spirits. A visitor to a liquor store will find the Laird's name not just on applejack, but on bottles of vodka, gin, rum and Canadian whiskey as well.</p>
        <p>Trends in alcohol consumption, of course, are forever fickle. Applejack, once the favorite of hard-drinking men, has only recently begun to woo a younger generation rediscovering mixed drinks. For the Lairds, the trick is adapting their historic product to changing tastes and times. ''There's always a discussion of just how much effort we should be putting into the applejack business,'' said Mrs. Dunn.</p>
        <p>One trend has proved a boon. American chefs say they prefer using applejack to flavor dishes instead of the more traditional  Calvados, a pricier apple brandy produced in Normandy. The Lairds' cookbook reflects the culinary trend, including dishes with a decidedly American flavor, such as butternut squash and apple soup, developed by Walter Plender at the American Harvest restaurant in Manhattan; sweet potato apple casserole, adapted from a dish by White House chefs; cider-steamed mussels with applejack cream (the Winnetka Grill in Winnetka, Ill.); and flaming sauteed shrimp (Chef Dan Cummings, the Peach Tree, in Wall).</p>
        <p>''It's an amazing feat for a family to continue a business for nine generations,'' said Mrs. Dunn. ''Our goal is to build it into a  business that will keep going into the 10th, 11th and 12th generation, a solid business that we can pass on to our kids.''</p>
        <p>In the next year, she hopes to devote some of her time to a slightly different challenge: transforming the company's homestead into a museum. (The home of her ancestors was built originally by Capt. Joshua Scobey, who was granted the land that later became  Scobeyville by the Crown to wean him off privateering.) An applejack museum would contribute a needed chapter to the state's history, and would recall a time when the fields teemed with apples, and one family churned out a drink for fit for the likes of common men, presidents, lairds and kings.</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF...</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
