<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books in Brief: Nonfiction</title>
    <meta content="RV091553" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robins, Carol Peace</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tulipomania (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DF133CF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books in Brief: Nonfiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Peace Robins</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robins, Carol Peace</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carol Peace Robins reviews book Tulipomania: TheB</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TulipoMania</p>
        <p>The Story of the World's Most Coveted Flower and the Extraordinary Passions It Aroused.</p>
        <p>By Mike Dash.</p>
        <p>Crown, $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TulipoMania</p>
        <p>The Story of the World's Most Coveted Flower and the Extraordinary Passions It Aroused.</p>
        <p>By Mike Dash.</p>
        <p>Crown, $23.</p>
        <p>In February 1637 in the Netherlands, a tulip bulb sold for 5,200 guilders -- nearly twice the annual earnings of a well-off merchant and 20 times the going price for eight fat pigs. It was the peak of the tulip boom, and most of the Netherlands was caught up in buying and selling bulbs. Why and how this obsession with tulips occurred is the subject of ''Tulipomania,'' by Mike Dash, a London-based writer and magazine publisher. He traces the flower's origins to the foothills of the Himalayas at the turn of the first millennium A.D. and its subsequent cultivation to the Ottomans. He reports that ruthless Ottoman sultans, whose robes and armor were emblazoned with tulips, showcased their flowers in hidden courtyard gardens of the Topkapi Palace -- along with the severed heads of offending notables. In the mid-16th century, the first tulip bulbs arrived in the Netherlands, where they were mistaken for Turkish onions and roasted for supper. It was only after the Johnny Appleseed of tulips, a botanist named Carolus Clusius, cultivated and cataloged tulip varieties and gave them away as gifts that tulipomania really took hold. No longer simply a beautiful flower, tulips became a commodity that was traded in the world's first futures market. Everyone from horticulturists to weavers and carpenters neglected work to buy and sell bulbs. The spectacular crash that followed, Dash writes, was ''far more rapid and complete than history's most notorious financial disaster, the Wall Street crash of 1929.'' Dash has clearly done his research, but he includes more of it than he needs to: far too many statistics about best-selling bulbs and comparisons of precious species for anyone but the most dedicated tulipophile. But, lax weeding aside, ''Tulipomania'' captures the frenzy of a fascinating phenomenon.</p>
        <p>Carol Peace Robins</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
