<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Syrians See In the Heir Possibility Of Progress</title>
    <meta content="11BASH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRANSITION IN SYRIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Bashar Al-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Hafez Al- (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1D8163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Syrians See In the Heir Possibility Of Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bashar al-Assad, presumptive new president of Syria, has waited in wings of power for six years, nurturing reputation as accessible and progressive man who wants to satisfy yearning of many Syrians to be part of modern world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bashar al-Assad, the presumptive new president of Syria, has waited in the wings of power for six years, nurturing a reputation as an accessible and progressive man who wants to satisfy the yearning of many Syrians to be part of the modern world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad, 34, is poised to take on the autocratic powers of his father, Hafez al-Assad, who died today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bashar al-Assad, the presumptive new president of Syria, has waited in the wings of power for six years, nurturing a reputation as an accessible and progressive man who wants to satisfy the yearning of many Syrians to be part of the modern world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad, 34, is poised to take on the autocratic powers of his father, Hafez al-Assad, who died today.</p>
        <p>The machinery of the Syrian state -- a quiescent Parliament, the ruling Baath Party and the state-controlled press -- has all but anointed him as his father's successor to rule a country that has spent most of the last 30 years as a heavily militarized socialist state living in political and economic isolation.</p>
        <p>Unlike his father, who never spent more than a few days outside of Syria in his life, the younger Mr. Assad knows something of the outside world, and was educated in part in the West. So, for many Syrians, the younger Mr. Assad is the antithesis of their inward-looking past, and the passing of power from father to son is not only seen as a characteristic of an authoritarian state, but also as a welcome demonstration of much-cherished stability.</p>
        <p>Before the elder Mr. Assad seized power, Syria had undergone a succession of military coups and social upheavals. Although he represented a tiny religious minority group, the Alawites, and brutally suppressed any political opposition, President Assad also won grudging public acceptance as the ruler who could bring a measure of calm to the fractious Syrian political scene.</p>
        <p>Until 1994, the heir apparent to the Assad dynasty was the eldest son, Basil, a dashing sportsman and military officer. But in January of that year, he died in a spectacular car crash. His funeral was conducted as a state event, with his grieving father shown on Arab television stations throughout the Middle East receiving the condolences of heads of state from around the region.</p>
        <p>Immediately after his elder brother's death, Bashar Assad, the next oldest son, was summoned home from London, where he had lived for two years while studying ophthalmology, and set on a track to accumulate the military and political honors seen as necessary for the next leader of Syria.</p>
        <p>Said by friends to be rather shy and apolitical at first, Mr. Assad has slowly built a reputation for being all that his father was not -- accessible, open and sophisticated in the ways of the world.</p>
        <p>Until very recently, however, he had not taken an active role in foreign policy except as his father's representative in Lebanon. He has traveled extensively in the Arab world in the past two years, meeting with several of its key leaders. His debut on the international stage outside the Middle East came in November on a visit to France, where he had been invited by President Jacques Chirac for his first official talks with a Western head of state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad has been associated, in press reports and in the minds of many Syrians, with a popular anticorruption drive that has already forced a number of his father's longtime supporters out of office. He is credited with hand-selecting many ministers in the new cabinet appointed in March and including a number of men considered open to the idea of a free market economy.</p>
        <p>''We do need a change today more than any time before,'' Mr. Assad told the pan-Arab newspaper Al Hayat, based in London, just before the new government was announced. He said the new government needed ''efficiency, honesty and administrative skills,'' adding, ''If these three elements are available, we will have the government we seek.''</p>
        <p>Long-anticipated changes in Syria's currency and investment laws, finally put in place by presidential decree two months ago, were also widely attributed to the influence of the younger Mr. Assad. In the last year, Syrians have become more aware of Mr. Assad's kitchen cabinet of advisers, which includes Western-educated economists, young entrepreneurs from some of the traditional Damascus elite families and newly rich scions of military figures.</p>
        <p>In Damascus, many businessmen and ordinary Syrians have told visitors that they know -- although they have not necessarily experienced it -- that Bashar Assad can be reached by phone or by fax with any problem anyone has with Syrian bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>He is perhaps best known, however, as Syria's only public advocate of computer literacy and the Internet. A group called the Computer Society, which he heads, offers free computer courses in a country where satellite television dishes are still outlawed and mobile telephones have just been permitted on a limited basis this year. With such restrictions, only the president's son could have promoted information technology.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Assad's success in developing an image as a modernizer, he has had also to cultivate a reputation as a tough political actor.</p>
        <p>Like his father, he comes from the Alawite sect, a small religious group that is regarded as heretical by many Sunni and Shiite Muslim clerics, and will rule a country that is predominantly Sunni Muslim. If he is to maintain his minority-led government, Mr. Assad will need the skills of his father to play one group of Syrians against another and instill fear in them.</p>
        <p>TRANSITION IN SYRIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
