<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Sammy Sosa? Yes for the Mets, No for the Yankees</title>
    <meta content="11ANDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sosa, Sammy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0DC163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Sammy Sosa? Yes for the Mets, No for the Yankees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses speculation that Chicago Cubs will trade Sammy Sosa to either New York Yankees or New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the middle of the Yankees-Mets interborough weekend, Sammy Sosa's name blew in from Chicago to intrude on conversations for at least a New York minute.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old right fielder, who hit 66 and 63 homers the last two seasons and has hit 19 so far this season, would prefer to finish his career in Chicago, but if he and the Cubs cannot get together on a multiyear contract for more than his current $10 million salary, he may be auctioned sooner or later to the highest bidder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the middle of the Yankees-Mets interborough weekend, Sammy Sosa's name blew in from Chicago to intrude on conversations for at least a New York minute.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old right fielder, who hit 66 and 63 homers the last two seasons and has hit 19 so far this season, would prefer to finish his career in Chicago, but if he and the Cubs cannot get together on a multiyear contract for more than his current $10 million salary, he may be auctioned sooner or later to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>That highest bidder could be the Mets; it probably would not be the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Neither New York club would comment officially yesterday on Sosa's possible availability, to avert any tampering complaints, but Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, said the idea of a big deal before the July 31 trade deadline did not scare his team's front office.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to get in on everything and find out what the price is,'' Phillips said, sitting in the Mets' dugout before yesterday's game at Yankee Stadium. ''If we want to make a big deal, I'm confident we could make it.''</p>
        <p>Phillips acknowledged the ''uncertainty'' in the Mets' outfield, which Sosa's presence would surely ease. Sosa would also give the Mets another power hitter in the middle of their batting order, either in front of or behind their cleanup hitter, Mike Piazza.</p>
        <p>During their desperate quest in recent years for a National League pennant and a real subway series with the Yankees, the Mets' owners have been willing to pay top dollar for a top performer, as they have for Piazza, Robin Ventura, Al Leiter and Mike Hampton.</p>
        <p>The Mets, again in second place in the National League East behind the Atlanta Braves, need Sosa much more than the Yankees do in their duel with the Boston Red Sox for first place in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Aware of Sosa's recent headlines in Chicago over his next contract and his edgy relationship with Don Baylor, the Cubs' new manager, George Steinbrenner has asked some of his advisers whether Sosa would be worth the Cubs' stiff price and another $10 million to the Yankees' payroll.</p>
        <p>At least one of Steinbrenner's confidants has suggested that Sosa is not what the Yankees need because he strikes out too often. With both David Cone and Roger Clemens struggling, the Yankees' primary need is a premier pitcher, not a slugger who swings and misses unless he hits a homer.</p>
        <p>As the most popular Cub since Ernie Banks, Sosa has often said that he wants to be a ''Cub for life, like Ernie was,'' even if that Hall of Fame slugger never played in a World Series. The Cubs have not been in a World Series since 1945; they have not won a World Series since 1908.</p>
        <p>Sosa also wants to know why the Cubs, who are always rebuilding, don't seem to want to rebuild around him and his big bat.</p>
        <p>Chicago cynics contend that executives of The Tribune Company, which owns the Cubs, have fostered the Sosa controversies over his next contract and his relationship with Baylor to grease the skids to his eventual departure. His contract expires after the 2001 season.</p>
        <p>Baylor apparently annoyed Sosa with a spring training comment that the right fielder had deficiencies defensively. That assessment is true, as any major league scout would tell you, but that line did not endear the new manager to the slugger who is cherished as this era's Mr. Cub.</p>
        <p>Sosa has also mentioned that if the Cubs are smart, they will sign him to a contract extension before Alex Rodriguez, the Seattle Mariners' shortstop, goes on the free-agent market after the World Series. Rodriguez is expected to lift baseball's top market price to at least $20 million a season.</p>
        <p>But since the free-agent era began, teams that have waited to sign their premier players have almost always paid many more millions than they would have if they had signed that player before he went on the market.</p>
        <p>Then again, that could be the very reason the Cubs are apparently not willing to sign Sosa now. The longer the Cubs wait, the more they can argue that they just can't afford Sosa's price, whatever it might be.</p>
        <p>After all, even with Sosa, the Cubs, with a 25-36 record before yesterday's game with the White Sox, are on another treadmill to oblivion, in fourth place in the N.L. Central. They wouldn't be much worse without him.</p>
        <p>So for all his home runs, for all his kisses to the Wrigley Field fans, Sammy Sosa might be changing uniforms. If that happens before the July 31 deadline, look for the Mets to explore whatever it would take to put him in right field at Shea Stadium. And maybe even get him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
