<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; House Democrats Have Money Edge on G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="11DONA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Election Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DF163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; House Democrats Have Money Edge on G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Election Commission data for 15 months ending March 31 show that Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee raised $15,082,503 in soft money and National Republican Congressional Committee raised $9,818,178; show that Democrats raised $9,308,266 in hard money and Republicans $8,449,372 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democrats have a financial advantage in the contest for control of the House of Representatives. That's right, Democrats.</p>
        <p>Ever since Republicans took control of the House in 1994, they have out-raised the Democrats. Contributors pay for access and influence, and they would much rather get to members of the majority party, especially subcommittee and committee leaders. When the Republicans took over those posts in 1995, business and trade groups no longer needed to give to Democrats, and Republican fund-raising soared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Democrats have a financial advantage in the contest for control of the House of Representatives. That's right, Democrats.</p>
        <p>Ever since Republicans took control of the House in 1994, they have out-raised the Democrats. Contributors pay for access and influence, and they would much rather get to members of the majority party, especially subcommittee and committee leaders. When the Republicans took over those posts in 1995, business and trade groups no longer needed to give to Democrats, and Republican fund-raising soared.</p>
        <p>Another piece of the Republican advantage was a more effective fund-raising operation, maintaining a base of small donors who were reliable.</p>
        <p>This year, neither factor seems to matter very much, as Democrats have greatly improved fund-raising efforts and contributors hedge their bets. They know it will take a net gain of only six Democratic seats to install Democrats in House positions of power, so they are giving to both sides.</p>
        <p>This week when the Federal Election Commission released data for the 15 months that ended March 31, it showed that the House Democratic campaign committee had substantially more money in the bank than did its Republican counterpart.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee reported $15,082,503 in soft money, the unregulated contributions from business, labor and rich people that these days are chiefly used for television advertisements attacking the other party's candidates. The National Republican Congressional Committee had $9,818,178.</p>
        <p>When it came to hard money, the regulated contributions from individuals and political action committees, Democrats held a narrower advantage. They had $9,308,266 in the bank, while Republicans had $8,449,372.</p>
        <p>Democrats held another advantage, although it is not so obvious, in the fund-raising of individual House candidates in crucial races.</p>
        <p>The Federal Election Commission report said that the median receipts of Republicans in open seats -- those most likely to change hands because no one has the advantage of incumbency -- were $165,775. For Democrats, the figure was only $75,820.</p>
        <p>But those figures were misleading. They include more than one candidate in places like Houston, where the contest for the seat of retiring Representative Bill Archer drew a big, well-heeled Republican field, six of whom raised more than $195,000, and one forlorn Democrat with no chance of being elected and a fund-raising total of $7,911.</p>
        <p>When The New York Times examined 24 districts widely believed to be winnable by either party, comparing only one candidate from each party (the nominee or, if none had been chosen, the leading fund-raiser), the advantage was with the Democrats. Their median receipt was $655,849, compared with $539,893 for the Republicans. And the Democratic candidates reported median cash on hand of $433,892, while the Republicans showed $325,907.</p>
        <p>When the focus was narrowed to the 11 open seats on that list of two dozen, the Democratic cash advantage grew. The Democrats' bank accounts held a median total of $395,911 to $237,067 for the Republicans'.</p>
        <p>None of this means that the Democrats are going to take control of the House. But it means that one traditional Republican advantage is gone.</p>
        <p>The spokesmen for the two campaign committees were oddly in sync in their comments. John Del Cecato of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee said the numbers showed that ''there will not be a single Democrat who loses a House race this year due to a lack of funds.''</p>
        <p>On the Republican side, Jim Wilkinson said that in ''any race in America that matters, both sides, the Democrats and the Republicans, are going to have all the money they ever want.''</p>
        <p>At the end of a redistricting cycle of 10 years, only a small number of seats are really in play. The weak incumbents have already either lost or retired. So that means the parties -- and outside groups like labor and  business -- can concentrate their attention, and their money.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Wilkinson said, ''We're going to have 20 to 30 mini-New Hampshires.'' In those contested House districts, he said, ''Your phones are going to be ringing, your mailbox is going to be stuffed, your TV will have constant commercials, and strangers are going to be knocking on your door.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
