<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hanover</title>
    <meta content="HANO.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HANOVER (GERMANY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, ROGER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Hanover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D6163FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hanover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COHEN, ROGER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column describes upcoming events, sightseeing, lodging and eateries in Hanover, Germany; photos; chart; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not even a $3 billion investment can transform this modest town 80 miles south of Hamburg into a thing of beauty. Its royal court migrated to London in the early 19th century; its heart was later bombed away during World War II.</p>
        <p>Hanover is a shadow of its former self, and like many German cities, functional and unobtrusive. But it has its idyllic corners: Herrenhauser Park, the Eilenriede forest, which encircles the city, and its 1.5-mile-long man-made lake, the Maschsee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not even a $3 billion investment can transform this modest town 80 miles south of Hamburg into a thing of beauty. Its royal court migrated to London in the early 19th century; its heart was later bombed away during World War II.</p>
        <p>Hanover is a shadow of its former self, and like many German cities, functional and unobtrusive. But it has its idyllic corners: Herrenhauser Park, the Eilenriede forest, which encircles the city, and its 1.5-mile-long man-made lake, the Maschsee.</p>
        <p>The money invested in preparations for Expo 2000, which began here June 1 and runs through Oct. 31, has produced a sprawling array of sometimes spectacular exhibits -- pavilions of cardboard, amphi theaters of cork -- to complement enduring attractions that include fine museums, exquisite gardens and a varied cuisine.</p>
        <p>The very notion of a world's fair has been widely questioned at a time when the Internet has placed the globe at push-of-a-button distance; the United States has decided against building a national pavilion  on the grounds that Expo is not cost-effective. But more than 180 countries are present, many of them with ambitious projects illustrating Expo's theme -- ''Humankind-Nature-Technology: A New World Arising.''</p>
        <p>The focus of the fair is balance -- between growing populations and limited resources, between technology's possibilities and its dehumanizing effect, between dying skills and new demands -- and the responses  often ingenious. The architect Shigeru Ban has come up with a vast pavilion made almost entirely of recycled paper for Japan; the Dutch have placed dunes, forests, flower arrangements and lakes on top of each other in a 125-foot structure whose clear message is that space constraints may oblige us one day to superimpose landscapes; the Spanish have built an amphitheater-like pavilion of recyclable cork complete with an attractive tapas bar.</p>
        <p>Expo is open 9 a.m. to midnight every day, although pavilions close at 10 p.m. The 395-acre site is south of the city, on grounds that are an extension of the German Trade Fair. At 2.15 marks to the dollar, admission costs $23.50 to $32, or $92 for two adults and a child age 6 to 17. Multiday tickets are $29 a day.</p>
        <p>Expo is about 25 minutes by tram or train from the center of Hanover (about $1.50, or free for those showing Expo tickets), better choices than the usually clogged roads. More than 50 restaurants and snack bars are serving food from all parts of the world at Expo. Information and tickets are available by calling (49) 2000, or on the Web at www.expo2000.de.</p>
        <p>There is nothing at the Expo of transforming ambition: no Eiffel Tower, no Crystal Palace. But as a cable car carries visitors over the vast site on the outskirts of Hanover, the lengths to which Germany has gone to provide an attractive, accessible setting for a varied millennial celebration become clear.</p>
        <p>''This should be a party, a feast, a place to bring people together,'' said Wiebke Bruhns, an Expo official. What Germany wants is to dispel, or at least dim, the dark images of the 20th century and replace them with something lighter, even festive.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The Sprengel Museum has one of the finest collections of 20th-century German art, including works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Lyonel Feininger, George Grosz, Kurt Schwitters and Max Beckmann. Coinciding with Expo, an intriguing exhibition, ''How You Look at It,'' juxtaposes photographs and paintings of various periods to illustrate their influence on one another. Among the photographers featured are Walker Evans, Robert Frank, Brassai, Robert Adams and Diane Arbus; among the painters, Francis Bacon, Edward Hopper, Mark Rothko and Rene Magritte. The exhibition runs through Aug. 6 at the museum, on Kurt-Schwitters-Platz. Admission is $5.55 and the museum is open 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; (49-511) 1684-3875.</p>
        <p>Darkness in all its forms will be celebrated at Expo on the shortest night of the year, June 21. Various orchestras and artists have been invited to perform in an eclectic concert, among them Marianne Faithfull; Amina Alaoui, a Moroccan singer; and the Malmo Symphony Orchestra playing Wagner, Stravinsky and other composers. Hildegard Behrens is one of the soloists. The styles may be diverse, and possibly discordant, but a lively night is promised at what is billed as ''The Night of Night.'' Curtain time is 7:30 p.m. at the Konzerthaus, Expo 2000 grounds, Hall 25, Thurnithstrasse 2. Tickets: $32 to $50 from (49) 2000.</p>
        <p>The Berlin Philarmonic Orchestra is invariably rated among the best in the world, its reputation based on the unusual combination of passion and precision that has long characterized the orchestra of Furtwangler, von Karajan and now Abbado. The orchestra comes to Expo on June 28 to perform Messiaen's ''Turangalila'' symphony under the direction of Kent Nagano. Curtain at 7:30 p.m., Konzerthaus, Expo 2000 grounds, Hall 25, Thurnithstrasse 2. Tickets: $32 to $50, (49-511) 02000.</p>
        <p>The Kestner Gesellschaft, or Society, (not the better-known Kestner Museum) is commemorating Expo with ''Picasso -- The Embrace.'' It will feature works by Picasso that dwell on various forms of physical intertwining -- passionate, brotherly, maternal, obsessive, insatiable, tender, protective, possessive. The exhibition covers the full span of the artist's career. From Aug. 29 to Oct. 31 at the Kestner Gesellschaft, Gose riede 11; (49-511) 701-200. Open Tuesday to Sunday, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m., Thursday until 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>The Staatsoper of Hanover, in a handsome 19th-century building, has commissioned an opera by Volker David Kirchner. Called ''Gilgamesh,'' it recounts the agonizing quest for eternal life by the Babylonian ruler of the same name. The premiere is June 18 at 7:30 p.m. at the Staatsoper, Opernplatz 1; (49-511) 9999-1111. Tickets $10.70 to $35. Subsequent performances July 7, 20 and 22 and Sept. 8, 10, 13 and 15.</p>
        <p>An unabridged 22-hour performance of Goethe's ''Faust'' (both parts) will be presented for the first time. The performances, with Bruno Ganz as Faust, take place over weekends at Expo, from 3 to 10 p.m. on Saturdays, and 10 a.m. Sunday to 1 a.m. Monday. Tickets are sold out, but enthusiasts may be able to obtain them at the door, at Hall 23; (49) 2000, fax (49-511) 840-4100. Performances July 22 and 23; Aug. 5 and 6, 19 and 20, 26 and 27; and Sept. 2 and 3, 9 and 10, and 16 and 17.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Visitors to Hanover are greeted outside the main train station by the Rote Faden, a red line that directs them on a roughly two-hour walking tour of the old city. The sites include the brick, neo-Gothic Marktkirche, or market church, with glass windows dating from the 14th century. Although 90 percent of the city was destroyed during World War II, several impressive half-timbered buildings from the late 19th century can be seen on the tour.</p>
        <p>The Herrenhauser Gardens were laid out in the 17th century by the enlightened Princess Sophia, who frequently invited Handel to the court at Hanover to give concerts. The four gardens, linked by an avenue of lime trees, amount to an idyllic retreat. The oldest part is adorned with Roman gods and allegorical figures, bordered by clipped hedges and graced with ornamental ponds. A central fountain sends a plume of water 270 feet into the air. Dance, music and arts festivals are held throughout the summer in the gardens, at Herrenhauserstrasse 4; (49-511) 1684-7576. Admission $2.30.</p>
        <p>Like many northern German towns, Hanover has a lake in the midst of it, the Maschsee, in the 22-acre Maschpark. This is a delightful place for a stroll, and small boats may be rented.</p>
        <p>Near the park is a moving war memorial, the St. Aegidienkirche, a church built in 1160 and destroyed by Allied bombing on Oct. 9, 1943. It stands roofless, with ivy twisting up its exposed walls. A peace bell presented by the City of Hiroshima is displayed. The reality of German suffering from the war, often unspoken because the Holocaust overshadows it, becomes apparent in such places.</p>
        <p>Two installations on the Expo grounds take visitors underground to mystery destinations. Gabriel Orozco has installed a Wheel of Fortune, a big wheel whose central axis is at ground level. So half the ride is above ground, the other half below.</p>
        <p>In a similar vein, an Austrian group called Gelatin has built the Eighth Wonder of the World, a hole filled with water into which people are invited to dive to discover, at a depth of just over 11 feet, the wonder in question. Even the organizers of Expo say they do not know what it is; the artists are silent. The message is clear enough: no risk, no gain.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Luxury: Hanover has no five-star hotels, but Forum Hotel Schweizerhof, Hinuberstrasse 6, (49-511) 34950, fax (49-511) 349-5102, is about as close as it comes. A very comfortable establishment near the railway station, it has 200 airy, modern rooms. A double costs about $185 (but expect hotel prices to rise during Expo).</p>
        <p>Maritim Grand Hotel, Friedrichswall 11, (49-511) 36770, fax (49-511) 325-195, does not have a great deal of charm but offers every facility and 285 modern, spacious rooms. Doubles start at $125.</p>
        <p>The 45-room Thuringer Hof Hotel, in the old city at Osterstrasse 37, is family run, cozy and charming. Doubles are about $140; (49-511) 36060, fax (49-511) 360-6277.</p>
        <p>Budget: The Mercure Hotel, Willy-Brandt Allee 3, (49-511) 80080, fax (49-511) 809-3704, is in a fine location, near the Maschpark. It has 145 modern if smallish rooms, with doubles from $110.</p>
        <p>A half-mile from the Expo grounds is the Copthorne Hotel, Wurzburgerstrasse 21, 30880 Laatzen; (49-511) 30880. Prices at this pleasant hotel, with 22 modern and spacious rooms, start at $99, including breakfast, on weekends.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Basil, Dragonerstrasse 30A, (49-511) 622-636, is an airy establishment with a delightful garden much frequented in an earlier life by Hanover's most famous son, Chancellor Gerhard Schroder. The menu offers fusion cooking with an accent on fish.  Try the sea bream in a lime sauce with spring onions, or the spinach-stuffed trout on a bed of mashed potatoes. Dinner for two, with a moderate wine, about $90.</p>
        <p>The Clichy, Weisserkreuzstrasse 31, (49-511) 312-447, serves some of the best French cuisine in the city in intimate and romantic surroundings. Wonderfully fresh shrimp with avocado is a starter; excellent sauteed lamb is served with green beans. The wine list is first rate and fairly priced. Dinner for two, with wine, about $115.</p>
        <p>A good place for lunch is Patio, Am Markt 14, (49-511) 300-8040, under a glass ceiling in the old city hall. A broad international selection ranges from Thai salads to ciabattas. Meal for two with wine, about $50.</p>
        <p>The German asparagus season is in full swing until late June, and a good place to sample some of the many delicious preparations is Die Insel, Rudolf-von-Beningsen-Ufer 81; (49-511) 831-214. You can't go wrong with asparagus with hollandaise sauce, boiled potatoes and a Wiener schnitzel. The sole is also recommended, as is the romantic setting on the Maschsee. Meal for two with wine, about $70.</p>
        <p>For a typical German dining experience, try Steinor-Quelle, Schmiedestrasse 39, (59-511) 363-1463. This is a lively place, with lots of local color, perfect for a bratwurst and beer, roast pork or other filling German meals. Dinner for two, with beer, about $25.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN ROGER COHEN is chief of the Berlin bureau of The Times.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 2, 2000, Sunday  The What's Doing column on June 11, about Hanover, Germany, misstated the date the royal court of Hanover moved to London. It was in 1714, not in the early 19th century, that King George I ascended to the English throne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The What's Doing column on June 11, about Hanover, Germany, misstated the date the royal court of Hanover moved to London. It was in 1714, not in the early 19th century, that King George I ascended to the English throne.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ROGER COHEN is chief of the Berlin bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
