<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Chicago, From Printing Plant to Technology Hub</title>
    <meta content="11AFOC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Donnelly, R R, &amp; Sons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lakeside Press</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlyle Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Core Location (Co)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DB123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Chicago, From Printing Plant to Technology Hub</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL SCHACHNER CHANEN</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Landmark R R Donnelly &amp; Sons Calumet Plant in Chicago, which once was Lakeside Press printing complex, is being concerted into mammoth 'carrier hotel' for multiple telecommunications and Internet companies; Carlyle Group is developing property in joint venture with Core Location; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LANDMARK building that once housed the country's largest commercial printing facility is now being converted into a mammoth ''carrier hotel'' housing multiple telecommunications and Internet companies.</p>
        <p>When renovation of the onetime R. R. Donnelly &amp; Sons Calumet Plant into the Lakeside Technology Center is completed this fall, it will hold what the developers say is the country's largest planned carrier hotel. It will offer more than 1.1 million square feet of space devoted to the technical needs of telecommunications providers and Internet companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LANDMARK building that once housed the country's largest commercial printing facility is now being converted into a mammoth ''carrier hotel'' housing multiple telecommunications and Internet companies.</p>
        <p>When renovation of the onetime R. R. Donnelly &amp; Sons Calumet Plant into the Lakeside Technology Center is completed this fall, it will hold what the developers say is the country's largest planned carrier hotel. It will offer more than 1.1 million square feet of space devoted to the technical needs of telecommunications providers and Internet companies.</p>
        <p>The eight-story, English Gothic-style Calumet Plant has been a fixture on Chicago's lakefront since it was built in the early 20th century as part of the historic Lakeside Press printing complex that was once owned by R. R. Donnelly. Publications including Life magazine, Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company's Big Book catalog and the Yellow Pages were printed in the complex before operations there ceased in 1993.</p>
        <p>Donnelly relocated its corporate headquarters from the complex to downtown Chicago in 1992 following the city's condemnation of part of the complex to expand the McCormick Place convention center. The company also moved most of its remaining printing work to other of its printing facilities throughout Illinois.</p>
        <p>Developers of the Lakeside Technology Center say that the market for these kinds of facilities is strong.</p>
        <p>''We felt that this was a relatively underserved market in general and in Chicago specifically,'' said Robert Stuckey, managing director of the Carlyle Group in Washington, which is developing the property in a joint venture with Core Location of Bethesda, Md. ''We felt that Chicago is a tier-one telecommunications hub, along with New York, San Francisco and Los Angeles, and that there was pent-up demand here that was not being served.''</p>
        <p>The onetime Lakeside Press complex, he said, ''had certain physical and technological features that set it apart from others.''</p>
        <p>Carrier hotels have unusual operational requirements, including multiple power sources, numerous ventilation outlets and floors capable of bearing heavy loads. Tenants of these facilities need to have self-contained heating, cooling and ventilation systems as well as extraordinary amounts of electric power and individualized security systems, said David B. Larson, a senior project architect for McClier Construction in Chicago, which reconstructing the building.</p>
        <p>Because the Calumet Plant was built as  an industrial facility, the building was ripe for transformation. It offered 14-foot ceiling heights, floors capable of bearing 250 pounds per square foot and approximately 30 existing shafts to allow McClier to adapt them as vertical risers for chilled water, electric wiring and exhaust, Mr. Larson said.</p>
        <p>More important, the plant is just blocks away from the North American fiber-optic long-haul route, a major transcontinental fiber-optic cable route. The proximity will allow the building's tenants easy access to the fiber optic infrastructure that they need to run their businesses, said Michael Jacoby, president of Core Location, a developer of carrier hotels, data centers and other high-tech buildings.</p>
        <p>The developers say that the renovation of this fabled building into the largest carrier hotel in the country is somewhat ironic, given that it was built as the largest producer of a different kind of communications. Built in four stages between 1912 and 1929, the Calumet Plant -- named for its location at the intersection of Calumet Avenue and 22nd Street on the South Side of Chicago along the Illinois Central Railroad tracks that follow the Lake Michigan shoreline -- doubled Donnelly's printing capacity. It also contained Donnelly's executive offices, an art gallery and a library.</p>
        <p>The developers plan to restore the building's Gothic-style executive offices and library and will allow tenants to use them for meetings. Some 600 printers' marks, decorative stone shields depicting printers' tools that once decorated the facade of the building over the main entrance, will also be restored, Mr. Jacoby said.</p>
        <p>THE Calumet Plant remained an active printing press plant for Donnelly until 1993, when Sears discontinued production of its Big Book catalog and company executives decided that operating the plant, which was spread over eight floors, was no longer economically feasible.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Donnelly sold the rest of the Lakeside Press complex, which included the Calumet Plant, to Landmark America, a Portland, Me., development company. The company originally planned to develop the property into a mixed-use development, though construction has not begun on any of the buildings.</p>
        <p>Landmark America sold the Calumet Plant to Core Location and the Carlyle Group last year for an undisclosed sum.</p>
        <p>Chicago officials, who once worried about the vacant Lakeside Press buildings, are applauding the transformation of the Calumet Plant because it has helped propel an ambitious plan by Mayor Richard M. Daley to position the city as a leader in technology. To spur that growth, the city provided the building's developers with a $3 million energy grant to help subsidize the costs of construction. An additional $1 million in tax abatements was given to the building's anchor tenant, Global Center of San Jose, Calif., a Web-hosting Internet services company. as an incentive to cement the deal, said Jimm Dispensa, assistant commissioner of the technology development unit of the city's Department of Planning and Development.</p>
        <p>Stephen Johnson, vice president of design and construction for Global Center, a unit of Global Crossing, a fiber optic network, said that the tax-increment funds had little to do with the company's decision to lease space in the carrier hotel, however. The company, which leased the center's 135,000-square-foot third floor, had been looking for a carrier hotel to house its operations in Chicago for some time. ''We have studies that tell us what particular arenas in the world we should be in,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''Chicago rated high in terms of what we could get for a customer base and for its proximity to fiber.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson said Global Center would like to double the amount of space it leased in the carrier hotel but would be unable to because the 1.1 million-square-foot building was already 75 percent leased. Rentals in the building range from $26 to $40 a square foot.</p>
        <p>Other tenants include 360networks, a fiber-optic network, and Qwest Communications and Level 3 Communications, both  telecommunications companies, according to Mr. Jacoby.</p>
        <p>David Love, senior vice president of network operations for the Vancouver-based 360networks, said that his company decided to lease space in the building because of its proximity to its own cable network. The company said that it would use its space to  drop off its voice and data traffic and pick up other traffic.</p>
        <p>''The fact that a number of other carriers like us are in the building'' was a plus, Mr. Love said. ''It makes it so easy to share traffic with them,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Even though the developers' research had shown a need for this kind of space in Chicago, they say they were being taken by surprise by the demand for the space. ''We thought it would take three years to lease this much space,'' Mr. Stuckey said. ''It looks like it will lease up in one year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
