<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Ossining, Where No Garlic Is Spared</title>
    <meta content="11DINE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guida's (Ossining, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D9123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Ossining, Where No Garlic Is Spared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>OSSINING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Guida's restaurant in Ossining, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the upper end of an attractive stretch of Ossining's reclaimed storefronts, Guida's stands across the road from those dual bastions of a stable community, a bank and a church. Above the Corinthian pilasters of the sturdy bank building is inscribed with much gravitas the ''Bank for Savings.''</p>
        <p>In its shadow, Guida's might, with some confidence, proclaim itself the ''Restaurant for Eating,'' as its appeal is likewise based on values of the past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the upper end of an attractive stretch of Ossining's reclaimed storefronts, Guida's stands across the road from those dual bastions of a stable community, a bank and a church. Above the Corinthian pilasters of the sturdy bank building is inscribed with much gravitas the ''Bank for Savings.''</p>
        <p>In its shadow, Guida's might, with some confidence, proclaim itself the ''Restaurant for Eating,'' as its appeal is likewise based on values of the past.</p>
        <p>For the last 10 years, this restaurant has been serving the surrounding community with warmth and graciousness.</p>
        <p>Recent visits found the pretty dining room on the street level as fresh and glowing as it was when the place first opened, and service, attentive and genial. Although it still has some fresh sparks, only the kitchen showed fatigue with the years. To our pleasure, however, it remembered to employ, with a liberal hand, whole roasted cloves of garlic, which were soft, sweet and delicious. Try to cajole a few cloves to mash in olive oil. A slathering would have greatly improved slices of insipid bread.</p>
        <p>Of the winning openers, a plate of clams posillipo with chunky tomato sauce was lifted to splendor by the seepage of clam liquor and all that good garlic the kitchen tosses into many of its dishes. And shaved asparagus wrapped with ham (prosciutto on the menu but the ham was fine) and a bit of melted cheese made a satisfying combination. Oysters oreganata, however, seemed stale and should not have been served.</p>
        <p>Pasta received careful timing, but dishes were haphazardly composed. But for its intense brininess, linguine with white clam sauce would have been the best of the pasta offerings. While those roasted cloves of garlic were divine, we wished for less olive oil and more of the broccoli promised with our bowl of cavatelli. And it was a pity that overcooked shrimps and scallops detracted from a dish of tasty squid-ink linguine alla pescatore and that the crabmeat and creamy tomato sauce that came with fettuccini Amalfitano was pulverized into mush.</p>
        <p>Entrees fared better. Most dining spots bypass whole chicken and cut up boneless breast meat for chicken scarpariello. But here there was no problem when we requested dark as well as white meat on the bone. A plate came piled with juicy parts, all glistening with lemon and garlic sauce: a leg and a thigh or two, wings and a chunk of breast.</p>
        <p>A bit of spicy heat picked up a few of Guida's offerings. Big rings, lots of tentacles and a fiery marinara sauce enlivened calamari fra diavolo. And on one evening, four excellent lamb chops, which would have been delightful simply seared, came arrabbiata style; the addition of hot peppers was unusual, but it worked.</p>
        <p>Meaty quail, another evening's special, was roasted to succulence; it deserved better than sticky garlic sauce. That sauce also seemed to gloss six shrimps scampi, a dish acceptable without being special.</p>
        <p>A choice of broccoli or escarole -- lots of those garlic cloves in both -- was available for side dishes. Pasta with lovely marinara sauce was another possibility.</p>
        <p>The dessert cart might have been provided by central casting. We have recently seen the creamy offerings, with slight variation, roll past at a number of Italian restaurants. Poached pear with vanilla ice cream made a safe choice. Cheesecake was once smooth and creamy, New York style, and once (ricotta) dry and chalky.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $33 without drinks, tax and tip. Guida's is just west of Route 9.</p>
        <p>Guida's  199 Main Street, Ossining.  941-2662</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Beyond the bar at the entrance, mirrors widen the narrow but lovely, intimate first floor dining room bathed in a rosy glow from sconces, candlelight and peachy walls, one lined with a banquette. The second floor dining room is gloomy and stuffy. Attentive, prompt service.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- At the bar.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Special asparagus with ham and melted cheese, clams posillipo, chicken scarpariello, lamb chops arrabbiata, quail, calamari fra diavolo.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Salad or pasta included. Lunch, main dishes, $11 to $14. Dinner, main dishes, $15 to $25.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch, Mondays through Saturdays, 11:30 A.M. to 3 P.M. Dinner, Mondays through Thursdays, 3 to 10 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 4 to 11 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 10 P.M.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street-level entrance; restrooms on second floor.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
