<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hip-Hop Meets Its Match</title>
    <meta content="11RADI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WQHT-FM (Radio Station) (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Star (Troi Torain)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buck Wild (Timothy Joseph)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Century, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6DE1E3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hip-Hop Meets Its Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS CENTURY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Century, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Star and Buck Wild Morning Show on WQHT-FM, New York's leading rap station, startles black audience with its lancing of sacred cows, from basketball players to 'hip hop' royalty; half-brothers Star (Troi Torain) and Buck (Timothy Joseph) were inspired by Howard Stern (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a drizzly morning late last month, just after 6 a.m., the radio waves crackled with scorn as Star and Buc Wild broadcast from the West Village studios of WQHT-FM, Hot 97. ''Sounds of venom!'' Star hissed, dressed in a carefully angled cream Kangol cap, rocking back and forth on his pumpkin-colored Timberland boots.</p>
        <p>''Spitting fire!'' added Buc Wild, who sat sleepy-eyed in a billowing black T-shirt, his hair springing up through his headphones like an electrified mop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a drizzly morning late last month, just after 6 a.m., the radio waves crackled with scorn as Star and Buc Wild broadcast from the West Village studios of WQHT-FM, Hot 97. ''Sounds of venom!'' Star hissed, dressed in a carefully angled cream Kangol cap, rocking back and forth on his pumpkin-colored Timberland boots.</p>
        <p>''Spitting fire!'' added Buc Wild, who sat sleepy-eyed in a billowing black T-shirt, his hair springing up through his headphones like an electrified mop.</p>
        <p>''I got venom in my heart because the Knicks are going down, folks,'' Star said, adding with a laugh, ''Oh yes you are.'' With the entire city gripped by orange-toweled Knicks playoff fever, Star and Buc Wild, the hosts of Hot 97's morning drive-time show, were heaping abuse on the hometown heroes. The previous night, in the opening game of the Eastern Conference finals, the Knicks had been drubbed by the Indiana Pacers, and now Star and Buc Wild could scarcely contain their contumely.</p>
        <p>''Can we get a thugged-out white boy on the New York Knicks?'' demanded Star with a mischievous grin. ''These Knick fans got me upset. I'm hyped. I'm riled up. A thugged-out white boy named Austin Croshere from Indiana ran circles around those bums last night. We need a thugged-out white boy on New York and then maybe, maybe, I'll become a Knick fan.''</p>
        <p>As a radio duo, Star and Buc Wild are fast becoming the most controversial figures in hip-hop. Since their show, ''The Star and Buc Wild Morning Show,'' began in March on New York's leading rap station, each weekday morning from 6 to 10, they hurl insults at athletes, movie stars and revered members of hip-hop royalty. Their style can be raunchy, tasteless and sometimes -- against one's better judgment -- sidesplittingly funny.</p>
        <p>While the pair might seem like just the latest members of radio's long-running school of shock jocks, the difference is that black-oriented radio has rarely seen this kind of lancing of sacred cows. Star and Buc Wild have landed in a music scene that, for all its seeming iconoclasm, is rife with boosterism and a fawning regard for celebrity. ''I'm not trying to be their buddy or their pal,'' Star said of the music-industry heavyweights he often lampoons, including Foxy Brown, Mariah Carey and Russell Simmons. ''That's why I can bring the fire the way I do.''</p>
        <p>Even Lauryn Hill, hip-hop's much loved philosopher-queen, has been a target. Introducing one of her hit songs recently, Star said with a cackle, ''Here she is, the woman who's running around with two kids out of wedlock and still has the nerve to get up on stage quoting Scriptures from the Bible -- Lauryn Hill.''</p>
        <p>Bill Adler, a longtime music journalist and author of a biography of Run-DMC, said: ''Star has definitely distinguished himself as a contrarian. A lot of what he's saying is quite brave. There ought to be more unfettered criticism of the big figures in hip-hop, and there's far too little of it right now.'' At the same time, Mr. Adler faults Star for often being sophomoric. ''I suppose the same can be said about Howard Stern,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That's an influence that Star -- who was born Troi Torain in Scotch Plains, N.J., and moved to Brooklyn when he was 18 -- happily acknowledges. ''I've always listened to Howard Stern,'' he said. ''I'm a big, big Stern supporter. In fact, I called up Gary Dell'Abate, Howard's producer, the first 30 days we were on the air, just to say, 'Hey we're just giving props to the King of All Media -- let Howard know we're not trying to rip off his style, but we are heavily influenced by him.' ''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Stern, whose own syndicated talk show on WXRK-FM continues to dominate the morning drive-time competition in Arbitron ratings, Star and Buc Wild have quickly polarized their radio audience. ''Their show is stupid, redundant, and most people definitely can't stand them,'' said Heide Alaia, a broadcasting student at New York University. ''There's no substance to what they do. All they do is player-hate, and they're just using it as a commercial ploy. To tell you the truth, they make me crazy.''</p>
        <p>The volume of reaction, both pro and con, has surprised the management of Hot 97, where the early morning show was led for several years by the more genial team of Ed Lover, Dr. Dre and Lisa G. ''Morning drive is the most competitive slot of the day,'' Tracy Cloherty, Hot 97's programming director, said. ''You're competing against 1010 WINS and Howard Stern and people watching 'Good Morning America.' Plus the younger audience, which is our core listening group, tends not to listen to the radio much in the morning. But for Star and Buc Wild, being on the air less than two months, the recognition is astonishing. We've never seen anything like it. The listeners might not like them, but they definitely know who they are.''</p>
        <p>The show regularly plays critical voice-mail messages left by listeners, many of which have to be bleeped clean of profanities. In the last few weeks, the show has managed to anger leading rappers like Foxy Brown, Method Man and his entire Wu-Tang Clan, incidents that Star and Buc Wild delightfully dissect on the air.</p>
        <p>''In the beginning, we called ourselves the Universal Player Haters,'' Star said, slipping off his headphones. ''Player haters are people who hate the players because they are not players themselves. But once you have achieved a certain level of success, and you've become a player yourself, you can no longer player-hate; you can only hate.''</p>
        <p>Buc Wild, nodding, added: ''We're the wrong teen idols. We're not role models, we're professional back-stabbers.''</p>
        <p>Some of this is obviously shtick, as Mr. Simmons, one of the most powerful figures in rap and an occasional Star and Buc Wild target, recognizes. In a recent on-air rant, the hosts accused Mr. Simmons, who runs Def Jam Records and Phat Farm clothing, of promoting a hip-hop Web site at the expense of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. It must have been a first -- radio personalities on New York's leading urban station sticking up for Mr. Giuliani at the expense of Russell Simmons. Several of Mr. Simmons's employees called the station to express concern.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Simmons, interviewed by cell phone later, took it in stride. ''That's their job,'' he said. ''They're professional haters.''</p>
        <p>As if to translate for the uninitiated, he added, ''In the ghetto when we say 'hate' it just means jealous talk and second-guessing.'' He said he found Star and Buc Wild entertaining. ''It's not exactly new -- the idea of second-guessing and making fun of everyone has been around for a long time -- but what's fresh and interesting about Star and Buc Wild is that they're funny and they have wit,'' he continued. ''Mind you, I don't know that every rap star is so open-minded.''</p>
        <p>Hip-hop has long been known for its ''diss'' records that heap insults on rival rappers, but journalists and radio personalities, with a few exceptions, have steered clear of controversy and confrontation.</p>
        <p>''There were artists dissing each other, sure, but there was no journalist who actually came forward and said, 'I don't like this,' or 'I don't like you,' and then told you where they laid their head at,'' said Star, who used to print his home address in a column he wrote in The Source, a hip-hop magazine.</p>
        <p>''I love the culture of hip-hop,'' he added, ''but there are a lot of things in it that I think are very ignorant, and I hate the state of hip-hop today.'' Currently high on the duo's target list, Star said, are ''studio gangsters -- young guys who come out of the gate with a hit single talking about flipping kilos, busting gunshots, chopping up bodies -- just delusional, fictional'' lyrics.</p>
        <p>''I mean, you got guys out here rapping about 'Do You Really Bust Your Guns?' '' Star said disgustedly. ''Is this what you want to tell kids? I'm not trying to take a stance on censorship, because everyone has a right to express themselves artistically, but when you live in the hood-slash-ghetto, there's certain things that you don't really want to hear.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons disagreed with the notion that Star and Buc Wild were alone in their critique of rap culture. ''The hip-hop press is as critical as any music media that we've ever had,'' he said. ''They're very critical of records and of artists' images and ideas. In the hip-hop community, not being hot is as big an event as being hot.''</p>
        <p>But clearly, no forum in hip-hop has pushed the envelope as far as Hot 97's hosts. Even a cursory listen will tell you that there are very few taboo targets on the morning show, which also includes a third personality, Miss Jones, who reports music industry gossip. A daily feature called Ghetto Network News finds bawdy humor in such topics as welfare mothers and crack addiction.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, there are those who find the act more obnoxious than sidesplitting. ''In order to do good radio, you shouldn't have to constantly malign people,'' said Marvet Britto, president of the Britto Agency, a public relations firm that represents African-American entertainers and athletes, including Foxy Brown. ''People love gossip, but there's a thin line between gossip and malicious slander.'' She said that the crucial difference between Star and Buc Wild's shock humor and Mr. Stern's is in the reaction of the audience.</p>
        <p>''The reason they can't be Howard Stern is that white folks take that stuff as being all a part of being a celebrity,'' Ms. Britto said. ''But black folks take that stuff to heart.''</p>
        <p>The hip-hop world has seen acts of violence reportedly committed by thin-skinned artists against black journalists, with the result that magazine editors say they are forced into self-censorship. In 1998, Jesse Washington, the editor of Blaze magazine, was badly beaten in his office by a group that he said included a disgruntled producer.</p>
        <p>Asked if he was worried about violent retaliations for his tirades, Star looked contemplative. ''You would have to be an idiot not to realize that an ignorant element is always lurking around the corner,'' he said. ''It's there, and that's why I pride myself on being consciously aware. But if that deters you, then I guess there's no real merit to what you're spitting.</p>
        <p>''We still do the street thing, out on Nostrand Avenue in Crown Heights, the same places we used to hang out, we're still there,'' he continued. ''And the artists know that. So if you've got issues, just come down there. We still hang out in strip clubs in our neighborhood. Same Kennedy Fried Chicken that we used to stand in front of, we still stand there now.''</p>
        <p>If Star seems to dominate both the on-air and off-air conversation, it may be because, until recently, Buc Wild was a figment of his imagination. In the mid-1990's Star wrote his Source column, Reality Check, using the pseudonym Buc Wild. ''When it really started popping, I said, 'Well, maybe I'm a little too old to try to look like I'm Buc Wild for the little girls,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>So Star, now 34, enlisted his half-brother, Timothy Joseph, 21, to play the Buc Wild role. Even today, Star is constantly teasing Mr. Joseph about being replaceable. ''I tell him, shape up, or I'll do you like Ozzie Osborne does his guitar players,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Hidden behind the bluster and crude insults, the show can have its softer, sentimental side. When the news came in last week that the Latin music great Tito Puente had died, ''The Howard Stern Show,'' down the radio dial, reported it irreverently. But on Hot 97, Star soberly dedicated the day's program to the memory of Mr. Puente, and he fielded calls from young Puerto Rican New Yorkers, who talked about how their parents and grandparents schooled them in the music of the Mambo King.</p>
        <p>Still, the show's dominant style is confrontational. Last week, in the heat of his spirited Knicks-bashing session, Star was all twitchy energy as he fielded calls from outraged fans. ''How long you been rooting for a losing squad, sir?'' he asked a caller from Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''We're not losers -- we're overachievers,'' the husky male voice on the line said. ''We never had the best talent in the N.B.A., but yet we've been in the playoffs, we've been in the finals.''</p>
        <p>''You were probably drinking Similac back when they won the championship,'' Star said.</p>
        <p>The next caller was less hostile, which left Star yawning and rolling his eyes across the table at Buc Wild and Miss Jones.</p>
        <p>''Yo, I thought you wanted to bring some fire to me -- I'm looking for a good brawl this morning, but you sound like you want to sit in my lap,'' Star said, ending the conversation with a click and a smile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
