<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kicking Back In the North Of Spain</title>
    <meta content="ASTUR.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HESSER, AMANDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6D6163FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kicking Back In the North Of Spain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HESSER, AMANDA</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amanda Hesser travel article on trip to Asturias and Cantabria regions of northern Spain; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS we traveled west from Bilbao along the northern coast of Spain, the landscape dulled. Behind us was the high drama of the Pyrenees, which we had skirted. Behind us were the elegant, well-ripened cities of San Sebastian and Bilbao. Before us lay, as far as we knew, a rural area of Spain with an ancient religious route leading to Santiago de Compostela and a climate like that of England, hardly the Spain of reputation.</p>
        <p>Of course, my friend and I were traveling on the A6, a major highway, zipping along so that what we were taking in was like frames of film, hardly enough to comprehend and consider. About two hours west of Bilbao, in the town of Torrelavega, something happened. The highway stopped. It was as if it had been sliced off at the end like sausage, diverting speeding cars onto a much smaller, much slower road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS we traveled west from Bilbao along the northern coast of Spain, the landscape dulled. Behind us was the high drama of the Pyrenees, which we had skirted. Behind us were the elegant, well-ripened cities of San Sebastian and Bilbao. Before us lay, as far as we knew, a rural area of Spain with an ancient religious route leading to Santiago de Compostela and a climate like that of England, hardly the Spain of reputation.</p>
        <p>Of course, my friend and I were traveling on the A6, a major highway, zipping along so that what we were taking in was like frames of film, hardly enough to comprehend and consider. About two hours west of Bilbao, in the town of Torrelavega, something happened. The highway stopped. It was as if it had been sliced off at the end like sausage, diverting speeding cars onto a much smaller, much slower road.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the highway ended right there, before we even got to Asturias, the region where we were headed for four days at the end of August. We swept through the seaside town of San Vicente de la Barquera, compressed into a sliver of an inlet.</p>
        <p>The road undulated between hills and the sea, offering us tempting glimpses. But dimming ones. It was getting dark and the roads were getting smaller, eventually narrowing to a single lane. We had booked a room in a bed-and-breakfast in a converted mill, which we had found on the Internet. And we wanted to get there.</p>
        <p>As we approached Tresgrandas, the town where our hotel was, we were in for another surprise. Tresgrandas was no town. It was barely a hamlet. And as we turned down the lane leading to our bed-and-breakfast, we were sure we had it all wrong. It was the kind of grade you find on a double black diamond ski slope, not a road, and it took us to what felt like the bottom of a well.</p>
        <p>But there was indeed a bed-and-breakfast and an enormous, friendly and slobbery mastiff to greet us. We settled in, had dinner and went to bed in our small rustic room. There were more surprises in the morning.</p>
        <p>Asturias is incongruous with much of the rest of Spain. It is green and damp and sprinkled with small farms. I sometimes felt that I was in Northern California, sometimes in England or Switzerland. The region has for the most part tried to avoid the sort of development that would change the landscape, and the visitors it draws are mostly Spaniards from the south and a few British tourists.</p>
        <p>In the area of Asturias and bits of Cantabria we were visiting, there were no great resorts to speak of, no architectural works of note by Gaudi, no wineries or great restaurants, and no well-known museums. Other than a little hiking in the national forest, we didn't have an agenda -- and as we discovered, we didn't need one.</p>
        <p>Our bed-and-breakfast was nestled in a valley of hills that rolled like the sea. A 10-minute drive north and the land dropped off into the ocean, much as it does in Dover, from high cliffs. A 10-minute drive south and we were in the bosom of the Picos de Europa, a mountain range that explodes from the earth like an iceberg on a calm sea. We could swim or go hiking or just take long drives down the narrow passages carved through the mountains. We did all three.</p>
        <p>In the morning, we woke to the cries of roosters and the rush of water. The roosters were out in the yard and the water ran right beneath the hotel, as it had when it was a flour mill.</p>
        <p>Breakfast was more than we could have wished for. The eggs were from the hens on the property, the cheese from the sheep, the jams, delicious reductions of fruits grown there in the valley. The owners, Luis Sanz and Carmen Garcia, raised the hens, made the cheese and jams (pumpkin and orange, berry and peach) and even the bunuelos, a kind of beignet, they served us. Each day the cheeses changed and so did the jams.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanz and Ms. Garcia moved to Tresgrandas to escape the pressures of city life in Madrid, where they were caterers. On their Internet site, they recount how they restored the 18th-century mill. We were charmed by it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanz and Ms. Garcia run their hotel with its handful of rooms well (just a few of the rooms were occupied when we were there, but weekends are booked through next February), though they come across more as idealists, determined to live close to the earth, than hosts. Mr. Sanz, whom we saw most often, has lots of information to share but you must work it out of him.</p>
        <p>That first day we took a drive, a drive that began as a morning excursion and lasted all day. We headed toward the Picos de Europa, intent on driving along the Desfiladero de La Hermida, a gorge cutting through the mountains near La Hermida. Getting there took us through village after village, each its own historical collage. New houses were latched to ruins, cars yielding to heifers and goats, old women in housedresses yelling after brightly dressed children.</p>
        <p>Before we reached the gorge, we stopped at the Hostal Covadonga, a hotel and restaurant in the center of Panes. The front porch was filled with men wearing berets and smoking cigars, their faces gray. I was the only woman there for lunch.</p>
        <p>We ordered beers and cocido, a stew of white beans, leeks, blood sausage and ham. It was as thick as mud, and unbelievably good. White cottony rolls were served to soak up the sauce. We sat out on the veranda and ate quietly, listening to the music of the place -- the church bells, the clapping of dominoes and the talk of men inside the restaurant. It was tempting to linger.</p>
        <p>Back on the road the hills rose and fell, then suddenly soared vertically all around us. These were the Picos de Europa. The road along the River Deva struggled and swerved through the gorge. At points the mountains were so steep and so close together the day became twilight. We drove and drove; it took us all afternoon on the two-lane road to pass through the range, a distance of about 35 miles.</p>
        <p>As the mountains again gave way to swells of green hills, we stopped in Carmona, a small village with nothing particular to offer other than a glimpse of the life of local farmers. We passed two men carving wooden clogs, then stopped to watch a game of bolos Palma, which is similar to boules. There was a healthy crowd of spectators, mostly older men in berets and clogs or felt slippers, murmuring to one another as the players tossed the ball with the grace and precision of dancers.</p>
        <p>We went hiking in the mountains another day, this time pressing by car further into the range, to Fuente De. Along the quiet, scenic roads, we stopped in Lebena to see the Santa Maria, a 10th-century Mozarabic church, our only glimpse of the ancient pilgrims' route to Santiago de Compostela. It sits dwarfed by a rock face so magnificent and large that the church seems to cower before it. In the capitals and cornices carvings of sun and stars remain.</p>
        <p>Just outside the church is a small food shack, run by a man who looks as if he just stumbled out of a tavern. He sells dated postcards and tour books, and local cheeses and beer. The cheeses sit under a towel in the open air with flies buzzing around. The man cut us wedges of Cabrales and a smoked sheep's milk cheese, and with his hands tore off a few pieces of baguette. Cabrales cheese is traditionally made in Asturias, but it is increasingly difficult to find made by artisan cheesemakers. These cheeses were it; they were nutty, rich and had an aroma as potent as lilacs.</p>
        <p>It was just the fuel we would need. At Fuente De the mountains do not so much rise as scream out of the ground. A gondola carries people up the 2,950-foot climb (the mountains rise 8,000 feet) in a few minutes that felt like hours, for me at least. At the top, there were hikers, paragliders and a number of people hanging out on rocks taking in the vast, majestic view of the mountain range. We hiked away from them, and soon were on open steep slopes of pasture with a light wind cooling us, and carrying the songs of bells on the cows and sheep in the hills. The air was thin and clear; beyond lay a jagged, steel-colored horizon of mountains.</p>
        <p>There are hiking trails throughout the mountain range for all skill levels. This challenging wander of a mile or so was more our speed.</p>
        <p>Another day -- which was warm and just suggestively humid as most of our days were -- we drove along the coast to Santi llana del Mar, a medieval town with cobblestone streets and architecture that is remarkably consistent and unchanged. A beautiful town that knows it, it is unfortunately littered with tourist shops.</p>
        <p>That excursion was one of a few mistakes we made. We also took a drive to Comillas, a town along the coast, to see El Capricho (The Whim), a house designed by Gaudi in 1885. It is wild and beautiful like much of his work, but it is merely a shell. The interior has been converted into an expensive restaurant.</p>
        <p>And we wasted a dinner at another ambitious restaurant in a small country village. The meal was fine, but had very little to do with Asturias or even Spanish food for that matter.</p>
        <p>Asturias is the kind of place where there is no artifice. The people are friendly and generous, the food is simple and satisfying, the landscape yours to admire. It reminded me of what I had read about rural France in old travel books but have yet to find there.</p>
        <p>Our best experiences were those we had tooling around the villages near our hotel. For lunch one day we stopped at the Meson el Paso, a truck stop along the regional coastal road, E70. When we entered, a woman turned on the lights and ambled back to the kitchen. It did not look promising.</p>
        <p>A waiter finally pulled himself from the television set in the bar and told us the fish of the day. I began with arroz con almejas, a dish of clams and rice in a bright green herb broth. My friend had scrambled eggs with shrimp, pleurottes (a mushroom) and roe. Both made us dizzy with pleasure. The shrimp were so fresh and so perfectly cooked, they popped in your mouth and were sweet as the sea. The mushrooms were nutty, the roe salty, the eggs like those from Mr. Sanz's hen.</p>
        <p>Next, we shared a daurade, or sea bass. It tasted, as my friend said, ''as if they had stuck a frying pan out the back window and it leapt in from the sea.'' We recovered at the Playa de la Franca, a beach just down the road, a suggestion of Mr. Sanz. We loved it so much we decided to spend our last day there as well.</p>
        <p>The beach is public and lies in a deep, narrow cove surrounded by high cliffs. When the tide is in, the beach is small and enclosed, but as the tide goes out, it rolls out like a great long carpet, allowing you to make your way along the shore and walk through vast tunnels carved by the sea water into the cliffs. It is a dream playground for children. And there are plenty of them, browned by the sun and gleeful. It was filled with Spanish families on summer vacation.</p>
        <p>At the back of the cove are a number of rundown shacks serving food. We thought we would grab a simple bite, a sandwich and beer. Seeing a menu of fish at one of them, we were skeptical, until a man in chef's whites appeared. I thought a long day in the sun must be playing tricks on my mind. But he helped us select a live crab, lifting some from a cooler and poking them as they crept across the counter. Then he cooked it for  us.</p>
        <p>We sat in our wet bathing suits and bare feet, looking out onto the beach. We had anchovies and peppers with the sweet crab, and a plate of cheeses to finish. The chef then brought us orujo, a local digestif.</p>
        <p>We wore ourselves out in the waves, then took a nap before dinner. Our last of the trip, it was at Casa Poli in nearby Puertas de Vidiago. It is a sidreria, or restaurant where the local cider and tapas are served. Locals will tell you that their sidra, or cider, is like the cider made in Normandy. Don't believe them. It is fruity, viscous and just a step up from vinegar.</p>
        <p>It is so vigorously acidic that it is not even drunk straight. To drink it the traditional way you must stand up holding the bottle above your head, then pour it behind your back into a glass held in your other hand.  As the liquid falls and hits the glass -- a  rare occurrence -- it aerates and lightens, making it more palatable. The idea is to pour just a little bit, a quarter inch or so, into the glass, then drink it quickly while  it's still good. Whatever is not drunk in  the first gulp is then poured into a bucket beside the table. Luckily it's cheap -- cheap enough not to perplex you too much about why the Asturians haven't just fixed the flavor.</p>
        <p>We may not have been drunk on sidra, but by this point we were drunk on Asturias. It is difficult in Europe to feel you are in a place that is somehow separate or undiscovered. But Asturias does feel that way. Perhaps that is why they have left the highway to the region severed the way it is -- a sign that fast-paced, ambitious tourists should stop right there.</p>
        <p>How to plan an idyll in Spain's unspoiled north</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>The closest airports are in Oviedo in Asturias and Santander in Cantabria. There are also flights to Bilbao, two hours east of Asturias. It is necessary to have a car. The best time to visit Asturias is in summer, when it's the least rainy and you can hike in the mountains and go to the beach. Fall and spring are also fine, though the Atlantic may be too chilly for swimming.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>El Molino de Tresgrandas, Tresgrandas, (34-985) 41-11-91, www.molinotresgrandas .com, has eight rooms, some in the main house, some in an attached cottage. All are simply furnished, with tiled bathrooms. There are no views to speak of, but every room is filled with the music of the stream running beneath the hotel. A full breakfast with homemade jams and eggs from the henhouse costs $4.65. Rooms are $52 plus 7 percent tax; the hotel is closed the first two weeks in February.</p>
        <p>Venta de Carmona, Barrio del Palacio, Carmona, (34-942) 72-80-57, stands like a grand villa in this small village. In fact, its eight rooms, all with bathrooms, $46 a night, 7 percent tax included, are all unpretentious, simple and spare; the hotel is decorated with antiques and still lifes of fresh gourds.</p>
        <p>''Casas de Aldea,'' available at local tourist offices, is a guide to Spanish country houses that, like Venta de Carmona, have been converted into hotels.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Meson el Paso de Buelna, (34-985) 41-12-05, is a small tavern on Route N634 in Buelna, frequented by truck drivers. The small restaurant serves extraordinary fresh fish, sauteed on its skin, rice with clams, sausages and unforgettable omelets; lunch for two is about $30.</p>
        <p>Hostal-Restaurante Covadonga, Plaza de la Iglesia, 33570 Panes, (34-985) 41-40-35, fax (34-985) 41-41-62, serves a vast menu of</p>
        <p>tapas, soups, hearty stews, and roasted meats. The three-course lunch menu is $6.50; entrees are $6 to $10. Open daily.</p>
        <p>Sidreria Casa Poli, Puertas de Vidiago, (34-985) 41-12-61, is a small cider restaurant set around a vine-draped courtyard. The lengthy menu offers everything from sliced cured ham and sauteed blood sausage to grilled sardines and blue cheese croquettes. Don't miss the cider. Tapas are $2 to $4, entrees $4 to $12. Open for lunch and dinner every day except between early January and April 1, when it is open Friday to Sunday only.</p>
        <p>AMANDA HESSER is a reporter for the Dining section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">AMANDA HESSER is a reporter for the Dining section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
