<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Filling the Need to Read With Tons of Books</title>
    <meta content="11VIEW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE VIEW FROM/DARIEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Darien Book Aid Plan Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierce, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DA123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Filling the Need to Read With Tons of Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA PIERCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pierce, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Darien Book Aid Plan Inc of Darien, Connecticut, whose volunteers have collected and donated 1,609 tons of books to more than 180 countries over past 50 years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO many books,'' 3-year-old Emily Snow murmured as she entered Darien Book Aid Plan Inc. on a recent Thursday morning. Emily and her mother, Laura Snow, 46, of Darien, had come to the white clapboard and brick firehouse on the Post Road to donate two bags of books.</p>
        <p>Donors like the Snows have been filling the shelves here for the past 50 years, allowing the group to distribute books to impoverished communities in the United States and abroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO many books,'' 3-year-old Emily Snow murmured as she entered Darien Book Aid Plan Inc. on a recent Thursday morning. Emily and her mother, Laura Snow, 46, of Darien, had come to the white clapboard and brick firehouse on the Post Road to donate two bags of books.</p>
        <p>Donors like the Snows have been filling the shelves here for the past 50 years, allowing the group to distribute books to impoverished communities in the United States and abroad.</p>
        <p>''This is sent overseas to children who don't have books,'' Ms. Snow said of her first donation to the nonprofit group. In the past the Snows had donated books to their local library. ''I'd rather send my books to people who don't have the opportunity to go to libraries.''</p>
        <p>The group keeps a tally of the tons and number of volumes of books that it has distributed over the years, a la the McDonald's ''hamburgers-sold'' signs, on a placard on the front of its building. So far it has distributed more than 1,609 tons of books to more than 180 countries. Yearly, the group ships about 50,000 pounds of books.</p>
        <p>The mission began in February 1949, when an inaugural shipment of four cartons was shipped to Germany and Austria. Founded by a group of Darien women who hoped to ''build peace, understanding and friendship by the free distribution of books around the world,'' the United States Army and State Department initially backed the venture by shipping donations. By the 1960's, just as the Peace Corps was established and requests began to mount, the government stopped paying for shipments.</p>
        <p>At the time the club boasted about 65 to 70 volunteers, all women (men were not admitted as members of the charitable society until 1985), who took on the cost of postage through dues and fund-raising. Three decades later, there are about 25 members.</p>
        <p>''We have a problem with getting volunteers. It's our biggest challenge these days,'' said Peggy Minnis, 55, who is in charge of overseas donations that go to the Peace Corp. ''Very few younger people are interested. Most of our members hover around 80.''</p>
        <p>The group's president, Janet Phyfe, 76, attributed the decline in volunteering to changing demographics.</p>
        <p>''For all of us in my age bracket a two-income family was most unusual,'' Ms. Phyfe said of the earlier days. ''As a consequence, the residents of Darien had time for starting the Darien Book Aid Plan. It's what ladies did after the war. Times have changed and volunteering has changed.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Minnis said she fears that without more young members, the group will be unable to fulfill its mission. Her daughter Jane, 27, is a volunteer with the group. ''The Peace Corps volunteers are depending on us,'' Peggy Minnis said. ''It's a shrinking but living thing.''</p>
        <p>Fewer volunteers now fill the 1,000 to 1,500 requests a year from such groups as Indian reservations, prisons, urban day-care centers, overseas hospitals and libraries and schools. The first obstacle for volunteers is wading through the vast number of inappropriate books to find the right  titles to fill orders.</p>
        <p>''Monday mornings you can't walk in the door sometimes, there are so many donations,'' said the shipping chairman, Dick Constable, 73, of Darien. ''Sometimes donors arrive and want a tax slip, but mostly they just drop off books under the cover of darkness,'' Ms. Minnis said.</p>
        <p>Many of those donations are unusable.  For example, books about how to get thinner thighs aren't likely to be of much use in a country where people are facing starvation, said a volunteer, Stuart Duffield, 73, of Darien, as he packed up a box of books headed for Bulgaria. At the same time, oft-requested categories, like the children's story books the Snows brought in, are always in short supply. Some of the most badly needed  categories include children's books, particularly those in Braille, Spanish and French. Other hard-to-keep-stocked categories are readers and grammar texts, teenage literature, reference books and books on medicine, agriculture and gardening.</p>
        <p>Ms. Minnis, who teaches environmental science at Pace University, said the group sends books to about 500 Peace Corps volunteers every year. ''They usually get 30 to 60 pounds of carefully selected books,'' she said. ''We have so much experience giving books to these types of places. We  know what they'll need.''</p>
        <p>Despite sending books to numerous war-torn countries, Ms. Minnis reported that only 25 to 30 cartons are sent back each year.</p>
        <p>In the 50 years of its existence, the volunteers have gotten thousands of letters of thanks. In January, a Peace Corps volunteer working in an Uzbekistan medical institute wrote to the group after getting a shipment that included medical reference volumes.  ''We have just received the recent shipment of books from your organization and cannot express out thanks,'' the volunteer wrote. ''To say we are delighted would be an understatement.'' Another Peace Corps volunteer working in Namibia wrote: ''Everyone in the community, especially the children, have been coming to use the books daily. Your donation is truly making an impact on our community.''</p>
        <p>Eleanor King, 82, a past president of the group, is known for her dedication to tracking down books, particularly children's readers, from among her friends. A few years ago a friend called to let her know that a school in Rowayton was throwing away obsolete second-grade readers.</p>
        <p>''They were in a Dumpster,'' said Mrs. King, who drove over to the school, climbed in the Dumpster and retrieved the readers.</p>
        <p>When Marion Murray, 66, returned from three years of Peace Corps service in Kenya to become parent liaison for Timothy Dwight Elementary School in New Haven, she remembered the shipments Mrs. King had sent and decided to call her for another donation.</p>
        <p>''The generosity of the organization was  just overwhelming,'' said Ms. Murray, who for the last three years has driven down to Darien to select story books and reference texts for the kindergarten-through-fourth-grade school.</p>
        <p>With the books she was given in Kenya, Ms. Murray was able to set up a lending library for teachers and students at a school for the deaf, while in New Haven she reported that the the books have encouraged children to read for pleasure and improve their skills.</p>
        <p>Group members cited only a few other programs that distribute books upon request, including the International Book Project in North Carolina and Brother to Brother in Pennsylvania. In Connecticut, the Literacy Volunteers of America in Danbury accepts books for donation to distribute to public agencies such as the housing authority.</p>
        <p>Local libraries will often accept book donations that are then sold to raise funds, and in lower Fairfield County the Darien, New Canaan, Norwalk and Wilton Smith Club will come to donors' homes to pick up books for its annual sale.</p>
        <p>''This is the ultimate recycling. People see their books as waste, but in other countries they're thrilled to get them,'' said Ms. Minnis.</p>
        <p>Those interested in volunteering to help the group, or those wishing to donate books may get more information by calling (203) 655-2777. Darien Book Aid Plan Inc. is located at 1926 Post Road. Books may be left in the lobby, which is always open.</p>
        <p>THE VIEW FROM/DARIEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
