<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feminism in Art, With Respect</title>
    <meta content="11SCHA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Heckscher Museum (Huntington, Li)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schapiro, Miriam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delatiner, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D9123FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feminism in Art, With Respect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delatiner, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>WAINSCOTT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Feminist artist Miriam Schapiro, whose Works on Paper--A 30-Year Retrospective is on view at Heckscher Museum of Art in Huntington, Long Island, comments on her views on feminism and her work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIRIAM SCHAPIRO has no trouble with labels. Being called a feminist artist is something she accepts, even relishes.</p>
        <p>It's in defining ''feminist art'' that problems arise; especially if Ms. Schapiro is asked how her iconoclastic, pioneering use of such traditional ''womanly'' arts as weaving, quilting and sewing to create her personal vocabulary fits in with the more strident strains of feminist art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIRIAM SCHAPIRO has no trouble with labels. Being called a feminist artist is something she accepts, even relishes.</p>
        <p>It's in defining ''feminist art'' that problems arise; especially if Ms. Schapiro is asked how her iconoclastic, pioneering use of such traditional ''womanly'' arts as weaving, quilting and sewing to create her personal vocabulary fits in with the more strident strains of feminist art.</p>
        <p>''Strident'' is a word that upsets Ms. Schapiro, whose ''Works on Paper -- A 30-Year Retrospective'' opened last Saturday at the Heckscher Museum of Art in Huntington.</p>
        <p>''Harsh, insistent, discordant; commanding attention by a loud or obtrusive quality,'' she read from the dictionary. ''Those are ugly words. Negative words. They have nothing to do with art or women.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schapiro finds her inspiration in positive elements of life and art. ''My father was a socialist and I was raised with a sensible attitude about humanism,'' she said. ''My feminism grew out of that humanism, a belief that men were in as much trouble as women were when it came to being victimized.</p>
        <p>''A feminist believes in sisterhood and that women have the right to be seen as philosophers and leaders. And should be treated as having the same potential as men have. I was raised by parents who encouraged me to be an artist, to be independent and not an appendix, subject to patriarchy and told all the time that women couldn't do that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schapiro, who was influenced by Abstract Expressionism and the New York School, started to develop her signature feminist art when her family was living in California.</p>
        <p>In California, Ms. Schapiro said: ''I had my epiphany and realized what I had to do was interpret feminism in my own way; that how you expressed yourself was based on all of your experience from the very beginning. I had the same life, the same experiences that everyone else had, and the parts of a woman's life that I love gave me satisfaction.''</p>
        <p>Attracted to their ''feel, colors and shapes,'' she began to include handkerchiefs and other pieces of material in her works. Her symbols became items traditionally associated with women: houses, hearts, aprons, fans. Eventually, she was instrumental in founding the Pattern and Decoration Movement, which questioned the notion that there is high art and low art.</p>
        <p>''It had to do with the democratization of art,'' she said. ''I hate elitism, and elitism in art through the centuries was handed down by men. We were never seen as makers of art. For thousands of years, weaving, ceramics, sewing were believed to be what untutored women made with their hands. But that was our art.''</p>
        <p>To help women ''build their artmaking out of their experiences as women,'' with Judy Chicago, the noted feminist artist, Ms. Schapiro founded the Feminist Art Program at the California Institute of the Arts in 1971.</p>
        <p>By the time Ms. Schapiro and her husband, Paul Brach, returned to New York in 1975, she was devoted to creating what she called ''femmages'': collages consisting of scraps of fabric, lace, handkerchiefs and doilies. Putting ordinary women and their mementos into her picture frames with such famous artists as Mary Cassatt and Frida Kahlo, she expanded these ''femmages'' into what she termed ''collaborations.''</p>
        <p>The critic Linda Nochlin, in ''Miriam Schapiro: Shaping the Fragments of Art and Life,'' a monograph accompanying ''Miriam Schapiro: A Retrospective,'' another exhibition on national tour, said taht in the process Ms. Schapiro ''has made a place for women in her art, and made it in a way that is completely contemporary and splendidly seductive in its sensuous pictorial fabric.''</p>
        <p>Despite losing her original gallery, which was not open to the feminist content of her new work, Ms. Schapiro has solidified her position in the art world over the last 25 years. In addition to continuing her work -- ''I've rediscovered my Jewish past,'' she said -- she has been in demand as a speaker about women and art. ''They call me 'Miriam Appleseed,' '' she said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>These last three years have been especially rewarding, with the two major national touring exhibitions; shows in Miami and at the Arlene Bujese Gallery in East Hampton, and the critic-author Gail Levin's award of a National Endowment of the Humanities grant to write Ms. Schapiro's biography.</p>
        <p>After taking some time off to recover from a life-threatening illness -- and ''living through the most traumatic experience of my life, moving from where we've lived for 25 years,'' she said -- Ms. Schapiro has resumed painting.</p>
        <p>''Steve Winn for whom I've done pieces before, commissioned a work for his new casino, Bellagio, I had only two months to do it,'' she said. ''It's 240 inches wide and 7 feet 6 inches high and I call it 'Diva.' Unfortunately, they changed the wall it was supposed to be on to glass and it was canceled. So it's now at my dealer's in Miami and got terrific reviews. But the commission did inspire me to get back to work.''</p>
        <p>The notion of ''Diva'' fits right into her life's work, she said. ''Everything I've done is about women. And every woman has the right to interpret her feminism on her own. There shouldn't be one agenda. Each woman, each artist, should work out her own agenda, just as I have.''</p>
        <p>''Miriam Schapiro: Works on Paper - A 30-Year Retrospective,'' organized by the Tucson Tuscon Museum of Art, runs through Aug. 13 at the Heckscher Museum of Art on Prime Avenue in Huntington. (631) 351-3250. A solo exhibition of recent work will be at the Arlene Bujese Gallery on Newtown Lane, East Hampton, through June 22. (631) 324-2823.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
