<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tossed Salad of Music on the Beach</title>
    <meta content="11BEAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FESTIVAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE103FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tossed Salad of Music on the Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on events slated for seventh annual Beach Fest in Atlantic City, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO ONE can accuse Kay Seelig of running a one-dimensional show. The seventh annual Beach Fest, the summer beach season entertainment opener for Atlantic City is, if nothing else, a well-wrought model of inconsistency.</p>
        <p>''I guess the easiest thing to say is, 'Why not?' '' said Ms. Seelig, the president and founder of Acora, the Beach Fest producers. ''Why not have something for everyone? There are so many festivals which are just for one group. We want to see everybody enjoying themselves.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO ONE can accuse Kay Seelig of running a one-dimensional show. The seventh annual Beach Fest, the summer beach season entertainment opener for Atlantic City is, if nothing else, a well-wrought model of inconsistency.</p>
        <p>''I guess the easiest thing to say is, 'Why not?' '' said Ms. Seelig, the president and founder of Acora, the Beach Fest producers. ''Why not have something for everyone? There are so many festivals which are just for one group. We want to see everybody enjoying themselves.''</p>
        <p>Over the course of next weekend, visitors can see, for instance, the 91-year-old jazz vibraphonist Lionel Hampton and the ultra-hard-rockers from a generation back Iron Butterfly (''In-A-Gadda-Da-Vida''); an Army marching band; and the Philadelphia 1960's pop group the Orlons (''South Street'').</p>
        <p>''Not exactly peas in a pod,'' Ms. Seelig said with a laugh. ''But we did want to be all over the spectrum. We think it doesn't bother everyone, but that it pleases everyone to have a little bit of disco, a little bit of jazz, a little bit of hard rock.''</p>
        <p>For a long time after casino gambling came to Atlantic City, despite the existence of various associations and groups, there was little coordination among the casino-hotels for promotion of entertainment. In the early 1990's, Ms. Seelig came up with an event to give a lift to the beginning of the summer season and got several casinos to help promote it. She called it Acora, for Atlantic City Off-Shore Racing Association.</p>
        <p>''It was a good event, but then we realized that we wanted something more participatory for everyone, which a power-boat race isn't,'' said Adrienne Beinfest, Beach Fest's marketing director. ''Music usually makes for a good time on the beach.''</p>
        <p>All of Beach Fest 2000's entertainment will be free and most will be on or within a few yards of the Boardwalk -- the exception being three Sunday concerts by the 1960's Philadelphia-based pop group the Soul Survivors (''Expressway to Your Heart''), on the deck of the Trump Marina Casino-Hotel.</p>
        <p>There will be stages in front of most of the casinos along the Boardwalk from the Hilton on the south to the Trump Taj Mahal on the north, with another pavilion at New Jersey Avenue and the Boardwalk, with displays by companies including Starbucks, Comcast and Green Mountain Coffee.</p>
        <p>The official opening of Beach Fest will be a parade down the Boardwalk with floats and the 63rd Army Marching Band at 6 p.m. Friday. But before that, Mr. Hampton and his band will be playing at 5 p.m. in front of the Sands Hotel at the Brighton Park Amphitheater.</p>
        <p>Saturday's big events include another 5 p.m. performance at the Brighton Park Amphitheater by Mr. Hampton; a ''Saturday Afternoon Fever'' disco party at 1 p.m., followed by a Roman Circus Performance at the Caesars Casino stage; three performances of a daredevil thrill show, including a human cannonball, at the Tropicana Hotel-Casino; and the Iron Butterfly concert at 8 p.m. at the Trump Taj Mahal.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Mr. Hampton will perform at Brighton Park twice, at 1 and 3 p.m.; the Soul Survivors will be at the Trump Marina Deck for three shows beginning at 2 p.m.; the daredevil show will be on again for three more performances, and there will be a closing concert featuring 1960's groups like the Dovells (''Bristol Stomp''), the Marvellettes (''Please Mr. Postman'') and the Orlons at Caesars.</p>
        <p>In addition, throughout the weekend, Budweiser will have a tent by the Resorts Atlantic City Casino with a mock brewery for visitors to see the process of making beer. Local bands will play more or less continuously on other stages.</p>
        <p>''Mostly,'' Ms. Seelig said, ''we figure people will bring lawn chairs and blankets, migrate back and forth to the beach, and catch a little bit of this and a little bit of that.''</p>
        <p>She said the casinos have been enthusiastic about this kind of event because mid-June has been a traditionally slow time.</p>
        <p>''Memorial Day takes care of itself and then it slows down for a few weeks until the weather gets really hot again and schools are all out,'' she said. ''Like Miss America, which was designed to push the summer season a little further into the fall, we want to push the season a little earlier with Beach Fest.</p>
        <p>''And if it takes a mixture of Iron Butterfly and Lionel Hampton to do it, well, isn't that fun?''</p>
        <p>BEACH FEST</p>
        <p>Acora.  Atlantic City Boardwalk, Atlantic City.  Friday, 3 p.m. to 10 p.m.; next Saturday and next Sunday, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.  www.acbeachfest.com  (609) 484-9020.</p>
        <p>FESTIVAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
