<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Group Therapy; The Lonely Crowd Joins the Party</title>
    <meta content="11GOOD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whyte, William H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glazer, Nathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denney, Reuel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bobos In Paradise (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lonely Crowd, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Organization Man, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DC1F3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Group Therapy; The Lonely Crowd Joins the Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Brooks's new book, Bobos in Paradise, about the blending of bourgeois and Bohemian cultures, looks back now and then to 1950's, the golden age of sociological journalism, which brought forth William H Whyte Jr's The Organization Man (1956) and Nathan Glazer and Reuel Denney's The Lonely Crowd (1950); sociological journalism at best provides snapshots of the big picture and does not have great reputation for prophecy; writers of the 1950's were unable to foresee the transformation of the economy that derailed to corporate conformity they feared; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN ''Bobos in Paradise,'' his acute if sometimes cutesy new book about the merger of America's bourgeoisie and its Bohemians (which he merges into ''Bobos''), David Brooks looks back now and then to the 1950's, the golden age of the liberal science of sociology.</p>
        <p>In those years, journalists like William H. Whyte Jr. (''The Organization Man,'' 1956) and sociologists like David Riesman and his colleagues Nathan Glazer and Reuel Denney (''The Lonely Crowd,'' 1950), were lamenting the plunge of the middle class into corporation-dominated conformity. A half-century later, Mr. Brooks, though mocking the tastes and pretensions of today's upper middle class, confesses to being generally satisfied with its success in combining acquisitiveness, social consciousness and easygoing tolerance into a genial life style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN ''Bobos in Paradise,'' his acute if sometimes cutesy new book about the merger of America's bourgeoisie and its Bohemians (which he merges into ''Bobos''), David Brooks looks back now and then to the 1950's, the golden age of the liberal science of sociology.</p>
        <p>In those years, journalists like William H. Whyte Jr. (''The Organization Man,'' 1956) and sociologists like David Riesman and his colleagues Nathan Glazer and Reuel Denney (''The Lonely Crowd,'' 1950), were lamenting the plunge of the middle class into corporation-dominated conformity. A half-century later, Mr. Brooks, though mocking the tastes and pretensions of today's upper middle class, confesses to being generally satisfied with its success in combining acquisitiveness, social consciousness and easygoing tolerance into a genial life style.</p>
        <p>They are antiestablishment establishmentarians. Sociological journalism, which at its best provides snapshots of the big picture, does not have a great reputation for prophecy, and the writers of the 1950's could not foresee the transformation of the economy and the creation of a far wealthier set of men and women whose loyalty is less to their company than to the perks it can deliver. (Whyte reported in 1956 that only ''the venturesome few buy stocks.'') Their admonitions about America's burgeoning consumer society are strikingly different from Mr. Brooks's amused welcome.</p>
        <p>Did the best-selling sociologists get everything wrong?</p>
        <p>Whyte was troubled by the postwar appeal of corporate power and authority, with its assumption that the interests of the companies where most Americans made their living coincided with morality. The key word was ''belongingness,'' which Whyte saw as a lure and a snare that threatened everyone's independence. He warned that the apparent beneficence of corporate life masked a basic conflict between the individual and society: ''The group is a tyrant; so also is it a friend, and it is both at once.''</p>
        <p>On the popular subject of consumerism, with the nation awash in cash after the scarcities of the war years, Whyte discerned that ''it is the group that determines when a luxury becomes a necessity.'' Who could foresee the amounts of money the Bobos would have to throw around and the ways, which Mr. Brooks describes so humorously, that marketeers would devise to relieve them of it? But Whyte's basic point, that most people with spare income don't know what they ''need'' until the commercial tastemakers tell them, is also evident in Mr. Brooks' up-to-date analysis. And it is how they spend that largely defines their class.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brooks is too sharp a reporter to miss the way his Bobos go about their socially inspired duties to consume. He even offers rules for Bobo buying: bathrooms and kitchens, however oversized and overequipped, are more virtuous than a wide-screen television set; gardening tools, however overpriced and underused, are more virtuous than jewelry. The adroit Bobo avoids vulgarly conspicuous consumption and practices ''one-downmanship'' in the form of very expensive simplicity.</p>
        <p>The underlying difference between Mr. Brooks and Whyte is ideological. While Whyte inveighed, ''We must fight the Organization!'' Mr. Brooks is comfortable with what he sees, at worst, as harmless excess. It's a generational and political divide. The 1950's sociologists, mostly left-leaning, drew on America's experience with the Depression and the New Deal; they were suspicious of corporate power in all its forms. Mr. Brooks, a senior editor at the conservative Weekly Standard, apparently learned his sociology at the lap of Irving Kristol and other neoconservative champions of the market economy.</p>
        <p>THAT would also account for the way he shrugs off the famous assertion of ''The Lonely Crowd'' that the nation's move from the age of production to the age of consumption was marked by the emergence of ''other-directed'' types, mostly white-collar folks who conform to the expectations of their peers and their betters. ''The other-directed person,'' Riesman wrote, ''is in a sense at home everywhere and nowhere, capable of a tepid if sometimes superficial intimacy with and response to everyone.''</p>
        <p>When Riesman, no humorist, addressed Bohemianism, he saw it as just another sort of other-directedness, made up of people who are ''often zealously tuned in to the signals of a group that finds the meaning of life, quite unproblematically, in an illusion of attacking an allegedly dominant and punishing majority of Babbitts and Kwakiutl chiefs.''</p>
        <p>He could have been writing about the 1960's. Mr. Brooks sees the co-option of Bohemia into the bourgeoisie as preferable to having rowdy demonstrators break windows and stall traffic. And the other-directedness that Riesman described as a threat to personal autonomy receives Mr. Brooks's embrace for the Bobos' contribution to community and social cohesion; he likes their centrist political inclinations and the value they put on consensus and civility. It's a sort of 5-C club.</p>
        <p>So he would never thunder about the organization man, as Whyte did: ''It is wretched, dispiriting advice to hold before him that ideally there need be no conflict between him and society. There always is; there always must be.''</p>
        <p>As Bobos find their way into Paradise, the presumed shackles of the 1950's have become designer accessories.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
