<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interns' Long Workdays Prompt First Crackdown</title>
    <meta content="11DOCS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DC163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interns' Long Workdays Prompt First Crackdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Authorities who evaluate medical education have begun to crack down on doctor-training programs that force interns and residents to work excessively long hours; Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education, which sets standards for training of doctors, says over 29 percent of training programs in surgery and internal medicine were cited for violations of work-hour standards last year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The authorities who evaluate medical education have, for the first time, begun to crack down on doctor-training programs that force interns and residents to work excessively long hours.</p>
        <p>More than 29 percent of training programs in surgery and internal medicine were cited for violations of work-hour standards last year, according to the private group that evaluates and accredits medical education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The authorities who evaluate medical education have, for the first time, begun to crack down on doctor-training programs that force interns and residents to work excessively long hours.</p>
        <p>More than 29 percent of training programs in surgery and internal medicine were cited for violations of work-hour standards last year, according to the private group that evaluates and accredits medical education.</p>
        <p>Moreover, after years of debate, some experts now say that sleep-deprived doctors are more likely than other physicians to make mistakes, threatening patients' safety. Medical errors are attracting increasing attention, and the government is contemplating new steps to strengthen how they are reported and corrected.</p>
        <p>The new data on work-hour violations came from the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education, the body that sets standards for the training of doctors and measures compliance.</p>
        <p>Doctors in training often work 36-hour shifts and 100-hour weeks, and experts in the field say that New York is the only state with a law limiting such work hours.</p>
        <p>The council has never before disclosed the number of violations. But Dr. David C. Leach, executive director of the council, said: ''There has been an increase in the frequency with which this issue provokes a citation. That reflects an increase in the number of programs that are in violation of the standard for work hours.''</p>
        <p>The council said it reviewed 69 training programs in general surgery last year and cited 25 of them, or 36 percent, for violating its standards on permissible work hours. Reviewers found similar violations at 7 of the 13 programs in pediatric surgery, 54 percent; 28 of the 92 programs in internal medicine, 30 percent; and 20 of the 69 programs in orthopedic surgery, 29 percent.</p>
        <p>The council did not identify the teaching hospitals with violations.</p>
        <p>Requirements vary from one specialty to another, but reviewers found frequent violations of three standards in particular. The standards state that residents must have off at least one day out of every seven, should not be on duty in the hospital more often than every third night and should not have to work more than a specified number of hours -- say, 80 hours a week, averaged over a one-month period.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rachel R. Marcus, a 32-year-old fellow in cardiovascular medicine at Stanford University, fondly remembers her years in training at a major teaching hospital in Boston, but said: ''I was chronically fatigued, so tired I felt as if I was operating in a daze sometimes. You go into medicine for idealistic reasons, but by the end of a grueling internship, you see each patient you admit to the hospital as a barrier to getting sleep. That's a horrible way to interact with people.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcus said residents' lack of sleep could affect their decision-making ability. ''I remember one night in the hospital when I told a nurse something that was wrong, the exact opposite of what I should have said about giving antibiotics to a patient,'' she recalled. ''Seconds later, when I was more awake, I realized my error, but I still wonder what might have happened if I'd gone back to sleep.''</p>
        <p>If a teaching hospital does not correct its violations, it can face serious penalties. A training program may lose its accreditation. If that happens, the hospital will lose some of its Medicare money, and residents will shun the program because they cannot be certified as specialists unless they graduate from an accredited training program.</p>
        <p>No training program has lost its accreditation exclusively because of work-hour violations.</p>
        <p>The effort to restrict work hours comes as Congress is considering legislation to reduce medical errors and as labor unions are intensifying their efforts to enlist doctors.</p>
        <p>Strict compliance with the work-hour standards could increase costs for teaching hospitals, which often rely on young doctors as a source of low-cost labor. Dr. Leach said that budget constraints had forced some teaching hospitals to cut back ''support staff,'' including the people who draw blood and transport patients. Some hospitals use residents to perform such tasks, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's said that the health care system is broken and has cracks in it, and that residents live in those cracks,'' Dr. Leach said. ''They are the glue that holds the system together. They get things done even though the system is dysfunctional.''</p>
        <p>For a decade, New York State has had a law that limits most interns and residents to 24-hour shifts and 80-hour workweeks. But in 1998, the State Health Department found widespread violations. Since then, the state has inspected 35 teaching hospitals and fined 26 of them for allowing residents to work hours that far exceed the limits set by state law.</p>
        <p>Without explicitly resisting the work-hour limits, many surgeons have expressed skepticism.</p>
        <p>Dr. George F. Sheldon, a former president of the American College of Surgeons who is chairman of the surgery department at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill, said: ''A surgeon has a fiduciary responsibility to care for a patient before, during and after an operation. You can't punch a clock and say, 'My time is up.' We believe in continuity of care. That is not always consistent with working a fixed number of hours.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Marvin R. Dunn, who coordinates the council's review of residency programs, agreed. ''Continuity of care by the same physician is very important, especially in surgery,'' Dr. Dunn said. ''Errors are made when patients are handed over from the care of one physician to another.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. William C. Dement of Stanford University, a pioneer in the study of sleep, said his research and observations strongly suggested that ''sleep deprivation contributes to medical errors,'' and that ''with more hours of sleep, doctors make fewer errors.''</p>
        <p>Mark L. Levy, executive director of the Committee of Interns and Residents, a labor union with 10,000 members, said that teaching hospitals and medical societies had for years opposed limits on residents' work hours. Medical educators are beginning to enforce such limits, he said, because they want to prevent unions from gaining ground.</p>
        <p>''Teaching hospitals and accrediting agencies are trying to clean up their act,'' Mr. Levy said. ''They are becoming more systematic in enforcing work standards. They are finally acknowledging that work hours are excessive. They are doing this, in part, to reduce the appeal of and need for unions.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard B. Reiling, who supervises the surgical residency program at Kettering Medical Center in Ohio, said it was inappropriate to set rigid limits on doctors' work hours.</p>
        <p>''In this day and age,'' Dr. Reiling said, ''a lot of residents want the time off not because they're tired, but because they want to moonlight to make extra money to pay off their monumental loans.''</p>
        <p>Moonlighting -- clinical activity outside an educational program -- is not counted in determining how many hours a doctor has worked. But Dr. Dunn, of the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education, said the organization was considering a change in policy to require that such work be counted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
