<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once a Tar Heel . . .</title>
    <meta content="11GOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstein, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Earley, Tony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jim the Boy (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D8103CF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once a Tar Heel . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill Goldstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldstein, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Goldstein interviews author Tony Earley, whose latest book is Jim the Boy; photo (M)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Earley doesn't live in North Carolina anymore, but the only real blot on what he calls his ''impeccable North Carolina credentials'' is that ''by military accident'' he was born in Texas and lived there for the first year and a half of his life.</p>
        <p>Earley's two books, ''Here We Are in Paradise'' (1994), a collection of short stories, and now ''Jim the Boy,'' his first novel, have a similar Carolina pedigree. They cover nearly a century of life in the state where both of Earley's parents grew up on farms and where Earley, who is 38, grew up the son of a father who worked in a factory and a mother who worked in a department store. ''I've written very little that was set anywhere else,'' he says. ''There's only one story in 'Here We Are in Paradise' set in another place, and that's about a North Carolinian trying to get back home.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony Earley doesn't live in North Carolina anymore, but the only real blot on what he calls his ''impeccable North Carolina credentials'' is that ''by military accident'' he was born in Texas and lived there for the first year and a half of his life.</p>
        <p>Earley's two books, ''Here We Are in Paradise'' (1994), a collection of short stories, and now ''Jim the Boy,'' his first novel, have a similar Carolina pedigree. They cover nearly a century of life in the state where both of Earley's parents grew up on farms and where Earley, who is 38, grew up the son of a father who worked in a factory and a mother who worked in a department store. ''I've written very little that was set anywhere else,'' he says. ''There's only one story in 'Here We Are in Paradise' set in another place, and that's about a North Carolinian trying to get back home.''</p>
        <p>His fiction may stay put, but Earley, who now teaches creative writing at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, has been going home -- and moving away again -- for much of his adult life. After graduating from Warren Wilson College in Asheville, N.C., he returned to his hometown, Rutherfordton, and spent three and a half years as a reporter for the local paper.</p>
        <p>''It's a pretty standard late-20th-century story,'' he says. ''I was an English major in college. I was an obnoxious, tortured poet who wasn't very good.'' While Earley was studying for an M.F.A. at the University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, he began writing stories, publishing them in small literary magazines and then in Harper's. By the time he got his degree, he had a two-book contract with Little, Brown.</p>
        <p>After the publication of ''Here We Are in Paradise,'' Earley fell into one of the ''periodic, chronic'' depressions he has suffered from since childhood. He didn't have a secure teaching job, and he realized, he says, ''that there are no guarantees. I wasn't sure I was ever going to be able to write again.''</p>
        <p>Things turned around in 1996, when Granta named Earley one of America's 20 best young writers. ''It really was a career-changing thing,'' he says. ''One day, I'm a depressed guy lying on the couch and the next day I'm one of the best young writers in America. It was bizarre. The phone rings and my wife goes, 'Oh, you're one of the best writers in America.' It was that quick a change in status, even though I knew that I was the same writer I was before the phone rang.''</p>
        <p>The Granta announcement led to his job at Vanderbilt, yet it also made Earley anxious -- he had yet to start on the novel that would become ''Jim the Boy,'' and he was already behind on his contract. But Earley found that his new teaching responsibilities were liberating. Before the job, he says, ''I had all the time in the world to write and actually wrote very little. Now I had much less time and I began to write reams of stuff. It's been the most prolific period in my writing life.''</p>
        <p>''Jim the Boy'' is a deceptively simple novel, an unembellished account of the year a boy named Jim Glass Jr. turns 10. Set during the Depression, ''Jim the Boy'' is a 21st-century novel that seems to reject the narrative and linguistic experimentation that have marked so much contemporary fiction. The novel's spare style grows partly from Earley's depression, during which he became fascinated with classic children's books -- Little House on the Prairie,'' ''The Chronicles of Narnia,'' ''Charlotte's Web,'' ''The Yearling'' -- and decided to attempt ''a children's book for adults, to use that simple narrative and that really clear language and yet use it to tell a complex story.''</p>
        <p>Jim had been with Earley for a long time as ''my main character,'' he says. An older Jim Glass, a father and grandfather, is the narrator of three stories in ''Here We Are in Paradise.'' Even before Earley knew Jim Glass would become the protagonist of ''Jim the Boy,'' he knew that he ''had a lot more to tell about him.''</p>
        <p>Earley makes it clear that the tales in ''Jim the Boy'' and in his short fiction are not autobiographical. The stories about the Glass family, he says, are either ''made up or appropriated'' from some source other than his family. ''I come from a family of storytellers,'' he says, ''and I've often been accused by my friends and my wife of telling stories and not telling them accurately. But it's a better story the way I tell it. And if the person who's speaking to me about this is involved in the story, then suddenly there are two people. And because I'm the one making up the story, they're both very real to me.''</p>
        <p>Playing around with ''the disparity between story-truth and truth-truth,'' Earley says, enables him ''in my own sneaky way to be postmodern in things that look like they have no influence of the postmodern in them at all.'' Earley says he pretends ''to be a reactionary and anti-postmodern and antitheory, and around my Ph.D. colleagues I pretend to be pretty ignorant.'' But his perspective is more subtle. ''I think character and narrative and story are the important things. And then if you do that well, if you can also wander into John Barth's fun house for a few minutes without making yourself obnoxious, well then, that's O.K. too.''</p>
        <p>Earley isn't finished with Jim Glass; his next book, as he envisions it, will be set when Jim is 17 and ''waiting to go off to World War II.'' One of Earley's ambitions is ''to see this really fat book that has five or six short stories and a couple of novels and a novella called 'The Complete Jim Glass,' where I do his whole life in as many different ways as possible.''</p>
        <p>Earley is aware that there are dangers in romanticizing the past. ''I have to be careful,'' he says. ''I never want to be a nostalgic writer. I don't want to write with the idea that the past was better and that things have gone to hell now, because I don't believe that. In the South of 'Jim the Boy,' while it might have been pastoral and bucolic to a kid growing up in a fairly well-to-do farming family, to a kid growing up in a black family in the same town it would have been a completely different experience. I think about that a lot. And I hope that if I ever become nostalgic, somebody will just tell me to shut up.''</p>
        <p>INTERVIEW Bill Goldstein is the books editor of The New York Times on the Web (www.nytimes.com/books), where a longer audio version of this interview is available.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bill Goldstein is the books editor of The New York Times on the Web (www.nytimes.com/books), where a longer audio version of this interview is available.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
