<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wars and Rumors of War</title>
    <meta content="11ADJAMIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Balkan States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ajami, Fouad (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glenny, Misha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judah, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ignatieff, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Balkans, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Kosovo: War and Revenge (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Virtual War: Kosovo and Beyond (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D6123CF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wars and Rumors of War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Fouad Ajami</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ajami, Fouad (Prof)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prof Fouad Ajami reviews books The Balkans: Nationalism, War and the Great Powers, 1804-1999 by Misha Glenny, Kosovo: War and Revenge by Tim Judah and Virtual War: Kosovo and Beyond by Michael Ignatieff; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Balkans</p>
        <p>Nationalism, War and</p>
        <p>the Great Powers, 1804-1999.</p>
        <p>By Misha Glenny.</p>
        <p>726 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $34.95.</p>
        <p>Kosovo</p>
        <p>War and Revenge.</p>
        <p>By Tim Judah.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 348 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $37.50. Paper, $17.95.</p>
        <p>Virtual War</p>
        <p>Kosovo and Beyond.</p>
        <p>By Michael Ignatieff.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 246 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Books. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Balkans</p>
        <p>Nationalism, War and</p>
        <p>the Great Powers, 1804-1999.</p>
        <p>By Misha Glenny.</p>
        <p>726 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $34.95.</p>
        <p>Kosovo</p>
        <p>War and Revenge.</p>
        <p>By Tim Judah.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 348 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $37.50. Paper, $17.95.</p>
        <p>Virtual War</p>
        <p>Kosovo and Beyond.</p>
        <p>By Michael Ignatieff.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 246 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Books. $23.</p>
        <p>''Talking of war, there'll be trouble in the Balkans in the spring,'' a character mutters in Rudyard Kipling's 1899 novel, ''The Light That Failed.'' He is a war correspondent idling his time away in London, hoping for deliverance in the Balkans, where he and all the other correspondents ''will have as much as ever we can do'' and ''the chance to see things'' that make reputations. It has been this way for a long time: We know the Balkans as metaphor, as a world where Europe (its meaning and boundaries uncertain at best) trails off and another reality begins, as a nemesis overtaking times and places of order.</p>
        <p>Nowadays the Balkans again belong to journalists; the histories of these lands are written by war reporters or those who can sense the approaching thunder of war. By the time that rumble is heard, the fire will have eaten up the social and economic history and the truths and arrangements that held a place together will have been torched. This ruin gives a certain liberty to authors. The older history and reality hadn't held. If conquest rounds out the borders, why bother with the history of land ownership in the Balkans? If civility cracks, why bother with the literature of the place?</p>
        <p>Eight years after the prison camps of Bosnia, five years after Srebrenica marked our age and mocked our pretensions that we have been delivered into a world beyond history's furies, we are wiser about the Balkans and Balkan legends. Few people are around now whose first acquaintance with them came from Rebecca West, the purveyor of Balkan legends, whose huge book of travel, ''Black Lamb and Grey Falcon,'' grew out of a six-week venture into Yugoslavia in 1937. We have had enough stories about the Serbian Czar Lazar being offered, on the Field of Blackbirds in June 1389, a choice between an earthly kingdom for a time and a heavenly kingdom that would last for ''eternity and its centuries.'' He opted for the heavenly one and we know what terrible crimes have been committed in his name. If the romance is gone, so is the moral fury with which the first round of Balkan terrors was treated by gifted authors who spoke for us. Readers now are wrung out of sorrow, out of the surprise and wonder we bring to reading.</p>
        <p>Misha Glenny, a British journalist, made his name with ''The Fall of Yugoslavia,'' published in 1993. He chronicled what he had witnessed on the scene. The present has clearly emboldened him, and he has come back with a big book, ''The Balkans: Nationalism, War and the Great Powers, 1804-1999.'' It claims to be nothing less than the history of the Balkans since the rebellion against the Ottoman Empire in the early 19th century.</p>
        <p>A few years ago Glenny's voice -- with its knowingness, its sly skepticism about all the competing nationalisms of the Balkans, the hints that outraged outsiders who fell for Bosnia's Muslims didn't really know the area -- could sustain a book of reportage, and his journalism. There were readers (myself included) who did not find in his writing enough of their wrath against the Serbian revanchists. But the war gave him material and confidence. He was in his early 30's. Those were the truths he brought out of the burning grounds of Vukovar and Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>Writing a big book of history is a different endeavor. Glenny tackles Balkan history in the manner of a CNN reporter working behind history's lines -- all the way from the revolts of Serbia and Greece in the 1800's to the present. The great historian Fernand Braudel wrote of history as the interplay of ''stillness and movement.'' He warned that chronicling events will not suffice: ''Events are the ephemera of history; they pass from the scene across its stage like fireflies, hardly glimpsed before they settle back into darkness and as often as not into oblivion.'' Glenny doesn't have the eye for ''stillness,'' for secrets of a people's history that aren't easily yielded up to us.</p>
        <p>He has assimilated and rewritten a huge amount of history, but his book is weighed down by its very bulk. He relies on anecdotes, so the book hangs by a slender thread. His theme -- that interventions by the great powers through the generations have added to the ruin of the Balkans -- is hardly novel. The observation that those interventions -- the Congress of Berlin in 1878, the wars and diplomacy that ushered in and settled World War I, World War II and its resolution -- guaranteed the relative economic backwardness of the Balkans, compared to the rest of Europe'' will not do as economic history. The tangled tale of new nationalisms filling the void left by the collapse of the Ottoman and Hapsburg Empires has been told by talented historians.</p>
        <p>The explanation offered for this book is that Glenny discovered that he had carried into his Balkan reporting ''prejudicial baggage'' and he had been ''obliged to make judgments about Yugoslav and Balkan history'' when he had only ''the vaguest acquaintance'' with historical matters. But that can hardly justify an inquiry of this length and ambition. With Glenny's new book, we are face to face with the fate awaiting places that succumb to political ruin: the outsider's presumption that a whole, big history is there for the plucking.</p>
        <p>In ''Kosovo: War and Revenge'' Tim Judah, a journalist who has covered with depth and intimacy the region for The Economist and other publications, gives himself a narrower mandate and delivers a superb political narrative of the fight for Kosovo. It is now Kosova (its Albanian name); the city of Pec goes by the name of Peja; the town of Podujevo is now Podujeva. The world has been turned upside down; two-thirds of the Serbs have left their homes behind and the old fight between Serbian claim and Albanian demography has been settled in favor of the Albanians. The place is an international protectorate; a force of 40,000 troops sent by the United Nations and NATO plays the role of reluctant imperialist. In an odd sort of way, Kosovo has been folded into a Pax Americana, a destiny prefigured by Bosnia. The rescue offered Kosovo was late and hedged; it was triggered by revulsion against the Serbs, but the troops came in subdued and wary of the Albanians. Judah covers this whole story authoritatively, so his is not a pretty book. But his instincts are good; he has no ax to grind. He recounts the Serbian horrors, but also the later massive flight of the Serbs that created a new order in Kosovo. He records the lawlessness of the new masters there, the hard boys of the Kosovo Liberation Army who emerged as the inheritors of the place.</p>
        <p>It was perhaps destined to end this way. Edith Durham, an English chronicler who was there in 1908 and is much quoted by Judah, glimpsed the great impasse between Serbs and Kosovars: ''The white castle of Czar Lazar was but a dream in the night of the past. Around us in the daylight was the Albanian population, waiting, under arms, to defend the land that had been theirs since the beginning of time.'' In the new American-led imperium lies the promise of a multiethnic Kosovo and the lingering juridical claim that Kosovo is still part of Serbia. But physically and morally, the Serbs have lost their hold. The NATO air campaign launched in March 1999 -- 78 days, 34,000 sorties -- delivered an astonishing reversal of fortunes. A young priest in a Kosovo monastery, the Rev. Sava Janic, one of the few clergymen of the Serbian Orthodox Church to withstand the temptations of radical nationalism, tells Judah: ''Kosovo has the same destiny as Asia Minor, once full of wonderful Christian sites and now all ruins and ash.''</p>
        <p>The Serbian leader Slobodan Milosevic, not known for a flair with words, did allow himself one rhetorical flourish as he began a campaign to drive out the Kosovars under cover of the NATO bombing: the Kosovars, he said, like the birds, were fleeing NATO bombs. This was one of the great moral riddles at the heart of the war in Kosovo. And it is a central moral issue raised by the intervention, which Michael Ignatieff takes up in ''Virtual War: Kosovo and Beyond.'' A talented and versatile Canadian writer based in London, Ignatieff comes to the Balkans with the gift of a family inheritance. In the Balkans he can tease out the presence of an ancestor who speaks to the present. His great-grandfather, Count Nicholas Ignatieff, a confidant of Czar Alexander II of Russia and in the 1860's and 70's a powerful emissary to the Turkish sultan in Constantinople, was one of the instigators of the pan-Slavic spirit then at play in the Russian Orthodox Church and among Slavophiles at court and in the press.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, as a boy Michael Ignatieff lived in Belgrade in 1958 and 1959, when his father, a Canadian diplomat, served there. Such are the meandering ways of modern exile. ''The bombing of Belgrade was never an abstraction to me,'' he writes. He recalls life there during ''Tito's heyday,'' and his family's big house in ''the leafy hills of Dedinje, near Tito's official residence''; he remembers rooting for a local soccer club and speaking Serbo-Croatian, a language that ''no longer officially exists.''</p>
        <p>Those shadows across Ignatieff's path give his book -- a series of previously published essays -- poignancy and engagement. He works a seam running across our world between landscapes of violence -- Rwanda, Burundi, Angola, Afghanistan, Kosovo, places given to blood feuds and boys with Kalashnikovs -- and nations celebrating the triumph of the market and the spread of the Internet. He straddles a moral fence of sorts as well. He can't give himself over to the morality of the new interventionists; he can't sanction the indifference of the realists. Back and forth he goes between these two sensibilities, and the tension can be felt in the book.</p>
        <p>In doctrines of just war, you can't kill unless you are willing to die. The ''virtual war'' in Kosovo, a ''set of split-second decisions made through the lens of a gun camera,'' runs up against those time-honored notions, Ignatieff writes. It was fought by air crews and technicians; NATO fought ''in the hope and expectation that there would be no casualties at all.'' Those were the terms under which the American president stepped into Kosovo. Technological mastery did the trick; the NATO leaders waged a war without mobilizing their societies. ''What was new about the Kosovo war, therefore, was the impunity with which it was waged. But if impunity is required before values are defended, what exactly are values worth?''</p>
        <p>I take Ignatieff's point about the ''virtuality'' of the war and the discrepancy between NATO firepower and Serbian capabilities. But Ignatieff exaggerates the novelty of this. After reading him, I picked up ''The Light That Failed.'' In that haunting semiautobiographical work of Kipling, colonial wars have their own ''virtuality''; the discrepancy between the colonial armies with the Maxim guns and native armies with primitive weapons foreshadows that between NATO and Serbia. The 1890's was a time of imperial sunset and Kipling must have intuited that: Charles George Gordon (Chinese Gordon) had lost his life in the Sudan. An army bent on revenge went up the Nile under the command of Horatio Herbert Kitchener. At Omdurman in the fall of 1898, Kitchener engaged the Sudanese. It was long ago, but a turkey shoot all the same: 28 Britons died, and 10,000 Sudanese. Over the horizon could be felt the tremors of the Boer War, which was for the world then what these wars of conscience are to ours today. Kipling lamented the distance of it all, its remoteness from England: ''With the soldiers sweated and toiled the correspondents of the newspapers, and they were almost as ignorant as their companions. But it was above all necessary that England at breakfast should be amused and thrilled and interested, whether Gordon lived or died, or half the British Army went to pieces in the sands.''</p>
        <p>When Milosevic called off his bid for Kosovo a year ago, he gave his countrymen an accounting of losses by Serbia's armed forces. If he is to be believed, the Yugoslav Army lost 462 men, the police force 114. Lovers strolled on the bridges of Belgrade, so precise was the NATO bombing and so restrained. In the annals of Serbian history chroniclers lament the misfortunes of Serbia in dark times. They ought to make an allowance for another history. They ought to tell of the small price paid by Serbia when outsiders came in, against the advice of the pollsters and realists and believers in the primacy of ''geoeconomics,'' to prosecute a just war, pulled into Kosovo as they had earlier been into Bosnia by the shame of what they witnessed, by the image of themselves they had seen in that Balkan mirror.</p>
        <p>Fouad Ajami, a professor of Middle Eastern studies at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, is the author of ''The Dream Palace of the Arabs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Fouad Ajami, a professor of Middle Eastern studies at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, is the author of ''The Dream Palace of the Arabs.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
