<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Television Sponsors the Film Industry</title>
    <meta content="11HOHE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOHENADEL, KRISTIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2D7143FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Television Sponsors the Film Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KRISTIN HOHENADEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOHENADEL, KRISTIN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kristin Hohenadel article on major role that Europe's public and private television networks has assumed in financing feature films for theatrical release; number of channels, particularly in France, Germany and Britain, are increasing financial support, garnered from public funds derived from taxes on television companies and by pre-sale agreements, in attempt to compete with Hollwyood; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TELEVISION may be the dirtiest four-syllable word in the American cultural lexicon. But if we like to blame the medium for dragging down our collective taste and I.Q., in Europe, television is still perceived as a cultural institution with a mission to inform as well as amuse. It may be host to dubbed ''Dukes of Hazzard'' reruns, American-style celebrity magazines and inane game shows, but turn on network television tonight in France and you're as likely to see a documentary about poverty in India or a full-length broadcast of ''Carmen.''</p>
        <p>You're also likely to see theatrical films that were not simply bought by the networks but were also made by them. Yes, there is made-for-TV drama in Europe, and it runs the gamut from movie-of-the-week melodrama to educational projects like the complete plays of Beckett on Channel 4 in Britain and the forthcoming ''Les Miserables'' with Gerard Depardieu and John Malkovich on TF1 in France. But there is also what you might call made-for-movies TV: European television networks, whether public or private, are the major players in financing feature films for theatrical release. Many observers believe that the dominance of television support has left Europeans to make small, cheap, character-driven films that can't compete in a world market. But a number of European channels -- particularly in France, Germany and Britain -- are devoting increasing financial resources in an attempt to compete with Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TELEVISION may be the dirtiest four-syllable word in the American cultural lexicon. But if we like to blame the medium for dragging down our collective taste and I.Q., in Europe, television is still perceived as a cultural institution with a mission to inform as well as amuse. It may be host to dubbed ''Dukes of Hazzard'' reruns, American-style celebrity magazines and inane game shows, but turn on network television tonight in France and you're as likely to see a documentary about poverty in India or a full-length broadcast of ''Carmen.''</p>
        <p>You're also likely to see theatrical films that were not simply bought by the networks but were also made by them. Yes, there is made-for-TV drama in Europe, and it runs the gamut from movie-of-the-week melodrama to educational projects like the complete plays of Beckett on Channel 4 in Britain and the forthcoming ''Les Miserables'' with Gerard Depardieu and John Malkovich on TF1 in France. But there is also what you might call made-for-movies TV: European television networks, whether public or private, are the major players in financing feature films for theatrical release. Many observers believe that the dominance of television support has left Europeans to make small, cheap, character-driven films that can't compete in a world market. But a number of European channels -- particularly in France, Germany and Britain -- are devoting increasing financial resources in an attempt to compete with Hollywood.</p>
        <p>According to a study by the European Audiovisual Observatory in Strasbourg, France, television investment accounts for between 30 and 74 percent of the financing for the production of feature films in Europe, depending upon the country. Much of that revenue is generated by public funds derived from taxes on television companies and by pre-sale agreements, in which television stations support projects in exchange for the right to broadcast the films two years after their theatrical release.</p>
        <p>The Audiovisual Observatory, which gathers data about broadcast media in 34 countries, reported that almost 80 percent of the feature films produced in Europe are made in Germany, France, Spain, Italy and Britain. And in all those countries, filmmakers receive some degree of financing from television.</p>
        <p>Television companies are the driving force in the business development of filmmaking in Europe, with Canal-Plus in France, Britain's Channel 4 and others acting as mini-film studios. In the last few years, they have expanded their involvement with the creation of Studio Canal-Plus and FilmFour Limited, stand-alone entities that receive funds from the channels that own them but produce movies for theatrical release. The films, of course, have second and third lives on free and pay channels; but European television serves to support, not compete with, national film industries. In France, for example, pre-sale contributions from television networks are generally not paid until the film is shown in theaters; this prevents the possibility of straight-to-TV movies, but has created the need for short-term bank loans to see filmmakers through development, production and post-production. Film advertising is not allowed on French television, to provide something of a level playing field for rich production companies and more modest independent producers.</p>
        <p>American network television's contribution to dramatic filmmaking is the Movie of the Week, but in Europe even commercial television isn't automatically dismissed as an ersatz vehicle for interesting work. ''There's no stigma for actors, writers, directors, because of the structure and depth of British television and the history of the BBC,'' said Paul Webster, who heads FilmFour. ''If Ian Holm does a TV production, it won't affect his career like it would Gene Hackman's.'' It was a British television performance that led to Ralph Fiennes's Hollywood career-launching role in ''Schindler's List.'' Ingmar Bergman's ''Scenes From a Marriage'' (1973) is an edited version of a six-part drama originally made for Swedish TV. Some of Britain's most experimental directors -- Ken Loach, Mike Leigh and Danny Boyle -- started in television. (In the case of Mr. Leigh, those were BBC plays done without a script.) Recently, two noted French directors made challenging films for the French-German channel Arte -- Claire Denis's ''Beau Travail'' and Erick Zonca's ''Petit Voleur'' -- that were later released theatrically, further obscuring the boundaries between films made for television and films destined for the multiplex.</p>
        <p>Of course, Arte, which is broadcast free in France, Germany, Belgium, Luxembourg and Switzerland, is considered the most broad-minded and erudite channel in Europe. Europeans grow up reading subtitles, and Arte's programs are often seen in their original language with local subtitles. Some 40 percent of Arte's content consists of documentaries from around the world, many shown in prime time. ''We are a European cultural channel, but we try to discover the world through beautiful films from everywhere,'' said George Goldenstern, general director of co-production for Arte. Mr. Goldenstern's channel participated in the international co-production of Lars von Trier's ''Breaking the Waves,''  ''The Idiots'' and ''Dancer in the Dark,'' which just won the Palme d'Or at the Cannes International Film Festival and was pre-sold to several European television channels.</p>
        <p>There is continuing debate in Europe about whether it's healthy for a handful of television executives to exert so much influence on the taste of feature filmmaking, but Mr. Goldenstern insists that he makes choices based on the strength of the script and if he interferes at all, it's during the editing stage of a film.</p>
        <p>Vibeke Windelov, who produces Mr. von Trier's films for the Denmark-based Zentropa Films, says: ''I've never had a comment from Arte or Canal-Plus. They have no influence on what I'm doing and never tried to.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Windelov estimated that about 25 percent of the funds for ''Dancer in the Dark'' came from television participation, including contributions from Arte and COBO, a Dutch cultural broadcasting fund whose revenue derives from reinvested foreign cable rights fees. ''Lars wouldn't be able to make movies if it wasn't for people like Arte and Canal-Plus who are willing to go in and give the real money,'' Ms. Windelov said. Mr. von Trier now makes his films in English, like many European filmmakers. It's a way for them to reach a wider audience and guarantee better distribution, but it also means that they don't qualify for subsidies intended to promote national language and culture.</p>
        <p>Vicente Gomez, the head of Lolafilms, Spain's largest film distributor, emphasizes that television investment is crucial to getting projects made in Spain: ''The average cost of a film in Spain is $2 million; of that, one-third comes from national subsidies that support Spanish-language films, another third from television, and the last from theatrical, video and foreign sales. Today all films end up on the small screen eventually, but European producers depend on television money because the budgets are lower. If the average cost of an American studio picture is $56 million, television is not going to be a determining factor. But for us the television money becomes crucial. Who's going to buy a $2 million picture around the world in Spanish?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gomez said that Spanish television executives favor films with a wide appeal that can be shown in prime time. ''They don't support sex, violence, auteur films,'' he explained. But the restrictions, he said, might be considered liberal by American standards: uncut versions of ''Basic Instinct'' and ''Last Tango in Paris'' were recently broadcast in Spanish prime time.</p>
        <p>And compared to executives at Fox or Disney, he said, Spanish executives are a piece of cake: ''They're not so pretentious and aggressive. They don't get too much involved. They either like a script or don't; but they won't keep you waiting for a year making changes.''</p>
        <p>The European Audiovisual Observatory reported that in newly privatized countries such as Hungary and Poland, television has sustained film production by taking up the slack left by weakened public funding. In Poland, for example, 75 percent of film production is now paid for by television. But some filmmakers feel that support is geared toward commercial films that are an easy sell. ''In Hungary, public television is not so open to the film industry and was never so important for the film industry as in western Europe,'' said the Hungarian director Istvan Szabo, who made his best-known film, ''Mephisto'' (1981), in German. ''Here there is a low-minded fight between television people and film people, so there is never very good work between them.''</p>
        <p>In the almost 20 years since its founding, Channel 4, the backer of ''Trainspotting'' and ''East Is East,'' has been widely credited with pumping life back into the ailing British film industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Loach, who has been making films in England for more than three decades, sees the involvement of television as ''the most important development in British and European cinema over the last 15 years.'' He began his career at the BBC, directing police shows in the 1960's; his last film, ''Bread and Roses,'' was in competition at Cannes and is scheduled to open in the United States later this year. Its $5 million budget included funds from FilmFour and Arte. ''Throughout the 70's,'' he said, ''it was virtually impossible to make cinema films -- certainly in our country -- that looked to Europe or to Britain. Everything had to look across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>''Channel 4's policy of investing in a film that was basically looking to  Britain or Europe on a budget that was appropriate for that audience, and withholding it on television for two years -- that really opened the doors for everyone. From the 80's up until now, it made it possible for some of us to work in the cinema.''</p>
        <p>But now that the world market is increasingly receptive to British talent, there is talk in Britain about whether the hand that has fed the film industry has also stunted its growth. ''It's always difficult to quantify what makes TV versus films,'' Mr. Webster said. ''But too often material that is better suited to the small screen ends up on the big screen in the U.K., and that's potentially the downside. I don't think that the power of television or the quality has held back the film industry in the U.K. or Europe in general, in fact, but it may lead to more mistakes; TV people don't know how difficult it is to get an audience. I think the immaturity that exists in the industry happens much more often at the level of sales and distribution.''</p>
        <p>And making films that can capture worldwide audiences whose moviegoing tastes have been shaped by the big American-style cinema experience seems to be the main objective of many European broadcasters, once content to satisfy their local markets. ''The point about movies is they ought to be seen, and quite a lot of movies go into a black hole in this country,'' said Alan Yentob, director of drama, entertainment and children's programming at the BBC, which is in the early stages of stepping up its feature filmmaking efforts. If nearly every film will end up on the network anyway, they reason, why not aim to make a go of it at the box office first? ''The BBC has always been involved in film,'' Mr. Yentob said, ''in that we've given opportunities to a lot of key talent. We want to use our leverage and clout now to make more ambitious films, greater in scale that will get an audience around the world.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Kristin Hohenadel is an American living in Paris and writing about the arts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kristin Hohenadel is an American living in Paris and writing about the arts.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
