<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trotting Out the Latest Reinvention of Al Gore</title>
    <meta content="11SUN3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EDITORIAL OBSERVER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DA1F3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trotting Out the Latest Reinvention of Al Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven R Weisman Editorial Observer column sees some historical basis for notion that Al Gore's repeated efforts to reinvent himself stem from the inherent difficulties of being Vice President, but worries that it also indicates Gore has not yet discovered his real personality and real views on issues</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the risk of self-parody, Al Gore is trying once again this month to break out of a slump by reintroducing himself to voters. He isn't changing his clothes this time, but he is avoiding personal attacks and unveiling big policy ideas connected in some way to life stories. Yet Mr. Gore still seems unable to exploit his obvious advantages as a partner in an administration with policies that most Americans support.</p>
        <p>Why, the candidate must wonder, can Gov. George W. Bush reposition himself as a moderate with such ease while his own reinventions draw ridicule?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the risk of self-parody, Al Gore is trying once again this month to break out of a slump by reintroducing himself to voters. He isn't changing his clothes this time, but he is avoiding personal attacks and unveiling big policy ideas connected in some way to life stories. Yet Mr. Gore still seems unable to exploit his obvious advantages as a partner in an administration with policies that most Americans support.</p>
        <p>Why, the candidate must wonder, can Gov. George W. Bush reposition himself as a moderate with such ease while his own reinventions draw ridicule?</p>
        <p>One reason may be that there have been so many of them. But the dominant theory is that Mr. Gore simply does not connect with people. He is seen as too stiff, too eager to please, too caught up in policy gobbledygook to excite voters. Campaign aides prefer, for obvious reasons, another explanation. They believe that most of Mr. Gore's problems stem from the inherent difficulties of being vice president. If so, they say, Mr. Gore may not be able to make serious headway in reversing his fortunes until the Democratic convention, when he assumes command of the party, selects a vice president and delivers an acceptance speech.</p>
        <p>It is a self-serving theory, but history provides some basis for it. In studying past election cycles, the Gore campaign has found that at this time of year, sitting vice presidents like George Bush in 1988, Hubert Humphrey in 1968 and Richard Nixon in 1960 were all behind in the polls. So were vice presidents who had acceded to the White House, like Harry Truman in 1948 and Gerald Ford in 1976. The problem is that, of all these, only Truman and Mr. Bush went on to win in November.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign likes to think of the Bush campaign in 1988 as  a model. Mr. Gore aims to raise doubts about the qualifications of his less experienced opponent the way the elder Mr. Bush did about Gov. Michael Dukakis of Massachusetts. But the more apt comparison may actually be 1960. Indeed, the author Richard Reeves, who is writing a book about Nixon, likens Mr. Gore's situation now to the one that Nixon found himself in against John Kennedy.</p>
        <p>In that year, Mr. Reeves points out, Nixon was the experienced Washington hand with a great reputation as a debater and infighter, running against an opponent widely dismissed as a charming lightweight. There were also a lot of ''new Nixons'' foreshadowing the ''new Gores'' of today. Many political experts back then said that all Kennedy had to do was deliver a credible performance at the debates, and he would be deemed a winner. Some even contend to this day that Nixon won the debates on points, while Kennedy won on style, changing politics forever, possibly to Mr. Gore's disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Nixon's narrow loss to Kennedy has been attributed to many things, including possible skulduggery in the voting in Chicago. But one factor may have also been Nixon's proud refusal to have President Dwight Eisenhower campaign for him except in the final rounds, when Nixon surged in the polls and almost caught up with Kennedy. Ike had a low opinion of Nixon, according to various memoirs, but still wanted him to win. He was said to have been puzzled and irritated by the Nixon campaign's attitude. ''All we want out of Ike,'' a Nixon adviser told Theodore H. White during the campaign, ''is for him to handle Khrushchev at the U.N. and not let things blow up there. That's all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's problem is that he may need President Clinton to help him, at least in the states where Mr. Clinton is most popular, without turning off voters in other states and making the vice president feel diminished just as he is trying to stand on his own. From Eisenhower to Lyndon Johnson to Ronald Reagan, there is a rich history of presidents having deeply mixed feelings about seeing their chosen vice presidents succeed them. Mr. Clinton apparently has no such ambivalence, although by some accounts he has been critical of Mr. Gore's stump style and his campaign team.</p>
        <p>Whether or not the theory of the burden of the vice presidency is valid, Mr. Gore's reinventions show that he has yet to communicate -- and perhaps settle on -- a riveting narrative for himself. It must be said that Mr. Bush, while he is campaigning more smoothly right now, has not exactly pulled the sword from the stone yet either. We are still waiting for the moment when a successful candidate fashions a reason for running and grows as a result of a series of ordeals. From Ronald Reagan's ''Shining City on the Hill'' to Bill Clinton's ''Man From Hope,'' truly successful politicians have a knack for sculpting a sense of destiny for themselves.</p>
        <p>Heroic or not, the vice president has done well in those moments when he appeared to be facing long odds. His campaign in the primary had its excesses, but he came across as a tough combatant and drew strength from that image. The challenge facing Mr. Gore now may paradoxically help him reach that image again. For now, however, he faces not only a contest against Mr. Bush, but also, after a lifetime in public life, a battle to define himself in the eyes of the nation he wants to lead.</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL OBSERVER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
