<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Cheap Stock Trades Aren't Cheap</title>
    <meta content="11WATC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Gretchen Morgenson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D81E3FF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Cheap Stock Trades Aren't Cheap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gretchen Morgenson Market Watch column warns online trading is far costlier than most investors seem to realize and has done little to level playing field in individual investors' competition with professionals; notes General Accounting Office study found delays and breakdowns are a big problem, online brokerages provide customers with little information, and investors often do not get best execution; notes Securities and Exchange Commission found 17 of 29 firms studied improperly emphasized payment for order flow in deciding where to send orders; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE popularity of online stock trading has exploded as individual investors have come to believe that their computers put them on the same level as the professionals, at a very low cost.</p>
        <p>But it is becoming increasingly clear that online trading is far costlier than most investors think. Moreover, it does little to level the investment playing field. Instead, judging from a report released last week by the General Accounting Office, online brokerage firms are Wall Street's latest incarnation of the Wild Wild West.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE popularity of online stock trading has exploded as individual investors have come to believe that their computers put them on the same level as the professionals, at a very low cost.</p>
        <p>But it is becoming increasingly clear that online trading is far costlier than most investors think. Moreover, it does little to level the investment playing field. Instead, judging from a report released last week by the General Accounting Office, online brokerage firms are Wall Street's latest incarnation of the Wild Wild West.</p>
        <p>Government researchers collected data from 12 online firms in 1999. They were not identified, but they accounted for almost 90 percent of online trades.</p>
        <p>Delays and breakdowns were a big problem -- so common at one firm that it said management did not track them.</p>
        <p>Online firms provide customers with little information, the G.A.O. found, on the risks of margin trading -- that is, using borrowed money to buy stocks. Nearly half the companies did not detail the risks for their customers opening margin accounts; only a third posted on their Web sites such information as the list of stocks they would not allow customers to buy on margin. One investor found he had bought such a stock only when his broker called to demand $75,000.</p>
        <p>But even these problems pale compared with the difficulties investors have getting online trades executed at the best possible price. Good execution is crucial to improving investors' profits. But because the way a firm handles a trade is not as apparent as the $8 commission it charges, few investors understand how important execution is or how they can be victimized.</p>
        <p>Included in the report was a review by the Securities and Exchange Commission of 29 online brokerage firms. Last year, the S.E.C. found, more than half were not meeting their obligation to provide the best execution for their customers' trades. A major reason is that most online firms have other firms complete their customers' trades in exchange for payments of as much as 1 or 2 cents a share. These payments, big surprise, determine where a customer's order is sent, even if another market or trader is offering a better price. On a 1,000-share sale, a customer would receive $62.50 more if he got a price one-sixteenth above the prevailing market.</p>
        <p>Of the 29 firms the S.E.C. investigated, 17 ''improperly emphasized payment for order flow in deciding where to send orders.'' The regulators said the firms did not even try to assess the prices available from trading firms other than those that were paying them. Indeed, most routed orders to traders whose execution quality was well below industry averages.</p>
        <p>It is high time investors understand that payment for order flow is corrupting trade executions at many online firms -- and costing investors a bundle. Steve Galbraith, a senior analyst at Sanford Bernstein, an investment firm in New York, said such conduct helped explain the outsized profitability of some online brokerage firms.</p>
        <p>''Execution is the securities industry's best-kept secret, and payment for order flow is part of that,'' Mr. Galbraith said. ''You're seeing monopolistic-type returns in what really should be structurally an economically competitive industry. I think it's one of the paradoxes of the market today.''</p>
        <p>Senator Carl Levin, the Michigan Democrat who requested the G.A.O. study, agreed. ''Pay for order flow is a good deal for the broker but is too often a bad deal for their clients,'' he said. ''The S.E.C. needs to get after this problem quickly and aggressively.'' Until then, investors are vulnerable to bad executions and the high costs associated with them.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. should require brokerage firms to monitor trade executions, tracking how many trades are done at prices better than those specified by investors. This is the information age. Why should investors be clueless about how much money they are losing when they trade stocks?</p>
        <p>MARKET WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
