<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Syria's Leader Assad Dies, Clouding Mideast Prospects</title>
    <meta content="11SYR.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRANSITION IN SYRIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Bashar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Hafez Al- (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Syria's Leader Assad Dies, Clouding Mideast Prospects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Hafez al-Assad, standard-bearer of Arab nationalism and anti-Zionist fervor who ruled Syria for three decades, dies at age 69; his death from heart attack casts cloud of uncertainty over dynamics of peace and conflict in Middle East; his son, Bashar, is expected to succeed him; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Hafez al-Assad of Syria, a standard-bearer of Arab nationalism and anti-Zionist fervor who ruled his country with an iron hand for three decades, died today at 69 in Damascus.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Assad had long been in ill health, his death from a heart attack casts a quick cloud of uncertainty over the dynamics of peace and conflict in the Middle East. [Obituary, Page 51.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Hafez al-Assad of Syria, a standard-bearer of Arab nationalism and anti-Zionist fervor who ruled his country with an iron hand for three decades, died today at 69 in Damascus.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Assad had long been in ill health, his death from a heart attack casts a quick cloud of uncertainty over the dynamics of peace and conflict in the Middle East. [Obituary, Page 51.]</p>
        <p>Syria itself, however, moved swiftly to give at least the appearance of stability. After the announcement of the death, Parliament began to pave the way for Mr. Assad's son Bashar, a 34-year-old ophthalmologist and army colonel, to take over.</p>
        <p>While an autocrat who brooked no dissent, Mr. Assad transformed Syria from a backwater nation into a semideveloped one and, more important, a regional power broker. Over the years, he earned begrudging acceptance from world leaders who criticized his outmoded Soviet-style leadership but came to appreciate his courtly tenacity and deep-seated convictions.</p>
        <p>''We had our differences, but I always respected him,'' President Clinton said today as he issued condolences from Northfield, Minn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad leaves big shoes to fill at the helm of a nation of 17 million whose isolation is reflected in the fact that it remains largely unconnected to the Internet.</p>
        <p>After the death of his oldest son in a car accident in 1994, Mr. Assad had turned to grooming his next oldest, Bashar, and a crucial formal step in the transition of power was to have taken place next Saturday during a rare political convention of Syria's ruling Baath Party.</p>
        <p>But Bashar Assad still has a potential family feud to quash with his uncle, Rifaat Assad, who always aspired to succeed his almost ascetic older brother. And beyond that, it is unclear whether the ruling Alawite ethnic minority led by the Assads will be able to retain its lock on Syrian politics under another member of the family.</p>
        <p>Bashar Assad, according to his father's authorized biographer, the English journalist Patrick Seale, ''would not deviate from his father's legacy.'' But even if he formally assumes power in the near future, it will take him considerable time to emerge from the shadow of his father and assert himself as leader.</p>
        <p>This opens up the possibility of a tense and destabilizing transition in Syria at a crucial time in the relationship between Syria and Lebanon and between Syria and Israel. Israel's recent troop withdrawal from southern Lebanon after 22 years scrambled the power lines in the Israeli-Lebanese-Syrian triangle.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Assad took a resolutely hard line toward Israel, many Western diplomats believed that he was the linchpin to any breakthrough between Israel and its northern neighbors. Many believed that only Mr. Assad was strong enough to deliver a change in five decades of hostile habits.</p>
        <p>Still, beneath anxiety about what lies in the immediate future, some Israeli and Western leaders expressed hope tonight that Mr. Assad's death could stimulate a new political and economic opening of Syria that could improve the chances for peace.</p>
        <p>''For 30 years, Assad was Syria, and Syria was Assad,'' said the Israeli Justice Minister, Yossi Beilin. ''With his death, this is undoubtedly a different Syria. My hope is that whoever will replace him will understand that Syria's only chance for serious economic growth will come by way of peace with Israel.''</p>
        <p>Palestinian leaders said they hoped that Palestinians and Syrians could reconcile after a long-strained relationship between Mr. Assad and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, which had put them at odds instead of side by side in their separate struggles with Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad had survived several assassination attempts and at least one previous heart attack and had suffered from a variety of debilitating illnesses for years. But despite his gaunt appearance and his infrequent travels abroad, many in Syria had wondered if talk of his imminent demise was not exaggerated.</p>
        <p>Syrian television made an official announcement only after the news had circulated first internationally. It showed members of the Syrian Parliament standing for a moment of silence, many of them crying and holding their heads in their hands.</p>
        <p>''This is a day of sadness and sorrow in every home, school, farm, factory and quarry,'' the announcer on state-run television said. ''Sadness is in the heart of every man, woman and child because the legacy of his accomplishments is a sun that will shine not just on this generation but on the many to come.''</p>
        <p>In Israel, state television interrupted regular programming to run live broadcasts from Parliament -- a highly unusual sight here -- that included recitations from the Koran in memory of Mr. Assad.</p>
        <p>When Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel first took office last sumer, he assiduously courted Mr. Assad, issuing flattering public messages about his strength as a leader. Mr. Barak and many Western experts believed that Mr. Assad wanted to return to peace talks with Israel in order to regain the Golan Heights in his lifetime and to ease the burden on his presumed successor, his son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad was Syria's defense minister when Syria lost the Golan in the 1967 Middle East war.</p>
        <p>But after the ice between Israel and Syria was broken last winter, the short-lived peace effort between the two nations, with the United States as intermediary, screeched to a halt.</p>
        <p>In Geneva in March, Mr. Clinton made a final, failed attempt to revive the talks at a meeting with Mr. Assad. The meeting ended with American pronouncements that its diplomatic focus would shift to the Israeli-Palestinian track.</p>
        <p>But after Israel withdrew its troops last month from Lebanon, where Syria is the power broker, officials here and in Syria voiced tentative questions about renewing the peace effort. Mr. Barak, however, said publicly this week that he was wondering if Mr. Assad would ever be fully behind it.</p>
        <p>Israel expressed condolences tonight to the Syrian nation, but it also voiced concern over how a transition period would affect the calm that has reigned on its northern border since the troop withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''Israel views with importance the keeping of quiet on its borders with Syria and Lebanon and expects that Syria will continue to do so, too,'' said a statement issued by Mr. Barak's office tonight.</p>
        <p>Syria possesses a largely Russian-equipped military machine that is believed to be far less potent today than when Mr. Assad, a career military man, assumed power in 1970. But with mid-range and long-range missiles, and with 30,000 troops stationed in Lebanon, it remains a force to be reckoned with in the region.</p>
        <p>Syria installed the current civilian leadership of Lebanon. But after the recent Israeli troop withdrawal and with eagerness to reconcile their nation, the Lebanese leaders as well as the Hezbollah guerrilla movement backed by Syria and Iran started to test just how much autonomy Damascus would permit. This transition period could strengthen their move in that direction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad, known as the Lion of Damascus because his family name means lion in Arabic, was one of the last surviving members of a generation of Arab rulers after the deaths of King Hassan of Morocco and King Hussein of Jordan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad had surprised Middle East observers by attending King Hussein's funeral, a visit that marked a warming in what had been an icy relationship with Jordan. Since then, the late King Hussein's son, King Abdullah, has been a frequent visitor to Damascus and has cultivated a personal relationship with his fellow Western-educated scion, Bashar Assad.</p>
        <p>In much of the Arab world, Mr. Assad was seen as a purist who remained until his death one of the last few believers in Arab nationalism. He disdained those, like Egypt, Jordan and lastly the Palestinian Authority, that negotiated individual peace treaties with Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Assad believed that Israel wielded too much power in the region, and that the peace treaties reflected the imbalance of power.</p>
        <p>The Arab League praised him tonight as ''one who devoted his life to serving the Arab and Islamic nations and fighting for the recovery of their land and for Arab right.'' And in Gaza City, Mr. Arafat called for a three-day period of mourning and said the Palestinian people ''would stand with their Syrian brothers and believe in their ability to survive this critical moment.''</p>
        <p>In Syria, Mr. Assad will be remembered quietly for some other traits as well -- like intolerance and the fear he inspired. A momentous marker of this was a massacre in Hama in 1982, when Mr. Assad succeeded in squelching an Islamic insurgency by having thousands killed.</p>
        <p>Still, the country immediately fell into deep mourning today. Black banners were unfurled from apartment house balconies in Damascus, and noise in the streets stilled. Preparation got under way tonight for his funeral, scheduled for Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Lebanese television reported tonight that Prime Minister Emile Lahoud of Lebanon had been talking to Mr. Assad on the telephone earlier today when the line suddenly went dead. ''His last words were, 'Our destiny is to build a better future for our countries,' '' Mr. Lahoud said of Mr. Assad. ''And then there was a silence, and I knew something had happened.''</p>
        <p>TRANSITION IN SYRIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
