<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coup Talk Empties Beaches And Fiji's Cash Registers</title>
    <meta content="11FIJI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fiji</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Fiji</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Fiji</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5DD163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coup Talk Empties Beaches And Fiji's Cash Registers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>NADI, Fiji, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fiji's tourism industry is drying up during attempted coup by rebels who occupy Parliament and hold three dozen hostages; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On approximately 299 and two-thirds of its 300 islands, there are no indications that Fiji is in turmoil, with rebels occupying Parliament and holding three dozen hostages who include the elected prime minister, much of his Cabinet and the daughter of the country's president.</p>
        <p>As Brad Ammann, a 29-year-old honeymooner from Hermosa Beach, Calif., put it: ''The only sign there's a coup going on is that there's nobody around.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On approximately 299 and two-thirds of its 300 islands, there are no indications that Fiji is in turmoil, with rebels occupying Parliament and holding three dozen hostages who include the elected prime minister, much of his Cabinet and the daughter of the country's president.</p>
        <p>As Brad Ammann, a 29-year-old honeymooner from Hermosa Beach, Calif., put it: ''The only sign there's a coup going on is that there's nobody around.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is very quiet here in the main tourist city. But if that is good news for the few visitors still enjoying these South Seas islands, it is also an economic disaster in the making.</p>
        <p>Fiji's primary industry is tourism, but with hotels and resorts at less than 10 percent of capacity, thousands of Fijians have been laid off or put on sharply reduced hours. The second-biggest industry is sugar cultivation, but with the European Union taking steps to boycott Fijian sugar and farmers refusing to harvest cane to protest the attempted coup, the Fiji Sugar Corporation also has said it may soon lay off 3,000 workers.</p>
        <p>The third big source of jobs is garment manufacturing, which has boomed since the mid-1990's when Australia granted preferential tariff treatment to Fijian-made clothes. But with Australian trade unions declining to handle any cargo to or from Fiji during the hostage crisis, that industry has quickly sagged too.</p>
        <p>Schools and many small stores are also closed. The armed rebels ''are not thinking of ordinary Fijians at all,'' Soni Kanta, the manager of Ashiyara, a nearly deserted Indian restaurant in the capital city, Suva, said the other evening as she made an angry gesture in the direction of the parliamentary complex. ''This is simply hurting everybody in the country.''</p>
        <p>Fijians are enormously graceful people, and many seem to have a remarkable ability to joke about their plight or say they have faith that all will be for the best. Still, individual tales of woe abound.</p>
        <p>One such story is that of Muhammad Ali Nasir, who emerged from his home the other day to give aid to a foreign visitor who had inadvertently lodged his rental car in a ditch while giving wide berth to an oncoming truck full of goats on a seaside road in Nadi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasir has been a woodcarver for 35 of his 49 years, and he has a little shop in one of the big resorts here. ''The hotel is first class, there is no doubt,'' Mr. Nasir said. ''And I am, if I may modestly say, a world-classy woodcarver. But right now, there is nobody to buy.''</p>
        <p>And so he is in danger of not being able to afford the rent anymore, explained Mr. Nasir, a Muslim man whose grandparents, as is the case with so many Fijians here of Indian descent, were brought to Fiji as indentured laborers in the sugar trade in the early 1900's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasir's economic distress soon made the foreigner's car-in-a-ditch quandary pale in comparison, and it was a problem soon solved anyway with the help of a friendly neighbor of Mr. Nasir's who hapaaaapened to own a tractor.</p>
        <p>Over a cup of tea in a neighbor's home, Mr. Nasir was philosophical: the crisis would soon end, he hoped, and he could resume selling his carvings, everything from salad bowls to statuettes of coconut palms swaying in the trade winds.</p>
        <p>''The tourists will return,'' he said, a mantra frequently repeated here.</p>
        <p>There are still tourists. But with the United States and other nations having advised citizens to defer ''nonessential travel'' to Fiji during the standoff, they are here in only a fraction of their normal numbers.</p>
        <p>Those that have come include travel-hardened young backpackers, imperturbable retirees and a group of Americans who made Nadi a port of call the other evening during a South Seas yachting trip from Palos Verdes, Calif., to New Zealand and back. (''Say, whatever happened to Microsoft?'' asked one sailor, who said he had been on the high seas for months and lost track of the government's antitrust battle with the software giant.)</p>
        <p>And many others explained, as did Mr. Ammann and his bride, that they lacked the travel insurance needed to reschedule a Fijian vacation.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't believe it when I heard there was a coup going on in Fiji,'' said Mr. Ammann, a 29-year-old contractor. ''I thought, what in the heck do Fijians have to be so upset about?'' (The rebels who seized Parliament are nationalistic indigenous Fijians agitated about the rise of Prime Minister Mahendra Chaudhry, the first ethnic Indian ever to hold that post. Indigenous Fijians make up about 51 percent of the population of 812,000; ethnic Indians, about 44 percent.)</p>
        <p>The Ammanns, married last month, decided to go ahead with their two-and-a-half-week honeymoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ammann concluded that the struggle was a ''local and political thing, something between Fijians'' that would be unlikely to visit violence upon foreigners.</p>
        <p>His wife, Lorren, 27, an interior designer, said: ''We'd planned this for so long. You only get one shot at a honeymoon.''</p>
        <p>Traveling around the islands, the Ammanns had Fiji virtually to themselves. On the island of Natadola, they checked into a dozen-room resort, only to find they were indeed the sole guests.</p>
        <p>It conjures up an image of Arcadia for a honeymoon couple, of course, to be alone on a South Pacific island.</p>
        <p>But as they walked about the resort, the two looked at each other and Mr. Ammann recalled remarking, ''This feels a little too weird. This is really creepy.'' Said Mrs. Ammann: ''I'm so glad you said that. Let's get out of here.''</p>
        <p>And so the couple high-tailed it to a hotel resort here, which, while uncrowded, does at least have a few people around.</p>
        <p>At the Shangri-La Fijian, on the island of Yanuca, occupancy is down to 8 percent of capacity, and 7,500 room nights have been canceled in the last three weeks, a loss of about $1.2 million for the 436-room resort, said Wolf-Dieter Flecker, the general manager.</p>
        <p>Asked what the resort told people who called to inquire about conditions, Mr. Flecker said: ''We tell them Shangri-La is fully operational, and it's up to them to choose whether to come.''</p>
        <p>In much of the country, there is no immediate sense of danger, but the United States Department of State describes the whole situation as ''highly volatile,'' capable of turning ugly at any moment.</p>
        <p>David Hausmann, 19, a visitor from London, who is ''taking sort of a gap here'' between his high school and college careers, said such warnings had added an undercurrent of tense excitement to his travels.</p>
        <p>''You never know what might happen. There is this sense of things sort of being on the edge,'' said Mr. Hausmann, who is wandering around the world with a backpack. ''There could be a civil war. I really doubt it, though.''</p>
        <p>So do most Fijians, though they fret constantly these days about what the current situation will do to their nation's image abroad. Fiji is one of several South Pacific nations that compete to market themselves as the ultimate tropical paradise.</p>
        <p>Here in the western part of the nation, which has the biggest resorts and best beaches, as well as most of the sugar and Fiji's biggest gold mine, and where race relations are often described as better than in eastern Fiji, some village chiefs and others have even proposed breaking off to form a separate country.</p>
        <p>That is an idea that has spread alarm in many quarters, though.</p>
        <p>''The unity of the Fijian people has never been more important than at this stage of our national development,'' Radike Qereqeretabua, a top tourism official in Fiji, told reporters. ''A secession of the western provinces will only break up the Fijian people even further, to the detriment of the country as a whole, and should not be a serious option.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
