<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books in Brief: Fiction &amp; Poetry</title>
    <meta content="RV091457" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waggoner, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rambaud, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Battle, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DF133CF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books in Brief: Fiction &amp; Poetry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeff Waggoner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waggoner, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Waggoner reviews book The Battle by Patrick Rambaud (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Battle  By Patrick Rambaud.  Grove, $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Battle  By Patrick Rambaud.  Grove, $25.</p>
        <p>A 313-page novel is tight quarters for a story about a battle that killed nearly 40,000 men in 48 hours, especially when practically every field commander is paraded past the reader, not to mention a crowd of lesser officers and orderlies, chasseurs and cuirassiers. Then there is the matter of special effects: providing the sounds of bugles and war cries; depicting the sabering, parrying and lunging, the men being run through the neck. All before a windup of death rattles, crying and screaming. ''The Battle'' is based in part on Balzac's notes on Napoleon's first major defeat on land -- in 1809 at Essling, near Vienna. Balzac apparently wanted to write about the battle but died before he could see the project through. In the notes accompanying his own novel, Patrick Rambaud speculates that Balzac was interested in the Battle of Essling because, as a historian of the Empire observed, it ''ushered in the era of the great hecatombs'' of modern warfare. This unsatisfying replacement for Balzac's book is long on scene setting and short on almost everything else, especially characterization. The reader follows the sensitive but courageous Col. Louis-Fran--&gt;ois Lejeune before and during the battle but is never quite sure why this particular soldier has been singled out. (We have to wait for the endnotes for an explanation: apparently Lejeune, a real historical figure, wrote his own memoirs of the event, providing Rambaud with his best first-person account.) ''The Battle,'' which has been ably translated by Will Hobson, has won a chestful of medals for its author, including the Prix Goncourt and the Grand Prix du Roman de l'Academie Fran--&gt;aise, but it is probably best left to aficionados of hailing round shot and green-plumed shakos.</p>
        <p>Jeff Waggoner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
