<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Presidential Challenger in Mexico Pitches Tent in Two Camps</title>
    <meta content="11MEXI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labastida, Francisco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardenas, Cuauhtemoc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1D8163EF932A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Presidential Challenger in Mexico Pitches Tent in Two Camps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicente Fox is mounting most serious challenge to Mexico's governing party in presidential election in 70 years; he has attracted supporters from across political spectrum; Francisco Labastida of governing Institutional Revolutionary Party is his main rival in July 2 presidential race; leftist candidate Cuauhtemoc Cardenas is running distant third; Fox photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To his opponents, Vicente Fox, who is mounting the most serious challenge to Mexico's governing party in a presidential election in 70 years, is a political chameleon who talks out of both sides of his mouth.</p>
        <p>To his supporters, he is a clever strategist who has built strength well beyond his small rightist party by defying ideological labels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To his opponents, Vicente Fox, who is mounting the most serious challenge to Mexico's governing party in a presidential election in 70 years, is a political chameleon who talks out of both sides of his mouth.</p>
        <p>To his supporters, he is a clever strategist who has built strength well beyond his small rightist party by defying ideological labels.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, it is clear that by pairing strong conservative credentials with a center-left position on a range of issues Mr. Fox has succeeded in attracting supporters from across the political landscape.</p>
        <p>He has received backing from conservative landowners and executives, and managed to wrest support from Cuauhtemoc Cardenas, the three-time leftist candidate who is running a distant third in the July 2 presidential race.</p>
        <p>In the process, however, Mr. Fox has wandered frequently into inconsistencies that have allowed his main rival, Francisco Labastida of the governing Institutional Revolutionary Party, to portray him as a slippery politician.</p>
        <p>In 1996, for instance, Mr. Fox acknowledged on a trip to New York that he favored privatizing the state-owned oil monopoly, Pemex, which is an icon of Mexican nationalism. In recent weeks, Mr. Labastida's commercials have portrayed those comments as treasonous. In response, Mr. Fox surrounded himself in one recent campaign ceremony with former communists and socialists who now back his candidacy and pledged never to privatize Pemex.</p>
        <p>In using issues against Mr. Fox, his adversaries have in some cases distorted his position. At other times, Mr. Fox has paid a price for speaking too glibly, as when he said in 1997 that he could solve the Chiapas conflict ''in 15 minutes.'' And sometimes he has waded into trouble by sharply changing the tone, if not the substance, of his statements before different audiences.</p>
        <p>This spring, for example, Mr. Fox attended a bankers' convention in Acapulco and, four days later, a congress of small entrepreneurs. Mr. Fox praised the bankers for keeping their institutions afloat in the turmoil that followed the 1994 peso devaluation. He mentioned, briefly, that financiers who committed fraud during the $90 billion taxpayer-financed bank bailout after the crisis ''must be brought to justice,'' but did not dwell on this uncomfortable topic. The bankers reacted with roaring applause. ''Fox told us what we wanted to hear,'' said Roberto Gonzalez, one bank president.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Fox met with the small entrepreneurs, who loathe the bankers because, even though taxpayer funds rescued the banks after the 1994 crisis, they have refused to extend new loans to thousands of small businesses sliding into bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the entrepreneurs voiced their resentments to Mr. Fox, who joined right in, this time detailing at length his plans for prosecuting those suspected of fraud. Mr. Labastida and Mr. Cardenas called him a hypocrite.</p>
        <p>''One day he says south and the next day he says north,'' Mr. Labastida said in a recent interview aboard his campaign jet. ''One day he tells the bankers they're guilty of nothing, and later he tells the industrialists he'll put the bankers in jail. He's a question mark in boots!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox wears boots to remind voters of his upbringing on an arid ranch in Guanajuato in central Mexico. In the 1920's, the armies of the postrevolutionary government waged a violent campaign in the region to suppress the Catholic Church, defended by peasant insurgents, the Cristeros. By some estimates, 250,000 Mexicans died.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox has invited comparisons between the Cristeros' struggle and his own crusade to defeat the governing party, ending campaign rallies with a Cristero war cry: ''If I advance, follow me! If I stop, push me! If I retreat, kill me!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox was educated by Jesuits before embarking on a business career that included five years as president of Coca-Cola's Mexican unit.</p>
        <p>When he entered politics with a 1988 run for Congress, he joined the National Action Party, known as the PAN. Founded in 1939 by Catholic professionals and shopkeepers opposed to President Lazaro Cardenas, Cuauhtemoc's father, whom they considered a socialist, the party was for half a century Mexico's only permanent opposition party. That made it a natural vehicle for Mr. Fox, but he had a complaint: the party had won few elections.</p>
        <p>After what many Mexicans considered to be a fraudulent victory by the governing party in the 1988 presidential voting, he and other opposition congressmen tried to retrieve disputed ballots from the basement of the Congress. Soldiers, rifles raised, barred their way, but his gutsy stand won him admirers.</p>
        <p>He turned his first run for Guanajuato governor in 1991 into a crusade against governing party corruption. After a disputed election that Mr. Fox called fraudulent, he led weeks of street protests but was denied the governorship. Running again four years later, he won easily.</p>
        <p>Throughout most of the 1990's, Mr. Fox pursued a cordial dialogue with a changing group of leftist intellectuals, often at the Mexico City home of Jorge Castaneda, the author. Roberto Mangabeira Unger, a Brazilian political theorist who is a professor at Harvard University, recalled meeting Mr. Fox in 1996. ''I'm always on the lookout for insurrectionists,'' he said. ''And my intuition told me, here's the man.''</p>
        <p>In the post-cold-war world, Mr. Unger said, being a leftist means encouraging grass-roots participation in democracies and seeking better access to credit, technology and markets for small producers.</p>
        <p>''Fox is willing to embrace these ideas,'' he said. ''He's not tied to the old orthodoxies, he's seeking a different way for Mexico. And by this standard he's much more of a leftist than Cardenas or Labastida.''</p>
        <p>One view Mr. Fox adopted during this dialogue was that Mexico must raise, not lower, tax revenues, a position at odds with the PAN's longtime call for a tax cut.</p>
        <p>His main economic thrust, however, has been a call to increase Mexico's growth rate to 7 percent through deregulation and foreign investment. Mr. Labastida called the suggestion ''unsustainable.''</p>
        <p>Recent zigzags in his posture toward the Catholic Church have hurt Mr. Fox. He celebrated his formal nomination as the National Action Party's candidate at a rally by holding aloft an image of the Virgin of Guadalupe, irritating millions of Protestants and anticlerical Mexicans. He quickly apologized.</p>
        <p>But last month newspapers published a letter from Mr. Fox to the bishops in which he pledged to lift restrictions on religious activity that are a holdover from Mexico's anticlerical past, and also to promote ''respect for life'' from conception to death. Mr. Fox has many times expressed his opposition to abortion, which is illegal in Mexico, but this pledge aroused fears that he might seek to make anti-abortion laws  more restrictive.</p>
        <p>He has sought to reassure feminists and leftists who fear the church by pledging ''never to use the power of the state to impose lifestyles or religious beliefs.'' Marta Lamas, a prominent feminist, is not convinced.  ''I hate the PRI, but my fear of Fox is so great,'' she said, ''that I'll heave a sigh of relief if the PRI wins.''</p>
        <p>But portrayals of Mr. Fox as a macho boor do not fit him either. After defeating Malu Micher, a feminist candidate who ran against him for governor in 1995, he worked with her to devise programs in Guanajuato to benefit rural women.</p>
        <p>''Vicente is a special case,'' Ms. Micher said recently. ''He views parties and all the formalities of politics as a bother. He doesn't fit within the framework of the traditional politician.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
