<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camby Misses Practice, But Says Don't Worry</title>
    <meta content="24KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/sports/24KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DB1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camby Misses Practice, But Says Don't Worry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., Oct. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses problems besetting New York Knickerbockers basketball player Marcus Camby (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just when Marcus Camby's play around the basket was beginning to outshine the condition of his ailing right knee, the Knicks were hit with a reminder of how frighteningly fragile the health of their gangly center is. Camby sat out of practice today with pain in his lower back.</p>
        <p>Camby said the injury was not serious, and that he would play Tuesday in an exhibition game against the Nets at the Meadowlands. But Camby's history of injuries makes it difficult to dismiss his pain as one of the inconsequential bumps and bruises that afflict players during a National Basketball Association season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just when Marcus Camby's play around the basket was beginning to outshine the condition of his ailing right knee, the Knicks were hit with a reminder of how frighteningly fragile the health of their gangly center is. Camby sat out of practice today with pain in his lower back.</p>
        <p>Camby said the injury was not serious, and that he would play Tuesday in an exhibition game against the Nets at the Meadowlands. But Camby's history of injuries makes it difficult to dismiss his pain as one of the inconsequential bumps and bruises that afflict players during a National Basketball Association season.</p>
        <p>How well the Knicks are able to overcome the absence of Patrick Ewing is tied directly to Camby's durability. And while Camby has played in all five preseason games, there have been signs that Coach Jeff Van Gundy's hopes of an 82-game season for Camby may be far-fetched.</p>
        <p>After resting his sore right knee for most of the summer, Camby opened training camp with complaints of pain in the knee and participated sparingly in the first few practices. He recovered quickly and competed fully over the next two weeks, but after battling the Washington Wizards' burly center, the 6-foot-9-inch, 290-pound Jahidi White, last week, Camby began experiencing back pain.</p>
        <p>Camby practiced and played through the pain for two games, but said the pain intensified today.</p>
        <p>''Ever since banging with Jahidi that night, it's been stiff and sore,'' Camby said. ''I'll be fine. I'll go and see the doctor today and just be cautious.''</p>
        <p>Camby has had back problems before. He missed 14 games during his rookie season with the Toronto Raptors with a lower back strain. He also had back pain during the 1998-1999 season, his first with the Knicks, but did not miss any games because of it.</p>
        <p>''He's always had something with his back,'' Van Gundy said today. ''But it's nothing major, I don't think.''</p>
        <p>Camby, who has never played more than 63 games in a season, said last week that his top goal this season was to stay healthy and to compete in all games and practices. Van Gundy is convinced that Camby, who has averaged 11.4 points and a team-high 8.6 rebounds during the preseason, will have a terrific season if he meets his goal.</p>
        <p>''I think he's going to have a big-time year the first year he plays close to 82 games,'' Van Gundy said. ''Our goal for him is 82, but if he plays a high number of games, he'll have a big-time year because any time you're going in and out of the lineup it takes time for you to get back to playing well, and then you're going out again.''</p>
        <p>While the Knicks have avoided any major injuries during training camp, nagging injuries have set them back.</p>
        <p>Glen Rice has been out for a week with a sore left knee, and though a magnetic resonance imaging test revealed no structural damage, he was not expected to play against the Nets.  Rice's unavailability has limited Van Gundy's chances to work him into the lineup with Latrell Sprewell and Allan Houston. But with the regular-season opener a week away, Van Gundy's main concern is fine-tuning his starting five. He noted that the Knicks' starting unit is the smallest in the league, averaging 6-5 1/2. The group's lack of energy defensively in hounding the ball and offensively in pushing it up the floor, disturbs him. He said his first team has been outscored over the first five minutes of the last six halves it has started.</p>
        <p>''We average 6-5 1/2 and we play as if we have a bunch of 7-footers,'' Van Gundy said. ''We're playing too slow. We don't play with enough ball pressure defensively. We're not swarming. I'd like to see our starters start doing that because if we're going to have a small starting team and we play like we're playing, it's going to be a really long year as far as digging ourselves holes.</p>
        <p>''I'm not bothered by being the smallest. I am if we're going to play as slowly and as lethargically and as low energy as we've been. When you've got small and slow, that's a bad combination.''</p>
        <p>If the agile Camby misses any time, the Knicks will be even smaller and slower.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Nets Chide Martin</p>
        <p>(By The New York Times), EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 23 -- Nets Coach Byron Scott today criticized Kenyon Martin, the team's top draft pick, for inconsistency and a lack of aggressiveness. Martin is averaging only 5 rebounds and 11.5 points in the preseason, with a total of two blocked shots.</p>
        <p>''I didn't see him being the aggressive Kenyon Martin I was used to seeing in college, just going after everything, blocking shots, rebounding the ball, defending, going up and down the floor,'' Scott said. ''He was doing it in spots.''</p>
        <p>Because Martin had not played for six months after he broke his leg last March, the Nets were bringing him along slowly in practices and Martin's conditioning has just been returning.</p>
        <p>''I knew I had been playing bad,'' Martin said. ''I produced one game, but it's got to be every night. I'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>The team said Kendall Gill will play against the Knicks after missing two games with a scratched left cornea.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
