<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Time for a Balkan Exit</title>
    <meta content="24TUE1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/opinion/24TUE1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5D81731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Time for a Balkan Exit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on way Bush campaign views America's proper military role in Europe, as described by Bush's foreign policy adviser, Condoleezza Rice; says Rice's proposal for reduced American military role in Balkans is misguided; says job of securing peace in Bosnia and Kosovo is far from complete; says NATO alliance is built on concept of shared risk that is inconsistent with total withdrawal of American ground forces from Balkan peacekeeping</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sharp contrasts emerged over the weekend in the way the Bush and Gore campaigns view America's proper military role in Europe. The debate began when Condoleezza Rice, one of Gov. George W. Bush's leading foreign policy advisers, told The Times's Michael Gordon that a Bush administration would ask European members of NATO to gradually take over full responsibility for providing peacekeeping forces for Bosnia and Kosovo. Vice President Gore countered that carrying out such a policy could destabilize the Balkans and jeopardize the future of NATO, America's most important military alliance.</p>
        <p>Debates over how and where United States military forces should be stationed are a healthy part of presidential contests. Ms. Rice's proposal is consistent with the Bush campaign's view that extended peacekeeping missions degrade the combat readiness of American military forces and that the Pentagon should concentrate its resources on preparing for crises where Washington alone has the might to deter, and, if necessary, combat aggression, whether in the Persian Gulf, the Korean Peninsula or a future military conflict in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sharp contrasts emerged over the weekend in the way the Bush and Gore campaigns view America's proper military role in Europe. The debate began when Condoleezza Rice, one of Gov. George W. Bush's leading foreign policy advisers, told The Times's Michael Gordon that a Bush administration would ask European members of NATO to gradually take over full responsibility for providing peacekeeping forces for Bosnia and Kosovo. Vice President Gore countered that carrying out such a policy could destabilize the Balkans and jeopardize the future of NATO, America's most important military alliance.</p>
        <p>Debates over how and where United States military forces should be stationed are a healthy part of presidential contests. Ms. Rice's proposal is consistent with the Bush campaign's view that extended peacekeeping missions degrade the combat readiness of American military forces and that the Pentagon should concentrate its resources on preparing for crises where Washington alone has the might to deter, and, if necessary, combat aggression, whether in the Persian Gulf, the Korean Peninsula or a future military conflict in Europe.</p>
        <p>But on the specifics of America's role in the Balkans, Ms. Rice's proposal is misguided for several reasons. The job of securing peace in Bosnia and Kosovo is far from complete. The American share of the peacekeeping has already been substantially reduced. Finally, the NATO alliance has been built on a concept of shared risk that is inconsistent with a total withdrawal of American ground forces from Balkan peacekeeping.</p>
        <p>It is true that military conditions in Bosnia are now more stable than they were when NATO troops were first introduced five years ago and that the situation in Kosovo has also improved in the year since Serbian forces withdrew. But in neither place is there yet enough security for displaced refugees to return to their homes or for elections to take place without the risk of physical intimidation. The departure of Slobodan Milosevic from Yugoslavia's presidency creates new opportunities for easing tensions in both Bosnia and Kosovo, provided local troublemakers can be kept in check. That will require a continued strong NATO presence.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration, meanwhile, has done a good job of insisting that America's share of peacekeeping responsibilities be steadily reduced. There are now only 11,400 American troops in the Balkans, about one-fifth of the NATO total. When NATO first went into Bosnia, about a third of its 60,000 troops were Americans. Balkan peacekeeping costs account for just over 1 percent of the Pentagon's $280 billion budget, leaving more than enough for military needs elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Asking Europe to accept a total withdrawal of American ground forces from the Balkans needlessly challenges some of the basic assumptions of the Western military alliance. NATO was formed not just to counter Soviet bloc military threats. It was also designed to eliminate some of the historic military rivalries in Europe that led to two world wars. NATO provides a framework for European and American forces to cooperate in joint operations under a single overall commander -- traditionally an American. Europe cannot be expected to accept an alliance in which Washington exercises political and military leadership but does not subject its own forces to any of the risks of ground operations. The Bush campaign is right when it insists that the United States must be selective in where it stations ground forces. But the Balkans is not the place to cut back.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
