<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testaverde Perseveres And Jets Follow</title>
    <meta content="24DOLP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/sports/24DOLP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dolphins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DA1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testaverde Perseveres And Jets Follow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Tuesday, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of New York Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde in victory over Miami Dolphins discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first time Vinny Testaverde dropped back to pass Monday night, he rolled to his right with ample time to survey the field. He continued floating toward the sideline in search of a receiver until he ran out of room and options, stepping out of bounds for a 2-yard loss.</p>
        <p>What Testaverde, the Jets' quarterback, saw on that first attempt hardly changed as the game wore on. He tried desperately to force his way through a stingy Miami Dolphins defense as the Jets' deficit grew larger and uglier. But as the scoreboard read 30-7 in favor of Miami, Testaverde stubbornly hung in, continuing to pick at the defense as the stands emptied in the third quarter, until his teammates and die-hard fans began to believe with him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first time Vinny Testaverde dropped back to pass Monday night, he rolled to his right with ample time to survey the field. He continued floating toward the sideline in search of a receiver until he ran out of room and options, stepping out of bounds for a 2-yard loss.</p>
        <p>What Testaverde, the Jets' quarterback, saw on that first attempt hardly changed as the game wore on. He tried desperately to force his way through a stingy Miami Dolphins defense as the Jets' deficit grew larger and uglier. But as the scoreboard read 30-7 in favor of Miami, Testaverde stubbornly hung in, continuing to pick at the defense as the stands emptied in the third quarter, until his teammates and die-hard fans began to believe with him.</p>
        <p>Testaverde forged an improbable comeback. Miami had not surrendered more than 16 points in a game this season, and the Jets needed 30 in one quarter to force overtime. But the Jets did come back, overcoming that 30-7 fourth-quarter deficit to knot the score at 30-30 with 3 minutes 55 seconds remaining on the way to a 40-37 overtime victory.</p>
        <p>Then, after the Dolphins jolted the Jets with a one-play drive, a 46-yard touchdown pass by Jay Fiedler to Leslie Shepherd, Testaverde took the field and methodically guided the Jets downfield again. And again.</p>
        <p>If it all seemed a little unbelievable, then it was no more unlikely that the 35-year-old offensive tackle Jumbo Elliott would juggle and then hang on to a pass from the 36-year-old Testaverde for a touchdown with 42 seconds remaining, tying the score at 37-37 and sending the game to overtime.</p>
        <p>In the extra session Testaverde completed the historic effort by driving the Jets 43 yards to set up a 40-yard John Hall field goal that gave the Jets the victory.</p>
        <p>Testaverde overcame a dismal performance through the first three quarters, finally providing a spark of life that ignited into an astounding fourth-quarter rally, finishing 36 of 59 for 378 yards and 5 touchdowns. Through three quarters, Testaverde was 15 of 28 for 102 yards with one touchdown and 3 interceptions. But in the fourth quarter, Testaverde completed 18 of 26 attempts for 235 yards and 4 touchdowns, carrying the Jets to the highest scoring quarter in their history. In overtime, he was 3 of 5 for 41 yards.</p>
        <p>Challenging a defensive unit that has allowed the fewest points in the National Football League this season, Testaverde struggled to find a crack, and also had little help from his teammates. Through three quarters, the Jets managed just 65 yards rushing on 16 attempts, most of it on draw plays as they desperately tried to loosen the Dolphins' defense. Testaverde stayed on the field and even showed a bit of dogged determination, refusing to slide on a scramble and battling tacklers for a first down in fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The Jets' offense did not record a first down until the midpoint of the second quarter and Testaverde was just 2 of 8 for 8 yards in the opening quarter. Things hardly got better for Testaverde in the second quarter. On the first play of the second quarter, he tried to force a ball to Laveranues Coles on a crossing pattern, but the ball was picked off as Sam Madison pushed in front of the Jets' rookie.</p>
        <p>As the deficit grew, Testaverde continued to try to get something started, but with little success. Trailing by 20-0, the Jets took possession on the Miami 49, but on the first play, Testaverde tried to go deep along the right sideline to Coles, but tossed the ball up for grabs. Miami took advantage with Patrick Surtain grabbing the interception.</p>
        <p>By the time Testaverde found Wayne Chrebet in the end zone for a 10-yard score with 53 seconds left in the first half, there was little emotion shown by the Jets, who were too far down to merit a celebration.</p>
        <p>The second touchdown pass by Testaverde also offered little reason to celebrate. He floated a ball to the end zone that Madison ran under and had in his hands. But the ball slipped out of his arms and was grabbed by Coles for his first career touchdown. Even that was dampened by a 2-point conversion attempt that failed when Testaverde threw to Curtis Martin, who was tackled short of the end zone by Zach Thomas, leaving the Jets trailing by 30-13 in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>But the Jets made another march, kept alive by a scramble by Testaverde as he crossed past the first-down marker and continued on, challenging tacklers. Testaverde then found Richie Anderson just in front of the end zone. The officials signaled touchdown, but on this night for the Jets, a challenge was upheld and it was ruled that Anderson's knee had touched on the 1-yard line. Testaverde then found tight end Jermaine Wiggins on the ensuing play with 9:51 to play, cutting the lead to 30-20.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
