<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Snappy Love Story on the Open Frontier</title>
    <meta content="24COPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/arts/24COPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joffrey Ballet of Chicago</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DA1731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Snappy Love Story on the Open Frontier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Joffrey Ballet of Chicago performances in Joffrey's Copland Centennial Celebration, at Auditorium Theater, Chicago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For even more proof of the renaissance of the Joffrey Ballet of Chicago, one had only to drop in on its new landmark stagings of Martha Graham's ''Appalachian Spring'' and Eugene Loring's ''Billy the Kid.'' Both 20th-century classics, odes to the American frontier, were part of a company tribute to Aaron Copland this weekend.</p>
        <p>''Appalachian Spring'' had a special interest in view of the shutdown last spring of the Martha Graham Dance Company's operations by a faction of that company's board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For even more proof of the renaissance of the Joffrey Ballet of Chicago, one had only to drop in on its new landmark stagings of Martha Graham's ''Appalachian Spring'' and Eugene Loring's ''Billy the Kid.'' Both 20th-century classics, odes to the American frontier, were part of a company tribute to Aaron Copland this weekend.</p>
        <p>''Appalachian Spring'' had a special interest in view of the shutdown last spring of the Martha Graham Dance Company's operations by a faction of that company's board.</p>
        <p>Luckily, Graham works are being staged by other troupes and even more fortunate is that there are experts like Yuriko, the 80-year-old Graham expert and former principal with the Graham company, who has staged the Joffrey's eye-opening production. It is one that should be a lesson to all who love Graham's work as a whole.</p>
        <p>That the Joffrey dancers do not all have training in Graham technique and dance differently from the Graham company is obvious. But this ''Spring'' is different because Yuriko has staged it. She has restored the work's coherence, clarifying the choreography's meaning and directed it so strongly that the whole piece snaps onto an emotional level that feels startlingly new.</p>
        <p>Essentially she has reinforced the idea of ''Appalachian Spring'' as a tender love story. As usual Graham worked on a multiplicity of levels, and ''Spring'' cannot be reduced to just a story about two people. Yet this love story is at the core of the work and Yuriko, assisted by her daughter Susan Kikuchi, another Graham ballet master, has triumphantly brought the tale of a newlywed couple on the American frontier into stronger focus than ever.</p>
        <p>The two performances on Saturday in the Joffrey's Copland Centennial Celebration at the Auditorium Theater here varied with the two casts. But there was one constant: Yuriko had obliged the dancers to relate to one another. Gone was the self-absorption of the bride, often stunning in technical brilliance in past years. Yuriko's bride is not as agitated. Maia Wilkins, with her Grant Wood demeanor, made her pure and innocent at the matinee. Taryn Kaschock, in the first cast in the evening, was passionate, and there was a sexual tension between her and Willy Shives, an astounding dancer who immerses himself completely into every role, in this instance the Husbandman, or frontier groom. He danced for her, she danced for him.</p>
        <p>Yuriko has restored the couple's numerous caresses and increased the number of kisses blown between the newlyweds. She has also banked more on spirit than literalism. When the Husbandman first enters, he passes his hand over the wall in the outline of the frame house of Isamu Noguchi's celebrated decor. He does not actually touch the wood, as many in the role do.</p>
        <p>At intermission Yuriko said she had staged the work based on her memory and an early film. She was a member of the cast at the 1944 premiere in Washington. Aaron Copland wrote the score and won a Pulitzer Prize for it.</p>
        <p>Earlier he had composed the music for the 1938 ''Billy the Kid,'' whose scenario was by Lincoln Kirstein, later co-founder of the New York City Ballet. Kirstein produced the work for his own company, Ballet Caravan, just after he had formed a close association with Graham at Bennington College in Vermont. Graham fell in love with Erick Hawkins, one of Kirstein's dancers. For Yuriko ''Appalachian Spring'' reflects Graham's happiest period with Hawkins.</p>
        <p>The Copland Centennial Celebration also presented two contemporary works: Randy Duncan's ''Copland Motets'' and a premiere, ''Lyric Discourse,'' for which the choreographer, Tony Powell, composed a percussion score in homage to Copland and his influence. That Copland can be a springboard for ballets that are a hit with the audience and that resemble works by Alvin Ailey and Gerald Arpino, the Joffrey's artistic director, is not at odds with the composer's lack of condescension to folk music and accessibility.</p>
        <p>''Appalachian Spring'' and ''Billy the Kid,'' however, come out of a specific nationalist aesthetic in the 1930's and 40's. Each had absorbed the influence of the open frontier theory of the American historian Frederick Jackson Turner. The image of the American frontier with its opportunities for the good folks of ''Appalachian Spring'' and malcontents like the Brooklyn-born William Bonney, later the outlaw Billy the Kid, remained a potent myth for generations. In the Loring-Kirstein ballet, Billy's crimes make up only an incident in the larger scheme of nation building, symbolized by the processionals of the Joffrey's extremely vivid staging (very different from the bland American Ballet Theater revival of two seasons ago).</p>
        <p>For Graham ''Appalachian Spring'' was a dance of settlement. She created the work during World War II, she said, as a way of affirming American values in a time of destruction. In her original script for Copland she referred to ''a legend of American living,'' that should ''by theatrical clarity, add up to a sense of place.''</p>
        <p>The Joffrey staging is the embodiment of this idea. One might note that the versatile Joffrey dancers could have benefited from Graham classes. The Followers (Deanne Brown, Stacy Joy Keller, Emily Patterson and Erica Lynette Edwards), who scurry around the vain Revivalist, were lighter than usual. Deborah Dawn, exquisite in the dream scene of ''Billy the Kid,'' also lacked weight as the Pioneer Woman. But Trinity Hamilton in the evening was marvelous, sagacity radiating from her every move.</p>
        <p>The preacher in each cast was stripped clear of a fanatical edge. Domingo Rubio was stern, and Calvin Kitten had more vitality and shape. Davis Robertson's ruggedness as the Husbandman was admirable.</p>
        <p>The main image to retain was that of Ms. Kaschock, her hand around Mr. Shives's neck. She was brimming with love, and after her angst-ridden solo it was he who calmed her down just as he sent her sailing into the air, exploding with joy in the hoedown that Graham distilled with such genius to a Shaker tune.</p>
        <p>The lighting was by Brad Fields and Ron Protas, the costumes supervised by Russ Vogler.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shives, strong and silent, was all vigor in ''Billy The Kid,'' changing before the audience's eyes from a child into a hardened criminal. Loring's storybook style is as brilliant as ever, and Mr. Robertson's Billy understood it. But Mr. Shives made us feel, yes, Billy's pain.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
