<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch Accepts Benching In Game 3</title>
    <meta content="24KNOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/sports/24KNOB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vizcaino, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EEDC1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch Accepts Benching In Game 3</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jose Vizcaino will play second base for New York Yankees in Game 3 of World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre said more than a week ago that Chuck Knoblauch would play second base in the World Series, when the games shifted to Shea Stadium. The Yankees manager spoke resolutely, in the same way he might declare Derek Jeter to be his shortstop.</p>
        <p>But on the eve of Game 3, Torre changed his mind, deciding to start Jose Vizcaino at second and in the leadoff spot, and shift Knoblauch to his bench. In another surprising decision, Torre decided to start Denny Neagle in Game 4, rather than David Cone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre said more than a week ago that Chuck Knoblauch would play second base in the World Series, when the games shifted to Shea Stadium. The Yankees manager spoke resolutely, in the same way he might declare Derek Jeter to be his shortstop.</p>
        <p>But on the eve of Game 3, Torre changed his mind, deciding to start Jose Vizcaino at second and in the leadoff spot, and shift Knoblauch to his bench. In another surprising decision, Torre decided to start Denny Neagle in Game 4, rather than David Cone.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch has been hampered by throwing jitters for most of the last three seasons, and although he doesn't have a throwing error since June 28, the rest of his defense seems to have been affected by the problem; he has struggled to turn double plays, or to make tougher plays, his movements stiff.</p>
        <p>Torre watched Knoblauch play second through much of September, but when the playoffs began, he opted to use Knoblauch as a designated hitter. Luis Sojo started every game at second in the first two rounds, and Vizcaino started at second in the first two games of the World Series. Knoblauch hasn't played second base since Sept. 29.</p>
        <p>Before yesterday, Torre felt comfortable with the concept of starting Knoblauch at second. After all, Knoblauch played the position for a decade, winning a Gold Glove in 1997.</p>
        <p>But Torre changed his mind after watching the first two games -- perhaps after seeing how each small mistake had the potential of being the difference between winning and losing, and after seeing the emotional atmosphere of these games. Had Knoblauch started at second base in Shea Stadium, he would have been a target of Mets fans, who naturally would have done everything to fuel the anxiety that is already built in to his defense. ''Defense was a factor,'' Torre acknowledged.</p>
        <p>The Yankees manager met with Knoblauch before yesterday's workout at Shea Stadium, and while Knoblauch was disappointed, he went along readily with the move. ''We're trying to win the World Series,'' Knoblauch said. ''He'd be taking a big risk with me not having played in three weeks.''</p>
        <p>There is a part of Knoblauch obviously wounded by the entire situation. Before reporters knew that Vizcaino would start at second, Knoblauch was asked about the prospect of playing second base again. ''You guys act like I'm just a baby starting to crawl,'' Knoblauch said. ''It's kind of irritating to me that I'm getting these questions. Even though I haven't played second base in three weeks or whatever, I've played 10 years in the big leagues. And then 20 other in Little League or whatever. I'm tired of it.''</p>
        <p>Cone, too, was disappointed, after Torre informed him and Neagle together that Neagle would start. Cone went 4-14, a miserable season for the 37-year-old former Cy Young Award winner, and he hoped that Torre would pick him to start Game 4, in Shea, where he had not pitched since leaving the Mets in 1992.</p>
        <p>But after seriously flirting with the idea of starting Cone, Torre ultimately picked Neagle. Cone hasn't started a game in weeks and Torre was concerned about how long he would last before being overtaken by weariness, and Torre also felt, after watching the first two games of the series, that the Mets are less effective against left-handed pitchers. Neagle, too, has pitched well against the Mets in the past, and in Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Torre was still undecided early this afternoon, and met with Cone and Neagle, sharing his thoughts, about his concerns regarding Cone's durability once the game started, and whether Cone could warm up quickly enough to pitch effectively out of the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Cone, probably sensing that Torre was leaning toward Neagle, went to the manager and assured him that he could warm up quickly and help the team out of the bullpen. ''I still believe that there will be a time that the bullpen phone will ring, and it will ring for me,'' Cone said. ''And I have to get myself ready for that possibility.''</p>
        <p>Neagle said: ''All along, I have been preparing myself as if I was going to pitch.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
