<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Embracing the Music, Twisting in Its Charms</title>
    <meta content="24BATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/arts/24BATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Battery Dance Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDD1731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Embracing the Music, Twisting in Its Charms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews dance program by Jonathan Hollander's Battery Dance Co, at John Jay Theater (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jonathan Hollander's Battery Dance Company has found a place in New York with an unusual range of activities: performing (often outdoors), teaching in public schools and introducing choreographers from Asia and Europe by inviting their companies to share programs during Battery's regular seasons.</p>
        <p>The company's 25th-anniversary gala at John Jay College Theater on Thursday night paid tribute to Mr. Hollander's commitment as the troupe's founder and director and to its chairman, Molly K. Heines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jonathan Hollander's Battery Dance Company has found a place in New York with an unusual range of activities: performing (often outdoors), teaching in public schools and introducing choreographers from Asia and Europe by inviting their companies to share programs during Battery's regular seasons.</p>
        <p>The company's 25th-anniversary gala at John Jay College Theater on Thursday night paid tribute to Mr. Hollander's commitment as the troupe's founder and director and to its chairman, Molly K. Heines.</p>
        <p>The all-Hollander program, which included a revival, was distinguished for its use of commissioned music, fine dancers and a sandpapered finish. The movement and compositional patterns were always smooth, with never an awkward moment. Whether Mr. Hollander succeeds in giving his choreography the weight of significance is another matter, but its sincerity is never in doubt.</p>
        <p>''Used Car Salesman,'' a premiere, was initially dominated by the xylophones and drums of Michael Daugherty's wide-ranging lively score, played onstage by the Ethos Percussion Group (Trey Files, Eric Phinney, Michael Sgouros and Yousif Sheronick). Ariel Bonilla and Vance Dugosh, two precise and agile dancers, finally caught up with the music's rambunctiousness as two reeling, cartwheeling and occasionally pugilistic fellows. They boxed, formed a two-man kick line and mimed a narrated text's pitch about selling used cars and winning their customers' trust and money.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Dugosh clasped his hands overhead and offered a serpentine image, the allusion to selling snake oil was a fillip to words and movement that did not necessarily add up to much beyond a romp.</p>
        <p>''Mother Goose,'' with Frank Carlberg's jazz score for his quintet adding a multifaceted luster to Mr. Hollander's dreamlike images, had more depth. The text by Kenneth Rexroth was sung by Christine Correa, whose husky neo-bebop initially hovered over the instrumentalists in the pit (Chris Cheek, Mr. Carlberg, John Hebert and Jim Black). Most of the words were inaudible, but a tale about stealing a king's crown was mimed by dancers in white pajamas or robes and slips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonilla, Mr. Dugosh, Katherine McGowan, Maurizio Nardi, Mariella Rietschel and Adrianna Thompson then moved into male-female duets, flowing easily from embraces on the floor into diagonal and circular patterns. There was a poetic edge as a woman performed magic tricks, pulling flowers out of a baton and scattering stardust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hollander is partial to dancers' moving in profile, which they did in abundance in ''The Anyones Ballet,'' inspired in 1988 by a poem by E. E. Cummings. The words were set to music by Ricky Ian Gordon (here sung on tape by Melanie Helton), but again it was hard to relate them to the action onstage. The finest passage, after some repeated backward striding, consisted of successive solos in which dancers twisted bodybuilding poses into evocative expressions of angst. Pat Dignan's excellent lighting, varied in its glow, created a sense of life lived.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
