<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martinez Is Hot, Williams Is Not</title>
    <meta content="MB030031" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Bernie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martinez, Tino</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DA1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martinez Is Hot, Williams Is Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Play of Bernie Williams and Tino Martinez in first 2 games of World Series discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was late September when a more patient Tino Martinez finally tossed an unsettling hitting slump aside. It appears to have it traveled like a virus to the bat of Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>As the postseason has unfolded, Martinez has batted .382, including a 5-for-11 (.455) effort in the World Series. Williams did not deliver a hit against the Mets in Games 1 and 2, and though he has a .300 average for the postseason, 10 of his 15 hits came during the American League Championship Series against Seattle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was late September when a more patient Tino Martinez finally tossed an unsettling hitting slump aside. It appears to have it traveled like a virus to the bat of Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>As the postseason has unfolded, Martinez has batted .382, including a 5-for-11 (.455) effort in the World Series. Williams did not deliver a hit against the Mets in Games 1 and 2, and though he has a .300 average for the postseason, 10 of his 15 hits came during the American League Championship Series against Seattle.</p>
        <p>So far, his low profile hasn't mattered.</p>
        <p>''You just want someone each night to come through,'' Martinez said yesterday. ''As long as one guy comes through each night, and you have good pitching, you have a chance to win. That goes for the World Series or any postseason game. If you have good pitching, all you need is that one guy each night. We've been fortunate to have that so far.''</p>
        <p>Martinez has often been a main supplier of good fortune for the Yankees this postseason. It's a pattern that began just after the worst hitting streak of his career ended at 0 for 28 on Sept. 23. The next day, Martinez crushed two two-run home runs against Detroit. Suddenly, he was staying back in the batter's box, going with the pitch and peeling the cover off his slump.</p>
        <p>''Tino just feels good right now,'' the Yankees' batting coach, Chris Chambliss, said. ''And most guys are the same way. It's a feeling. It's something you search for all the time.''</p>
        <p>Tamed for the Series so far, Williams has still been handled with caution by the Mets, who have issued him four walks.</p>
        <p>''Bernie is always working hard on ways to get himself going,'' Chambliss said. ''That's what he's done all year long. He's been that kind of hitter.</p>
        <p>''In a short series, you always get the question: why is this guy 2 for 20? If you did that during a regular season, you probably wouldn't think too much of it.</p>
        <p>''But it does mean a lot because it's the postseason, but somebody's going to be 2 for 20. If everyone was 10 for 20, there would be 12 runs every night.</p>
        <p>''Bernie's going to contribute whether it's a big hit the other way or a home run. He'll make his presence known sooner or later.''</p>
        <p>Pinstriped Library?</p>
        <p>Some players noticed a quieter Yankee Stadium crowd in Game 2 on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>''I thought the Yankee Stadium crowd was very low key, especially for a Subway Series,'' said Todd Zeile, the Mets' first baseman. ''I heard Yankee players comment that they couldn't believe how quiet it was. It's very rare in Yankee Stadium when the scoreboard has to prompt the crowd noise. I was surprised by that. I took note of it mentally. I'm hoping the fans at Shea take an active role in every pitch.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
