<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>J. Walter Thompson will acquire Tonic 360 of San Francisco to help with interactive marketing.</title>
    <meta content="Y24ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/business/24ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thompson, J Walter, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tonic 360 (Ad Agency)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED91731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>J. Walter Thompson will acquire Tonic 360 of San Francisco to help with interactive marketing.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>J Walter Thompson Co is expected to acquire Tonic 360 of San Francisco, which specializes in digital branding campaigns; acquisition will expand interactive marketing capabilities of Thompson, unit of WPP Group that operates online division known as DigitalatJWT (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN another shift in the fast-changing realm of interactive advertising, the J. Walter Thompson Company in New York is poised to acquire Tonic 360 of San Francisco, which specializes in digital branding campaigns.</p>
        <p>The acquisition, which is expected to be announced today, will expand the interactive marketing capabilities of Thompson, a unit of the WPP Group that operates an online division known as Digital@JWT.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN another shift in the fast-changing realm of interactive advertising, the J. Walter Thompson Company in New York is poised to acquire Tonic 360 of San Francisco, which specializes in digital branding campaigns.</p>
        <p>The acquisition, which is expected to be announced today, will expand the interactive marketing capabilities of Thompson, a unit of the WPP Group that operates an online division known as Digital@JWT.</p>
        <p>The deal, whose terms have not been disclosed, comes a month after Thompson and Tonic 360, which has handled interactive advertising for Sun Microsystems, formed a bicoastal partnership to land the entire Sun account, with estimated total billings of $100 million.</p>
        <p>''They really, really complement each other,'' said Tracey Stout, vice president for brand marketing at Sun, who is based in Menlo Park, Calif.</p>
        <p>''We get the heft and creative and strategic focus of J.W.T., which has done a good job, better than most agencies, in trying to get its arms around what it takes to do business in today's culture,'' she said. ''And we get the digital branding expertise from an experienced team at Tonic 360 that gets the market we're going after.''</p>
        <p>The acquisition is taking place at a time when the big, traditional Madison Avenue agencies are reassessing how they should proceed in the digital advertising field as the carnage mounts among dot-coms. At the same time, many members of the new generation of shops devoted to online marketing are suffering as World Wide Web sites report declines in ad revenue.</p>
        <p>''Digital started to become an issue for the ad business in 1994-95,'' said Chris Jones, chief executive at Thompson. ''The first three years were years of glorious inertia; from 1998 onward, we started to take this seriously.''</p>
        <p>''With Tonic 360, we saw an agency that could add a huge amount to J.W.T.,'' he added, ''as we seek to deliver solutions to traditional clients like Unilever, Pfizer and Ford, along with clients like Sun, that see enormous enhancements to their business with the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Tonic 360 will operate as a stand-alone unit of the Thompson North America division, separate from Digital@JWT, which has offices in several cities in Europe and North America but not in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>''We badly wanted a partner on the West Coast,'' Mr. Jones said, ''because if it's happening, it's happening in the Valley or it's happening in the Alley.'' (Those references, for those who think ''salsa'' when hearing the word ''chips,'' are to the Silicon Valley in Northern California and the Silicon Alley in Manhattan.)</p>
        <p>Tonic 360 has 85 employees and billings it estimates at $150 million from marketers like AvantGo, Go .com, iBeam Broadcasting, the Macy's West unit of Federated Department Stores and TechTV in addition to Sun. It was opened in December as one of two successor shops to a San Francisco agency named Left Field, which was dissolved after two years of operations.</p>
        <p>Is there some law in San Francisco requiring agencies to have silly names? Tonic 360 is supposed to connote the refreshing, invigorating qualities associated with the word ''tonic''; the ''360'' refers to a kind of comprehensive branding campaign that uses online and offline media to surround consumers, in a 360-degree manner.</p>
        <p>Tonic 360 will continue to be headed by Kevin Burke and Fred Schwartz, who were two of the three managing partners at Left Field. Mr. Burke, 39, is partner and general manager at Tonic 360, and Mr. Schwartz, 47, is partner and creative director.</p>
        <p>''Fred and I both felt that in order to grow the agency to the next level,'' Mr. Burke said, ''we needed to be part of some global network.''</p>
        <p>''We talked to quite a few,'' he said, ''and felt that Chris Jones and Bob Jeffrey got it the most.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jeffrey is the president of the flagship New York office of Thompson, and he led the agency's efforts to land the Sun account.</p>
        <p>''Everything happened all at once,'' Mr. Jeffrey said. ''I started talking to Tonic in June, and in August, I was in San Francisco to talk to Sun.''</p>
        <p>''You have to do everything you can to drive a new way of looking at the world,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The bulk of the Sun account had been handled since April 1997 by the San Francisco office of Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners Worldwide. Sun and Lowe Lintas, part of the Lowe Group unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies, said Sept. 11 that they would part ways because of what they described as a conflict stemming from the merger that created Lowe Lintas; the merger brought under one roof the accounts of Sun and a competitor, Dell Computer.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
