<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jets Are the Last Team Standing</title>
    <meta content="24JETS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/sports/24JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dolphins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DA1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jets Are the Last Team Standing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Tuesday, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets defeat Miami Dolphins, 40-37, in overtime; overcome 23-point Miami lead in 4th quarter to tie game before winning in 5th period; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first cheers the Jets heard Monday night did not come until just 6 minutes 33 seconds remained in the first half, long after the color had drained out of Coach Al Groh's face, after the humiliation seemed to be well under way.</p>
        <p>But those derisive cheers from the Jets faithful, to honor their team's first first down of the game, were long forgotten early this morning at the end of a four-hour-plus epic. Marcus Coleman's interception set up John Hall's 40-yard field goal with 8:13 remaining in overtime to give the Jets a 40-37 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first cheers the Jets heard Monday night did not come until just 6 minutes 33 seconds remained in the first half, long after the color had drained out of Coach Al Groh's face, after the humiliation seemed to be well under way.</p>
        <p>But those derisive cheers from the Jets faithful, to honor their team's first first down of the game, were long forgotten early this morning at the end of a four-hour-plus epic. Marcus Coleman's interception set up John Hall's 40-yard field goal with 8:13 remaining in overtime to give the Jets a 40-37 victory.</p>
        <p>It was the greatest comeback in team history, the previous best coming in 1978 against Denver, when the Jets erased a 21-point deficit to win, 31-28.</p>
        <p>At the end, several Dolphins collapsed on the field, heaving their helmets in frustration. The Jets (6-1) are now in first place in the American Football Conference East, but they were so exhausted in the aftermath of this comeback, they could barely lope off the field.</p>
        <p>The damage Miami (5-2) inflicted in the first three quarters would have been much more final if the Dolphins had a fully formed offensive attack. But they had survived almost exclusively on a defense that had yielded just 51 points in their first six games.</p>
        <p>So what is a 30-7 deficit in the fourth quarter to a team that seems to specialize in providing new definitions of indefatigable? Facing a defense that had not allowed more than 16 points in a game this season, quarterback Vinny Testaverde, who had thrown three interceptions, and the Jets bested even their own spectacular comebacks this season. They scored 23 unanswered points in the fourth quarter to tie the game, 30-30, with 3:55 remaining. Then, after the Dolphins scored a quick touchdown to reassume the lead, 37-30 with 3:33 left, the Jets drove again and, stunningly, threw the ball to tackle Jumbo Elliott for a touchdown that tied the game once again and sent it to overtime with 42 seconds left.</p>
        <p>The 30 points the Jets scored in the fourth quarter was the most points the Jets have ever scored in a single quarter, and they had an astounding 20 first downs in the fourth quarter alone. Testaverde, who had just 102 yards and 3 interceptions in the first three quarters, had 235 yards and 4 touchdown passes in the fourth quarter. He was 36 of 59 for 378 yards, with 5 touchdowns and 3 interceptions.</p>
        <p>This game was billed as a battle of two of the premier defenses in the league. One defense, the Dolphins', showed up from the start, holding the Jets to five straight three-and-out drives to open the game, and exposing the Jets' inconsistent  downfield passing attack. But the first half was 30 minutes out of the Jets defense's worst nightmare. Although the Dolphins' first drive netted just 3 points, it was an ominous forecast of things to come. Jay Fiedler, the Dolphins' quarterback by way of Long Island and Dartmouth, had previously not thrown for more than 175 yards in a game, an indicator of a conservative passing game in which his lone goal was to avoid catastrophic errors. But on third down from the Jets' 34-yard line, on the Dolphins' first drive, Fiedler found wide receiver Oronde Gadsden on a fade that burned free safety Kevin Williams for 26 yards. The Jets' defense held at the 1-yard-line, but that was just the beginning.</p>
        <p>On the next drive, which began less than two minutes after the first one ended, Fiedler again saw Gadsden in the right seem for 27 yards. On the next play, Fiedler, whose early performance was probably making the Jets long for Dan Marino to come out of retirement, saw the backup receiver Leslie Shepherd split Williams and Green. Fiedler's pass caught Shepherd in stride and the Dolphins led, 10-0.</p>
        <p>After the Jets' next possession -- this time they gained 9 yards before punting -- the Dolphins began their drive on the 32-yard line. On the first play from scrimmage, running back Lamar Smith took a handoff and broke down the right sideline. Fullback Rob Konrad, who Jets linebacker Bryan Cox had said could not block his way out of a paper bag, threw a critical block that leveled Green and sprung Smith for a 68-yard touchdown run that was the longest run by the Dolphins since 1997. Dolphins 17, Jets 0.</p>
        <p>The Dolphins had already accumulated 205 yards in offense by that point in the first quarter, more total yards than any team had had in the league in the first quarter this season. The first quarter would end with the Jets gaining only 9 yards of offense and no first downs. The Dolphins had 8 first downs and 207 yards. The Jets' drive that straddled the first and second quarters ended on the first play of the second quarter when Dolphins cornerback Sam Madison stepped in front of receiver Laveranues Coles to pick off Testaverde's pass.</p>
        <p>That's when Jets center Kevin Mawae, with the offense gathered around him, began to bellow. Even an amateur lip reader could get his message: ''We're not going out like this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Dolphins added a 42-yard Olindo Mare field goal on the next drive to push their lead to 20-0. On the Jets' next drive, the frustration became obvious.</p>
        <p>After they were stopped again on three downs, Brad Banta, the long snapper, shed the anonymity of his position when he committed two personal fouls after the punt by shoving two Dolphins.</p>
        <p>The Jets fans, who had been stunned into silence, finally had a chance to vent, when, on the Dolphins' next drive, Mare missed a 36-yard field goal. A huge, sarcastic roar went up. Would this be the turning point in an extraordinary comeback? Well, at least the Jets got a first down on the next drive, when Richie Anderson went 4 yards on a third-and-1. Still, that drive ended in a punt.</p>
        <p>As woeful as their performance was to that point, the Jets were still within striking distance.</p>
        <p>After their next drive ended when Patrick Surtain picked off Testaverde near the two-minute warning, the Dolphins could not move the ball. Then, the Jets got a huge break. Testaverde's pass to Coles on the left sideline appeared to have been cleanly broken up.</p>
        <p>But Dolphins safety Brian Walker, who seemed to bang into Coles while going for the ball, was called for a personal foul that gave the Jets first down on the 17-yard line. Chrebet caught a 10-yard touchdown pass to finally get the Jets on the board, 20-7.</p>
        <p>For good measure, the Dolphins, who were aided on their next drive when John Hall's kickoff went out of bounds, added a 44-yard field goal as the half ended.</p>
        <p>The Jets had just 99 yards total offense, to the Dolphins' 299. The meltdown was complete.</p>
        <p>At least that's what everyone could have been thinking.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
