<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watching Volunteers, Experts Seek Clues to Eating Disorders</title>
    <meta content="24FAT.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/science/24FAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="THE FAT EPIDEMIC/When Eating Is Disordered" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bulimia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goode, Erica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Bulimia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DB1731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watching Volunteers, Experts Seek Clues to Eating Disorders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERICA GOODE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goode, Erica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series The Fat Epidemic describes scientific studies on eating disorders at St Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital in Manhattan and elsewhere; scientist probe why some people are able to control how much they eat, while others seem helpless to stop, how eating patterns of peple with anorexia or bulimia differ from those of other people, how dieting to lose or maintain weight relates to more extreme eating behavior, and when normal eating behavior crosses the line into the abnormal; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a small room on the ninth floor of St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital in Manhattan, volunteers come to eat in the name of science.</p>
        <p>They sip milkshakes through polyethylene straws. They munch on baked chicken, sliced apples, potato chips and chocolate cake. They finish off meals composed entirely of Breyer's ice cream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a small room on the ninth floor of St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital in Manhattan, volunteers come to eat in the name of science.</p>
        <p>They sip milkshakes through polyethylene straws. They munch on baked chicken, sliced apples, potato chips and chocolate cake. They finish off meals composed entirely of Breyer's ice cream.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, following instructions, they eat as much as they would in a normal meal. Other times they ''binge,'' consuming as much as they can, or they eat continuously until an experimenter tells them to stop.</p>
        <p>All the while, machines measure their food intake. Questionnaires, filled out at regular intervals, gather information on how hungry or full they feel, how much they feel in control of their eating, how much they like or dislike what they eat.</p>
        <p>This orchestrated frenzy of deglutition has a purpose: through such studies, researchers at centers like the hospital's Human Ingestive Laboratory, which is affiliated with Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons, hope to answer critical questions about one of life's most basic activities.</p>
        <p>Why are some people able to control how much they eat while others seem helpless to stop? How do the eating patterns of people with anorexia or bulimia differ from those of other people? How does dieting to lose or maintain weight, an activity that more than two-thirds of Americans report engaging in, relate to more extreme eating behavior? And in a culture where fattening food is everywhere, thinness is a national ideal and 55 percent of the population is officially overweight, what is normal and what is abnormal?</p>
        <p>Over the last two decades, scientists have progressed both in their understanding of eating disorders and their ability to treat them.</p>
        <p>Researchers have found, for example, that cognitive therapy and antidepressants are effective therapies for bulimia nervosa.</p>
        <p>They have uncovered abnormalities in the biological systems controlling hunger and satiety that may play a role in many eating disturbances.</p>
        <p>And they have learned that eating disorders tend to run in families, suggesting that the vulnerability to such problems may be at least in part genetic.</p>
        <p>Yet despite these advances, researchers still know surprisingly little about how normal eating should be defined, or where its exact boundaries lie. And in many areas, debates continue over how severe symptoms must be to be called ''disordered,'' how eating disorders intersect with other psychiatric diagnoses like anxiety, depression or obsessive compulsive disorder, and how different types of eating problems relate to one another.</p>
        <p>''There's no question that there's an arbitrariness in the way the lines are drawn in these disorders,'' said Dr. B. Timothy Walsh, director of the eating disorders research program at New York State Psychiatric Institute in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''And while we have made progress, we have also recognized how much we don't know, even about who should be considered as having an eating disorder.''</p>
        <p>Part of the difficulty is that for most people, eating is not just a matter of stoking up on fuel.</p>
        <p>Instead, from early childhood food becomes tied up with other things, with love and hate, power and control, with culture, religion, social circumstance and personal belief. A piece of chocolate cake can be an oasis of comfort, a reliever of stress, a cure for boredom, a balm to loneliness. French fries can be Prozac on a plate.</p>
        <p>''Food is obviously the staple of our lives and we need it in order to keep our glucose levels up,'' said Dr. C. Peter Herman, a professor of psychology at the University of Toronto,  who studies dieting and eating disorders. ''But it quickly goes beyond its biological aspect and basically runs riot through our lives.''</p>
        <p>Adult humans display an impressive array of eating styles and preferences. In any random sample of people, some will eat fast, some slowly. Some will pick at their food, others will behave more like human vacuum cleaners. In stressful situations, some people will stop eating, others break out the banana cream pie.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in the panoply of human diners there are broccoli haters and meat avoiders, health food addicts and carbohydrate phobics. There are those who will eat only foods that have not touched on the plate, who eat the same thing for lunch every day of the year, who always eat their carrots first and their meatloaf second.</p>
        <p>One Philadelphia woman, interviewed as part of a study of picky eaters by Dr. Paul Rozin and Dr. Marcia Pelchat at the University of Pennsylvania, refused to eat anything with lumps, effectively ruling out beef stew, most forms of spaghetti sauce and chocolate chip cookies.</p>
        <p>Such gastronomic eccentricities are widespread, Dr. Rozin and Dr. Pelchat have found, and largely benign. But for other people, food becomes a torment.</p>
        <p>Anorexics starve themselves to emaciation. Bulimics binge eat uncontrollably, then induce vomiting, abuse laxatives or exercise frantically to compensate for their overindulgence.</p>
        <p>Others who seek help at eating disorder clinics chew their food and then spit it out, or count calories compulsively, or are unable to eat in public. Or perhaps they suffer from ''night eating syndrome,'' a disorder described by Dr. Albert Stunkard, a professor of psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania, and other researchers, which involves nearly constant nibbling, beginning in the late afternoon, coupled with depression and insomnia.</p>
        <p>Mark Roth, a 50-year old pharmacist in Philadelphia, is one of those who sought treatment for the condition at the university. His eating problem, he said, ''felt like a compulsion.'' He would skip breakfast, eat a ''haphazard'' lunch at work, then go home and begin munching, extending his repeated trips to the refrigerator into the wee morning hours. He edged up from 180 pounds to a chunky 230.</p>
        <p>Sometimes he would fantasize about the pork chop left over from dinner, eventually retrieving it and devouring it hungrily. Other times he would make do with nuts, potato chips, popcorn or other tempting snacks. ''Basically, I'd eat just about anything,'' Mr. Roth said.</p>
        <p>What Is Normal?</p>
        <p>For mental health professionals, parsing a landscape of such vastness and diversity is not always an easy task.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, psychiatrists have limited the definition of ''disordered'' eating to behaviors that threaten health or are distressing enough to drive people into treatment.</p>
        <p>Anorexia and bulimia, the two eating disorders included in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, the American Psychiatric Association's official roster of psychiatric illness, clearly fit these criteria. The two involve extreme behaviors -- self-starvation in the case of anorexia, frequent bingeing and purging in bulimia -- that most people would agree are aberrant. And each has a significant effect on health.</p>
        <p>Anorexia, which surveys find affects half of 1 percent to 1 percent of adolescent and young adult females, is perhaps the deadliest of mental disorders: in one long-term study, 7 percent of the anorexic subjects who participated had died within 10 years. Bulimia, two to six times as common as anorexia, has less severe health consequences, but takes over patients' lives and destroys their psychological well-being.</p>
        <p>Obesity, on the other hand, also impairs health, but it is not considered an eating disorder.</p>
        <p>To be sure, psychoanalysts once treated obesity as a symptom of neurosis, the legacy of unresolved childhood conflict. But in the last two decades, the consensus of medical experts has been that the obese are as normal as anyone else -- they just weigh more.</p>
        <p>Obese people, experts agree, are no more likely to binge eat than their less adipose counterparts, though, in proportion to their size and energy demands, they eat more. And though studies have found that the incidence of anxiety and depression is slightly higher among the obese, they are, as a group, no more prone to psychiatric illness than other people.</p>
        <p>Perhaps reflecting this, obesity has never been included in the psychiatric association's diagnostic manual, which insurance companies use to guide their coverage.</p>
        <p>''It was always understood that there were many reasons that people were obese,'' said Dr. Michael First, a professor of psychiatry at Columbia and one of two editors of the association's manual, known as D.S.M.IV.</p>
        <p>Still, some obese people seek help from mental health professionals because they feel that their overeating is out of control. Others come for treatment because the stigma associated with their heft has itself caused psychological distress. And while research increasingly suggests that obesity has genetic roots, like anorexia and bulimia it is also influenced by environmental factors.</p>
        <p>As a result, at least a few experts argue that it makes no sense to omit obesity in discussions of eating disorders.</p>
        <p>In a recent editorial in the journal TEN: The Economics of Neuroscience, for example, Dr. Myrna M. Weissman, a professor of epidemiology at Columbia, suggested that obesity be added to the psychiatric diagnostic manual.</p>
        <p>''Obesity,'' Dr. Weissman argued, while not a psychiatric disorder in itself, ''is associated with psychopathology, social morbidity and stigmatization.''</p>
        <p>Treatment for obesity, she pointed out, often involves behavioral therapies, antidepressant drugs and other tools of the psychiatric profession. And basic research on why people become obese is intertwined with the investigation of the biological underpinnings of other eating disorders.</p>
        <p>The Binge Eater</p>
        <p>Dr. Weissman's proposal is bound to be controversial. But so is ''binge eating disorder,'' a diagnosis increasingly given to obese people who identify their eating patterns as a problem.</p>
        <p>The disorder, now listed in the appendix of D.S.M.IV as a provisional diagnosis in need of further study, is defined by recurrent episodes of binge eating that occur at least two days a week for at least six months.</p>
        <p>In addition, to qualify for a label of binge eating disorder, patients must feel distressed about their overeating, and meet three of six other criteria, including experiencing guilt or depression over eating too much, eating more rapidly than usual, eating until uncomfortably full, eating when not feeling physically hungry or eating alone because of embarrassment over the quantity being consumed.</p>
        <p>Surveys indicate that about 2 percent of the population qualify for a diagnosis of binge eating disorder using these criteria. More than half of those are obese. And about 30 percent of obese people unhappy enough to seek treatment for their obesity engage in binge eating, according to studies. In patients who undergo a drastic weight reduction procedure called gastric bypass surgery, that figure rises to more than 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Binge eating disorder appears to be distinct from bulimia: binge eaters do not engage in extreme measures like vomiting or abusing laxatives to compensate for their overeating, nor do they restrict their food intake when not bingeing, as many bulimics do.</p>
        <p>Yet labeling binge eating as pathological is problematic in a culture of Big Macs, super sundaes and all-you-can-eat buffets, where overeating is a staple of every college dorm, and a routine way for adults to celebrate, recreate and respond to stresses of all kinds.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the binge eating disorder diagnosis contend that it describes an identifiable group of people, who are troubled and in need of treatment.</p>
        <p>''If you actually talk with people who have binge eating disorder, it takes over a large part of their lives,'' said Dr. Susan Yanovsky, director of the obesity and eating disorders program at the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases. ''They don't want to go out because of it. They feel distressed about it. I think this is distinguishable from the normal, everyday binge eating that so many women go through.''</p>
        <p>But the diagnosis also has more than a few critics.</p>
        <p>''Outside North America, it's basically a laugh,'' said Dr. Christopher Fairburn, a professor of psychiatry at Oxford University in England, who has studied binge eating disorder in the general population. ''No one thinks it's a serious condition. There is no literature on it. There are no meetings.''</p>
        <p>Arguing against the usefulness of binge eating disorder as a diagnostic category are some studies that suggest that the condition, as defined in the diagnostic manual, responds to virtually any type of treatment, including no treatment or treatment with sugar pills.</p>
        <p>''These are overeaters,'' Dr. Fairburn said, ''and the times when their life gets difficult, they overeat more, and they get very low about it. Then things improve and they stop. And whatever you do, including nothing, the bingeing goes away.''</p>
        <p>Still, many scientists believe more research will clarify how binge eating disorder fits into the eating disorder spectrum, and whether it should be included as a formal diagnosis in future editions of the manual.</p>
        <p>''I think everybody is agreed that there is something out there,'' said Michael Devlin, a Columbia University psychiatrist who studies the disorder.</p>
        <p>Mapping the Unknown</p>
        <p>The difficulties associated with drawing a clean line between normal and abnormal are not limited to overeating.</p>
        <p>A parade of help seekers arrive at eating disorder clinics distressed by symptoms not quite severe enough to meet the diagnostic criteria for anorexia or bulimia.</p>
        <p>Some come because they are endangering their health through dieting, for example, but do not stop menstruating or drop enough weight to qualify for an official diagnosis.  Others eat large amounts of food and then try to get rid of it by vomiting, extreme exercise or abusing laxatives, but do not do so twice a week for three months -- the frequency required in the manual's diagnosis of bulimia.</p>
        <p>Countless more never seek treatment at all, but, buffeted by the cultural pressures to eat too much on the one hand and to be unrealistically slim on the other, play out in their daily lives some variation of an anorexic or bulimic theme.</p>
        <p>''Picture a tug of war with a massive, muscular giant at each end of the rope,'' said Dr. Kelly Brownell, director of the Yale University Center for Eating and Weight Disorders. ''People are caught in the intersection of these forces. There are the healthy few who manage not to yield, but nearly everybody has at least a little of one problem or another.''</p>
        <p>At present, symptoms that do not fit neatly into the currently available diagnostic pigeonholes are lumped under a catch-all diagnosis, ''Eating Disorder Not Otherwise Specified,'' a category regarded by many health insurance companies as not severe enough to warrant reimbursement.</p>
        <p>Yet eventually, scientists may know enough to map with some certainty those behaviors that are simply the far end of normal eating and those that represent a step into illness. One way they hope to gain such knowledge is to bring patients with different diagnoses into the laboratory and study their eating patterns.</p>
        <p>And scientists at St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital, which recruits volunteers to eat under scientific scrutiny, are trying to do just that.</p>
        <p>Dr. Harry Kissileff, an associate professor of clinical psychology in psychiatry and medicine at Columbia, who is director of the lab, said his research team was one of the first to ask subjects to binge eat in a laboratory setting.</p>
        <p>''People didn't think it could be done because it was such a private behavior,'' he said. ''But we just brought people in and asked them to do it.''</p>
        <p>With Dr. Walsh and other collaborators, Dr. Kissileff has studied bingeing in patients with diagnoses of bulimia and binge eating disorder, in the obese and in control subjects, whose eating patterns are supposedly ''normal.''</p>
        <p>Through such studies, they have been able to tease out some differences between diagnostic groups, discovering variation in how much food they consume, what foods they select and how quickly they eat.</p>
        <p>In studies where subjects were asked to binge, eating as much as they possibly could, subjects with binge eating disorder ate slightly less than bulimic subjects, and were more fussy about the foods they chose to binge on, Dr. Kissileff said.</p>
        <p>Bulimic subjects, though they ate substantially more when told to binge than both control subjects and those with binge eating disorder, actually ate less than the other groups when asked to eat normally.</p>
        <p>And, presented with a smorgasbord of foods to choose from, bulimic subjects structured their meals differently from normal subjects and those with binge eating disorder.</p>
        <p>''Normal folk tend to eat meat early in the meal and toward the end of the meal eat dessert foods,'' said Dr. Walsh. ''In contrast, people with bulimia got to dessert much earlier.''</p>
        <p>The results of such studies have led researchers at Columbia and elsewhere to form a number of hypotheses about the mechanisms that underlie bulimia. Studies have found, for example, that bulimic subjects produce abnormally low amounts a hormone called cholecystokinine, or CCK, released by cells in the wall of the small intestine when food is present, indicating that the disorder may involve a disruption in the physiological signals that normally tell people when they have eaten enough.</p>
        <p>But scientists still have a long way to go in understanding the ways that one of life's most pleasurable activities can derail. In the meantime, Dr. Yanovsky said, what is an eating disorder can be defined very simply:</p>
        <p>''If it's something that's having an impact on your life or your health or your ability to function,'' she said, ''you ought to go out and get help.''</p>
        <p>The Fat Epidemic</p>
        <p>Previous articles in this series examined an extreme surgical treatment for weight loss, new obesity research, exercise and weight, chronic dieters and overweight children. Later articles will investigate the diet business, the culture and history of fat, and discrimination. The series is available online: www.nytimes.com/obesity</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
