<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russia Shifts Its Focus Away From Mir</title>
    <meta content="24STAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/science/24STAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mir (Space Station)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russia Shifts Its Focus Away From Mir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Once-mighty Russian space program, out of money and buried in debt, is fighting to survive through imagination, guile and forging of worldwide partnerships; Mir, Russia's pioneering space station, is reportedly scheduled for destruction in February; Russian Aviation and Space Agency and country's aerospace industry are shifting their focus from Mir to Internatioinal Space Station and other multinational projects as a survival strategy; drawing of commercial module that would offer broadcasting and Internet services from the space station (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The once-mighty Russian space program, out of money and buried in debt, is fighting to survive through imagination, guile and the forging of worldwide partnerships.</p>
        <p>Time appears to be running out for Mir, Russia's pioneering space station.  Russian space agency officials met last week to discuss Mir's fate, but did not issue public recommendations to the government on when to bring the station down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The once-mighty Russian space program, out of money and buried in debt, is fighting to survive through imagination, guile and the forging of worldwide partnerships.</p>
        <p>Time appears to be running out for Mir, Russia's pioneering space station.  Russian space agency officials met last week to discuss Mir's fate, but did not issue public recommendations to the government on when to bring the station down.</p>
        <p>However, the Itar-Tass news agency quoted Victor Blagov, a senior Russian space official, saying on Sunday that a plan to destroy Mir in February has been drafted and is awaiting government approval. And the Interfax news agency reported that Deputy Prime Minister Ilya Klebanov said on Monday that a formal decision on Mir was expected soon. ''We are planning to bring Mir down and sink it in the ocean in late February,'' Mr. Klebanov was quoted as saying.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Russian Aviation and Space Agency and the country's aerospace industry are shifting their focus to the International Space Station and other multinational projects as a survival strategy.</p>
        <p>Even as the Russian government struggles to find money for its promised contributions to the $60 billion International Space Station, Russian companies are aggressively seeking partners in the West to finance commercial modules that they can supply to the growing orbital outpost. Some of Mir's projects might move to the new venue, experts say.</p>
        <p>For instance, RSC Energia, the company that built and operates Mir, has signed an agreement with an American company, Spacehab Inc., to build a $100 million attachment to the station that would provide broadcasting and Internet services from space. And M. V. Khrunichev, a rival industrial center that produced the first segment of the new space station for the Russian government, is working with Boeing on a  competing commercial module.</p>
        <p>Russia considers its space industry a crown jewel of its past and future economy, experts say. Russia's president, Vladimir V. Putin, has called the aerospace business an important part of future economic development, as well as a source of national prestige.</p>
        <p>But with little hope for infusions of government money in the near future, that industry is increasingly trying to pull in international business to keep its factories open and its workers paid. Russian companies market rockets to launch other nation's satellites, and are involved in several partnerships with foreign concerns to provide similar launching services.</p>
        <p>Charles P. Vick, an expert on the Russian space program with the Federation of American Scientists, in Washington, said it was in the interest of the United States and other nations that want Russia to succeed as a democratic, free-market country to preserve its aerospace sector and the skills it represents. ''If it didn't have the International Space Station and commercial satellite launch contracts, that industry would collapse,'' Mr. Vick said.</p>
        <p>The recent state of the Russian space program can be characterized by the Mir space station, which will mark its 15th year in orbit next February if it remains in orbit until then.</p>
        <p>The station has had a crew for most of its life, but the last full-time crew left in August 1999, and mission control switched off most of its systems. The government said last spring that it could no longer afford the estimated $200 million annual cost of sustaining Mir, and planned to bring it down unless private money could be found. The prospect of closing the station was a blow to many Russians, who saw Mir as the symbol of a once-great space program.</p>
        <p>MirCorp, a private company based in the Netherlands and backed by Western investors, stepped in early this year and signed an agreement with Energia to license the station for commercial use. Energia, which is 38 percent owned by the Russian government, became a 60-percent stockholder in MirCorp, and its president, Yuri Semenov, became director of the board.</p>
        <p>MirCorp raised more than $40 million for missions to Mir, sponsoring two cargo ship flights carrying supplies and the first privately financed manned spaceflight with two Russian astronauts traveling to the station in April for a 73-day refurbishing mission. The company also signed several commercial deals, including a $20 million agreement to send an American millionaire to Mir next year as the first ''citizen explorer'' and a $20 million project with NBC for a televised competition that would send the winner to the station.</p>
        <p>However, Russian officials said MirCorp had not been able to raise enough money fast enough to sustain Mir. Earlier this month, the company announced that it planned a public stock offering next year in hopes of raising $117 million for Mir projects. But Mr. Semenov of Energia and others questioned whether the money would arrive in time to save Mir.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Russians sent up an unmanned Progress cargo ship carrying fuel and supplies which docked with Mir late Friday. MirCorp promised to pay the $10 million to $12 million cost, but said the money would not be available until possibly Dec. 1, which irked the Russians, according to Russian spokesmen.</p>
        <p>The 143-ton station, slowed by the drag of the thin upper atmosphere, is slowly sinking toward Earth. So, the Progress spacecraft will be used to stabilize Mir in space and possibly boost it to a higher orbit. Or it could be used to begin the process of bringing the station down.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Lenorovitz, a spokesman for MirCorp, said company officials have been told by the Russians that they have a month to decide which way to go. ''There is no pressure to make an immediate decision to boost or deorbit,'' Mr. Lenorovitz said. He said MirCorp felt Russian officials were giving it time to deliver on its financial promises before setting a date for Mir's destruction.</p>
        <p>Experts believe much of Mir would not burn up upon re-entry and could pose a major hazard to people and property if it fell on land. So Energia has proposed that the Russian government send up another Progress carrying even more fuel to guide Mir down to an isolated spot in the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>Mr. Semenov was in Washington earlier this month to complete agreements between his company and Spacehab for a pressurized commercial module to attach to the Russian segment of the international station.  Mr. Semenov's discussions included the possibility of transferring some of MirCorp's ideas to the new station if Mir were no longer available. ''We are willing to consider accommodating any reasonable commercial suggestions,'' said Dr. Shelley A. Harrison, chairman of Spacehab.</p>
        <p>Spacehab's cylindrical module, measuring 36 feet long and 12 feet in diameter, is set to be launched in 2003 on a Russian rocket. Dr. Harrison said it was to contain a full broadcast studio, laboratory space for lease and room for customized facilities for clients. Russian astronauts would be trained to operate equipment in the module.</p>
        <p>Officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration overseeing the new station have said they are open to commercializing much of the new space outpost. But any major change to the station or sizable use of its resources would have to be approved by the other partners. And because of the tight construction schedule over the next five years, NASA officials said outside visitors might be restricted in early years.</p>
        <p>The Spacehab module could face some immediate competition if the proposal by Boeing and Khrunichev goes forward. The Russian company wants to take a backup spacecraft it built for the Zarya control module and convert it into a commercial vehicle. Zarya was the first section of the space station launched in November 1998, to which the United States Unity connecting node was attached the following month.</p>
        <p>Ralph N. Moslener, director of business development for Boeing International Space Systems, said his company was evaluating the needs of potential users and trying to finish the design of the module, which is already 70 percent complete. Potential clients include those who want to do mapping from space, media companies and pharmaceutical companies interested in drug processing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moslener said Boeing and Khrunichev had not formally agreed to build the commercial module, but would decide by the end of the year whether or not to go ahead with the project, expected to cost $200 million, including launching expenses.</p>
        <p>Although neither the Boeing-Khrunichev nor Spacehab-Energia commercial modules has been built, the competition has already begun.</p>
        <p>Someone will have to make a decision on where to park the competing units. Both groups want to attach their modules on the Russian part of the station at the same docking port. The prime spot is the so-called nadir port at the bottom of the station that always points toward Earth.</p>
        <p>Spacehab officials say they have a solid contract for the spot, but some experts believe Boeing may be able to claim it if its module goes up first. ''Our contention is that we are going to put together a proposal and submit it to the owners of the International Space Station,'' Mr. Moslener of Boeing said. ''As to who will park where, it's up to the partners.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
