<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Coach in Chief</title>
    <meta content="24TUE2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/opinion/24TUE2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5D81731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Coach in Chief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Pres Clinton clearly wants to campaign for Vice Pres Al Gore, and jumpy Democrats are talking about Clinton as unused campaign resource; says Gore must have discipline to stick to his convention declaration about being his own man; notes that adding series of joint appearances with Clinton now would carry whiff of panic; says Clinton should discipline his tendency to upstage and undercut Gore with speeches he makes</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The campaign is ticking by and the alarm meter among the Democratic faithful is ticking up. What happened to the Vice President Al Gore who made the smashing convention speech in Los Angeles and seemed ready to snatch Florida away from Gov. George W. Bush? How did the Democrats' Great Debater manage to let Mr. Bush slip-slide away with generalities about leadership and Beltway bickering? Finally, is it time to send out an S O S to the most restless lame duck in modern presidential campaign history?</p>
        <p>No one who has watched Bill Clinton over the past five days can doubt that he is ready to carry the battle to the Republicans. In addressing Congressional Democrats in Washington last week and at a rally for Hillary Rodham Clinton on Long Island on Sunday, he defended his administration's record. But he also sounded like a debating coach dictating lines to a struggling student, in this case his vice president. ''They're wrong. We're right. You've got to fight,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''We tried it our way. We tried it their way. Our way is better.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The campaign is ticking by and the alarm meter among the Democratic faithful is ticking up. What happened to the Vice President Al Gore who made the smashing convention speech in Los Angeles and seemed ready to snatch Florida away from Gov. George W. Bush? How did the Democrats' Great Debater manage to let Mr. Bush slip-slide away with generalities about leadership and Beltway bickering? Finally, is it time to send out an S O S to the most restless lame duck in modern presidential campaign history?</p>
        <p>No one who has watched Bill Clinton over the past five days can doubt that he is ready to carry the battle to the Republicans. In addressing Congressional Democrats in Washington last week and at a rally for Hillary Rodham Clinton on Long Island on Sunday, he defended his administration's record. But he also sounded like a debating coach dictating lines to a struggling student, in this case his vice president. ''They're wrong. We're right. You've got to fight,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''We tried it our way. We tried it their way. Our way is better.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, for his part, faces both a generic and a specific problem. Vice presidents as different as Richard Nixon, Hubert Humphrey and George H. W. Bush have faced the general problem of stepping out of the shadow of large, and in some cases flawed, figures. Mr. Gore's special problem is that his senior partner's main achievement -- the best economic record in modern times -- ought to be a highly marketable political advantage. But when Mr. Gore dwells on Mr. Clinton's record, he plays into two main themes of the Bush campaign. Those are that Mr. Bush will bring a loftier standard of personal behavior to the Oval Office and that, in the long view, character is more important than experience.</p>
        <p>From the standpoint of the Bush campaign, the more prominence for Mr. Clinton the better. Bush strategists had hoped all along to run against the president's personal reputation rather than Mr. Gore's policies. They profess to welcome a more prominent role for Mr. Clinton and see his direct attacks on Mr. Bush as actually adding to the governor's stature by elevating him to the presidential plateau.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's not inconsiderable ego also played a role in the construction of the tactical box in which he finds himself. Since midway in the second term he has been hoping to run as the candidate who could deliver Clintonism without all that Arkansas-Lewinsky-Lincoln-Bedroom baggage. Now as his fellow Democrats are getting jumpy and talking about Mr. Clinton as an unused campaign resource, Mr. Gore needs to have the discipline to stick to the plan implicit in his convention declaration that ''I stand here tonight as my own man.''</p>
        <p>Adding a series of joint appearances with Mr. Clinton now would carry the whiff of panic, especially given the convincing reports in The Times about the level of antipathy between the two men and their families. Mr. Clinton can and should be of use in targeted appearances to push Democratic turnout in places where he would be an unalloyed asset. Louisiana, where minority turnout is critical, and the tightening race in California come to mind.</p>
        <p>But the president ought to discipline his tendency to upstage and undercut Mr. Gore with speeches in which the subtext is, ''Hey, Al, here's how you make the case.'' Although Mr. Bush is holding a small, steady lead, neither candidate has closed the deal with the swing voters. Moreover, the decisive opinion shifts could come very late. Mr. Gore's best strategy is to remain the star of his campaign, no matter how loudly Mr. Clinton clears his throat and taps his foot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
