<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; This is the story of Wall Street's most influential Internet analyst and how she got that way.</title>
    <meta content="Y24PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/business/24PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Becker, Holly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1D91731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; This is the story of Wall Street's most influential Internet analyst and how she got that way.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Berenson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on rapid rise of Holly Becker, Lehman Brothers analyst who has beccome one of Wall Street's most influential voices on Internet stocks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the land of the blind, the one-eyed analyst is queen.</p>
        <p>That seems to be the lesson of the rapid rise of Holly Becker, a Lehman Brothers analyst who has quickly become one of Wall Street's most influential voices on Internet stocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the land of the blind, the one-eyed analyst is queen.</p>
        <p>That seems to be the lesson of the rapid rise of Holly Becker, a Lehman Brothers analyst who has quickly become one of Wall Street's most influential voices on Internet stocks.</p>
        <p>A former top-ranked consumer products analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, Ms. Becker began covering Internet companies like Amazon .com and eBay only last December. She did not issue her first bearish rating on an Internet stock until May, when she turned negative on eToys, which had already fallen more than 90 percent from its highs. At that point, most Internet stocks had already crashed.</p>
        <p>Then, in June, Ms. Becker began coverage on Yahoo, which at the time had largely escaped the worst of the Internet sector's plunge, with a warning that the Web portal company was unlikely to grow fast enough to justify its $70 billion market valuation.</p>
        <p>After talking to 60 big advertisers like Procter &amp; Gamble, she concluded that old economy companies would be slow to shift a significant portion of their ad spending onto the Internet and that Internet companies, which accounted for nearly half of Yahoo's ad sales, would soon cut spending to conserve cash.</p>
        <p>And unlike many Internet analysts, who fell into the habit in 1998 and 1999 of valuing Internet companies by page views, projected lifetime customer profitability, and other dubious metrics, Ms. Becker stuck to the tried and true method of valuing Yahoo based on its price-earnings ratio and earnings growth rate. She rated Yahoo neutral, a sharply negative signal, considering that outright sell rankings on stocks are rare.</p>
        <p>Since Ms. Becker's report, Yahoo has fallen about 60 percent. And Ms. Becker has become Wall Street's most influential Internet analyst, replacing Mary Meeker of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter and Henry Blodget of Merrill Lynch, bulls who were heroes in 1998 and 1999 as Internet stocks soared. (Ms. Meeker and Mr. Blodget did not return calls for comment on this article.)</p>
        <p>Last week, Ms. Becker again demonstrated her power. Her warning that America Online, the world's largest Internet company, was no longer a short-term ''trading buy'' helped knock AOL shares from $53 on Oct. 16, to $37 by Oct. 18, shaving nearly $40 billion from the company's market valuation. The stock later regained some of its losses, closing yesterday at $47.94.</p>
        <p>''Holly went out on a limb at a time when every other sell-side analyst was pounding the table, and she looks really smart now,'' said Seth Tobias, manager of a $450 million hedge fund and a big fan of Ms. Becker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tobias said the bullishness displayed by Ms. Meeker and Mr. Blodget had damaged their credibility as Internet stocks plunged this year. Those analysts have maintained positive ratings on nearly all the companies they cover this year, even as Internet stocks have plunged in the face of mounting concerns that many Internet companies will never be profitable.</p>
        <p>''If you carried your buy rating all the way down, how can you be effective anymore? People gravitate to the guy who is right,'' Mr. Tobias said.</p>
        <p>But a closer look at Ms. Becker's record reveals that she has been wrong more than right this year. According to Bloomberg, the business news service, she has posted ''outperform'' or buy ratings on six Internet stocks since December, when she began covering the sector for Salomon Smith Barney. (She moved to Lehman in March.) Over the course of the year she lowered her rating on three of the stocks to neutral, while she continues to recommend the other three.</p>
        <p>And the results? Not one of the six stocks -- Amazon.com, America Online, Drugstore.com, eBay, eToys, Priceline.com -- has risen since Ms. Becker's initial positive recommendation. Drugstore.com, which Ms. Becker still recommends, has fallen 94 percent. Priceline fell from $57 to $13, losing almost 80 percent of its value before Ms. Becker cut her initial outperform recommendation on the company to neutral in late September. America Online is down 21 percent since she opened coverage on it with an outperform rating in June.</p>
        <p>Over all, an investor who bought equal amounts of each of the stocks -- including selling the three stocks Ms. Becker initially recommended after she cut her ratings -- would have lost more than half his money this year.</p>
        <p>By the standards of Ms. Becker's peers, who have seen many of their recommendations drop 90 percent or more since March, that is a good return. But it hardly qualifies her as a guru.</p>
        <p>Indeed, only a month before she lowered her rating on Amazon, Ms. Becker dismissed a report from Ravi Suria, another Lehman analyst, that warned that Amazon was burning cash and might never be profitable.</p>
        <p>That is an unfair analysis, according to Ms. Becker. ''Your methodology is wrong.'' Institutional investors care much more about the fact that Yahoo has fallen 60 percent since she rated it neutral than they do about her other ratings, she said, because Yahoo is in the S.&amp; P. 500 index and has a huge market valuation.  ''There's nobody on Wall Street that hasn't congratulated me for my neutral rating on Yahoo,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In addition, Ms. Becker said institutional investors understand that a neutral rating is equivalent to a sell  because analysts face heavy pressure from investment bankers and the companies they cover not to have sell or underperform ratings. ''A neutral rating keeps people out of stocks that go down.''</p>
        <p>But at least one Internet analyst has bucked that pressure. Faye Landes of Sanford Bernstein began coverage of Amazon.com this summer with an underperform rating.  Ms. Landes, who worked with Ms. Becker at Salomon Smith Barney, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>In any case, Ms. Becker noted that her recent ratings have been more negative, and more accurate, than her earlier comments. ''My calls have been recently quite a bit better,'' she said. ''I think I just got a little more confident. I got to know the business models better, and I had a higher level of conviction that these models didn't make sense. I really do think in the last few months, I've been pretty right on the sector.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
