<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Threw a Bat, Fox Dropped the Ball</title>
    <meta content="24SAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/sports/24SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DE1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Threw a Bat, Fox Dropped the Ball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV Sports column discusses television coverage of Game 2 of World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens pitched brilliantly in Game 2 of the World Series, putting the Yankees up, two games to none, against the Mets. But was that the story? Hardly. What people will remember in a week, and in 10 years, is that Clemens hurled the sawed-off barrel of Mike Piazza's bat toward the Mets' catcher in the first inning.</p>
        <p>It was the perfect bookend to Clemens's beaning of Piazza in July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roger Clemens pitched brilliantly in Game 2 of the World Series, putting the Yankees up, two games to none, against the Mets. But was that the story? Hardly. What people will remember in a week, and in 10 years, is that Clemens hurled the sawed-off barrel of Mike Piazza's bat toward the Mets' catcher in the first inning.</p>
        <p>It was the perfect bookend to Clemens's beaning of Piazza in July.</p>
        <p>Fox surely captured the bizarre tale with frequent replays of the incident throughout the game. The announcers Joe Buck and Tim McCarver weighed in with their revulsion and opinions yet they never debated ejecting Clemens.</p>
        <p>The closest they came was when Buck said: ''You have to ask the question whether if, during the regular season, Roger Clemens did that would he have stayed in the game after the act. I think the answer is no.'' McCarver agreed.</p>
        <p>So while they implied that Clemens might have escaped ejection because he was too important to oust at the World Series, they ventured no firm opinion about an ejection.</p>
        <p>Buck and McCarver should have dipped into baseball's rule book. What if the sheared-off barrel had injured Piazza, and it achieved the seriousness of Juan Marichal clubbing John Roseboro on the head during a Giants-Dodgers game in 1965?</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball's viewpoint was not pursued. Ed Goren, the president of Fox Sports, said that past practice dictated that top baseball officials would not comment on such an incident in the middle of the game -- or even at the end.</p>
        <p>Keith Olbermann, Fox's on-site reporter, nonetheless walked over to Bud Selig, baseball's commissioner, seated behind home plate, who said he didn't think the Clemens incident required immediate attention because it was quelled so quickly and the Mets did not demand Clemens's immediate ejection.</p>
        <p>Olbermann relayed the comments to Mike Weisman, the game's producer, who said there was no need to report Selig's words. Wrong.</p>
        <p>Hurling a jagged bat shard within 2 feet of Piazza demanded an on-camera response from Selig, even a noncommittal one. Selig was obligated to respond. But Olbermann didn't ask him to speak on the air and Weisman was too underwhelmed to interrupt any play by play.</p>
        <p>By game's end, here was a chance to talk to Selig or Frank Robinson, baseball's disciplinarian. But Goren said he only cared to get Clemens. ''He was the story,'' he said. ''Everything else was speculation.''</p>
        <p>Fox tap-danced while waiting for Clemens, showing four and a half minutes of network promos and clips from the game. The result was less than enterprising.</p>
        <p>There were candidates to fill time until Clemens appeared -- or until he declined to speak -- but Goren insisted, ''If we did three other interviews, I feared not getting Roger.''</p>
        <p>By the time Clemens emerged, Olbermann believed that the Piazza bat incident was no longer the game's lead story. So before he asked the question everyone wanted to ask Clemens -- what were you thinking? -- Olbermann asked Clemens about watching the ninth inning from the clubhouse and why he was so dominant.</p>
        <p>Maybe the result of the game confirms Olbermann's approach, but broader news value of the incident does not. Clemens threw a spear, in anger, that could have maimed Piazza, no matter the intent.</p>
        <p>Yet, Olbermann said yesterday, ''By the fourth, fifth or sixth inning, it was the opinion of nearly everyone that we were a little too obsessed with the incident and I didn't want to add to that.'' But, he added, he didn't want to risk Clemens bolting by starting the interview with a question about throwing the bat. ''The only thing I might have asked was if he wanted to apologize,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A night highlighted by extreme, untoward action by Clemens, yielded some extreme analysis. After the game, the MSG Network's Michael Kay suggested that the Mets wimped out by not rushing Clemens en masse. ''For the last two months, all the Mets talked about was how they wanted to get at Roger Clemens, they wanted to get at Roger Clemens to pay him back. Every single one of the Mets had a chance at Roger Clemens. They were 5 inches from him. Mike Piazza could have darted out to the mound quicker than anybody. But they didn't.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Here was your carte blanche and nobody made a move. They had their chance to get him but they never did.'' Strong comments from Kay, who is closely identified with the Yankees through calling their radio games on WABC.</p>
        <p>But he insisted yesterday that he was not criticizing the Mets without stinging the Yankees. ''I said what Clemens did was reprehensible,'' Kay said. ''But I was saying the Mets should have done something.''</p>
        <p>Yet he scorned the Mets for not beating Clemens to a pulp, without apparently seeing the wisdom of the Mets' calm response to Clemens's action. Had Piazza attacked, he would have risked a suspension.</p>
        <p>But Kay also inflated the Mets' anger toward Clemens's beaning of Piazza. They never forgot it, but did not resume talking aloud about some type of payback until the Subway Series became a reality. And even then, the revenge they sought was more in line with Clemens's potential reaction to batting in Shea Stadium -- not a bloodletting.</p>
        <p>Airwaves</p>
        <p>While Fox adoringly focuses on Hollywood stars in the stands during the game, it is ignoring the heritage of the Subway Series. During these games, the voices of old Dodgers, Yankees and Giants have been nearly absent, as have clips. A few more memories from Ralph Branca or Yogi Berra would be preferable to another shot of Billy Crystal or Calista Flockhart.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
