<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jury Seen as Divided in Doctor's Murder Trial</title>
    <meta content="24DOCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/nyregion/24DOCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bierenbaum, Robert (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz-Bierenbaum, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DC1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jury Seen as Divided in Doctor's Murder Trial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jury deliberations begin in trial of Dr Robert Bierenbaum, plastic surgeon charged with killing his wife 15 years ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An alternate juror in the trial of a plastic surgeon charged with killing his wife 15 years ago said yesterday that he and other jurors thought the prosecutors' case was weak, since there was no body or direct evidence.</p>
        <p>As the jury began deliberations, the four alternate jurors were dismissed and allowed to speak about the trial of Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, which lasted three weeks. The juror, who refused to allow his name to be published, said that he believed the jury was divided and that a number of others shared his view.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An alternate juror in the trial of a plastic surgeon charged with killing his wife 15 years ago said yesterday that he and other jurors thought the prosecutors' case was weak, since there was no body or direct evidence.</p>
        <p>As the jury began deliberations, the four alternate jurors were dismissed and allowed to speak about the trial of Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, which lasted three weeks. The juror, who refused to allow his name to be published, said that he believed the jury was divided and that a number of others shared his view.</p>
        <p>His comments came on a day in which a defense lawyer and a prosecutor presented the jury with two entirely different explanations of the defendant's actions since 1985, when Mr. Bierenbaum's wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, vanished.</p>
        <p>David Lewis, the defense lawyer, contended that Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum might have been killed by a drug dealer or another unsavory character she met while experimenting with drugs and casual sex in a city of heightened violence. The couple's brief, unhappy marriage, as they lived together on Manhattan's Upper East Side, was laced with abuse and infidelity.</p>
        <p>But Daniel Bibb, an assistant Manhattan district attorney, said that Dr. Bierenbaum was the only person with the motive and means to kill his wife and dispose of her body. He then recounted, in his closing statement of an hour and 45 minutes, the defendant's ''proactive lies, his reactive lies, his omissions and a calculated pattern of deception.''</p>
        <p>Despite copious evidence of violence in the Bierenbaum marriage -- in one incident, he choked his wife to unconsciousness; in another, he tried to drown her cat -- prosecutors have a difficult case to prove without a body, forensic evidence or eyewitnesses.</p>
        <p>The alternate juror said of the prosecution's case: ''Where's the body? How do you even know she's dead?'' Given this doubt, he added that defense lawyers might have erred by even acknowledging that Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum was probably dead. As to incidents of violence, he said simply, ''Everybody has fights in their marriage.''</p>
        <p>During deliberations yesterday, the jury seemed to be weighing the prosecutors' theory that on the day his wife disappeared, Dr. Bierenbaum, a licensed pilot, flew a Cessna airplane over the Atlantic Ocean for two hours, but later failed to tell detectives of his trip.</p>
        <p>The jury asked to review the following material: Dr. Bierenbaum's flight log book, in which prosecutors contend he tried to alter the date of that flight by changing the month of July to August; flight records from the aviation company he chartered the plane from; and pictures of a family birthday party that show a smiling Dr. Bierenbaum on the night his wife disappeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lewis contended in his closing statement that even the actions of an innocent person may seem suspicious when viewed in retrospect. After his wife disappeared, Dr. Bierenbaum ''feels lonely, abandoned,'' Mr. Lewis said. And as each new event occurs in the investigation: ''Does he react? Does he rebound?''</p>
        <p>As for the ''pattern of deceit'' claimed by prosecutors, he addressed Dr. Bierenbaum's shifting statements about the case by saying, ''If you've ever waited for a child or a spouse to come home, explanations change as you're talking to yourself or other people.''</p>
        <p>In his closing argument, Mr. Bibb tried to eliminate all explanations for Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum's disappearance other than death at her husband's hands. He wanted control of his wife but never achieved it, Mr. Bibb said. When she vanished, he did nothing to find her, except post a few signs in Central Park at the urging of others.</p>
        <p>As for her supposedly risky behavior, he said she was hardly having affairs with homeless men, but rather with an investment manager and a psychologist. And her drug use -- she tried cocaine twice -- was hardly the stuff of uncontrolled street buys, but rather a neophyte's experiment with samples obtained from a girlfriend.</p>
        <p>There is no evidence that she was killed by anyone but her husband, Mr. Bibb said. Recounting the testimony of a witness that Dr. Bierenbaum had said, ''I hate her so much I could kill her,'' Mr. Bibb asked the jury, ''In how many of your relationships have you said that where your spouse ended up dead?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
