<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Bach and Soulmate, Song Is Hardly the Whole Story</title>
    <meta content="24PERA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/arts/24PERA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perahia, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DB1731F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Bach and Soulmate, Song Is Hardly the Whole Story</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Griffiths reviews piano recital by Murray Perahia at Avery Fisher Hall (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Murray Perahia began his Great Performers recital at Avery Fisher Hall on Sunday afternoon with a group of Bach chorale preludes as transcribed by Busoni. ''Nun Komm, der Heiden Heiland'' was a gem of counterpoint in which the voices were equally clear, equally melodious and equally distinct in color. There was a beautifully soft bass line -- a special characteristic of Mr. Perahia's, freely and wonderfully used throughout the recital -- and a firm sounding of the chorale tune. In ''Nun Freut Euch, Lieben  Christen,'' the rushing right hand was all joy. In ''Ich Ruf' zu Dir, Herr Jesu Christ,'' what mattered was the slow melody, and the want that it created for a much larger musical span.</p>
        <p>That want was duly satisfied -- and how -- by the ''Goldberg'' Variations. Mr. Perahia did not only make his piano sing the opening ''Aria,'' he had it sing in three subtly different voices one after the other, voices arising from the different registers of the melody and all concurring in phrasing and feeling.</p>
        <p>Singing tone remained of paramount importance, not just singing melody but also, as in the chorale preludes, singing polyphony. Sometimes the song in a movement would not finish until the last few notes of the final harmony had been sung into place, giving musical life to a gesture which could seem merely functional, a matter of routine. In Mr. Perahia's view, nothing in the piece is routine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Murray Perahia began his Great Performers recital at Avery Fisher Hall on Sunday afternoon with a group of Bach chorale preludes as transcribed by Busoni. ''Nun Komm, der Heiden Heiland'' was a gem of counterpoint in which the voices were equally clear, equally melodious and equally distinct in color. There was a beautifully soft bass line -- a special characteristic of Mr. Perahia's, freely and wonderfully used throughout the recital -- and a firm sounding of the chorale tune. In ''Nun Freut Euch, Lieben  Christen,'' the rushing right hand was all joy. In ''Ich Ruf' zu Dir, Herr Jesu Christ,'' what mattered was the slow melody, and the want that it created for a much larger musical span.</p>
        <p>That want was duly satisfied -- and how -- by the ''Goldberg'' Variations. Mr. Perahia did not only make his piano sing the opening ''Aria,'' he had it sing in three subtly different voices one after the other, voices arising from the different registers of the melody and all concurring in phrasing and feeling.</p>
        <p>Singing tone remained of paramount importance, not just singing melody but also, as in the chorale preludes, singing polyphony. Sometimes the song in a movement would not finish until the last few notes of the final harmony had been sung into place, giving musical life to a gesture which could seem merely functional, a matter of routine. In Mr. Perahia's view, nothing in the piece is routine.</p>
        <p>But song is not the whole story. He responded to Bach's humor, especially in movements where some bumptious little figure goes leap-frogging down the octaves. The gigue-style variation provided an example, with laughter in the running figuration, and the comedy was given a reprise in the next movement.</p>
        <p>As the performance went on, so the connections began to broaden and deepen, and what had opened as a suite of character variations started to come into view as one whole body of music. After the Adagio -- where the climax in the second half was prepared and executed with a purely musical poignancy, acutely to the point -- all the variations seemed to flow on from one another, the relationships of motif and harmony effortlessly revealing themselves, the lines singing still and now also gamboling. The last variation, the ''Quodlibet,'' was part of this flow of song, humor and athleticism, and at the same time it referred back to the comic pomposity of the French overture at the start of the work's second half.</p>
        <p>After this, the repeat of the ''Aria'' came just as it should. Simplicity was being recovered, but it was both the same and not the same. The notes were, yes, identical to those that had been heard an hour before. But what one might hazily have recognized as implications in that first playing were now returning as full, solid memories, Bach's memories and, installed with Bach's, Mr. Perahia's: memories not to be forgotten.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
