<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio and Clinton Find Foreign Policy Differences Only on the Prickly Margins</title>
    <meta content="24FORE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/politics/24FORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDB1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio and Clinton Find Foreign Policy Differences Only on the Prickly Margins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lazio and Clinton Find Foreign Policy Differences Only on the Prickly Margins** Senate candidates Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A Lazio largely share foreign policy agenda based on expanding trade, paying America's bills at United Nations and forgiving some of debt of many developing nations; their positions on key foreign policy issues likely to require Senate action are so similar that they are largely indistinguishable (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For all their sniping about misplaced kisses and handshakes abroad, Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio largely share a foreign policy agenda based on expanding trade, paying America's bills at the United Nations and forgiving some of the debt of many developing nations.</p>
        <p>Both candidates for Senate from New York support normalizing trade with China as a prod for political reform, moving the American Embassy in Israel to Jerusalem as a sign of commitment to the Jewish nation, and maintaining sanctions against President Fidel Castro of Cuba until democracy takes root.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For all their sniping about misplaced kisses and handshakes abroad, Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio largely share a foreign policy agenda based on expanding trade, paying America's bills at the United Nations and forgiving some of the debt of many developing nations.</p>
        <p>Both candidates for Senate from New York support normalizing trade with China as a prod for political reform, moving the American Embassy in Israel to Jerusalem as a sign of commitment to the Jewish nation, and maintaining sanctions against President Fidel Castro of Cuba until democracy takes root.</p>
        <p>Their positions on key foreign policy issues likely to require Senate action are so similar that they are largely indistinguishable, according to independent analysts as well as a review of their public remarks, Mr. Lazio's voting record and his responses to questions submitted by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>But that does not mean that the candidates are prepared to declare a common worldview. Locked in a gloves-off campaign that is intensified by New York's media glare and its ethnic and religious mix, Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton have sought advantage by calling attention to marginal but incendiary topics, like his 1998 handshake with Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, and her kiss of Mr. Arafat's wife, Suha, last year.</p>
        <p>Such jousting has largely substituted for a full-throated debate on foreign policy, especially as the candidates have sought to make inroads with politically important groups, including Jews, Puerto Ricans and Irish-Americans.</p>
        <p>''You see catering to ethnic groups,'' said Robert Jervis, a professor of political science at Columbia University. ''Mostly, you don't see much foreign policy at all.''</p>
        <p>Still, on close analysis, differences emerge in the way Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton view America's role in the world.</p>
        <p>She is a proponent of internationalism, contending that Americans should not limit their notion of the national interest to the traditional areas of military conflict, terrorism and trade. The United States' foreign policy objectives, she says, should include the fight for women's rights, as well as the struggles against deadly diseases, extreme poverty, forced migration and environmental degradation.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton did not respond to questions submitted by The Times, but in a speech last week before the Council on Foreign Relations, she said her expansive view was where realpolitik met ''real-life politics.''</p>
        <p>''There is a refrain that runs through some of those arguments,'' Mrs. Clinton said, ''that we should intervene with force only when we face splendid little wars that we surely can win, preferably by overwhelming force in a relatively short period of time. To those who believe we should become involved only if it is easy to do, I think we have to say,  'America has never and should not ever shy away from the hard task if it is the right one.' ''</p>
        <p>The debate over when America should become involved in foreign strife surfaced again last week as a presidential campaign issue when George W. Bush's top national security aide, Condoleezza Rice, declared that a Bush administration would withdraw United States peacekeeping troops from the Balkans. Vice President Al Gore denounced such a move, saying it would deal a ''damaging blow'' to NATO.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio supports what he calls ''global engagement,'' but on a more limited level. He stops short of backing Mr. Bush's call for a withdrawal from Bosnia and Kosovo, but warns that Mrs. Clinton's attempt to broaden American objectives overseas is too costly and could distract the military from its principal mission.</p>
        <p>''I would take exception with her if she is trying to suggest that we ought to commit troops any time somebody asks,'' he said. ''We've got to make some very tough decisions, and those decisions include having to say no sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio said the United States should commit troops overseas only when there is a clear military objective and an exit strategy.</p>
        <p>In 1994, he joined House leaders in calling for a withdrawal of American troops from Haiti. Two years later, he supported a ban on sending ground troops to Bosnia, and this year he voted to withhold payment for American operations in Kosovo until the president certified that Europeans were meeting specific burden-sharing targets by April 2001.  Mr. Lazio did support airstrikes against Yugoslavia last year in defense of Kosovo Albanians.</p>
        <p>Both candidates are proponents of free trade. Mr. Lazio voted in support of enforcing trade rules through the World Trade Organization, backed the North American Free Trade Agreement with Canada and Mexico, and sought to extend some Nafta benefits to Central America and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton qualifies her support for trade expansion, asserting that it is ultimately self-defeating for the United States to try to remain an ''island of prosperity'' that ignores depressed living standards abroad. ''Ensuring fair labor standards, environmental protection and transparency in international organizations should go hand in hand with free trade,'' she said to the Council on Foreign Relations.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who said she had visited every continent except Antarctica since moving to the White House, discusses foreign affairs with confidence and polish, whether examining nuclear tensions on the Indian subcontinent or sympathizing with Colombia's president in the battle against narcoguerrillas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's work in Congress has been concentrated in the House Banking and Commerce Committees. Although he has not yet appeared before the Council on Foreign Relations, the elite East Side forum for foreign policy devotees, he burnished his credentials last week by winning the endorsement of Henry A. Kissinger, the former secretary of state.</p>
        <p>Both candidates have flipped on important positions in recent years.  Mr. Lazio, for instance, voted in July against forgiving hundreds of millions of dollars in foreign debt held by developing nations. Three months later, he came out in support of debt relief. The congressman's stance on national missile defense has also changed. He voted against a bill last year that called on the president to deploy the missile shield as soon as technologically feasible. He now supports deployment of the shield.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who expressed fears that a missile shield could unleash a new arms race with Russia and China, said she supported a ''limited'' system as soon as its effectiveness can be proven.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's most marked shift  involves her support, expressed two years ago, for an independent Palestinian state. Facing the anger of Jewish voters in recent months, she has since toughened her stance toward the Palestinians. This summer, she called for the United States to cut off aid if Palestinian leaders declare statehood absent a peace settlement with Israel. And she said her embrace of Mrs. Arafat last year was a mistake.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Mrs. Clinton pointedly put the onus on Mr. Arafat and the Palestinians ''to end the violence'' that erupted after the visit of Ariel Sharon, the hard-line Israeli politician, to Muslim holy sites in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>With Jews, in particular, she is helped by her marriage to ''the most  popular president among the Jewish community in decades,'' said Ira Forman, executive director of the National Jewish Democratic Council.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lazio has sought to cut into that support, inspired perhaps by the success of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, a Republican, among Jewish voters. Pro-Israel lobbyists in Washington describe Mr. Lazio's voting record as ''perfect'' in terms of maintaining sanctions against Israel's enemies and using foreign aid to strengthen Israel's hand in the peace process.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Forman, a Democrat, calls the candidates' positions on Israel ''indistinguishable,'' Matt Brooks, executive director of the Republican Jewish Coalition, asserts that Mrs. Clinton has raised suspicions about her loyalties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio ''has been the beneficiary of Mrs. Clinton's mistakes,'' Mr. Brooks said.</p>
        <p>Some have watched the elaborate jockeying over Middle East policy with distaste.</p>
        <p>Hussein Ibish, communications director for the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee, said, ''Both candidates have pandered most shamelessly'' by ''demonizing'' the Arafats. Moving the American Embassy to Jerusalem, which they both advocate, would ''disrupt the peace process beyond recognition,'' Mr. Ibish said.</p>
        <p>But other analysts say the candidates are merely acting within the time-honored tradition of assimilating the aspirations of New York's  dominant ethnic and religious groups. Their challenge lies in finding the right balance between national and local interest.</p>
        <p>''It's a very complicated problem for the candidates,'' said Walter Russell Mead, senior fellow for United States foreign policy at the Council on Foreign Relations. ''Things can backfire on you. You want to pander, but you don't want a reputation as a panderer. It's a matter of finding the sweet spot.''</p>
        <p>Hispanic leaders complain that they have largely been ignored by the candidates, written off by Mr. Lazio and taken for granted by Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>One exception has been Puerto Ricans in New York, who saw Mrs. Clinton twice clash with her husband over policy. She initially opposed his offer of clemency last year to 16 members of the Puerto Rican independence group known as F.A.L.N. who had been imprisoned, provided that they renounced violence. Then, facing the anger of many Puerto Ricans in New York, she backtracked, saying she had spoken too soon. She then called for an end to military target practice on the island of Vieques off eastern Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has opposed clemency for activists he considers to be ''terrorists,'' aides said, but he supports ending target practice on Vieques.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
