<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Such Fascinating Creatures . . . So Beguiling, So Special and, Um, He Oughta Know</title>
    <meta content="13WOME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/movies/13DRT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gere, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hunt, Helen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fawcett, Farrah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dr T and the Women (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DB143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Such Fascinating Creatures . . . So Beguiling, So Special and, Um, He Oughta Know</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Such Fascinating Creatures . . . So Beguiling, So Special and, Um, He Oughta Know</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie Dr T and the Women, directed by Robert Altman; Richard Gere, Helen Hunt and Farrah Fawcett star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first scene in Robert Altman's ''Dr. T and the Women'' shows a proper Dallas lady of a certain age, in an elegantly plumed and veiled pillbox hat, making nervous small talk with her gynecologist as he performs an internal exam. The man with the speculum is Sully Travis, the most popular ob-gyn in Dallas and the only man in the city, by his own estimation, who truly understands women. His examination rooms are named after local heroines -- Belle Starr, Phyllis George and Gov. Ann Richards.</p>
        <p>''Women are by nature sacred and should be treated as such,'' Sully lectures his hunting buddies. And he believes it. In guileless earnest he tells the pretty new golf pro at his country club, on whom he has a big crush, that every woman is unique. She concedes that if anyone would know, it's Dr. T.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first scene in Robert Altman's ''Dr. T and the Women'' shows a proper Dallas lady of a certain age, in an elegantly plumed and veiled pillbox hat, making nervous small talk with her gynecologist as he performs an internal exam. The man with the speculum is Sully Travis, the most popular ob-gyn in Dallas and the only man in the city, by his own estimation, who truly understands women. His examination rooms are named after local heroines -- Belle Starr, Phyllis George and Gov. Ann Richards.</p>
        <p>''Women are by nature sacred and should be treated as such,'' Sully lectures his hunting buddies. And he believes it. In guileless earnest he tells the pretty new golf pro at his country club, on whom he has a big crush, that every woman is unique. She concedes that if anyone would know, it's Dr. T.</p>
        <p>And if anyone could play this character without smutty self-consciousness, simpering sentimentality or off-putting sleaze, it's probably Richard Gere. For much of his career, Mr. Gere has coasted on his easy charm and slow-burning intelligence, and he's lent his considerable talents to a depressingly long list of mediocre movies. But here, a sensitive masculine presence in a sea of flighty, extravagant femininity, he seems to be having the time of his life. His performance is relaxed and generous, a show of beleaguered, sincere chivalry.</p>
        <p>The movie is a frothy, slapdash riff on the biblical book of Job, with the garish opulence of modern Dallas standing in for ancient Uz. Sully has clearly been blessed by fortune. His practice is so busy that his waiting room is a hive of haute couture anarchy, with nurses and society matrons fluttering hither and yon, vying for the good doctor's attentions. For all the temptation that flings itself across his examination tables, Sully is devoted to his wife, Kate (Farrah Fawcett), and his two daughters, one of whom is about to get married.</p>
        <p>But things quickly start to unravel. His recently divorced sister-in-law,  Peggy (Laura Dern), blows in on a cloud of fake leopard-skin and champagne, with her three young daughters in tow. Kate, suffering from a devastating emotional disorder caused by too much happiness, takes off her clothes in an upscale shopping mall and cavorts naked in a fountain, after which she is hospitalized. The betrothed daughter, Dee Dee (Kate Hudson), her career as a Dallas Cowboys cheerleader on the skids, may be carrying a torch for her maid of honor (Liv Tyler). And then there's that golf pro, Bree, in the fetching person of Helen Hunt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman is an unmatched choreographer of life's chaos, and he is at his best when he lets his characters loose, like paramecia in a petri dish, within an enclosed social milieu: Hollywood in ''The Player,'' the campaign trail in ''Tanner '88,'' Nashville in ''Nashville.'' ''Dr. T and the Women'' uses its affluent milieu to good comic effect, but it's mellower and more forgiving than these movies, and less interested in social criticism than in the celebration of human foible. In spite of Sully's troubles, the emotional stakes never seem very high. Everyone seems to be having too much fun to be suffering terribly much.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's the clothes. Mr. Altman's unerring eye for crowded, multihued composition is brilliantly served by his costume designer, Dona Granata. At times the movie feels like a nature documentary about some exotic species of bird, in which the females display all the bright plumage. Aside from Mr. Gere, who is attired in soft, expensive neutral tones, the men in the movie are nearly invisible. They appear in drab hunting clothes or, as in the case of Dee Dee's fiance, barely at all. And who cares about men, when you can see Ms. Hudson in a frosted pink muff, Ms. Dern in enough feathers to stuff a king-size bed and Ms. Hunt in smartly creased chinos (and, for a moment, in nothing at all)?</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman has always been interested in women, but he's rarely treated them as sacred. His fascination with their bodies, their sexuality and their psychology has sometimes verged on cruelty, and a streak of misogyny runs through his work. An astonishing number of his movies feature, at a crucial narrative juncture, the sexual humiliation of a female character, and sometimes, it has seemed, of an actress: Sally Kellerman's inadvertently public shower in ''M*A*S*H*''; the ''smoker'' strip-tease scene in ''Nashville''; Julianne Moore's tearful, half-naked confession of adultery in ''Short Cuts'' -- this is a very partial list. A number of the characters in ''Dr. T'' seem to be perfect candidates for such treatment. But when it happens  -- to Sully's loyal office manager (Shelley Long) -- Sully responds with instinctive tact, and Mr. Altman follows suit.</p>
        <p>The movie's sexual politics are as contrived as its plot, which veers off into one of the surprise endings of which Mr. Altman is so fond. (I'm on my honor to give nothing away.) But the slightly anachronistic absurdity of the conceit -- the travails of a lone gentleman in a world of ladies -- gives the actors room to do some wonderful work. Mr. Gere and Ms. Hunt are especially fine together. Bree is direct and sexually unguarded, unlike any of the women Sully knows and, in some ways, more of a man than he is. She repeatedly foils his instinctive courtesy on and off the golf course (''You're driving?'' he asks incredulously, seeing her behind the wheel of a golf cart), and it drives him wild.</p>
        <p>Like last year's ''Cookie's Fortune,'' which also had a screenplay by Anne Rapp, ''Dr. T and the Women'' finds Mr. Altman, who turned 75 in February, in a gentle, forgiving mood. The keen, almost cynical edge that characterized his masterpieces of the mid-70's and early 90's has softened, but his capacity to be surprised by what people can do, and to communicate that surprise to his audience, has not diminished.</p>
        <p>''Dr. T and the Women'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has brief nudity and several sexual situations.</p>
        <p>DR. T AND THE WOMEN  Directed by Robert Altman; written by Anne Rapp; director of photography, Jan Kiesser; edited by Geraldine Peroni; music by Lyle Lovett; production designer, Stephen Altman; costume designer, Dona Granata; produced by Mr. Altman and James McLindon; released by Artisan Entertainment. Running time: 122 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Richard Gere (Dr. T), Helen Hunt (Bree), Farrah Fawcett (Kate), Laura Dern (Peggy), Shelley Long (Carolyn), Tara Reid (Connie), Kate Hudson (Dee Dee), Liv Tyler (Marilyn), Robert Hays (Harlan), Matt Malloy (Bill), Andy Richter (Eli), Lee Grant (Dr. Harper) and Janine Turner (Dorothy).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
