<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plan B That Gets Straight A's</title>
    <meta content="13ROWA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/sports/13ROWA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rowan University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cortland State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keeler, K  C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DA153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plan B That Gets Straight A's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Rowan University Coach K C Keeler in view of upcoming game against Cortland State notes that he has led team to 4-1 record this season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>K. C. Keeler, the successful football coach at Rowan University, says he has no resume. A resume is as vital to a young, aspiring college football coach as a good whistle. Keeler says he has better things to do with his time.</p>
        <p>''If you spend a lot of time worrying about what your next job will be,'' he said, stabbing into his ravioli during a rare lunch at a restaurant, ''you're not worrying enough about your own.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>K. C. Keeler, the successful football coach at Rowan University, says he has no resume. A resume is as vital to a young, aspiring college football coach as a good whistle. Keeler says he has better things to do with his time.</p>
        <p>''If you spend a lot of time worrying about what your next job will be,'' he said, stabbing into his ravioli during a rare lunch at a restaurant, ''you're not worrying enough about your own.''</p>
        <p>Keeler, 41, is energetic and enthusiastic, respected and admired by his players. He has also won 74 games in fewer than eight seasons as Rowan's head coach.</p>
        <p>Although the Profs had to replace 12 starters, 5 of whom were Division III all-Americans, they are 4-1 this season and ranked No. 12 in Division III heading into tomorrow's important home game against Cortland State in Glassboro, N.J. Rowan, which was ranked No. 2 last week before a 20-17 loss to Buffalo State, can earn an automatic berth in the Division III playoffs by winning its final four New Jersey Athletic Conference games.</p>
        <p>Should Rowan make it to the Amos Alonzo Stagg Bowl, the Division III version of the national championship game, that would make six trips to the title game in eight years under Keeler, a former linebacker at Delaware, who helped the Blue Hens win a national championship in 1979.</p>
        <p>This is the kind of accomplishment that makes athletic directors at bigger schools take notice. And this is the kind of accomplishment that many football coaches would sell to bigger schools.</p>
        <p>Keeler will take phone calls, but he will not make them.</p>
        <p>He says he is not ''politically in tune.'' Besides, he has a lot invested in the program at Rowan, a southern New Jersey institution with a student body of 9,000 that was Glassboro State College until Henry and Betty Rowan gave $100 million to the school in 1992.</p>
        <p>Keeler has been here for 17 years, after he was a late training-camp cut by the Philadelphia Eagles and his wife told him that he was probably not cut out to be a salesman.</p>
        <p>Although the Rowan football office is in a squat, worn, cramped, one-story building on the edge of campus, and although the team sometimes has to meet in the showers, the biggest room in the building, Keeler has helped this program come a long way. There are plans to build a new football facility, and there is a part of Keeler that wants to move boxes there someday.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to sound arrogant,'' he said, ''but I have a really great job.''</p>
        <p>What Keeler has is a job that may be more difficult than Bobby Bowden's or Joe Paterno's. Though Rowan is undergoing a drastic campus expansion, the football program is very much without frills.</p>
        <p>Keeler's predecessor, the former Eagles linebacker John Bunting, was the school's first full-time head coach. Keeler has only two paid assistants, his offensive and defensive coordinators, and an intern. Rowan travels to every game, even to the national playoff games, in a bus.</p>
        <p>''Usually I tell recruits, 'Once you get out of my office, the campus is really kind of pretty,' '' Keeler said, smiling.</p>
        <p>Rowan is a member of the New Jersey Athletic Conference, which limits its members' football rosters to 100 players. By contrast, Mount Union in Ohio, which Rowan beat in the Division III semifinals in an epic upset last year, has more than 200 players in its program. As a result, Rowan has no junior-varsity program.</p>
        <p>Keeler recruits very differently from a typical major-college coach. The entrance standards at Rowan are high; Keeler says there are typically only five or six players who do not fit the general student-body profile. The average Rowan freshman, he said, has an average score of 1,200 in the SAT.</p>
        <p>Keeler cannot offer athletic scholarships, so everyone pays his own way. Because tuition for an in-state student is much less than it is for an out-of-state student, Keeler concentrates on players from New Jersey. Of the 95 players on the roster for the Profs' Sept. 29 game against the College of New Jersey, 83 were from New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''We tell them, 'We might just be the best Plan B for you,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>And then there is the psychological factor. Keeler has to sell Rowan to players who thought they were good enough to play for at least a Division I-AA school, like Delaware, but somehow slipped through the recruiting net because their grades were not high enough or because they were an inch too short or a tenth of a second too slow in the 40-yard dash.</p>
        <p>Mike Warker, Rowan's sophomore quarterback, has the typical Rowan recruiting story. As a senior at Oakcrest High School in Egg Harbor, N.J., he was considered to be one of the top quarterback prospects in the state, maybe behind only the high school all-American Chris Simms, who went to Texas.</p>
        <p>''A lot of things didn't pan out,'' Warker said.</p>
        <p>''I thought I was a Division I athlete, and it was a big disappointment,'' he added. ''I had worked so hard. But looking back, it was the best decision I ever made.''</p>
        <p>Warker's high school coach went to Rowan. Warker found Rowan's successful record appealing. He actually liked how Keeler emphasized that he would need to blend in with the program, that the program would not be built around him -- or, for that matter, anyone else.</p>
        <p>''He didn't sugarcoat it,'' Warker said.</p>
        <p>Warker was starting by the end of his first season. Rowan ended Mount Union's national-record 54-game winning streak by defeating the Purple Raiders in overtime at Mount Union. The Profs lost the championship game to Pacific Lutheran, 42-13, but this year's team was given a cause, as if it needed one.</p>
        <p>''There are just high expectations all over the place around here,'' said Luke Carpenter, a senior defensive end from Pennsville, N.J. ''It's probably pride more than anything that keeps us going. It's not like we have an angel sitting on our shoulders or anything.''</p>
        <p>The Profs do set their goals very high, though. The goal, as always, is to get to the Stagg Bowl, then to win it, which is something Rowan has yet to do. The players and coaches focus on eliminating the kinds of mistakes that could doom the Profs in a championship game.</p>
        <p>''Even though it's Division III, there's a program here; the players in the past have set a tempo for what's going on here now,'' said Mark Hendricks, a first-year assistant coach who was an outstanding outside linebacker for Rowan.</p>
        <p>''And he makes you feel like you're a part of this thing,'' Hendricks said, referring to Keeler.</p>
        <p>Now, Keeler said, he can be more selective in the players he takes. ''We actually scare kids off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Keeler won't pepper his roster with transfers. His quarterback two years ago was a senior transfer named Gus Ornstein, a Jersey kid who had played at Michigan State and Notre Dame. But Ornstein, Keeler said, more than met the Rowan entrance requirements, and Keeler needed a quarterback for that one season.</p>
        <p>''It gets frustrating,'' Keeler said. ''People don't understand. These kids are getting their degrees. They're not paying $12,000 to play one semester of football.''</p>
        <p>A player like Warker clutches to the dream of playing professional football someday, somewhere. The Seattle Seahawks drafted Rowan defensive tackle Tim Watson in the sixth round earlier this year. Fourteen Rowan players have signed National Football League contracts in the last seven years. So it is not as if nobody from the N.F.L. is noticing.</p>
        <p>But that is not the emphasis, either. The players say they came to Rowan to win championships, and that is what Keeler, who spends most of his lunch hours drinking power shakes, wants to continue to help them do.</p>
        <p>''We've created this monster kind of from out of nowhere,'' Keeler said, and he sounds as if being part of the monster is a good thing.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
