<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Oasis for Programmers in Bali</title>
    <meta content="13BALI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/technology/13BALI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bali (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Malaysia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BaliCamp (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sigma Citra Harmoni</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sugiri, Otto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia/Bali</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DA143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Oasis for Programmers in Bali</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>PACUNG, Indonesia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>BaliCamp, computer software development enterprise owned by Sigma Citra Harmoni, is launched in center of Indonesia's legendary island, Bali; companies in the West are farming out more of spadework of building networks and sending them to programmers in Asia; India, Malaysia and Philippines are known for offering well-educated, English-speaking computing talent at fraction of what it costs to pay programmers at home; BaliCamp chairman, Otto Sugiri, says he hopes BaliCamp will serve as programming colony, where computing talent from Indonesia and abroad can write software for companies worldwide; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every start-up company has its tales of sacrifice. But few can equal the sacrifices accompanying the birth of Indonesia's latest bid to join the new economy.</p>
        <p>A pig, a goat and a duck were among the animals laid out beneath a bamboo altar as ritual offerings at the official opening on Oct. 7 of BaliCamp, a software development enterprise in the center of Indonesia's legendary island, Bali. While musicians hammered out a hypnotic cadence on chimes, gongs and cymbals, a local priest recited prayers to bless the undertaking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every start-up company has its tales of sacrifice. But few can equal the sacrifices accompanying the birth of Indonesia's latest bid to join the new economy.</p>
        <p>A pig, a goat and a duck were among the animals laid out beneath a bamboo altar as ritual offerings at the official opening on Oct. 7 of BaliCamp, a software development enterprise in the center of Indonesia's legendary island, Bali. While musicians hammered out a hypnotic cadence on chimes, gongs and cymbals, a local priest recited prayers to bless the undertaking.</p>
        <p>It was not your typical business start, certainly. But this is Indonesia's deeply religious Hindu holiday playground, and the gods sit on the board of any venture.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to integrate very tightly with the local community,'' said Otto Sugiri, chairman of BaliCamp's owner, Sigma Citra Harmoni, who was dressed for the occasion in a sarong and headdress.</p>
        <p>Mystical, laid-back Bali may seem like an unlikely location for anything high-technology. But Mr. Sugiri thinks Bali's magic can gather Indonesia's creative talent and help the country grab a slice of what Balicamp executives say is a $32.6 billion market for farming out programming to other companies.</p>
        <p>BaliCamp, he hopes, will serve as a programming colony, where computing talent from Indonesia and abroad can write software for companies worldwide.</p>
        <p>The enterprise is part of a well-worn path in developing countries, one made increasingly cost-effective by the Internet. With bits and bytes now cheaper to transport than bodies, companies in the West are farming out more of the spadework of building networks and sending them to programmers in Asia.</p>
        <p>India, Malaysia and the Philippines are known for offering well-educated, English-speaking computing talent at a fraction of what it costs to pay programmers at home.</p>
        <p>''They're cheap, and they have the skills,'' said Dane Anderson, vice president for Internet research at the International Data Corporation, a market research firm. Indonesia's programmers may be less numerous and their English skills may be poorer, but BaliCamp is counting on the advantage of location. Set on a lush hillside garlanded with rice paddies, the compound is within a two-hour drive of Bali's most popular surfing beaches, golf courses and tourist districts.</p>
        <p>From the outside, BaliCamp resembles some of the island's many luxury resorts. A string of bungalows surround an airy central office complex of hardwood and whitewash, complete with swimming pool and koi ponds. Inside, however, are banks of personal computers networked to a satellite link that gives BaliCamp superfast connections to the Internet via Hawaii.</p>
        <p>Each bungalow is an office for a team of programmers working on their project. One team, for instance, is developing an online trading system for a Singapore securities firm, while another is writing software for a credit union in Utah.</p>
        <p>BaliCamp has already won the support of Sigma's big-name suppliers: Microsoft, Oracle, Cisco and International Business Machines. The Microsoft Corporation, which lent software to the venture, has also hired BaliCamp to develop an Indonesian-language spell-checker for use in its operating system, said Richard Kartawijaya, general manager of Microsoft Indonesia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sugiri, 47, was born south of Jakarta in Bandung. He studied programming in Germany. He returned to Indonesia in 1983 to work for an oil company and then worked for a bank.</p>
        <p>In 1989, he left the buttoned-down banking world behind and joined the founders of a hardware distribution start-up company called Sigma. Today, Sigma is a $21-million-a-year holding company with seven subsidiaries involved in areas that include World Wide Web sites, corporate networks and software design.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sugiri came up with the idea for BaliCamp in 1998, during the Asian financial crisis. Many programmers were taking jobs abroad to avoid the rioting and religious strife, he said. But Bali has remained an oasis of calm, offering refuge to both Jakarta-based expatriates and persecuted ethnic Chinese.</p>
        <p>Years of tourist inroads have made Bali one of Indonesia's wealthiest and most-developed islands. It has an international airport with direct links to much of Asia and Australia. Bali is also home to a thriving arts scene that Mr. Sugiri says complements the kind of creative Web programming in demand today.</p>
        <p>All these things, together with BaliCamp's communal atmosphere, Sigma executives say, will lure not only Indonesian programmers but also foreign software developers eager for the chance to visit. BaliCamp also plans to hire several foreigners to work as project managers and marketing executives, said Marina Budiman, the company's president director.</p>
        <p>Foreigners seem to take to Bali's lifestyle. Jason Swanson, 30, a Canadian working in Singapore for DataOn, a software start-up company, spent two weeks at BaliCamp while it was under construction. ''It was great,'' he recalled. ''Here's a commute where you're driving through these terraced rice fields.'' After a week of 10-hour days, he said, he was able to unwind by playing volleyball on the beach.</p>
        <p>BaliCamp executives say the new company is already on track to pull in up to $10 million in sales in 2001.</p>
        <p>''I think $10 million is quite low for them, to be frank,'' said Mr. Kartawijaya of Microsoft.</p>
        <p>BaliCamp, however, may have some difficulty expanding without sacrificing quality. It already has more than 80 full-time programmers and plans to more than double that number this year. With an average annual programmer salary of $8,000, roughly eight times the national average, there is no shortage of applicants. But of the 150 programmers who have taken the company's entrance exam in the last three months, only 10 have passed, said BaliCamp's general manager, Gunawan Tenggarahardja.</p>
        <p>Most of Indonesia's programming talent comes from technical universities on neighboring Java. Mr. Sugiri foresees having to build BaliCamp branches near Java's college towns to be closer to his source.</p>
        <p>Life at BaliCamp already resembles a campus more than the colony Mr. Sugiri envisions. Many programmers, like Yusuf Riza, 24, who is from eastern Java, walk to work each day from nearby villages. Others take a bus from Bali's main city, Denpasar. But many nights are spent sleeping in the bungalows in front of their terminals. ''My home sweet home,'' Mr. Riza said, laughing. And there are no 24-hour pizza or coffee joints in Pacung, only a staff cafeteria and restaurant, in BaliCamp.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sugiri and other Sigma executives say the isolation is intentional. They settled on Pacung not only for its beauty, but also for its distance from the heat and the distractions of the coast.</p>
        <p>''You can't work at the beach,'' said a Sigma executive, Djarot Suiantoro. ''You'll be tempted to go surfing.''</p>
        <p>WORLD BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
