<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seattle Journal; In a Turbulent Year, a City Is Cheered by Baseball</title>
    <meta content="Y13SEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/national/13NAT-SEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D9153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seattle Journal; In a Turbulent Year, a City Is Cheered by Baseball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Seattle, Wash, are in frenzy at prospect that Seattle Mariners may defeat New York Yankees and win American League championship and go on to World Series for first time in city's history; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's being  called  what else to call it? -- ''the Battle in Seattle.''</p>
        <p>Powerful, important visitors have just arrived in the Pacific Northwest, vilified here as big shots bent on global domination (in three of the last four years, anyway). In outbursts and raucous demonstrations, Seattleites have made it clear: they do not want these visitors to achieve what they have come here to do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's being  called  what else to call it? -- ''the Battle in Seattle.''</p>
        <p>Powerful, important visitors have just arrived in the Pacific Northwest, vilified here as big shots bent on global domination (in three of the last four years, anyway). In outbursts and raucous demonstrations, Seattleites have made it clear: they do not want these visitors to achieve what they have come here to do.</p>
        <p>And so some 48,000 people are vowing to converge just south of downtown late Friday afternoon, as the visitors' first scheduled meeting here gets under way.</p>
        <p>The screaming crowd will do everything it can to distract the visitors from their business, and the whole event will be captured live on television and broadcast around the world.</p>
        <p>The New York Yankees are in town.</p>
        <p>Nearly a year after the anti-globalization protests here captured international headlines, the town is in a frenzy again. This time, it is not about a meeting of the World Trade Organization, but a berth in the World Series -- the prize at stake in the Yankees' American League championship series with the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>After splitting the first two games in Yankee Stadium, the Mariners have returned to Seattle with the home-field advantage in the best-of-seven series and stirred the hopes of their fans that they might make it to the World Series for the first time in the city's history.</p>
        <p>Oh sure, people here are keenly aware that on the other side of the continent, there is fever over the possibility of a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>In fact, they are mightily irked at their perception that New Yorkers do not take the Mariners seriously. They are dismissed as ''unwashed visitors from the hinterland,'' ''an afterthought,'' and ''rubes from the Northwest,'' Art Thiel, a sports columnist for The Seattle Post-Intelligencer, reported the other day.</p>
        <p>But actually, people here quickly add, if the quest for a championship involves the possibility of facing not one but two teams from New York City, so much the better.</p>
        <p>''A Subway Series? You bet I want to see a Subway Series,'' said 23-year-old Aaron Galloway of Lacey, Wash., who was camped out in a ticket line the other day at Safeco Field, the Mariners' half-billion-dollar, retractable-roof ballpark. ''I want to see the New York Yankees take the subway to watch us beat the New York Mets in Shea Stadium.''</p>
        <p>The Mariners' successful run so far, including a three-game sweep last week of the Chicago White Sox, the team with the best record in the American League this season, has clearly amounted to a huge civic boost for Seattle.</p>
        <p>The city has hardly had the most stellar of years. Investigations, lawsuits and various recriminations are still flying over the World Trade Organization debacle, in which the police arrested more than 500 demonstrators and fired tear gas and rubber pellets to disperse the crowds. More broadly, with the word ''Seattle'' now a virtual synonym for anti-globalization sentiment, residents here still argue about whether the whole fracas was a black eye or a badge of honor for their city, hitherto known as one of the more mellow places on the planet.</p>
        <p>While New Year's Day 2000 was rung in around the world with joyful celebrations, a celebration at Seattle Center was canceled because of terrorism concerns. Microsoft remains under legal assault, and its stock closed at $54.37 a share today, less than half its high for the year. And many ''dot-com'' Internet companies are struggling to hold on and find more investment capital.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the place is clearly still awash in high-technology money, and for many, last year's protests are a distant memory anyway. And few residents seem obsessed over their impact on Seattle's image, especially since the standard local preoccupation is with getting fewer people to move here, not more.</p>
        <p>''The general feeling is, 'Something happened late last year, and gee, that was a mess, but life goes on,' '' said Walt Crowley, an author and director of historylink.org, a Web site of Seattle history and lore. ''I haven't seen a lot of people wandering the streets, you know, flagellating themselves and throwing ashes on their heads because someone might have a lower opinion of Seattle.''</p>
        <p>And now that the Mariners are playing for the World Series, baseball is far and away the biggest story in town, topping local television news and relegating violence in the Middle East, the fall of Slobodan Milosevic, and Wednesday's presidential debate to later spots in the broadcasts.</p>
        <p>Since beating the Yankees in an  epic 1995 playoff series, the Mariners team has undergone a fundamental shake-up. The front office traded away Randy Johnson, one of the game's dominant pitchers, and Ken Griffey Jr., an outfielder who was widely seen as the pre-eminent all-around talent in baseball. It finally assembled a bullpen, too, quelling the threat of more notorious late-inning collapses, a longstanding problem for the team.</p>
        <p>In each case, the moves seemed to have worked out. In trading Johnson, for instance, the team wound up with its two starting pitchers for the games in Yankee Stadium, Freddy Garcia and John Halama, each of whom pitched shutout ball. (Halama left after the sixth inning in Game 2, which the Yankees soon broke open.)</p>
        <p>A mainstay of the club is the manager, Lou Piniella, once a player, manager and general manager for the Yankees. Once known for his volcanic temper, though, Piniella seems to have mellowed somewhat.</p>
        <p>He pulled off what was widely seen as a brilliant managing ploy in the Chicago series, when he called time out at a critical juncture to have a talk with his center fielder, Mike Cameron, then on first base. The exchange seemed to rattle the Chicago pitcher: Cameron soon stole second base and the team's slugger, Edgar Martinez, shortly belted a home run, providing the team's winning edge.</p>
        <p>Asked afterward what he had told Cameron, Piniella offered an answer light on baseball strategy but perfect for a capital of the high-technology world.</p>
        <p>''I told him the Nasdaq was down 113 points,'' Piniella deadpanned, ''and that Cisco was a good buy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
