<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TiVo teams up with the Omnicom Group to tell the world about digital video recorders.</title>
    <meta content="Y13ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/business/13ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tivo Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Omnicom Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5DE153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TiVo teams up with the Omnicom Group to tell the world about digital video recorders.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TiVo Inc, leader in field of digital video recorders--set-top boxes that allow consumers to record and store shows without tape, is forming partnership with Madison Avenue advertising giant Omnicom Group to explore what could be next generation of television advertising; TiVo plans to announce that Omnicom will become first member of what is known as TiVo strategic advertising agency partnership program; agreement will give Omnicom agencies ability to test alternative methods of advertising that take advantage of TiVo time-shifting technology and offer Omnicom clients potential discounts if they work with TiVo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEADER in the field of digital video recorders -- the set-top boxes that allow consumers to record and store shows without tape -- is forming a partnership with a Madison Avenue giant to explore what could be the next generation of television advertising.</p>
        <p>TiVo Inc., which is promoting its digital video recorders with an aggressive consumer campaign, plans to announce today that the Omnicom Group in New York will become the first member of what is known as the TiVo strategic advertising agency partnership program. The agreement will give Omnicom agencies the ability to test alternative methods of advertising that take advantage of the TiVo time-shifting technology and offer Omnicom clients potential discounts if they work with TiVo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEADER in the field of digital video recorders -- the set-top boxes that allow consumers to record and store shows without tape -- is forming a partnership with a Madison Avenue giant to explore what could be the next generation of television advertising.</p>
        <p>TiVo Inc., which is promoting its digital video recorders with an aggressive consumer campaign, plans to announce today that the Omnicom Group in New York will become the first member of what is known as the TiVo strategic advertising agency partnership program. The agreement will give Omnicom agencies the ability to test alternative methods of advertising that take advantage of the TiVo time-shifting technology and offer Omnicom clients potential discounts if they work with TiVo.</p>
        <p>Omnicom is the world's second-largest agency company in revenue, at $5.7 billion, and third largest in billings, at $45.5 billion. Omnicom agencies include BBDO Worldwide, DDB Worldwide and TBWA; another shop owned by Omnicom, Goodby, Silverstein &amp; Partners in San Francisco, has been the TiVo consumer agency since February.</p>
        <p>The desire to study developing forms of advertising different from traditional commercials stems from a crucial feature of the systems sold by TiVo and a competitor, ReplayTV: they enable viewers to pause, replay, rewind and fast-forward through television programs -- and commercials -- as they are watched.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, advertising will change in a dramatic way,'' Stacy Jolna, chief programming officer and vice president for advertising and media partnerships at TiVo in San Jose, Calif., said yesterday. ''Viewers have never been more central in half a century of watching TV.''</p>
        <p>''The point of this is for agencies to work with us to experiment with and get a better understanding of the new advertising and marketing techniques we'll develop,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Any decline in the viewership of commercials resulting from use of digital video recorders, also known as personal video recorders or personal television, would of course make for anxious days among marketers and agencies, which have been seeking for years to counter the consumer's ability to use videocassette recorders to fast-forward through commercials.</p>
        <p>''There's always a certain degree of trepidation when change is in the wind,'' Mr. Jolna said in offering a preview of the Omnicom alliance in a telephone interview. ''But there's also a certain degree of excitement about the opportunity to learn and innovate.''</p>
        <p>The TiVo and ReplayTV systems, as well as one coming from Microsoft under the brand name Ultimate TV, also store data on program preferences, enabling marketers to aim specific pitches at households based on prior viewing habits. Personal video recorders are expected to be among the best-selling consumer electronics products during the coming holiday shopping season.</p>
        <p>Personal TV is only one new technology being scrutinized by agencies and advertisers; others include interactive television and wireless devices. Also this week, Wink Communications, which is developing interactive entertainment and advertising for television, signed agreements with four agencies including Goodby, Silverstein calling for them to offer commercials enhanced with Wink's technology to clients.</p>
        <p>Among the alternative advertising opportunities TiVo is developing are sponsorships modeled after the sponsored shows that predominated during the so-called golden age of television in the 1950's. For instance, the hard drives of the TiVo systems, sold as the Philips Personal TV Recorder and the Sony Digital Network Recorder, come with 30 minutes of programming called TiVo Direct, sponsored by Ifilm.com, the Professional Golfers Association and cable TV networks like Encore, Starz and Showtime. The Showtime parent, Viacom, is a backer of TiVo along with the Walt Disney Company and the NBC unit of General Electric.</p>
        <p>''There's a little bit of 'back to the future' here,'' Mr. Jolna said, ''getting sponsors to integrate their brands with programming content like the 'Hallmark Hall of Fame' has done for so many years.''</p>
        <p>ReplayTV has signed deals with Coca-Cola and Universal Pictures to explore ad alternatives like sponsorships, banners and cross-promotions. Omnicom is also a backer of ReplayTV, along with the Grey Global Group and the Interpublic Group of companies.</p>
        <p>TiVo will also soon have ''several other big agencies coming on board'' to join Omnicom, Mr. Jolna said. Asked whether his nautical phrasing was a hint that one would be the J. Walter Thompson unit of the WPP Group -- that agency's namesake founder was a commodore -- Mr. Jolna laughed.</p>
        <p>Owen Dougherty, a spokesman for Thompson in New York, said the agency was indeed working with TiVo.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
