<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="13PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/nyregion/13PUBL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hamptons International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philbin, Regis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philbin, Regis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suna, Stuart Match</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lupone, Patti</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Hamptons International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDD153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column comments on TV personality Regis Philbin, Hamptons International Film Festival chmn Stuart Match Suna and actress Patti LuPone; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not Quite Live With Regis</p>
        <p>Maybe the television personality REGIS PHILBIN needs some fresh material.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not Quite Live With Regis</p>
        <p>Maybe the television personality REGIS PHILBIN needs some fresh material.</p>
        <p>As the master of ceremonies at the annual Rita Hayworth Gala for the Alzheimer's Association on Wednesday, he began by telling the crowd in the ballroom at the Waldorf-Astoria that he was pleased to see so many people ''looking like a million dollars.'' Then he said that he had just finished taping two episodes of the game show ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' and that no one had hit the jackpot -- ''to the relief of ABC.''</p>
        <p>''I didn't help the guy that had the best chance, too,'' he said, explaining how, as the host of a high-pressure, high-stakes program, he tries to help contestants, ''to relax them, to give them the confidence and the strength they need'' to arrive at a final answer. He added that he had been no help ''to this poor guy tonight'' when he made a joke playing on the contestant's name -- DAN DOODY.</p>
        <p>The name got a laugh, as Mr. Philbin clearly intended. But there were those in the audience who watch ''Millionaire'' often enough to know that Mr. Doody could not have appeared on the episodes Mr. Philbin had taped on Wednesday -- Mr. Doody was a contestant on the episode broadcast on Jan. 27 and won $1,000.</p>
        <p>Others in the audience go to benefits often enough to remember hearing Mr. Philbin tell the same story last month, at a benefit for the National Museum of Catholic Art and History, scheduled to open next year.</p>
        <p>One of the honorees at the Alzheimer's benefit was CLAUDIA COHEN, the entertainment reporter on Mr. Philbin's other show, ''Live With Regis.'' She thanked her former husband, the billionaire RONALD O. PERELMAN, for covering some of the expenses for the gala; Mr. Perelman was not there.</p>
        <p>Something Extra For the Movies</p>
        <p>As the Middle East crisis intensified yesterday, the organizers of the Hamptons International Film Festival asked for extra police protection and hired bodyguards for the Palestinian and Israeli filmmakers who had been invited because their work concerns conflict resolution in the Middle East. ''One of the things we were concerned about is not everybody respects the intellectual forum of discussing these things, and some people can get violent,'' said STUART MATCH SUNA, the chairman of the festival and the president of Silvercup Studios. ''Was I worried about terrorist activity? No. I was worried about someone getting out of control.'' No one did.</p>
        <p>A Loose Nest For a Diamond</p>
        <p>The actress PATTI LuPONE -- she appears in the film ''Just Looking,'' which opens today -- was just looking at the world's largest green diamond, a 41-carat behemoth known as the Dresden Green.</p>
        <p>''You have to work out and be in pretty good shape to carry that,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Not that she was going to carry it anywhere. On Wednesday, it was sitting comfortably in a display case at the Harry Winston store on Fifth Avenue, and the only place it will be going is Washington, where it will be displayed at the Smithsonian Institution.</p>
        <p>''If I had the chance I think I would wear it here,'' she said, patting the top of her head. And hope that she could keep track of it better than some of the jewelry she was wearing. One of her earrings fell off while she was talking.</p>
        <p>''It's been falling off all night,'' she said. She added: ''In my case, 'Diamonds are a girl's best friend' is not true. In fact, I wouldn't know where or what occasion to wear diamond jewelry. I don't have diamonds. I don't even know what that concept is all about.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
