<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Navy's Visits to Risky Port Sought Better Ties to Yemen</title>
    <meta content="13YEME$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/world/13YEME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE WARSHIP EXPLOSION: YEMEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-International Relations-Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Persian Gulf War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">iraq-international relations-yemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Becker, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saleh, Ali Abdullah (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D7153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Navy's Visits to Risky Port Sought Better Ties to Yemen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH BECKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Becker, Elizabeth</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American ships like destroyer Cole have made refueling stops in Yemen 12 times in recent months, despite known risks of terrorism there, as part of American strategy to improve ties with Yemen; Pentagon officials say security precautions have been taken on each occasion, and there was no specific intelligence warning of threat to Cole when it visited port; American officials say budding relationship with Yemen recently bore fruit, when Pres Ali Abdullah Saleh visited Washington in April and met with Pres Clinton; says Yemen now allows allied forces in region to use its port when it intercepts ships accused of violating sanctions against Iraq, step that has distanced Yemen from Iraq; during gulf war Yemen refused to join allies against Iraq; Yemen has been haven to international terrorist groups, who operate and train in its hinterlands (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the known risks of terrorism in Yemen, American ships like the destroyer Cole have made refueling stops there 12 times in recent months as part of an American strategy to improve ties with the Arab country.</p>
        <p>After consultations with the White House and the State Department, the Pentagon decided last year that Navy ships would refuel in Yemen's deep sea port of Aden, at the southern tip of the Arabian peninsula. Security precautions were taken on each occasion, Pentagon officials said today, adding that there had been no specific intelligence warning of a threat to the Cole when it visited the port.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite the known risks of terrorism in Yemen, American ships like the destroyer Cole have made refueling stops there 12 times in recent months as part of an American strategy to improve ties with the Arab country.</p>
        <p>After consultations with the White House and the State Department, the Pentagon decided last year that Navy ships would refuel in Yemen's deep sea port of Aden, at the southern tip of the Arabian peninsula. Security precautions were taken on each occasion, Pentagon officials said today, adding that there had been no specific intelligence warning of a threat to the Cole when it visited the port.</p>
        <p>Yemen, an impoverished nation of some 16 million people, refused to join the allies against Iraq during the gulf war and has been a haven to international terrorist groups, who operate and train in its hinterlands, according to the current State Department report on terrorism.</p>
        <p>''We have been working to improve our relations with Yemen for some time,'' Adm. Vern Clark, chief of naval operations, said today. ''And I'm sure that that was at the heart of the motivation'' of commanders in the region when they established refueling operations at Aden, he said.</p>
        <p>American officials said today that the budding relationship with Yemen had recently seemed to be bearing fruit. In April, Yemen's president, Ali Abdullah Saleh, visited Washington and met with President Clinton. And as allied forces in the region have intercepted ships accused of violating the sanctions against Iraq, Yemen has allowed them to bring the offending vessels to the port at Aden, another step that distanced Yemen from Iraq, and angered the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>In recent days, however, Yemen's government had helped organize large demonstrations against Israel and the United States in Aden, in the capital, Sana, and other cities, residents said.</p>
        <p>Gen. Anthony C. Zinni, the recently retired Pentagon regional commander for the Middle East, pressed the decision to brave the mixed security situation in Yemen, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>''In the last couple of years, Yemen has been doing a better job trying to control terrorism,'' said Kenneth H. Bacon, the Pentagon spokesman. ''We obviously felt that it was safe to take our ships there.'' All ships in the area prepare and follow a detailed security plan against possible terrorist attack, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we missed any specific threats,'' Defense Secretary William S. Cohen said. ''There are general threats in the region, and we understand that. And that's the reason why we have such precautionary measures we take.''</p>
        <p>The ship came into the port at the second-highest level of alert, Admiral Clark said, and the sailors had undergone security training before this mission. Admiral Clark refused to discuss details of the security measures involved.</p>
        <p>Officials said that security training includes precautions against terrorist attacks from small boats, but that in this case the boat appeared to be part of the refueling operation itself and was not suspect.</p>
        <p>The Cole was the 12th ship to visit Yemen, and the third since May, officials said.</p>
        <p>Even though the State Department dropped Yemen from its list of terrorist nations 10 years ago when North Yemen merged with formerly Marxist South Yemen, diplomats say the Yemeni government is too weak to control radical groups from Palestine, Egypt, Libya and Algeria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saleh, the former army general who is Yemen's president, denied that terrorists were responsible for today's explosion. ''Yemen does not have any terrorist elements, and there is no relationship between this and what is happening in the occupied territories,'' Mr. Saleh told CNN, referring to Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>But Daniel Benjamin, an anti-terrorist expert who recently resigned from the National Security Council, said, ''Yemen is a troubled spot because central authority is limited largely to control of a few major centers.'' He added, ''There is no shortage of bad actors who would like nothing better than to attack the United States.''</p>
        <p>The groups stationed in and around Yemen include Hamas, the Palestinian Islamic Jihad and sympathizers or members of other international groups like the Egyptian Islamic Jihad, al-Gama'at al-Islaymiyya and the Algerian Armed Islamic Group, according to the State Department terrorism report.</p>
        <p>Other experts suggested that Osama bin Laden, who the United States believes was behind the bombing of two American embassies in Africa in 1998, comes from an ethnically Yemeni family and has influence there, as does Iraq. The American ships refueling in Aden, which are part of the Fifth Fleet, largely help enforce the sanctions against Iraq.</p>
        <p>''It's really too early to speculate, but you have to ask who is angry enough at us to attack an American target, and you may pick the Iraqis,'' said Jerry Bremer, a former State Department terrorist expert who this year chaired a national commission on terrorism.</p>
        <p>A land of arid, rocky deserts and remote mountains, Yemen has existed in its present form only since 1990, when the two Yemens that emerged from Turkish and British colonial domination in the 19th and 20th centuries were united.</p>
        <p>The union has been uneasy, and a civil war in 1994 that ended in victory for the new national government in Sana left deep schisms, with tribal fiefdoms in the hinterland that have served as strongholds for the Islamic terrorist groups. Armed groups have made targets of American, British and other foreign visitors and institutions, including tourists who began returning in the mid-1990's to explore the remains of ancient civilizations.</p>
        <p>Without the oil resources of its richer neighbors, Yemen has sent many thousands of its people to work in richer and less populous Arab states, often manning their militaries. Many Yemenis also fought with the mujahedeen against Soviet forces in Afghanistan in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>THE WARSHIP EXPLOSION: YEMEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
