<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain and Bush Seldom Connect on the Trail</title>
    <meta content="Y13MCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/politics/13MCCA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ARIZONA SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D9153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain and Bush Seldom Connect on the Trail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain, busy making commercials for Republican Congressional candidates and stumping for them in their districts, has made no commercials or appearances for Gov George W Bush since early Aug; many Republicans are urging Bush to use former rival more aggressively on campaign trail; note he is popular with kind of independent and swing voters who could decide race's outcome; McCain aides cite his offers to help Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the last few weeks, Senator John McCain has been one busy surrogate. He has made more than 90 radio and television commercials for Republicans running for Congress. He has stumped for dozens of those candidates in their districts. He is scheduled to appear in spots for people running for state legislature seats. He has even performed in a public service announcement produced by Comedy Central.</p>
        <p>So, one might ask, how many commercials has Mr. McCain appeared in for the man at the pinnacle of his party's ticket, Gov. George W. Bush? The answer is: zero. And how many surrogate speaking engagements has he done for Mr. Bush? Zero again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the last few weeks, Senator John McCain has been one busy surrogate. He has made more than 90 radio and television commercials for Republicans running for Congress. He has stumped for dozens of those candidates in their districts. He is scheduled to appear in spots for people running for state legislature seats. He has even performed in a public service announcement produced by Comedy Central.</p>
        <p>So, one might ask, how many commercials has Mr. McCain appeared in for the man at the pinnacle of his party's ticket, Gov. George W. Bush? The answer is: zero. And how many surrogate speaking engagements has he done for Mr. Bush? Zero again.</p>
        <p>Ever since he campaigned with Mr. Bush in early August, Mr. McCain has maintained what many Republicans consider a perplexingly low profile on the presidential trail. And though he is scheduled to campaign with Mr. Bush in Florida and New Hampshire later this month, Mr. McCain plans to devote the last crucial week of the campaign to Republican Congressional candidates, not Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Now, with the race heading toward what political analysts predict will be a photo finish, many Republicans are saying that Mr. Bush would be wise to use his former rival more aggressively on the campaign trail. Mr. McCain, they argue, remains too popular a commodity not to be exploited.</p>
        <p>''If I were making the decisions for Bush, I'd be asking him to go everywhere,'' said John Nevin, campaign manager for Mike Rogers, a Congressional candidate from the Lansing, Mich., area, who has asked Mr. McCain to campaign with him. ''But I don't know that he wants to do that.''</p>
        <p>Robert M. Teeter, a Republican pollster, said Mr. McCain was admired by the kind of independent and swing voters who could decide the outcome of the race.</p>
        <p>''It would make sense for them to use him in almost any state with large numbers of swing voters.'' Mr. Teeter said.</p>
        <p>A senior Republican official on Capitol Hill said he was bewildered  ''that the Bush people aren't using him more.''</p>
        <p>''He's the most popular politician in America,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>Advisers to Mr. Bush offered an array of reasons that the two camps had not worked more closely together. Some said it was simply due to scheduling conflicts. Others said Mr. McCain's recent treatment for skin cancer had restricted his activities. Still others argued that it would seem strange to give anyone other than Mr. Bush's running mate a prominent role in the campaign.</p>
        <p>''You can overdo these things,'' one Bush adviser said. But the adviser also acknowledged that ''McCain has the ability to be more helpful to us than maybe anybody else'' in certain states.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. McCain contend that they have done almost everything Mr. Bush's campaign has asked, with one exception: they turned down a request to appear at the first presidential debate in Boston, arguing that there were plenty of other ''spinners'' available to help Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>They also say they offered to campaign with Mr. Bush for seven days this month but were asked to do only five. And they have expressed surprise that the Bush campaign had not asked them to make radio or television commercials in Michigan or New Hampshire, closely contested states where Mr. McCain won the presidential primaries by substantial margins.</p>
        <p>One senior Republican official who has advised Mr. Bush said ''hubris'' on the part of both men and their top aides had made cooperation difficult.</p>
        <p>''Campaigns and candidates have corporate egos,'' the Republican said. ''The McCain corporate ego is such that the folks around him won't meet the Bush campaign halfway. The Bush corporate ego is such that they won't bend any further than that. They won't be magnanimous winners and say, 'What days are you available?' ''</p>
        <p>Whatever the reasons, Mr. McCain and Mr. Bush often seem like boats passing in the night. Today, both men were in Michigan: Mr. Bush in Grand Rapids for a rally this evening, Mr. McCain in Lansing, about a two-hour drive away, for a televised town meeting late this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Yet there was no effort to have the two men's paths cross. And there are no plans right now for Mr. McCain to campaign with Mr. Bush in Michigan, though he may appear with Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's running mate.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain has not always been an effusive supporter of the Republican ticket during his appearances. On ''Larry King Live'' last week, Mr. McCain offered equal praise to Mr. Cheney and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, the Democratic vice-presidential candidate. And he did not mention Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>On the Democratic side, former Senator Bill Bradley has also spent little time campaigning on behalf of the man who beat him in the primaries, Vice President Al Gore. But unlike Mr. Bradley, who did not win a single state, Mr. McCain won seven primaries, and some polls suggest that he remains one of the most popular politicians in the country.</p>
        <p>Some Republicans argue that it would be risky for Mr. Bush to use Mr. McCain extensively in the waning days of the campaign because the Arizona senator can be so unpredictable and outspoken, particularly on issues on which the two men disagree, like campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>A case in point, they say, is a recent appearance by Mr. McCain with Representative Rick A. Lazio. In response to questions from reporters, Mr. McCain -- a leading opponent of unregulated soft money -- stopped short of defending Mr. Lazio's decision to accept $1.8 million from the Republican Party for television advertisements in his New York Senate race. Democrats asserted that the commercials violated Mr. Lazio's pledge not to use soft money.</p>
        <p>''He embarrassed Lazio,'' one New York Republican said.</p>
        <p>But others say Mr. McCain's electric personality and appeal to independent voters and swing Democrats make him worth the risk.</p>
        <p>''I'd be saying to John McCain: 'I'll give you whatever it takes -- a plane, a staff, whatever,' '' said the senior Republican adviser to the Bush campaign. ''But I guess that's not the view from Austin, Tex.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ARIZONA SENATOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
