<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Instant Media Analysis Often Proves at Odds With Public Opinion</title>
    <meta content="Y13MED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/politics/13MEDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PUNDITS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jamieson, Kathleen Hall</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2D9153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Instant Media Analysis Often Proves at Odds With Public Opinion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rapidity with which consensus developed among many commentators and news organizations that Gov George W Bush 'won' second presidential with Gov Al Gore raises questions about whether pundits' views are shared widely by people outside insular circle of media and politics; Kathleen Hall Jamieson, news media expert, advised viewers to avoid post-debate commentary as meaningless and dangerous (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone unsure of who ''won'' the second presidential debate had only to consult a newspaper, Web site or television network yesterday for an unequivocal answer.</p>
        <p>''Bush Scores in Second Debate'' said the front-page headline in The New York Daily News.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone unsure of who ''won'' the second presidential debate had only to consult a newspaper, Web site or television network yesterday for an unequivocal answer.</p>
        <p>''Bush Scores in Second Debate'' said the front-page headline in The New York Daily News.</p>
        <p>''Bush Beat Gore'' was the elegantly simple banner on Slate, the political Webzine.</p>
        <p>''I do think Bush won,'' declared William Kristol, a conservative Republican commentator on CBS's ''Early Show.'' ''Al Gore was Samson after the haircut.''</p>
        <p>It was not a unanimous verdict, of course, as some reports mentioned misstatements by Gov. George W. Bush or his response to questions about poor health care in Texas. But in the immediate aftermath of the debate on Wednesday night in North Carolina, a consensus rapidly developed among commentators and news organizations across the nation: not only had Governor Bush performed better than in the Boston debate a week earlier, but he had also out-and-out defeated his subdued rival, Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Surfing the channels and the Web after an event like the presidential debate, it is almost possible to watch conventional wisdom solidifying before one's eyes. And in the minutes after the debate, the common verdict emerged as the networks broadcast data from their ''instant polls'' and on-air focus groups, and correspondents offered instant analyses.</p>
        <p>''All the polls tonight show that he won,'' George Stephanopoulos said on ''Nightline,'' a mere hour after the debate. Indeed, the comprehensive daily pulse-taking of the news media by Hotline, the online political journal, showed that the pattern in newspaper and television coverage was national. ''It definitely leaned Bush,'' said Chuck Todd, Hotline's editor.</p>
        <p>The trend was so strong that Mr. Todd and his colleagues got to wondering. ''We were talking about this this morning,'' he said. ''We're kind of curious what the coverage would have been like if you could have locked every reporter in a soundproof chamber, and seen what they said if they hadn't heard the immediate polls and immediate spin on TV.''</p>
        <p>Those who study viewer and voter attitudes say the question of whether such conclusions are shared widely by people outside the insular circles of media and politics grows ever more doubtful.</p>
        <p>''There is increasing evidence the American public has an ability to ignore what the pundits say,'' said Andrew Kohut, director of the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press.</p>
        <p>As an example, Mr. Kohut pointed to the disparity last week between the news media and the public in their reactions to the Boston debate. ''At least for a while, the pundits were saying Gore won,'' Mr. Kohut said. ''But the subsequent polling showed that he lost support, because when people focused on the candidates, they personally liked Gore less.''</p>
        <p>In the hours after the second debate, writers and television commentators frequently concentrated on the toning down of Mr. Gore's debating style, and contrasted it with the seemingly more confident Mr. Bush. On ''The Early Show'' yesterday, an interview taped after the debate showed the reporter Bill Plante asking Mr. Gore, ''What do you make of the fact that all the snap polls showed you losing tonight?''</p>
        <p>''Not much,'' Mr. Gore replied, adding, ''Last week they all showed me winning, and then within a few days the pundits kind of took a different view. I think that snap polls are not really worth that much.''</p>
        <p>On the same program, Mr. Bush was told by another reporter, Bill Whitaker, that the polls Wednesday night gave him the advantage and, ''What do you think accounts for it?''</p>
        <p>''Gosh, I don't know, Bill,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I guess, maybe it's because of the format. Spent a lot of time on foreign policy, and I think I might have surprised some people about my ability to converse in foreign policy.''</p>
        <p>Whether it is even a useful exercise for commentators to declare a winner in a presidential debate seems debatable. Kathleen Hall Jamieson, dean of the Annenberg School for Communication at the University of Pennsylvania, said she advised viewers to turn off their televisions the moment the debate was over because everything they heard in the post-debate chatter was meaningless to efforts to form an opinion.</p>
        <p>''It's dangerous,'' said Ms. Jamieson, who often appears on network talking-head programs as an expert on the news media. ''And the reason it's dangerous is that it displaces information that's useful with information that's useless.''</p>
        <p>Of the networks' penchant for identifying the victor and the vanquished in the debate, she added: ''I don't know what it means and I am a former varsity debater. I can tell you how to call a college debate, but I can't tell you how to call a presidential debate.''</p>
        <p>Even some of those who do the tea-leaf-reading acknowledge that the analysis can sometimes be less than either a science or an art.</p>
        <p>''I think the American people have a funny way of deciding for themselves that pundits are often full of it,'' said Brian Williams, the MSNBC anchor who presided over the channel's coverage of the debates. ''We can act as the viewer's guide, and some among us have been terribly wrong at times.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Williams does not apologize for reporting on both the weighty and the frivolous things on viewers' minds.</p>
        <p>''I will say this,'' he added. ''If all of this stuff counts, if we are really and truly worried about scarecrow makeup and suits riding up on the backs of candidates, then this is an awfully silly age we're living in.''</p>
        <p>The networks and newspaper alike seem consumed these days with filling time and space with the results of instantaneous polling and the trendy instrument of the moment, the focus group. Hotline, in fact, has added a new feature this year, a roundup of the outcomes of focus groups that many news organizations have set up on the evenings of convention speeches and debates. Yesterday, the online journal reported on focus groups conducted by news organizations in 21 states.</p>
        <p>Among them were groups organized in Washington State by The Seattle Post-Intelligencer and in Michigan by The Detroit News. At least they did not reflect any lockstep tendencies. While Mr. Bush was the choice of seven of the eight college debaters assembled by the Post-Intelligencer, Mr. Gore was the favorite of seven of the nine Oakland County undecided voters selected by the News.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PUNDITS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
