<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Batsman, Guard Your Wicket!</title>
    <meta content="13CRIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/living/13CRIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND WARRIOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cricket (Game)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demarco, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED9163FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Batsman, Guard Your Wicket!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER DeMARCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demarco, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter DeMarco Weekend Warrior article on cricket in New York region, which has 12 leagues and 200 teams; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the score 118 to 36, it was officially garbage time in the night's match between Putnam and Simply Paradise, two teams in the Calypso Night Cricket League. The mostly West Indian crowd of about 300 had lost all interest in the game, turning its attention to Red Stripe beer, fried codfish cakes and the reggae music blaring on the sound system. Even the participants had grown weary of the game. ''We can come back against them, right?'' I asked Putnam's manager, Nigel Seale. He stared into the distance, forlornly shaking his head.</p>
        <p>A few pitches later, our team captain, Victor Niles, was bowled out, cricket's equivalent of being struck out. Putnam needed a new batsman, and Mr. Seale, surmising that the situation was hopeless, decided to symbolically throw in the towel: he put me in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the score 118 to 36, it was officially garbage time in the night's match between Putnam and Simply Paradise, two teams in the Calypso Night Cricket League. The mostly West Indian crowd of about 300 had lost all interest in the game, turning its attention to Red Stripe beer, fried codfish cakes and the reggae music blaring on the sound system. Even the participants had grown weary of the game. ''We can come back against them, right?'' I asked Putnam's manager, Nigel Seale. He stared into the distance, forlornly shaking his head.</p>
        <p>A few pitches later, our team captain, Victor Niles, was bowled out, cricket's equivalent of being struck out. Putnam needed a new batsman, and Mr. Seale, surmising that the situation was hopeless, decided to symbolically throw in the towel: he put me in.</p>
        <p>Wearing an ocean blue V-neck shirt and white windbreaker pants, I strode to the center of the field at Kingston Park, in Brooklyn, for the first cricket at-bat of my life. After a three-week crash course in cricket, I was boldly going where few born-in-the-U.S.A. souls had gone before. I was about to bat, not in front of a catcher and umpire but in front of a three-foot-tall wooden wicket. And while I had the chance to deliver six runs with one swing of the bat, I could just as easily encounter a googly (a loopy curve ball) or endure every batsman's nightmare, the dreaded golden duck (being bowled  out on the first ball).</p>
        <p>But I'm getting ahead of myself. The object of cricket, as with baseball, is to score more runs than the opposing team. Likewise, there are batsmen and pitchers, fielders, outs, and innings. But the similarities end right there. In cricket, there are no bases and there is no dirt diamond. Two batsmen stand on the field at once, facing each other the way a pitcher and a catcher would. Nobody uses gloves, and when batsmen run, they carry their bats, which look like short canoe paddles. Pitchers, called bowlers, throw the ball on a bounce and can plunk a batsman without fear of penalty. Meanwhile, when a batsman hits a ball, he doesn't have to run if he thinks he'll be thrown out. And did I mention where the foul lines are? There aren't any.</p>
        <p>In its own way, though, cricket is a structured and orderly game. It's played on a grass, oval field about the size of a soccer field. In the exact center of the field is a dirt rectangle about the length of a tennis court.  This is the pitch. At both ends of the pitch, there are three thigh-high wooden stakes, called stumps, with two Magic-Marker-size wooden dowels, called bails, resting across the  top. The stumps and bails together are called a wicket. The batsmen, both on the same team and each one holding a bat, stand in front of their wickets and face each other.</p>
        <p>The bowler starts from a spot about 15 feet behind one of the batsmen. He always pitches to the batsman at the far wicket, who is facing him. The bowler runs in at full tilt, and when he reaches the first wicket he hurls the ball 66 feet -- the length of the dirt -- toward the batsman. If the ball gets past the batsman and hits the wicket, knocking off the bails, the batsman is out. If the ball is hit and then caught in midair, he's out, too. But if the batsman hits the ball, and it isn't caught before it touches the ground, the batsmen can try to score runs.</p>
        <p>How do they score runs if there's no home plate? Simple. Each batsman runs to the opposite wicket area, passing the other in mid-run like two subway shuttles moving in opposite directions between Times Square and Grand Central. If both batsmen reach their wickets safely, the team gets a run. If the fielders are slow at retrieving the ball, batsmen can run back and forth again to score another run. That's all they ever do: run back and forth. An out is made when a fielder throws the ball into the wicket, knocking off its bails, before the advancing runner reaches the ''popping crease,'' a line on the ground that marks the starting point of the wicket area.</p>
        <p>A hit that eludes the fielders and rolls off the playing field -- a ''boundary hit'' in cricket parlance -- is an automatic four runs; any ball that leaves the field's boundary in the air is good for six runs. Again, since there is no foul territory, any batted ball is a fair ball, even one that glances backward off a bat.</p>
        <p>There are no balls or strikes in cricket, and a batsman doesn't have to run after a hit. As a matter of fact, the batsman stays at bat until he's out, which could be an eternity.</p>
        <p>Though it's hard to believe, cricket, which originated in Britain around the 16th century, was immensely popular in America before the Civil War, until baseball eclipsed it after 1865. But with the influx of immigrants in recent decades, cricket has made a comeback, at least in New York City. Immigrants from former British colonies, including the West Indies, India and Pakistan,  fill the rosters of more than 200 teams. For them and their families, cricket is an obsession. In Canarsie Beach Park, home to the best grass cricket field in the city, Sunday matches can attract crowds of nearly 3,000.</p>
        <p>Being a neophyte, I was advised to try my hand at a variation of cricket called softball cricket, which is nothing more than cricket played in a schoolyard with a tennis ball instead of on grass with the standard hard, red ball. I arranged to meet two of the best cricket players in New York,  Richard Louis and Wayne Headley, both of whom have played for the United States in international competition, at a game for a private tutorial.</p>
        <p>My first practice with the Putnam team came a few days later, and having played baseball all my life, I must admit I thought hitting would be a cinch. A large, friendly private contractor who went by the name of Crush, the only American member of the team, told me I was dreaming. I stepped up to the wicket with Crush's bat, a flat-faced paddle with a rubber grip handle, and set my sights on the bowler, a gangly teammate nicknamed Spooner, who immediately broke into a slightly unnerving full sprint in my direction. As he reached the wicket area, his arms went flailing windmill-style, and before I knew it, the ball was out of his hand and coming my way. It bounced a few feet in front of me and I managed to swing and fight it off, nubbing a grounder.</p>
        <p>I fared no better at my next practice; my teammates said I swung too hard and needed serious work at angling my flat bat the proper way. But like it or not, I was ready to play. Our team assembled at dusk at Kingston Park, in Bedford-Stuyvesant, with its fenced-in, rubberized recreational field, and during warm-ups I was issued a blue jersey. Mr. Seale, our manager and one of the founders of the 30-year-old softball cricket league, called the team together for a few inspirational words before I jogged out to my position somewhere in the cricket outfield.</p>
        <p>The first ball to come my way was a quick-moving grounder that was headed for the boundary line. Victor, my team captain, and I raced to the ball and I, gloveless, went into a full-body slide to block it with my leg. Had the ball bounced off the field, Simply Paradise would have scored four runs. Instead, throwing the ball in quickly, I held them to just two, and to my surprise earned an ovation from the crowd and handshakes from my teammates.</p>
        <p>My next chance did not go as well. Their batsman lofted a ball into the lights, and I camped under it. But when I went to catch it, the tennis ball popped out of my hands and fell to the ground. Instead of getting an out, I had given Simply Paradise four more runs, as their batsmen exchanged places twice during the play. Lucky for me, those four runs didn't make the difference. Simply Paradise was simply devastating, running up 118 runs before using up all their pitches. (Each team got 96.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Seale sent up our best batsmen to start things off, but they ran into trouble early, scoring a paltry six runs before one of them was thrown out. One by one our batsmen went down, and after Victor made the sixth out, I got the call to bat. I stood motionless as the bowler's first pitch came flying at me, plunked my leg and bounded harmlessly away. Phew! Getting hit was no great accomplishment, but I had dodged the golden duck.</p>
        <p>The remainder of my time at bat, judging from the crowd's reaction, was rather comical. Bowlers change directions after every six pitches (called collectively an ''over'') and the next pitches happened to be to Wendell Jones, my batting partner. He fought off a few bowls before bouncing a ball to the outfield. ''C'mon! C'mon!'' he yelled at me as he started running. I broke late for the opposite wicket and, fearing I might be thrown out, I slid across the popping crease, tearing a hole in the knee of my pants. The ball, however, was nowhere near me, and the crowd hooted at my unnecessary enthusiasm. But I had scored a run, which brought cheers from my teammates.</p>
        <p>My final tally, after being thrown out on a close play, was four runs, two scored on Wendell's hits, two scored when pitches again hit me in the leg and bounced so far away that I was able to sprint to the opposite wicket. With my knees scraped and my pants torn, I dusted myself off and walked toward the Putnam bench, where my teammates praised my hustle while noting I was good entertainment for the crowd.</p>
        <p>A few bowls later, the game was mercifully over, with Putnam losing, 118-48, and my cricket career had come to an end. Walking back to the A train, a few members of the crowd stopped me to ask whether I had liked the game. Reflecting for a moment, I told them I truly had. Cricket, for all its bizarre terminology and rules, is at its core an innocent game of hit the ball, catch the ball, throw the ball. It requires skill, hustle, strategy and most of all, teamwork -- just like baseball.</p>
        <p>Bowled Over</p>
        <p>There are 12 cricket leagues and 200 teams in the New York region. Softball cricket leagues play May through October at parks in Queens, the Bronx and Brooklyn. (Most hardball leagues play from May through September, at grass cricket fields at Van Cortlandt Park in the Bronx and Canarsie Beach Park in Brooklyn, among other places.)</p>
        <p>Information about joining a team is available by contacting Selwyn Caesar, (914) 969-4779, or selwync  @prodigy.net. Complete listings of all New York cricket teams, along with schedules, can be found on the Internet at http://members.aol  .com/nycr1/.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND WARRIOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
