<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martial Arts For Americans</title>
    <meta content="13FLIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13FLIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bunuel, Luis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Jackie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Diary of a Chambermaid (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Legend of Drunken Master, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2DE143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martial Arts For Americans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rick Lyman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, Oct. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At the Movies column; Jackie Chan comments on re-release of 1994 movie The Legend of Drunken Master; photo; new version of Luis Bunuel's 1964 movie Diary of a Chambermaid to open in New York (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Stand up,'' Jackie Chan said. ''Come here.''</p>
        <p>He rose from his chair, smoothing the folds of his cream-colored Nehru suit, set his feet apart in a fighting stance, held his left forearm back against his side, the fingers extending like an elegant claw, and pushed the right arm forward, his hand twisting in the air and then beckoning. This man could snap your spine like a twig. ''I want to show you something,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chan has been the dominant martial-arts star in the world for more than 20 years, largely on the strength of his deft mixture of martial mayhem with astonishing physical comedy. (Born in China, he was sent by his parents to train with the Beijing Opera at age 6 before being lured away to the world of Hong Kong filmmaking.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Stand up,'' Jackie Chan said. ''Come here.''</p>
        <p>He rose from his chair, smoothing the folds of his cream-colored Nehru suit, set his feet apart in a fighting stance, held his left forearm back against his side, the fingers extending like an elegant claw, and pushed the right arm forward, his hand twisting in the air and then beckoning. This man could snap your spine like a twig. ''I want to show you something,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chan has been the dominant martial-arts star in the world for more than 20 years, largely on the strength of his deft mixture of martial mayhem with astonishing physical comedy. (Born in China, he was sent by his parents to train with the Beijing Opera at age 6 before being lured away to the world of Hong Kong filmmaking.)</p>
        <p>In recent years, he has crossed over into American films, most notably ''Rush Hour'' with the comic actor Chris Tucker.</p>
        <p>He was in this strangely large and empty meeting room at the Four Seasons Hotel in Los Angeles, though, to help promote the spiffed-up and redubbed re-release by Dimension Films of a movie he made in 1994, a film cherished among his hard-core enthusiasts. Originally called ''Jui Ken II'' (''Drunken Master II''), it will be released this month as ''The Legend of Drunken Master,'' on the theory that American audiences are unlikely to remember the original ''Drunken Master,'' made in 1979.</p>
        <p>''In the big fight at the end, against the main bad guy, it looks as though we are pushing and fighting against each other,'' he said, reaching forward with his right hand to grab a wrist and yank. ''But really, we are helping one another. This is how it is done.'' He leaned forward, slowly, making it look as if he was punching  when he was actually ''resting forward,'' enabling him to extend his left leg in an elegant pivot.</p>
        <p>''No one will do fighting scenes today the way we did them in 1994,'' he said. ''Four days we work on a fight that lasts six minutes. No one can do this anymore. It is too expensive.''</p>
        <p>The film is set in a small town in China where the father of the hero (Mr. Chan) owns a karate school. Mr. Chan has been forbidden by his father to indulge in a style of martial arts known as ''drunken boxing,'' meaning he carefully drinks just enough alcohol to make himself limber but not so much as to make himself awkward, and then can bob and weave, somewhat comically, through a whole platoon of bad guys.</p>
        <p>''The first 'Drunken Master' we made for less than $200,000, and the people love it, but I know that it is very cheap and I wanted to make it again, but better,'' Mr. Chan said, explaining the sequel. ''I want to have jokes that are not like the cheap jokes and fighting that is not so cheap and, more important, is more reasonable.''</p>
        <p>In his earliest fighting, Mr. Chan said, he overemphasized the acrobatics and the artistic poses at the expense of plausibility. ''We want too much to show the pretty'' is the way he put it. Later, when he had the money, he tried to concoct fighting scenes that were elegant but also more credible, if one man fighting off 200 can ever be truly credible.</p>
        <p>He is delighted that Dimension is rereleasing the film, with a new soundtrack, a new print and fresh English dubbing. (Mr. Chan does his own voice; the others are American actors.) These days, Mr. Chan said, he alternates between making films for American and Hong Kong audience, having concluded that their tastes were too different to be accommodated in any one film. In May, he released ''Shanghai Noon,'' a western, for his American fans, and he has just finished ''Accidental Spy,'' about a man who sells exercise equipment who becomes embroiled in espionage in Istanbul, for his Hong Kong fans. Next, he will shoot ''Rush Hour II'' for his American audience.</p>
        <p>''I really feel that I have two kinds of audiences,'' Mr. Chan said. ''And I don't want to lose either of them. Some movies are very big in Asia, do very little here. 'Rush Hour' was very big here. In Asia they do not understand; they do not get the jokes.''</p>
        <p>He smoothed his jacket again and returned to his chair. ''Please be seated,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bunuel, Refurbished</p>
        <p>Jackie Chan is not the only one seeing an old film get a polished re release. It is a growing trend to refurbish classics digitally and give them a fresh theatrical release, though they haven't tended to make a fortune. The phenomenally successful rerelease of ''The Exorcist'' is the most prominent recent example, and its success presages more.</p>
        <p>Jean-Claude Carriere was excited as he spoke over the telephone from his home in Paris about the prospect that American audiences would soon see a fresh version of Luis Bunuel's ''Diary of a Chambermaid'' (1964), starring Jeanne Moreau, which Mr. Carriere adapted for the legendary Spanish director. The new version is opening on Friday at Film Forum in the South Village for a two-week run.</p>
        <p>''In France, we used to see the re-release of classic films every 15 or 20 years, but it is something that we are losing,'' he said. ''It is a pity, but it rarely happens here anymore. So it is very encouraging that it is beginning to happen in America because, you know, some films can get lost with time, completely disappear, even well-regarded films.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carriere is one of the most prolific and highly regarded international screenwriters of the last 40 years, with a mind-boggling array of screenplays to his credit. With Mr. Bunuel, perhaps his most famous collaborator, he also made ''Belle de Jour'' in 1967 and ''The Discreet Charm of the Bourgeoisie'' in 1972. But even a cursory look at his credits shows that he also worked with Louis Malle (''Le Voleur,'' 1967), Volker Schlondorff (''The Tin Drum,'' 1979, and ''Swann in Love,'' 1984), Andrzej Wajda (''Danton,'' 1982), Daniel Vigne (''The Return of Martin Guerre,'' 1982) and Philip Kaufman (''The Unbearable Lightness of Being,'' 1988).</p>
        <p>''I am afraid,'' Mr. Carriere said, ''that if we continue to ignore the great films of the past, the commercial side of the industry will take over completely and we will lose the other tradition. The art of the great films will become a vanished art.''</p>
        <p>But he knows film companies will not put the time and money into refurbishing and rereleasing classics unless there is an audience for them, which remains to be seen. It is one thing for the masses to turn up afresh to watch Linda Blair spit pea soup at Ellen Burstyn; it is another to have them bend their minds around a scabrous Bunuel satire of the upper crust.</p>
        <p>''I will be 70 next year,'' Mr. Carriere said. ''I have seen a decline in filmmaking from the days when I first began in the 1950's and 60's. It is not so much in the quality of films as in the impact they have on society. There was a time you could not go to a dinner party without being ready to discuss your reaction to the latest films. But not so anymore. Not so. It is a pity. Perhaps it will come back.''</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
