<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EATING OUT</title>
    <meta content="13EATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDF163FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EATING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out reviews of some Manhattan restaurants where one can have a quiet conversation; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Serenity</p>
        <p>Finding peace and quiet in a noisy, bustling city like New York can be a challenge. But refuges do exist. Here are 12 places in Manhattan where you can hold a peaceful conversation. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Serenity</p>
        <p>Finding peace and quiet in a noisy, bustling city like New York can be a challenge. But refuges do exist. Here are 12 places in Manhattan where you can hold a peaceful conversation. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Alley's End</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 627-8899</p>
        <p>311 West 17th Street, Chelsea</p>
        <p>$$ Discover, Mastercard, Visa</p>
        <p>Walk through a portal and traverse a passageway, and you leave the workaday Chelsea world for Alley's End, a lovely network of dining rooms and a garden that feels as pastoral and isolated as an oasis. The food has always managed to match the romantic draw of the interior. Both the chef and the menu have changed since this restaurant was last reviewed. The current menu includes roast pork loin and apple succotash, pan-roasted wild striped bass with warm chickpea salad, and herbed vegetable pot pie with chanterelles and sweet peas.</p>
        <p>2. Bayard's</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 514-9454</p>
        <p>1 Hanover Square</p>
        <p>Financial district</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The former Cotton Exchange, now India House, a business club, has been beautifully restored to create one of New York's most gracious dining rooms. The service is decorous, too, and the wine list is encyclopedic and affordable. Main courses include roasted veal medallions with wild mushroom cream and fettuccini, and grilled dover sole with sauteed spinach and mustard sauce. For dessert there is a fun assortment of cremes brulees in silly flavors that change nightly but often include licorice, strawberry and espresso.</p>
        <p>3. Cello</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 517-1200</p>
        <p>53 East 77th Street</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The interior design of this tiny French seafood restaurant is quiet and neutral, seemingly intended to keep the focus on the lush creations of Laurent Tourondel, the executive chef. The menu includes appetizers like warm gratin of crab Parmentier with a crisp celery salad, and Maine scallops with pan-seared foie gras, roasted corn and ketchup emulsion. Main courses include potato-crusted halibut with glazed salsify and mushroom cappuccino, and Atlantic turbot with sage-wrapped foie gras. Desserts are top-notch, and the wine list is well chosen.</p>
        <p>4. Chanterelle</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 966-6960</p>
        <p>2 Harrison Street, at Hudson Street</p>
        <p>TriBeCa</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The glory is in the details at this dreamy TriBeCa temple, where the spare simplicity of the food and the dining room almost conceals the high level of care and luxury. But you soon notice the perfection of the service, the gorgeous flowers, the artistic menu covers, the wonderful lighting that makes everybody beautiful. Once you are served, layers of flavor begin to unfold, calling your attention to the food in a sort of culinary double take. Grilled seafood sausage is a Chanterelle hallmark. The menu, which changes monthly, now includes striped bass with lobster mashed potatoes, and loin and rack of lamb with ginger and Chinese eggplant. Don't miss the cheese course, or the fresh and fragrant desserts.</p>
        <p>5. La Grenouille</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 752-1495</p>
        <p>3 East 52nd Street</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>At La Grenouille the light is golden, the floral displays are magnificent and the staff is professional and caring. The menu at this venerable restaurant still gives classics, including quenelles de brochet, pride of place. But nowadays you can be adventurous, with wonderfully creative dishes like grilled wild striped bass with truffle-impressed pasta and warm squab salad with figs. And the dessert souffles are the best in New York.</p>
        <p>6. Gus's Place</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 645-8511</p>
        <p>149 Waverly Place, near Christopher Street</p>
        <p>Greenwich Village</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>If the first waves of crisp weather hadn't already reached New York, you could easily imagine Gus's Place on a Greek island, cooled by gentle breezes rippling in from the sea. Tiny fried fish are hard to stop eating, while traditional Greek spreads like taramosalata, tzatziki and melitzanes salata are fine renditions. You can make a meal of mezedes like chickpea fritters and tender, lemony sauteed squid. Main courses include baked salmon in phyllo and grilled shrimp with orzo. Gus's also has a nice selection of Greek wines.</p>
        <p>7. Hangawi</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 213-0077</p>
        <p>12 East 32nd Street</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The air is full of music as fresh as wind whispering through branches in a remote mountain forest. Then it drops until it has turned into the melodic sound of water rushing over rocks. Slippers pad reverently across pine floors, and servers kneel to place lacquered dishes on low tables. This restaurant, dedicated to ancient principles of Korean cuisine, is a shrine to the vegetarian impulse, with all the cleanness, lightness and purity so often attributed to it fully in evidence. Wondrous dishes abound, like pumpkin porridge, a fresh, clean vegetable balanced by spicy bites of transparent noodles. Mountain roots like lanceolata, sliced and marinated in chili paste, are downright exotic. Most people haven't tried food like this, and it can be a marvelous adventure.</p>
        <p>8. Honmura An</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 334-5253</p>
        <p>170 Mercer Street</p>
        <p>SoHo</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The buckwheat noodles called soba are notoriously difficult to make, but the chefs at this elegantly spare, quietly soothing Japanese restaurant have mastered the art. You can begin with a dish of edamame, fresh salted soy beans still in their pods, and cold sake, served in a salt-edged cedar box that somehow makes the flavor of the sake seem even purer. Try another appetizer if you're hungry, like tori dango, lightly fried balls of ground chicken that are intriguingly flavorful. Then bring on the noodles. In their most elemental form, they are eaten cold, dipped in a sauce of soy, rice wine, bonito flakes, kelp and sugar. They are also served hot with toppings like sliced duck or button mushrooms.</p>
        <p>9. Lhasa</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 674-5870</p>
        <p>96 Second Avenue, near Fifth Street</p>
        <p>East Village</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This Tibetan restaurant is a mellow, quiet place with tranquil music playing softly in the background and a staff that is friendly, calm, alert and responsive. With its Chinese and Indian influences, you'd expect Tibetan food to be spicy, but in fact it's mild. Some of the better dishes include shrimp patties, firm disks filled with chopped shrimp that are delicious with their minty dipping sauce; wonderfully savory fried momo, or dumplings, stuffed with chicken; and tsel gyathuk ngopa, or egg noodles, sauteed until almost crisp and topped with spinach, carrots and bok choy.</p>
        <p>10. Oceana</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 759-5941</p>
        <p>55 East 54th Street</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Oceana's downstairs dining room is small and pretty, with an old-fashioned air. The intimate upstairs dining room is small with a sedate sound level and enough polished wood to give it the luxurious air of a dining room on a private yacht. Rick Moonen, the chef, has mastered the art of cooking fish. His grasp is global, and he uses accents from all over the world to enhance the essential nature of each kind of fish. Main courses are superb, whether fancy, like Brazilian green tail snapper with steamed baby bok choy, sweet and sour cabbage, in a spicy lemon grass coconut nage; or plain, like lemon-glazed mahi-mahi served with basmati rice, roasted root vegetables and a citrus herb emulsion. Desserts are understated but wonderful.</p>
        <p>11. San Domenico</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 265-5959</p>
        <p>240 Central Park South</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>One of the few American restaurants to showcase the cooking of the aristocratic Italian kitchen, San Domenico serves food far more ambitious than that of the average Italian restaurant. And far more rewarding. The restaurant's signature dish is uovo in ravioli al burro nocciola tartufato: a single large puff of ravioli filled with ricotta and spinach perfumed with truffle butter. Snuggled inside is an egg that spurts golden yolk onto the plate as you begin to eat. Garganelli, hand-rolled penne, come tossed with caviar and chives. But the kitchen does not need luxury ingredients to show its stuff. The simple spaghetti alla chitarra, in a tomato and basil sauce, is like no spaghetti you have ever tasted. The dining room is dignified, quiet and comfortable.</p>
        <p>12. La Soiree d'Asie</p>
        <p>* [Rating: 1 star]</p>
        <p>(212) 421-7899</p>
        <p>156 East 64th Street</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>It would be difficult to imagine a more peaceful restaurant than this Upper East Side town house where beautiful waitresses in silk dresses glide serenely through quiet rooms. It would be even harder to imagine a less threatening Vietnamese menu. Appetizers include the familiar spring rolls, dumplings and fried ravioli. The best of the main courses are among the house specials. Sugar-cane shrimp, a traditional dish of shrimp paste broiled on sticks of sugar cane and served with rice pancakes, are fun to eat. The special clay-pot rice mixed with shrimp, chicken and crunchy bits of black mushroom is slightly sweet and surprisingly delicious.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
