<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="13ART.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0D9163FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="8567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''AMAZONS OF THE AVANT-GARDE,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500 (through Jan. 7). A concise exercise, monographically arranged, this show focuses on six Russian women who painted around the time of the revolution. Several continued to work much later and do more than paint, but this is a tendentious affair, plausibly so. If only a couple of the women, Natalia Goncharova and Liubov Popova, were truly great painters, the exhibition still isn't a case of special pleading. The Russian avant-garde wouldn't have been what it was without them collectively. The story as it unfolds here seems, if anything, more remarkable, not less, for having as little to do with sex as it does and almost everything to do with painting. Many of the works have a surprising fortitude. Revolution. A brave new art world. The dream persists even though the form it takes keeps changing. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission: $12; $8 for students and the elderly (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''AMAZONS OF THE AVANT-GARDE,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500 (through Jan. 7). A concise exercise, monographically arranged, this show focuses on six Russian women who painted around the time of the revolution. Several continued to work much later and do more than paint, but this is a tendentious affair, plausibly so. If only a couple of the women, Natalia Goncharova and Liubov Popova, were truly great painters, the exhibition still isn't a case of special pleading. The Russian avant-garde wouldn't have been what it was without them collectively. The story as it unfolds here seems, if anything, more remarkable, not less, for having as little to do with sex as it does and almost everything to do with painting. Many of the works have a surprising fortitude. Revolution. A brave new art world. The dream persists even though the form it takes keeps changing. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission: $12; $8 for students and the elderly (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''ART AND THE EMPIRE CITY: NEW YORK, 1825-1861,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through Jan. 7). The point is that during the antebellum years New York began to become, well, New York, America's megalopolis and an international crossroads. The great metaphor was the plan to grid Manhattan: unsentimental, open-ended, utilitarian and democratic, it created the blank sheet on which the city could draw its future. Amusing, gigantic, only marginally an art exhibition, the show is really an ostentatious illustrated history lesson via hundreds of pieces of old crockery, etchings, paintings, rosewood firescreens, daguerreotypes and mother-of-pearl folding fans. Custom-made for today's acquisitive age, the exhibition is probably the only occasion on which a 19th-century brown ceramic water cooler and a six-sided pitcher with pictures of the presidential candidate William Henry Harrison have been presented in the style of the treasures of the pharaoh's palace in ''The Ten Commandments.'' Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:15 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 8:45 p.m. Admission: $10; $5 for students and the elderly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''A BRUSH WITH NATURE: THE GERE COLLECTION OF LANDSCAPE OIL SKETCHES,'' Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 (through Nov. 12). Most of the artists in this show -- English, French, Italian, German, Belgian and Scandinavian, from the 17th to the 19th centuries -- are barely known today. In their own age they did something quite offbeat: they left studios to paint outdoors, registering transient moments of light and atmosphere by sketching quickly in oil from nature. Until recently it was assumed that this plein air approach, used to train hand and eye for more ambitious compositions, began with the Impressionists. These canvases today are sought-after prizes. The 68 on view here were assembled by a pioneering scholar and collector in the field, John Gere (1921-1995), former keeper of prints and drawings at the British Museum, and his wife, Charlotte. Mostly painted in Rome and the surrounding countryside, they capture such painterly events as the seamed face of a rock, the rush of water through a valley, the play of sunlight on a ruin, the quirky architecture of a building or a wall. Tune your eye to small when you look at this show, and you'll find it a treasure. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Admission: $7; $5 for students (over 10) and the elderly (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''THE EMBODIED IMAGE: CHINESE CALLIGRAPHY FROM THE JOHN B. ELLIOTT COLLECTION,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through Jan. 7). In China the written word has traditionally been the highest art form and a source of political and emotional power. To see that power in action, check out this grandly scaled exhibition, which brings together two superb calligraphy collections -- from Princeton University and the Met -- in the most comprehensive survey yet seen in these parts. The dozens of scrolls covered with hand-written words collectively radiate a kind of conversational buzz and suggest a richly varied cast of personalities: fastidious court functionaries, impulsive social agitators, unworldly monks, visionary poets. Together they offer an ice-breaking introduction to an art that can all too easily seem, to non-Chinese speakers, unapproachable. Hours and admission: See above (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>''HIP-HOP NATION: ROOTS, RHYMES AND RAGE,'' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 (through Dec. 31). The complex cultural amalgam of music, poetry, break-dancing, art and fashion that is hip-hop poses a serious challenge to any art museum, but with the proper resources and curatorial expertise, it could have been done. Instead this show offers a partial outline of hip-hop history, conveyed by photographs, posters, magazine and album covers, memorabilia and monotonous expanses of clothes that make the show nearly indistinguishable from the gift shop. Garnished with graffiti art, it bypasses many other equally interesting connections to contemporary art. Because the show omits music videos, it manages to be virtually devoid of the sounds, words and moving bodies that are the essence of hip-hop. The results are a cross between a mall and a mausoleum. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 11 p.m. on the first Saturday of each month); Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $4; $2 for students and the elderly (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>LEE KRASNER, Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 (through Jan. 7). Despite its restless energy and moments of formal power and elegance, Lee Krasner's career in this economical retrospective looks more like one of tantalizing frustration than real fulfillment. In the 1950's and early 60's, Krasner painted splattery, ambitious Abstract Expressionist works, but they look indebted to other artists, Pollock and de Kooning mainly. Where she looks most herself is in collage; a set of large collages on canvas from the early 50's have raw density or explosive buoyancy. Collages made in the 1970's using 40-year-old charcoal drawings have a beautiful Cubistic elegance; they are the best works of her career. Hours and admission: See above (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>''OPEN ENDS,'' Museum of Modern Art, 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400 (through Jan. 2). The third and final cycle of ''MOMA 2000,'' the year-and-a-half-long, millenium-marking rethinking of the Modern's permanent collection, is off and running, with the first of three staggered floor-through sections in place. The dates covered are 1960 to the present, so there's some sense of how a bastion of modernism is dealing with a postmodern world. Pretty well, judging from recent acquisitions of work by Pipilotti Rist, Matthew Barney and Cai Guo-Qiang. The real interest, though, is in smart theme shows that play with such contemporary fixations as childhood innocence and adult experience, and the blend of art, abjection and design. (The fourth-floor galleries will open on Thursday and the third-floor galleries on Nov. 5.) Hours: Saturdays through Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays, 10:30 a.m. to 8:15 p.m. Admission: $10; $6.50, students and the elderly (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''THE OPULENT EYE OF ALEXANDER GIRARD,'' Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400 (through March 18). The first comprehensive look at the multifaceted work of the architect and designer. Girard's contribution to contemporary design was a free approach that incorporated all sorts of visual stimuli, from Italian stage sets to Mexican folk art to motifs from modern technology, making exuberant use of color, pattern, texture and ornament. In photographs, models and objects, the exhibition displays his fabrics, graphics, interiors, furniture, tableware, radio cabinets and much else. A whole room is devoted to the more than 300 fabric and wallpaper designs he created for the Herman Miller Furniture Company from the 1950's to the early 1970's with fresh patterns and colors that pushed the limits of middle-class taste. While Girard may not have been a heavyweight in American design, he was one of its liveliest figures. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays until 9 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $8; $3 for students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''PIERRE ET GILLES,'' New Museum of Contemporary Art, 583 Broadway, near Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 219-1222 (through Jan. 7). No history of postmodern photography, fashion photography, celebrity portraiture, record album covers or the highbrow beefcake tradition would be complete without the work of the French photo team known as Pierre et Gilles, who have collaborated on over-the-top, tightly styled, hand-finished photographs since 1976 and become wildly famous in Europe in the process. In their first American museum retrospective, their work feels more than a little embalmed, existing behind a not-so-invisible shield of artistic conservatism. Certain images come to life as art objects -- most notably, one of a beautiful young sailor up to his chest in water with an iridescent night sky behind him -- but those are few. Hours: Wednesdays and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays through Saturdays, until 8 p.m. Admission: $6; $3 for students, artists and the elderly (Smith).</p>
        <p>* BRIDGET RILEY, ''Reconnaissance,'' Dia Center for the Arts, 548 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 989-5566 (through June 17). Once overly identified with Op Art, this British abstract painter never got her due in anti-Op New York, but this beautifully installed show of 40 paintings from 1961 to 1984 should change things. Concentrating on the early black-and-white paintings that made Ms. Riley famous, it presents stringently pure yet accessible works that have, at their best, extended the optical potential implicit in the work of Mondrian, Josef Albers and Ad Reinhardt. At their weakest, their meticulously calibrated patterns can be so aggressive that they virtually kidnap the eye, take it on a joy ride and leave it in a crumpled heap. Either way, the overall effect is of an artist of unusual dedication who has remained loyal to the original premises of her art and yet steadfastly refused to repeat herself. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $6; $3, students and the elderly (Smith).</p>
        <p>''RUSKIN'S ITALY, RUSKIN'S ENGLAND, ''Pierpont Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, (212) 685-0610 (through Jan. 7). This show commemorates the 100th anniversary of the death of John Ruskin (1819-1900), artist, art and architectural critic, social reformer, educator and the first official professor of art in England. From its own collections, the Morgan has mined a biographical medley of letters, manuscripts, photographs, drawings, paintings and artifacts relating to the life of this Victorian giant, whose published writings run to 39 volumes. Although not really an art show, it includes paintings and drawings by Ruskin and artists he admired, among them J. M. W. Turner and the Pre-Raphaelites John Everett Millais, William Holman Hunt, Edward Burne-Jones and Dante Gabriel Rossetti. It touches on his widely influential books of criticism, his beautifully finished sketches of architectural structures, his teaching and his monographs on proposed social reforms. Not omitted are his 1877 attack on James McNeill Whistler, his failed marriage and attraction to young girls and his sad end after a long siege of mental illness. But there is much to celebrate in his life, and this show doesn't stint. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; $6 for students and the elderly; free for children under 13 with an adult (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* EDWARD STEICHEN, Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, through Feb. 4. A big, thorough exhibition, maybe a little too big and glossy, of one of the great photographers in American history, a restless, benign, flawed genius. Steichen also painted, made films, designed textiles, organized aerial reconnaissance photography in two world wars and put together the most popular photography exhibition ever, ''The Family of Man.'' We'll see how people respond to someone whose eclectic work can look, if anything, almost too elegant and self-regarding. Steichen ultimately seemed to reduce everything and everyone to props to demonstrate his own refined and stage-savvy sensibility. But what refinement. His best work has a finesse that borders on the erotic. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 9 p.m. Admission: $12.50; $10.50 for students and the elderly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''THE YEAR ONE: ART OF THE ANCIENT WORLD EAST AND WEST,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 879-5500, through Jan. 14. The Met puts the millennial-marking art exhibition in a new perspective with a show that only an institution of its stature and girth could pull off. Drawn from seven departments, it revisits the beginning of the ''modern era'' around the time of the birth of Jesus with 150 sometimes tiny artworks that sample the nearly two dozen cultures flourishing at the beginning of the first millennium. The array stretches from imperial Rome to Han dynasty China, with many stops in between. High points include bronzes from Thailand and Indonesia, a Chinese mortuary pillar and a stunning recreation of the frescoed bedroom of a Roman villa. The display is supposed to reflect the beginning of a new world consciousness brought on by expanding empires and trade, a thesis more complex than the actual objects can sustain. But, no matter, most of them are considered masterpieces, all are beautifully installed and the opportunities for cross-cultural visual comparisons are rich. Hours and admission: See above (Smith).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>''IN THE EYE OF THE BEHOLDER,'' Kaikodo, 164 East 64th Street, (212) 223-0121 (through Oct. 21). Kaikodo's sales exhibitions are always a treat, and the sheer number of Chinese and Japanese paintings in this one is a major lure. These days New Yorkers rarely get to see material in this quantity and variety outside museums. Highlights include an album painting of a flower attributed to the 13th-century artist Qian Xuan (it's very fragile, so you have to ask to see it); a 17th-century calligraphic scroll by the fractious Fu Shan; and a witty four-panel portrait of a family of gibbons, gold-medal acrobats all. Devotees of ceramics and textiles will also find much to admire (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>MARK DI SUVERO, Danese, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 223-2227 (through Oct. 21). This small retrospective presents pedestal-scale sculptures from three decades by an artist best known for his monumental industrial-strength abstractions. Each rough, heavy metal piece has a Cubist assemblage balanced Calder-like on one point of another assemblage. There is a clunky sameness to most of the works; Mr. di Suvero has always been most inventive when he works big (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* RINEKE DIJKSTRA, Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 977-7160 (through Oct. 28). This Dutch artist's solo debut in the United States includes a video (much seen elsewhere) of dancing teenagers in European clubs and a series of photographs she has been taking since 1997 of children in parks. In the video the kids preen touchingly. The photographs, color pictures along the lines of Thomas Struth's but more casual and less chilly, are heroic portraits, acutely sympathetic (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>GERHARD RICHTER, Barbara Mathes, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 752-5135 (through Oct. 21). This exhibition of small works by the enigmatic and hugely influential German painter features a group of canvases from the 80's and 90's bearing his familiar brand of beautifully scraped, dragged and squeegeed Abstract Expressionism and an intriguing six-part photographic self-portrait in which blurry shirtless men -- the artist himself multiply exposed -- do mysterious things in dim, empty rooms (Johnson).</p>
        <p>BRIDGET RILEY, ''Paintings 1982-2000 and Early Works on Paper,'' PaceWildenstein, 32 East 57th Street, (212) 421-3292 (through Oct. 21). This show picks up where the small survey of Bridget Riley's paintings at the Dia Center for the Arts in Chelsea leaves off, following her continued involvement with color through nine recent canvases, while a group of gouache studies from the 1960's documents the transition from black-and-white to color, through subtlely vivid tones of gray (Smith).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>MONICA KULICKA, John Gibson, 568 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 925-1192 (through Oct. 30). As a protest against modern civilization's mechanization of the world, this young Polish artist who now lives in New York has slathered real, mossy green chlorophyll over five pieces of old wood furniture in a quixotic attempt to restore the dead wood to life. The absurdity of the gesture is amusing and yet somehow a little sad (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''LIFE, AFTER THE SQUIRREL,'' Location One, 26 Greene Street, (212) 334-3347 (through Oct. 28). This nutty fun house of a show begins with Filipe Miguel's rustic shed, supposedly inhabited by post-apocalyptic squirrels. The main exhibition space has a squishy plastic floor and a ceiling of inflated pine trees. Works include Tony Tasset's stuffed ''Dead Bluejay''; Aernout Mik's video of old men horsing around; a hypnotic video by Pipilotti Rist; John Neff's deadpan video recital of Hal the computer's last speech; and Vincent Pruden's provocative makeup table for applying blackface (Johnson).</p>
        <p>MANUEL NERI, Charles Cowles, 74 Grand Street, (212) 925-3500 (through Oct. 21). This veteran Bay Area Figurative School artist continues to produce his signature female figure sculptures in bronze or marble, in which the combination of smooth, finished parts and rough, unfinished parts (accented in the bronzes by expressionistic painting) produces tension between raw physicality and classical illusionism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''PARADISE NOW: PICTURING THE GENETIC REVOLUTION,'' Exit Art, 548 Broadway, near Prince Street, (212) 966-7748 (through Oct. 28). ''We are at a threshold,'' declares the text panel at the start of this show. And we are, you know. Never mind that most of the art isn't great, because with more and more artists tapping into science, something big is bound to happen soon. Think of this as a preliminary report. The works span a decade and run the gamut from paintings and sculptures to the collecting of sperm and the breeding of very tiny exotic frogs. The artists fret predictably about tampering with Mother Nature and stress identity politics, also predictably, but the spirit of the show, an intangible, tips the scales in a positive direction (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>GENEVIEVE SEILLE, Luise Ross, 568 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 343-2161 (through Oct. 21). This English-educated French artist is not a real outsider, but she does a good imitation. Her large, distressed, patched-together pages supporting dense, crazy-quilt accumulations of patterns, numbers and illegible writing suggest a collaboration between Jean Dubuffet and Adolf Wolfli (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* NEIL WINOKUR, Janet Borden, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 431-0166 (through Oct. 28). For this delightful portrait of his hometown, Mr. Winokur has produced a series of 32 still-life photographs, each a crystal-clear, deadpan picture of an ordinary but richly iconic object against a bright colored backdrop. A Greek-style paper coffee cup, a Chinese food container, a Giants pennant, an old Broadway playbill, a Con Edison orange cone, a hot dog, a rat, a toy-size Empire State Building: these images produce a resonantly evocative cross-section of New York experience (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>SUZANNE ANKER, Universal Concepts Unlimited, 507 West 24th Street, (212) 727-7575 (through Oct. 21). One of those Leonardo types who like to combine art and science, Ms. Anker presents silkscreened paintings and sculptures addressing the representation of genetics. Silkscreen panels display silvery, gridded fields of chromosome symbols with little human images mixed in. The 500 silver-painted, three-dimensional letters A, C, T and G piled on a glass panel refer to DNA. It is all rather more decorative than conceptually illuminating (Johnson).</p>
        <p>LOUISE FISHMAN, Cheim &amp; Read, 521 West 23rd Street, (212) 242-7727 (through Oct. 21). Ms. Fishman's Abstract Expressionist painting is still tough and gritty in its bluntly gestural, grid-based physicality, but now it has a lusciousness of color that verges on the hedonistic. ''A Stranger,'' with its web of impulsively made, wide slate-gray lines over a salmon pink field, is a voluptuous yet still excitingly raw picture (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DAMIEN HIRST, Gagosian Gallery, 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111 (through Dec. 16). Welcome to the Damien Hirst Universe. It's a big shiny place with mathematical grid paper printed on the walls, pale pristine dot paintings and many large vitrine sculptures, including two outfitted as gynecological examining rooms and filled with water and fish. It shows the artist moving beyond the dead animals and putrefying flesh that catapulted him to fame while clarifying and enriching the grandiose themes of his art: life and death and their complex, sometimes oppressive relationship to science and commerce. It contains some undeniable duds, but if it doesn't win over those who have resisted the work of this notorious young British artist, it won't be for lack of trying (Smith).</p>
        <p>ALBERT RENGER-PATZSCH, Tatintsian, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 633-0110 (through Oct. 28). If the German photographer Renger-Patzsch (1897-1966) were working today, he would probably make his formally perfect, subtly poetic pictures of industrialized landscapes, medieval church interiors and close-up plant studies into glossy, sofa-size Cibachromes. These small black-and-white vintage prints from the 1920's and 30's offer a welcome, intimately evocative respite from today's overly-showy photoaesthetics (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>TORBEN GIEHLER, Leo Koenig, 359 Broadway, at Franklin Street, TriBeCa, (212) 334-9255 (through Oct. 21). In bright acrylic colors, this young painter produces eye-grabbing gridded fields extending into deep space. The images suggest microscopic visions of computer circuitry or aerial views of futuristic cities. Mr. Giehler is indebted to Al Held for his hard-edged abstract illusionism and sci-fi fantasy, but he has his own promising vision (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''PASTORAL POP!,'' Whitney Museum of American Art at Philip Morris, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917) 663-2453 (through Dec. 15). Nature-inspired kitsch is the theme of this delirious seven-artist show. It includes Rob de Mar's comical landscape in the form of a spindly tree, Lisa Ruyter's psychedelic update of Seurat's ''Grande Jatte,'' Alyson Shotz's grove of weird plant machines, Peter Gould's transformation of the guard station into a bucolic cartoon, Jason Middlebrook's Styrofoam stonewall planter, Katrin Asbury's miniature diorama in a planter and Rachel Feinstein's suspended Rococo-style pitcher exploding flowers like a pinata (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''RE-DRAWING THE LINE,'' Art in General, 79 Walker Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-0473 (through Oct. 28). This unfocused show of works in which line figures, literally or conceptually, includes an invigorating giant doodle by Diana Cooper; whited out ledger pages by Peter Wegner; the image of a scribble cut from brown felt by Arturo Herrera; a dripped line from a performance by Francis Alys; a string sculpture by Pae White; and tangled plastic zip ties by Mungo Thomson. The importance of line in obliquely conceptual works by Alessandro Balteo and Sophie Tottie is harder to see (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>WILL BARNET, ''Works on Paper,'' Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, at 57th Street, (212) 262-5050 (through tomorrow). Mr. Barnet is known today for his illustrative, poetically classicizing figurative paintings. This survey of drawings over seven decades shows that the artist, who was born in 1911, has tried his always adept if rarely original hand at most of the major 20th-century styles, from Social Realism to Cubism to flattened and simplified 50's-style abstraction. Some drawings of children, penciled with exacting, curvy lines in the 1940's, are particularly affecting (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>STEPHANIE BROOKS, Ten in One, 526 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 604-9660 (through tomorrow). In her funny and inventively designed works, this young Chicagoan conflates ordinarily unrelated systems of verbal or visual signification (Johnson).</p>
        <p>NICOLE EISENMAN, Jack Tilton, 49 Greene Street, SoHo, (212) 941-1775 (through tomorrow). Since making her mark as a wickedly provocative, often hilarious cartoonist, Ms. Eisenman has mutated into a would-be fine painter. Her first New York exhibition in four years features carefully made, Renaissance-inspired paintings that depict extremes of lesbian sisterhood, including a neo-classical mural in which Amazon cannibals dine on stew made from butchered men. She is still at her best with her more spontaneous and darkly idiosyncratic drawings (Johnson).</p>
        <p>APRIL GORNIK, Edward Thorp, 210 11th Avenue, near 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-6565 (through tomorrow). Ms. Gornik continues to combine 19th-century Transcendentalism and 20th-century Modernism in the production of expansive dreamlike landscapes. At best, optical intensity goes hand in hand with divine immanence, as in ''Mirror Forest,'' in which greenish sunlight pours meltingly through a grove of young trees (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ALICE NEEL, ''The Last Years,'' Robert Miller, 524 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 366-4774 (through tomorrow). Late portrait paintings and a fine small drawing retrospective complement the Whitney's recent Neel retrospective. Some of the most arresting paintings are of children. The ghoulish-looking Jonathan in the arms of his father, Don Perlis, radiates demonic energy. The 15 drawings on paper, from the smoothly penciled ''Sam'' to the densely hatched ''Phil'' to the almost Minimalist ''Andy Warhol,'' argue persuasively for a more extensive show of drawings (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SELECTIONS FALL 2000,'' Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166 (through tomorrow). The center's latest show of emerging artists focuses on schematic drawing. It includes Mary Lum's cutout and layered painted line images of buildings; Lucas Monaco's crystalline transparent street maps; Oona Stern's cartoon wood floor; a mural by Geraldine Lau that resembles an air-traffic map; architectural and topographical fragments finely inked and layered by Julie Mehretu; Miranda Maher's semitransparent stacks of utilitarian illustrations; Glenn Grafelman's smudgy fenestration drawings; and photographs of Grady Gerbracht that trace passing scenes on a bus window (Johnson).</p>
        <p>BETTINA VON ZWEHL, Lombard-Freid Gallery, 531 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 967-8040 (through tomorrow). Ms. von Zwehl, a young German artist living in London, is one of several young photographers who fit a strict Conceptual framework around traditional portraiture. For her first solo show she invited young children into her studio, dressed them in identical (black) clothes and let them take their own pictures. She then juxtaposed the images in pairs, matching or contrasting poses, expressions and appearances. The disarming results rely too completely on the emotional transparency of children while also resembling Gap ads (Smith).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
