<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Williams's Serenity Sets Tone for Yankees</title>
    <meta content="13VECS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/sports/13VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Bernie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EED9153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Williams's Serenity Sets Tone for Yankees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column notes that New York Yankees center fielder Bernie Williams is not known as leader but his poise is transferable to his teammates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY say the great DiMaggio was a model of grace under pressure (as Hemingway's fisherman might have said).</p>
        <p>In that respect, Joe DiMaggio has a spiritual heir playing his old position for his old team. Bernie Williams's poise had a great deal to do with the Yankees arriving here tied at one game each and knowing it could have been much, much worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY say the great DiMaggio was a model of grace under pressure (as Hemingway's fisherman might have said).</p>
        <p>In that respect, Joe DiMaggio has a spiritual heir playing his old position for his old team. Bernie Williams's poise had a great deal to do with the Yankees arriving here tied at one game each and knowing it could have been much, much worse.</p>
        <p>The great DiMaggio (he was always ''the great DiMaggio'' to Hemingway's fisherman) showed frustration only once that anyone can remember. That was, of course, in the sixth game of the 1947 World Series when the diminutive Al Gionfriddo of the Brooklyn Dodgers ran a long, long way to catch a ball that DiMaggio expected to be a home run.</p>
        <p>As the Yankee Clipper got near second base -- in those days, every hitter ran out every ball because there was always somebody escaping the Depression who wanted a job -- and he took one kick at the ground. A bit of dust or sand flew up. And that was it. That was Joe D.'s career explosion.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams has never lost it in public.</p>
        <p>''The cameras don't reach where I do it,'' Williams said with his pacific smile yesterday.</p>
        <p>Williams had every excuse to lose it Wednesday when he produced one of the most raggedy, weak, piffling double plays possible.</p>
        <p>He came up in the first inning with the bases loaded -- just what the Yankees needed after being shut out the day before. This was a spot in which the Yankees of 1996, 1998 and 1999 had broken games open.</p>
        <p>Instead, as everybody knows by now, Williams tapped the ball straight down, about a foot in front of home plate. Catcher Dan Wilson  merely had to tick home plate and fire to first base for a double play that just about killed the Yankees' momentum, maybe even for the month of October.</p>
        <p>''Just an awful at-bat,'' Williams said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Managers and fans and broadcasters and writers and sometimes even teammates believe that if a player throws a tantrum or a helmet, it shows that he cares.</p>
        <p>Williams did not toss his bat, his helmet, his lunch, his soul. ''It doesn't do me any good,'' Williams said.  ''It's more meaningful for me to sit down.''</p>
        <p>He trotted to the bench with the bemused stare of a man who just had a bus door slammed in his face but wasn't going to let it ruin his day.</p>
        <p>''He didn't come in and say what a bad break he got,'' Joe Torre said. ''That was Bernie.''</p>
        <p>Torre, who freed Williams to become a Yankee star when he took over in 1996, sees his center fielder in the mold of another epic athlete. ''I never met Arthur Ashe,'' Torre said yesterday, referring to the late Davis Cup captain and tennis star, ''but from what a lot of people tell me, Bernie is a lot like him. They have the same dignity.''</p>
        <p>Williams, 32, has kept his composure since he was a Yankee rookie, and was teased mercilessly by Mel Hall, the itinerant outfielder. Williams was taught by his parents in Puerto Rico not to come back with fists or words.</p>
        <p>''You want to hug him,'' Torre said. ''He can go from 0 to 100 when he gets that look in his eye.''</p>
        <p>The look does not come through in overt gestures, like the fury of Paul O'Neill, who thought he was robbed of a ball four on Wednesday and then was called out at first on a very close play. O'Neill was cool enough not to get tossed, but as he gesticulated at first base, it was clear he was still dwelling on the lost walk. The public loves Paul for his histrionics, as well it might, but Williams's silent water also runs deep.</p>
        <p>In the eighth inning Wednesday, with the Yankees six outs from being in huge trouble, David Justice hit a double and Williams fouled off a few pitches and then stroked a single that gave the Yankees their first run. Six more runs followed, and they could take their long flight knowing they had escaped. Did Williams attribute his artful single to his composure seven innings earlier?</p>
        <p>''I'd like to say it is,'' he said, ''but it's a different situation, with two different pitchers. One of them was moving the ball back and forth and the other was throwing 95 miles an hour. My job in the eighth was to move the guy over. It made me realize I didn't have to hit a home run, which is what I was trying to do in the first inning.''</p>
        <p>Williams will not say it, but his poise was transferable to his teammates. He is not known as a leader, but cleanup hitters must set a tone.</p>
        <p>The next time the Yankee nostalgia machine is evoking Joe D. and the Mick and Reggie and Donnie Baseball, think about the beatific smile on Bernie Williams, and enjoy another great old Yankee while he is in his prime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
