<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Whispers'</title>
    <meta content="RV000243" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13WHI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Joubert, Dereck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Whispers: An Elepphant's Tale (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED8153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Whispers'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews Disney movie Whispers: An Elephant's Tale, directed by Dereck Joubert (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'An Elephant's Tale' Directed by Dereck Joubert  G; 72 minutes</p>
        <p>Eyes wide open. Ears stuffed shut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'An Elephant's Tale' Directed by Dereck Joubert  G; 72 minutes</p>
        <p>Eyes wide open. Ears stuffed shut.</p>
        <p>That is the recommended recipe for ingesting ''Whispers: An Elephant's Tale,'' a custard of cloying anthropomorphism under the Walt Disney Pictures label compounded out of extraordinary nature film bonded to a layer of inane dialogue.</p>
        <p>Perhaps not since Woody Allen's ''What's Up, Tiger Lily?'' in 1966 has the application of concocted speech to essentially unrelated images produced such a clash of cultures.</p>
        <p>Here, remarkable film of African wildlife in Botswana is enslaved to a G-rated story of the travails of a newborn male elephant expressed in a way that might well trigger the gag reflex of Babar.</p>
        <p>The splendid scenes of elephants, lions, hippos and great herds of other animals in Botswana are the work of Dereck and Beverly Joubert. On the other side of the scale, the Jouberts created the story; Mr. Joubert shares responsibility for the screenplay with Jordan Moffet and Holly Goldberg Sloan, and Mr. Joubert directed the resulting film.</p>
        <p>A rival to Disney's animated classic ''Bambi'' this is not.</p>
        <p>Not when the older elephants greet baby Whispers with lines like ''He's got his mother's trunk'' or his early trumpeting with ''What a great set of pipes.'' Or, later in the film, when a mature female supposedly says, ''You can never be too fat or too gray.''</p>
        <p>To its credit, ''Whispers'' captures astonishing film of a newborn elephant and of a nocturnal attack by a pack of lions on an elephant. And the film's honorable message is that its heroic elephants are rare treasures that must be protected from slaughter by the people the film's elephants call takers.</p>
        <p>So named because these hunters take only tusks after killing the elephants, these hunters are the villains of ''Whispers.'' Not long after his birth, Whispers is told by his mother, Gentle Heart, to run and hide from an attack by the takers. She promises that she will find him again.</p>
        <p>But Whispers soon finds himself alone. Unwelcome in a new herd, he goes off in search of water with a lone female, the crusty Groove. Initially eager to rid herself of this youngster, she gradually warms to him in the course of their adventures, leading to a climax in which Whispers rediscovers his ability to trumpet in time to become a hero.</p>
        <p>The film uses the voices of Angela Bassett as Groove, Anne Archer as Gentle Heart and Debi Derryberry as Whispers. According to the publicity, Whispers and Groove were portrayed by trained elephants.</p>
        <p>In ''Whispers: An Elephant's Tale,'' brilliant film of nature has been warped into something jarringly unnatural.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
