<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surfing the Music Scene With Web Masters of Rock</title>
    <meta content="13ROSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13ROSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Radiohead (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DB143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surfing the Music Scene With Web Masters of Rock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews performance by English band Radiohead; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sweeping comparisons can be useful in assessing pop obscured by media hoopla. When the noise surrounding a band is big, think big. To wit: Radiohead is the rock equivalent of the Internet.</p>
        <p>This English band, which played on Wednesday at Roseland Ballroom, invites such analogies with ''Kid A'' (Capitol), its fourth release. Practically crushed by the embrace of critics and making a surprise No. 1 chart debut, ''Kid A'' is as musically vast and hard to navigate as mainstream pop gets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sweeping comparisons can be useful in assessing pop obscured by media hoopla. When the noise surrounding a band is big, think big. To wit: Radiohead is the rock equivalent of the Internet.</p>
        <p>This English band, which played on Wednesday at Roseland Ballroom, invites such analogies with ''Kid A'' (Capitol), its fourth release. Practically crushed by the embrace of critics and making a surprise No. 1 chart debut, ''Kid A'' is as musically vast and hard to navigate as mainstream pop gets.</p>
        <p>Listeners will need a good search engine to surf this record. It begins with two tracks reminiscent of Brian Eno's elusive ambient records of the mid-1970's, then veers into free jazz and many corners of electronica, yielding only one obvious single, ''Optimistic,'' in 10 tracks.</p>
        <p>The lyrics intoned by the singer Thom Yorke are like glimpses of the artist Jenny Holzer's electronic billboards. The phrases drift by, accidentally poignant: ''I'm lost at sea''; ''You can try the best you can''; ''This isn't happening.'' They embed themselves in protoplasmic melodies loosely shaped by the guitarist, keyboardist and sound collagist Jonny Greenwood. The life of these songs depends on the listener's willingness to link with them.</p>
        <p>Yet like most deliberately important art, ''Kid A'' centers on time-tested major themes of self-estrangement and existentialist enlightenment. At Roseland, in a set that dipped into the band's catalog and into new material, Radiohead made them easier to decode. Emerging to a hero's welcome, with an eight-piece horn section in tow, the five-member band bounded into ''The National Anthem,'' one of the new album's most raucous cuts. Mr. Yorke twitched and sweated like an old-school frontman as the bass playing of Colin Greenwood, Jonny Greenwood's brother, steered the band into a harder-than-recorded version of the song. It was an announcement: this may not be rock as you know it, friends, but give in to it as if it were.</p>
        <p>The horns departed, and Mr. Yorke stepped behind a keyboard for ''Morning Bell,'' setting a pattern that stressed musicianship over star quality. Throughout, Radiohead's members (aside from the drummer, Phil Selway) moved from stringed instruments to keyboards, until finally Jonny Greenwood and the second guitarist, Ed O'Brien, hunched on the floor over synthesizers, guitars abandoned. Versatility was an attraction, as the band involved the crowd in its song-building process.</p>
        <p>Standard rock moves were part of the foundation, especially in hard-hitting older songs like ''The Bends,'' but also in the new songs. This is Radiohead's innovation: to neither break from rock nor serve its paradigms. Like a good Web page, its songs allow listeners to click on a variety of connections.</p>
        <p>Highly accelerated Latin rhythms slid beneath punk riffs; a sweeping pseudo-classical keyboard line meshed with a psychedelic groove. Mr. Yorke's high, tensile voice blended fury with rapture. This was fusion of the first order, not forcing elements together but letting them entangle organically.</p>
        <p>It is not an irony but an accomplishment that this band, fixated on the theme of alienation through technological growth, should ultimately sound so natural. Countless artists address the negative impact of what leaders call progress. Radiohead considers its irresistible beauty and makes music from it. Like cyberspace, the band's art isn't new, but its possibilities seem endless.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
