<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Haze As Ever Purple</title>
    <meta content="13JIMI$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13JIMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hendrix, Jimi (1942-70)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DA143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Haze As Ever Purple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers Critic's Notebook review of musical inheritance of Jimi Hendrix, and concerts marking 30th anniversary of his death from overdose of sleepig pills; self-proclaimed voodoo child who never saw 30 remains object of widespread fascination among musicians and fans; concerts and new CD's noted; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY now everyone should be good and tired of thinking about Jimi Hendrix. He may have been the ultimate icon of countercultural rock, but decades have passed since his death. In the hip-hop era, whole new sound worlds have emerged. The three genres Hendrix helped found -- heavy metal, jazz fusion and funk -- have evolved beyond his contributions. After the millionth time around on classic rock radio, it seems impossible that songs like ''Purple Haze'' could offer anything new.</p>
        <p>Yet Hendrix, the self-proclaimed voodoo child who never saw 30 (not to mention Watergate, glasnost or cable television), remains an object of widespread fascination. He is the most prolific ghost in pop-music history. All Music Guide, an online database, lists 196 nonbootleg releases from Hendrix and his two bands, the Experience and Band of Gypsies, nearly half of which were issued in the last decade. Compare this with the catalog of the two other stars lost at about the same time: Janis Joplin, with 18 releases, and Jim Morrison of the Doors, with 33.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY now everyone should be good and tired of thinking about Jimi Hendrix. He may have been the ultimate icon of countercultural rock, but decades have passed since his death. In the hip-hop era, whole new sound worlds have emerged. The three genres Hendrix helped found -- heavy metal, jazz fusion and funk -- have evolved beyond his contributions. After the millionth time around on classic rock radio, it seems impossible that songs like ''Purple Haze'' could offer anything new.</p>
        <p>Yet Hendrix, the self-proclaimed voodoo child who never saw 30 (not to mention Watergate, glasnost or cable television), remains an object of widespread fascination. He is the most prolific ghost in pop-music history. All Music Guide, an online database, lists 196 nonbootleg releases from Hendrix and his two bands, the Experience and Band of Gypsies, nearly half of which were issued in the last decade. Compare this with the catalog of the two other stars lost at about the same time: Janis Joplin, with 18 releases, and Jim Morrison of the Doors, with 33.</p>
        <p>Given this constant flow of Hendrix material, it is hard to remember that this is a notable year, the 30th since his overdose of sleeping pills. The expected tributes, which include the deluxe box set ''Jimi Hendrix Experience'' (Experience Music/ MCA) and the all-star concert ''A Magic Science: Celebrating Jimi Hendrix'' at the Brooklyn Academy of Music next weekend, happen to coincide with another crest in the Hendrix wave. Anniversaries have nothing to do with his current influence; it is simply another sign of his inexhaustibility as a source.</p>
        <p>Young soul musicians are making much of Hendrix's influence on black music, with D'Angelo, who recorded his latest album, ''Voodoo'' (Virgin), at Hendrix's studio, Electric Ladyland in New York, leading the way. Such devotion is also surfacing in hip-hop, with the forward-thinking duo Outkast ending its latest single, ''B.O.B.,'' with a screaming, Hendrix-esque solo. Even post-punks who scorned Hendrix's style may be reaching into his catalog for reference points as Jonny Greenwood of Radiohead makes guitar heroism chic again.</p>
        <p>The musicians playing at the academy are, for the most part, more seasoned Hendrix devotees. The guitarist Vernon Reid has long been acknowledged as a major Hendrix inheritor, continuing to mine the link between rock and jazz. He will be the center of a group that includes three generations of musicians, from the seven-piece Gil Evans Orchestra, which was to play with Hendrix at Carnegie Hall at the time of his death, to the hip-hop turntablist DJ Logic.</p>
        <p>Each participant is a genre-bender. The tabla player Badal Roy is known for his jazz work with Miles Davis. The organ-driven trio Medeski, Martin and Wood and the guitarist Hiram Bullock blend jazz, funk and rock. Chris Whitley is a bluesman with a post-punk edge. The singers Sandra St. Victor and Marc Anthony Thompson stretch the definition of soul.</p>
        <p>Kissing the Sky</p>
        <p>The fact that Hendrix is an inspiration to all of these players suggests the reason for his inexhaustible appeal. It's not just that he was eclectic or, to invoke a cliche, beyond category. Hendrix never reached the point of categorization; instead, he made music evoking the moment before decisions must be made. In an either-or world, he was both-and. He would not say no to an option.</p>
        <p>Hendrix was an ironic idealist whose hallucinogen-fueled visions were tempered by a constant awareness of the racism he endured. He was a tragic humorist equally intrigued by the death drive and the pull of eroticism, and able to chuckle in the face of horror.</p>
        <p>He was a sexy introvert, waving his mojo in songs like ''Let Me Stand Next to Your Fire'' and bending gently into ballads like ''Little Wing.'' He was a black power integrationist who reclaimed rock music as an African-American tradition. He was a hook-happy art rocker whose experimentalism never caused him to abandon great sing-along riffs. He was a singing guitarist when most rockers were one or the other, and he used his extraordinary instrumental gifts to extend the range of a very human voice.</p>
        <p>Most of all, Jimi Hendrix was a seasoned innocent. In his short life he learned more about rock 'n' roll and the story that feeds it, the struggle over American identity, than most of his peers. But in the process of creation, he always made what he called that ''slight return'' to a state where such awareness would not shut him down.</p>
        <p>''A musician, if he is a messenger, is like a child who hasn't been handled too many times by man, hasn't had too many fingerprints across his brain,'' Hendrix told an interviewer in 1969. ''That's why music is so much heavier than anything you ever felt.'' And that attitude, resonant throughout his music, is the challenge that makes it impossible to put Hendrix to rest.</p>
        <p>During a recent rehearsal at SIR Studios in Midtown Manhattan, the ''Magic Science'' ensemble wrestled with the intimidating task of making Hendrix interpretation fresh. Leadership bounced around. Miles Evans, son of the orchestra's founder and now its leader, steered the horns while playing trumpet himself. John Medeski advised on dynamics and Mr. Reid guided the general tone. Danny Kapilian, the event's producer, spoke about how the light show provided by the visual artist Glen McKay, incorporating 1,600 hand-painted slides, would maximize the music's heady effect.</p>
        <p>Each musician took the rehearsal down a slightly different path. Possibility shaped the music's design. As Ms. St. Victor sang a blues based on ''Are You Experienced?,'' tipped toward greasy funk by the bassist Chris Wood, Mr. Roy gradually took center stage on tablas, incorporating Indian-style vocals that carried the lead singer into an ear-opening duet. Mr. Reid, returning after a fresh-air break, broke out laughing at this unexpected alchemy.</p>
        <p>Surprising Moments</p>
        <p>Such surprising moments are what Hendrix craved. They provide the highlights on the ''Jimi Hendrix Experience'' box, which fans will treasure as an excellent compendium of the master's official studio output. Intriguing, different versions show the careful, but always playful, construction of hits like ''Third Stone From the Sun'' and ''Hey Joe,'' while live tracks clarify the difference between Hendrix's interplay with his rock-oriented English bandmates in the Experience, Mitch Mitchell and Noel Redding, and his soul-trained collaborators in Band of Gypsies, Billy Cox and Buddy Miles.</p>
        <p>With outstanding remixing by the longtime Hendrix engineer Eddie Kramer and detailed liner notes from the critic Dave Marsh and the Hendrix biographer John McDermott, ''The Jimi Hendrix Experience'' is a boon for the converted. It's also fun for nonbelievers, who will discover the warmth and humor of Jimi the man along with the genius of Jimi the rock star.</p>
        <p>This is the apex, so far, of what should be a continuing series of high-quality sets organized by Hendrix's family and friends.</p>
        <p>Beyond the archives, and beyond next weekend at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, Hendrix's presence floats on. After its academy debut, ''A Magic Science'' travels to Seattle, where it will be sponsored by the Experience Music Project, the rock 'n' roll museum that opened this year under the patronage of the ultimate Hendrix fan, the billionaire entrepreneur Paul Allen. The concert opens the first of the museum's new ''Innovators'' series of weeklong celebrations of legendary rock artists; Hendrix inspired the series and it opens on Nov. 26, the day before what would have been his 58th birthday.  Meanwhile, in Cleveland, the Rock 'n' Roll Hall of Fame is featuring an exhibition of artwork and other Hendrix artifacts.</p>
        <p>Fresh Nuances</p>
        <p>Back in Brooklyn, the jazz singer Nora York will bring her intelligently cheeky versions of Hendrix music to the BAM Cafe on Oct. 26. (She promises to perform ''Foxy Lady'' in the first person, countering the effects of the Playboy-fantasy version of that song so memorable in the movie ''Wayne's World.'')</p>
        <p>Ms. York approaches Hendrix as a songwriter, finding fresh nuances in his work by clearing away the brilliant debris of his guitar playing. She is one in a long line of Hendrix interpreters; another batch is represented on ''Blue Haze'' (Ruf Records), a new tribute album that emphasizes his blues roots, with performances from, among others, Taj Mahal, Eric Burdon, Alvin Youngblood Hart, Michele Shocked, Mr. Reid and Buddy Miles, the drummer for Band of Gypsies.</p>
        <p>Hendrix would probably have been pleased to see his ideas teased out on such projects. ''He was very scared of being boring,'' Robert Wyatt, the English singer and songwriter whose band, the Soft Machine, toured with the Experience in 1968, recently told a writer for the English magazine Uncut. Although critics have made much of Hendrix's other anxieties -- his racial ambiguity, sexual machismo, fear of and longing for death -- this creative tension is the real key to his music.</p>
        <p>A back-to-back listen of rough mixes and finished cuts reveals something fascinating: Hendrix songs never sound finished. That does not mean they are rough; his technical prowess was unmatched. But whether it's the thuddingly familiar ''Manic Depression'' or the obtuse ''1983 . . . (A Merman I Should Turn to Be),'' his psychedelic blues emphasize process over results, alternative realities over firm conclusions.</p>
        <p>The mirrorlike veneer of his music was inspired by mind-expanding drugs, a strong interest in science fiction and his Bob Dylan fixation. But that sense of productive inconclusiveness permeates deeper, into Hendrix's very style of playing and singing, and in the frenetic arrangements he created, whether in the rock-oriented Experience or his more overtly jazz-based later work.</p>
        <p>''He was not a hyphenated man; he did not play hyphenated music,'' wrote Charles Shaar Murray, whose biography ''Crosstown Traffic: Jimi Hendrix and the Rock 'n' Roll Revolution'' (St. Martin's Press, 1989) remains the definitive book on the icon.</p>
        <p>Hendrix's peers, from Eric Clapton to Mick Jagger, were firmly entrenched by the time they reached their prime; their challenge was finding ways to escape their solidifying artistic dispositions. Although Hendrix sometimes felt trapped by his wild persona, as a musician he remained willfully unsettled. That is why listeners never exhaust his work. It may have been frozen in time by his death, but its core still radiates with questions.</p>
        <p>Voodoo Child</p>
        <p>The Jimi Hendrix events and CD's in the critic's notebook article:</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>''A MAGIC SCIENCE: CELEBRATING JIMI HENDRIX,'' Brooklyn Academy of Music, Howard Gilman Opera House, 30 Lafayette Street, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100. Next Friday at 8 p.m. and Oct. 21 at 7:30 p.m; tickets are $17, $30, and $40. In downtown Seattle on Nov. 26 at 7:30 p.m. at Benaroya Hall, 200 University Street, at Fourth Avenue; (206) 770-2700.</p>
        <p>POST-''MAGIC SCIENCE'' DANCE PARTY, with Free Radicals, BAM Cafe, 30 Lafayette Street, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100. Oct. 21 at 9 p.m.; admission is free, with a $10 food and drink minimum.</p>
        <p>NORA YORK INTERPRETS JIMI HENDRIX, BAM Cafe, 30 Lafayette Street at Ashland, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100. Oct. 26, at 9 p.m.; admission is free, with a $10 food and drink minimum.</p>
        <p>''JIMI HENDRIX,'' an exhibition of artifacts and artwork, on view indefinitely at the Rock 'n' Roll Hall of Fame, and Museum, 1 Key Plaza, Cleveland; (888) 764-7625 or www.rockhall.com.</p>
        <p>New Releases</p>
        <p>''JIMI HENDRIX EXPERIENCE,'' four-CD box set (Experience Music/MCA), $69.97.</p>
        <p>''BLUE HAZE: SONGS OF JIMI HENDRIX'' (Ruf Records). $15.98.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
