<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behrens to Test Lemon Drop Kid in Gold Cup</title>
    <meta content="13RACI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/sports/13RACI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jockey Club Gold Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Park Race Track</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DF153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behrens to Test Lemon Drop Kid in Gold Cup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming Jockey Club Gold Cup at Belmont Race Track; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''He's developed into a man,'' Scotty Schulhofer was saying yesterday at Belmont Park, saluting his horse, Lemon Drop Kid. ''He belongs in the big leagues.''</p>
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid, the 4-year-old star who has won four straight stakes this year, is considered the leading candidate for Horse of the Year, especially now that Fusaichi Pegasus has been withdrawn from tomorrow's $1 million Jockey Club Gold Cup with a slight cut on his left front hoof. And, although the two colts were still expected to meet in a showdown in the $4 million Breeders' Cup Classic at Churchill Downs on Nov. 4, Schulhofer left no doubt about his choice for the title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''He's developed into a man,'' Scotty Schulhofer was saying yesterday at Belmont Park, saluting his horse, Lemon Drop Kid. ''He belongs in the big leagues.''</p>
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid, the 4-year-old star who has won four straight stakes this year, is considered the leading candidate for Horse of the Year, especially now that Fusaichi Pegasus has been withdrawn from tomorrow's $1 million Jockey Club Gold Cup with a slight cut on his left front hoof. And, although the two colts were still expected to meet in a showdown in the $4 million Breeders' Cup Classic at Churchill Downs on Nov. 4, Schulhofer left no doubt about his choice for the title.</p>
        <p>''In my mind,'' he said, ''Lemon Drop Kid is the Horse of the Year, and if he doesn't get it, there is no justice.''</p>
        <p>But horse racing is not famous for dispensing justice, as the early odds showed when horses were entered in the five stakes tomorrow that constitute Breeders' Cup Preview Day at Belmont.</p>
        <p>In the Gold Cup, the main event, seven horses were entered and Lemon Drop Kid drew the No. 5 post position and was made the 4-5 early favorite. His old rival, the 6-year-old Behrens, who lost the Woodward to him by a head last month and also ran second in the Suburban and the Dubai World Cup, drew the No. 4 post and was listed next at 2-1.</p>
        <p>''I still believe in him, even if some people have written him off,'' James Bond, Behrens's trainer, said from his base in Saratoga. ''He is just a hard-luck type of horse. He has barely lost three Grade I races. Those could have made him a 'super horse.' ''</p>
        <p>But the Kid and Behrens both had big threats on the inside, where Albert the Great drew the rail at 8-1, and the outside, where Skimming drew the No. 7 post at 6-1. Albert the Great, the only 3-year-old to enter the Gold Cup, ran second to Unshaded in the Travers in August and third behind Fusaichi Pegasus and El Corredor in the Jerome in September. Skimming won the Pacific Classic at Del Mar in August and ran fourth in the Woodward in September.</p>
        <p>The field was rounded out by the French star Agol Lack; by Gander, third in the Woodward, and by Vision and Verse, who lost the Belmont to Lemon Drop Kid last year by a head.</p>
        <p>The $750,000 Beldame for fillies and mares, at a mile and an eighth, could settle a title between last year's champion, Beautiful Pleasure, and this year's challenger, Riboletta. Bred in Brazil, Riboletta won her last five races, including the Ruffian at Belmont.</p>
        <p>Riboletta drew post No. 1 on the rail and was made the 4-5 favorite by the Belmont oddsmaker. Beautiful Pleasure drew the outside post, No. 6, and was a close second choice at even money.</p>
        <p>The rest of the five stakes will be completed by twin races for 2-year-olds -- the Champagne for colts and the Frizette for fillies -- and the Forest Hills sprint. In the Champagne, City Zip who swept all three stakes for juveniles at Saratoga and is trained by Linda Rice, goes against Scorpion, trained by D. Wayne Lukas.</p>
        <p>In the Frizette, the favorite will be Raging Fever. In the Forest Hills, at six furlongs, Inda's Forest Camp is challenged by Shadow Caster, who won the Forego at Saratoga at memorable odds of 50-1.</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>BARRY K. SCHWARTZ, the incoming chairman of the New York Racing Association, said yesterday that he believed the six-week summer season at Saratoga was long enough and should not be extended. Schwartz was appointed chairman on Wednesday after KENNY NOE had resigned. The two appeared at a news conference at Belmont Park, and Schwartz praised Noe for reforms he had undertaken.</p>
        <p>Schwartz, a prominent horse owner and breeder, also said he would not favor prolonging the Saratoga meeting to eight weeks, a step long rumored to be planned for the year 2002.</p>
        <p>''Six weeks is long enough,'' said Schwartz, who is also chairman and chief executive officer of Calvin Klein Inc. ''By the end of the season, everybody is tired and has had enough.''</p>
        <p>Noe repeated that he resigned for health and family reasons and a desire to return to his home in Florida.</p>
        <p>''There is no truth to the suggestion,'' he said, ''that I resigned because of any investigations at the track. Period.''</p>
        <p>The New York State attorney general is investigating an alleged money laundering scheme involving parimutuel clerks at New York tracks, but investigators said Noe was not under scrutiny.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
