<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Evil Is Lurking, Having a Devil of a Time</title>
    <meta content="13SOUL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13SOUL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryder, Winona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaminski, Janusz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lost Souls (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EEDC143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Evil Is Lurking, Having a Devil of a Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews 1998 movie Lost Souls, directed by Janusz Kaminski and starring Winona Ryder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most movies aren't like wines; they don't improve by sitting on the shelf. So the news that the new horror-suspense film ''Lost Souls'' was made in 1998 and is just being released makes the picture less of a  Pahlmeyer and more of a Thunderbird. ''Lost Souls'' almost looks as if it were sitting in the sun for the last couple of years, bleached in tone.</p>
        <p>Although the movie predicts the rise of Satan, there are no deep reds in the color scheme, which is the only subtle thing about the film. It has the unusual effect of making Winona Ryder look even paler than normal; she has gone from her normal Limoges porcelain skin to looking like the star of a video by the slash metal band Tool. Except for the fiery will that flashes in her eyes, she doesn't look strong enough to plant her feet and do battle with the forces of evil in her role as Maya, a former victim of demonic possession who is now part of a team of Catholic lay people and priests -- the X-Fathers, led by Father Lareaux (John Hurt) -- devoted to exorcising demons from their host bodies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most movies aren't like wines; they don't improve by sitting on the shelf. So the news that the new horror-suspense film ''Lost Souls'' was made in 1998 and is just being released makes the picture less of a  Pahlmeyer and more of a Thunderbird. ''Lost Souls'' almost looks as if it were sitting in the sun for the last couple of years, bleached in tone.</p>
        <p>Although the movie predicts the rise of Satan, there are no deep reds in the color scheme, which is the only subtle thing about the film. It has the unusual effect of making Winona Ryder look even paler than normal; she has gone from her normal Limoges porcelain skin to looking like the star of a video by the slash metal band Tool. Except for the fiery will that flashes in her eyes, she doesn't look strong enough to plant her feet and do battle with the forces of evil in her role as Maya, a former victim of demonic possession who is now part of a team of Catholic lay people and priests -- the X-Fathers, led by Father Lareaux (John Hurt) -- devoted to exorcising demons from their host bodies.</p>
        <p>Church officials won't sanction Maya's studies and beliefs, probably because they have seen much better movies on the subject, like ''Rosemary's Baby,'' ''The Exorcist'' or ''The Omen,'' among the thousands of other movies whose footprints this film does a very sloppy job of treading over. Unlike those pictures, ''Lost Souls'' has long patches of tedium, occasionally interrupted by a loud noise or an absurd spectacle like a cocktail party that ends with an assailant's neck being broken -- proof positive that New York literary gatherings are dangerous in ways that even Truman Capote never dreamed of.</p>
        <p>The barely relieved boredom is, apparently, an attempt to contradict David Byrne's contention that only ''Heaven is a place where nothing really happens.''</p>
        <p>Maya has a suspicion that the smug best-selling crime author Peter Kelson (Ben Chaplin) may be the manifestation of Evil as spelled out in the quotation that starts the film:  ''A man born of incest will become Satan and the world as we now know it will exist no more.'' How can you not be amused by the idea that a man who exploits serial killers in his books is the Devil? Especially one given to using phrases like ''malignant narcissism'' to describe the murderers. .</p>
        <p>Maya determines that a solution to his transformation into the Devil  must be found before Kelson's 33rd birthday, or Evil will be the order of the day.</p>
        <p>Too late to seize on any New Year dread -- though at one point, Philip Baker Hall, as a faux priest, gets to say, ''They had their 2,000 years; now it's our turn'' -- the picture settles for a muted hysteria and cockroaches flailing about on their backs.</p>
        <p>This is stuff from page 19 of the Evil 101 handbook and other ''approach of the end of the world'' spectaculars from New Line Cinema, like ''In the Mouth of Madness.'' As soon as Kelson says, ''I don't believe there's such a thing as Evil with a capital E,'' those poor little roaches trying to right themselves on the shiny hardwood floors start rolling their little eyes or antennae or whatever it is they have to roll. Any neighborhood where ''Lost Souls'' is playing is bound to be scarier than the movie.</p>
        <p>What is truly frightening is the waste of talent gathered for this film. Besides Ms. Ryder and Mr. Chaplin, there is the talented Janusz Kaminski, the cinematographer whose work includes ''Saving Private Ryan'' and ''Schindler's List,'' here making his directorial debut. Perhaps he wanted to try a genre piece for his initial effort. There are some particularly fine visual details; it's the central story that's lacking.</p>
        <p>After what is supposed to be a harrowing moment, Kelson says, ''I was surprised but I was never frightened.'' That about sums up ''Lost Souls.''</p>
        <p>''Lost Souls'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes violence, adult language and suggestions of the rise of Satan not even as scary as a Marilyn Manson CD cover.</p>
        <p>LOST SOULS  Directed by Janusz Kaminski; written by Pierce Gardner, based on a story by Mr. Gardner and Betsy Stahl; director of photography, Mauro Fiore; edited by Anne Goursaud and Andrew Mondshein; music by Jan A. P. Kaczmarek; production designer, Garreth Stover; produced by Nina R. Sadowsky and Meg Ryan; released by New Line Cinema. Running time: 102 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Winona Ryder (Maya Larkin), Ben Chaplin (Peter Kelson), Philip Baker Hall (Father James), Elias Koteas (John Townsend), Sarah Wynter (Claire Van Owen), John Beasley (Mike Smythe) and John Hurt (Father Lareaux).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
