<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Marriages Go Happily Bad</title>
    <meta content="13BROA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/arts/13BROA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON STAGE AND OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Circle in the Square Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibsen, Henrik (1828-1906)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strindberg, August (1849-1912)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baitz, Jon Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ivey, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Danner, Blythe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sondheim, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hedda Gabler (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dance of Death (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Follies (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rocky Horror Show, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Thou Shalt Not (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Stephen Sondheim</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Richard Greenberg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Henrik Ibsen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DB143FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Marriages Go Happily Bad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; two new adaptations of Ibsen and Strindberg classics are wheeling into sight: Jon Robin Baitz's adaptation of Hedda Gabler and Richard Greenberg's version of Dance of Death; revival of Stephen Sondheim's Follies to star Blythe Danner, Judith Ivey and several famous Broadway veterans; Circle in the Square revives Rocky Horror Show; photo; musical Thou Shalt Not will have private showing at Lincoln Center (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two new adaptations of Ibsen and Strindberg classics -- both awash in marital woe and both adapted by bright American talents -- are wheeling into sight for possible spring productions.</p>
        <p>The first is Jon Robin Baitz's adaptation of ''Hedda Gabler,'' Ibsen's depiction of a bored and willful wife, which had its debut in Los Angeles in 1999 and had successful runs over the summer at the Williamstown Theater Festival in Massachusetts and the Bay Street Theater in Sag Harbor on Long Island. Now plans are afoot to stage Mr. Baitz's adaptation on Broadway in time for the Tony deadline in May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two new adaptations of Ibsen and Strindberg classics -- both awash in marital woe and both adapted by bright American talents -- are wheeling into sight for possible spring productions.</p>
        <p>The first is Jon Robin Baitz's adaptation of ''Hedda Gabler,'' Ibsen's depiction of a bored and willful wife, which had its debut in Los Angeles in 1999 and had successful runs over the summer at the Williamstown Theater Festival in Massachusetts and the Bay Street Theater in Sag Harbor on Long Island. Now plans are afoot to stage Mr. Baitz's adaptation on Broadway in time for the Tony deadline in May.</p>
        <p>The producers, led by Randall L. Wreghitt, met on Wednesday to determine a budget and other details. Mr. Wreghitt confirmed that plans call for the production to transfer here from Boston, where it will play at the Huntington Theater Company in December and January. The production will be directed by Nicholas Martin, the director in Williamstown and the new artistic director of the Huntington, and it will star Kate Burton. A Shubert house has been promised, Mr. Wreghitt said.</p>
        <p>The Shuberts are also involved in another classic. It is Strindberg's ''Dance of Death,'' a vitriolic portrait of a married couple celebrating their long companionship by tearing each other apart. The writer in this case is another playwright who has shown a knack for the neurotic: Richard Greenberg, author of ''Eastern Standard'' and ''Three Days of Rain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg has been very busy of late, with the premieres of two new plays (''The Dazzle'' upstate and ''Everett Beekin'' on the West Coast) in the last three months. Now, he has been commissioned to write an adaptation of ''Dance'' for a possible late spring or early summer opening at a Shubert theater. Few details are available, but Shubert officials confirmed that the British director Sean Mathias has been talked of as a possible director. Also mentioned is an even more intriguing British import: Sir Ian McKellen, who has expressed interest in returning to Broadway.</p>
        <p>The Cast for 'Follies'</p>
        <p>''Follies'' has its Phyllis. And its Ben and Sally and Buddy, too.</p>
        <p>After weeks of rumors and speculation, producers of the revival of Stephen Sondheim's sentimental 1971 masterpiece, ''Follies,'' will announce its cast today, and it will include Blythe Danner in the role of the glamourous ex-chorus girl Phyllis Stone.</p>
        <p>Other principals, some of whom were cast and hinted at months ago, will be Judith Ivey as Sally Plummer, Phyllis's more pedestrian friend; Gregory Harrison as Phyllis's unhappy hubby, Ben; and Treat Williams as Sally's cheating husband, Buddy.</p>
        <p>The Broadway cast will also include veteran talents like Marge Champion, Polly Bergen, Larry Keith, Betty Garrett, Donald Saddler, Carol Woods and Joan Roberts, whose Broadway debut came in 1943 in the original cast of ''Oklahoma!''</p>
        <p>Matthew Warchus, who will direct the show, starting at the Belasco on April 5, was 5 years old when ''Follies'' was first produced. He said: ''It's quite a privilege to cast a show like this because you get to meet such an array of theatrical personalities. There's a real sense of life mirroring art.''</p>
        <p>Wrapping 'Rocky'</p>
        <p>A little bit uptown, the Circle in the Square Theater is getting wrapped up in its new tenant. Literally.</p>
        <p>For the last couple of weeks, the theater's walls have been swathed in red fabric, the backdrop for an inventive set for the revival of ''The Rocky Horror Show,'' which begins performances next Friday. In fact, the audience will encounter the red fabric -- suggestive of the musical's main setting, the Frankenfurter castle -- upon walking into the lobby. They will also probably encounter a few mannequins poking out here and there as well as live actors popping up -- and down -- from all sorts of unexpected places.</p>
        <p>The set is the brainchild of the director Christopher Ashley and the architect David Rockwell, whose designs include the restaurant Nobu and the W Hotel on Lexington Avenue. But this is his first foray onto Broadway.</p>
        <p>''My first passion was theater,'' Mr. Rockwell said. ''I mean, I remember seeing 'Fiddler on the Roof' in 1964, standing room only.''</p>
        <p>Many of the innovations in the design were by necessity. The Circle's thrust stage is unusual and has no fly space above. As a result, props have to serve two functions to save space. Keep an eye out for the piece of lab equipment, for example, that transforms into a motorcycle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rockwell said such inventions were just part of the fun. ''I view it as part Rube Goldberg device,'' he said, ''and partly like a game of 'Mousetrap.' ''</p>
        <p>Along the Way</p>
        <p>*A workshop to note: ''Thou Shall Not,'' a musical collaboration between the director and choreographer Susan Stroman and Harry Connick Jr., has been rehearsing in the basement of Lincoln Center for several weeks and will have a presentation next week. Unfortunately for fans, that showing will be private, though Lincoln Center officials would certainly love to let the public in sometime soon.</p>
        <p>*Todo Con Nada, a longtime bastion of downtown theater, is once again facing eviction, this time because of more than $20,000 in back rent. To raise money, Nada supporters are staging a one-night performance of the Capra classic, ''It's a Wonderful Life'' at the theater (167 Ludlow Street on the Lower East Side) on Monday at 8 P.M. The stage version will feature many Nada alumni, including Kate Hampton from ''The Best Man'' on Broadway. Short of raising the rent, said Aaron Beall, the company's founder, the doors will be locked on Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>*''End of the World Party,'' a new play by Chuck Ranberg, a five-time Emmy winner for his witty banter on ''Frasier'' on television, will begin performances Oct. 25 at the 47th Street Theatre.</p>
        <p>*A piping hot ticket: ''A 12 Lb. Discourse,'' perhaps the only show in history whose climax involves a 12-pound pizza. This slice of absurdist comedy, created by Pete Simpson, a member of the Blue Man Group, and Matt Schneck, plays tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 P.M. at SoHo Rep, 46 Walker Street in TriBeCa.</p>
        <p>ON STAGE AND OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
