<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Edmonds Shoulders Blame For Loss</title>
    <meta content="13CARD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/sports/13CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLAYOFFS 2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edmonds, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D6153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Edmonds Shoulders Blame For Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Louis Cardinals center fielder Jim Edmonds says he let team down in New York Mets 6-5 victory in second game of National League Championship Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony La Russa played manager tonight. He began with making a 50 percent turnover of his roster to combat the Cardinals' offensive woes. He continued by pulling pitcher Rick Ankiel after the rookie allowed two runs in a disastrous first inning.</p>
        <p>On and on the moves went. With perhaps the questionable move of wasting Mark McGwire's bat in the eighth inning, almost all of the moves La Russa made tonight worked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony La Russa played manager tonight. He began with making a 50 percent turnover of his roster to combat the Cardinals' offensive woes. He continued by pulling pitcher Rick Ankiel after the rookie allowed two runs in a disastrous first inning.</p>
        <p>On and on the moves went. With perhaps the questionable move of wasting Mark McGwire's bat in the eighth inning, almost all of the moves La Russa made tonight worked.</p>
        <p>But La Russa could not control Mike Timlin's 1-2 pitch that Jay Payton slapped into center field in the ninth inning, allowing Joe McEwing to score the go-ahead run for the Mets in their 6-5 victory. Nor could La Russa have foreseen the ball bouncing over Jim Edmonds in center field, allowing Payton to slide into third base and preventing Edmonds from making a throw to the plate.</p>
        <p>Entering the ninth inning, the Cardinals seemed to have an answer for the everything the Mets did. But as Edmonds stood by his locker, blaming himself for letting the team down both in the field and at the plate, one wondered if the Cardinals would still be trailing the National League Championship Series two games to none had Edmonds performed like the front-runner for most valuable player that he is.</p>
        <p>Instead, Edmonds spoke softly in the quiet Cardinals clubhouse saying: ''I didn't do much today. I came up in situations where if I could put the ball in play I could drive a run in. I didn't, and I made a bad play at the end so sitting down at my locker it feels like I pretty much lost the game all by myself.''</p>
        <p>As the Cardinal players showered and dressed, large red boxes were wheeled out and onto trucks. They were destined for Shea Stadium, where the N.L.C.S. continues Saturday afternoon. If Edmonds continues playing as he has for two games, the rabid Cardinal fans have seen their last game at Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Outside, a public fountain in a plaza facing the Gateway Arch bleeds red, part of pep rallies fans have held the last two days.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals will need a lot more than fan support if Edmonds continues to struggle. Tonight, he was 0 for 4 with two strikeouts. In the field, he made two questionable plays.</p>
        <p>The first came in the eighth inning. The Cardinals had tied it, 3-3, three innings earlier and the Mets' rookie Timo Perez hit a two-out single. Edgardo Alfonzo then sliced a high fastball from the reliever Matt Morris into right-center field. Edmonds, playing deep to prevent a double, was slow retrieving the ball and the relay throw home was late and up the line. Alfonzo went to second on the throw and later scored on Todd Zeile's single for a 5-3 Mets lead.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals tied it when John Franco's wild pitch scored one run and Turk Wendell allowed a two-out double to J. D. Drew to make it 5-5. La Russa said he yelled at Drew to stop at first base because he had McGwire ready to pinch-hit next.</p>
        <p>When Drew advanced to second, La Russa let McGwire bat and the Mets walked him, as expected, taking the bat away from the Cardinals' best hitter. Craig Paquette struck out to end the Cardinals' last threat.</p>
        <p>Robin Ventura led off the ninth with a grounder to first base, where it bounced off Will Clark's foot for an error. Clark expected the ball to come up and it did not. After a sacrifice, Payton slapped a single to center where Edmonds waited to field the ball on one hop. But the ball bounced off his glove and over his head, preventing him from making any play at home. McEwing, pinch-running for Ventura, scored the run.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think it was going to travel as far,'' Edmonds said. ''I probably should have caught it. I tried to take it nice and easy and field it on one hop and throw the guy out. Looking back, maybe I should have taken a chance and I probably would have caught it.''</p>
        <p>Edmonds appeared slow in the outfield, which he attributed to ''minor difficulties'' with his leg.</p>
        <p>Gone from tonight's starting lineup were right fielder Eric Davis, catcher Carlos Hernandez, left fielder Drew and third baseman Placido Polanco. In their place were Shawon Dunston, Eli Marrero, Ray Lankford and Fernandez Tatis, who combined to go 3 for 12 with two runs batted in.</p>
        <p>But La Russa had no way of knowing Ankiel would implode again in the first inning. His first pitch to Perez hit the backstop and sent Perez on his back. Four more pitches to the backstop followed.</p>
        <p>La Russa took as much of the heat off Ankiel as he could, although the move appeared to be his biggest attempt at managing.</p>
        <p>''The manager's responsibility is to put guys in the right position,'' La Russa said. ''I blame myself. I don't blame Rick Ankiel. He's too special.''</p>
        <p>PLAYOFFS 2000</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
