<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Michigan Unions Push Hard for Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y13LABO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/politics/13LABO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE LABOR VOTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DF153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Michigan Unions Push Hard for Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>LANSING, Mich., Oct. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In Michigan, long the heart of nation's labor movement, unions are making all-out push to give Vice Pres Al Gore the edge in pivotal state where presidential race is neck and neck; dozens of union members take leaves from their jobs to do full-time, union-paid campaign work for six weeks; Michigan's--and nation's--labor leaders are making major effort to rouse enthusiasm for Gore among union members, many of whom were ambivalent or hostile toward him just few months ago; Gore's often-frosty relations with labor unions stem from his support of trade deals that unions opposed; but labor leaders now say that differences are so stark between Gore and Bush on other matters that they are lining up behind Gore, even beginning to feel enthusiastic toward him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From a purple trailer emblazoned with the Service Employees International Union name, 18 corrections officers at a computerized telephone bank were calling 1,500 union members an hour this week to tell them that Al Gore is a friend of working families.</p>
        <p>In Flint, 50 miles east of here, Jessie Cloman, a city housing inspector, was setting up a ''mentoring'' program in which 190 shop stewards have each been assigned 100 union members who have voted only once in the last six years. The mentors' responsibility: make sure their 100 people vote this November, preferably for Mr. Gore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From a purple trailer emblazoned with the Service Employees International Union name, 18 corrections officers at a computerized telephone bank were calling 1,500 union members an hour this week to tell them that Al Gore is a friend of working families.</p>
        <p>In Flint, 50 miles east of here, Jessie Cloman, a city housing inspector, was setting up a ''mentoring'' program in which 190 shop stewards have each been assigned 100 union members who have voted only once in the last six years. The mentors' responsibility: make sure their 100 people vote this November, preferably for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>And in Detroit today, Don Smith, president of the Teamsters' local once headed by Jimmy Hoffa, chatted up dozens of dock workers and drivers at a Yellow Freight terminal to tell them Vice President Al Gore, not Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, was good for the working man and woman.</p>
        <p>In Michigan, long the heart of the nation's labor movement, unions are making an all-out push to give Mr. Gore the edge in a pivotal state where the presidential race is neck and neck. Dozens of union members have taken leaves from their jobs to do full-time, union-paid campaign work for six weeks. And the state's unions plan to send more than two million pieces of mail in support of Mr. Gore and other Democratic candidates.</p>
        <p>The state's -- and the nation's -- labor leaders are making a major effort to rouse enthusiasm for Mr. Gore among union members, many of whom were ambivalent or hostile toward him just a few months ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has often had frosty relations with labor unions, which resent his support of the China trade deal and the North American Free Trade Agreement. Several unions have also been tempted to support Ralph Nader, the Green Party presidential candidate and a fierce opponent of Nafta and the deal to liberalize trade with China.</p>
        <p>But union leaders said the differences were so stark between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush on tax cuts, privatizing Social Security, raising the minimum wage and other issues that most union members have lined up behind Mr. Gore and even begun feeling enthusiastic toward him.</p>
        <p>To underscore labor's importance in Michigan politics, Mark Gaffney, the new president of the state A.F.L.-C.I.O., is fond of noting that President Clinton would have lost Michigan in 1996 were it not for union members. Most of the state's nonunion voters backed Bob Dole, while Michigan's union members voted for Mr. Clinton more than two to one.</p>
        <p>''The labor movement's strength is the percentage of our more than one million members and retirees who will vote for Gore,'' Mr. Gaffney said. ''That means educating these members and retirees and getting them to the polls.''</p>
        <p>Both candidates consider Michigan's union membership crucial. Mr. Bush, who plans to visit a General Motors plant in Pontiac on Friday, is  making a play for the state's ''Reagan Democrats'' who drifted into the Republican fold in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>But union leaders here say they are confident that this time around, most of these voters will support Mr. Gore, who plans to hold a rally with thousands of union members in Detroit on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Rusty Hills, chairman of the Michigan Republican Party, acknowledged that ''labor's pretty darn powerful in this state.''</p>
        <p>''But there's a fundamental problem with labor leaders trying to push Al Gore over the top,'' Mr. Hills said, ''And that is we have a lot of inroads with working men and women frankly because Al Gore is not good for the auto industry. Remember, he once said that the internal combustion engine is the single greatest threat to mankind.''</p>
        <p>The A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s internal polls show that Michigan union members favor Mr. Gore over Mr. Bush, 60 percent to 23 percent.</p>
        <p>Michigan's 50 labor unions, with about 900,000 members, are seeking to maximize both the number of union members who vote and the percentage who back Mr. Gore. To this end, unions have undertaken their biggest voter registration drive ever, with the U.A.W. boasting that it has registered more than 10,000 new voters in Michigan alone.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a new clause in its contract with the Big Three automakers, the U.A.W. hopes to exercise more electoral clout than ever before. Tens of thousands of auto workers are being given Election Day off as a holiday, enabling them to devote themselves to getting people to the polls.</p>
        <p>Labor has revamped its campaign strategy since 1996. It is spending less on advertisements and more on contacting members individually. This ''worker-to-worker'' strategy  produces results at the voting booth. The A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s polls show that when a union member or shop steward gives another member campaign literature at the workplace, that worker votes for the union-endorsed candidate 76 percent of the time. When there is no such contact, union workers vote for labor's candidate 58 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>''We're putting a whole lot more people power into it than last time,'' said Richard Long, the U.A.W.'s national political director. ''We're giving everything we got.''</p>
        <p>In mounting their pro-Gore offensive, unions have pushed aside a thorny issue, trade. That issue caused the mighty U.A.W. and Teamsters, both livid about the Clinton administration's support of the China trade bill, to delay endorsing Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''On one hand, union members are critical of the administration on the China trade issue,'' said John J. Sweeney, president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. ''But on the other hand, they recognize the contrast between the two candidates is so great. They realize that Gore by far will be much better for working families.''</p>
        <p>For labor leaders, one big worry has dissipated. Several months ago, Mr. Nader reached 8 percent in some state polls, partly because many workers liked his views on trade. This made union leaders worry that Mr. Gore would lose the state, but new polls show that Mr. Nader's support has fallen sharply.</p>
        <p>One problem for Mr. Gore is that some union members believe that President Clinton has done too little for labor. In the lunchroom of the Yellow Freight terminal in Detroit, Tim Brochue, a truck driver who supports Mr. Bush, said, ''These Democrats haven't done anything for the unions. Clinton was a liar, and Gore was right at his side.''</p>
        <p>Across the long lunch table, Doug Ray, a fellow Teamster, disagreed, saying, ''I'm voting for Gore. Bush is mostly for the rich people. The only reason he's running is to help big money and big business.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE LABOR VOTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
