<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Pledges Backing For Police Patrol Program</title>
    <meta content="13POLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/13/nyregion/13POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Operation Condor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Overtime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rashbaum, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DA153FF930A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Pledges Backing For Police Patrol Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rashbaum, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani reiterates his support for Operation Condor; says aggressive police program of overtime for drug sweeps and quality of life patrols will be expanded (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani reiterated his support for Operation Condor yesterday, saying the aggressive program of overtime for drug sweeps and quality of life patrols would not only be continued, but expanded.</p>
        <p>His statement came a day after police officials disclosed that undercover drug purchase operations and quality of life patrols financed through the often criticized $55 million program had been suspended for 10 days to evaluate its effectiveness. Officials had said the program reduced crime and reversed an increase in the murder rate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani reiterated his support for Operation Condor yesterday, saying the aggressive program of overtime for drug sweeps and quality of life patrols would not only be continued, but expanded.</p>
        <p>His statement came a day after police officials disclosed that undercover drug purchase operations and quality of life patrols financed through the often criticized $55 million program had been suspended for 10 days to evaluate its effectiveness. Officials had said the program reduced crime and reversed an increase in the murder rate.</p>
        <p>''There was a cutback in Condor for one week to see what the impact would be and see if there were ways of improving it,'' the mayor said yesterday outside the new Fire Department information center in Rockefeller Center. ''And the result is that crime went up by a percent. So Condor was reinstated, and not only has it been reinstated, it is going to be refunded and probably increased.''</p>
        <p>When he made his remarks, the mayor provided no details of his plans for the expansion of the nine-month-old program, which was started in January to halt a jump in the murder rate, which at the end of 1999 showed a 6 percent increase over the previous year. A spokeswoman for the mayor, Sunny Mindel, did not respond to a request for details.</p>
        <p>Police officials said on Wednesday that they had stopped the drug sweeps and quality of life patrols as part of Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik's assessment of the department's overall anti-narcotics efforts and the use of overtime funds. Officials said Mr. Kerik, who took office in August, wanted to know whether a break in the program would affect the crime rate. In the last fiscal year, Operation Condor  accounted for more than 17 percent of the department's overtime budget.</p>
        <p>Some police officials had said that Commissioner Kerik had questions about the high percentage of low-level arrests made as part of Operation Condor and also was concerned that some narcotics detectives were claiming the overtime despite a lack of productivity.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, Mr. Kerik agreed with the mayor that the program had been effective. ''If you look from January on, we took an 8 percent reduction'' in crime, he said in an interview. ''Did we put a lot of money out there? Yes. But for what the city gets back in crime reduction, it's well worth it.''</p>
        <p>In addition to challenging the program's cost, some senior police officials, judges and prosecutors have privately questioned the wisdom of using millions in overtime funds to make the mostly low-level drug arrests produced by Operation Condor. The program has also been criticized for its aggressive street enforcement, which community leaders say has further strained already frayed relations between the police and residents of poor neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>At a committee hearing on Wednesday, several City Council members, including Phillip Reed, said they had serious questions about whether more funds should be provided for Condor, which police officials said had cost $55.5 million so far and still has about $8 million budgeted through the end of November.</p>
        <p>''You can't come back and say we are still evaluating, and by the way what we did just cost $10 million,'' Mr. Reed told Assistant Chief Charles Kammerdener, who was testifying. ''I don't think we want to give you the PIN number of our ATM.''</p>
        <p>But Commissioner Kerik said yesterday that improvements in the city's quality of life were worth ''10 times'' the cost of Operation Condor. ''The increased tourism -- that doesn't happen by accident, it happens because streets are safer and the environment is safer,'' he said. ''That's as a result of the initiatives that we put in place. If it takes that extra funding in Condor to do that, then we're doing it.''</p>
        <p>The mayor also took issue with an article in The New York Times yesterday saying the Condor patrols had been suspended for 10 days. Mr. Giuliani said the program had only been scaled back for a week. But police officials said yesterday that while they had planned to halt it for only a week, the Columbus Day holiday and other administrative work delayed the resumption of patrols until Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
