<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Come on Down for a Tan and a Sofa</title>
    <meta content="04MIAM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DF1E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Come on Down for a Tan and a Sofa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MASON</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER an exasperating search in New York for a set of dining chairs for a Sunday night dinner party at his Riverside Drive apartment, Augustus Butera was exhilarated when he found the perfect chair at Room -- a sleek new store in Miami.</p>
        <p>''I ordered six, and they were delivered in three days,'' marveled Mr. Butera, a commercial photographer who stumbled onto the Miami design district, a formerly desolate home-furnishings quarter north of downtown, while shooting an advertising campaign nearby. Since 1998, more than 50 stores, many of them beacons of fresh, new design, have opened in that 10-block area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER an exasperating search in New York for a set of dining chairs for a Sunday night dinner party at his Riverside Drive apartment, Augustus Butera was exhilarated when he found the perfect chair at Room -- a sleek new store in Miami.</p>
        <p>''I ordered six, and they were delivered in three days,'' marveled Mr. Butera, a commercial photographer who stumbled onto the Miami design district, a formerly desolate home-furnishings quarter north of downtown, while shooting an advertising campaign nearby. Since 1998, more than 50 stores, many of them beacons of fresh, new design, have opened in that 10-block area.</p>
        <p>When Milly de Cabrol headed to Florida not long ago to unwind from the cruel vexations of life as a New York interior designer, she paid a first-time visit to the newly dynamic district and was startled by what she saw. ''I found a fantastic mix of ethnic and contemporary stuff at incredibly reasonable prices,'' she said. ''And I discovered that it's a lot more fun to shop in Miami. The sun's shining, everyone's helpful and you get to see a lot in a short time because everything's concentrated in one area.''</p>
        <p>At Orson, a store crammed with decorative American and French furniture, Ms. Cabrol found a 1940's sofa for $2,400. It would cost, she said,  $8,000 in New York. In June, she plans to come to Miami again, bringing a client who has a Park Avenue town house. ''We're going to fly down there, fill a container and have it sent,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Until recently, the notion of traveling to Miami for furnishings would have struck many as preposterous. But with the expanding lineup of sophisticated stores and with cheap round-trip air fares, the design district is emerging as a mecca for those in search of high style, welcoming the public with none of the to-the-trade restrictions of many New York showrooms.</p>
        <p>''Spectacular, huh?'' said Craig Robins, the neighborhood's foremost developer, as he bounded up a glass stairway at the new Holly Hunt store, designed by Alison Spear. Mr. Robins is leading an ambitious effort to revitalize the formerly woebegone district, once plagued by muggings and burglaries.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Robins, 37, a Miami Beach native, the opening of Ms. Hunt's showroom is a remarkable coup. Just two years ago, he said, the building was a dark, dilapidated quilting factory. Over the last year, however, news of the 25,000-square-foot Holly Hunt store has spurred confidence in the district. It has become a gleaming showcase for the wares of innovators like Rose Tarlow and Christian Liaigre, current darlings of design. These days, there are 120 or so storefronts in the district, many concentrated along Northeast 40th Street and Northeast Second Avenue -- the principal thoroughfares of an area that is now abuzz with commerce.</p>
        <p>In a controversial move, the Chicago-based Ms. Hunt has abandoned to-the-trade-only rules for her Miami showroom. Like Mr. Robins, she believes that the best way to expand the market for upscale furnishings is to admit the public. Such populist tactics are crucial to Mr. Robins's agenda, which has been driven by past successes. In 1987, he was one of the first to redevelop the shabby, boarded-up Art Deco hotels of South Beach and to reap a handsome profit when the area became a booming resort. Now, in his efforts to reinvigorate the design district, he hopes to capture some of the dynamism of South Beach, a five-minute drive across Biscayne Bay.</p>
        <p>''The goal is to be a place that inspires creativity, where it's fun for the public to come and check out great design and hang out at cool cafes,'' Mr. Robins said. So far, however, the cafes are in the planning stage. And just how eager Miami's thong, sarong and bikini set will be to abandon the beach and come ogle furniture remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>If anyone stands to profit from that eventuality, it is Mr. Robins. Through Dacra, his real estate company, he has since 1994 bought 18 buildings in the area, investing about $25 million, which makes him its biggest landlord. ''To me, it's not about what percentage we own,'' he said, earnestly. ''What's important is that the whole neighborhood be vibrant and successful.''</p>
        <p>RENTS in Mr. Robins's buildings in the district are $20 to $25 a square foot, he said, and 85 percent of the 500,000 square feet he controls is rented. When Dacra began investing in there, 50 percent of the neighborhood was vacant, and rents were about $5 a square foot.</p>
        <p>At the end of the 1980's, when the district took a nose dive, store owners fled to the Design Center of the Americas, an immense, corporate-looking edifice on the outskirts of Fort Lauderdale. The 120-showroom center is, like the Design and Decorating Building in New York, open officially to the trade only. Anyone wishing to view or buy its upscale wares must be accompanied by an interior designer, a restriction that has long exasperated sellers and buyers. An April visit to the fortresslike Design Center of the Americas proved how intractable the to-the-trade-only rule can be.</p>
        <p>This writer, intent on shopping, was met with questions and comments like these: ''Are you a designer?'' ''You can't come in without an appointment.'' ''Are you registered with us?'' ''If you need any help, I have to have a letter from your architect or designer.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, at Sola Topee, in the Miami design district, where Indian daybeds, arches and columns summon up tropical splendor, a jug of fresh iced tea awaits visitors who wander in from Northeast Second Avenue. Espresso, wine and Champagne are also available.</p>
        <p>''If our guests are furnishing their home, we want them to feel at home, so they can experience what it's like to live with our furniture,'' said Bruce Platt, the store's sales director. A former model, Mr. Platt worked at the Polo Ralph Lauren store on Madison Avenue before moving to Miami in 1996.</p>
        <p>That Miami is a resort destination for visitors with large disposable incomes has contributed to the district's rising fortunes. Mr. Platt said that a majority of Sola Topee's out-of-town clients are from New York, Europe and South America, either vacationers or owners of second or third homes. ''Because of where we are, we're tapping a huge audience,'' he said. ''The design district is only five minutes from Miami Beach, the airport and the port of Miami, so it's easy for people to drop by.''</p>
        <p>After 5 p.m., the district is usually deserted. But lately, openings for photography exhibitions in the neighborhood have drawn large crowds after dark. So far, Room, the smallest of the furniture showrooms, is making the biggest splash. It is run by Juan-Carlos Arcila-Duque, an interior designer who furnished a waterfront home in Coconut Grove for the architects Laurinda Spear and Bernardo Fort-Brescia, founders of Arquitectonica. Room recently played host to a packed reception for Fernando Bengoechea, a New York-based interiors photographer.</p>
        <p>Unlike South Beach, with its winning cluster of Art Deco buildings, the design district holds little appeal beyond the convenience of storefront buildings within easy walking distance of one another.</p>
        <p>Determined to transform the district and set the design standard for others to follow, Mr. Robins hired the New York architect Walter Chatham in 1997, starting him with a slender budget of $1 million to spruce up Dacra properties.</p>
        <p>''The first time I saw it, the district was completely shabby and deserted,'' Mr. Chatham said. ''So we began by giving the buildings a fresh coat of paint, putting on awnings, adding new signs and planting trees in order to cultivate a sense of neighborhood.'' Mr. Chatham's efforts with Dacra properties have prompted others to play catch-up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robins persuaded city officials to underwrite a detailed plan for improvements conceived by Andres Duany and Elizabeth Plater-Zyberk, the Miami-based urban designers known for their New Urbanist plans for Seaside, Fla. The design district plan, based on a workshop held three years ago, takes note of Little Haiti, a low-income community to the north, and sets guidelines for everything from street plantings and improved signs to the creation of public spaces and improved access from the expressway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chatham has also worked on the art-filled waterfront home on nearby Sunset Island that Mr. Robins shares with his Cuban-born wife, Ivelin, and their two young children. That house has been furnished with acquisitions from the design district. A family favorite, Mr. Robins said, is a new living room sofa from Dilmos, a fashionable Milan-based company that has opened a showroom on Northeast Second Avenue. The sofa has surprisingly comfortable clear-plastic cushions stuffed with straw. ''I love it,'' he said. ''Because it makes you ask, What's art, and what's furniture?''</p>
        <p>Visitors intrepid enough to venture into the design district before last year were unlikely to come away with anything resembling a chic straw-filled sofa. In 1994, the area was mostly composed of showrooms and quiet antiques stores. Mr. Robins lured his first tenant, Knoll, with an offer of a prime corner and, as he put it, ''an extremely affordable rent,'' roughly half the market rate. Jim Lutz, the national sales manager for KnollStudio, said that the gamble paid off. Since the store relocated from upscale Coral Gables in June 1998, he said, retail sales have doubled. Since Knoll's arrival, other well-known showrooms have followed, including ICF and Waterworks, where gleaming faucets designed by Thomas O'Brien of Aero Studios are on display.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robins also rented the Moore Building, a majestic four-story 1921 structure at 191 Northeast 40th Street, to Leah Kleman, who arrived from Lincoln Road in Miami Beach in 1998 with a following for a mad mix of neo-Classical-style, vaudevillian and Deco antiques. ''For me, the design district is a major gig,'' said Ms. Kleman, who counts Sylvester Stallone, Cher, Elton John and Michael Jackson as clients.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kleman has observed a turnaround in the district in two years. ''First off, it was like a war zone,'' she said. ''But I started renting out my space for events, and everyone came.'' In 1999, she was one of the first in the district to open her store on Saturdays for weekend visitors. ''The South Americans love glamour, and they're compulsive buyers,'' she said. ''They all have pied-a-terres, and they come in on Saturdays in the complete Chanel hardware, his and hers couture.''</p>
        <p>Leading Miami interior designers have also set up offices in the district. ''It's handy, having everything on the doorstep,'' noted Peter Page, a New York transplant, whose projects include elegant redesigns of the Astor and Nash hotels in South Beach. ''Without getting in my car, I can check out samples at Knoll, ICF, Dilmos, Waterworks or Holly Hunt. And I can walk my clients over to check out the marble for their bathroom without having samples shipped in.''</p>
        <p>When Alison Spear, a celebrated interior designer, architect and social force in New York, relocated to her native Miami in 1998, she was reluctant to take an office in the district. She said: ''A friend told me, 'You can't do that, it's too dangerous. You could never bring your kids there.' ''</p>
        <p>But she has seen the neighborhood improve. Much of the turnaround, she noted, is owed to the marketing and advertising by Mr. Robins's company. ''It makes you wonder -- is the hype driving the success, or is the success driving the hype?'' Ms. Spear said. ''Whatever it is, it seems to be working.''</p>
        <p>Turn Left At the Beach</p>
        <p>THE heart of Miami's design district is the intersection of Northeast Second Avenue and Northeast 40th Street. Nearby are the new Holly Hunt showroom, and the 1921 Moore Building. Some stores of particular interest follow:</p>
        <p>DELGRECO -- Handsome furniture for garden, terrace and pool; 4025 Northeast Second Avenue, (305) 573-2200.</p>
        <p>DILMOS -- Milan-based showroom, contemporary furniture; No. 105, 3930 Northeast Second Avenue (Melin Building), (305) 572-1182.</p>
        <p>ETHNIC DESIGN -- Rare furniture and objects, African to Oceanic; 53 Northeast 40th Street (305) 573-8118.</p>
        <p>FORECAST -- One-of-a-kind outdoor benches; 180 Northeast 39th Street (Buena Vista Building), (305) 572-1111.</p>
        <p>HOLLY HUNT -- Designer furnishings in a spectacular setting; 3833 Northeast Second Avenue, (305) 571-2012.</p>
        <p>LEAH'S -- Madcap design supermarket, neo-Classical style to Art Deco; 191 Northeast 40th Street (Moore Building), (305) 573-9700.</p>
        <p>MARC CORBIN -- Midcentury furniture, European lighting, accessories; 3820 Northeast Second Avenue, (305) 573-1705.</p>
        <p>MONICA JAMES -- George Smith sofas, European fabrics and accessories; 140 Northeast 40th Street, (305) 576-6222.</p>
        <p>ORSON -- 19th- and 20th-century American and French decorative furniture; 74 Northeast 40th Street, (305) 573-6805.</p>
        <p>ROOM -- Stylish contemporary furniture from the Room catalogue; 99 Northeast 39th Street, (305) 438-1966.</p>
        <p>SOLA TOPEE -- British colonial antiques from around the world; 3925 Northeast Second Avenue, (305) 576-8510.</p>
        <p>WATERWORKS -- Chic designer bathroom fixtures; 191 Northeast 40th Street (Moore Building), (305) 573-5943.</p>
        <p>WORLD RESOURCES -- Global roundup of furniture and objects, reasonably priced; 56 Northeast 40th Street, (305) 576-8799.</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHER MASON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
