<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Museum Sees Business as Usual In Strike but Halts Fund-Raiser</title>
    <meta content="04MOMA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DA1E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Museum Sees Business as Usual In Strike but Halts Fund-Raiser</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials at the Museum of Modern Art said yesterday that a strike by a union representing 260 workers has failed to turn away visitors, but it has had one noteworthy effect: it caused the museum to postpone a fund-raiser this week starring the singer Sheryl Crow.</p>
        <p>Museum officials said they postponed the fund-raiser, which had been scheduled for Tuesday night, because they did not want Ms. Crow or ticket holders to face the unpleasant situation of having to cross a picket line. The museum, which had sold 450 tickets priced at $500, $750 and $1,000 each, is offering refunds to ticket holders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Officials at the Museum of Modern Art said yesterday that a strike by a union representing 260 workers has failed to turn away visitors, but it has had one noteworthy effect: it caused the museum to postpone a fund-raiser this week starring the singer Sheryl Crow.</p>
        <p>Museum officials said they postponed the fund-raiser, which had been scheduled for Tuesday night, because they did not want Ms. Crow or ticket holders to face the unpleasant situation of having to cross a picket line. The museum, which had sold 450 tickets priced at $500, $750 and $1,000 each, is offering refunds to ticket holders.</p>
        <p>Maida Rosenstein, the president of the union, voiced delight about the postponement, saying it showed that the strike was starting to sting.</p>
        <p>Representatives of the museum and the union said yesterday that they had not held any negotiations since the strike began last Friday, raising the possibility of a long walkout. The workers on strike -- librarians, assistant curators, bookshop employees, visitor assistance workers -- are represented by Local 2110 of the United Automobile Workers.</p>
        <p>Robert Batterman, the museum's chief negotiator, asserted that the strike was not going well for the union. He said that the museum's galleries were being run as usual and that about 90 of the 260 workers in the bargaining unit were crossing the picket line.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Rosenstein of the union said that the museum was in ''lock down'' mode and that only about 30 workers had crossed the picket line.</p>
        <p>She said the main issue was the union's demand for the museum to agree to rehire all employees after the museum completes a four-year, $650 million expansion project, during which much of the museum will be closed and many workers will be laid off.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenstein said the union was eager for a five-year contract, rather than the three-year one proposed by management, because the workers wanted to make sure that any job security clause did not expire until after construction was completed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman denied that job security was the main issue, saying the two sides were not far apart about how much severance pay the furloughed workers would receive.</p>
        <p>He said a major obstacle to a settlement was the union's demand that all new workers be required to join the union or, if they decided not to, to pay the equivalent of union dues. Union officials want such a clause, saying it is needed to build a strong union, but Mr. Batterman said such a clause might make it harder for the museum to attract top-flight professionals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batterman said the other main issue was the health plan. The union's members are part of the management health plan, and the union is demanding the right to bargain over any changes in the plan. The museum is refusing to grant that demand, saying that if the union wants to bargain over a health plan, then a new, separate plan should be set up for the union. But the union says it fears that a new union health plan will not be as good as the management plan.</p>
        <p>Within the union, there is a wide salary range, with bookstore workers starting at $17,000 a year while some associate curators are paid more than $45,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
