<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vatican's Selection Method Is Shrouded in Secrecy</title>
    <meta content="04PROX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE SUCCESSOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DC1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vatican's Selection Method Is Shrouded in Secrecy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the death of Cardinal John O'Connor, the question arises of who will succeed him as New York's ninth archbishop, spiritual head of 2.4 million Roman Catholics.</p>
        <p>Even before Cardinal O'Connor underwent surgery for removal of a brain tumor, there had been speculation throughout church circles. This week, the name of Bishop Edward Michael Egan of Bridgeport, Conn., was at the top of a list of candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the death of Cardinal John O'Connor, the question arises of who will succeed him as New York's ninth archbishop, spiritual head of 2.4 million Roman Catholics.</p>
        <p>Even before Cardinal O'Connor underwent surgery for removal of a brain tumor, there had been speculation throughout church circles. This week, the name of Bishop Edward Michael Egan of Bridgeport, Conn., was at the top of a list of candidates.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan, 68, was made an auxiliary bishop for education in the New York archdiocese in 1985, arriving from Rome just after Pope John Paul II named Cardinal O'Connor to head the New York church. He holds a degree in canon law, and served in Rome for 18 years.</p>
        <p>In 1988, Bishop Egan was sent to the Bridgeport diocese, which includes Greenwich, among the wealthiest in the country, where he is considered a gifted fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>If selected, he would most likely be seen as an interim head of the church in New York. Under church tradition, Bishop Egan would offer his resignation upon turning 75 in seven years, allowing Rome time to groom a new head of the New York church in the interim.</p>
        <p>Other candidates on the list included William F. Murphy, an auxiliary bishop of Boston; Edwin O'Brien, who heads the archdiocese for the military services; Henry J. Mansell, the bishop of Buffalo; Theodore E. McCarrick, the archbishop of Newark; and Justin F. Rigali, the archbishop of St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The question of a successor may be an obvious one for anyone wishing to look ahead to the future of the archdiocese, whose leader plays a pre-eminent role in the Catholic Church in America. But the answer, for now, is uncertain.</p>
        <p>That is because the appointment of an archbishop is not an open process. Instead, it is a matter that rests in the hands of the Vatican, and is shrouded in such secrecy that the appointments to head some of the most important archdioceses in the United States have often come as a surprise to those within the church who thought they were in the know.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the appointment process begins in Washington and moves to Rome.</p>
        <p>In Washington, the apostolic nuncio, a prelate appointed by the Vatican who functions as its ambassador to the federal government and also as Rome's representative to the American church, comes up with a short list of possible candidates when an archdiocese or diocese becomes vacant, or is about to become so.</p>
        <p>Since 1998, the nuncio in Washington has been Archbishop Gabriel Montalvo, 70, a native of Colombia.</p>
        <p>''He draws up a list of three names,'' said the Rev. Thomas Reese, editor of America magazine, a Jesuit publication, and author of ''Archbishop: Inside the Power Structure of the American Catholic Church,'' (Harper &amp; Row, 1989).</p>
        <p>Those choices, Father Reese added, are based on the nuncio's research, with information obtained through conversations with other American cardinals, bishops and prominent Catholics. The discussions are conducted in the strictest secrecy and those consulted promise they will not even mention that they have been approached.</p>
        <p>But if the past is any guide, a few details can be hazarded about the candidates likely to be recommended for a major archdiocese like New York -- whose occupant can expect to be named a cardinal, with the right to vote in the selection of a future pope.</p>
        <p>Because of New York's importance in the American Catholic world, anyone considered to run the archdiocese is likely to have experience as head of another archdiocese or a diocese. He is also likely to be a senior figure in the church, in his late 50's or 60's. He may have studied or worked in church institutions in Rome. And he may have a doctorate.</p>
        <p>The nuncio ranks his three candidates, then forwards the recommendations to Rome, to be considered by the Congregation for Bishops, the  body charged with making the final recommendations of men to head dioceses worldwide.</p>
        <p>The congregation is composed of ''mostly cardinals, some of whom are resident in Rome, and some are diocesan bishops around the world,'' said the Rev. John Beal, a professor of canon law at Catholic University of America. ''For example,'' he added, ''Cardinal O'Connor for a very long time was a member of the congregation.''</p>
        <p>After its deliberations, the congregation sends its selection to the pope, who may accept it or reject it, asking the congregation to go back over the list. Or, Father Beal said, the pope may choose someone else.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, choosing a person for New York is a matter that rests with the pope alone.</p>
        <p>''Don't underestimate the possibility of surprise,'' Father Beal said. ''I recall that no one had predicted that Cardinal O'Connor would go from Scranton to New York when it happened.''</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE SUCCESSOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
