<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meet Mr. Sprewell, N.B.A. Marketing Tool</title>
    <meta content="04SPRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5D81E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meet Mr. Sprewell, N.B.A. Marketing Tool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just two years ago, it was the look of an American pariah, the facial expression of perhaps the nation's most contemptible athlete. Latrell Sprewell's scowl -- the one that becomes fiercely exaggerated after breakaway dunks -- was seen as the window to what was viewed as one of the darkest souls in the National Basketball Association.</p>
        <p>But the hardened, chiseled look Sprewell wears on the court has become an N.B.A. favorite, a marketing tool. Far from the face of a crazy man, it is the face of the Knicks, the face the league picked to represent New York in its playoff promotional ads that are running on TNT and TBS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just two years ago, it was the look of an American pariah, the facial expression of perhaps the nation's most contemptible athlete. Latrell Sprewell's scowl -- the one that becomes fiercely exaggerated after breakaway dunks -- was seen as the window to what was viewed as one of the darkest souls in the National Basketball Association.</p>
        <p>But the hardened, chiseled look Sprewell wears on the court has become an N.B.A. favorite, a marketing tool. Far from the face of a crazy man, it is the face of the Knicks, the face the league picked to represent New York in its playoff promotional ads that are running on TNT and TBS.</p>
        <p>The ads, which feature Sprewell before a surreal backdrop of the city, are a sign of how the electrifying swingman has become a darling of not only the Knicks, but the league. Instead of choosing the clean-cut All-Star, Allan Houston, or the future Hall of Famer and longtime king of the Knicks, Patrick Ewing, the league chose Sprewell, who was largely seen as a villain after choking his Golden State Warriors coach, P. J. Carlesimo, 14 games into the 1997-1998 season.</p>
        <p>''That's saying a lot, especially coming from two years ago where things were the total opposite,'' Sprewell said yesterday, after the Knicks prepped for Sunday's Game 1 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series against Miami. ''I'm just glad to be back here, and to have such open arms embracing me the way they have here in this city and now the way the league is.</p>
        <p>''I'm just glad I was able to turn it around, because it could have easily gone the other way. I always wondered, was I going to get back to my form before I had gotten suspended or if I was going to come in and go south? I think I've done a good job of keeping my head above the water, and I want to stay there.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, who was suspended for the final 68 games of the 1997-98 season, has actually exceeded the status he held as a member of the lowly Warriors. Though he has yet to attain the individual accolades he won out West, he is arguably the top player on a championship contender. His fearless and effective play has won over the fans, and his articulate and insightful comments have made him a go-to guy for the news media. And yesterday, he was celebrated by the Knicks for donating $100,000 to Madison Square Garden's Cheering for Children Foundation, which provides uniforms and sports equipment for children in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''The image now, hopefully, is a positive one,'' Sprewell said.</p>
        <p>Sprewell recognizes that N.B.A. Commissioner David Stern, whom he was often at odds with during his 68-game suspension after the choking incident, is among those who have done an about-face concerning his personality.</p>
        <p>''That is surprising, but I'm glad we're doing well now and we're not going back and forth at one another,'' said Sprewell, who has pending a lawsuit he filed against the league for the $6.4 million he lost in salary during his suspension. ''It's nice to be able to focus in on basketball and not have to worry about how Stern feels or if he's upset about what I'm saying or doing.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell's image adjustment is not limited to how the league and its fans perceive him. Though he earned three All-Star berths and one first-team all-N.B.A. selection while at Golden State, he eventually came to be viewed by many as a selfish, statistics-driven player who could never rein his game to blend in with a winning team.</p>
        <p>But all this season, Coach Jeff Van Gundy and his Knick teammates have praised Sprewell for his unselfishness. Sprewell, who has a career assist average of 4.4 a game and averaged a career-high 6.3 for the Warriors in 1996-97, maintains that his outlook on the game has not changed. But he said he understands why others have that perception.</p>
        <p>''I'm surrounded by players here on this team that are really good,'' he said. ''At Golden State, I was forced to have to score more. I had to carry the load because of the personnel that we had on that team. Here, we're loaded on the bench with guys that can even score for us or that could start on other teams. So I'm going to keep moving the ball and try to pile up some assists.''</p>
        <p>Another key component in Sprewell's changed public image is his defense. Because of his tremendous athleticism and quickness, he has always been regarded as a potentially outstanding defender and he was named to the N.B.A.'s all-defensive second team over the 1993-1994 season. But his style in Golden State was to gamble in the passing lanes in search of steals.</p>
        <p>With the Knicks, and particularly in the first-round series against Toronto and Vince Carter, Sprewell has become more of a position, containment defender. He gambles less -- he had no steals in the three games against Toronto -- but makes it hard on opponents with his steady on-the-ball defense. And the spectacular job he did on Carter will have to be duplicated against the versatile Jamal Mashburn against Miami.</p>
        <p>''I like that pressure, and I like that challenge,'' Sprewell said of his emerging image as a defensive stopper. ''I love it. I've always considered myself a defensive player, so for people to put that label on me is nothing but positive.''</p>
        <p>Positive seems to be all Sprewell sees these days.</p>
        <p>''They had their arms wide open, and when I got there they gave me a big hug,'' he said of the Knicks' fans. ''So I'm thankful for that.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
