<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suit by Democrats Attacks Republican's Fund-Raising</title>
    <meta content="Y04DON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MONEY FIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DD1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suit by Democrats Attacks Republican's Fund-Raising</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a federal lawsuit filed today, Congressional Democrats accused Representative Tom DeLay, the House majority whip, of engaging in extortion, racketeering and money laundering in his aggressive fund-raising for Republican candidates and causes.</p>
        <p>Representative Patrick J. Kennedy, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, said the suit was filed in Federal District Court here in an effort to stop ''massive illegal conduct'' by Mr. DeLay, a Texas Republican who has raised millions of dollars for the Republican party through a variety of committees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a federal lawsuit filed today, Congressional Democrats accused Representative Tom DeLay, the House majority whip, of engaging in extortion, racketeering and money laundering in his aggressive fund-raising for Republican candidates and causes.</p>
        <p>Representative Patrick J. Kennedy, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, said the suit was filed in Federal District Court here in an effort to stop ''massive illegal conduct'' by Mr. DeLay, a Texas Republican who has raised millions of dollars for the Republican party through a variety of committees.</p>
        <p>The suit is the third attempt in the last year by Democrats to corral Mr. DeLay's fund-raising empire that some critics and admirers call ''DeLay Inc.'' Democrats last year complained to the Justice Department and the Federal Election Commission about Mr. DeLay's tactics, without immediate result.</p>
        <p>''Mr. DeLay is unfortunately conducting these activities under the color of his office,'' Mr. Kennedy said at a news conference today. ''He seeks through the use of systematic extortion to coerce the contribution of millions of dollars to Republicans and to intimidate those inclined to support Democrats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay declared himself ''saddened and disappointed'' that Democrats would tarnish the House's dignity ''by resorting to ugly, unfounded, politically motivated charges for their own political gains.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Baron, a spokesman for Mr. DeLay, said that the charges are baseless and that Mr. DeLay would vigorously contest them, if they are not quickly dismissed by the court.</p>
        <p>''This is a tactic designed to limit Republican fund-raising, that's all this is,'' Mr. Baron said.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit tries to apply the civil provisions of the Federal Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act, known by the acronym RICO, to Mr. DeLay's fund-raising activities through a variety of linked committees.</p>
        <p>The evidence is drawn chiefly from news reports over the last year that detail Mr. DeLay's forceful efforts to persuade corporate lobbyists to donate large sums to political action committees he and his associates control.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Bauer, the Democratic lawyer who drew up the complaint, said he believed it was the first time the racketeering statute has been applied in a political fund-raising case, although the conservative legal watchdog group Judicial Watch cited the law in one of its complaints against the Clinton-Gore re-election committee of 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bauer said the law can be applied against any form of bribery or extortion by an organized group. He also said federal money-laundering laws govern political as well as criminal activities.</p>
        <p>However, Kenneth A. Gross, a former chief of enforcement at the Federal Election Commission, said the effort to apply the racketeering law to political fund-raising was creative but legally questionable.</p>
        <p>''There's no question that Mr. DeLay is an aggressive fund-raiser,'' Mr. Gross said, ''but to allege that he's crossed the line into racketeering as a legal matter is a real stretch.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross speculated that the Democrats were hoping to use the lawsuit to engage in extensive pre-trial discovery, allowing them to pore over the records of Mr. DeLay's various fund-raising committees.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit names several DeLay-related committees as part of a scheme to extort and launder illegal political funds, but focuses on the Republican Majority Issues Committee, a group that plans to spend $25 million on voter turnout and issue advertising in the fall campaign.</p>
        <p>The group is organized under a provision of the Internal Revenue Code known as section 527, which allows it to raise and spend unlimited amounts with no disclosure, as long as it does not advocate the election or defeat of candidates. The Democrats contend that such activities amount to illegal money laundering.</p>
        <p>Karl Gallant, chairman of the Republican Majority Issues Committee, said the lawsuit was a threat to the group's free-speech rights and an effort by Democratic ''hacks'' to stifle independent political groups. He said liberal groups were also taking advantage of the section 527 loophole.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MONEY FIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
