<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberty Huffs and Puffs at Training Camp</title>
    <meta content="04LIBE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7D81E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberty Huffs and Puffs at Training Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York Liberty players were still talking about ''the shot'' yesterday at the opening of training camp.</p>
        <p>That is the label the team has given to Teresa Weatherspoon's 47-foot desperation bank shot in Game 2 of the championship series that the Houston Comets eventually won in three games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York Liberty players were still talking about ''the shot'' yesterday at the opening of training camp.</p>
        <p>That is the label the team has given to Teresa Weatherspoon's 47-foot desperation bank shot in Game 2 of the championship series that the Houston Comets eventually won in three games.</p>
        <p>The Liberty, the defending Eastern Conference champion, began training camp at Chelsea Piers in Manhattan with Coach Richie Adubato describing his players as so poorly conditioned ''they couldn't play a halfcourt game.''</p>
        <p>''We have people that can't walk, people that can't run and people ready to play,'' Adubato said. ''We're just not in great condition right now and our frontline people really need a lot of work.''</p>
        <p>Tamika Whitmore, the 6-foot-2-inch, 195-pound power forward who played well off the bench last year, arrived in camp 30 pounds overweight. Whitmore, a third-round draft pick last year, said she was trying to add some bulk to her frame. Adubato was not buying that.</p>
        <p>''She tried to bulk up and turned her ankle,'' Adubato said. ''So instead of bulking and running, she bulked up and didn't push herself away from the table.''</p>
        <p>The coach said he was concerned about Whitmore's weight four months ago and flew to Memphis and put her on a strict regimen. Since then, she has lost 10 pounds.</p>
        <p>Adubato believes success may have spoiled his rookie star and ''now she's gotten very complacent.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty's biggest needs are at power forward and center. Rebecca Lobo reinjured her left anterior cruciate ligament last December and is not expected to play until mid-June. Kym Hampton has come out of retirement for the moment. How long or whether she plays, depends on whether the knees hold up.</p>
        <p>The 6-3 Sue Wicks, who had what many said was her best pro season last year, has proven capable of shooting from the perimeter, posting up and playing defense. But at 33, Wicks may not be able to put in the 29.3 minutes a game she averaged last year, especially with the league playing a condensed schedule. The regular season is scheduled to end on Aug. 9 to accommodate the 2000 Olympic Games in Sydney, Australia, in late September.</p>
        <p>Once again, the Liberty hopes to solve its post problem with a rookie -- Olga Firsova, 6-6 center from Kansas State. Firsova, who is from Ukraine, plays a more physical game than Michele VanGorp, who was picked up by the Portland Fire in the expansion draft.</p>
        <p>''I got the size to play a physical game,'' said Firsova, who blocked a record 51 shots last season at Kansas State. ''I know they're going to bang me around, but I've prepared for it.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty had expected 18 players to attend to its four-week camp, but only 14 were present. The two fourth-round draft picks, Jessica Bibby and Natalie Porter, both of Australia, had visa problems, but are expected to arrive later this week. Two other players, Alessandra Santos de Oliviera of Brazil and Marina Ferragut of Spain, are also expected in camp soon. Carolyn Young, who missed all of the 1999 season, is rehabilitating her right anterior cruciate and medial collateral ligaments and is unlikely to play until late July.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
