<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.D.A. Says Researchers Failed to Report a Second Death Linked to Gene Therapy</title>
    <meta content="04GENE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Therapy and Rehabilitation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DF1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.D.A. Says Researchers Failed to Report a Second Death Linked to Gene Therapy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers at St. Elizabeth's Medical Center here failed to report the death of a patient in gene therapy experiments and might have contributed to the growth of cancer in another patient, whose condition was also reported improperly, investigators for the Food and Drug Administration have said.</p>
        <p>Their accusations were made in April in a letter to the hospital and the chief researcher in the experiment, Dr. Jeffrey M. Isner, and were recently posted on the agency's Web site. The experiment has been stopped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers at St. Elizabeth's Medical Center here failed to report the death of a patient in gene therapy experiments and might have contributed to the growth of cancer in another patient, whose condition was also reported improperly, investigators for the Food and Drug Administration have said.</p>
        <p>Their accusations were made in April in a letter to the hospital and the chief researcher in the experiment, Dr. Jeffrey M. Isner, and were recently posted on the agency's Web site. The experiment has been stopped.</p>
        <p>The news comes as scientists, hospitals and companies sponsoring gene therapy experiments have been working to assure the public of the safety of the experiments after the death of a patient in a gene experiment at the University of Pennsylvania last year.</p>
        <p>Jack Cumming, president of the Vascular Genetics Inc. of Durham, N.C., the company sponsoring the experiment at St. Elizabeth's, acknowledged today that there had been some ''problems'' in the gene therapy experiment. Mr. Cumming  said the company would do everything it could to satisfy the F.D.A. in correcting the problems. He said he was ''very optimistic'' that positive results would be presented to the agency this summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cumming said he would not dispute the agency's findings and said that his company had hired two outside groups to audit and monitor all the experiments it had begun around the country, including the one at St. Elizabeth's. The groups were hired after the company learned that the federal agency was writing a warning letter, he said.</p>
        <p>Sonia Hagopian, a spokeswoman for the St. Elizabeth's, said the hospital took the warning letter very seriously, and added: ''We are focusing all our resources on producing a thorough and thoughtful response to the F.D.A.''</p>
        <p>The hospital's public relations office said Dr. Isner would not be available for comment at this time.</p>
        <p>The problems in the experiment were reported on Tuesday in The Washington Post and The Boston Herald.</p>
        <p>About 300 gene therapy experiments are under way around the country. Troubles with some of the experiments have become public, especially since the death of a patient, Jesse Gelsinger, 18, in the University of Pennsylvania experiment.</p>
        <p>In the experiment at St. Elizabeth's, which was jointly sponsored by Tufts University, a gene that makes a substance called V.E.G.F. (for vascular endothelial growth factor) was injected directly into the hearts of patients with blocked heart vessels. Researchers hoped  the gene would start making the growth factor, which is the body's natural substance to make blood vessels grow.</p>
        <p>Inspectors for the federal agency  said they found several violations of the rules of the experiment in a routine check in March. One patient in the experiment died two months after receiving the experimental therapy, but the researchers did not report the death to the agency. The agency is investigating to determine if the treatment was the cause of the death.</p>
        <p>In another case, a patient was included in the study although he should have been kept out under the rules of the experiment. The patient was a heavy smoker and a small mass had appeared in one lung, the agency said. Because the experimental therapy used a chemical designed to increase the growth of blood vessels, the agency said, it was possible that it increased the supply of blood to the growing tumor.</p>
        <p>The agency's warning letter noted that the St. Elizabeth's researchers saw the mass when it was less than a centimeter in July 1999, then again in August when it was two centimeters in diameter, but went ahead with the treatment on Sept. 21, 1999. Two months later, the agency said, the patient was hospitalized with chest pain, and the mass was found to have grown to five centimeters.</p>
        <p>There was no evidence in the patient's records or the experiment records that either the patient or his doctor was notified of the growth of the mass, investigators said.</p>
        <p>Instead, one of the researchers  sent a letter to the patient's doctor saying that the patient was doing better with his heart problem since receiving the therapy. The letter did not mention the lung mass.</p>
        <p>In addition, the agency noted that in the experiment records the growth in the mass was noted and marked as a ''severe'' change for the patient. This word should have set off an immediate call to the F.D.A. Instead, the agency said, the word ''severe'' was struck out and the word ''mild'' substituted.</p>
        <p>The agency's letter also noted that because the researchers apparently did nothing to notify the patient or his doctor, ''your site appears to have failed to provide adequate medical care for this subject.''</p>
        <p>In another case, a patient in the study had a heart attack just after getting the experimental injection. The attack led to multiple organ failure, a long hospitalization, and death a few months later.</p>
        <p>But the researchers reported to authorities only that the patient was hospitalized, not that she had died.</p>
        <p>Such events are required to be reported because it is possible the therapy itself was the cause of death, and it would be urgent to consider whether to take precautions with other experimental subjects.</p>
        <p>In addition, the agency reported that Dr. Isner himself carried out an autopsy on the woman's heart, although he is not a certified pathologist and has no hospital privileges to carry out autopsies.</p>
        <p>The inspectors also cited several other problems with the methods of enrolling patients in the experiment: needed tests were not done in some cases, and other patients enrolled might not have been eligible for the study.</p>
        <p>The hospital and the researchers have 15 days to tell the agency how they will correct the problems in the experiment. There is no set punishment for the violations, but the F.D.A. has the authority to ban the researchers from future work using federal money.</p>
        <p>This and three other experiments carried on by Dr. Isner were stopped when the agency first began its inspection in February and have not resumed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Isner is a founder of the company leading the trials and is a major stockholder in it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
