<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Regulators Give Approval to Viacom's Buyout of CBS</title>
    <meta content="Y04MER$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DE1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Regulators Give Approval to Viacom's Buyout of CBS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal officials today approved the largest broadcast merger in history -- Viacom's $30 billion acquisition of CBS -- just a day after two other media giants resolved a dispute that was, in large part, a byproduct of consolidation in the broadcasting and cable industry.</p>
        <p>The decision by the Federal Communications Commission to approve a merger that will give Viacom control of 35 percent of the broadcasting market represents the high-water mark of a Clinton administration policy of promoting consolidation in a number of industries as a way of encouraging competition. It was immediately hailed by top executives of the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal officials today approved the largest broadcast merger in history -- Viacom's $30 billion acquisition of CBS -- just a day after two other media giants resolved a dispute that was, in large part, a byproduct of consolidation in the broadcasting and cable industry.</p>
        <p>The decision by the Federal Communications Commission to approve a merger that will give Viacom control of 35 percent of the broadcasting market represents the high-water mark of a Clinton administration policy of promoting consolidation in a number of industries as a way of encouraging competition. It was immediately hailed by top executives of the company.</p>
        <p>Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman and chief executive of Viacom, said that the acquisition would be completed on Thursday morning and that CBS's ticker symbol would never again be trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>''This has really worked perfectly,'' an ebullient Mr. Redstone said in an interview this afternoon. ''We basically got everything we had wanted.''</p>
        <p>The administration's policy of permitting consolidation in the telecommunications industry will be on display again later this month, when the F.C.C. is expected to approve a staff recommendation to permit AT&amp;T to complete its acquisition of MediaOne, giving it control of more than a third of the cable industry. Many experts expect that the Justice Department, which is reviewing that deal for antitrust issues, will also approve it.</p>
        <p>The policy is rooted in the notion that a few corporate behemoths battling over control of the market can be both more efficient and more competitive than any regulation and control from bureaucrats in Washington.</p>
        <p>''We don't think big is per se bad,'' said Joel I. Klein, the assistant attorney general in charge of the Justice Department's antitrust division. ''We analyze mergers in terms of relevant markets.''</p>
        <p>But such mergers do not always come without a price. The policy helped both the Walt Disney Company, ABC's parent company, and Time Warner grow into formidable broadcasting and distribution companies in recent years. But this week, some 3.5 million customers of Time Warner cable television lost their ABC signal for almost two days as the two companies wrangled over retransmission agreements.</p>
        <p>The consolidation has created bottlenecks that have made it easier for one company to block the access of another. Moreover, government officials and industry analysts say negotiations between Time Warner and ABC had grown more strained after Time Warner's announcement that it intended to merge with America Online.</p>
        <p>Moments after approving the merger of Viacom and CBS, the F.C.C. ruled that Time Warner had violated a regulation that prohibits a company from removing a network's signal during the sweeps rating month and said it would consider what penalty to impose. The fine will be symbolic, as the agency can only  penalize the company $7,500 for each violation each day.</p>
        <p>But consumer groups say the larger lesson from this week's events is that further consolidation of the cable and broadcast industries will lead to similar disputes and blackouts, as the survivors struggle to control both the content and distribution of what appears on television and the Internet.</p>
        <p>As the number of dominant players in telecommunications and other industries dwindles, some regulators are also beginning to question how much further the government should go in approving large pending deals.</p>
        <p>''Quite often the best consumer competition comes from big companies fiercely competing against each other,'' said Robert Pitofsky, chairman of the Federal Trade Commission. ''But in some sectors of the economy, we are running out of big companies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitofsky declined to discuss his agency's review of the proposed merger of America Online with Time Warner. But other government officials said today that Time Warner's decision to remove ABC this week from its cable systems had undermined the companies' repeated pronouncements when the merger was announced that they would never try to shut out others from using their enormous Internet and cable backbone.</p>
        <p>In approving Viacom's acquisition of CBS, the regulators gave the companies a year to come into compliance with a rule that prohibits a television network from having an ownership interest in a second network. Viacom holds an interest in the fledgling UPN, and some experts predict that the agency may relax the dual network rule over the next 12 months.</p>
        <p>Viacom will also have a year to meet the national television ownership cap, which prohibits a company from controlling more than 35 percent of the broadcast market. The combined reach of CBS and Viacom is now more than 41 percent. As part of the regulatory order, the companies will have six months to sell some radio and television stations in the Los Angeles, Chicago, Baltimore, Dallas-Fort Worth and Sacramento, Calif., areas.</p>
        <p>But those divestitures are relatively small pieces of the deal, which involves the transfer of 38 television stations and more than 160 radio stations.</p>
        <p>With a few exceptions, regulators during the Clinton years have signed off on big mergers, many of which would have been unimaginable a generation ago.</p>
        <p>''In merger law, the Clinton administration has a great deal in common with the Reagan and Bush years,'' said John Shepard Wiley Jr., a law professor at the University of California at Los Angeles. ''The analysis has become bipartisan.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, in the 1960's, the Justice Department successfully blocked one deal that would have resulted in a grocery store merger that would have resulted in a company controlling 7.5 percent of the industry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
