<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happiness, Seen From Diverse Angles</title>
    <meta content="04FLAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CABARET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DF1E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happiness, Seen From Diverse Angles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It takes a certain chutzpah for an operatic and concert performer to take art songs into a cabaret setting. But Lauren Flanigan, the New York City Opera soprano, demonstrated more than enough nerve and charisma at Joe's Pub on Monday evening to make the transition a dramatic occasion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Flanigan is, in a word, fearless. Her densely packed program was a loosely thematic series of abrupt musical mood swings that led off and ended with Aaron Jay Kernis's ''Pure Suit of Happiness'' and was made up of songs that she declared made her happy and that included flatted seventh chords.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It takes a certain chutzpah for an operatic and concert performer to take art songs into a cabaret setting. But Lauren Flanigan, the New York City Opera soprano, demonstrated more than enough nerve and charisma at Joe's Pub on Monday evening to make the transition a dramatic occasion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Flanigan is, in a word, fearless. Her densely packed program was a loosely thematic series of abrupt musical mood swings that led off and ended with Aaron Jay Kernis's ''Pure Suit of Happiness'' and was made up of songs that she declared made her happy and that included flatted seventh chords.</p>
        <p>Happiness for Ms. Flanigan proved not to be limited to expressions of joy and contentment. It was closer to raw feeling pushed in her bright, thickly textured voice to the sort of extremes associated with a singer like Maria Callas.</p>
        <p>Like Callas, Ms. Flanigan is perfectly willing to sacrifice tonal refinement and precise pitch to extract a song's emotional viscera. And in a program of two dozen numbers by composers ranging from Debussy to Leonard Bernstein to William Bolcom, she brought a special intensity to the music of Kurt Weill and Ricky Ian Gordon.</p>
        <p>Weill's ''Youkali'' and ''Je Ne T'Aime Pas'' found Ms. Flanigan emoting to the brink of tears, blending her personality with the lyrics to such a degree that she appeared personally shattered at the end of each performance.</p>
        <p>The evening's high point was a performance of Mr. Gordon's exquisitely melodic setting of an Emily Dickinson poem, ''Will There Really Be a Morning?,'' transforming a song usually treated as a sad midnight reverie into an increasingly desperate cry in the dark.</p>
        <p>Kamal Khan, who accompanied on piano, matched Ms. Flanigan's fervor with a vigorous percussive power.</p>
        <p>CABARET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
