<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cardinal John O'Connor</title>
    <meta content="04SUB3$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDE1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cardinal John O'Connor</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cardinal John O'Connor, who died yesterday after 16 years as the voice of American Catholicism, was a strong-willed, conservative theologian whose views were tempered with a pastoral concern for the sick, the weak and the poor. For the two million Roman Catholics in the New York Archdiocese, the cardinal brought a return to a rigorous traditional Catholicism. He passionately opposed abortion, birth control, homosexuality, the ordination of women and even baseball on Good Friday. Such views stirred controversy among many New Yorkers and even some of his own parishioners, but he balanced them with a plea for those in need, even when the needy were at odds with his strong Catholic message.</p>
        <p>In the days when AIDS patients had trouble getting medical care, he appealed to Catholic medical workers to help. He battled to better conditions for immigrant drivers and underpaid health care workers. Even in his last months, the cardinal mustered the strength to speak out against Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's plans to require the homeless to work for their shelter. And he had begun to worry that America was returning to the robber-baron era, ''creating a survival-of-the-fittest society.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cardinal John O'Connor, who died yesterday after 16 years as the voice of American Catholicism, was a strong-willed, conservative theologian whose views were tempered with a pastoral concern for the sick, the weak and the poor. For the two million Roman Catholics in the New York Archdiocese, the cardinal brought a return to a rigorous traditional Catholicism. He passionately opposed abortion, birth control, homosexuality, the ordination of women and even baseball on Good Friday. Such views stirred controversy among many New Yorkers and even some of his own parishioners, but he balanced them with a plea for those in need, even when the needy were at odds with his strong Catholic message.</p>
        <p>In the days when AIDS patients had trouble getting medical care, he appealed to Catholic medical workers to help. He battled to better conditions for immigrant drivers and underpaid health care workers. Even in his last months, the cardinal mustered the strength to speak out against Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's plans to require the homeless to work for their shelter. And he had begun to worry that America was returning to the robber-baron era, ''creating a survival-of-the-fittest society.''</p>
        <p>Describing himself as ''a kid from an ordinary family in Philadelphia,'' the cardinal was ordained into the priesthood in 1945. He became a Navy chaplain and rose to the rank of rear admiral. In 1984, he became archbishop of New York and a year later was named cardinal, replacing the quiet leadership of Cardinal Terence Cooke. The shift was dramatic, with progressive New Yorkers forced to adjust to a new cardinal who supported the war in Vietnam and had compared abortion to the Holocaust, a statement that so enraged Jewish leaders that one rabbi labeled it an ''obscenity.''</p>
        <p>It was in those early years that Cardinal O'Connor proclaimed his plain-spoken message not only from the pulpit at St. Patrick's Cathedral on Fifth Avenue, but also at regular press conferences after mass or on his own weekly television show. As a very public priest in the nation's media capital, he soon became not only America's top Catholic but also American Catholicism's No. 1 conservative communicator. His critics began to label him a papal disciplinarian who enforced Pope John Paul II's strict church doctrine within his church as forcefully as he preached his Catholicism in the less-obedient political arena.</p>
        <p>In later years, the cardinal's rhetoric softened and, although never very far out of the city's political mix, he began to remove the press conference from his weekly rituals. In one interview a few years ago, he mused that the church might have been better off ''if, when I came here, I had just become a silent servant of the people.'' It was a view his fans soundly rejected.</p>
        <p>He also regretted denouncing Salman Rushdie without first reading ''The Satanic Verses'' and was distressed that his challenge of Geraldine Ferraro's views on abortion was used against her unfairly.  The cardinal's supporters felt that his political troubles arose when he tried to reassert the church's fundamental principles as Pope John Paul's agent in New York. But this firm theological stand against reform or even moderation in his own church also gave him clout as a mediator in other areas. The cardinal was a strong force for ecumenism and worked to improve his church's relations with the Jewish community. His career as military chaplain and support of Vietnam, which he later revised, nevertheless brought more attention to his anti-nuclear stance and his push to cut defense spending. More recently, after the shooting of Amadou Diallo by police last year, the cardinal tried to bring all sides together to defuse racial anger ignited by the innocent black man's death.</p>
        <p>As archbishop, he watched over a changing flock, with a growing Hispanic community and  diverse population of immigrants. Cardinal John O'Connor will be remembered as the pope's dutiful emissary in New York City, a powerful advocate for Catholic theology and human charity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
