<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testimony Clouds Proposal By Hearst to Buy Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="Y04PAP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DD1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testimony Clouds Proposal By Hearst to Buy Chronicle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>San Francisco's two daily newspapers have made their names and reputations covering the sometimes arcane and often vindictive power struggles of their city, whose political fault zones have made the most commonplace business interactions unstable. Now the newspapers themselves have become front-page news.</p>
        <p>Over and over again since last August, the Hearst Corporation's $660 million deal to buy The San Francisco Chronicle and abandon The San Francisco Examiner seemed on the verge of completion. But over and over again, it has foundered in the face of dogged opposition. First, from Mayor Willie L. Brown Jr. and the district attorney, Terence Hallinan, then from antitrust lawyers in the United States Justice Department. And this week, it was a lawsuit by a businessman and sometime politician who is seeking to scuttle the sale of both papers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>San Francisco's two daily newspapers have made their names and reputations covering the sometimes arcane and often vindictive power struggles of their city, whose political fault zones have made the most commonplace business interactions unstable. Now the newspapers themselves have become front-page news.</p>
        <p>Over and over again since last August, the Hearst Corporation's $660 million deal to buy The San Francisco Chronicle and abandon The San Francisco Examiner seemed on the verge of completion. But over and over again, it has foundered in the face of dogged opposition. First, from Mayor Willie L. Brown Jr. and the district attorney, Terence Hallinan, then from antitrust lawyers in the United States Justice Department. And this week, it was a lawsuit by a businessman and sometime politician who is seeking to scuttle the sale of both papers.</p>
        <p>Whether the businessman, Clinton Reilly, prevails in his civil antitrust action, his lawsuit has already claimed one victim. On Tuesday, Hearst issued a statement saying that Timothy O. White, the publisher of The Examiner, would take ''an indefinite leave of absence'' after his testimony on Monday that he offered favorable editorial treatment if the mayor dropped his opposition to Hearst's purchase of The Chronicle.</p>
        <p>The mayor was in a tough re-election campaign at the time.</p>
        <p>The course of the lawsuit, and the sale, may not turn on Mr. White's sensational testimony, with its clear implication of journalistic log-rolling and dishonesty. Still, it did nothing to clarify the deal's murky prospects.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Broadwater, the managing director of Veronis Suhler &amp; Associates, Hearst's investment banker for the sale of The Examiner, said yesterday, ''None of us would have thought that, nine months after the fact, we would not have closed the transaction, we would not have gotten approval from Justice and we would have had this local problem crop up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White almost immediately disavowed his testimony, saying he was ''tired and confused'' by the question. But then Mr. Reilly's lawyer, Joseph M. Alioto, the son of a former San Francisco mayor, produced an e-mail message that Mr. White sent to George Irish, president of Hearst Newspapers, on Sept. 1, the same day that Phil Bronstein, the newspaper's executive editor, had lunch with Mayor Brown and Mr. White.</p>
        <p>In the message Mr. White wrote, ''I asked Willie how I was going to justify to my superiors in New York wanting to support him and cooperate with him when he was seeming to go out of his way to make our lives difficult.''</p>
        <p>The notion that the publisher of the first newspaper owned by the legendary William Randolph Hearst had reverted to his old habits of using the paper for political ends prompted a quick reaction from company executives. Late on Monday, the Hearst Corporation issued a statement saying, ''It is not now -- nor has it ever been -- a policy of The San Francisco Examiner to trade favorable editorial coverage for any gains, including political influence.''</p>
        <p>An even stronger disavowal, drafted by Examiner journalists, appeared on the paper's front page. It read in part: ''The newsroom employees of The Examiner are proud that our editorial support is not, and never has been, for sale. We fully expect any employee to be held accountable for actions that undermine our editorial integrity.''</p>
        <p>In the newsroom of The Chronicle, which has shared its building and its profits with The Examiner for more than three decades, the prospect -- however unlikely -- that the new owners might condone such behavior prompted an equally strong reaction.</p>
        <p>Nanette Asimov, an education reporter, joined with dozens of colleagues in supporting a petition that, she said, declared that ''the appearance of trading our integrity for favors is what we abhor.'' The petition, Ms. Asimov added, calls on Hearst, the newspaper's prospective owner, to declare that ''this is in no way Chronicle policy.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference yesterday, Mayor Brown, whose political dealings have long been the subject of tough, even harsh coverage in The Examiner, said he remembered no deal. In a telephone interview, the mayor's deputy press secretary, Ron Vinson, quoted Mr. Brown as mocking the notion of a deal by saying, jokingly: ''The Examiner didn't keep up their end of the bargain. We've never gotten a break from The Examiner editorial board.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, James A. Finefrock, the editor of The Examiner's editorial pages, put a memorandum to his colleagues into the paper's computer system saying: ''I don't know what Tim White said or meant in his conversations with Willie Brown. But I do know that Tim has never asked me to go easy on Brown or anyone else on our editorial page, nor would he have succeeded had he tried.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Finefrock said in his memorandum that he wrote the newspaper's endorsement of Mr. Brown's candidacy after all five members of the editorial board had agreed.</p>
        <p>Other Examiner editors point to the newspaper's aggressive coverage of a federal grand jury investigation of abuses in the selection of contractors for the long-running expansion of San Francisco International Airport. One of the people indicted on charges of fraud last week in connection with the investigation worked in a city agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronstein, the executive editor, said he believed that Mr. White's remarks about cooperation with the mayor at the Sept. 1 lunch were ''entirely jocular.''</p>
        <p>But there is nothing jocular about Mr. Reilly's lawsuit. The Chronicle itself, in a recent reconstruction of the star-crossed sale, called Mr. Reilly ''a wild card slipped into the deck'' after all other obstacles to sale seemed to be overcome. He remains the lone opponent to the deal, now that Hearst, succumbing to Justice Department pressure, found a buyer willing to keep The Examiner running and keep San Francisco a two-newspaper town.</p>
        <p>The Examiner, an afternoon paper whose 102,000 circulation is less than one-fourth that of The Chronicle's, which is about 465,000, has remained financially viable only because of the profit-sharing arrangement that is part of the joint operating agreement between the two papers, an agreement set to end when Hearst completes its deal to buy The Chronicle from the Chronicle Publishing Company.</p>
        <p>After the Justice Department made it clear that a sale of The Examiner was essential before it would consider approving Hearst's purchase of The Chronicle, Hearst announced in March that it was selling The Examiner to Ted Fang, a politically well-connected supporter of Mayor Brown and the publisher of a group of neighborhood newspapers. Hearst is providing Mr. Fang with $66 million over the course of three years to keep The Examiner going.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, whose bid to buy The Examiner was rejected, is now trying to convince Judge Vaughn R. Walker of United States District Court in San Francisco that the sale is a sham and that The Examiner cannot survive under Mr. Fang's stewardship. Still to testify in the trial are Mr. Fang, Mr. Reilly and Hearst's president and chief executive, Frank A. Bennack Jr.</p>
        <p>''This is like a soap opera, except it's real life,'' said Tom Ammiano, the president of the city's Board of Supervisors who was a candidate for mayor last fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ammiano added, facetiously: ''Do we want a two-newspaper town? Maybe we should have a no-newspaper town. I'm joking, but people feel the public trust has been betrayed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
