<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Derby Pick Gets Post 16 in Field of 20</title>
    <meta content="04RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D81E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Derby Pick Gets Post 16 in Field of 20</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky., May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A full field of 20 horses was entered today in the 126th Kentucky Derby on Saturday, with Fusaichi Pegasus starting from the 16th stall in the outside auxiliary gate and ranked as the 9-5 favorite.</p>
        <p>''It should keep him out of trouble,'' said Neil Drysdale, who trains the star for the Japanese venture capitalist Fusai Sekiguchi. ''The other spots give you a long time to stand in the gate. So, why wait?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A full field of 20 horses was entered today in the 126th Kentucky Derby on Saturday, with Fusaichi Pegasus starting from the 16th stall in the outside auxiliary gate and ranked as the 9-5 favorite.</p>
        <p>''It should keep him out of trouble,'' said Neil Drysdale, who trains the star for the Japanese venture capitalist Fusai Sekiguchi. ''The other spots give you a long time to stand in the gate. So, why wait?''</p>
        <p>The second choice, The Deputy, trained by Jenine Sahadi, will start from the 11th slot at 4-1. And D. Wayne Lukas, who has won the Derby four times, selected three positions near the outside: No. 13 for Commendable, No. 17 for Exchange Rate and No. 18 for High Yield, winner of the Fountain of Youth Stakes and the Blue Grass and the third choice for the Derby at 5-1.</p>
        <p>Outside post positions were favored for several of the most highly rated horses in the Derby as part of an evolving strategy for the mile-and-a-quarter race, since maximum fields of 20 tend to create traffic jams near the rail that often determine the outcome.</p>
        <p>Historically, the inside or rail position has produced the most winners, 12 in all; the outside slots, the fewest. But even with two starting gates in use, 14 horses starting in the main gate and 6 in the auxiliary, trainers tend now to favor the less cluttered outside.</p>
        <p>Three of the last five runnings of the Derby have been won by horses who started in the auxiliary gate. Last year, Charismatic broke from the 16th slot and Menifee, who finished second, started from No. 18.</p>
        <p>''Each time we won it,'' Lukas said, ''we had to agonize over the draw. But we found that, more important than where you start, is which horses start next to you.''</p>
        <p>Barry Irwin, one of the owners of The Deputy, agreed. He reported that once Fusaichi Pegasus had drawn the 16th spot, the people directing strategy for The Deputy changed their minds.</p>
        <p>''We thought about taking No. 17,'' Irwin said, ''but instead of getting next to a keg of dynamite. we decided to go inside of him and took No. 11.''</p>
        <p>Todd Pletcher, making his first appearance as a trainer in the Derby, entered all four of his candidates and spread his post positions this way: No. 6 for the undefeated speed horse Trippi, No. 10 for More Than Ready, No. 14 for Graeme Hall and No. 15 for Impeachment. He, too, admitted that some strategy had prompted his picks.</p>
        <p>''More Than Ready won't have to stand in the gate too long,'' he said, ''and Graeme Hall has extra space because he's at the end of the main gate and there's more room between that spot and the auxiliary gate.''</p>
        <p>The draw was conducted in two tiers: First, an order of selection was established by lot. Then, according to the order of selection, post positions were chosen. The first pick went to Bob Baffert, who has won the Derby twice in the last three years but who has become a kind of lonesome man this year. He selected the No. 8 stall in the center of the pack for his horse, Captain Steve, who was made the fifth choice at early odds of 8-1.</p>
        <p>Pletcher, with his team of four starters, is a former assistant to Lukas, who saddled five horses in the 1996 Derby and who won with Charismatic last year. When Lukas was asked if he had any advice for his onetime pupil, he replied with a straight face: ''I told him it was a big job, and he should scratch three.''</p>
        <p>The full field meant there was no room for Unshaded, who won the Lexington Stakes but was never nominated for the Kentucky Derby, His trainer, Carl Nafzger, has been training the colt at Churchill Downs in case the owner, James Tafel, was willing to put up the supplemental fee of $150,000 to enter his horse, and if the field fell short of the maximum of 20 horses, all of whom would get preference. But when Ronton was confirmed as a starter, Unshaded was blocked out.</p>
        <p>Another candidate who dropped out of the Derby was Harlan Traveler, third in the Lexington and third in the Swale. The decision was left to the colt's trainer, Ray Lawrence Jr., who decided this morning that Harlan Traveler simply didn't have enough seasoning.</p>
        <p>''I'm behind the 8-ball with him,'' Lawrence acknowledged. ''I just don't have enough into him. This race is plenty tough if you've got all your ducks lined up. But when you're trying to play catch-up, it's just about impossible. I look at this race and I see five or six horses I know we can't beat right now, so what are we running for?''</p>
        <p>Harlan Traveler's defection opened a slot for Curule, a second runner for the Godolphin stable from the Middle East, who will join China Visit among the 20 starters. Curule has raced only four times, all four in Dubai, with one victory. But the trainer, Saeed bin Suroor, who saddled Worldly Manner in the Derby (seventh last year), expressed satisfaction with both colts' workouts.</p>
        <p>China Visit held his final workout this morning, going five furlongs in 1:012/5 . Curule arrived Tuesday, cantered this morning and will gallop up to the Derby.</p>
        <p>The invaders are a continuing part of the strategy of Sheik Mohammed al-Maktoum of Dubai to extend his racing empire internationally.</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>The rider on China Visit will be FRANKIE DETTORI, while the jockey on Curule will be MARLON ST. JULIEN. And, according to the Churchill Downs records, St. Julien will be the first African-American rider in the Derby since Henry King in 1921. St. Julien comes from Louisiana, made his reputation at Texas tracks and recently has had two smashing seasons at Keeneland. In the early years of the Kentucky Derby, black jockeys predominated, winning 15 of the first 28 runnings. And 13 of the 15 horses in the inaugural Derby in 1875 were ridden by black jockeys.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
