<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cruelty of Childhood Returns to Haunt Adults</title>
    <meta content="080357SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A.O.</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Spin the Bottle (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DA103AF937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cruelty of Childhood Returns to Haunt Adults</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A.O.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Spin the Bottle'' takes place in and around a creaky, isolated lakefront house somewhere in the wilds of Vermont. Four childhood friends, now in their late 20's, have been summoned to this lonely spot by another old acquaintance, a mysterious fellow named Jonah (Holter Graham), whom none of them have seen in more than a decade and who suffered hurt and humiliation at their thoughtless young hands.</p>
        <p>You may think you know where this is going, and nothing would make me happier than to report that Jonah responds to this ''Friday the 13th''-style setup by dispatching his erstwhile tormenters, one by one, using the most gruesome cinematic means at his disposal. But instead Jonah takes his revenge by setting in motion a series of cat-and-mouse sexual mind games designed to humiliate his guests, who are in the neighborhood for a wedding, and to expose their hang-ups and hypocrisies. The movie would have been shorter, more entertaining and a richer source of insight into human psychology if he had simply cut them into pieces with a chain saw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Spin the Bottle'' takes place in and around a creaky, isolated lakefront house somewhere in the wilds of Vermont. Four childhood friends, now in their late 20's, have been summoned to this lonely spot by another old acquaintance, a mysterious fellow named Jonah (Holter Graham), whom none of them have seen in more than a decade and who suffered hurt and humiliation at their thoughtless young hands.</p>
        <p>You may think you know where this is going, and nothing would make me happier than to report that Jonah responds to this ''Friday the 13th''-style setup by dispatching his erstwhile tormenters, one by one, using the most gruesome cinematic means at his disposal. But instead Jonah takes his revenge by setting in motion a series of cat-and-mouse sexual mind games designed to humiliate his guests, who are in the neighborhood for a wedding, and to expose their hang-ups and hypocrisies. The movie would have been shorter, more entertaining and a richer source of insight into human psychology if he had simply cut them into pieces with a chain saw.</p>
        <p>''Spin the Bottle,'' which was completed in 1997 and is now, for some reason, playing at the Two Boots Pioneer Theater, is certainly gruesome (though not graphic) but hardly cinematic. The Vermont wilderness is pretty enough, and the moon looks lonesome shining through the trees, but the director Jamie Yerkes has nothing much to do besides watch people talk. And what they say, thanks to a script by Amy Sohn, a novelist and former sex columnist for The New York Press, consists of exchanges like this:</p>
        <p>''I don't believe in betrayal.''</p>
        <p>''I'll believe enough for the both of us.''</p>
        <p>''The road to ultimate human tranquillity is not paved with the hands of good girlfriends.''</p>
        <p>Jonah and his pals are meant to be, I guess, a sampling of the jaded, overprivileged generation now facing the complications of adulthood. Ted (Mitchell Riggs) is engaged to Bev (Kim Winter), though he is plagued with doubts about his commitment to monogamy and his law school career. Alex (Jessica Faller), the ensemble's designated slut, exploits these doubts by flirting shamelessly with Ted, while Rachel (Heather Goldenhersh), the one with low self-esteem, whines about the man who dumped her.</p>
        <p>Into this nest of seething insecurity comes Jonah, who we know to be a dangerous, ambiguous sexual dynamo because he wears a sheepskin vest with no shirt underneath and has pierced ears and nose.</p>
        <p>The film turns, as you may have surmised, on a midnight game of spin the bottle, after which Jonah has sex with two visitors. I won't reveal which ones, because you couldn't possibly care. The poor actors arch their brows and enunciate their lame witticisms as if they were performing Noel Coward, or else rage and parry as if auditioning for an imported-beer commercial loosely based on ''Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?'' Perhaps the characters are meant to remind you of people you know, but if that's the case, they are people you would do everything in your power to avoid, on screen or off.</p>
        <p>SPIN THE BOTTLE</p>
        <p>Directed by Jamie Yerkes; written by Amy Sohn; director of photography, Harlan Bosmajian; produced by Ms. Yerkes and Kris Hornsher; released by CineBlast! Productions. At the Two Boots Pioneer Theater, 155 East Third Street, East Village. Running time: 86 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mitchell Riggs (Ted), Kim Winter (Bev), Jessica Faller (Alex), Heather Goldenhersh (Rachel) and Holter Graham (Jonah).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
