<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proposal to Shake Up the Primaries Is Met With Scrutiny and Skepticism</title>
    <meta content="Y04ELEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN PLAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E7D81E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proposal to Shake Up the Primaries Is Met With Scrutiny and Skepticism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Republican leaders proposed scrapping the current presidential nominating system, they immediately confronted a series of questions, ranging from their motives to their chance of success to whether their new idea would work as they hoped -- or at least work better than the system they wanted to replace.</p>
        <p>The proposal, unveiled Tuesday, would start the primaries with the nation's smallest states, plus the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico and three tiny American territories. They could have primaries no sooner than the first Tuesday in March. Slightly bigger states could go in April, medium-size states in May, and big states in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Republican leaders proposed scrapping the current presidential nominating system, they immediately confronted a series of questions, ranging from their motives to their chance of success to whether their new idea would work as they hoped -- or at least work better than the system they wanted to replace.</p>
        <p>The proposal, unveiled Tuesday, would start the primaries with the nation's smallest states, plus the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico and three tiny American territories. They could have primaries no sooner than the first Tuesday in March. Slightly bigger states could go in April, medium-size states in May, and big states in June.</p>
        <p>As outlined by the former senator and Republican Party chairman Bill Brock, the plan seeks to maintain and deepen the public's sense of having a role in the choice of nominees by maintaining competitive races through June, when nearly half the delegates would be chosen. Mr. Brock also hopes the plan would make it somewhat easier for underfinanced candidates to make an impact by keeping the early stages of the race cheap.</p>
        <p>While many Democrats, instinctively assuming deviousness, were trying today to figure out how the scheme would give the Republicans an advantage, they could not find a lever.</p>
        <p>Unless the plan suddenly attracts public interest and support, a truly remote possibility, there is nothing in it to benefit the Republicans over the Democrats. Indeed the burden of making some politicians mad -- and Californians are already in a snit over the idea of their primary being pushed back to June -- falls only on the Republicans. Democrats can sit back and see what happens.</p>
        <p>As to the likelihood of success, Republicans can probably get this plan past their rules committee, on which territories and small states have one vote each, just like California.</p>
        <p>But they could have a difficult time at their convention, where the big states pushed back to June have more votes. After that, they would try to make some post-election deal with the Democrats and try pushing the states to change their primary dates. In sum, a very difficult task.</p>
        <p>But would it work? Previous efforts to change the system have not always succeeded as the sponsors had hoped. Some failed immediately. In 1988, for instance, Southern Democrats' effort to exert conservative influence by grouping their primaries on what became known as Super Tuesday failed, giving more aid to two liberal candidates, Michael S. Dukakis and Jesse Jackson, than their favorite son, Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Others fail over time, like the 1974 Federal Election Campaign Act, which ensured clean presidential races until the accountants figured out soft money in 1988 and perfected it in 1992.</p>
        <p>Two operational problems stand out. Nelson Polsby, a political scientist at the University of California at Berkeley, said the news media would thwart the plan by continuing to declare winners on the basis of the early primaries. News organizations, he said, ''legitimately report early results and these early results influence later results.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Patterson, a Harvard political scientist, said he thought the first time a bunch of primaries came on the same day, the results would be covered as if they were decisive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brock disagreed. ''The press is composed of human beings, and they very much like a contest, and that makes news.'' If the contest lasted until the third group of states, in May, ''the odds of anyone having mathematical certainty are zero,'' he said. ''I think people would be very careful until the big states are heard from.''</p>
        <p>Another major problem would be money. One dirty little secret of the present system is that while it schedules primaries from January until June, the federal matching grant system does not provide money for a primary contest that lasts beyond April, when recent races have been over. Even the wealthy Bush campaign, which rejected public funding to avoid donation limits, would be flat broke if it were still buying television time today.</p>
        <p>Bob Shrum, a veteran Democratic consultant now working for Vice President Gore, said that ''for people who are relying on public funding, it would be a huge problem.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''People spend early to try to get a knockout. They would run out of gas.''</p>
        <p>Former Gov. Lamar Alexander of Tennessee, an early dropout from this year's Republican race, said a stretched-out calendar would help lesser-known candidates, but the goals would not be reached with the current $1,000 limit on campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>''I don't know where we ever got the idea that it takes money to put out The New York Times, and invade Normandy and to build New York University -- but not to run for president,'' Mr. Alexander said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brock said his critics were right -- ''if people acted as they do now.'' He said if candidates prepared for a long haul, they would spend more carefully.</p>
        <p>He said that would give ''lesser-known candidates a chance to stay in, which is very much a part of our purpose.'' But, he said, ''maybe this will force us to address the insanity of present campaign laws which promote the importance of money over issues.''</p>
        <p>Darrell West, a political scientist at Brown University, suggested that even without more money, the Brock system could work if it forced candidates to reach voters in ways other than television advertisements, by emphasizing debates, the Internet and personal campaigning.</p>
        <p>Even skeptics like Mr. Alexander said the proposed system would be ''much better than the crammed-up primaries we have today.'' Professor Polsby said ''it might shift the front load to middle front load.'' And Mr. Brock said: ''There is no perfect system. We're trying to improve the present system. We don't say this is nirvana.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN PLAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
