<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico's Biggest Bank Enters Contest to Acquire No. 2</title>
    <meta content="Y04BAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D81E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico's Biggest Bank Enters Contest to Acquire No. 2</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mexico's largest financial group, Banacci, said today that it had begun merger talks with Bancomer, the country's second-largest financial group, raising questions about the anticipated takeover of Bancomer by a Spanish financial group.</p>
        <p>The financial group that would result if the two Mexican groups were to merge would be Latin America's largest, with more than 11 million customers and nearly $60 billion in assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mexico's largest financial group, Banacci, said today that it had begun merger talks with Bancomer, the country's second-largest financial group, raising questions about the anticipated takeover of Bancomer by a Spanish financial group.</p>
        <p>The financial group that would result if the two Mexican groups were to merge would be Latin America's largest, with more than 11 million customers and nearly $60 billion in assets.</p>
        <p>''This is not an attempt at a hostile takeover,'' Manuel Medina Mora, Banacci's chief executive, said at a news conference. ''It's an unsolicited offer, certainly, but by no means an unfriendly one.''</p>
        <p>At Bancomer, a spokesman acknowledged that Bancomer executives had received Banacci's proposal today and were studying it. ''Our board will decide now what's most beneficial to shareholders,'' the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The proposal stunned Mexico's banking world, coming amid merger  talks between Bancomer and the Spanish financial group, Banco Bilbao Vizcaya Argentaria S.A., known as BBVA. When the Spanish group proposed to merge with Bancomer in March, many analysts presumed that the deal would succeed.</p>
        <p>Analysts noted that a year ago, Bancomer was ailing, with a portfolio of nonperforming loans slowing operations there, as at most of the nation's 37 banks. ''For Bancomer, this is an amazing turnaround,'' said Ursula Wilhelm, a director at Standard &amp; Poor's in Mexico City. ''It's dramatic to see how quickly the outlook is changing for the entire banking system.''</p>
        <p>One of the motives behind the Banacci proposal was to block the Spanish group from making further inroads in Mexico's financial industry, said a Banacci executive who explained the arrangement.</p>
        <p>''This is the best way to defend the domestic market,'' the executive said. ''We're just taking the offense instead of the defense.''</p>
        <p>In March, Grupo Financiero Banamex Accival, known as Banacci, had $29 billion in assets, while Grupo Financiero Bancomer, had $28 billion in assets. Banamex, the bank that is Banacci's main business, is Mexico's largest.</p>
        <p>To carry out the merger, the two financial groups would undertake a stock swap, a transaction that would yield an ownership split of 65 percent for Banacci shareholders and 35 percent for Bancomer shareholders in a new, still unnamed, financial company according to the Banamex proposal. The proposal was explained in a four-page statement issued by Banacci today.</p>
        <p>The giant company resulting from the merger would raise $2.4 billion in new capital, most of which would be used to put Bancomer on a sound financial footing by covering the bank's portfolio of nonpaying debts, the Banacci statement said.</p>
        <p>The $2.4 billion in new capital would be raised from several sources, the statement said. About $1 billion would come from sales of redundant assets at the two banks and $300 million from Aegon N.V., a Dutch insurance company that is Banacci's partner in a pension management company. The new company would raise $500 million by issuing new shares of common stock, and $600 million by issuing up to $600 million in nonconvertible capital securities, the statement said.</p>
        <p>Both the BBVA merger proposal and the Banacci proposal are subject to the approvals, first of the shareholders at the companies involved and then of the Mexican banking authorities. The BBVA proposal would also be subject to approval of Spanish regulatory officials.</p>
        <p>A Banacci-Bancomer merger would involve a delicate marriage of two banking companies that have long been rivals. The president of Banacci, Roberto Hernandez, is a hard-driving financier who bought Banamex when it was privatized during the presidency of Carlos Salinas de Gortari. He is a close friend of President Ernesto Zedillo. Mr. Hernandez's No. 2 is Alfredo Harp Helu, another Mexican financial titan.</p>
        <p>The largest shareholders in the Bancomer group are members of the Monterrey-based Garza Laguera family. Bancomer's board president since October has been Ricardo Guajardo Touche, an engineer from Monterrey.</p>
        <p>The merger proposed by Banacci would unseat dozens of executives appointed by the Garza Laguera family. Banacci proposed a 15-member board for the new financial giant, with nine members coming from Banacci management and six members from Bancomer.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
