<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; 'Th-Th-That's All, Folks!'</title>
    <meta content="04SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DA1E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; 'Th-Th-That's All, Folks!'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''When elephants fight,'' goes the African proverb, ''it is the grass that suffers.''</p>
        <p>When the cable operator Time Warner blacked out the programs provided by filmmaker and broadcaster ABC-Disney, millions of viewers were denied what they had come to expect on their screens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''When elephants fight,'' goes the African proverb, ''it is the grass that suffers.''</p>
        <p>When the cable operator Time Warner blacked out the programs provided by filmmaker and broadcaster ABC-Disney, millions of viewers were denied what they had come to expect on their screens.</p>
        <p>Loss of the entertainment was merely an annoyance, but the shutdown of any major news outlet is a kick in the head to the public interest. Time should no more have the power to force ABC News off the screen than ABC should have the power to block delivery of Time magazine.</p>
        <p>Newspaper wars are nothing new; the egos of James Gordon Bennett and William Randolph Hearst in past centuries are legendary. But now the news has become a casualty of warring entertainment and information empires, and the conflict has escalated from one locality to the globe.</p>
        <p>For a decade, ambitious titans assured us that media mergers were the wave of the future. We were told that only by concentrating communications in multinational behemoths could U.S. companies compete with monopolies in Europe and Asia. Size guaranteed efficiency and the consumer could look forward to lower cost and better service.</p>
        <p>Baloney. Mere size is no synergy. With all-consuming conglomeration comes huge investment risk and, as we saw this week, unbridled arrogance. To those lusting after world communications domination, the game is not to win customers but to destroy competitors, leaving the losers to think about the ravages of giantism: cogito; ergo zero sum.</p>
        <p>We are too quick to take for granted  federal approval this fall of the amalgamation of Time Warner with America Online. That would carry into the future the mistake we make today of marrying the creation of content to the transmission of signal.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, a nail-nibbling Federal Communications Commission solemnly declared that it would rap knuckles at Time Warner because present rules say that ''no deletion of a local commercial television station shall occur during a sweeps period,'' when ratings are used to set advertising rates. Thanks a bunch, F.C.C.; that ruling means that such ''deletion'' is O.K. at all other times.</p>
        <p>On the same day, the same F.C.C. approved the purchase of broadcaster CBS by Viacom. Industry insiders expect the same financial exploitation of a device called ''retransmission consent'' being used by ABC-Disney. That would provoke the same superdog-eat-superdog response against ''CBS News With Dan Rather'' by cable powers that shut out ''ABC News With Peter Jennings'' to millions of people for a day and a half.</p>
        <p>What's to stop this trampling of the grasses of the masses by the elephantine corporate combatants?</p>
        <p>Not Congress; ignoring Senator John McCain's warnings, it has been rolling over regularly, giving the broadcasting and cable lobbies all they demand (except when they disagree) lest local stations support opponents of elected officials.</p>
        <p>Not the regulatory agencies. In approving mergers beyond the communications world, the Federal Trade Commission seems to have bought the bill of goods being sold by gurus of globalization that enormity will be the norm.</p>
        <p>Conservatives do not suggest that government regulation of more monopolies and semi-monopolies is the answer; bureaucrats in Washington have a poor record of running large enterprises.</p>
        <p>Advocates of megamergers have been saying that only giants can compete with giants. But to let the behemoths fight it out until one becomes a monopoly is just another road to regulation.</p>
        <p>The answer is vigorous antitrust prevention and enforcement. Do trustbusters at Justice have their hands too full with Microsoft to look hard at the plans of AT&amp;T and MediaOne or MCI-Worldcom-Sprint? Then the times require that we hire more trustbusters.</p>
        <p>We should say no to more megamergers before they take place -- and before having to begin painful corporate divorce proceedings.</p>
        <p>This week's blackout is no jousting between Time Warner's Porky Pig and Disney's Mickey Mouse for the entertainment dollar. Concentration of power over what we see in the news -- and even if we see a competitor's news -- is a danger to democracy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
