<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton Calls On Giuliani To Reject Independence Party</title>
    <meta content="04HILL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E5DC1F39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton Calls On Giuliani To Reject Independence Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <dateline>FORT EDWARD, N.Y., May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton called on Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani today to reject the nomination of the Independence Party if the organization nominates Patrick J. Buchanan to run for president.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton again attacked Mr. Buchanan for making what she described as bigoted and anti-Semitic statements. The first lady, without mentioning Mr. Giuliani by name, said that her Republican opponent in the race for the United States Senate should decline to run on the Independence Party line if Mr. Buchanan is at the top of the ticket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton called on Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani today to reject the nomination of the Independence Party if the organization nominates Patrick J. Buchanan to run for president.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton again attacked Mr. Buchanan for making what she described as bigoted and anti-Semitic statements. The first lady, without mentioning Mr. Giuliani by name, said that her Republican opponent in the race for the United States Senate should decline to run on the Independence Party line if Mr. Buchanan is at the top of the ticket.</p>
        <p>''I would not run on a ballot with him,'' Mrs. Clinton said at a news conference here as she traveled through the Adirondacks. ''And I think that is the position that anyone who wants to represent all of New York and all New Yorkers should be taking.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani has in the past attacked Mr. Buchanan, though he stopped short, on an appearance last night on MSNBC, of saying he would not accept the support of the Independence Party if it endorsed Mr. Buchanan as its presidential candidate. Mr. Giuliani's aides have been pushing to win the Independence Party endorsement, in the belief that it could provide Mr. Giuliani an important source of votes in what is expected to be a close election. The Independence Party is the New York arm of the Reform Party.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I could do that, but I'm hoping they don't do that,'' Mr. Giuliani said at the prospect of running on the same ticket as Mr. Buchanan. ''I'm hoping they make some other choice. I think it's a very important party; the Independence Party is a very important party.''</p>
        <p>''If they ended up doing that,'' Mr. Giuliani added, ''then I'd have to think long and hard about it. I probably wouldn't want to be on that ticket.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton attacked Mr. Buchanan, the conservative commentator, eagerly at her news conference today after he attacked her on Tuesday, while praising Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton made her comments at the start of a two-day sweep into the Adirondacks and the Republican heart of upstate New York.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who moved to New York in January, sounded almost like a tourist promoter as she recounted her travels through the state, learning about local issues and history.</p>
        <p>''I am finding that as I talk about it, more New Yorkers are saying, I didn't know that; I had no idea that was going on in the north country or western New York,'' she said. ''I am hoping not only will I have a very firm grounding in what goes on all over the state but that more New Yorkers will learn about the history.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
