<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You Kibitz, Can You Spot the Pros and Amateurs?</title>
    <meta content="04CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2D91139F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You Kibitz, Can You Spot the Pros and Amateurs?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suppose that you are an experienced player and you wander into Honors Club in Manhattan while a pro-am event is in progress. Each of the 58 partnerships consists of one expert, perhaps a national champion, and one relatively inexperienced player, perhaps a near-beginner. If you sit and kibitz at a table with four players you do not know, you should quickly be able to determine which two players are the experts.</p>
        <p>Test your expert-spotting ability on the diagramed deal, remembering that this is a match-point game in which overtricks are crucial. After an opening bid of one diamond, South overcalls one no-trump. Since South has a double stopper in diamonds, this is rather better than a routine overcall in hearts. It describes the hand accurately, and the concealment of the heart suit may have an impact on the play. It also makes life easy for North, who passes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suppose that you are an experienced player and you wander into Honors Club in Manhattan while a pro-am event is in progress. Each of the 58 partnerships consists of one expert, perhaps a national champion, and one relatively inexperienced player, perhaps a near-beginner. If you sit and kibitz at a table with four players you do not know, you should quickly be able to determine which two players are the experts.</p>
        <p>Test your expert-spotting ability on the diagramed deal, remembering that this is a match-point game in which overtricks are crucial. After an opening bid of one diamond, South overcalls one no-trump. Since South has a double stopper in diamonds, this is rather better than a routine overcall in hearts. It describes the hand accurately, and the concealment of the heart suit may have an impact on the play. It also makes life easy for North, who passes.</p>
        <p>At many other tables South plays in two hearts and usually emerges with nine tricks. How will one no-trump fare? The choice of opening lead is a close decision, and a diamond lead would turn out quite well for the defense. But West leads a spade, as many would, and the queen and king are played.</p>
        <p>Now South makes a good move by allowing the king to win. No other suit represents a threat, and the hold-up makes it much less likely that West will be able to use his spade suit. East decides that spades are hopeless, and leads the heart king. Since West's 10 looks like a signal, the ace comes next and the appearance of the jack is a serious disappointment.</p>
        <p>All this makes South very, very happy. East shifts to a club, and West allows the king to win. South continues with the queen, and, as hoped, West holds up again, trying to shut out dummy's clubs. But holding up an honor in a black suit does not work as well for the defense as it does for the declarer. After cashing three heart winners, South takes two spade winners and the diamond king. Since East must have something for his opening bid, the diamond finesse is taken at the 12th trick. Making 10 tricks for a score of 180 is a clear top score for North-South.</p>
        <p>So who was who? Among the defenders, West was the expert and East was the inexperienced player, although that is not entirely obvious. It may seem clear to you that South, who did everything just right, is the expert.</p>
        <p>But not so. South, Reene Schisgall of Manhattan, was an Am who was playing like a Pro. She is a newcomer to duplicate but won the event on Sunday with Elliott Grubman, who scored his second victory in three years. All he contributed to the good result on this deal was some post-mortem admiration.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
