<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Would A Breakup Matter?</title>
    <meta content="04PETE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/State of the Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4D61139F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Would A Breakup Matter?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Proposed Final Judgment in the case of the United States v. Microsoft Corporation is on the Internet at www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/ms</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Proposed Final Judgment in the case of the United States v. Microsoft Corporation is on the Internet at www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/ms</p>
        <p>As if you haven't already read or heard enough about the proposal to cleave Microsoft, you can follow the link and view the document in one of three formats: in Hypertext Markup Language (HTML), which requires a standard Web browser; in Adobe's Portable Document Format (PDF), which requires a free program called Acrobat Reader; or as a WordPerfect document (WPD), which requires any word processing program that can read WordPerfect files. Besides the government's petulance in not making the document available in the popular Microsoft Word's .doc format, what do you notice?</p>
        <p>The operating system does not matter. HTML is the common language of the Web, and it is operating system-agnostic. Adobe Reader can handle 13 different operating systems, including Windows, Macintosh, OS/2, Unix and Linux, and 14 different languages.</p>
        <p>The operating system is just the dial tone that you need to make a call to the Internet. Just as any phone company can provide the dial tone for a telephone these days, any company -- not just Microsoft -- can provide the operating system for an Internet-connected device.</p>
        <p>In other words, Windows is not a requirement to use the Internet. And that worries Microsoft far more than the dubious proposal made last week by the Justice Department and 17 states to break up the company into two companies. One would be based on operating systems, and the other would be based on a gaggle of applications that include Microsoft Office, Internet Explorer, the MSN network and the Microsoft Mouse.</p>
        <p>Technology is moving so fast that by the time this legal mess is resolved, consumers may not even notice or care whether Microsoft is one company, two, or 57. The Internet, not the desktop computer, is becoming the center of power. Consumers will routinely tap into the Internet not just from personal computers, but from a variety of devices, including smart phones, handheld computers, Internet appliances, Web pads, television sets, A.T.M. machines and automobile dashboards.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has no monopoly in this world of Internet-enabled devices, and almost no chance of creating a monopoly even if it ultimately wins its court case. When people decide to go online to read the latest headlines, check their e-mail or trade stocks, chances are that they do not pause to consider their operating systems. They may think ''AOL'' or ''WebTV'' or even ''browser,'' but when it comes down to it, I suspect that most people do not care whether their Internet access devices are powered by Windows, Linux, BeOS, America Online, Sprint, DoCoMo, Palm OS, Java, Odwalla juice or hamsters on a treadmill.</p>
        <p>Macintosh users are a special case. They care passionately about the Mac OS and would rewire their own bodies to run on Mac OS X if such a thing were possible. But for most other people, the operating system is about as significant in their daily lives as the plumbing system.</p>
        <p>In no way is this argument intended to diminish the findings that Microsoft violated Federal and state antitrust laws through its predatory behavior, which in turn was fostered by its Windows monopoly. A lot of people lost jobs and money when Microsoft unfairly bullied rival companies out of the market.</p>
        <p>Nor does it suggest that personal computers are on the wane. PC sales have never been more robust, in fact. Microsoft still puts its plumbing in more than 90 percent of all new desktops and laptops. When the PC first emerged as an alternative to big, expensive mainframe computers, I compared it to the small mammals that eventually inherited the world from the dinosaurs. Is the PC now itself a dinosaur? No way. But insects outnumber even the mammals, and cell phones outsell desktop computers by a big margin. In several countries, cell phones outsell even regular phones. Phones that surf the Web and handle e-mail are just around the corner, and Microsoft has the wrong number.</p>
        <p>There has been a lot of conjecture about what impact the proposed breakup of Microsoft would have on people who use personal computers.</p>
        <p>First, Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson is under no obligation to accept the proposed remedy. He may decide that disintegrating Microsoft is a fundamentally dumb idea, given that the integration of new features into software, and the integration of one piece of software with another, is the goal of every other company in the industry. He may decide instead to fine Microsoft several bazillion dollars for making annoying software. (If I were judge, I'd fine them a billion dollars just for trying to foist Microsoft Bob on an unsuspecting public. And I'd fine them another billion for that silly ''Where Do You Want to Go Today?'' marketing tag.)</p>
        <p>Second, Microsoft will appeal whatever remedy the judge proposes, with all the legal firepower at its disposal. A higher court could reverse Judge Jackson's ruling. Meanwhile, the breakup order will be stayed until all appeals are concluded, which could take a couple of years. If you think it takes a long time for Windows 98 to boot up and shut down, just wait until you see the Windows appeals process.</p>
        <p>Third, the appeals could extend well past the election of a new administration, and a new attorney general might be more inclined to settle the case instead of pursuing a breakup, even though the state cases could remain active.</p>
        <p>''I'd say the chances of Microsoft being broken up are zero,'' said Mark R. Anderson, author of the influential Strategic News Service newsletter (www.stratnews.com), which has an admirable track record for technology forecasts.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's president, Steven Ballmer, vows that the company will never be broken up. In a letter published in newspaper ads earlier this week, Mr. Ballmer wrote that the proposed remedy would ''send a signal that companies in America that are 'too' successful will be punished harshly -- a signal that will be welcomed by foreign competitors seeking to overtake America's global leadership in technology.''</p>
        <p>In other words, a half-century after General Motors made the same arrogant argument, Microsoft is saying that what's good for Microsoft is good for America.</p>
        <p>In hindsight, Japanese carmakers clobbered General Motors in the 1970's and 1980's, not because G.M. was hamstrung by unreasonable government regulations, but because it failed to react to the changing market caused by the demand for smaller, less expensive and more fuel-efficient cars. Today you may be driving a car made by a company you had never heard of a decade ago.</p>
        <p>The software market is now in a corresponding upheaval because of  the rising demand for access to the Internet through small, inexpensive devices. A few years from now, you may be connecting to the Internet using software from companies that you don't hear much about today.</p>
        <p>Years ago, the dial tone was always provided by AT&amp;T. Today there is so much competition that obnoxious calls from phone companies are as much a part of the dinner hour as family conversation.</p>
        <p>As recently as 1987, there was an opportunity for companies besides Microsoft to dominate the market for personal computer operating systems. Apple's Mac OS was at its peak, and I.B.M.'s OS/2 was superior to Windows in many ways. But both Apple and I.B.M. blundered, and Microsoft seized power.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's monopoly on personal computer operating systems seems bulletproof, even in the unlikely event that the government succeeds in its plan to give the software giant a lobotomy, separating the left-brain lobe (operating systems) from the right-brain lobe (applications). But even without the surgery, Microsoft is in no way assured of dominating the Internet era in the same way it has dominated the PC era.</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
