<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albright Rebukes Diplomats for Security Slips</title>
    <meta content="Y04LAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD91E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albright Rebukes Diplomats for Security Slips</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a fierce speech transmitted around the world, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright today told American diplomats that protecting the nation's secrets was at the core of their mission and warned that enemies abounded even in a post-cold-war world.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright, who said she was furious over both the disappearance of a laptop computer packed with classified information and other recent security lapses at the State Department, summoned more than 800 staff members to the department's auditorium to hear her remarks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a fierce speech transmitted around the world, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright today told American diplomats that protecting the nation's secrets was at the core of their mission and warned that enemies abounded even in a post-cold-war world.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright, who said she was furious over both the disappearance of a laptop computer packed with classified information and other recent security lapses at the State Department, summoned more than 800 staff members to the department's auditorium to hear her remarks.</p>
        <p>The speech was broadcast live on the department's internal television network and beamed by satellite to American missions in dozens of countries.</p>
        <p>''I don't care how skilled you are as a diplomat, how brilliant you may be at meetings, or how creative you are as an administrator,'' Dr. Albright said in stern tones reminiscent of her days as a Georgetown University professor, ''if you are not professional about security, you are a failure.''</p>
        <p>''You may have seen reports indicating that I am furious about these incidents,'' she said. ''Well, I am, and I hope you are, too.''</p>
        <p>Officials said it was the first time a secretary had held a department-wide meeting on security. It came as Dr. Albright's aides were exploring new measures to protect classified materials and guard against espionage.</p>
        <p>Officials said Dr. Albright was embarrassed by the laptop incident, which she learned about through newspaper articles more than two months after the computer was reported missing to State Department security officers by the Bureau of Intelligence and Research.</p>
        <p>The computer's disappearance, which is being investigated by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, was just a month after federal agents found an electronic listening device in a department conference room. A Russian diplomat was expelled after the discovery.</p>
        <p>Republican lawmakers have critcized the breaches. Dr. Albright is scheduled to testify today before the House Select Committee on Intelligence. The chairman of the House Committee on International Relations, Representative Benjamin A. Gilman, Republican of New York, has invited her to a panel next week.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright, who last week announced an overhaul of department security, transferred two officials from Intelligence and Research and stripped that office of its ability to police itself, complained today that she had met resistance from a diplomatic culture that played down the importance of security.</p>
        <p>American diplomats privately acknowledged that they were occasionally cavalier about security. Many said their public profiles required a steady stream of foreign visitors and contacts, unlike many of their colleagues at the Pentagon or the intelligence agencies.</p>
        <p>A diplomat said the department in recent years had ordered a halt to nightly office-by-office security checks by marines -- a training maneuver for marines bound for overseas posts -- because they turned up so many violations, creating a morass of paperwork.</p>
        <p>''Nobody cares about security within the department,'' said the diplomat, who has served three decades at the State Department.</p>
        <p>An interagency group that includes members of the F.B.I., the C.I.A. and the Secret Service is preparing recommendations to improve the department's security. Among the options being considered are closing off two entrances and streets adjacent to the department's headquarters, increasing camera surveillance throughout the facility and limiting the number of electronic building passes, officials said.</p>
        <p>Despite the end of the cold war, Dr. Albright said, the threats to American interests are more varied and less predictable than ever.</p>
        <p>''Spy novelists may be having trouble thinking up plots,'' she said. ''But our nation still has enemies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
