<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Changes in the earned-income tax credit are a success in the effort to fix welfare, but there's room for improvement.</title>
    <meta content="Y04SCEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DB1E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Changes in the earned-income tax credit are a success in the effort to fix welfare, but there's room for improvement.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. Bradford DeLong</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 1990's began with a burst of intellectual and political energy in support of genuine welfare reform. By the beginning of the decade mainstream political opinion had finally coalesced around the idea that the welfare system based on Aid to Families With Dependent Children -- cash payments to nonworking single mothers -- was a failure. Welfare recipients remained very poor, the incentives the system gave them were horrible, and the lessons implicitly taught about responsibility and opportunity were destructive.</p>
        <p>It seemed better, according to the consensus of opinion makers, to make a big push to shift people from welfare to work. The idea was to bolster the wages of low-skilled workers, to provide training programs so that long-term A.F.D.C. recipients could build enough skills to escape the system and to offer job-search assistance so that they could find employers who would pay for those skills. Such an extensive welfare overhaul would be more expensive for the government than would simple cash grants to nonworking single mothers, but to many liberals and conservatives it seemed worth the price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 1990's began with a burst of intellectual and political energy in support of genuine welfare reform. By the beginning of the decade mainstream political opinion had finally coalesced around the idea that the welfare system based on Aid to Families With Dependent Children -- cash payments to nonworking single mothers -- was a failure. Welfare recipients remained very poor, the incentives the system gave them were horrible, and the lessons implicitly taught about responsibility and opportunity were destructive.</p>
        <p>It seemed better, according to the consensus of opinion makers, to make a big push to shift people from welfare to work. The idea was to bolster the wages of low-skilled workers, to provide training programs so that long-term A.F.D.C. recipients could build enough skills to escape the system and to offer job-search assistance so that they could find employers who would pay for those skills. Such an extensive welfare overhaul would be more expensive for the government than would simple cash grants to nonworking single mothers, but to many liberals and conservatives it seemed worth the price.</p>
        <p>The 1996 welfare reform of Newt Gingrich, Bob Dole and Bill Clinton, however, largely dropped the ball. Instead of making a big push on training and job searching, it basically gave each state a blank check -- roughly equal to the money the federal government had formerly spent on welfare -- to spend as it saw fit. A few states have used their money to do remarkable and innovative things. But a lot more have paid lip-service to the goal of reform, and used large chunks of the federal money for programs that the state budget used to pay for, reducing rather than increasing the total amount of money spent to help the poor.</p>
        <p>True, the number of people on welfare has dropped significantly. But in spite of a booming economy, the incomes of the poor have not risen significantly. Very little money has been spent on building skills. Little has been devoted to providing assistance in finding jobs. No one knows but everyone fears what will happen to America's single-parent poor when the boom ends and the next recession begins.</p>
        <p>One piece of the original welfare reform program, however, was quietly put into place in 1993, as part of President Clinton's deficit-reduction program. And unlike the 1996 law, it may prove to be the most enduring and effective antipoverty instrument the federal government has ever devised.</p>
        <p>The instrument is the earned-income tax credit. While already in existence, in 1993 the government significantly expanded the program so that it now gives a family with two children a 40-cent payment from the Internal Revenue Service for every dollar of income earned up to $9,500. A part-time $8-an-hour job thus becomes, after taxes, an $11.20 an hour job for the working poor.</p>
        <p>The tax credit means that a two-child family with a full-time minimum-wage worker is lifted -- just barely -- above the poverty line. Two economists at the Economic Policy Institute (epinet.org), Max Sawicky and Robert Cherry, have found that more than five of six families eligible for the tax credit actually collect it, and that the credit manages to push more families above the poverty line than any other government program.</p>
        <p>Is the earned-income tax credit perfect? No. But, like democracy, it is better than any of the alternatives.</p>
        <p>There are three standard criticisms of the program: It is a subsidy to low-wage employers, and low-wage employers should be discouraged; it penalizes working-class two-earner families; and it is overly bureaucratic and complicated.</p>
        <p>The first criticism seems completely wide of the mark. If we want to raise the wages of the working poor, we want to see a lot of employers competing to hire them. To provide subsidies to employers of low-wage labor is to raise their numbers and so increase the  bargaining power of low-wage workers in the labor market.</p>
        <p>The second criticism has a point. As the income of a two-child family increases from $12,500, to $30,850, it gradually loses its  $3,816 tax credit. When this reduction is combined with the 15.3 percent Social Security wage tax paid by both employee and employer and the payment of income tax at a 15 percent rate, the burden on American families earning $28,000 ends up with them paying the highest marginal federal tax rates of anyone.</p>
        <p>An easy way to make the earned- income tax credit a better program would be to reduce the speed with which the credit is phased out as income rises. But that takes money. Politicians are almost always more excited about seeing their signature on some new initiative than about improving effective but existing programs. Moreover, the political leaders who made the credit their signature initiative -- former Senators Russell Long and Lloyd Bentsen in particular -- are mostly long gone from Washington.</p>
        <p>And the third criticism has a point as well. The earned-income tax credit is a social insurance program administered by the Internal Revenue Service, an agency whose core mission does not involve lifting the incomes of the working poor. Moreover, the tax credit's details are unnecessarily complex: the family as defined by the earned-income tax credit is not necessarily the family as defined by the rest of the tax code, and the income concept that determines whether you qualify for the program is not necessarily the income that appears anywhere else on your tax form.</p>
        <p>But this flaw could be overcome with relatively modest changes. Mr. Cherry and Mr. Sawicky have made a proposal to fix it by simplifying the tax credit and combining it with other child-centered tax provisions into a universal unified child credit.</p>
        <p>Most important of all, even if nothing is done to improve the program right away, the validity of these criticisms should not blot out the tax credit's broad success: $32 billion a year channeled to 15 million working poor and lower-middle-class families to increase their real wages and make work pay.</p>
        <p>I wonder whether the training and skill-building and job-search components of the original 1990's welfare reform dream would now be regarded as equal successes, had they been undertaken, too.</p>
        <p>This column appears here every Thursday. J. Bradford DeLong is a professor of economics at the University of California at Berkeley and co-editor of The Journal of Economic Perspectives. Four economic analysts -- Professor DeLong, Jeff Madrick, Virginia Postrel and Alan B. Krueger -- rotate as contributors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column appears here every Thursday. J. Bradford DeLong is a professor of economics at the University of California at Berkeley and co-editor of The Journal of Economic Perspectives. Four economic analysts -- Professor DeLong, Jeff Madrick, Virginia Postrel and Alan B. Krueger -- rotate as contributors.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
