<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor Acknowledges 'Very Good Friend'</title>
    <meta content="04MAYO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4D61E39F937A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor Acknowledges 'Very Good Friend'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that a woman who has accompanied him on public occasions and has frequently dined with him is ''a good friend, a very good friend.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani made his comments in response to numerous questions from reporters at his daily City Hall briefing. Photographs of the friend, Judith Nathan, were published in yesterday's New York Post.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that a woman who has accompanied him on public occasions and has frequently dined with him is ''a good friend, a very good friend.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani made his comments in response to numerous questions from reporters at his daily City Hall briefing. Photographs of the friend, Judith Nathan, were published in yesterday's New York Post.</p>
        <p>The mayor was straightforward in replying to the questions about Ms. Nathan, but said he was ''annoyed'' by what he indicated was the invasion of Ms. Nathan's private life. ''I am not annoyed for me because this is the job I have and the life I decided to have,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''I am annoyed that people would have invaded the privacy of people who are not in that life and who have not made that choice. But you know, you get used to it and you move on.''</p>
        <p>At one point yesterday, the mayor joked that he could understand journalists' pursuit of public officials. ''You can pursue public officials all you want,'' he said. ''But you should pursue just us. Maybe it comes from my reading of 'The Godfather.' You know, you leave civilians alone.''</p>
        <p>Asked if there was anything more he could say about how his relationship with Ms. Nathan might affect his public life, Mr. Giuliani responded: ''Nope. I have told you everything you need to know or have a right to know about how it affects my public life. I have told you about my health. That affects my public life. There is nothing else you need to know about my public life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani and his wife, Donna Hanover, have led separate public lives since 1996, when Ms. Hanover began more actively pursuing a career in television and film. The two are almost never seen together in public, and he no longer wears his wedding ring.</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Giuliani's announcement last week, Ms. Hanover issued a statement saying she fully supported him and pleading for his privacy. This week she said that she was postponing her appearance in the Off Broadway hit ''The Vagina Monologues'' because of ''personal family circumstances.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan has been seen with Mr. Giuliani at restaurants around the city and at numerous public events, including the Inner Circle dinner, at which reporters perform skits poking fun at the mayor and other elected officials and the mayor returns the barbs at the night's close.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan is single, with a 15-year-old daughter who attends private school on the East Side.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
