<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unsecret Garden Is Tribute to Love</title>
    <meta content="04GARD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Snug Harbor Cultural Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gretz, Connie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grezt, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5D61339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unsecret Garden Is Tribute to Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connie Gretz Secret Garden, in Snug Harbor Cultural Center on Staten Island, was built by Randy Gretz in memory of wife who died in 1996 from cancer; garden includes castle, puppet theater and hedge maze; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After generations on family bookshelves, the tale in Frances Hodgson Burnett's children's book ''The Secret Garden'' is widely familiar: two children, unloved and neglected, find new life in the discovery of an unloved and neglected garden.</p>
        <p>Perhaps as inspirational, but far less familiar, is the tale behind the Connie Gretz Secret Garden, a children's center in the Snug Harbor Cultural Center on Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After generations on family bookshelves, the tale in Frances Hodgson Burnett's children's book ''The Secret Garden'' is widely familiar: two children, unloved and neglected, find new life in the discovery of an unloved and neglected garden.</p>
        <p>Perhaps as inspirational, but far less familiar, is the tale behind the Connie Gretz Secret Garden, a children's center in the Snug Harbor Cultural Center on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Along with her husband, Randy, Connie Gretz had raised two healthy children, and enjoyed a loving marriage, a nice house on Staten Island and an ever-increasing income. A few months before their 25th wedding anniversary, Mrs. Gretz discovered that her stomachache was spindle-cell cancer, very rare and incurable. She died in 1996, at 46, less than two months after the disease was diagnosed.</p>
        <p>Trapped in grief, Mr. Gretz, a stockbroker, was prodded by friends and relatives who wanted him ''to focus on something that wasn't Connie.'' He compromised, and focused on a memorial that would keep her memory alive.</p>
        <p>He cast back to his previous experiences with profound grief, when their first child, John Lawrence, was stillborn and a second pregnancy ended in miscarriage. Since, at the time, it was looking as if they might never have any children, they began talking about creating a children's place, a playground, perhaps, in memory of John Lawrence. Mr. Gretz's brother, Bill, who also lives on Staten Island, suggested creating a secluded garden like the one in the 1911 children's classic.</p>
        <p>''I love that book,'' Mr. Gretz, 52, said. ''It was read to me by my mother, and I read it myself when I was 10. Connie loved it, too, and read it to our kids.''</p>
        <p>With the book in mind, Mr. Gretz constructed the Connie Gretz Secret Garden, a brick-walled center with a fort, a puppet theater and a hedge maze that leads to an enclosed garden similar to the one described in the novel. The garden cost about $750,000; friends contributed about $100,000, and Mr. Gretz, a broker at Merrill Lynch, paid for the rest.</p>
        <p>The tower in the children's garden, made of cinder block, is modeled after one that Mr. Gretz's father, who designed toys for Fisher-Price, made for his sons. It is two stories high, with turrets, a metal spiral staircase and an open roof where parents can watch small children make their way through the maze below, with two circuitous pathways leading to the garden doors. Inside the walls are wide beds of roses and orchids.</p>
        <p>Karen McGee, a neighbor from Staten Island, said the tribute to Mrs. Gretz was fitting. ''She reveled in her children,'' Ms. McGee said. ''Her birthday cakes were always awesome. I remember she went to five stores once to find red shoestring licorice to make strings for the Cookie Monster's balloons. She was utterly unpretentious. She would have been content with a bed of tulips.''</p>
        <p>The plot of the book seems similarly fitting as inspiration for a place built, in part, to ease emotional pain and mark a brighter outlook.</p>
        <p>''It's the story of an Englishman, very wealthy,'' Mr. Gretz said. ''His wife sits on a swing, which snaps and she's killed. They have one son, and they think he's crippled. A little girl, a niece, comes to live with them from India and she finds the boy and says: 'Why don't you get out of bed?' And he says: 'I can't. I can't get up. I can't walk.' The little girl finds the garden, which the boy's father has walled up, and she brings the son out in his wheelchair and with the help of a shepherd boy, he learns to walk. They bring the garden back to life, resplendent, and they bring the father and show him the son he thought was crippled, walking.''</p>
        <p>During the four years it took to design and construct the tower, maze and garden, Mr. Gretz's life and those of his children, Laura, now 16, and Randy Jr., 13, seemed to return to life, too. Mr. Gretz met and married Hannah Judy Gretz, who was divorced and caring for her two teenage children. She said Mr. Gretz's devotion to building a memorial to Connie Gretz was part of what made her love him.</p>
        <p>''The first time I met Randy, I fell madly in love with him because of the way he spoke about Connie -- that he could love so deeply,'' she said. ''I even told my friends that the only man I will ever even talk to is one who had a long and happy marriage whose wife died tragically. I think the garden is a lovely tribute.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gretz said the completion of the children's garden had stilled his grieving. ''It gives me an amazing sense of peace,'' he said. When Hannah asked him how he felt, his reply was: ''Lighter.''</p>
        <p>''I had this desperate sense that somehow Connie would be forgotten,'' he said, as a couple of children who had wound through the maze ducked their heads into the garden. ''Now I know she won't.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
