<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Prize for Reality Is $1 Million. Isn't That Unreal?</title>
    <meta content="04NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boorstin, Daniel J (Prof)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Image, The: Or What Happended to the American Dream? (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Brother (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EED61239F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Prize for Reality Is $1 Million. Isn't That Unreal?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Goodman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman Critic's Notebook on prescient theories of Prof Daniel J Boorstinin light of 'reality television' programs like Survivor and Big Brother; Boorstin, in 1961 book The Image: Or What Happned to the American Dream?, posited that in a society dominated by televison tecniques like 'synthetic novelty' and people 'known for their well-knownness,' authenticity diminishes and citizens come to inhabit a world where fantasy is more real than reality; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a safe guess that few of the millions of young and middle-aged fans of ''Survivor,'' the smash hit CBS specimen of ''reality television,'' have ever heard of Daniel J. Boorstin. Yet the show's arrival certifies Professor Boorstin as a prophet in his time. (Speaking of prophecy, CBS is banking on a second reality series, ''Big Brother,'' which begins tomorrow and continues for five nights a week, to give a further lift to its ratings.)</p>
        <p>It was in 1961 that Mr. Boorstin, then a history professor at the University of Chicago who had won a Bancroft Prize for ''The Americans: The Colonial Experience'' (Random House), came out with a new work. ''The Image: Or What Happened to the American Dream?'' (Atheneum) took aim at the unreality of much that was being marketed as the real stuff of American life. Although the indictment was not entirely original, he applied it broadly and forcefully, in particular to the delivery of ''reality'' in all its dubious forms by television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a safe guess that few of the millions of young and middle-aged fans of ''Survivor,'' the smash hit CBS specimen of ''reality television,'' have ever heard of Daniel J. Boorstin. Yet the show's arrival certifies Professor Boorstin as a prophet in his time. (Speaking of prophecy, CBS is banking on a second reality series, ''Big Brother,'' which begins tomorrow and continues for five nights a week, to give a further lift to its ratings.)</p>
        <p>It was in 1961 that Mr. Boorstin, then a history professor at the University of Chicago who had won a Bancroft Prize for ''The Americans: The Colonial Experience'' (Random House), came out with a new work. ''The Image: Or What Happened to the American Dream?'' (Atheneum) took aim at the unreality of much that was being marketed as the real stuff of American life. Although the indictment was not entirely original, he applied it broadly and forcefully, in particular to the delivery of ''reality'' in all its dubious forms by television.</p>
        <p>Everywhere he looked, he found fake events, planted for the profit of the planters and the delectation of a mass audience.</p>
        <p>But in his direst nightmares, even Mr. Boorstin, who would go on to become the Librarian of Congress, apparently never envisioned a show quite like ''Survivor,'' which under the guise of delivering real experience serves up a voyeuristic feast drawn from adventure tales, game shows, soap opera and anything else, be it bowel movements or rat-eating, that might titillate the impressionable.</p>
        <p>Where ''Survivor'' placed 16 scantily clad campers on a remote island in the South China Sea, ''Big Brother'' installs 10 people in a locked house under constant television scrutiny. Where the cast members of ''Survivor'' get to choose which of them will be knocked off the show each week, ''Big Brother'' gives the choice to the audience. Both series trade in what Mr. Boorstin called ''synthetic novelty.''</p>
        <p>To borrow another of his favorite phrases, ''Survivor'' is a total ''pseudo event.'' Although the merchandise is presented as realism, the essential criterion is simply whether it will pay off. So, Mr. Boorstin charged in 1961, in a society dominated by television techniques, authenticity is in short supply and getting shorter.</p>
        <p>The success of ''Survivor'' four decades later is evidence of his prescience: millions are relishing, as examples of reality, concoctions contrived to meet the market's taste. The Boorstin rule: ''By this new Gresham's law of American public life, counterfeit happenings tend to drive spontaneous happenings out of circulation.''</p>
        <p>On CBS, as Bill Carter wrote in The New York Times, the line between news and entertainment is being further eroded by tacking on a network news announcer, Julie Chen, to play the role of Big Brother and to interview psychologists and sociologists who don't mind lending their credentials to the enterprise.</p>
        <p>''Why are these people willing to do these things?''asks Susan Zirinsky, referring to the contestants on the programs. Ms. Zirinsky is the executive producer of the CBS news magazine ''48 Hours,'' which adds to tomorrow's prime-time takeover by devoting a segment to the ''Survivor'' participants.</p>
        <p>Why is an ostensible news program willing to do these things? Well, there's the fact that CBS has paid $20 million for ''Big Brother.'' Mr. Boorstin offered another answer: Overnight, the people on a reality program or a game show or a chat show become the talk of the tube, media-created creatures who, as Mr. Boorstin put it, are known for their well-knownness.</p>
        <p>The network publicity engines do their job. For a season or more the audience is entranced by who will win the quiz show. Or, now, it is enthralled by who will get kicked out of the locked house or whether the former member of the Navy Seals, suddenly a national figure by virtue of ''Survivor,'' will survive longer than the truck driver and maybe end up with $1 million, which seems to be the going rate for victory these days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boorstin might have been aiming directly at ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother'' when he wrote, ''The American citizen thus lives in a world where fantasy is more real than reality.'' The time and attention the nation lavishes on television and the popularity of a series like ''Survivor'' lend weight to his assertion that ''in American public life today pseudo events tend to drive all other kinds of events out of our consciousness, or at least to overshadow them.''</p>
        <p>Attributing the blurring of news and pseudo news to a combination of technical virtuosity and audience democratization, he wrote: ''The image, more interesting than its original, has become the original. The shadow has become the substance.''</p>
        <p>Are the many millions tuning into ''Survivor'' able to sort out what is real from what is flagrantly exploitative? Does anybody care? The soaring ratings seem to signal something more than just a diverting hour a week and suggest that Mr. Boorstin was not giving way to hyperbole when he wrote that images, synthetic and simplistic yet vivid and believable, have become the nation's measure of what is real.</p>
        <p>In a sentence that the creators of ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother'' might borrow to promote their goods, Mr. Boorstin wrote: ''By a diabolical irony the very facsimiles of the world which we make on purpose to bring it within our grasp, to make it less elusive, have transported us into a new world of blurs.''</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
