<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mapei Rider Is First for Second Time</title>
    <meta content="04TOUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steels, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6DF1039F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mapei Rider Is First for Second Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>NANTES, France, July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tour de France bicycle race continues; Tom Steels wins second stage; David Miller is overall leader; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Steels, a Belgian with Mapei, won his second successive stage today by sprinting to victory in the 100-mile race from the hospitable town of Loudun to this city in western France.</p>
        <p>David Millar retained the yellow jersey of the overall leader despite crashing with about a mile left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Steels, a Belgian with Mapei, won his second successive stage today by sprinting to victory in the 100-mile race from the hospitable town of Loudun to this city in western France.</p>
        <p>David Millar retained the yellow jersey of the overall leader despite crashing with about a mile left.</p>
        <p>Steels was clocked in 3 hours 37 minutes 51 seconds for the ride along rolling terrain in cool weather.</p>
        <p>The same time was given to Marcel Wust, a German sprinter with the Festina team from Spain, who finished second by inches to Steels. Erik Zabel, a German with Telekom, was in third place with the same time as were 22 others.</p>
        <p>A bigger pack that finished nine seconds behind included Lance Armstrong, the defending champion, who is second over all in this race, and Millar, a Scot with Cofidis and the man ahead of Armstrong by four seconds after three of the 21 stages.</p>
        <p>Millar crashed into a crowd barrier with about 1.5 kilometers to go and was left behind by the riders charging for the line.</p>
        <p>''I thought I'd lost the yellow jersey there,'' Millar said.</p>
        <p>With no teammate inexplicably at his side to assist him, Millar had trouble slipping the bicycle chain back on its ring so that he could pedal. Finally he got going again.</p>
        <p>''I sprinted all out to catch the pack,'' Millar said.</p>
        <p>He did hook on and, since Armstrong was in the same group -- and not the one that was ahead by nine seconds -- the Scot continues another day in the leader's jersey.</p>
        <p>Laurent Jalabert, a Frenchman with ONCE, is third over all, six seconds behind, and Jan Ullrich, a German with Telekom, is fourth, seven seconds behind.</p>
        <p>Millar seems unlikely to be wearing the yellow jersey after a long team time trial on Tuesday because his Cofidis colleagues have been working hard the last two days at the head of the pack, chasing breakaways to protect their leader's edge.</p>
        <p>The team time trial, over 43.5 miles, is expected to be the first big challenge of the 87th Tour and possibly the only one before the race starts to sort itself out next week in the Pyrenees.</p>
        <p>Despite its imminence, the race against the clock was not a subject of conversation today among the riders. They preferred to talk soccer, specifically the European Championship, which was won by France over Italy on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''I didn't watch the match,'' said Paul Van Hyfte, a Belgian with Lotto. ''I don't have any interest in teams from France and Italy.''</p>
        <p>He was more than willing, however, to discuss the Belgian team in Euro 2000, an early casualty.</p>
        <p>Both Roland Meier, a Swiss with Cofidis, and Jesper Skibby, a Dane with Memory Card, said that they felt they had more difficult jobs than the men on the soccer pitch.</p>
        <p>''They have hard work, but it's not an everyday job like this,'' Meier said.</p>
        <p>Even less respectful was Wurst, today's runner-up.</p>
        <p>''I think they're paid too much money for what they do,'' Wurst said of soccer players. ''This Euro 2000, they've been going three and a half weeks and they did 10 hours' work in three weeks. We do that in two days sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Fred Rodriguez, an American with the Mapei team from Italy, said: ''I watched it a little bit. It wasn't that interesting to me. It was more interesting to watch my teammates go crazy.''</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
