<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row</title>
    <meta content="04FRON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1DD1339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Singing, but Not for His Supper</p>
        <p>At 2 a.m. in the lobby bar of the Hotel Principe di Savoia, throngs surrounded the baby grand piano screaming out requests: ''Desperado!'' ''The Beatles!'' ''Hotel California!'' ''Come on!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Singing, but Not for His Supper</p>
        <p>At 2 a.m. in the lobby bar of the Hotel Principe di Savoia, throngs surrounded the baby grand piano screaming out requests: ''Desperado!'' ''The Beatles!'' ''Hotel California!'' ''Come on!''</p>
        <p>Molly Shannon of ''Saturday Night Live'' was singing along, stopping to remark on how good the keyboard talent was. The talent, as it happened, was Lucas Babin, who had taken over in the absence of other lobby-bar entertainment and who, hours earlier, on June 26, had made his runway debut in the Versace men's wear show, walking Donatella Versace down the catwalk at the finale.</p>
        <p>Ten months ago, Mr. Babin, a native of Longview, Tex., was an aspiring actor who walked into the Ford modeling agency in Los Angeles on an impulse. Not long after, he was chosen for a Gucci ad campaign. He will also appear in the fall Versace campaign with the British model Sophie Dahl, shot by Steven Meisel. ''I think he's going to help hook me up,'' Mr. Babin said of his wish to see Ms. Dahl again socially.</p>
        <p>By 3 a.m., after Mr. Babin announced that he would play ''Rocket Man'' just once more, he still didn't know how many other men's shows, if any, he would be in. But he was busy all week, modeling for Byblos, D Squared and others. Considerably less sullen and more spirited-looking than most male models, Mr. Babin, one of the most talked-about new faces of the week, fits the more party-focused mood of current men's clothes.</p>
        <p>New Women's Line for a Men's Wear Team</p>
        <p>Over five seasons, the New York team of Richard Bengtsson and Edward Pavlick have developed a devoted following with the Richard Edwards men's wear line. However much the name suggests staid clothes for the man in the gray flannel suit, it is more in sync with Helmut Lang or Costume National.</p>
        <p>This season Mr. Bengtsson, a Swede who used to work for H&amp;M, and Mr. Pavlick, an American who was an industrial designer, introduced a women's line. It included urbane tennis skirts, heavy cotton on top, organza underneath; lean, subtly provocative cigarette pants; and shirts of yellow netting, which could have looked too aggressively street-influenced, but didn't. There were 11 pieces in all. ''We had lots of other things,'' Mr. Pavlick said, ''but we didn't want to overwhelm anyone. People come here to see men's clothes, after all.''</p>
        <p>Richard Edwards sells its men's wear at stores like Jeffrey in New York and Stanley Korshak in Dallas, but Mr. Pavlick says Italy is its biggest market. ''In the States, you ask someone who their favorite designer is and they'll say Ralph Lauren,'' Mr. Pavlick said. ''Ralph Lauren is a great designer. But people are a little more open-minded here.''</p>
        <p>A Spaghetti Western Star He's Not</p>
        <p>Even beyond the realm of fashion, Milan is a city of rarefied tastes. At downtown newsstands, you find magazines with nude pictures of Naomi Campbell on the cover displayed under videotapes less predictably salacious. Where one might guess that pornography was for sale, there are copies of Roman Polanski's ''Frantic'' and Martin Scorsese's ''New York, New York.''</p>
        <p>Here, too, actors whom Americans may have let slip from their radar remain a focus of fascination. A few months ago, Matthew Modine was the subject of an extensive photo shoot in Italian Vogue Uomo. Last week, he became the new face of Vestimenta, the Italian purveyor of men's sportswear. The ads were shot in Venice and are running in magazines and newspapers and on billboards in Italy. He also greeted visitors at a Vestimenta store that opened last week on the Via Monte Napoleone.</p>
        <p>''He's an actor, but he's not an actor,'' explained Massimo Mosterts, Vestimenta's president, suggesting that Mr. Modine was not one to throw around too much attitude. Mr. Mosterts went on to cite the popularity of ''Birdy'' and ''Full Metal Jacket,'' movies Mr. Modine made in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''I guess my films are always quite popular in Italy,'' said Mr. Modine, who will appear as a hit man in the forthcoming film ''In the Shadows'' with James Caan.</p>
        <p>Of his new spokesman's role, he said he was happy to have it. ''I live in New York and have two kids in private school,'' he said. ''And it's not Whoopi Goldberg on the side of a bus,'' he added, referring to Ms. Goldberg's currently ubiquitous flog for an Internet company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
