<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Americans Capture Gold Cup In Rematch</title>
    <meta content="04CUPP$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gold Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DF1039F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Americans Capture Gold Cup In Rematch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass., July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States defeats Brazil, 1-0, to win championship match in women's Gold Cup soccer tournament; China takes third place (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having relied on a coin toss to prevail over Brazil earlier in the Gold Cup, the United States achieved a more satisfying result tonight with a 1-0 victory in an important tuneup for the Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>A half-volley by forward Tiffeny Milbrett in the 44th minute gave the Americans the championship in this regional tournament before 20,123 at Foxboro Stadium. It was their fifth tournament victory of the year and an encouraging send-off for a series of matches this month in Europe against China, Norway and Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having relied on a coin toss to prevail over Brazil earlier in the Gold Cup, the United States achieved a more satisfying result tonight with a 1-0 victory in an important tuneup for the Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>A half-volley by forward Tiffeny Milbrett in the 44th minute gave the Americans the championship in this regional tournament before 20,123 at Foxboro Stadium. It was their fifth tournament victory of the year and an encouraging send-off for a series of matches this month in Europe against China, Norway and Germany.</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday the United States and Brazil played to a scoreless tie, finishing group play with identical records, and a coin flip gave the group title to the United States. Tonight the Americans labored to put away a flurry of chances provided by the assertiveness of Milbrett and the passing of Mia Hamm and escaped with a shutout victory after a smothering save in the 60th minute from goalkeeper Siri Mullinix.</p>
        <p>Earlier tonight, China, the 1999 Women's World Cup runner-up, struggled against Canada in the consolation match before prevailing, 2-1. The Chinese played this tournament without their star forward, Sun Wen, who has a knee injury, and the team appeared tired and overtrained. China's Olympic prospects remain uncertain with the Summer Games beginning in two months.</p>
        <p>Coach April Heinrichs of the United States continued to experiment with a three-forward lineup tonight, putting Cindy Parlow alongside Milbrett and Hamm instead of Shannon MacMillan, who has the hardest shot on the team and who scored two goals in a 4-1 semifinal victory against Canada on Saturday. The Americans had repeated chances to score in the first half but could not put the ball into the net until the 44th minute, while Brazil threatened twice as midfielder Sissi hit the crossbar on a 22-yard shot and forward Katia volleyed another shot just high in the 29th minute.</p>
        <p>Milbrett, the Americans' leading scorer on the victorious 1999 World Cup team, spent much of the half in front of the Brazilian goal, blasting a left-footer just over the crossbar in the 40th minute. She has great vision and a searing burst of speed in tight spaces, and it seemed inevitable that she would get a goal tonight. Four minutes later, Hamm angled a low bouncing pass into the penalty box, and this time Milbrett expertly one-timed it past the Brazilian goalkeeper, Andreia.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes we catch ourselves watching her, she's so explosive,'' Hamm said of Milbrett. ''I think she's even faster with the ball at her feet than without.''</p>
        <p>Although she led the team in scoring last year, Milbrett has said that she felt somewhat constricted by the style of Tony DiCicco, who coached the Americans to the 1996 Olympic title and the 1999 World Cup title.</p>
        <p>With Heinrichs, Milbrett and Hamm say, there is more opportunity to be creative and to take risks.</p>
        <p>''We feel the freedom to go out and express ourselves and not to worry about making mistakes,'' Hamm said.</p>
        <p>Until Milbrett scored, the Americans had a paucity of goals against the world's top teams in recent months, scoring once against Norway in March and failing to score against China and Brazil in previous matches. Hamm is the career leading scorer in the women's game, but she ranks fifth on the American team this year, with seven goals. When she is not scoring, the United States often finds it difficult to manufacture goals, but one characteristic of Hamm's career has been her continued willingness to pass the ball and play defense when her offense eludes her. Her assist to Milbrett tonight gave her 10 this year, tops among the Americans.</p>
        <p>Mullinix, the American goalkeeper, whose play has been notable for her aggressive roving in the penalty box, prevented the tying goal in the 60th minute after Sissi played a pass to Cidinha behind the American defense. Left alone in front of the United States goal, Cidinha hesitated slightly, and Mullinix charged 6 yards off her line to smother the ball.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
