<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Just Do It</title>
    <meta content="04FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFDB1339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Just Do It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says it is time for Palestinians and Israelis to decide on their future, and Pres Clinton should summon leaders to Camp David for put-up-or-shut-up summit to finally put end to conflict; says only way to find out whether chasm can ever be bridged is by bringing together US president like Clinton, who is trusted by all parties; Israeli leader like Ehud Barak, who understands what Israel will have to give for secure peace; and Palestinian leader like Yasir Arafat, who has stature, and interest in his dying days, to make hard concessions for his own people (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it says in Ecclesiastes, for everything there is a season -- a time to be born and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up what is planted. The same is true in diplomacy -- there is a time to stall and a time to yak, a time to hide and a time to decide. For Israelis and Palestinians, this is the season for deciding, and President Clinton should usher it in by summoning the Israeli and Palestinian leaders to Camp David for one last cards-on-the-table, in-your-face, put-up-or-shut-up summit to finally, finally put an end to this conflict.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Secretary of State Madeleine Albright has been deftly squeezing the parties to help ensure that a possible Camp David summit would have a reasonable chance of closing the remaining gaps. In some cases those gaps have narrowed, in others they remain a chasm. Never mind. There is only one way to find out whether that chasm can ever be bridged and that is by bringing together a U.S. president like Bill Clinton, who is trusted by all the parties; an Israeli leader like Ehud Barak, who understands what Israel will have to give for a secure peace; and a Palestinian leader like Yasir Arafat, who has the stature, and the interest in his dying days, to make the hard concessions for his own people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it says in Ecclesiastes, for everything there is a season -- a time to be born and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up what is planted. The same is true in diplomacy -- there is a time to stall and a time to yak, a time to hide and a time to decide. For Israelis and Palestinians, this is the season for deciding, and President Clinton should usher it in by summoning the Israeli and Palestinian leaders to Camp David for one last cards-on-the-table, in-your-face, put-up-or-shut-up summit to finally, finally put an end to this conflict.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Secretary of State Madeleine Albright has been deftly squeezing the parties to help ensure that a possible Camp David summit would have a reasonable chance of closing the remaining gaps. In some cases those gaps have narrowed, in others they remain a chasm. Never mind. There is only one way to find out whether that chasm can ever be bridged and that is by bringing together a U.S. president like Bill Clinton, who is trusted by all the parties; an Israeli leader like Ehud Barak, who understands what Israel will have to give for a secure peace; and a Palestinian leader like Yasir Arafat, who has the stature, and the interest in his dying days, to make the hard concessions for his own people.</p>
        <p>At this moment the Clinton team is considering whether to shake the dice and just invite the parties to Camp David, even though the chances of success are 50-50. The Palestinians have been resisting, until they are assured that they will get all they want and won't be trapped in a Clinton-Barak vice. Mr. Barak has been pushing for the summit, arguing that the only way he can make big concessions is a one-time, finish-it-all deal. Mr. Clinton has been worried that if the summit tries and fails, the whole fabric of Arab-Israeli peacemaking could unravel.</p>
        <p>All these concerns notwithstanding, you are never going to have a better alignment of the stars for making a deal than you have now in the Clinton-Arafat-Barak trio. If these three leaders can't close the deal, no one can, and we need to know that now. Trying and failing won't be any worse than not trying, because without a framework deal for a final peace, the situation will unravel anyway -- the Palestinians will unilaterally declare a state by Sept. 13 and Israel will unilaterally annex the West Bank Jewish settlements, and Lord only knows what will happen after that.</p>
        <p>The biggest problem will be Jerusalem. Mr. Barak can muster an Israeli majority for giving back some 90 percent of the West Bank (while retaining the 10 percent where 80 percent of the Jewish settlers live), provided he doesn't appear to be redividing Jerusalem. Mr. Arafat can give up some West Bank land, provided he doesn't give up the Arab-Muslim claim to Jerusalem. Everyone knows the solution: Let the Palestinians also have a capital in Jerusalem, based outside the current municipal boundary in Abu Dis, and give them authority over the Arab neighborhoods in East Jerusalem, while the Israelis retain authority over the Jewish neighborhoods, which become part of Israel.</p>
        <p>Israelis rarely go to the Arab neighborhoods anyway, and they certainly don't need to worry about their garbage collection. The Palestinians already have control over the Muslim holy places in East Jerusalem and the Palestinian neighborhoods there already vote in Palestinian elections. This sort of practical solution would still leave Israel with control over the biggest Jewish Jerusalem in Jewish history -- one that would unite the Jewish neighborhoods in East and West Jerusalem under Israeli sovereignty, with international recognition. Better to share the city this way, so Jews will feel free to go anywhere there, than maintain a formal control everywhere, and Jews will only dare go into their own neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>This is the hard price of peace. You can have it now or after a lot more bloodshed, but it's not going to change. So let's try now. If you summon them, they will come; if they come, they will compromise; if they compromise enough -- maybe you'll have a deal. The only people who would criticize Bill Clinton for trying and failing would be those who either don't want a deal or hate him to begin with -- in other words, the same people who would never give him credit if he tried and succeeded. So just do it. As it also says in Ecclesiastes: ''He who observes the wind will not sow; and he who regards the clouds will not reap.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
