<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazil Pulls Out of Bidding Process</title>
    <meta content="SOC04.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK -- 2006 WORLD CUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morocco</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DE1039F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazil Pulls Out of Bidding Process</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brazil drops bid to host 2006 World Cup soccer tournament, throwing support to South Africa; Germany, England and Morocco are also under consideration (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brazil dropped its bid to play host to the 2006 World Cup yesterday and threw its support (and the votes of the two other South American representatives on FIFA's committee) to South Africa.</p>
        <p>England, Germany and Morocco are also under consideration, but recent acts of hooliganism by English fans at the European Championships have damaged that nation's chances, and Germany appears to have only the support of Europeans from among the five confederations of FIFA, the sport's world governing body.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brazil dropped its bid to play host to the 2006 World Cup yesterday and threw its support (and the votes of the two other South American representatives on FIFA's committee) to South Africa.</p>
        <p>England, Germany and Morocco are also under consideration, but recent acts of hooliganism by English fans at the European Championships have damaged that nation's chances, and Germany appears to have only the support of Europeans from among the five confederations of FIFA, the sport's world governing body.</p>
        <p>A number of Brazilians, including PelE and JoAo Havelange, FIFA's former president, have said that Brazil was not ready to stage the tournament and urged Ricardo Teixeira, the president of the Brazilian confederation, to back South Africa in return for its support for Brazil to be host to the tournament in 2010.</p>
        <p>FIFA's president, Sepp Blatter, has been saying for months that the tournament should be held in Africa, preferably South Africa. The 24-member executive committee will vote Thursday at FIFA's headquarters in Zurich. A simple majority will win the bid, and South Africa could garner enough votes to win on the first ballot.</p>
        <p>''I am genuinely of the opinion that the World Cup must be awarded to Africa before long,'' Franz Beckenbauer, the leader of Germany's bid, said last month in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. ''But is Africa ready now? I don't know. Let us organize the 2006 World Cup in Germany and then the next one in Africa.''</p>
        <p>When the German Football Federation filed its first application in 1993, Havelange supported it, saying It has a strong economy, a stable currency, a great culture, an outstanding infrastructure, an exemplarily organized federation and large stadiums.</p>
        <p>Germany staged (and won) the 1974 World Cup during Havelange's first year as FIFA president. He was replaced by Blatter two years ago.</p>
        <p>METROSTARS</p>
        <p>There is no longer any doubt about the MetroStars' turnaround; they have gone from worst to first in half a season. Even though they played their last game without the injured Lothar MatthAus and Thomas Dooley, the two veterans who are supposed to be the backbone of the team, the MetroStars have not lost in their past five games.</p>
        <p>After finishing with a 7-25 record last season, the worst in Major League Soccer, the MetroStars (9-7-2) are in first place in the Eastern Division, 3 points ahead of New England, after Saturday's 2-0 victory in Tampa, Fla., against the Mutiny.</p>
        <p>Matthaus (lower back) and Dooley (left hamstring) will most likely miss tomorrow night's game against visiting Dallas. But their injuries are secondary in the scheme of things because the MetroStars have enough good players to replace them this season.</p>
        <p>A healthy Tab Ramos has made a huge difference. The skillful midfielder has been playing with such gusto that there is talk he may be recalled by Bruce Arena, the United States national team coach, for the coming World Cup qualifying games. The first player to be signed by the league, Ramos has been playing better and better since his return last month from reconstructive surgery on his right knee.</p>
        <p>Ramos has not been the only MetroStars player drawing attention. Clint Mathis was named player of the month by the league yesterday after his three goals and five assists in June helped the MetroStars to a 3-2-1 record. Mathis, who was recently acquired from Los Angeles, is the first MetroStars player to be so honored.</p>
        <p>The league's annual Independece Day showcase will have 10 teams playing today, with the MetroStars-Dallas game the only one tomorrow. Four of today's five games will feature postgame fireworks. Last year's five games on July 4 averaged 46,238 fans.</p>
        <p>GERMANY</p>
        <p>The coaching staff of the national team, which had a disastrous showing in the European Championships, needs a new vision and foreign influence to help rejuvenate the team. That was the consensus among Germans with authority and knowledge just hours after Rudi VOller was named as interim coach until Christoph Daum becomes free from Bayer Leverkusen and takes the reins.</p>
        <p>Voller has no coaching experience and even lacks the coaching license required in Germany to run a team. Franz Beckenbauer took over as coach under similar circumstances 15 years ago and led Germany to the World Cup championship in 1990 after losing the title game to Argentina in 1986.</p>
        <p>Voller, who played in Italy for several years, was a striker who scored 47 goals in 90 games for Germany. He was one of the key players in 1990, and he will be assisted by Bayern Munich's vice president, Karl-Heinz Rummenigge, another former striker of the national team. Rummenigge will lead a task force to find an assistant for Voller.</p>
        <p>Gunter Netzer, a former midfielder who is now a popular television commentator, is among those Germans urging the new regime to give the team less of a German look and reflect the country's multicultural makeup.</p>
        <p>Netzer and others have urged the country's governing body to follow France's example and allow players of different cultural backgrounds to join the national team. More than half the players on the French team that captured the World Cup in 1998 and the European Championship this past Sunday are children of immigrants, including Zinedine Zidane, the son of Algerian immigrants, who is currently considered the world's top player.</p>
        <p>Like France, Germany has a huge immigrant population, with nearly 10 percent of the country's 82 million people considered foreigners. Unlike in France, it is extremely rare in Germany for such players to be included in the national team, mainly because it is difficult to become a German citizen.</p>
        <p>EUROPEAN CHAMPIONSHIPS</p>
        <p>After their triumph over Italy in Rotterdam, the Netherlands, on Sunday, the French made a triumphant entry into the heart of Paris yesterday for a welcome from tens of thousands of fans who chanted, On est champions! The players sprayed Champagne from the balcony of a hotel and flung T-shirts to the crowd.</p>
        <p>It was a significant day for some players. Emmanuel Petit was married, Zinedine Zidane shaved his already sparse head of hair on a bet and Robert Pires signed a four-year contract with Arsenal of the English Premier League.</p>
        <p>ALEX YANNIS</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK -- 2006 WORLD CUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
