<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; A Tea Party Like Boston's, Over Wine?</title>
    <meta content="04BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFDA1339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; A Tea Party Like Boston's, Over Wine?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column discusses shipping wine from out-of-state wineries to New York; vintners from California and West Virginia have joined with consumers in lawsuit seeking to overturn prohibition against shipment of wine directly to New Yorkers; although many states allow wine to be shipped to residents, Governor George E Pataki vetoed legislation on ground that such trade would take business from New York State liquor stores, it would facilitate underage access to alcoholic beverages and limit State's ability to collect applicable tax (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TODAY, as we celebrate our independence from one form of tyranny, many New Yorkers may be consorting with a new foreign menace. They may be drinking out-of-state wine.</p>
        <p>Most of them won't even know the danger in their glasses. They haven't heard of the arguments over New York's liquor laws that are set to begin this month in Federal District Court in Manhattan. Vintners in California and Virginia have joined with consumers in New York in a suit seeking to overturn the law prohibiting out-of-state wineries from shipping directly to New Yorkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TODAY, as we celebrate our independence from one form of tyranny, many New Yorkers may be consorting with a new foreign menace. They may be drinking out-of-state wine.</p>
        <p>Most of them won't even know the danger in their glasses. They haven't heard of the arguments over New York's liquor laws that are set to begin this month in Federal District Court in Manhattan. Vintners in California and Virginia have joined with consumers in New York in a suit seeking to overturn the law prohibiting out-of-state wineries from shipping directly to New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>This menace is tricky to understand. There are whole states, even apparently functioning ones like Connecticut, that blithely allow their citizens to order wine directly through catalogues and the Internet. There are even some New York legislators who tried to win this same right by passing a bill in 1995, but it was vetoed by Governor Pataki.</p>
        <p>The governor was not swayed by arguments from consumers desiring wines not available in stores. He was not moved by traditional Republican arguments on the benefits of free trade. Mr. Pataki was not even persuaded by the many small wineries in New York State that favored opening the border. Although they could legally ship to customers within New York, they were shut out of larger markets in states allowing shipments only from states with reciprocal open borders.</p>
        <p>The governor was concerned instead with the licensed cartel of wholesale distributors and their unionized drivers with a monopoly on out-of-state wines. ''A significant increase in mail-order wines,'' Mr. Pataki warned, ''could, in turn, lead to a decrease in sales for New York liquor stores and their distributors.''</p>
        <p>The wholesale distributors insist that they're not merely concerned with profits. ''Direct shipping is a Pandora's Box to under-age access,'' declares the Americans for Responsible Alcohol Access, a national advocacy group financed largely by alcohol wholesalers and retailers seeking to preserve the exclusive distribution systems in New York and 29 other states.</p>
        <p>In 1997, the group arranged a press conference on ''cyberbooze'' at which Dennis C. Vacco, then the New York State attorney general, announced a sting operation in which teenage children of his staff members had successfully ordered wine from California over the Internet. Mr. Vacco, however, was not able to point to any minors in New York State who had ever ordered wine on the Internet without the assistance of his office.</p>
        <p>Even if you believe that teenagers across New York are scheming to order cases of merlot, it's not clear how much good is being accomplished by the current prohibition against interstate shipments. As long as it's legal to order from wineries in the state, teenagers could presumably get just as drunk on merlot from Long Island.</p>
        <p>DEFENDERS of the law argue that New York is justified in discriminating against out-of-state wineries because they're harder to police. ''New York can take away the license of a winery in the state that sells to minors,'' said C. Boyden Gray, a former White House counsel, who represents wine wholesalers. ''It doesn't have jurisdiction over one in California.''</p>
        <p>Out-of-state vintners say the best way to stop minors from ordering wine is for New York to pass a law, as other states have, requiring all shipments of alcohol to carry a warning label and all shippers to obtain a signature from an adult before releasing the package.</p>
        <p>''New York's law protects wholesalers, not minors,'' said Deborah Simpson, a senior attorney at the Institute for Justice, a public-interest law firm in Washington that filed the suit seeking to overturn New York's law as an unconstitutional infringement on interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>''The law preserves a monopoly that collects 18 to 25 cents of every dollar spent on a bottle of wine,'' Mrs. Simpson said. ''It's even illegal to send an out-of-state price list into New York, which means that an out-of-state winery is violating the law if it maintains a Web site with its prices. This is allowing the protectionist policies of the 18th century to rule 21st-century technology.''</p>
        <p>Some Internet wine merchants have managed to ship to New York by making arrangements with licensed wholesalers, but the process can be cumbersome, and it adds what is essentially a tax to the transaction. Mr. Pataki may be worried about depriving the wholesalers of their cut, but a surcharge on imported beverages can lead to other sorts of local happiness, as another sovereign named George discovered at the Boston Tea Party.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
