<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Light Show, Jersey City Hopes to Make a New Name for Itself</title>
    <meta content="04JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jersey City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Rudi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4D61339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Light Show, Jersey City Hopes to Make a New Name for Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY, July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jersey City plans illuminated extravaganza, light show designed by artist Rudi Stern, that will be projected on facade of 10-story office building facing Manhattan; officials hope to raise city's profile as waterfront grows and scores of companies and residents come from Manhattan, finding more affordable rents and lower taxes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Call it a case of light-show envy.</p>
        <p>Long overshadowed by its neighbor across the Hudson, this booming back-office hub will not allow itself to be entirely upstaged by Macy's 60,000 exploding rockets, most of which will burst just beyond the view of the 250,000 people expected to gather Tuesday night in Jersey City's Liberty State Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Call it a case of light-show envy.</p>
        <p>Long overshadowed by its neighbor across the Hudson, this booming back-office hub will not allow itself to be entirely upstaged by Macy's 60,000 exploding rockets, most of which will burst just beyond the view of the 250,000 people expected to gather Tuesday night in Jersey City's Liberty State Park.</p>
        <p>With millions of spectators oohing and aahing over the pyrotechnics on the New York side, Jersey City officials proudly plan to launch their own illuminated extravaganza Tuesday night, an eight-and-a-half-minute splash of psychedelic imagery projected on the facade of a new 10-story office building that faces Manhattan. The weeklong show, which was to begin tonight but was rained out, is to be visible each night from sundown until 1 a.m. It is the work of Rudi Stern, 63, a lighting artist who has collaborated with the likes of Igor Stravinsky, Timothy Leary and the Doors over a 40-year career.</p>
        <p>But unlike parts of New York's fireworks display, which Jersey City's mayor, Bret Schundler, has loudly complained will be hidden from viewers in his city, Mr. Stern's illuminated projections are clearly visible to those on the opposite side of the river. ''We're sharing our show with everyone,'' said Mr. Schundler, who is planning to run for governor in 2001. ''We just wish they would share theirs with us.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Jersey City's ''Theater of Light,'' as it is called, is not meant to compete with New York's fireworks display, which is being billed as the largest in history. It is a relatively modest affair, a $60,000 production that includes prerecorded music and a 50-foot-high kaleidoscope of hand-painted abstractions, which Mr. Stern describes as ''a romantic voyage and visual story involving sensual shapes and forms.''</p>
        <p>The installation, using municipal money, says a lot about how this city of 238,000 is trying to reinvent and market itself, especially now that it is no longer an economic basket case. As its waterfront bulges with office construction, drawing scores of companies from Manhattan, Jersey City officials want to make sure that it does not end up as a staid collection of buildings best known for cheap rents, low taxes and nice views.</p>
        <p>Stuart Koperweis, president of the city's Economic Development Corporation, said many prospective tenants tell him they have no interest in relocating to a sterile office park, no matter how enticing the rents are. ''At this point, development is taking care of itself,'' he said. ''Now, we have to let people know that Jersey City has all the amenities of a great city, including art and culture.''</p>
        <p>City officials boast about their special arts district, where rents are shielded from steep increases, and the old Jersey Loews, a 1929 movie palace once destined for demolition but now being restored as a nonprofit performance space. In an impressive sign that Jersey City is becoming more culturally relevant, workers broke ground in April on an $11 million museum to showcase the work of Jersey City artists.</p>
        <p>Eager to raise his city's profile, Mayor Schundler said it was no coincidence that the light show was largely aimed at those living on the other side of the river. ''With all the national media here for the Fourth of July, we're literally beaming our message to the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's a chance for us to flaunt the artistic abilities of our citizens.''</p>
        <p>In that sense, it is especially fitting that the city has chosen Mr. Stern for its cross-Hudson flourish. Mr. Stern, a longtime resident of Lower Manhattan, moved to Jersey City last year after he was unable to find an affordable space to construct his sprawling light displays. Like the dot-com start-ups, accounting firms and investment banks that have fled Manhattan rents, Mr. Stern, who had never before set foot here, said he was surprised by what he found. ''It's so diverse, so vibrant,'' he said.</p>
        <p>This is the first time that Mr. Stern is trying to show his work on a building, and he said he was finding it hard to persuade all the tenants of 90 Hudson Street to turn off their lights or shade their windows after sunset. ''With all the moldings and mullions, it's like projecting onto a crossword puzzle,'' he said. ''If the facade isn't dark, it just doesn't look right.''</p>
        <p>Using nail polish and paint, Mr. Stern creates his images on glass and transfers them to Mylar scrolls, which are fed through 350-pound projectors with huge 6,000-watt bulbs. The result is colorful but understated. Those expecting a soul-shaking display of light and booming sound, he said, may be underwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Across the river, Macy's officials expressed annoyance over Mr. Schundler's repeated claims of being snubbed, saying their fireworks would be visible from all points along the Jersey City riverfront. ''They can see them bright and beautiful,'' said Ronnie Taffet, a spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Though she said she had not heard about Mr. Schundler's light show, she said it was in no way competition. ''I'm sure it will be nice,'' she said. ''But it just can't compare to 60,000 shells going off at once.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
