<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Change in Leadership Is Welcomed as an Opportunity for Greater U.S.-Mexican Cooperation</title>
    <meta content="Y04POL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEXICAN ELECTION: WASHINGTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D91339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Change in Leadership Is Welcomed as an Opportunity for Greater U.S.-Mexican Cooperation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton administration welcomes transition of power in Mexico, saying election of Vicente Fox Quesada is evidence of maturing of democratic institutions and that it sets stage for economic growth; Pres Clinton telehones Fox to congratulate him, and also speaks to Pres Ernesto Zedillo, thanking him for his role in strengthening democracy in Mexico; during campaign, Clinton administration had been scrupulous in not showing preference for either Fox or his opponents (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton administration welcomed the transition of power in Mexico, saying today that the election of Vicente Fox Quesada was evidence of the maturing of democratic institutions and that it set the stage for economic growth.</p>
        <p>President Clinton telephoned Mr. Fox to congratulate him, and also spoke to President Ernesto Zedillo, the departing leader, to express his gratitude for his role in strengthening democracy in Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton administration welcomed the transition of power in Mexico, saying today that the election of Vicente Fox Quesada was evidence of the maturing of democratic institutions and that it set the stage for economic growth.</p>
        <p>President Clinton telephoned Mr. Fox to congratulate him, and also spoke to President Ernesto Zedillo, the departing leader, to express his gratitude for his role in strengthening democracy in Mexico.</p>
        <p>''Mexicans should be proud of the extraordinary steps they have taken during the last six years to strengthen and consolidate democratic institutions and set Mexico on a course of economic growth and prosperity,'' Mr. Clinton said in a statement released by the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton dealt frequently with Mr. Zedillo in the past six years, especially after the passage of the North American Free Trade Agreement, which saw trade between the two nations soar. The two leaders held their eleventh meeting here last month when Mr. Clinton praised Mr. Zedillo for advancing the process of trade integration with the United States.</p>
        <p>During the campaign, the Clinton administration had been fairly scrupulous in not showing a preference for either Mr. Fox or his main opponent, Francisco Labastida Ochoa of the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party, or PRI.</p>
        <p>It also had expressed confidence in the integrity of the electoral process.</p>
        <p>That confidence was borne out in the conduct of the elections on Sunday and in the results, the White House said.</p>
        <p>For Washington, dealing with a Mexican administration led by the PRI, which had been in power for 71 years, has been an ingrained habit that survived countless bouts of economic crisis in Mexico and American-led financial bailouts. Through all the crises, Washington was generally grateful to have a stable neighbor even though it was poor and in more recent years became the major conduit for illegal narcotics into the United States.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fox is not an unknown quantity in Washington. In an introductory pre-election visit here in May, he met with Under Secretary of State Thomas Pickering and gave talks at several foreign policy institutions.</p>
        <p>He impressed people here not only as a businessman who once worked for Coca-Cola but also as a politician who understood the United States, a senior administration official said.  One of his major points was further expansion of American investment in Mexico.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to reassure us that the United States would have a good partner, that he would be reliable and would co-operate across the board,'' the official said. ''Relations under Zedillo had reached an all-time high and we would expect Fox to continue the momentum.''</p>
        <p>But this was not to say that Mr. Fox would not inject some new ideas into the relationship.</p>
        <p>On the three main issues between Mexico and the United States -- immigration, trade and the flow of drugs -- Mr. Fox, as a former governor of a northern Mexican state, would likely bring some fresh thinking, officials said.</p>
        <p>During his campaign, Mr. Fox said he would like a more even relationship with Washington on the handling of immigration which, from the Mexican point of view, has largely been treated by the United States as a criminal justice and police issue.</p>
        <p>''I think this is one issue that the new president and the new president of the United State will have to deal with quite quickly,'' said Andres Rozental, a business consultant in Mexico City, who was a deputy secretary of state dealing with American relations in a former Mexican government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rozental said he believed that Mr. Fox would like to look beyond just ''managing'' the question of illegal Mexican immigrants into the United States and turn toward reaching agreements with Washington that would allow better terms for semi-skilled Mexican migrants to enter the United States.</p>
        <p>He pointed out that the A.F.L.-C.I.O. had recently noted the value of semi-skilled foreign workers to the United States, and that the Treasury Department had attributed some of the economic growth during the Clinton administration to immigrant labor. This presented a ''window of opportunity'' for Mexico to try to persuade Washington to sit down and take a new look at immigration policies with Mexico, he said.</p>
        <p>Despite disputes involving trucking and sugar -- two sectors in which Mexico would like a bigger share of the American market -- Mexico's trading relations with the United States have moved steadily since NAFTA was signed into law by President Clinton in 1993.</p>
        <p>An administration official said that Mr. Zedillo had refrained from repeating the practice of his predecessors of ramping up the Mexican economy in an effort to have his party win the election.</p>
        <p>''There is stability, not boom,'' in the Mexican economy, an administration official said.</p>
        <p>There was also the prospect of continuity in the economy with the head of the central bank, Guillermo Ortiz, slated to stay. It also appeared possible that the finance minister, Jose Angel Gurria, might remain in office.</p>
        <p>THE MEXICAN ELECTION: WASHINGTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
