<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MEXICO, VOTING IN NEW LEADER, BEGINS A POLITICAL SEA CHANGE</title>
    <meta content="04MEXI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEXICAN ELECTION: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardenas Solorzano, Cuauhtemoc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labastida Ochoa, Francisco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DF1039F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MEXICO, VOTING IN NEW LEADER, BEGINS A POLITICAL SEA CHANGE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres-elect Vicente Fox Quesada of Mexico begins transition from republic led for decades by autocratic presidents to one in which political power is now up for grabs; election returns show he won 43 percent of votes, while Francisco Labastida Ochoa, candidate of governing party, won 36 percent and Cuauhtemoc Cardenas Solorzano, leftist candidate, got 17 percent; Fox's victory over governing party is far more decisive than any poll had predicted; Fox receives contratulatory phone calls from world leaders, including Pres Clinton, and meets with Pres Ernesto Zedillo; Fox says he assured Zedillo that he will not carry out purge of government bureaucracy after he takes office Dec 1; says two will meet frequently before than to plan next year's budget and to discuss transition; Fox will preside over government unused to coalition politics; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Swept to power by younger, better-educated voters fed up with corruption and one-party rule, President-elect Vicente Fox Quesada today began the transition from a republic led for decades by autocratic presidents to one in which political power suddenly seemed up for grabs.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Fox fielded congratulatory phone calls today from world leaders, including President Clinton, and met with President Ernesto Zedillo, election returns showed that Mexican voters on Sunday handed him a substantially more decisive victory over the governing party than any poll had predicted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Swept to power by younger, better-educated voters fed up with corruption and one-party rule, President-elect Vicente Fox Quesada today began the transition from a republic led for decades by autocratic presidents to one in which political power suddenly seemed up for grabs.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Fox fielded congratulatory phone calls today from world leaders, including President Clinton, and met with President Ernesto Zedillo, election returns showed that Mexican voters on Sunday handed him a substantially more decisive victory over the governing party than any poll had predicted.</p>
        <p>With 93 percent of the ballots tabulated, the Mexican electoral agency reported that Mr. Fox had won 43 percent of the votes, while Francisco Labastida Ochoa, the candidate of the governing party, won 36 percent and Cuauhtemoc Cardenas Solorzano, a leftist candidate, 17 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox will take office on Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>For many Mexicans it was still sinking in today that after 71 years, the Institutional Revolutionary Party, which evolved from an alliance of revolutionary generals into a model nationalist party imitated across Latin America before degenerating into a clique of corrupt insiders, was finally deposed from the presidency.</p>
        <p>But when the dust settles on the first democratic transition of power in this country's history, for the first time none of the major parties -- the deposed one, Mr. Fox's center-right party or the largest leftist grouping -- will be in control of either house of Congress.</p>
        <p>At a news conference tonight, Mr. Fox said he had assured President Zedillo that he did not intend to carry out a purge of the government bureaucracy, at least in the first stage of his new administration. The two leaders agreed to meet frequently between now and December to plan next year's budget and to discuss the transition, Mr. Fox added.</p>
        <p>''Our team will take office with creative ideas and new philosophies, but there'll be no change in federal work rhythms,'' Mr. Fox said. ''Mexico will be a country on the move, headed by a government that keeps its commitments.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox will preside over a government unused to coalition politics but one in which all major business will require the consent of one or the other of his rival parties.</p>
        <p>''All the parties are going to have to relearn the art of making politics,'' said Carlos Elizondo Mayer-Serra, a political scientist who is rector of the Center for Research and Teaching. ''The fundamental pillars of Mexico's political system have changed.''</p>
        <p>These unsettled results were reflected around the country. Mr. Fox's National Action Party won the two governors' seats up for grabs on Sunday and will now govern in 7 of Mexico's 31 states. In Mexico City, the leftist Party of the Democratic Revolution, or P.R.D., retained control of the mayor's office, but the president-elect's party took control of the City Council.</p>
        <p>As president, Mr. Fox will face the ticklish task of meeting the hopes for quick and sweeping change of the diverse voters who backed him. He has promised, simultaneously, to modernize the economy and spur 7 percent growth, carry out political reforms and initiate an ''educational revolution.''</p>
        <p>He has pledged to better the lot not only of the largely young, middle-class professionals in his own party, but also millions of poor urban workers as well as dirt farmers who have in the past supported the governing party.</p>
        <p>''We've all got to get to work right away,'' Mr. Fox said in an interview early today after his triumph. ''I want to be certain to deliver good results to the people of Mexico, to govern and to govern well.''</p>
        <p>The election results provoked a debate over how successfully President Zedillo's party would navigate its journey from its powerhouse position into the ranks of the opposition. Some said the party had already proven its adaptability and resilience in states where Mr. Fox's party had already won control of the governors' chairs.</p>
        <p>But others, comparing the position of the Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI, to some Communist parties in Eastern Europe, argued that without presidential support and control over federal patronage, the party would crumble.</p>
        <p>Dulce Maria Sauri, the party chairwoman during the presidential campaign, quickly announced her resignation, and some party officials said they feared that it could be the first in a significant exodus.</p>
        <p>The results of the elections to fill all 128 seats in the Senate and all 500 in the Chamber of Deputies indicated that Mr. Fox's party would finish with its powers significantly enhanced, mainly at the expense of the leftist P.R.D., with which it shared opposition powers during the last legislature. Still, it will not control a legislative majority.</p>
        <p>The PRI lost the Senate majority it had enjoyed since the party's creation, and without the power of the president to coordinate its efforts, the PRI's entire legislative delegation will wield considerably less strength.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox's party was receiving 38 percent of the votes for Congress, the returns showed. The PRI was receiving 36 percent and the P.R.D. 18 percent.</p>
        <p>As the ballot counting continued, Mr. Zedillo met privately in the presidential compound with the top PRI leaders. Aides said Mr. Zedillo had outlined his views of the challenge to the survival of the party, which had gone undefeated in presidential voting -- often through the simple exercise of its vast powers of patronage and public works and sometimes through outright ballot fraud -- for 71 years.</p>
        <p>In a second encounter, Mr. Zedillo addressed the 21 of Mexico's 31 state governors who belong to his party, urging them to cooperate fully with Mr. Fox's government.</p>
        <p>''The PRI is like the phoenix,'' Melquiades Morales, the PRI governor of Puebla, told reporters as he entered the meeting. ''It will rise again from its own ashes.''</p>
        <p>If Mexico is entering absolutely new political terrain with the PRI's defeat, neither foreign nor domestic investors appeared concerned. The Mexican stock market surged 6.1 percent on news of Mr. Fox's victory, and the value of the peso, which had been battered in recent weeks as nervous Mexicans converted savings to dollars, climbed 2.7 percent.</p>
        <p>''Investors are very enthusiastic,'' said Rogelio Ramirez de la O, president of Ecanal, a Mexico City consulting firm. ''The market is seeing Fox as a man who can bring important changes, in the sense of modernizing the economy and the system.''</p>
        <p>In the interview early today, hours after his triumph became apparent, Mr. Fox outlined his hopes to forge tighter relations with the United States, where he has traveled extensively and attended high school for a year, in Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>''Fortunately, I know well the philosophy of the American people, because I've worked all my life there both in business and in politics,'' he said. ''I know that we are going to be able to accomplish many things together. We can develop our great potential, which still stretches before us. I want to work intensely with the United States because it is the world's largest market. It's our neighbor. It's our partner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox offered words of conciliation to Mr. Labastida and to Mr. Cardenas, after having traded extraordinarily harsh criticisms with both during the campaign.</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Labastida, he said: ''I send him my regards. I recognize his participation and his passion in defending his ideas.''</p>
        <p>In a victory speech, Mr. Fox said he would withdraw the libel suit he filed last week against his rivals, who had accused him, without providing documentation, of accepting illegal campaign donations from a Belgian company.</p>
        <p>''Ours is going to be a government of national concord, a government of unity, a government with its eyes fixed on the future,'' Mr. Fox said.</p>
        <p>President Clinton called Mr. Fox this morning to congratulate him on the election.</p>
        <p>Several delegations of international observers praised the elections as well organized and free of fraud. Jimmy Carter called the elections ''a turning point of great significance.''</p>
        <p>Analysts were puzzled about why Mr. Fox's victory was far more extensive than most surveys had predicted. Several polls had shown Mr. Fox and Mr. Labastida running neck and neck, but Mr. Fox won by a 9-point margin.</p>
        <p>Stanley Greenberg, an American pollster who worked on contract to the PRI, said Mr. Labastida had failed to compete for young, urban middle-class voters.</p>
        <p>''Labastida and the PRI simply had to attract votes beyond their longtime base in the rural areas,'' Mr. Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>THE MEXICAN ELECTION: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
