<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>9 POLICE OFFICERS FACING  DISCIPLINE IN  PARK ATTACKS</title>
    <meta content="04PARK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safir, Howard (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E4DF1039F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>9 POLICE OFFICERS FACING  DISCIPLINE IN  PARK ATTACKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police Comr Howard Safir says 9 police officers, including 6 supervisors, will be disciplined for mistakes that allowed unruly mob to turn section of Central Park into menacing gantlet where men assaulted dozens of women after National Puerto Rican Day Parade on June 11; says two high-ranking chiefs who were in charge of parade would be given letters of instruction noting shortcomings of operation and three civilian 911 employees will be punished for improper handling of calls reporting the attacks, thus delaying police response; department's review, based on interviews with 236 officers, paints detailed picture of day in which bawdy horseplay developed into sexual abuse; review finds grossest failures among officers who disregarded women who complained that they had been attacked; Central Park rampage has been major embarrassment for Giuliani administration, which has prided itself in Police Dept that prevents, not merely contains, public disorder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nine New York police officers, including six supervisors, will be disciplined for mistakes that allowed an unruly mob to turn a section of Central Park into a menacing gantlet where men sexually assaulted dozens of women after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, Police Commissioner Howard Safir said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The commissioner also said the two high-ranking chiefs who were in charge at the June 11 parade would  be given letters of instruction noting the shortcomings of the operation, and three civilian 911 employees would be punished for improper handling of calls reporting the attacks, thus delaying the police response.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nine New York police officers, including six supervisors, will be disciplined for mistakes that allowed an unruly mob to turn a section of Central Park into a menacing gantlet where men sexually assaulted dozens of women after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, Police Commissioner Howard Safir said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The commissioner also said the two high-ranking chiefs who were in charge at the June 11 parade would  be given letters of instruction noting the shortcomings of the operation, and three civilian 911 employees would be punished for improper handling of calls reporting the attacks, thus delaying the police response.</p>
        <p>''We are better than how we acted on that particular day,'' Mr. Safir said at one point. ''Responsibility? We all feel responsible.''</p>
        <p>The Central Park rampage has been a major embarrassment for the Giuliani administration, which saw its record for cutting crime overshadowed for weeks by publicity that recalled the days when the police were content to contain, not prevent, public disorder.</p>
        <p>The department's review, based on interviews with 236 officers, painted a more detailed picture of a sweltering day in which bawdy horseplay  developed into sexual abuse. The review found that some commanders failed to deploy officers properly and failed to adjust to changing crowd conditions when the parade ended earlier than expected and many of the one million spectators began to move about. In the grossest failures, the review found, some officers disregarded women who complained that they had been attacked.</p>
        <p>The officers who were cited face a variety of punishments, from letters of reprimand to formal misconduct charges, which carry a maximum penalty of dismissal, although a senior police official said it was unlikely anyone would be fired. The report immediately started a debate about whether the sanctions were too strong or too weak.</p>
        <p>Of the nine officers cited, two were accused of failing to respond properly to women who had tried to report sexual assaults. Officials said Officer Michael Bonefant refused to leave his post directing traffic at Central Park South and Seventh Avenue and instead directed two victims to take their complaint to a mobile command post on Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>A second officer, Scott Hyndman of the 17th Precinct, was accused of failing to prepare a report when a victim arrived at his East Side station house to complain that she had been sexually assaulted in the park.</p>
        <p>''Police officers who ignore or brush off a plea for help violate their oath to this city, and deserve severe and decisive punishment,'' Mr. Safir said.</p>
        <p>One officer and one supervisor were faulted for leaving their posts on Central Park South. Five commanders were cited for mistakes in deploying officers or for letting officers go home even as the unruly crowd was growing inside the park.</p>
        <p>The union representing superior officers dismissed the investigation as a witch hunt, while several victims said the department did not seem to have done enough. Although six victims have reported that about a half-dozen officers failed to take their complaints seriously, only two officers were cited for such misconduct yesterday.</p>
        <p>Susan M. Karten, a lawyer for one  victim, said, ''This doesn't make any women in this city, which is supposed to be safe, feel any safer.''</p>
        <p>Police officials said their investigation had been complicated by the fact that two victims would not cooperate while others had difficulty identifying the officers involved.</p>
        <p>Department officials also said it was a coincidence that the city chose to release its findings about the embarrassing incident on July 3, when much of New York is away or preoccupied with holiday celebrations.  ''We released this report when I believed it was done,'' Mr. Safir said.</p>
        <p>Fifty-nine women have reported to the police that they were assaulted in the park or its environs by men who doused them with water and beer, tried, successfully at times, to remove their clothes, and groped them. So far, 29 men have been arrested and officials have said they are looking for 17 more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Safir said that the parade itself had been adequately policed, but the review proposed a number of training and tactical changes to improve crowd control at future events, like live video transmission at important intersections. ''In future events, police tactics -- like rooftop observation posts and helicopter flyovers -- will be utilized to identify emerging conditions, even if the event is expected to be a peaceful one,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani cited the tactical recommendations as evidence of the city's commitment to ensure that similar attacks do not occur in the future. ''I think when people read the report,'' Mr. Giuliani said, ''people will see that this is a police department that knows how to discipline itself and that knows how to improve based upon things that have happened in the past.''</p>
        <p>In the days after the attacks, Mr. Giuliani and Mr. Safir had appeared to minimize the assaults as isolated incidents. But the mayor's and the commissioner's tone grew more serious as women came forward to complain about police inaction and videotapes surfaced showing the severity of the abuse.</p>
        <p>Capt. John Driscoll, president of the Captain's Endowment Association, which represents supervisors up to the rank of deputy chief, said the captains and inspectors cited were scapegoats who had done nothing wrong. There was no one assigned to work the problem area of the park, he said, and no way for the line supervisors to have known a problem was developing.</p>
        <p>Patrick Lynch, president of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, was more muted. He released a statement that said the union would defend its members but did not criticize the internal investigation.</p>
        <p>Those facing formal charges have the right to a public trial before an administrative law judge who will issue a recommendation on punishment to the commissioner, who decides disciplinary matters.</p>
        <p>Police officials were careful to note that the letters of instruction received by Chiefs Allan H. Hoehl, the commander for southern Manhattan, and Nicholas Estavillo, the commander for northern Manhattan, are not considered discipline and will not be placed in their personnel files.</p>
        <p>But letters of reprimand will become part of the folders of four commanders responsible for areas near where the assaults occurred: Inspector Jeremiah Quinlan of Manhattan South; Deputy Inspector Richard Heegan, the commander of the Sixth  Precinct; Deputy Inspector James Secreto, commander of the 28th Precinct; and Capt. Peter Tuffey, commander of the 70th Precinct.</p>
        <p>The investigators, however, did not find that the commanders had known about the building crowd inside the park. But they did fault another supervisor, Lt. Thomas O'Malley, for allowing a police detail to be dismissed after he had been informed of the growing crowd. Formal misconduct charges were filed against Lieutenant O'Malley.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
