<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virtual Reality Finds a Real Place as a Medical Aid</title>
    <meta content="04VIRT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Phobias</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Phobias</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DF1339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virtual Reality Finds a Real Place as a Medical Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virtual reality, interactive world created by computers, is finding a place in health care, particularly in pain management and helping people overcome phobias; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>James Pokorny sat upright in bed in his room at the University of Washington Burn Center at Harborview as a nurse prepared to unwrap his bandages. Working on a car when the fuel tank exploded, Mr. Pokorny received third-degree burns on about 42 percent of his body.</p>
        <p>Despite pain-killing drugs, Mr. Pokorny was in agonizing pain, which intensified when his bandages were changed. So doctors tried a new approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>James Pokorny sat upright in bed in his room at the University of Washington Burn Center at Harborview as a nurse prepared to unwrap his bandages. Working on a car when the fuel tank exploded, Mr. Pokorny received third-degree burns on about 42 percent of his body.</p>
        <p>Despite pain-killing drugs, Mr. Pokorny was in agonizing pain, which intensified when his bandages were changed. So doctors tried a new approach.</p>
        <p>Wearing a black plastic helmet with a computer monitor inside, headphones and a tracker that monitored the position of his finger, Mr. Pokorny entered a virtual world. Multicolored three-dimensional graphics, along with sound and tactile input created a realistic virtual kitchen, with a stove, teapots, cabinets and clouds outside a curtained window.</p>
        <p>There was also a virtual spider. The tracker on his finger allowed him to chase the spider with his hand, force it down the sink and grind it up by switching on a virtual garbage disposal. All of which, Mr. Pokorny said, made the wound care seem far less painful.</p>
        <p>''You're concentrating on different things, rather than your pain,'' he said. ''The pain level went down significantly.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hunter Hoffman, a cognitive psychologist at the Human Interface Technology Laboratory at the University of Washington, conducted the experiment with a colleague at the university, Dr. David Patterson, a professor of rehabilitation medicine, surgery and psychology. Dr. Hoffman said that conscious attention was like a spotlight.</p>
        <p>With this therapy, he added, ''we are attracting that spotlight to the virtual world and away from pain.''</p>
        <p>Virtual reality, the name for the interactive artificial worlds created by computers, is finding a place in health care, especially among psychologists.</p>
        <p>It is being used for treating fear of flying or thunderstorms, helping diabetics warm their hands and mitigating the crippling memories of war.</p>
        <p>Although virtual reality for entertainment received much attention in the early 1990's, the systems were too expensive -- nearly $200,000 -- for most applications.</p>
        <p>But the systems, which are now driven by desktop computers, cost as little as $20,000, making them more practical in a growing number of medical and psychological disciplines.</p>
        <p>''You're not watching something, you're in something,'' said Dr. David Ready, a clinical psychologist at the Atlanta Veteran's Administration Medical Center, where a virtual reality system is being used to treat post-traumatic stress disorders in combat veterans. ''All you see is what's in the goggles and all you hear is what's on the headphones.''</p>
        <p>That does not mean the virtual world looks extremely realistic. The one in use at Harborview is a cartoon representation of a kitchen. But nothing else is visible and the scene changes realistically as the user's head swivels, giving the patient a strong sense of being somewhere he or she is not.</p>
        <p>In the study by Dr. Hoffman and Dr. Patterson, published in the March issue of Pain, a British medical journal, patients with skin grafts at the burn treatment center either played Nintendo or wore the kitchen virtual-reality gear during the painful removal of surgical staples.</p>
        <p>One patient thought of his pain 95 percent of the time while playing Nintendo, but just 2 percent of the time while using the virtual reality gear. The other patient went from 91 percent in video to 36 percent in virtual reality.</p>
        <p>''The preliminary findings are exciting,'' said Dr. Mark Jensen, a professor of rehabilitation medicine and a specialist in pain at the University of Washington. ''I think it can be widely used for chronic pain. But it needs to be tried with a variety of painful procedures -- dentistry and dialysis for example -- to see how well it works for those applications.''</p>
        <p>The capacity of virtual reality to convince the mind is also effective in the treatment of phobias. The virtual kitchen with the spider that Dr. Hoffman uses to treat pain can be adapted to treat spider phobias.</p>
        <p>For more than 20 years, for instance, Joanne Cartwright suffered a debilitating fear of spiders. ''I washed my truck every night before I went to work in case there were webs,'' she said. ''I put all my clothes in plastic bags and taped duct tape around my doors so spiders couldn't get in. I thought I was going to have a mental breakdown. I wasn't living.''</p>
        <p>Twelve sessions of spider virtual-reality treatment with Dr. Albert Carlin, a professor of behavioral psychology at the University of Washington, greatly eased her fear. ''I'm amazed,'' she said, ''because I am doing all this stuff I could never do -- camping, hunting and hiking.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Brenda Wiederhold, the director of the Center for Advanced Multimedia Psychotherapy at the California School of Professional Psychology, uses a virtual reality system to treat several kinds of panic and phobia disorders, including fear of flying.</p>
        <p>For the treatment at the school, which specializes in training clinicians, patients sit in real airplane seats wearing the head-mounted displays that surround them with realistic airplane interiors. The seats vibrate as the sound of engines is heard.</p>
        <p>As the sweat and rapidly beating heart that accompany panic start to increase, the patient is taught to stop the cascade of negative thoughts by yelling ''stop'' or by using a distraction technique like counting back from 1,000 by 7.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wiederhold also teaches clients how to rein in their anxiety by taking deep slow breaths to slow pounding hearts and reduce the sweating.</p>
        <p>Dr. Larry Hodges, an associate professor of computing at the Georgia Tech College of Computing, developed the fear-of-flying equipment that Dr. Wiederhold uses, and he has created virtual reality software that allows people to experience thunderstorms. He is also working on a virtual audience for people who fear public speaking.</p>
        <p>Using a system Dr. Hodges built, Dr. Barbara Rothbaum, an associate professor of psychiatry and director of the trauma and anxiety recovery program at the Emory School of Medicine in Atlanta, conducted a study of what is known as exposure therapy to treat fear of heights.</p>
        <p>The 10 people who received the treatment all reported a substantial reduction in their fear of heights, while there was no improvement among the 7 in a control group, according to the study results published in The American Journal of Psychiatry in 1995.</p>
        <p>The systems have also proven useful in treating the lasting shock caused by violent wartime experiences. For the last year and a half, Dr. Ready of Atlanta has been treating those with post-traumatic stress syndrome with virtual reality on an experimental basis. The work, so far, is promising in reducing the severity of flashbacks, he said.</p>
        <p>Veterans with stress syndrome put on virtual reality goggles and re-experience violent wartime events, complete with helicopter rides, gunfire and jungle walks. During the therapy, Dr. Ready progressively exposes the patient to realistic simulations of the situations that affected them.</p>
        <p>''I'm like a movie director,'' Dr. Ready said. ''If a guy says, 'I was walking through the jungle and mortars came in,' I bring in the mortars with the computer.''</p>
        <p>During all 12 of the 90-minute sessions, the experiences increase in intensity until the patients begin to experience the stress with increased heart rates and sweating. As the clients begin to react, Dr. Ready talks them through it.</p>
        <p>''During a flashback, a veteran has both feet in Vietnam,'' Dr. Ready said. ''With virtual-reality therapy, he has one foot in Vietnam and one foot in the laboratory. And he's got a buddy there talking to him.''</p>
        <p>So far, Dr. Ready has seen the severity of the symptoms reduced by a third in all 10 people who who have completed the training, on par with other therapies. Early indications are that the effects last for months.</p>
        <p>The realistic nature of virtual reality, the feeling of being there, is also helping to increase the effectiveness of traditional kinds of biofeedback.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan T. Pope, a researcher at the Langley NASA Research Center in Langley, Va., has devised a virtual reality system to treat restricted blood flow to the hands, a problem that afflicts people with diabetes and Raynaud's disease.</p>
        <p>The patient wears sensors on the hand and arm that provide data to a computer, which converts the information into a simulation of the blood-vessel network. The three-dimensional blood vessel graphics are displayed on a computer monitor in a pair of goggles that the patient wears.</p>
        <p>''They see these blood vessels expand and contract in keeping with the temperature at their fingertips and their pulse,'' Mr. Pope said. Because the subjects are immersed in virtual worlds and their conscious attention is solely devoted to hand-warming, the task becomes easier.</p>
        <p>Hand-monitoring is one of the most widely used types of biofeedback for cold extremities, anxiety, migraine and headaches. And now, the approach with virtual reality gear is being tested at the Eastern Virginia Medical School and the University of Virginia for symptoms of diabetes.</p>
        <p>''If you provide a compelling and engaging display,'' Dr. Pope said, ''it's more motivating.'' And, he added, the patients stay with it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
