<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Myth and Superstition in Ancient Medicine</title>
    <meta content="04MYST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS ON HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tarkan, Laurie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nuland, Sherwin B (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mysteries Within, The: A Surgeon Reflects on Medical Myths (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Books on Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Books on Science and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DF1339F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Myth and Superstition in Ancient Medicine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE TARKAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarkan, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laurie Tarkan reviews book The Mysteries Within: A Surgeon Reflects on Medical Myths by Dr Sherwin B Nuland; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Mysteries Within: A Surgeon Reflects on Medical Myths'' by Dr. Sherwin B. Nuland (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2000).</p>
        <p>Don't take the scientist's objective observation for granted, cautions Dr. Sherwin B. Nuland in ''The Mysteries Within.'' Until the 19th century, the greatest thinkers in medicine (Hippocrates, Galen, Paracelsus) turned to supernatural powers, superstition, fanciful spirits and energies to fill the holes in their medical theories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Mysteries Within: A Surgeon Reflects on Medical Myths'' by Dr. Sherwin B. Nuland (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2000).</p>
        <p>Don't take the scientist's objective observation for granted, cautions Dr. Sherwin B. Nuland in ''The Mysteries Within.'' Until the 19th century, the greatest thinkers in medicine (Hippocrates, Galen, Paracelsus) turned to supernatural powers, superstition, fanciful spirits and energies to fill the holes in their medical theories.</p>
        <p>Most memorably, the ancient Egyptians believed that organs were animals with minds of their own. The tradition of magical thinking has died hard. Dr. Nuland writes: ''Mankind naturally inclines in the opposite direction from critical thought; supernature and superstition supersede reason -- reason is a hard-earned product of advanced civilization, requiring, like freedom, eternal vigilance.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Nuland, a clinical professor of surgery at Yale who was praised for his 1994 book ''How We Die,'' tells an engaging tale of five organs -- the stomach, liver, spleen, heart (his favorite) and uterus -- and the history of those who tried to understand them. First, he introduces the reader to each organ and its idiosyncrasies by describing, in edge-of-the-seat fashion, a modern operation on it.</p>
        <p>He then goes back in time, laying out the curious mythology of each organ -- a much slower read, but no less fascinating. Though Dr. Nuland gets sidetracked by his passions for anything scholarly, these tangents make the book engaging on many fronts.</p>
        <p>The final chapters on the uterus provide the most vivid example of the impact early thinkers had on medicine today. He offers this rendering of Plato on the uterus: ''When it remains unfertilized for a long time during the proper season the uterus becomes seriously angry and moves all over the body; by obstructing the outlets of the pneuma [spirit] it prevents respiration, throws the patient in confusion and provokes a variety of other diseases.''</p>
        <p>From this emerged the diagnosis of hysteria, from the Greek for uterus, hystera, (cured, by the way, with genital massage); the term persisted and hampered the treatment of women until recent decades.</p>
        <p>Though Dr. Nuland's warnings of a tendency to turn to magical thinking seem like that of a worried mother, the fact that many patients today put their faith in unproven and often mysterious alternative practices does support his contention and his concern.</p>
        <p>BOOKS ON HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
