<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Truest Measure of Patriotism</title>
    <meta content="04KENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED91739F937A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Truest Measure of Patriotism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Kennedy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, David M</byline>
      <dateline>STANFORD, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Prof David M Kennedy on nature of patriotism in America; says truest patriotism--critical patriotism--will not hesitate to hold up mirror of nation's better, ideal self to expose its wrongs and urge its citizens to right them; says critical patriotism is necessary if nation, conceived in liberty and dedicated to proposition that all are created equal, is to long endure; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Commodore Stephen Decatur, freshly returned in 1816 from subduing the Dey of Algiers and swollen with nationalist fervor, rose to his feet at a banquet in Norfolk, Va., and offered a notorious toast. ''Our country!'' he said, glass held aloft. ''May she always be in the right; but our country, right or wrong.'' Decatur's salute is often cited as the quintessence of American patriotic feeling. It's also the kind of remark that has given patriotism a bad name.</p>
        <p>In our own time, sentiments like Decatur's have fallen far out of fashion, but so has a more tempered and cogent kind of patriotism, a classic case of throwing out the baby with the bath water. ''A patriot is a fool in every age,'' jeered Alexander Pope, but perhaps in no age have patriots been deemed more foolish than in our own. To confess love of country today is to invite sneers from sophisticates, to court banishment to the supposedly lunatic fringe, to risk indictment as smug, stupid and reactionary -- or, vilest of all possible epithets, corny. How did this sorry state of affairs come to be?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Commodore Stephen Decatur, freshly returned in 1816 from subduing the Dey of Algiers and swollen with nationalist fervor, rose to his feet at a banquet in Norfolk, Va., and offered a notorious toast. ''Our country!'' he said, glass held aloft. ''May she always be in the right; but our country, right or wrong.'' Decatur's salute is often cited as the quintessence of American patriotic feeling. It's also the kind of remark that has given patriotism a bad name.</p>
        <p>In our own time, sentiments like Decatur's have fallen far out of fashion, but so has a more tempered and cogent kind of patriotism, a classic case of throwing out the baby with the bath water. ''A patriot is a fool in every age,'' jeered Alexander Pope, but perhaps in no age have patriots been deemed more foolish than in our own. To confess love of country today is to invite sneers from sophisticates, to court banishment to the supposedly lunatic fringe, to risk indictment as smug, stupid and reactionary -- or, vilest of all possible epithets, corny. How did this sorry state of affairs come to be?</p>
        <p>Always a plural people, Americans in recent years have grown downright fractious -- not a condition that conduces to patriotic emotion. Loyalties to tribe and race and communities both virtual and vital, not to mention ardor for mergers and startups and global networking, have apparently crowded out love of nation. The booming economy also tends to make mere sunshine patriots of us all.</p>
        <p>''The days of palmy prosperity are not those most favorable to the display of public virtue,'' wrote Edward Everett -- the other speaker at Gettysburg on Nov. 19, 1863, when Abraham Lincoln managed in just three pithy paragraphs to craft a surpassing argument for devotion to American nationhood. Only ''in hard, doubtful, unprosperous and dangerous times,'' Everett claimed in an 1860 essay, do the ''patriotic find their way.''</p>
        <p>It has been a long time since privation and danger have blighted this lucky land. The Civil War was one such occasion. The era of the Great Depression and World War II was another -- a decade-and-a-half-long ordeal when widely shared penury and peril combined to nurture a feeling of common cause and to inspire a truly healthy sense of patriotic feeling. It was a momentous era, one that has lessons to teach us still, not least about our relation to our country.</p>
        <p>The patriotism of the generation that suffered the Depression and waged the war was no witless endorsement of ''our country right or wrong.'' So far from being ''the last refuge of a scoundrel,'' their patriotism was the first haven of those who revered the promise of America even while recognizing its defects.</p>
        <p>Franklin Roosevelt knew how stricken his land was. He demanded relief for the one-third of its people who were ill-housed, ill-clad and ill-nourished. But in the opening words of his first inaugural Roosevelt also affirmed that ''this great nation will endure as it has endured,'' and in the next breath gave his famous warning that ''the only thing we have to fear is fear itself.'' That passage amounted to a fond appreciation of the high value of American institutions, even as F.D.R. was about to extend their embrace to that excluded one-third.</p>
        <p>Popular culture in the Depression decade reflected the same fusion of admonition and attachment. Through all the prodigious outpouring of contemporary photographs, films and writings that documented the Depression's devastation -- works like Walker Evans's and James Agee's portraits of busted tenant farmers in ''Let Us Now Praise Famous Men,'' or Pare Lorentz's dirge for the despoiled Mississippi in his haunting film, ''The River,'' or John Steinbeck's indictment of the ravages of capitalist agribusiness in ''The Grapes of Wrath'' -- there beats a clear subtext.</p>
        <p>All throb with shame for their country, with anger at its failures, but they pulse with unmistakable affection for it, too. The critic Alfred Kazin recognized this distinctively American attitude of what might be called critical patriotism when he described the cultural mood of the 1930's as ''born of the depression and the international crisis,'' but also suffused with a feeling of ''affirmation,'' with ''an insistence to know and to love what it knew.'' It was as if artists and writers in Depression-era America turned instinctively to the better angels of their nation's nature to guide their countrymen through their greatest crisis in nearly a century.</p>
        <p>World War II, of course, unleashed a further upwelling of patriotic fervor. But even wartime patriotism was not without its critical element. Black Americans, for example, embraced the ''double-V'' campaign, demanding both victory over aggressors abroad and victory over discrimination at home, deftly combining loyal commitment with constructive criticism.</p>
        <p>No less striking was the publication in 1944 of the Swedish economist Gunnar Myrdal's classic investigation of race relations, ''An American Dilemma.'' Its basic argument was twofold: in accents that even the most red-white-and-true-blue American could endorse, Myrdal praised ''the American Creed,'' a set of values that included ''liberty, equality, justice and fair opportunity for everybody.''</p>
        <p>But he also composed a withering condemnation of racial oppression, inequality, injustice and denial of opportunity -- probing America's most vexed social issue even during the most anxious months of the war, and thereby helping to lay the foundation for the triumphs of the civil rights movement in the succeeding generation. ''Let us go forth to lead the land we love,'' said John F. Kennedy on the eve of those triumphs. But Kennedy also branded the current treatment of black Americans as a ''moral crisis,'' and summoned his fellow citizens to honor their own best beliefs. That second statement was surely no less patriotic than the first.</p>
        <p>The words ''patriot'' and ''paternal'' stem from the same Latin root, meaning ''father.'' Critical patriotism toward one's country might be likened to the love that fathers and mothers alike ideally tender to their children: unconditional, but still demanding. What good parents do not both love and challenge their young, supporting them but at the same time pushing them to be all they can be?</p>
        <p>Stephen Decatur got it only half right. May our country always be in the right, to be sure. But the truest patriotism -- critical patriotism -- will not hesitate to hold up the mirror of this nation's better, ideal self to expose its wrongs and urge its citizens to right them. Critical patriotism demands not mindless veneration, but strict accountability. It judges as well as celebrates. It is neither foolish nor corny. It is simply necessary if this nation, conceived in liberty and dedicated to the proposition that all of us are created equal, is to long endure.</p>
        <p>David M. Kennedy teaches history at Stanford University. His most recent book, ''Freedom From Fear: The American People in Depression and War, 1929-1945,'' won the Pulitzer Prize.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David M. Kennedy teaches history at Stanford University. His most recent book, ''Freedom From Fear: The American People in Depression and War, 1929-1945,'' won the Pulitzer Prize.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
