<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eccentric and Extreme, A Miler Emerges</title>
    <meta content="18JENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jennings, Gabe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DF103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eccentric and Extreme, A Miler Emerges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gabe Jennings discusses his winning 1,500 meters at Olympic trials to qualify for 2000 Summer Olympic Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gabe Jennings grew up in a wilderness community in northern California where his home was one of the few with indoor plumbing, electricity came from generators and television was nonexistent. He never watched the Olympic track and field trials or the Summer Games until four years ago, when his family had moved to Madison, Wis., and he was a senior in high school, working in a running-shoe store.</p>
        <p>''That was my first taste of the Olympics,'' Jennings said. ''I remember dreaming about where I would be in four years. All kids with aspirations do that. But it's one thing to dream. It's quite another thing to make your dreams come true.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gabe Jennings grew up in a wilderness community in northern California where his home was one of the few with indoor plumbing, electricity came from generators and television was nonexistent. He never watched the Olympic track and field trials or the Summer Games until four years ago, when his family had moved to Madison, Wis., and he was a senior in high school, working in a running-shoe store.</p>
        <p>''That was my first taste of the Olympics,'' Jennings said. ''I remember dreaming about where I would be in four years. All kids with aspirations do that. But it's one thing to dream. It's quite another thing to make your dreams come true.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, using a punishing kick that began with 550 meters left in the 1,500-meter race, Jennings surged to the front and never relinquished his lead at the Olympic trials, winning in a personal-best 3 minutes 35.90 seconds. He is also the collegiate 1,500-meter champion from Stanford who, at 21, is the most visible symbol of an encouraging emergence of young American middle-distance runners.</p>
        <p>He runs with shuffling strides, speaks in jazzy riffs, which befits a music major, and is often referred to as a throwback to the 1960's because of his counterculture nature. He has been known to sleep on the roof of his co-op at Stanford, wear a flowing Moroccan robe around campus and attend his classes in bare feet. Last week, in an online column for Runners World magazine, he ranted about everything from his training to his bowel movements. He credited his victory here to the energy of a full moon and said that his emergence from a bout of depression earlier this season came from consorting with nature, which should not be surprising for a guy whose middle name is Harmony.</p>
        <p>''I feel the earth, the wind, the trees,'' Jennings said. ''I feel its spirit. It puts me in the moment.''</p>
        <p>He resists easy categorizing, however. The laid-back hippie image is popular but incorrect. More accurately, he is a sort of type-A Maynard G. Krebs, emotional, highly driven, wildly elated over success and badly discouraged over defeat, which is the most attractive and troubling aspect about his personality, according to his coach, Vin Lananna.</p>
        <p>Jennings once injured the band of connective tissue that runs down the outside of his legs from clasping bongo drums tightly for hours. To become proficient enough to major in music at Stanford, he played the keyboard six hours a day until he wrenched his back. Wanting to run like a Kenyan, he began trying to train like a Kenyan, logging more than 100 miles a week as a sophomore and developing shinsplints. And he is the rare athlete to injure himself by running too aggressively in a pool.</p>
        <p>''Gabe is a man of extremes,'' Lananna said. ''He strives for perfection. You worry about stuff like that. Every time, you might not be able to be first or get the world record. There's a difference between shooting for this and being devastated if it doesn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Lananna, a native of Brooklyn, has decided to temper his young runner's obsessive training but not to rein in his aspirations for greatness. Stanford has become the epicenter for a revival of hope for American distance running. Jennings's teammate Michael Stember finished third in the 1,500.</p>
        <p>Too much time is spent complaining that environmental, genetic and sociological reasons prevent Americans from competing with Africans and other runners, Lananna said.</p>
        <p>''We're finally coming to accept in the U.S. that the bar is not going to get lower and we need to step up,'' the coach said.</p>
        <p>That step will require a giant leap to the next rung of international competitiveness. ''I feel reborn, ready to run with the big guys,'' Jennings said. Despite his breakthrough performance on Sunday, though, he is nearly 10 full seconds behind the world record-holder and Olympic favorite in the metric mile, Hicham el-Guerrouj of Morocco.</p>
        <p>''I guess I'm running for the silver medal now,'' he said today after being told of el-Guerrouj's enervating training regimen.</p>
        <p>Still, the success of Jennings is not so unlikely as it might sound. He grew up in Forks of Salmon, Calif., on the Salmon River in Klamath National Forest, where the family chopped its own wood for heat and grew its own food in a garden. His parents, Jim and Suzanne Jennings, were teachers at the community school. Once a year, Gabe said, youngsters  from three area communities participated in what was called the River Olympics, which included picnic events like three-legged races but also serious running events. To train for the yearly competition, Gabe said he ran about two miles to school.</p>
        <p>''My dad said, 'If you want to be good, you've got to run to school every day,' '' Gabe said.</p>
        <p>The family moved to Wisconsin when Gabe was 13, first to Jefferson, then to Madison, the capital, which has its own thriving counterculture scene. He played quarterback in junior high, then began running full time when the family moved to Madison, ''where the whole city doesn't revolve around Saturday night football games.'' He won nine state titles, ran a 4:02.81 mile and received a scholarship to Stanford.</p>
        <p>''People who know me don't see it  as conflict,'' Jennings said of his running and his lifestyle. ''The media tries to categorize me, call me hippie, alternative. I work hard. My social life and beliefs don't interfere with my running or get in the way of my training.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday morning, he said, he awakened to find his foot tapping and realized it would be his day. He took his customary nap before the race and awakened so overcome with happiness that he said he began crying. ''I felt like I had already won the race,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With his parents banging drums in the stands, Jennings crossed the finish line first, took off his spikes and heard Lananna say, ''Jennings, put your shoes on.''</p>
        <p>''But coach, I already ran the race,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>Today, as he began the formal processing for the American Olympic team at a local hotel, Jennings wore a gauzy shirt and jeans and carried his slippers in his hand, the soles of his bare feet as black as chimney soot.</p>
        <p>''The bourgeoisie lifestyle makes my skin itch,'' Jennings said. ''I feel a need not to fit the norm.''</p>
        <p>Running for him seems as free as the wilderness that he grew up in, he said.</p>
        <p>''There are no limits,'' he said, ''no boundaries, no fields, no courts to cage you in.''</p>
        <p>Well, he did make one recent concession, he admitted, as a friend approached and congratulated him on the shaving of his goatee.</p>
        <p>''I have to go a little more mainstream,'' Jennings said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
