<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; General Mills is under pressure to make its Pillsbury deal pay off.</title>
    <meta content="Y18PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Mills Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pillsbury Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Diageo Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DA133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; General Mills is under pressure to make its Pillsbury deal pay off.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance L. Hays</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on General Mills Corp's acquisition of Diageo PLC's Pillsbury unit; says General Mills, which has served notice that it wants to be king of convenience foods, is under pressure to make its Pillsbury deal pay off; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN announcing that it would pay $10.5 billion for Pillsbury, General Mills served notice yesterday that it wanted to be the king of convenience foods, an important area for time-pressed consumers and the companies that want their business.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street turned the tables on General Mills, putting pressure on the company to make the deal with Diageo, the owner of Pillsbury, pay off. Concerns about the bite the acquisition will take out of earnings for the foreseeable future caused investors to push down General Mills' share price by $2.6875, or 7.4 percent, to $33.625.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN announcing that it would pay $10.5 billion for Pillsbury, General Mills served notice yesterday that it wanted to be the king of convenience foods, an important area for time-pressed consumers and the companies that want their business.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street turned the tables on General Mills, putting pressure on the company to make the deal with Diageo, the owner of Pillsbury, pay off. Concerns about the bite the acquisition will take out of earnings for the foreseeable future caused investors to push down General Mills' share price by $2.6875, or 7.4 percent, to $33.625.</p>
        <p>Particularly distressing was the company's forecast of a 20 percent reduction in earnings the next two years. While investors had expected earnings of $2.20 a share in fiscal 2001, they will get $1.73, estimated John M. McMillin, a food stocks analyst at Prudential Securities.</p>
        <p>''The stock is down because when General Mills shareholders saw that 20 percent hit, they felt like they needed one of Diageo's stiffest drinks,'' Mr. McMillin said. With Pillsbury off its books and a partial spinoff of Burger King under way, Diageo becomes a company focused on its global liquor and beer businesses. Diageo's American depository receipts gained 62.5 cents, to $36.4375.</p>
        <p>Stephen W. Sanger, chairman and chief executive of General Mills, said the combination would make the company the fifth-biggest food maker in the United States, with more than 80 percent of its products in the convenience-food or quick-preparation categories. He also predicted that it would add to earnings in 2004 through product innovation, international expansion, a doubling of the company's food-service business and savings from streamlining production and purchasing. Mr. Sanger said he planned to keep all the brands, except for the Pillsbury cake mixes and Green Giant canned vegetables.</p>
        <p>Sacrificing some earnings along the way to a sound strategic goal can be palatable to investors if a company is in a rapidly growing industry. But in the food industry, where growth of 5 percent is respectable these days, the specter of diminished earnings made investors uneasy.</p>
        <p>''I'm used to hearing that from Amazon, but that is not what you want to hear from a food maker,'' said Daniel Peris, a stock analyst with Argus Research who downgraded General Mills. ''When investing in a food company, one is looking for stability.''</p>
        <p>General Mills is already a player in the cereal, cake mix, yogurt and meal-solution areas of the supermarket, where its brands include Lucky Charms, Betty Crocker, Yoplait and Hamburger Helper. The merger will give it a presence in some other aisles, with products like Green Giant frozen vegetables, Progresso soups, Pillsbury ready-to-bake biscuits and Haagen-Dazs ice cream.</p>
        <p>The combination would seem to make a stronger company. But some analysts and investors are concerned that fitting all those new elements into the corporation will take up much of management's attention -- maybe more than they bargained for.</p>
        <p>''There remains skepticism about whether General Mills can really use this acquisition to grow its top line,'' said Erika Gritman Long, an analyst with J. P. Morgan. ''People are very focused on what Pillsbury's been able to do. The data the company gave was that it grew 1 percent, while the rest of the category grew 4 percent. It has lagged its own category.''</p>
        <p>Still, the deal represents the so-called second stage in food-company consolidation. In the first stage, top companies like Bestfoods and Nabisco were swept up for premium prices. Now, with companies of similar size pairing off to improve their competitive position against behemoths, the task gets more complex.</p>
        <p>''These mergers of equals are going to require work,'' Mr. McMillin said. ''I do think this will build a better General Mills, but they are having to take a step back. There were people in the room today at the analysts' meeting who were wondering, 'Are they marrying the girl next door just because she's the girl next door? Or were they really dying to get their hands on the Doughboy?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanger said he was enthusiastic about the Pillsbury lineup and was convinced the market would share his enthusiasm once the news was absorbed. There is a $642 million bet riding on that, by the way. Under terms of the deal, General Mills has to pay just $4.5 billion in cash, together with $5.4 billion in stock, if the share price reaches $42.55 within a year after the deal closes in December. If the price is $38 a share or lower, it pays $5.1 billion in cash, along with the stock.</p>
        <p>''It's a bet that doesn't look too good out of the gate,'' Mr. McMillin said. ''But it's a creative way to share the potential benefits down the road.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
