<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Look at the Other Central Figure In the Famous Case of Oscar Wilde</title>
    <meta content="18WILD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilde, Oscar (1854-1900)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murray, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Douglas, Alfred (Lord) (1870-1945)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bosie (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Oscar Wilde</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E2DD133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Look at the Other Central Figure In the Famous Case of Oscar Wilde</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Douglas Murray, Oxford University student who has written a biography of Lord Alfred Douglas, Bosie, says Oscar Wilde was prosecuted for his relationship with male prostitutes, not his relationship with Douglas; notes Douglas spent two years Wilde was in prison defending Wilde and seeking his release; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I am true Love, I fill the hearts of boy and girl with mutual flame,'' Lord Alfred Douglas wrote in 1892, when he was 22. ''I am the Love that dare not speak its name.'' And oh, he was dangerous, pouty lipped, sweet voiced, capable of ruining the thing he loved best.</p>
        <p>''I know Hyacinthus, whom Apollo loved so madly, was you in Greek days,'' Douglas's lover, Oscar Wilde, wrote to him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I am true Love, I fill the hearts of boy and girl with mutual flame,'' Lord Alfred Douglas wrote in 1892, when he was 22. ''I am the Love that dare not speak its name.'' And oh, he was dangerous, pouty lipped, sweet voiced, capable of ruining the thing he loved best.</p>
        <p>''I know Hyacinthus, whom Apollo loved so madly, was you in Greek days,'' Douglas's lover, Oscar Wilde, wrote to him.</p>
        <p>And of course Douglas, or Bosie, as he was called, has gone down in history as the man who ruined Wilde. In 1895 Wilde was convicted of ''gross indecency'' and imprisoned because of his homosexuality.</p>
        <p>But 20-year-old Douglas Murray, who is ending his second year at Magdalen College, Oxford, thinks that Lord Alfred, who died in 1945, has gotten a bad rap. Mr. Murray is the author of ''Bosie,'' a new biography of Douglas (Talk Mirimax Books/Hyperion, $27.95). Wilde ''was not sent to prison for Douglas,'' Mr. Murray said.</p>
        <p>''He was prosecuted for his relationship with rent boys,'' he added, using a term for male prostitutes.</p>
        <p>''Bosie spent the two years Wilde was in prison defending Wilde, writing articles to newspapers,'' Mr. Murray said. ''He petitioned Queen Victoria for the release of Wilde.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murray, who has been called the youngest biographer in England by British newspapers, was speaking on the telephone from Magdalen, Lord Alfred's former college. He said he had uncovered hundreds of letters that had not been seen by previous biographers. And he added that he has drawn a more balanced portrait of a man who has been portrayed as the epitome of spite and manipulativeness.</p>
        <p>Douglas was born in 1870 into a noble Scottish family, the son of the famously nasty Marquess of Queensberry. He met Wilde, by then the successful author of ''The Picture of Dorian Gray,'' in 1891. Wilde was bloated, awkward, a married father of two sons. He was soon besotted, although their sexual relationship seems to have been brief. Bosie taunted Wilde by taking other lovers.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Bosie and his father had a hysterical dislike for each other. ''You impertinent jackanapes,'' his father wrote him.</p>
        <p>And after Bosie received a letter from his father condemning his homosexuality, he wrote back, trying to infuriate him, ''What a funny little man you are.'' It was Douglas who urged Wilde to sue for libel after his father delivered a card to Wilde that the Marquess later testified was meant to read, ''For Oscar Wilde -- Posing as a sodomite.'' Wilde lost, but that trial led to the one that resulted in his imprisonment.</p>
        <p>While in prison Wilde turned on Douglas himself, writing the famous ''De Profundis,'' a long diatribe against Bosie. Although it contained some of his finest prose, the letter also took Bosie to task for slights like failing to serve him lemonade when he was ill.</p>
        <p>When Wilde, broken in body and spirit, was released in 1897, the two men reunited. Apparently they did not resume a sexual relationship but rented a villa in Italy, pursuing their writing and influencing each other's work, Mr. Murray said.</p>
        <p>Finally Bosie's mother threatened to cut off his allowance if he didn't leave Wilde. Bosie agreed, but only after his mother promised to give Wilde money. When Wilde died in 1900 from injuries suffered in a fall in prison, Bosie mourned him desperately and paid for his funeral.</p>
        <p>Bosie's biographer, Mr. Murray, was born in West London. His father is a civil servant, his mother a teacher. His older brother is a lawyer. At 8 he began singing in the St. Margaret's Church choir. He went on to the Royal Academy of Music, then won a scholarship to Eton, which he was the first in his family to attend. Mr. Murray said he was 14 when he came across ''De Profundis.'' He went on to read Douglas's poetry and was entranced by it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At first, he explained, he planned to write about Douglas's poetry but discovered how autobiographical it was and decided to write his life  instead. After Eton, when he was about 17, he said, he began researching and writing the book. At the time he was teaching at a school near Aberdeen, Scotland.</p>
        <p>Douglas's executor, Sheila Colman, who, with her husband, looked after Douglas in his final months, made his papers available to Mr. Murray. After he finished the manuscript, Mr. Murray said he sat on it for a year. Then, in his second term at Oxford, he was introduced to Belinda Harley, a literary agent, who quickly sold it.</p>
        <p>In writing Douglas's biography, Mr. Murray had to contend with Douglas's malice and his anti-Semitism. ''The effort of spending time on him was only partly possible because he was such an interesting and variable character,'' Mr. Murray said. ''The fact that he changed so much, that fascinates me.''</p>
        <p>After Douglas left Wilde, he renounced homosexuality, converted to Roman Catholicism and married Olive Custance. The marriage failed. ''Bosie and Olive got on each other's nerves,'' Mr. Murray said. ''But in later life, they saw each other every day. He was absolutely distraught when Olive died.'' They had one son, Raymond, who was institutionalized at 24 for schizophrenia. Douglas fought for custody of his son, but it was denied because of his relationship with Wilde.</p>
        <p>Eventually Douglas became a carbon copy of his father. He denounced Wilde, calling him talentless. He became so litigious, Mr. Murray said, that ''at one point in the 1900's he couldn't stand in court for one case because he was running in four cases at the same time.'' In 1923 Douglas accused Winston Churchill of engaging in war profiteering with Jewish friends and helping to blow up Lord Kitchener.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murray said Douglas taunted Churchill, saying, ''If you honestly believe you're not guilty, then why haven't you sued me?'' Churchill did sue and won, and Douglas went to prison for six months.</p>
        <p>Douglas ended his life penniless, his talent exhausted, living in a basement apartment in Sussex. When he applied to the state for a pension, it was denied because of his past.</p>
        <p>But in his 1938 memoir, ''Without Apology,'' he seemed to have achieved some understanding of his life. In one passage he referred to Wilde's last work, ''The Ballad of Reading Gaol'': ''The thought that has only recently occurred to me is a terrible one. Did my father really love me all the time, as I certainly loved him before he turned against me, and was he only doing what Oscar says in his great ballad all men always do, killing the thing he loved? Didn't we all three, Wilde, my father and I, do it, more or less?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
