<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welcoming Different Ideas Into a Playwrights' Nest</title>
    <meta content="18ONEI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Playwrights Conference</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Houghton, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gussow, Mel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DE133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welcoming Different Ideas Into a Playwrights' Nest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gussow, Mel</byline>
      <dateline>WATERFORD, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Houghton, new artistic director of National Playwrights Conference at Eugene O'Neill Theater Center, Waterford, Conn, comments on his efforts to put conference's stress even more firmly on writers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 35 summers the National Playwrights Conference has been the tall ship of the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center, giving a berth to hundreds of new plays and new playwrights. This year there is a major difference: James Houghton as the new artistic director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houghton, 41, the founder and director of the Signature Theater Company, has succeeded Lloyd Richards, 80, the first, and until now, the only head of the conference commonly known as ''the O'Neill.'' Looking ahead, Mr. Houghton said, ''The O'Neill is about to be born again.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For 35 summers the National Playwrights Conference has been the tall ship of the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center, giving a berth to hundreds of new plays and new playwrights. This year there is a major difference: James Houghton as the new artistic director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houghton, 41, the founder and director of the Signature Theater Company, has succeeded Lloyd Richards, 80, the first, and until now, the only head of the conference commonly known as ''the O'Neill.'' Looking ahead, Mr. Houghton said, ''The O'Neill is about to be born again.''</p>
        <p>In his first season at the conference Mr. Houghton is trying to put the emphasis even more firmly on the writers, and he has made small but significant alterations. For the first time all the writers are living on the O'Neill ''campus'' for the month of their residency instead of being boarded at a nearby college, and they are encouraged to bring their families with them.</p>
        <p>On a recent weekend, playwrights were very much in evidence in the grand O'Neill environment, an elegant estate with a green lawn leading down to Long Island Sound. The writers were in rehearsals or staged readings, talking to members of the staff or simply meeting their colleagues and comparing notes about their plays in progress.</p>
        <p>In the past there were critical forums following the readings, with directors, dramaturgs and critics (from the National Critics Institute, an adjunct of the conference) speaking out about the plays while the playwrights were asked to remain silent. In some cases the result was a wounded playwright. Now there are no longer such sessions. Criticism of the work may be offered privately and informally.</p>
        <p>Greeting the audience at the opening event of the monthlong conference, a staged reading of ''Parts Unknown,'' a new play by Ron Fitzgerald, Mr. Houghton spoke about ''the need to take the time and to have the patience to allow the writers to create.'' He said that when the process works, ''it elevates us all.''</p>
        <p>John Henry Redwood, one of this year's playwrights, was at the O'Neill in 1995 with ''The Old Settler,'' which was later presented at Primary Stages in Manhattan. Looking back on his first residency, he said, ''It served me, and it served the play.'' His new play, about the rape of a black woman by a white man in North Carolina in 1949, has the provocative title ''No Niggers, No Jews, No Dogs.'' Mr. Redwood, who is black, said he was aware that the title might present problems for any theater producing the work. Informally, he was referring to it as ''The No Play.''</p>
        <p>In the limited rehearsal time he had not done much work on it, but the actors (Tonya Pinkins and Ruben Santiago Hudson) and David Esbjornson, as director, were adding their touches. The playwright said he would be seeing the results that evening when the play had the first of two readings.</p>
        <p>On opening night theatergoers, some from Boston, some from New York, many of them from the O'Neill center and the surrounding area, filled the bleachers in the outdoor theater, named the Edith in memory of Edith Oliver, the longtime Off Broadway critic for The New Yorker and an O'Neill dramaturg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houghton made his introductory remarks, again stressing that the conference was for the playwrights. Then on an open stage under a large tree Mr. Redwood's play began. After the performance, as is customary at the O'Neill, the actors did not take a curtain call. But the audience, realizing that the playwright was seated in a rear row, rose, turned and applauded him.</p>
        <p>Afterward there was no critical forum, no outsiders dissecting a writer's work, but Mr. Redwood has the option of private conversations with his director, Mr. Houghton or others. Then, in the O'Neill tradition, he can go back to work on his new play.</p>
        <p>Each year at this conference a dozen or more plays go through a period of brief but intensive rehearsal and then have public readings on the various stages. Many of the plays have gone on to great success, beginning with the work of August Wilson.</p>
        <p>George C. White created the center in 1964, leasing eight and a half acres of the former Hamman Estate. The following year, with Mr. Richards, he began the playwrights conference. The center itself also includes a music theater conference, a symposium on cabaret, the National Theater Institute and the Monte Cristo Cottage, Eugene O'Neill's childhood home in nearby New London. Mr. White, 64, is retiring at the end of this year, to be succeeded as executive director by Howard Sherman, 38, the managing director of the Geva Theater in Rochester. During Mr. White's years in Waterford, the O'Neill has inspired similar conferences in other states and also in Russia and China.</p>
        <p>In an interview Mr. Houghton said that he admired the pioneer work of Mr. Richards and Mr. White, but he also made it clear that he was aware of his position as a new artistic director in a new century. He said that his first responsibility was ''to empower the playwrights, to give writers a place where they can explore their plays in a relatively safe environment.''</p>
        <p>In various developmental programs ''there are too many chefs in the mix way too soon,'' he said. ''I'm trying to take the emphasis away from fixing and doctoring plays and to encourage writers to listen to the impulse that's inside them and to honor that impulse. Across the country plays are being 'developed' to death. I'm encouraging a notion of play evolution versus play development. I want to let a play find itself and to let a writer find himself within a play.''</p>
        <p>This year there are 13 playwrights at the O'Neill, ranging from Sarah C. Diamond, who is there with her first full-length play, to experienced writers like Lee Blessing and Daisy Foote. There are also several graduates of the playwriting seminar taught by Marsha Norman and Christopher Durang at the Juilliard School.</p>
        <p>In previous years four or five directors would each stage three plays. Now there are 13 directors, one for each play. Mr. Houghton has also made staff changes, and many of the actors are new to the O'Neill. There are three special projects, including one (written by John Belluso and directed by Joseph Chaikin) that dramatizes experiences of the disabled.</p>
        <p>Computers have been installed, and a script department helps playwrights find information. For example, Wendy Hammond, one of this year's playwrights, needed to clarify a minor point in her play. She wanted to know if a cell phone could be bugged. After inquiries were made to the C.I.A. and the F.B.I., she was quickly given an affirmative answer.</p>
        <p>Some things remain the same. Plays are rehearsed over a four-day period, and when they are performed, actors carry their scripts onstage. There is a minimum of modular scenery. The emphasis is on the process, and during the remainder of their time at the conference playwrights can restudy and reshape their plays. As in the past the O'Neill is a cross between a festival and an adult summer camp, with playwrights, actors and directors freely communicating. Wherever one turns, there is theater talk: over meals, a drink in the O'Neill pub or a walk across the lawn.</p>
        <p>In earlier days producers and agents often scouted plays. Mr. White said that there was one stricture. No negotiations were to take place on the O'Neill grounds: ''If a playwright said, 'So and so is interested in my play, who's interested in yours?,' that would ruin a playwrights conference.'' As before Mr. Houghton places no restriction on who can see the plays; they are open to the public.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the principal change is in the play selection process, which has been broadened geographically as well as aesthetically. In order to ''open this conference up to a national theatrical landscape,'' Mr. Houghton enlisted readers from around the country, more than 60 theater professionals who read plays without knowing the names of the authors (always the case at the O'Neill). This year the process winnowed 750 submissions to 45, which then went before a selection committee. Every script accepted had been read by four people. Mr. Houghton said that as director he retained the prerogative to name two writers of his own choice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houghton has invited guest artists (Edward Albee, Paula Vogel, Ed Bullins and Doug Hughes, the head of the Long Wharf Theater in New Haven) to give seminars. In one session Romulus Linney spoke to the playwrights about his own choice of material for plays, saying that even when the subject is historical, it has a relationship to his own life. He also suggested that the playwrights have to take responsibility for their work. ''You have to decide at what point you're willing to please people in order to get your play on,'' he said, ''and at what point you don't care if they do it or not.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Linney the Signature Theater was a turning point. After Mr. Houghton had appeared as an actor in one of Mr. Linney's plays, he raised the possibility of producing an entire season of his work in New York. That was the beginning of the Signature, and it was followed by seasons of plays by Mr. Blessing, Mr. Albee, John Guare, Arthur Miller and others. It was Mr. Houghton's work with playwrights at that company that brought him to the attention of the O'Neill.</p>
        <p>Mr. White said the principal reasons he was chosen to head the conference were that he was highly recommended by a search committee of playwrights and other theater professionals and that he had never been to the O'Neill before. ''I wanted somebody to come in and see it fresh,'' Mr. White said. ''He brought no baggage, none of this, 'It's always been done this way.' '' He added: ''The O'Neill needed an infusion of youth. There's a new spirit blowing here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
