<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks' Frustration With Weis Is Growing</title>
    <meta content="18KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weis, Frederic</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0DE103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks' Frustration With Weis Is Growing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, July 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses future of 7-foot-2-inch basketball player Frederic Weis with New York Knickerbockers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He has been criticized for everything from his wind to his lack of toughness, and knowledgeable basketball people question whether the 7-foot-2-inch Frederic Weis will ever be good enough to move into the rotation of a National Basketball Association team.</p>
        <p>But when the Knicks and nine other clubs began the Shaw's Pro Summer League at the University of Massachusetts-Boston today, Weis was the most sought-after and intriguing player on any roster. Despite the many doubts about his ability, Weis has become a mystery man, one that even his American agent, the bewildered Frank Catapano, cannot solve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He has been criticized for everything from his wind to his lack of toughness, and knowledgeable basketball people question whether the 7-foot-2-inch Frederic Weis will ever be good enough to move into the rotation of a National Basketball Association team.</p>
        <p>But when the Knicks and nine other clubs began the Shaw's Pro Summer League at the University of Massachusetts-Boston today, Weis was the most sought-after and intriguing player on any roster. Despite the many doubts about his ability, Weis has become a mystery man, one that even his American agent, the bewildered Frank Catapano, cannot solve.</p>
        <p>Like Knicks General Manager Scott Layden, Catapano has no idea why Weis did not arrive in New York on an airplane Sunday afternoon. He spoke with Weis's European agent, Didier Rose, an hour before the plane was supposed to land and was told that Weis was on it. Since then, he has not been able to contact Rose.</p>
        <p>''They're coming here by air balloon,'' Catapano joked today. ''Really, I have no idea why he's not here. None at all.''</p>
        <p>Theories abound as to why Weis, who averaged just 8.1 points and 6.2 rebounds a game in France last season, has remained in Europe.</p>
        <p>His story since June has been that he is tending to his sick father. There is also the belief that he may be close to signing a deal with a team in Europe, perhaps Olympiakos of the Greek League.</p>
        <p>Then, there is the speculation that Rose is playing hardball with the Knicks in hopes of getting them to tender his client a contract before Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>''I haven't been told that he has a deal with another team,'' said Catapano, who insisted that Weis wanted to play in New York. ''From my standpoint, that's not why he's not here.''</p>
        <p>If Weis, the 15th selection of the 1999 draft, signs with a European team before Sept. 1, the Knicks retain his rights once the contract ends. If he signs after Sept. 1 and the Knicks do not offer him a contract, they lose their rights to him. ''I've talked at length to Frank Catapano and we've put in calls to his French agent, Didier, but we're not sure why he hasn't shown up,'' Layden said. ''So we'll just have to wait and see.''</p>
        <p>After extravagantly entertaining Brian Grant last week, the Knicks continue to hold out hope for pulling off a sign-and-trade deal with Portland. While Grant closed his New York visit by saying he could see himself playing for the Knicks, it is highly doubtful that he will end up calling Madison Square Garden home. The Blazers are demanding either Latrell Sprewell or Allan Houston from the Knicks, who are trying fruitlessly to entice them with a package involving Marcus Camby.</p>
        <p>Mark Bartelstein, Grant's agent, said his client, who is being courted by several other teams and will soon visit Detroit, will not sign for the $2.25 million midlevel exception, which is all the Knicks can offer him as a free agent. It is also beginning to look as if Boston's Danny Fortson, the other player at the top of the Knicks' list of power forward hopefuls, could also wind up elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Lakers, Golden State, Orlando and Atlanta are looking into sign-and-trade deals with Boston, which is believed to have offered Fortson a seven-year deal worth close to $42 million. Fortson is expected to visit Golden State soon, and the Lakers may have replaced the Knicks as his top choice.</p>
        <p>It is not out of the question that the Knicks may try to rekindle talks with Grant Hill, whom they tried to woo heavily two weeks ago. Hill has orally committed to playing in Orlando next season, but with Tim Duncan's recent announcement that he will remain in San Antonio, there is the possibility that he may reconsider.</p>
        <p>No contracts can be signed before Aug. 1, so the Knicks have two weeks to try and sell him on their team. Layden would not discuss Hill, but neither would he rule out anything. ''Everything I've seen reported is that he's going to Orlando,'' he said.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks lost their opening game of the tournament, 69-62, to the Milwaukee Bucks, but the former St. John's standout LAVOR POSTELL was a bright spot. Impressing everyone but himself, Postell made 8 of 15 shots in leading all scorers with 20 points. He showed aggressiveness, skill off the dribble and with the jump shot. He converted two of four 3-point shots, but was disappointed because he had no assists, one rebound and two turnovers. ''It was horrible,'' Postell said. ''I didn't have an all-around game. I didn't get any rebounds, any assists and my man scored too many points.'' Postell was guarding MICHAEL REED, who scored 13 points.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
