<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Prozac Takes Center Stage, In Furor</title>
    <meta content="18PROZ$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prozac (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antidepressants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goode, Erica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glenmullen, Joseph (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Healy, David (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Prozac (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antidepressants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antidepressants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DD133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Prozac Takes Center Stage, In Furor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERICA GOODE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goode, Erica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prozac is at center of new furor as result of books by Drs Joseph Glenmullen and David Healy claiming that antidepressants are often indiscriminately prescribed and that long-term use may cause brain damage; claims have drawn harsh criticism from scientists, psychiatric clinicians and mental health groups, who view them as alarmist and overblown; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prozac has never been just any drug.</p>
        <p>Soon after arriving on drugstore shelves 12 years ago, Eli Lilly's antidepressant transcended simple pilldom, becoming instead a cultural icon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prozac has never been just any drug.</p>
        <p>Soon after arriving on drugstore shelves 12 years ago, Eli Lilly's antidepressant transcended simple pilldom, becoming instead a cultural icon.</p>
        <p>Hailed as a wonder drug one minute, cast as evil incarnate the next, the green and white capsule has generated multitudes of lawsuits, and garnered more attention than some presidential candidates.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because Prozac treats the ills of the mind, not the complaints of the body, it has also served as a kind of public Rorschach test, a screen upon which Americans project deeply rooted attitudes about illness, character, biology and free will.</p>
        <p>So, perhaps predictably, as the drug edges into adolescence and Lilly's exclusive patent on the medication nears expiration, Prozac is once more causing a stir.</p>
        <p>More or less at the center of the newest squall are two psychiatrists, Dr. Joseph Glenmullen, the author of a recently published book, ''Prozac Backlash'' (Simon &amp; Schuster), and Dr. David Healy, author of ''The Antidepressant Era'' (Harvard University Press, 1998). They claim that Prozac and its chemical cousins are often indiscriminately prescribed and have more serious and more frequent side effects than the public is aware of or than the package labeling indicates.</p>
        <p>Many of their assertions are old ones, in particular the notion that the drugs cause some people to become suicidal or violent, an accusation that Lilly and other antidepressant manufacturers deny and that has so far failed to persuade juries in product liability lawsuits.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Glenmullen, who is on the staff of the Harvard University Health Services, and Dr. Healy, a lecturer in psychological medicine at the University of Wales College of Medicine, raise new fears. They suggest that Prozac and similar drugs, like the antipsychotic medications of the 1950's and 1960's, might pose a significant risk of neurological side effects, that long-term use of the drugs might cause brain damage and that future generations might look back on the antidepressants and other psychiatric drugs, in Dr. Glenmullen's words, ''as a frightening human experiment.''</p>
        <p>''Too many people have been lulled into thinking that they have no side effects and no risk,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The contentions of Dr. Glenmullen, Dr. Healy and other critics, however, have themselves drawn harsh criticism from scientists, psychiatric clinicians and mental health groups, who view them as alarmist and overblown.</p>
        <p>Some scientists whose studies are cited in ''Prozac Backlash'' to support its thesis said that the author never contacted them about their work and they strongly disagreed with his conclusions.</p>
        <p>And many psychiatrists said they worried that the new dispute would discourage people with depression from seeking needed treatment.</p>
        <p>''Some of the statements that Glenmullen makes are simply outrageous,'' said Dr. Frederick Jacobsen, a psychopharmacologist in Washington. ''He trashes any benefit of the drugs and selectively quotes studies in a very biased way.''</p>
        <p>The idea that Prozac and its later-arriving relatives are dangerous drugs runs counter to the experience of most psychiatrists and researchers. They see the medications -- which enhance the availability in the brain of serotonin, a neurotransmitter believed to be involved in depression -- as useful, and sometimes lifesaving, tools for treating a variety of psychiatric disorders.</p>
        <p>In their view, the antidepressants have both advantages and limitations. The drugs, called selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors or S.S.R.I.'s, are far less lethal in overdose than the older generation of so-called tricyclic antidepressants, making them more difficult for depressed patients to use in suicide attempts. And they lack some annoying side effects of the earlier drugs, like dry mouth, constipation and weight gain.</p>
        <p>Yet 30 percent to 40 percent of patients given the newer antidepressants receive no benefit from them, a weakness they share with earlier medications. Studies indicate the drugs may be less effective than tricyclics for severe depression. And the medications, like all drugs, have side effects of their own, including loss of libido and other sexual difficulties, which occur in anywhere from 36 percent to 75 percent of patients, and a host of other, mostly mild, adverse reactions.</p>
        <p>Their long-term side effects, if any, are less clear. No scientist can offer an ironclad guarantee that Prozac and its counterparts -- or for that matter, any other potent drugs -- are absolutely safe when taken continuously for long periods.</p>
        <p>Yet what is known, scientists say, suggests that the medications are more benign in their long-term effect on the brain than many other psychoactive drugs. And 12 years of widespread use have convinced most researchers and clinicians of the antidepressants' basic safety.</p>
        <p>''The S.S.R.I.'s are not innocuous,'' said Dr. Matthew Rudorfer, associate director for treatment research at the National Institute of Mental Health's Division of Services and Intervention Research, ''and they should not be used casually. But it's a vast overinterpretation to say that they are dangerous and should be avoided.''</p>
        <p>The Arguments  A Calm Critique Amid Strong Claims</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen and Dr. Healy said they were not opposed to the use of Prozac or similar drugs, and that they prescribed them regularly in their own practices. But they deplore their use for people whose complaints are very mild and they criticize physicians who place patients on the drugs for long periods with little or no supervision, a trend that has increased under managed care.</p>
        <p>Lilly estimates that 38 million people worldwide have taken Prozac since it was introduced in 1988. And 10.3 million new prescriptions for the drug were written in 1999, says IMS Health, a market research firm.</p>
        <p>''For people with only mild to moderate symptoms whose functioning is not compromised,'' Dr. Glenmullen said, alternative approaches, like psychotherapy and exercise, ''are preferable forms of treatment.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen also educates readers of his book about the withdrawal effects -- including nausea, vertigo, flu-like symptoms, mood swings and irritability -- that can result if newer antidepressants are stopped too abruptly. (Prozac, which leaves the body more slowly than other S.S.R.I.'s, is an exception). And both he and Dr. Healy criticize the pharmaceutical companies, which they say influence medical research and often minimize adverse side effects in an effort to make their products look good.</p>
        <p>Yet it is difficult to find scientists or clinicians who support the more extreme suppositions of Prozac's critics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen and Dr. Healy, for example, argue that neurological side effects -- including muscle spasms, facial tics, Parkinson's diseaselike symptoms, extreme agitation and even tardive dyskinesia, a disabling movement disorder -- are more common in patients taking newer antidepressants than the labeling on the drug packaging indicates, and that their occurrence augurs serious problems to come.</p>
        <p>Such side effects are frequently produced by older medications used to treat psychosis. But Dr. Glenmullen said it took decades for doctors to recognize the extent or severity of the reactions.</p>
        <p>''Do we this time want to ignore the early warning signs of these effects with serotonin boosters?'' he asks in ''Prozac Backlash.'' ''Even if disfiguring tic disorders turn out to be infrequent, with tens of millions of people having been on serotonin boosters, hundreds of thousands could be affected.''</p>
        <p>But other scientists say it is misleading to compare antipsychotic drugs, which directly act on the neurotransmitter dopamine, with the antidepressants, which affect dopamine only indirectly.</p>
        <p>''If S.S.R.I.'s do in fact cause tardive dyskinesialike syndromes, and that's far from proven,'' said Dr. William Wirshing, a professor of psychiatry at the University of California at Los Angeles and an expert on neurological problems caused by antipsychotic drugs, ''they do at a rate so low that it's indistinguishable from background noise in the untreated general population.''</p>
        <p>Although some neurological side effects are reported in patients taking Prozac and similar antidepressants, researchers and clinicians say that in their experience the reactions are infrequent; some are so rare that many psychiatrists never see them in years of practice. In many reported cases patients have used other medications, making cause and effect difficult to determine.</p>
        <p>The Prognosis  Cause for Concern Or Reassurance?</p>
        <p>Many scientists said that in their views ''Prozac Backlash'' also blurred distinctions between newer antidepressants and many other types of drugs. In a discussion of possible long-term effects of Prozac and similar drugs, for example, Dr. Glenmullen drew analogies to cocaine and MDMA (the recreational drug known as ecstasy), which are known to cause brain damage, and diet drugs like Redux, which was pulled off the market in 1997.</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen said research was scant on how Prozac and other S.S.R.I.'s affected nerve cells in the brain with long-term use, but he argued that findings on the effects of ecstasy and other drugs offered reason for concern about the antidepressants.</p>
        <p>''Surely we already know enough to indicate these drugs should be prescribed far more cautiously than they typically are today,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>But Dr. George Ricaurte, an associate professor of psychiatry at Johns Hopkins University and a leading expert on ecstasy's effects on the brain, said that MDMA and newer antidepressants ''are two entirely different classes of drugs.''</p>
        <p>''The toxicity produced by MDMA is not produced by Prozac and related drugs,'' Dr. Ricaurte said. ''Quite the contrary, they prevent the toxicity of MDMA and related drugs.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Efrain Azmitia, a professor of biology and psychiatry at New York University and an authority on serotonin, said he regarded the newer antidepressants as ''remarkably effective and in a way, remarkably safe,'' because unlike many drugs their mechanism of action had ''a more physiological flavor, more in harmony with the body's natural rhythms,'' offering the possibility that ''you're not going to all of a sudden see something appear that you didn't see at two years.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen, asked about other scientists' disparate views, said that in his book, ''I'm very careful to be really clear about when I'm talking about S.S.R.I.'s versus other classes of drugs'' and his point was that ''we badly need more research.''</p>
        <p>The Suicide Question  'A Needle In a Haystack'</p>
        <p>Of all the issues raised by Prozac skeptics, the most difficult for many people to sort out is the accusation that the drug is linked to suicide, an association that began in 1990 when a Harvard University researcher, Dr. Martin Teicher, reported on six patients who ''developed intense, violent suicidal preoccupation'' shortly after starting Prozac.</p>
        <p>Dr. Teicher's report was followed by a few other case descriptions from other researchers. Some scientists offered hypotheses about how such an effect, if it existed, might occur.</p>
        <p>One theory centered on an infrequent reaction to Prozac and other medications, a state of agitation and restlessness known as akathisia. In some cases, researchers suggested, akathisia may be so uncomfortable that it sets off suicidal thoughts, or intensifies existing suicidal impulses.</p>
        <p>Other investigators proposed that in rare cases the drugs might paradoxically produce a drop in serotonin levels. Lowered serotonin levels have been associated in some studies with suicide and other forms of violence.</p>
        <p>In the public arena, the suicide question also created a commotion. Of the more than 100 lawsuits filed against Lilly, many have been dismissed, and some -- the drug company will not say how many -- have been settled out of court. Two have come to trial, with both resulting in jury verdicts in favor of the pharmaceutical company. In one case Lilly paid the plaintiffs an undisclosed amount.</p>
        <p>By the mid-1990's, however, most scientists had lost interest in the issue. Several larger studies -- which compared Prozac to other antidepressants or to dummy pills, including a reanalysis of Lilly's clinical trial data -- concluded that subjects on Prozac showed no increase in suicidal acts or feelings; some reported that the drug reduced suicide risk. In 1991, a Food and Drug Administration advisory committee concluded that there was no persuasive evidence for a suicide link, allaying many people's fears.</p>
        <p>The consensus of most researchers was that, in any case, disentangling the effects of the antidepressants from the effects of depression itself, a disease that has a high rate of suicide, was difficult or impossible.</p>
        <p>''It would always be a needle in a haystack,'' said Dr. Rudorfer, of the National Institute of Mental Health.</p>
        <p>For its part, Lilly said there was no data supporting the idea that Prozac increased suicidal risk. ''On the contrary,'' said Dr. Steven Paul, a psychiatrist who is a vice president at Lilly Research Laboratories, ''all the available data supports the fact that Prozac reduces suicidal risk in depressed patients.''</p>
        <p>In reviving the issue, Dr. Glenmullen and Dr. Healy, like earlier critics, focus on Lilly's role in lawsuits and research. They reprise, for instance, accusations that the F.D.A.'s inquiry was tainted by some scientists' drug company ties. And they criticize the larger studies of Prozac and suicide, citing problems in methodology, and pointing out that they were carried out by scientists financed by Lilly or working for the company. They also recycle excerpts from internal Lilly memos, retrieved by lawyers for plaintiffs in earlier lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Dr. Healy recently published a study in which 20 normal volunteers, who told researchers they had no history of depression or other psychiatric problems, were alternately given Zoloft, an S.S.R.I., and reboxetene, another antidepressant that has not been approved for use in the United States. Two of the volunteers, Dr. Healy reported, became acutely suicidal while taking Zoloft.</p>
        <p>Dr. Healy said that compared with the normal suicide rate in Great Britain, the healthy volunteers on Zoloft showed a 2,000-fold increase in suicide risk. He believes the same is true for other S.S.R.I.'s. ''My estimates are that Prozac alone has led to 25,000 people committing suicide'' who would not have otherwise, Dr. Healy said.</p>
        <p>But the Zoloft study, published in a British journal, Primary Care Psychiatry, is controversial. Critics said its methodology was flawed -- for example, they said, the study included no placebo control, the subjects were employees of the hospital where Dr. Healy practiced, and no medical records or other independent sources were evaluated to confirm the subjects' reports about their psychiatric histories.</p>
        <p>To conclude that Zoloft made the subjects suicidal, , said Dr. Wirshing of U.C.L.A., ''is ludicrous.''</p>
        <p>Celeste Torello, a spokeswoman for Pfizer Inc., which manufactures Zoloft, Prozac's closest competitor, said the drug's ''safety and efficacy has been proven time and again, in more than 180 clinical trials involving more than 10,000 patients worldwide.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, some researchers whose early reports on the suicide issue were cited in ''Prozac Backlash'' said they did not agree with the way the issue was characterized in the book.</p>
        <p>One is Dr. Anthony Rothschild, a professor of psychiatry at the University of Massachusetts in Worcester and the author of a 1991 report of three patients who developed akathisia and became more suicidal on Prozac. ''Akathisia can occur,'' Dr. Rothschild said, ''and in some people, who have a previous propensity to feel suicidal and are still suffering from depression, this can sometimes push them over the edge. But is it common? No. Can it be easily recognized and treated? Yes.''</p>
        <p>Even Dr. Teicher, author of the original suicide report, said he viewed the risk for suicide as something ''that clinicians need to be aware of but it's generally not a huge problem.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Teicher, who along with others holds the patent on R-fluoxetene, a refined version of Prozac that Lilly has licensed and is testing in clinical trials as a potential successor to the drug, speculated that patients who became suicidal on Prozac and other drugs in the early 1990's might have done so as a result of the higher doses prescribed by physicians. Lilly's exclusive patent on Prozac expires in December 2003.</p>
        <p>Dr. Glenmullen has written to the F.D.A. requesting that stronger warnings about akathisia and suicides be added to labels for antidepressants.</p>
        <p>But the federal agency, a spokesman said, is satisfied that current warning labels, which mention both akathisia and suicidal thoughts as having been reported since the drugs reached the market, are sufficient. The agency said it had no plans to begin another official investigation into the issue, although it would review any new data that emerged, as it does routinely on topics of public concern.</p>
        <p>In the end, the message for anyone contemplating taking Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil, Luvox or other antidepressants, scientists said, may be simply that drugs have side effects, and the decision to take medication always involves the weighing of benefit against risk.</p>
        <p>''No one should really be on any type of medication for long periods of time unless they have to,'' said Dr. Azmitia, of N.Y.U. ''But some people really can't function unless they are on these drugs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
