<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Tie, U.S. Men Search for Answers</title>
    <meta content="MB032037" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trecker, Jamie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DC103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Tie, U.S. Men Search for Answers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE TRECKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trecker, Jamie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problems besetting US men's national soccer team discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Arena, soaked to the skin by the oppressive humidity of the Guatemalan jungle, looked like a man with a bad migraine Sunday after his team, the United States men's national team, played to a  1-1 draw with Guatemala in a World Cup qualifier -- a match his side should have won.</p>
        <p>That hangover may have gotten a little worse today with this news: Barbados 2, Costa Rica 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bruce Arena, soaked to the skin by the oppressive humidity of the Guatemalan jungle, looked like a man with a bad migraine Sunday after his team, the United States men's national team, played to a  1-1 draw with Guatemala in a World Cup qualifier -- a match his side should have won.</p>
        <p>That hangover may have gotten a little worse today with this news: Barbados 2, Costa Rica 1.</p>
        <p>That shocking result means that the United States now faces extra pressure in its next game on the road, because Costa Rica cannot afford to be humiliated twice. And, should the United States fail to take 3 points, they face the unsettling prospect of falling into last place in their regional qualifying group.</p>
        <p>By any estimation, this can only be called a disastrous start for a team that has plowed millions of dollars into salaries and development costs since starting to take international soccer seriously about a decade ago.</p>
        <p>While the Americans did not make excuses Sunday, they did not have any answers, either. Arena maintained that his side was the superior team, leaving open for interpretation why his squad essentially drifted so badly out of the match in the second half. After getting stellar first half play from the likes of Claudio Reyna, David Regis and Eddie Pope, Arena saw his squad hit the wall and struggle for the final 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>Keeper Kasey Keller was characteristically blunt: ''We were not 100 percent fit coming into this match.''</p>
        <p>''We can't make any excuses,'' defender Robin Fraser said. ''We just didn't do what we had to do.''</p>
        <p>The biggest problem facing the American team, however, is the crippling lack of depth. With Ben Olsen, Jeff Agoos, Eddie Pope and Earnie Stewart injured, Arena has precious few choices for quality replacements.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, the United States has not been able to develop a new cadre of young players inside the country -- in fact, one could be excused for doing a double-take Sunday as the aging Tab Ramos made an appearance as a second-half sub. In many ways, this team is essentially unchanged from the squad that finished a humiliating last in France in 1998. Major League Soccer is still not a factor -- the international game is a much faster, tougher brand than the fairly weak brew that the American league serves up.</p>
        <p>Absent from the team were Gregg Berhalter and John O'Brien. Landon Donovan, who has been stellar for the Olympic squad after under-17 World Cup stardom, is a quality finisher for the future but is also unseasoned.</p>
        <p>And, because of Arena's decision to play with Cobi Jones up front, there are few other forwards available to team with him because Brian McBride (cheekbone) is out injured. Jason Kreis is more comfortable in a withdrawn role while Jovan Kirovski seems to have fallen out of favor. This lack of power up front has been apparent all through this year -- this squad rarely, if ever, tests goalkeepers since it rarely take shots.</p>
        <p>The Americans are going to have to take some against Costa Rica, and that team -- despite this weekend's result -- is a far better one than Guatemala. The United States will have to contend with Harold Wallace and Hernan Medford, two players who tormented the United States in 1998 qualifying. Add in emerging talents Paulo Wanchope and Jafet Sato and it is not a stretch to suppose that Coach Nilson Gomes's squad will be more than a match for the United States.</p>
        <p>JAMIE TRECKER</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
