<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comets' Thompson Leads West to Victory</title>
    <meta content="18WNBA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All-Star Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women's National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurnick, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DD103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comets' Thompson Leads West to Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN GURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurnick, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, July 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Assn All-Star Game held, Phoenix; West defeats East, 73-61; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Professional sports leagues portray themselves as fan-friendly. Val Ackerman, facing a fan uprising, backed up such talk with action by naming Brandy Reed to tonight's Women's National Basketball Association All-Star Game roster.</p>
        <p>Neither the league's fans, who vote for the starting lineup, nor the league's coaches, who pick the alternates, selected a member of the host team, the Phoenix Mercury, to participate in the second renewal of the game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Professional sports leagues portray themselves as fan-friendly. Val Ackerman, facing a fan uprising, backed up such talk with action by naming Brandy Reed to tonight's Women's National Basketball Association All-Star Game roster.</p>
        <p>Neither the league's fans, who vote for the starting lineup, nor the league's coaches, who pick the alternates, selected a member of the host team, the Phoenix Mercury, to participate in the second renewal of the game.</p>
        <p>An embarrassing boycott of the league's nationally televised showcase event was threatened until Ackerman, the W.N.B.A. president, added the Mercury forward.</p>
        <p>''It did seem like it was in the best interests of the fans,'' Ackerman said today during her state-of-the-league address before the game. ''That's the clause I invoked.''</p>
        <p>Reed had a tough game, hitting only 1 of 11 shots and scoring 3 points. But her Western Division teammates fared better in beating the Eastern Division again, 73-61, in front of an announced sellout of 17,717 at America West Arena that included the N.B.A. stars Gary Payton and Jason Kidd and the boxer Mike Tyson.</p>
        <p>Houston Comets forward Tina Thompson, who scored 13 points and had a game-high 11 rebounds, received the most valuable player award. Her West teammate Lisa Leslie of the Los Angeles Sparks, last year's M.V.P., led all scorers with 16 points.</p>
        <p>''They were double-teaming Lisa a little bit, and that left me open,'' Thompson said.</p>
        <p>The West, which won last year's All-Star Game by 18 points, outscored the East in the paint, 46-28, outrebounded the opposition by 20 (60-40) and got 25 second-chance points to the East's 12.</p>
        <p>Ackerman hopes the real winner is the league. The game was a nationally televised vehicle for the W.N.B.A., which, as Ackerman concedes, has an uphill climb in establishing its viability on the professional sports landscape.</p>
        <p>Attendance is down this year compared with last year, and there is no wave of women's sports popularity to ride as there was last year when the United States captured the Women's World Cup soccer championship and put women's sports on the global center stage.</p>
        <p>The league started play this season 10 days earlier than last year to allow players to participate in the Olympics in Australia. But Ackerman said the league did not foresee how that would affect attendance by putting the season's early games up against two rounds of N.B.A. post-season play. In addition, one of the game's most successful players, Houston Comets guard Cynthia Cooper, who missed the All-Star Game with a sprained ankle, has announced she will retire after this season.</p>
        <p>''We are a new business and we face many challenges and quite a few growing pains,'' said Ackerman, a former N.B.A. official. ''We have not had a lot of consistency. We have had expansion, unionization, an extraordinary influx of new players. We've changed the playoff format and changed the start of the season. But I'm proud of where we are. We are very well positioned to grow and our prospects are outstanding.''</p>
        <p>Ackerman said the league, now at 16 franchises, is the largest in women's professional sports and will not expand again at least for another year. She blamed that early start of the season for a decline in per-game attendance of 16 percent compared with last year, but said the gap has closed in recent weeks and she predicted a final season total of 2.5 million, which would be another record for the four-year-old league.</p>
        <p>She said she was pleased that ratings for games televised by the league's three networks -- NBC, ESPN and Lifetime -- were holding steady and reaching 2.5 million viewers a week.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
