<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; French Chefs Cast an Eye On Le Big Mac</title>
    <meta content="18BIG.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcdonald's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDF103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; French Chefs Cast an Eye On Le Big Mac</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column on fast food becoming despised symbol of globalization in France, where men on trial for wrecking McDonald's have become national heroes; interviews with many French chefs on McDonald's food found majority of favorable reviews (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN fast food has become the despised symbol of globalization in France, where the men on trial for wrecking a McDonald's have become national heroes. But there are other gastronomic imperialists with a far more insidious record of globalization: French chefs.</p>
        <p>Shouldn't proud New Yorkers be rising up against the foreigners imposing their tastes on us? How can indigenous cuisine survive when culturally oppressed diners keep giving so much of their money to ruthless French capitalists? Alain Ducasse's new restaurant here (he has 10 others around the globe) has a three-month waiting list of natives desperate to pay $50 for an appetizer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICAN fast food has become the despised symbol of globalization in France, where the men on trial for wrecking a McDonald's have become national heroes. But there are other gastronomic imperialists with a far more insidious record of globalization: French chefs.</p>
        <p>Shouldn't proud New Yorkers be rising up against the foreigners imposing their tastes on us? How can indigenous cuisine survive when culturally oppressed diners keep giving so much of their money to ruthless French capitalists? Alain Ducasse's new restaurant here (he has 10 others around the globe) has a three-month waiting list of natives desperate to pay $50 for an appetizer.</p>
        <p>Some chauvinists might feel an urge to retaliate for the McDonald's attack by spray-painting the rosewood walls and silk upholstery at Ducasse, but violence is not the answer. What we need is a Franco-American dialogue on culinary globalization.</p>
        <p>Seeking to ease international tensions (and perhaps subconsciously hoping to avenge personal humiliations at French restaurants), I asked several of the city's greatest French chefs to contemplate McDonald's cuisine. They were surprisingly kind, even about ketchup.</p>
        <p>''Ketchup is not that bad,'' said Christian Delouvrier, the executive chef at Lespinasse. Mr. Delouvrier, who once had a signature dish of a foie gras ''burger,'' said he had no objection to the ground beef variety.</p>
        <p>''When you eat a good hamburger that's cooked properly, it's delicious,'' he said. When pressed, Mr. Delouvrier couldn't quite bring himself to put the Big Mac in that category, but he was diplomatic nonetheless. ''I'm not interested in a well-done hamburger, but I'm pretty sure some French people like it.'' He also called the French fries ''pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Eric Ripert, the executive chef at Le Bernadin, cheerfully confessed to the occasional Big Mac attack himself. ''I guess I'm becoming a local,'' he said. ''To stop at McDonald's is amusing to me. About twice a year I go. I get the fries and the Coke, and I take a ton of ketchup and mayonnaise with the hamburger. My favorite was the Arch Deluxe hamburger. It was very simple, with a mustardy sauce. I don't know why they stopped making it.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Boulud, the chef responsible for Daniel and Cafe Boulud, recalled a furtive McDonald's meal at Dulles Airport. ''There was no other choice,'' he said. ''I took my hamburger and French fries, went to an empty gate and ate in a corner with no paparazzi around.''</p>
        <p>How was the food? Mr. Boulud was tactful. ''There is no shame in going to McDonald's,'' he said. ''The food is predictable. You go there 20 years later, and it tastes the same. It's very hard for any restaurant to do that. McDonald's is helping a lot of people. If you ask a French kid today what he wants, he will say McDonald's.''</p>
        <p>Then why are the McDonald's bashers so popular in France? ''The French are jealous,'' Mr. Boulud said. ''The hamburger may be the most successful snack in the world. The French wish they could have invented McDonald's.''</p>
        <p>THEN Mr. Boulud made an extraordinary gesture to bring Americans and French together at the peace table. The revered chef from Lyon offered to create a burger.</p>
        <p>I rushed to his restaurant on East 65th Street to witness the grande premiere. Mr. Boulud let me sit in what he called his sky box, a glass-walled room overlooking the kitchen of Daniel, as he deftly assembled the ingredients.</p>
        <p>The bun was a petit pain rond, in texture a cross between a baguette and focaccia. Instead of ketchup, Mr. Boulud used a tomato confit with olive oil, herbs and garlic, plus a horseradish mayonnaise and curly chicory.</p>
        <p>The burger consisted of two patties of Wyoming beef sandwiching a daring central layer: Black Angus short ribs from Colorado that had been braised in red wine sauce, shredded and mixed with black truffles.</p>
        <p>''The braised beef gives it a different dimension,'' Mr. Boulud said. ''It's an adult burger.'' He said he might add it to the lunch menu, perhaps for $26 or $28, although he was also beginning to get into the spirit of McDonald's.</p>
        <p>''I'll call it the DB Burger,'' he said, smiling. ''Maybe we'll open a drive-in window and sell it in a bag.''</p>
        <p>I had intended to head straight from Mr. Boulud's restaurant for a comparative taste test at McDonald's, where, I hoped, the culinary patriot in me would find the Big Mac superior. But I gave up that plan as soon as I bit into the DB Burger. Call me a traitor, but globalization suddenly seemed sublime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
