<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assad Looks at Syria's Economy in Inaugural Talk</title>
    <meta content="Y18SYR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Golan Heights</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Golan Heights</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Bashar al- (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0D6133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assad Looks at Syria's Economy in Inaugural Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, July 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bashar al-Assad gives inaugural speech as Syria's new president, focusing on repairing country's ailing economy; gives no indication that he will be more flexible than late father in negotiating peace deal with Israel; reiterates father's vow that Syria will never make peace until Golan Heights are returned; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his inaugural speech as president of Syria, Bashar al-Assad focused today on repairing his country's ailing economy and gave no sign that he would be any more flexible than his late father in negotiating a peace deal with Israel.</p>
        <p>President Assad, an ophthalmologist by training, officially began a seven-year term after taking the oath of office before the 250-member Parliament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his inaugural speech as president of Syria, Bashar al-Assad focused today on repairing his country's ailing economy and gave no sign that he would be any more flexible than his late father in negotiating a peace deal with Israel.</p>
        <p>President Assad, an ophthalmologist by training, officially began a seven-year term after taking the oath of office before the 250-member Parliament.</p>
        <p>He has been running the country since the death of his father, Hafez al-Assad, on June 10. In a referendum last week, in which the choice was between saying yes or no to Dr. Assad's presidency, he won the approval of 97.29 percent of the voters.</p>
        <p>Recovering the Golan Heights, the Syrian plateau that Israel occupied in the 1967 war, is a top priority, Dr. Assad said. He repeated his father's formulaic language in adding that Syria would not make peace unless all the Golan Heights was returned. ''However long it takes, this land is ours, and it will return to us in full,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Syrian-Israeli peace negotiations have been frozen since mid-January, mainly over a small strip that borders the Sea of Galilee, the major source of Israel's water. Syria has insisted on regaining its section of shore. Israel has sought to maintain control over access to the sea.</p>
        <p>For nine years, American and European efforts have failed to find a compromise that would satisfy both sides. Many Western diplomats had hoped that Dr. Assad, who was an infant when Syria lost the Golan Heights, would bring a less ideological approach to the peace efforts.</p>
        <p>His father, who was defense minister in the 1967 war and president in 1973, when Syria failed to regain the Golan Heights in renewed fighting, repeatedly proclaimed that any compromise with Israel would tarnish Arab dignity.</p>
        <p>Most of Dr. Assad's speech, his first major policy address, was devoted to economic issues. He pledged to reform the economy, which is largely state controlled and dependent on oil exports, by streamlining the bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>Like his father, who spoke about the need for modernization but approved few changes in laws and the ubiquitous security apparatus, the new president pledged to move slowly. Economic change, he said, will come about step by step.</p>
        <p>Business owners, who have labored under a system with no private banks and strict controls on currency, have urged a major overhaul of the economic system.</p>
        <p>Dr. Assad, 34, begins his tenure by eschewing the state-orchestrated personality cult that his father fostered. Newspapers, all run by the state, said he did not want to see his picture adorning every public and private building.</p>
        <p>But he also made a point in his speech of saying he did not intend to pursue political reform that would threaten the dominance of the one-party system that his father built. Freedom of expression should be encouraged, Dr. Assad said, but in the form of ''positive criticism'' of government policies.  Democracy as practiced in the West, he added, cannot and should not be grafted onto Syria.</p>
        <p>''We have to have our own democracy to match our history and culture, arising from the needs of our people and our reality,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
