<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="18OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caffeine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Algae</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caulerpa Taxifolia (Seaweed)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">King County (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Puget Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mediterranean Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Diego (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DD163BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>King County, Wash, water-quality experts abandon plans to use caffeine as tracer to determine where treated waste water flows when it enters Puget Sound; find small concentrations of caffeine in nearly all samples from around sound; a lot of coffee apparently ends up in storm drains and then goes untreated into sound; Caulerpa taxifolia, algae that has caused severe ecological problems in northwestern Mediterranean, is found for first time off West Coast of Americas, north of San Diego; astronomers find simple sugar molecule, glycoaldehyde, in gas and dust cloud near center of Milky Way; discovery bolsters theory that some chemicals thought to be precursors to life formed before planets developed and may provide some insight into how such molecules formed on early earth; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coffee Everywhere</p>
        <p>The jitters brought on by too much coffee can ruin many a delicate, hands-on scientific experiment. But too much coffee, it seems, has ruined a much larger experiment in the latte capital of the world, Seattle.</p>
        <p>Water-quality experts with King County, which includes Seattle, have abandoned plans to use caffeine as a tracer to determine where treated waste water flows when it enters Puget Sound. The problem, they found, is that caffeine is everywhere in the sound.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coffee Everywhere</p>
        <p>The jitters brought on by too much coffee can ruin many a delicate, hands-on scientific experiment. But too much coffee, it seems, has ruined a much larger experiment in the latte capital of the world, Seattle.</p>
        <p>Water-quality experts with King County, which includes Seattle, have abandoned plans to use caffeine as a tracer to determine where treated waste water flows when it enters Puget Sound. The problem, they found, is that caffeine is everywhere in the sound.</p>
        <p>Scott Mickelson, a water quality planner with the county, said that caffeine had been thought to have great potential as a tracer because it was not found naturally in the local environment but got  into the waste water through coffee drinking. The idea was to analyze water samples in the sound for caffeine concentration to determine where plumes of effluent traveled.</p>
        <p>But the scientists found small concentrations of caffeine in nearly all of the samples, totaling more than 200, that they gathered. ''It's all over the place,'' Mr. Mickelson said. Because the sound has about the same concentration of caffeine everywhere, it couldn't be used to determine any kind of gradient that would track waste water flow.</p>
        <p>The problem, Mr. Mickelson said, is that a lot of coffee apparently ends up in storm drains, and then goes directly into the sound. ''We have an awful lot of sidewalk baristas out here, he said, ''and at the end of the day, the dregs go out into storm drains.''</p>
        <p>Troublesome Algae</p>
        <p>A feather-like algae that has caused severe ecological problems in the northwestern Mediterranean has been found for the first time off the West Coast of the Americas. The algae, Caulerpa taxifolia, was discovered by divers with a biological consulting firm studying transplanted eelgrass beds in a coastal lagoon about 20 miles north of San Diego.</p>
        <p>Caulerpa is native to the tropics, and when introduced into more temperate waters it quickly crowds out other species as there are few marine animals that graze on it. It was used for decoration in saltwater aquariums in Europe starting about two decades ago. Then in the late 1980's it was found in the Mediterranean (the source was believed to have been an oceanographic museum in Monaco that drained its tanks).</p>
        <p>The seaweed now covers thousands of acres of the Mediterranean floor from Croatia to Spain, smothering native sea grass beds that are the habitat for many other marine organisms. It spreads rapidly, often carried by the anchors and anchor chains of boats.</p>
        <p>Caulerpa had been available for use in home aquariums in the United States until last year, when its importation was banned. The San Diego patch probably came from aquarium water dumped into a storm drain or into the lagoon directly. The patch, which measures about 60 feet by 30 feet, will be destroyed.</p>
        <p>Clues to Early Earth</p>
        <p>To the list of things found in space -- giant planets, dark matter and the Voyager 2 spacecraft, to name just a few -- can be added sugar.</p>
        <p>Astronomers using a radio telescope on Kitt Peak in Arizona have discovered a simple sugar molecule, glycoaldehyde, in a gas and dust cloud near the center of the Milky Way. With eight atoms of carbon, oxygen and hydrogen, it is one of the more complex of the roughly 120 molecules found in interstellar clouds.</p>
        <p>Given the right conditions, glycoaldehyde can combine with other molecules to form ribose, which is the basis for the nucleic acids RNA and DNA.</p>
        <p>Because the interstellar clouds are the material from which new stars are made, the finding shows that it is increasingly likely that some chemicals that are thought of as the precursors to life formed before the planets developed.</p>
        <p>And because in some cases the conditions in a cloud are similar to conditions on the just-forming earth, the discovery may provide some insight into how such molecules formed on the early earth, the astronomers said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
