<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Syrians, After Generations in Egypt, Are Still French</title>
    <meta content="18EDER$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sole, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Birds of Passage (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1DF133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Syrians, After Generations in Egypt, Are Still French</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews Birds of Passage by Robert Sole; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIRDS OF PASSAGE  By Robert Sole</p>
        <p>Translated by John Brownjohn. 375 pages. Harvill Press. $26.</p>
        <p>For the Syrian colony in Egypt, well to do, long established and Francophile, the favored obstetrician in the 1930's and 40's was a Professor Martin-Berard. The narrator of ''Birds of Passage'' imagines this fashionable doctor palpating his mother's belly and sensing how she and her friends ''adored France without having a drop of French blood in their veins, just as they knew Paris by heart without ever having set foot there.'' And he reflects:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BIRDS OF PASSAGE  By Robert Sole</p>
        <p>Translated by John Brownjohn. 375 pages. Harvill Press. $26.</p>
        <p>For the Syrian colony in Egypt, well to do, long established and Francophile, the favored obstetrician in the 1930's and 40's was a Professor Martin-Berard. The narrator of ''Birds of Passage'' imagines this fashionable doctor palpating his mother's belly and sensing how she and her friends ''adored France without having a drop of French blood in their veins, just as they knew Paris by heart without ever having set foot there.'' And he reflects:</p>
        <p>''And what of us, the occupants of those bellies, the Rafiqs or Nabils, Pauls or Pierres? You, monsieur, were our first contact with the outside world. When our noses or rumps emerged, the hands that hauled us out were French: France was there to greet us! In other words, the concept of a motherland has never been too well defined in our minds.''</p>
        <p>Robert Sole's mischievous birth conceit is about not being too well defined. Not every people can hew to Socrates' caution that the unexamined life is not worth living. Sometimes it is only when there is not too much examining that life remains possible. Perhaps it was better, after all, when the vague ''Yugoslav'' was allowed to blur the exactness of ''Serb'' and ''Croat.'' These weeks, along the Garvaghy Road and other scenic routes in Northern Ireland, the marching Orange Order has been defining those it claims to defend to the point where most of them hardly recognize themselves.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sole, born and raised in Egypt, writes a mix of fiction and history to portray the life of one of the many minorities blown about the Middle East. The narrator's grandfather, Georges Batrakani, comes from a clan settled in Egypt for three generations before him. In long languorous lunches -- Mr. Sole does them wonderfully well -- uncles and cousins embroider dreamy variations on their Syrian origins: from Lombardy or from a Greek Patriarch or, an aunt insists, right back to the Crusaders.</p>
        <p>Identity, though, becomes not what you are but what you are not. The grandmother's relatives left Syria two centuries earlier and, like the Batrakanis, are still not really Egyptian. They are not Muslim either, of course, nor Roman Catholic nor Greek Orthodox. They belong, along with the rest of their community, to a splinter Greek Catholic sect in disputatious communion with Rome.</p>
        <p>The Syrians prospered in an Egypt ruled by the Ottomans, who made a point of giving positions of trust and profit to foreigners, even in the Court of Constantinople. Cut flowers are as decorative as rooted ones, and they don't inconveniently grow or spread. When the British took over in the early 1800's, they found a similar convenience in these same educated and enterprising Syrians and Greeks, aloof to the rising hungers of Egyptian nationalism. When nationalism took over, in the army coup led by Nasser, the aloofness paid its price. The minorities were gradually squeezed or threatened out.</p>
        <p>In his three-generation story, Mr. Sole portrays the rise, golden time and eventual scattered departure of the Batrakanis and their circle. There is George's father, Elias, with no head for business. He settled, instead, for a modest job with the British-run public works department. His lifelong regret (regret is hope backward, and sustains almost as well) was failing to get rich at the building of the Suez Canal. A Cairo millionaire used to trace the origins of his engineering fortune back to having imported 300 cats to solve an advertised rat problem at the canal site. ''I thought of cats too,'' Elias would chime in at family gatherings, ''but I was too busy to answer the advertisement that day.''</p>
        <p>There is George's self-indulgent brother, Nando, who makes a cheerful fortune buying up rural property and taking no account of local resentments till the day he is murdered. There is George's son Michel, who develops an obsession with Hussein Kamil, installed by the British in 1914 with the title sultan (a move against Germany's ally, the Ottoman sultan).</p>
        <p>Michel's obsession stems from childhood, when he was called on to recite a La Fontaine fable during a royal school visit. The Sultan recited ''The Grasshopper and the Ant'' in return. Michel's glory lasts a lifetime: one more member of this Syrian clan who pursues his illusions in Egypt without quite living there.</p>
        <p>Andre, another son, has a clearer vision. This is a result, though, of studying abroad as a Jesuit (only in France did he learn Arabic properly) and returning to take part in his order's painstaking if slipping local involvement. He is the wisest of the Batrakanis: arriving back in Cairo while King Farouk is still in power, he sums up old Egypt in a remark about the baggy-trousered traffic policemen: ''They conveyed all the wretchedness and gentleness of a country that failed to take itself seriously.''</p>
        <p>Mainly, of course, there is Georges, a man of great enterprise and exuberant life: a minor Sun King to family and friends. They share the pleasurable existence he provides for them: meals, expeditions and long summers on the beaches of Alexandria. The key to George's fortune is also the key to its decline. He achieves a near monopoly manufacturing the tarboosh, or fez. It is the national headgear of the old Egypt he lived in and kept an intimate distance from. The new Egypt discards tarboosh and Baktrakanis, though they move and prosper elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''Birds of Passage,'' translated by John Brownjohn from the French, is in a line of other, much greater works that evoke the cosmopolitan redolence of the foreign communities in pre-Nasser Egypt. The Greek-Egyptian Constantine Cavafy comes to mind, and Lawrence Durrell's Alexandria Quartet; but most of all Andre Aciman's recent ''Out of Egypt.'' At its best, ''Birds'' is delightful, despite a junky subplot or two and some thinly fictionalized history. But it is a long way from Mr. Aciman's fictional memoir, which goes beyond a golden look backward to send its characters into the world, their gold devaluing as they live in the puzzlement, displacement, comedy and regret of universal human exile.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
