<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="18MBRF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000720T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFD8133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PEDESTRIAN KILLED  An elderly woman died yesterday after being struck by a tractor-trailer on Amsterdam Avenue in Washington Heights, the authorities said. The police said the woman, a 74-year-old resident of West 164th Street, was crossing Amsterdam Avenue at West 161st Street at noon when she was hit. She was pronounced dead at Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center. The police said that the truck received seven summonses after the accident but that none of its deficiencies contributed to the accident. The police withheld the woman's name because her family had not yet been notified.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PEDESTRIAN KILLED  An elderly woman died yesterday after being struck by a tractor-trailer on Amsterdam Avenue in Washington Heights, the authorities said. The police said the woman, a 74-year-old resident of West 164th Street, was crossing Amsterdam Avenue at West 161st Street at noon when she was hit. She was pronounced dead at Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center. The police said that the truck received seven summonses after the accident but that none of its deficiencies contributed to the accident. The police withheld the woman's name because her family had not yet been notified.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: OFFICERS HIT BY BRICK  Two city traffic agents were assaulted by a man with a chunk of brick late Sunday night after writing a parking ticket in Highland Park, Brooklyn, the authorities said yesterday. The agents, Rhonda Pinkny and Bernice Forte, placed a ticket on a vehicle parked in front of 105 Shepherd Avenue about 11:45 p.m. As they were driving away, a man hurled a hunk of brick through their car's open window, striking Agent Pinkny in the arm and then Agent Forte in the leg. Neither woman was hurt, and there were no arrests in the case.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: POLICE SHOOTING TRIAL  A civil trial involving one of the officers acquitted in the Amadou Diallo case began yesterday with jury selection in Federal District Court in Brooklyn. The trial centers on the shooting death of Patrick Bailey on Oct. 31, 1997. The officers involved in the shooting, including Kenneth Boss, left, who was cleared in the fatal shooting of Mr. Diallo in February, say that Mr. Bailey had a shotgun when the officers fired. Mr. Bailey's parents, who filed the federal suit, say their son was unarmed.</p>
        <p>Alan Feuer (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DRUGSTORE PROTEST  A group of Upper West Side residents plans a protest tomorrow evening against a new CVS store and against what they consider an unwanted proliferation of drugstores in their neighborhood. A four-block area from 102nd to 106th Streets has two Duane Reades, one Rite Aid and one independent drugstore, and the CVS is scheduled to open at 102nd Street and Broadway after Labor Day. Civic associations are scheduled to meet at 7:30 p.m. at Ansche Chesed Synagogue, 251 West 100th Street.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>SYRACUSE: DENNY'S SUIT DISMISSED  A federal judge dismissed a racial discrimination lawsuit brought by nine Chinese-Americans and African-Americans who said they were thrown out of a Denny's restaurant and beaten by white customers while security guards watched. Judge Frederick Scullin of Federal District Court said the plaintiffs failed to show they were denied seating or security services. The Asian-American Legal Defense and Education Fund, which handled the case,  said an appeal was likely.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>NEWARK: AIRPORT CONGESTION WARNING  The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey has called on members of Congress to speed a national plan for easing air traffic congestion and airport construction nationwide. In a May 25 letter to the area's Congressional delegation, the authority noted that recent federal legislation could mean increased noise and flight delays at Kennedy and La Guardia airports. In a statement yesterday, elaborating on the letter, the authority said airlines could immediately increase the number of flights of small regional jets by as much as 640 new flights daily. The change does not affect Newark International Airport.</p>
        <p>Ronald Smothers (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: CONVICTION OVERTURNED  A state appellate panel yesterday struck down the conviction of a man a juror might have accidentally seen in handcuffs. The defendant, Matthew Pugh, had admitted stealing $300 from a Monmouth County mall, but he denied using force, the legal definition of the more serious crime of robbery. The trial judge refused the defense lawyer's request to question a juror who might have seen the defendant being led out of court in handcuffs. The appeals panel found that the trial judge risked allowing the juror to conclude that Mr. Pugh was violent.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: DRUG SENTENCE REDUCED  A state appeals panel yesterday shortened a drug sentence to 7 years from 10 after concluding that the trial judge had been too harsh. In August, the Appellate Division sent the case back for resentencing after the judge ordered the defendant, Ralph Davis, to serve an extended term. Mr. Davis's cocaine possession charge was within 10 years of Mr. Davis's release on a 1963 murder conviction. In reducing the sentence yesterday, the panel said the judge failed to focus on the nonviolent nature of the cocaine charge.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>PARAMUS: 2 FLEE PSYCHIATRIC WARD  Two teenage girls who walked away from a hospital psychiatric ward on Sunday may have had outside help, the authorities said. The girls, who were not identified because of their age, were being held under court order at the Bergen Regional Medical Center. The authorities said they climbed a fence after 1 p.m. and jumped into a car.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: MUSEUM TO EXPAND  Maya Lin, the artist and designer best known for the Vietnam Memorial in Washington, has been chosen to design a new facade and landscaping for the Wadsworth Atheneum, the 156-year-old museum in downtown Hartford and one of the oldest in the nation, museum officials said yesterday. Ms. Lin will help in the expansion of the museum, which is running out of space for exhibits. Ms. Lin won a national competition for the design of the Vietnam Memorial while an undergraduate at Yale in 1981.</p>
        <p>Theresa Crapanzano (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: INMATE ABUSE ALLEGED  State officials are investigating allegations that Connecticut inmates sent to a Virginia prison have suffered physical abuse and racial discrimination. Next month, representatives from the state's Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities are to visit Wallens Ridge Correctional Facility in Big Stone Gap, Va., where nearly 500 Connecticut inmates have been sent to ease crowding in their state's prisons.</p>
        <p>Theresa Crapanzano (NYT)</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 20, 2000, Thursday  A brief report by The Associated Press on Tuesday about the dismissal of a racial discrimination lawsuit filed against a Denny's restaurant near Syracuse, N.Y., misstated the number of plaintiffs and omitted some ethnic groups represented. Ten people sued, not nine. Besides one Chinese-American and three African-Americans, they included one Filipino-American, four Japanese-Americans and one white person.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 20, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A brief report by The Associated Press on Tuesday about the dismissal of a racial discrimination lawsuit filed against a Denny's restaurant near Syracuse, N.Y., misstated the number of plaintiffs and omitted some ethnic groups represented. Ten people sued, not nine. Besides one Chinese-American and three African-Americans, they included one Filipino-American, four Japanese-Americans and one white person.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
