<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eschmeyer Puts Skills To Early Test for Nets</title>
    <meta content="18NETS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eschmeyer, Evan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DE103BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eschmeyer Puts Skills To Early Test for Nets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, July 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets basketball player Evan Eschmeyer discusses his playing in summer league (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hands are steady and, this summer, becoming more sure. But they are not the delicate tools of a surgeon, which Evan Eschmeyer once thought he might become after graduating from Northwestern with a degree in education and a minor in pre-med.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if my hands will last,'' he said jokingly today after grabbing rebounds and banging bodies with some free agents in a shoot-around to prepare for the Nets' first game in the Shaw's Pro Summer League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hands are steady and, this summer, becoming more sure. But they are not the delicate tools of a surgeon, which Evan Eschmeyer once thought he might become after graduating from Northwestern with a degree in education and a minor in pre-med.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if my hands will last,'' he said jokingly today after grabbing rebounds and banging bodies with some free agents in a shoot-around to prepare for the Nets' first game in the Shaw's Pro Summer League.</p>
        <p>For Eschmeyer, the scalpel and the sleepless nights can wait. So can his plans to teach.</p>
        <p>''I want to play basketball as long as they let me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot-10-inch Eschmeyer is entering his second year with the National Basketball Association and is hoping to emerge as a more formidable presence at center -- one of the two unsettled positions the Nets still have entering the preseason.</p>
        <p>With Jayson Williams retiring, Eschmeyer is contending for the starting job in the low post, along with the 7-1 Jim McIlvaine and the 6-8 Jamie Feick, who could be traded before the season.</p>
        <p>Last year at the summer league, Eschmeyer struggled as a rookie fresh from the Big Ten. Now he is the only player on the Nets' 14-man summer squad who was on the roster last season. The Nets' new coach, Byron Scott, welcomes the experience.</p>
        <p>''His hands are pretty good; he has a good way of finishing down there and he's big and strong,'' said Scott, who sat in the stands critiquing his team while his assistant Eddie Jordan coached. The Nets beat San Antonio, 76-68, tonight. Eschmeyer had 6 points, 4 rebounds and 5 quick personal fouls in 18 minutes.</p>
        <p>Eschmeyer has been teaming with Anthony Goldwire on some freelance plays during the minicamp.</p>
        <p>''They were things I wanted to put in but haven't introduced yet,'' Scott said about pick-and-roll variations. ''It just shows he's a little bit further ahead than the rest of these guys.''</p>
        <p>At the beginning of last season Eschmeyer lost valuable time. In a freakish weight-lifting accident in September he snapped a muscle between his right shoulder and chest and had to have surgery. He missed the first 28 games of the season. Then he missed the final eight games because of a sprained left ankle.</p>
        <p>''The injuries were frustrating; I'm not going to lie,'' Eschmeyer said.</p>
        <p>Last season Eschmeyer worked his way into the rotation in March, earning five starts. Not known for his speed or overwhelming athleticism, he compensated with his strength and rebounding. He scored a career-high 9 points on March 26 against the Denver Nuggets and finished the season averaging 2.9 points and 3.5 rebounds in 12 minutes a game.</p>
        <p>''It's what you expect when you come in the league,'' Eschmeyer said. ''You stick it out, put extra time in practice and work, and hopefully that will come in time.''</p>
        <p>Scott has seen progress in Eschmeyer in five days.</p>
        <p>''He works extremely hard,'' Scott said. ''He puts a body on people. He's very enthusiastic, very intelligent, the type of player you love to have around. It's good for him to be with us. He'll have a head start when we get to the fall.''</p>
        <p>Eschmeyer is not fazed by coaching changes, which seem to have followed him throughout his playing career. At Northwestern, he had three different coaches.</p>
        <p>''Whenever you go through coaching changes, it's a feeling of rebirth, excitement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As to how the change is working thus far, Eschmeyer, his soft, thick hands at his side, just smiled and said, ''Ask me in 12 months.''</p>
        <p>Kittles Lost for Season</p>
        <p>General Manager John Nash confirmed today what the Nets had suspected since June: Kerry Kittles will miss the coming season.</p>
        <p>The team's doctors determined that, while they expect a full recovery, Kittles would not be able to rehabilitate his surgically repaired right knee in time for the season.</p>
        <p>Nash said the Nets have applied for another medical exception with the league, in addition to the one they filed for Jayson Williams's salary, in hopes of receiving the $3.8 million-plus for each player. . . . Kevin Freeman, a 6-7 forward from Connecticut and Paterson Catholic High School, joined the Nets in Boston today and led all scorers, producing 18 of his 22 points in the second half.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
