<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y18BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DC133BF93BA25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>SCOTLAND: NATIONALIST STEPS DOWN -- Alex Salmond, leader of the Scottish National Party, said he was stepping down after 10 years in the post. The party, which advocates full independence, had been gaining against the ruling Labor-Liberal Democrat coalition in the new Scottish Parliament, and the resignation was a surprise. Mr. Salmond, 45, said he expected the nationalists to win the next election three years from now and he feared that would ''lock'' him in for another decade.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>SCOTLAND: NATIONALIST STEPS DOWN -- Alex Salmond, leader of the Scottish National Party, said he was stepping down after 10 years in the post. The party, which advocates full independence, had been gaining against the ruling Labor-Liberal Democrat coalition in the new Scottish Parliament, and the resignation was a surprise. Mr. Salmond, 45, said he expected the nationalists to win the next election three years from now and he feared that would ''lock'' him in for another decade.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>ENGLAND: WOODWARDS ON TRIAL -- The parents of Louise Woodward, the English au pair convicted of manslaughter in 1997 in the death of an infant in Massachusetts, went on trial in Chester accused of forging invoices claiming $15,400 in rent from her defense fund while they were living free of charge in Boston during her trial. Gary and Sue Woodward, now separated, have pleaded not guilty to fraud.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: PROTESTS ON BASQUES -- Hundreds of thousands of people across the country marched and held silent rallies to protest three attacks by the Basque rebel group E.T.A. in less than a week. The largest protest was in Malaga, where a suspected E.T.A. gunman shot to death a city councilman. The group was also blamed for two car-bomb blasts in Madrid and the northern city of Soria, setting off fears of a new rebel offensive.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>ROMANIA: PRESIDENT'S LAST TERM -- Saying he was disgusted by corruption, President Emil Constantinescu, 60, said he would not run for re-election this fall. ''There is a blind fight for personal interests,'' Mr. Constantinescu said in a television address. ''People buy and sell places in the Parliament, using lies and blackmail.'' Mr. Constantinescu is trailing in opinion polls behind former President Ion Iliescu. Elections are expected in November.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: RIGHTIST TO RUN -- Stockwell Day, Canada's rising right-wing politician, will seek to enter Parliament by running in a special by-election in British Columbia. Prime Minister Jean Chretien is expected to call the by-election before mid-September to allow Mr. Day, the new leader of the Canadian Alliance, to run for a southern British Columbia seat vacated by Jim Hart, an alliance member who is retiring. Mr. Day, an Albertan who once lived in the district, was elected July 8 as leader of the alliance, the largest and newest opposition party.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>NIGERIA: PIPELINE TOLL RISES -- The death toll in the latest oil pipeline blaze climbed to 100 as local authorities prepared a mass grave for the victims, government officials and hospital workers said. The explosion near the oil town of Warri came less than a week after more than 250 people were killed in a similar incident six miles away.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: SHARIF REFUSAL -- Former Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif refused to testify before a special court trying him for corruption. In remarks to the one-judge Accountability Court, he said the hasty trial was convened only to convict him. Mr. Sharif said he was boycotting the trial, on tax evasion charges, because it had been started without allowing him to consult his lawyers.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: GERMAN FREED -- Muslim rebels freed an ailing German woman, one of 19 mostly foreign vacationers who have been held hostage for nearly three months. Renate Wallert, 57, is the third to be released, following two Malaysians.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>MALAYSIA: SMOG HITS CAPITAL -- A blanket of smog from forest fires in neighboring Indonesia has returned to the capital, Kuala Lumpur. Some haze has also been reported in Singapore. The pollution comes from illegal fires set mostly by plantation owners who were protected by the government of former President Suharto and appear to be beyond the control of the incumbent, Abdurrahman Wahid.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>MALAYSIA: ANWAR TAKES OVER -- Taking over from his lawyers to make his own closing statement, former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim called the sexual misconduct case against him ''a dirty, despicable conspiracy.'' Mr. Anwar faces a prison term of up to 20 years in addition to the six-year term he is already serving for corruption.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>DIEGO GARCIA: ISLANDERS SUE BRITAIN -- Hundreds of islanders deported from the British-run Chagos archipelago 30 years ago to make way for a United States military base sued the British government in the High Court in London for the right to return home. The islanders were moved to the Seychelles and Mauritius in the late 1960's so the United States could build a base on Diego Garcia. Britain leased the island to the United States and in 1971 barred anyone without a permit from entering. The islanders say they have a right to return.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: JOURNALIST JAILED -- A journalist convicted of insulting Islam was sentenced to a five-and-a-half years in prison, the official news agency reported. Emadeddin Baqi was convicted of ''insulting Islamic sanctities, spreading falsehoods to divert public opinion, libel and insult,'' his lawyer was quoted as saying.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>PACIFIC</p>
        <p>FIJI: SANCTIONS IMPOSED -- New Zealand announced penalties against Fiji and warned of stiffer curbs if a new government does not restore multiethnic democracy. Indigenous rebels in Fiji ousted a government led by an ethnic Indian. New Zealand development aid will be cut in half, to $1.15 million. Joint military exercises, as well as training, have been suspended, and government-backed student visits have been ended.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
