<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tipper Gore Seeks Privacy Under a Public Microscope</title>
    <meta content="19TIPP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT'S WIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Tipper</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zappa, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tipper Gore Seeks Privacy Under a Public Microscope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore's wife, Tipper, appears firm in her conviction that she can maintain zone of privacy even as her husband runs for president; she is reluctant to talk about public-private balancing act, but campaign aides say she is fearful of how presidential campaign might consume her family life; she says she hopes to continue activities she does now with relative anonymity, like volunteer work and going to movies with her husband, even as campaign heats up; Tipper Gore's mixed feelings about her public and private lives may stem from her very public role as voice of parental outrage over sexual and violent content of rock music lyrics in mid-1980's; that effort led to recording industry's placement of warning labels on albums with explicit content, but it also earned her enmity of many in music industry, and she was called 'cultural terrorist' by musician Frank Zappa; campaign advisers say Tipper Gore's real value in campaign is helping her husband relax and keeping family's priorities in front of him; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is one difference between Tipper Gore and Hillary Clinton.</p>
        <p>At Sunday's Million Mom March on behalf of gun control, Mrs. Clinton, wearing a light spring pantsuit and straw hat, was so busy working the crowds that she created rally gridlock. Mrs. Gore, wearing a white T-shirt tucked into her blue jeans, marched arm in arm with other women, without an entourage and relatively unheralded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is one difference between Tipper Gore and Hillary Clinton.</p>
        <p>At Sunday's Million Mom March on behalf of gun control, Mrs. Clinton, wearing a light spring pantsuit and straw hat, was so busy working the crowds that she created rally gridlock. Mrs. Gore, wearing a white T-shirt tucked into her blue jeans, marched arm in arm with other women, without an entourage and relatively unheralded.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, of course, is first lady, a candidate for Senate, and an international celebrity. But, if any political wife in America has been presumed to be her heir, and had an opportunity to study Mrs. Clinton's example up close, it is the fellow blonde who rode the bus with her and their husbands in the 1992 presidential campaign and who broke into a spontaneous dance-like hug with her at the 1992 Democratic convention.</p>
        <p>But the two women's different styles at the march offered a vivid contrast between their current approaches to their public roles. Mrs. Clinton's high-stakes political ambition has thrust her into a public life with very little private space. Mrs. Gore, on the other hand, appears reluctant and ambivalent about her public role yet firm in her conviction that she can maintain a zone of privacy -- a phrase that Mrs. Clinton coined -- even if her husband, Al, happens to be running for president.</p>
        <p>Having spent nearly half of her life as a political wife, Mrs. Gore, who is 51, has had plenty of opportunity to consider what may lie ahead if her husband, the vice president for seven years and now the presumptive Democratic nominee, becomes president. But, she said with some trepidation in a recent interview, ''It's a whole new territory for me.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore is reluctant to talk about the public-private balancing act, but campaign aides said she was fearful of how a presidential campaign might consume her family life. At times the Gores' 26-year-old daughter, Karenna Gore Schiff, seems more comfortable in the public spotlight than her mother.  (Karenna is an adviser to the Gore campaign, but her siblings -- Kristin, who is 23; Sarah, 21; and Albert 3d, 17 -- have kept lower profiles.)</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore ''wants to maintain her individuality,'' an aide to Mr. Gore said. ''That will be a struggle.''</p>
        <p>Even as the campaign heats up, Mrs. Gore said, she hopes to continue activities she does now with relative anonymity -- like searching out the homeless at night and encouraging them into shelters, or going out with her husband to see movies in actual theaters, rather than in private screening rooms.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore's mixed feelings about her mixed lives may stem from her very public role as the voice of parental outrage over the sexual and violent content of rock music lyrics, a self-styled crusade in the mid-1980's that earned her the enmity of many in the music industry. At the time, the musician Frank Zappa branded her as a ''cultural terrorist'' and dismissed her effort as a ''housewife-hobby project.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore defends those efforts, which led to the recording industry's placement of warning labels on albums that contained explicit content.</p>
        <p>''Music labeling has been going on long enough now that it's just part of the cultural tableau,'' she said. ''The generations change and people who might have had a different opinion understand it now, actually appreciate it and actually use it.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore may insist on her privacy -- Friday is the Gores' 30th wedding anniversary, an occasion that her husband has trumpeted on the campaign trail, but that she wants to be spent privately -- but also lives a public life.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, for instance, she appeared on stage at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium in Washington and played the drums in front of 45,000 people at a concert on the eve of a gay rights march. (Mrs. Gore played the drums in a girl group, the Wildcats, in high school and is surely the only candidate's wife to have played with members of the Grateful Dead.)</p>
        <p>''I was asked to do it and I believe in the cause,'' she said. ''And I thought, Yeah, it'll be fun. It's a continuation of my commitment to have fun on the campaign trail.''</p>
        <p>How much fun she is actually having is not clear, nor is her precise role. She campaigns separately from her husband, adapting to each occasion and generally steering clear of policy. She provides what campaign advisers say is a much-needed human, down-to-earth dimension to the legendarily stiff vice president.</p>
        <p>She frequently talks to youth audiences and, having disclosed last year that she fought her own battle with depression, the conversations often touch on the darker side of teenage life. On Wednesday, she represented the Gores at the funeral for the son of Representative Bart Stupak, Democrat of Michigan. The 17-year-old son had committed suicide.</p>
        <p>At a recent speech in Virginia to the parents of gays and lesbians, Mrs. Gore talked in a soft, hesitant voice about the need for ''unconditional love.'' But she also advocates on behalf of her husband's causes. At a union event last week in Cincinnati, she called for equal pay for women.</p>
        <p>Campaign advisers said Mrs. Gore had ''a seat at the table'' but this is more figurative than literal. She is not involved in the day-to-day tactical discussions or strategy conference calls, they said. But she is perceived as a valuable asset who can cover the so-called secondary media markets. Her real value, said those who know her well, is helping Mr. Gore relax and keeping the family's priorities in front of him.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore does not much like to describe how she would see her role as first lady or to compare herself with Mrs. Clinton. But from all indications, she would be in the more traditional mold.</p>
        <p>In an interview last year with The Associated Press, Mrs. Gore said: ''With four children and aging parents, I find that I only spend so much time on issues that I care about, and I spend a lot of time on keeping the family together.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore's counterpart on the Republican side, Laura Bush, has also seemed somewhat uncomfortable in the spotlight. She was a reluctant participant in George W. Bush's first political race, in 1978, and was not eager for him to run for governor of Texas or for the presidency.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore's campaign appearances trail have subsided since her husband wrapped up the nomination in March. In February, she campaigned on 20 of 28 days of the month in 22 states. By April, she was down to 10 days. ''We expect to be back in action fairly soon,'' said Camille Johnston, Mrs. Gore's spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the traditional campaign role of chief family helpmate sometimes seems to be occupied by her daughter Karenna, who graduated from Columbia Law School on Tuesday. Mrs. Schiff has emerged as an influential adviser to her father, particularly on addressing concerns of  her generation. And Mr. Gore appears keen on grooming her for a life in politics.</p>
        <p>Over the years, and especially in this campaign, Mr. Gore has sent mixed signals about what he views as private, often drawing on his family archives to help soften his image.</p>
        <p>At the 1992 Democratic convention, he talked extensively about his son's near-death experience; at the 1996 convention he discussed his sister's death from lung cancer.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore and his son hiked up Mount Rainier last summer, reporters were not told of the outing until the two had reached bottom. But before the Washington State primary this year, his campaign used the trek in a commercial.</p>
        <p>Gil Troy, a professor of American history at McGill University and author of a book about presidential couples (''Mr. and Mrs. President, from the Trumans to the Clintons,'' University Press of Kansas), said that much of Mrs. Gore's life was ''poignant and frustrating'' but also a bit disingenuous.</p>
        <p>''She had a searing experience in the 80's with the crusade against the cultural pollutants in Hollywood, and she was badly abused,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Troy added, ''if Tipper Gore really wants her privacy, she should have told Al to run for president of the Kiwanis Club.''</p>
        <p>Patricia Ireland, president of the National Organization for Women, said she hoped that the next first lady would work to complete the ''unfinished business'' of issues of women's equality.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ireland said she did not expect Mrs. Gore ''to be out there articulating the intricacy of issues,'' but that she could help gain respect for full-time mothers and homemakers.</p>
        <p>''She's pretty consistent in being who she is,'' Ms. Ireland said, ''and who she is is a more traditional role, but she does it well.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT'S WIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
