<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs</title>
    <meta content="19FRIE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DC153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says future of Democratic Party is at stake in coming vote by Congress over whether to grant China permanent normalized trade relations; says leadership of Democratic Party, including Pres Clinton, is at war with its rank-and-file labor union base, which is spending millions of dollars on nationwide advertising campaign to kill what would be one of Clinton's most important foreign policy achievements: bringing China's 1.3 billion people under rules of World Trade Orgn; says there are real fears among American workers about trade deal, and now is time for united, progressive Democratic Party, along with business leaders, to address those anxieties,</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At stake in next week's vote by Congress over whether to grant China permanent normalized trade relations -- which in plain English means a long-term, open trade relationship between America and China -- is not just the future of U.S.-China relations but also the future of the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Let's be honest, we have a bizarre situation here that can't go on indefinitely for the Democrats: We have the leadership of the Democratic Party, including the president, at war with its rank-and-file labor union base. Labor is now spending millions of dollars on a nationwide jihad to kill what would be one of President Clinton's most important foreign policy achievements: bringing China's 1.3 billion people under the rules of the World Trade Organization and into a long-term open trading relationship with the U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At stake in next week's vote by Congress over whether to grant China permanent normalized trade relations -- which in plain English means a long-term, open trade relationship between America and China -- is not just the future of U.S.-China relations but also the future of the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Let's be honest, we have a bizarre situation here that can't go on indefinitely for the Democrats: We have the leadership of the Democratic Party, including the president, at war with its rank-and-file labor union base. Labor is now spending millions of dollars on a nationwide jihad to kill what would be one of President Clinton's most important foreign policy achievements: bringing China's 1.3 billion people under the rules of the World Trade Organization and into a long-term open trading relationship with the U.S.</p>
        <p>There is only one way to heal this breach in the Democratic Party, and that is, first, for labor to be thoroughly defeated on this China vote.</p>
        <p>Because only once this deal is passed, only once one-fifth of humanity -- the Chinese people -- have been brought into the W.T.O. and into an open-ended trading arrangement with the U.S., will labor's leadership have to conclude that, at least for now, it is time to stop fighting over whether we globalize and to start focusing instead on how we globalize. Labor then might finally put forward a positive global agenda that addresses how to strengthen U.S. workers -- other than by pushing hidden and real trade barriers. Labor's failure to do that up to now has only been eroding its own power and has put it in a reactionary corner with Patrick Buchanan.</p>
        <p>But while defeating labor on this issue is necessary, it's not sufficient. As dangerous as losing this China trade bill would be for the Democratic Party, and the country as a whole, equally dangerous would be if the winners treat victory on this bill as a final victory against all the forces in this country uncomfortable with globalization, and therefore a free pass to forget the concerns about free trade.</p>
        <p>I disagree with labor's stand on China, but the zeal with which labor's rank and file have fought this war, and the passive support the unions clearly have around the country, underscore that there are real anxieties out there -- about globalization, about losing manufacturing jobs to lower-wage countries, about people feeling that they are not winning from this new economy the way they would like -- that would be reckless to ignore.</p>
        <p>If at this time of rising prosperity in the country as a whole, with unemployment at record lows for all sectors of the population, a bill to extend permanent normal trade relations to China can win only by one vote, then, folks, we have a problem. Imagine what will happen when we have our next, inevitable, recession and unemployment really rises. There could be a ferocious backlash against all these free-trade initiatives and a real mass move to put back the walls.</p>
        <p>That's why now is the time to be addressing the anxieties and myths about globalization. That is what a united, progressive Democratic Party agenda should be about. But while progressive politics requires a labor base that is ready to embrace the new economy, it also requires business and government leaders ready to finance the training programs, health care reforms, public education programs and labor laws that give workers the security to try to master change rather than stop it, and to open up, rather than hunker down.</p>
        <p>Right after this vote, if labor loses, would be the ideal time for a labor-government-business conference in which government and business say to labor: Look, we know you have concerns; what can we do to address them without putting up walls?</p>
        <p>I believe you dare not be a globalizer in this world (and this is business' mistake), an advocate of free trade and integration, without also being a social democrat, ready to spend what it takes to bring the have-nots, know-nots and left-behinds along -- otherwise they will eventually shut the doors on you. But you dare not be a social democrat today (and this is labor's mistake) without also being a globalizer, because without embracing globalization and free trade you will never have all the resources, markets, immigrants and knowledge needed to keep generating rising incomes to redistribute.</p>
        <p>The trick is finding the right balance. Defeating labor on this China bill is necessary for that, but it will be sufficient only if the winners also draw the right conclusions.</p>
        <p>Gail Collins is on vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gail Collins is on vacation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
