<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="19DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DC153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Health Giant Agrees to Fine To Settle Part of Fraud Case  Columbia/HCA Healthcare, the nation's largest health care company, has agreed in principle to pay $745 million in civil penalties to resolve a portion of the government's inquiry into whether its success was achieved in part by defrauding federal health programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Health Giant Agrees to Fine To Settle Part of Fraud Case  Columbia/HCA Healthcare, the nation's largest health care company, has agreed in principle to pay $745 million in civil penalties to resolve a portion of the government's inquiry into whether its success was achieved in part by defrauding federal health programs.</p>
        <p>If approved, the settlement would be the largest health care fraud settlement ever obtained by the Justice Department, exceeding the next highest by more than 50 percent. But the deal does not close the sprawling investigations into Columbia/HCA, some of which have lasted more than seven years. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Chief of JDS Uniphase Steps Down  JDS Uniphase, the component manufacturer for fiber optic equipment, said that Kevin Kalkhoven had retired as co-chairman and chief executive. Mr. Kalkhoven, 55, is succeeded by Jozef Straus, 53, who has been co-chairman, president and chief operating officer since the company was formed 18 months ago through the merger of JDS Fitel and Uniphase. Shares of JDS Uniphase fell $5.75, to $86.75. [C2.]</p>
        <p>E.P.A. Pressed 3M on Scotchgard  The Environmental Protection Agency said that it had pressed Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing to come up with a solution after the company's tests did prove that a chemical compound used in Scotchgard and other household products could pose a risk to human health and the environment. The E.P.A. account differs from that of 3M, which said that it had voluntarily decided to stop making the chemical by the end of the year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Falter in a Technology Slump  Technology stocks slumped as investors became concerned about developments at several companies. The Nasdaq composite index fell 106.25 points, or 2.9 percent, to 3,538.71. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 10.59 points, to 1,437.21, while the Dow Jones industrials rose 7.54 points, to 10,777.28. [C8.]</p>
        <p>MetLife Prepares to Enter Banking  For the first time since Congress eliminated barriers last fall that prevented banks and insurance companies from intermingling their businesses, a major insurance company, MetLife, said that one of its units was taking steps to go into full-service banking. [C5.]</p>
        <p>ABC to Promote Its Soap Operas  The ABC television network is introducing an ambitious advertising campaign intended to stimulate demand among consumers 16 to 24 for four of its daytime soap operas -- ''All My Children,'' ''General Hospital,'' ''One Life to Live'' and ''Port Charles.'' The ads present younger cast members from the four soaps. Each is identified with a word meant to describe the character, including the ''Rebel.'' Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Competing Social Security Plans  Social Security is slowly going broke, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas agree, but they differ on the solutions for fixing it. Mr. Gore would channel the benefits of the federal budget surplus into the system. Governor Bush would establish private investment accounts through which workers could seek higher returns on their contributions to the retirement system. [A23.]</p>
        <p>European Inquiry Into Coke Widens  Investigators from the European Commission raided Coca-Cola's office in Brussels as well as the office of the company's largest bottler, in London, expanding an inquiry into Coke's marketing practices that began last summer. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Dresdner Bank to Lay Off 5,000  Dresdner Bank, which abandoned a merger with Deutsche Bank last month, is expected to announce plans today for reducing its work force by 5,000 people. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
