<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Team to Car, Woe Is Van Gundy</title>
    <meta content="19WISE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gundy, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DC153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Team to Car, Woe Is Van Gundy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Wise comments on New York Knicks' coach Jeff Van Gundy's woes after his team's loss in Game 5 of playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He stepped off the team's charter plane about 3 a.m., the loss in Game 5 still gnawing at him. A tired and beleaguered Jeff Van Gundy would soon have to worry about more than why his Knicks team could not grab an important rebound or make a defensive stop. As he walked down the plane's stairwell at Westchester County Airport, he soon learned he had another problem.</p>
        <p>His car was totaled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He stepped off the team's charter plane about 3 a.m., the loss in Game 5 still gnawing at him. A tired and beleaguered Jeff Van Gundy would soon have to worry about more than why his Knicks team could not grab an important rebound or make a defensive stop. As he walked down the plane's stairwell at Westchester County Airport, he soon learned he had another problem.</p>
        <p>His car was totaled.</p>
        <p>While the plane was backing up in the area where the players and the coaches park their vehicles, a propulsion thrust from the plane picked up Van Gundy's 1995 Honda Civic as if it were tornado fodder and sent it end over end.</p>
        <p>''It was compacted,'' Van Gundy said yesterday afternoon. ''The windshield was totally blown out along with the rest of the windows. It's just a car.''</p>
        <p>Baggage attendants, limousine drivers and family members waiting for the team were nearby, but no one was hurt. Only the cars of Allan Houston, assistant coach Brendan Malone and another team employee were damaged from the impact of Van Gundy's car.</p>
        <p>''He would have been safer if he had run into a telephone pole, the way his car looked,'' Houston said. ''It's a car, you know what I mean. Nobody got hurt. That's what insurance is for. It capped off a beautiful night. Nobody said life or every day is going to be easy. You get up and recover from it, just like we have to do in our next two games.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy telephoned his wife, Kim, at about 3:30 a.m. She answered groggy, unsure of what she was hearing. He gave her the details quickly and told her he would sleep in his office and see her in the morning.</p>
        <p>The game was lost. The car was totaled. Yet win or lose tonight in Game 6, Jeff Van Gundy's job status is not an issue. A year ago, he couldn't say that.</p>
        <p>Sometimes you come so far, so fast, you forget where you were 11 months ago.</p>
        <p>Kim Van Gundy came by the team's practice facility yesterday afternoon. She dreaded peeling the license plates off the Civic. So many memories from that car.</p>
        <p>It was just last February when Van Gundy hopped in the car for the 45-minute ride home from Madison Square Garden to Chappaqua, N.Y. The Knicks were 0-2 at the time, and their coach would soon become embattled, locked in a power struggle with the team president, trying to coach a team he was not entirely comfortable with.</p>
        <p>A distant Marcus Camby was months away from swooping down on Indiana in the Eastern Conference finals, and the trigger-happy Latrell Sprewell had just had an abysmal performance against the reviled Miami Heat in the home opener of the lockout-shortened season. Nothing was working.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy, a glass-half-empty kind of person, figured his team could genuinely go 0-50. He got off the Saw Mill River Parkway and soon pulled into his driveway that night.</p>
        <p>With millions of thoughts percolating in his mind -- How can I get this team to mesh and win? Is Patrick Ewing's body going to hold up? Can Camby give us anything? -- he kept on driving.</p>
        <p>Until he rammed the Civic smack into the garage door. Van Gundy had forgotten to hit the remote control button to raise the door. Another Knick-Heat casualty.</p>
        <p>After a surreal run to the finals and the long-term financial security it brought, Van Gundy is still asking himself some of the same questions. He knows how well they can play, what kind of talent and limitations he has on his roster and how much closer the Knicks have become as a team since all the tumult from last season.</p>
        <p>But after all this time, Van Gundy still doesn't know who will take the court tomorrow. The players who saved his job and their season a year ago, stunningly winning the conference championship. Or the frustrated team he saw on Wednesday night, the players who didn't carry out the right defensive assignments, enabling Dan Majerle and Bruce Bowen to knock down crucial 3-pointers in the final two minutes.</p>
        <p>''The tortured soul?'' he said yesterday. ''Yeah, that's me.''</p>
        <p>He was asked what he slept on last night. ''I've got a couch,'' said Van Gundy, adding ''for my shrink.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks are down to their last game, and Van Gundy is learning again how crazy this game can make you. How, after all the prodding and button-pushing, the occasional profane tirades about urgency, sometimes the players don't listen.</p>
        <p>They go on memory, the idea that the regular season did not matter a year ago, that when they want to, they can find the desire they need to get back to the finals. That, deep down, they're better than the Heat. Isn't that what everybody has been writing and saying?</p>
        <p>Until, over time, they convince themselves they're all right, they'll find their A-game before it's over. In sports and in life, this is called mentally giving in, creating a reality for yourself that does not actually exist.</p>
        <p>It's almost like losing a huge playoff game, finding out your car is totaled and having to sleep in your office because you don't have a ride home.</p>
        <p>''Thankfully, no one was hurt,'' he said. ''It really is just a car. I mean, I would've rather had the win.''</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
