<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Taiwan Leader Said to Plan No Sudden Shifts That Would Antagonize Beijing</title>
    <meta content="Y19TAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tien Hung-mao</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen Shui-Bian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0D8143AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Taiwan Leader Said to Plan No Sudden Shifts That Would Antagonize Beijing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>TAIPEI, Taiwan, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tien Hung-mao, Taiwan's soon-to-be foreign minister, says new president, Chen Shui-bian, would make no sudden shifts in Taiwan's policy toward China and would continue to send soothing signals to Beijing; says Chen's inaugural address will give China no easy excuse to retaliate with force; warns outsiders not to expect any dramatic overture from Chen, noting that he won with less than 40 percent of vote and does not have mandate to shake things up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of an extraordinarily sensitive transfer of power here, Taiwan's soon-to-be foreign minister said the new president, Chen Shui-bian, would make no sudden shifts in Taiwan's policy toward China and would continue to send soothing signals to Beijing.</p>
        <p>''Chen Shui-bian will not give China any easy excuse to retaliate with force,'' said the minister, Tien Hung-mao, referring to the closely watched inaugural address that Mr. Chen will deliver on Saturday. ''It's going to be a very conciliatory kind of speech.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of an extraordinarily sensitive transfer of power here, Taiwan's soon-to-be foreign minister said the new president, Chen Shui-bian, would make no sudden shifts in Taiwan's policy toward China and would continue to send soothing signals to Beijing.</p>
        <p>''Chen Shui-bian will not give China any easy excuse to retaliate with force,'' said the minister, Tien Hung-mao, referring to the closely watched inaugural address that Mr. Chen will deliver on Saturday. ''It's going to be a very conciliatory kind of speech.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tien also warned outsiders not to expect any dramatic overture from Mr. Chen, who swept the Nationalist Party from power in March after a half-century of rule. Since Mr. Chen won with less than 40 percent of the vote, Mr. Tien said, the president-elect did not have a mandate to shake things up.</p>
        <p>''On the fundamental principles that our country stands for, he will not make a concession,'' Mr. Tien said. ''He cannot. He's not mandated to make a concession.''</p>
        <p>That makes it very unlikely that in the speech, or in the near future, Mr. Chen will grant Beijing's demand for reopening negotiations across the Taiwan Strait: that Taiwan accept the idea that it and the People's Republic are part of a single China. Since his election, Mr. Chen has said he is willing to discuss the concept of ''one China'' but will not accept it as a precondition for talks.</p>
        <p>China has repeatedly warned that if Taiwan veers toward independence, it will use force to take the island. With Beijing likely to scrutinize Mr. Chen's words like freshly cut diamonds, Mr. Tien said the president-elect was putting the passage of the speech that deals with China through endless drafts.</p>
        <p>''We hope there will be enough of a way out for China to say: 'At least Chen Shui-bian did not say that. He met our minimum criteria for continuing,' '' Mr. Tien said.</p>
        <p>The deadlock between Taipei and Beijing on ''one China'' has brought relations to one of their tensest points in years. China's leaders were rattled by the election of Mr. Chen, whose Democratic Progressive Party formally espouses independence. Mr. Chen has said such a step is unnecessary, but recent remarks by his vice president, Annette Lu, have led China to unleash threats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tien denied a recent report that the new Taipei administration had requested that the United States play a more active role in mediating the dispute. He also played down recent remarks by the new head of Taiwan's Mainland Affairs Council, Tsai Ying-wen, in which she expressed hope that Washington would be a ''facilitator'' of new talks.</p>
        <p>''This has been happening for many years,'' Mr. Tien said, referring to frequent discussions about cross-strait policy held in the United States. Those talks, though not official, bring together Taiwanese, Chinese and American scholars and former government officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tien, who is the chairman of a policy research institute, said that as foreign minister he would push for more such exchanges.</p>
        <p>In the absence of a political breakthrough, Mr. Tien said he counted on flourishing economic ties between Taiwan and China to bridge the gap. Shortly after the election, Mr. Chen proposed to lift the ban on direct trade, transportation and postal service between the two countries. He also said he would consider lifting strict limits on Taiwanese investment on the mainland.</p>
        <p>Although Taiwanese companies are not allowed to invest more than $50 million in any single project in China, there are an estimated 35,000 Taiwan companies with operations there. Businesses are pushing to be allowed to invest in infrastructure projects in China, investment that is now prohibited.</p>
        <p>But there are signs that business people are starting to be subjected to the same pressure as politicians like Mr. Chen. The Chinese government recently summoned the local representatives of Taiwanese companies with ties to Mr. Chen and his party to warn them that their mainland operations would be penalized if they were perceived as advocating independence for the island.</p>
        <p>''They are pressuring a lot of businessmen to verbally express their loyalty to the 'one China' principle,'' Mr. Tien said. ''Taiwanese businessmen will have to come to a decision whether it is worth it for them to make a political concession to make a few extra dollars in China.''</p>
        <p>One of Taiwan's leading industrialists, Stan Shih, visited Beijing two weeks ago to try to assure the Chinese authorities that he planned to steer clear of the independence debate. Mr. Shih, chairman of the computer maker Acer, is a longtime supporter of Mr. Chen.</p>
        <p>''We've been worried by unnecessary political pressure from the Beijing authorities,'' said Rick Lei, the president of Acer's digital services division, who accompanied Mr. Shih on the trip. Acer recently obtained a license to run a test of an Internet-access service in mainland China.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
