<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camby Shows No Fire and His Game Is Up in Smoke</title>
    <meta content="19CAMB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DB153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camby Shows No Fire and His Game Is Up in Smoke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., May 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks' Marcus Camby has been struggling through nightmarish playoff series against Miami Heat; Camby comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marcus Camby slipped out of the gym at SUNY-Purchase, hurriedly making his way to the stairs with his head down, trying to ignore the news media, perhaps making the most aggressive move he has displayed during the Eastern Conference semifinals.</p>
        <p>For five games, Camby has been trying to finesse his way through the rugged Miami frontcourt. When he came back up from the locker room and found the questions still awaiting him, he tried finessing his way through an explanation of how he has managed to disappear when the Knicks needed him most.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marcus Camby slipped out of the gym at SUNY-Purchase, hurriedly making his way to the stairs with his head down, trying to ignore the news media, perhaps making the most aggressive move he has displayed during the Eastern Conference semifinals.</p>
        <p>For five games, Camby has been trying to finesse his way through the rugged Miami frontcourt. When he came back up from the locker room and found the questions still awaiting him, he tried finessing his way through an explanation of how he has managed to disappear when the Knicks needed him most.</p>
        <p>His usual contagious smile and boundless enthusiasm have been grounded by the Heat's constant pressure. With Jeff Van Gundy begging his team to display some sort of fortitude in the paint, Camby has been unwilling to absorb the contact. In Game 5, as the Knicks fell behind, three games to two, with an 87-81 loss, he left American Airlines Arena with just 2 points and 4 rebounds, missing his first 5 field-goal attempts before finally rolling in a layup in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Last year, when the playoffs became a coming-out party for the slender 6-foot-11-inch Camby, it began with an efficient series against Miami in which he converted 68.2 percent of his shots.</p>
        <p>But this season, with the expectations higher, he has struggled through a nightmarish series, shooting just 35.5 percent, including 1 of 6 on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''I'm just not finishing the same,'' Camby said. ''I'm not finishing strong to the basket, rushing a lot of my shots, easy shots, and it's definitely been discouraging. Those are shots I should be making. I feel like I'm letting the team down.''</p>
        <p>While Alonzo Mourning has thrown his muscular body around the paint and the reserve point guard Anthony Carter gathering more rebounds than Camby over the last three games, Camby has found his production lost in a stream of finger rolls that do not come close to the target and aborted flights toward the rim.</p>
        <p>He left the gym today with ice packs strapped to his knees, but said that his knee ailments, which sidelined him for the last week of the regular season, have less to do with his troubles than his frustration with his game.</p>
        <p>''I'm fine, well enough to go out there and play,'' Camby said. ''I'm not making no excuses. I've just been ineffective these last couple of games, and I have to assert myself more tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>He has appeared lost in the games, and even in today's brief workout he was wandering around the court without a purpose when the assistant coach Brendan Malone called him over for a more disciplined shooting drill.</p>
        <p>''Finger rolls are not going to get it against Miami or any team in the playoffs,'' Malone said. ''What he has to do is go in strong and dunk it, or if he makes a move, drop his shoulder and really finish strong. When he does get shots inside, he's not going up strong.</p>
        <p>''He has to run. Marcus's game is speed and quickness and also it's emotion. He's playing kind of flat. He's not playing with that emotion or that spark that he had in the playoffs last year. He seems like he's feeling pressure. I don't know if that's it or he's thinking too much, but he's an action-reaction, rhythm player where he plays his best in the open court. He plays his best slashing in and getting offensive rebounds, tap-ins, and blocking shots. You don't set plays for Marcus. Marcus will get shots within the flow of the game on hustle play.''</p>
        <p>Camby has been unable to find a rhythm. After an 11-point, 13-rebound effort in Game 1, he has done little else, with just 12 points and 13 rebounds against 16 personal fouls in the last three games.</p>
        <p>''He's probably down about his game,'' Malone said. ''But I think if he gets himself up emotionally, not worrying about his makes or misses or mistakes, just go out and play, he's a game-changer with his emotions. People in the Garden love watching him play. When he blocks shots or runs down courts and scores in transition, he makes everybody alive. Right now he's not doing that because he is not alive.</p>
        <p>''He has to play with emotion. I'd like to see Marcus start playing with a smile on his face like he used to. Right now he's not playing with emotion or any kind of joy out there. He seems to be burdened by his inability to score right now.''</p>
        <p>Camby added: ''I think I'm a rhythm player. I like to get into a rhythm, get myself going, get myself and my teammates pumped up. Definitely, being in foul trouble hurts, too.</p>
        <p>But he still has high hopes.</p>
        <p>''The series is not over,'' Camby said. ''If we can get this one tomorrow, we feel comfortable going back down there on Sunday.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
