<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southern Baptist Consider Check on Women as Pastors</title>
    <meta content="Y19BAP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baptist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ministers (Protestant)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baptist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ministers (Protestant)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DD153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southern Baptist Consider Check on Women as Pastors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leaders of Southern Baptist Convention, nation's largest Protestant denomination, propose revising denomination's basic statement of faith to say that Bible allows only men to be church pastors; proposed phrase reflects theologically rightward turn by denomination, in which few women have been hired as pastors; if revision is adopted by denomination, it would have effect of strongly discouraging Southern Baptist congregations from calling women as pastors; it could not prevent them from doing so, because congregations are self-governing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaders of the Southern Baptist Convention, the nation's largest Protestant denomination, yesterday proposed revising the denomination's basic statement of faith to say that the Bible allows only men to be church pastors.</p>
        <p>The proposed change -- to a document called the Baptist Faith and Message -- would declare that ''the office of pastor is limited to men as qualified by Scripture.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leaders of the Southern Baptist Convention, the nation's largest Protestant denomination, yesterday proposed revising the denomination's basic statement of faith to say that the Bible allows only men to be church pastors.</p>
        <p>The proposed change -- to a document called the Baptist Faith and Message -- would declare that ''the office of pastor is limited to men as qualified by Scripture.''</p>
        <p>The proposed phrase reflects the theologically rightward turn by the denomination, historically a conservative body in which few women have been hired as pastors. If adopted by the denomination, it would have the effect of strongly discouraging Southern Baptist congregations from calling women as pastors. But it could not prevent them from doing so, because the congregations are self-governing.</p>
        <p>The proposed revision would also be another in a series of recent moves sharply distinguishing Southern Baptists from other major Protestant bodies.</p>
        <p>Since their denomination underwent a wrenching internal power struggle in the 1980's, Southern Baptists have been guided by leaders who regard the Bible as ''inerrant'' -- literally true in all matters -- and have been firm in saying Scripture prohibits women from being spiritual leaders over men.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Southern Baptists amended the faith statement to declare that ''a wife is to submit herself graciously'' to her husband's leadership.</p>
        <p>In 1996, the convention called for new efforts aimed at converting Jews to Christianity.</p>
        <p>In addition to saying women should not be pastors, the proposed revisions call on Christians to oppose racism, homosexuality and pornography, to speak out against abortion and to bring government and society ''under the sway of the principles of righteousness, truth and brotherly love.'' The proposals will be voted on at the 15.8-million-member denomination's convention, in Orlando on June 13 and 14.</p>
        <p>The proposed changes are ''historically significant,'' said the Rev. R. Albert Mohler, president of Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Ky., and a member of the committee that proposed the revisions.</p>
        <p>''A confession of faith is a very concrete representation of what Baptists believe,'' Mr. Mohler said, adding that it was ''appropriate that every generation'' be able to consider such revisions.</p>
        <p>''One of the issues that is important here is that the opposition to the idea of a woman serving as pastor is not culturally driven,'' he said. ''It is a matter of biblical conviction.''</p>
        <p>But Carolyn Weatherford Crumpler, a former executive director of Woman's Missionary Union, the major women's organization in the Southern Baptist Convention, said she would not support the proposed revision.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a misinterpretation of Scripture,'' said Mrs. Crumpler, who is also a former moderator of the Cooperative Baptist Fellowship, a network of theologically more moderate congregations in the denomination.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Daniel Vestal, the fellowship's top official, said the proposed revision ''is based on a bad interpretation of Scripture, an insensitivity to the Holy Spirit and an unwillingness to see what God is doing in the world today.'' He said that were the clause against women as pastors to be incorporated into the faith statement, it would have a profound effect among the denomination's 40,000 congregations.</p>
        <p>''Symbol is sometimes substance,'' he said. ''It will definitely affect the local congregation over time, because the document is a document for hiring and firing in all institutions. So it's going to affect faculty and it's going to affect missionaries, and that has an effect on all congregations.''</p>
        <p>The faith statement was written in 1925 and revised in 1963. Since the last major revision, several Protestant denominations have ordained women.</p>
        <p>These days, women make up a significant proportion of clergy members in the United Methodist Church, the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America and the Episcopal Church. All three denominations also ordain women as bishops. In one small religious body, the Unitarian-Universalist Association, women make up a slight majority of clergy members.</p>
        <p>Sarah Frances Anders, a retired sociology professor who is moderator of the Cooperative Baptist Fellowship, said that in 1964, the first Southern Baptist woman was ordained since before the Civil War. But that woman, she said, found a job as a pastor in another denomination, the American Baptist Churches.</p>
        <p>Since then, she said, about 1,600 Southern Baptist women have been ordained, although many are chaplains, ministers of music or supervisors of educational programs. She said about 100 women were pastors and about 100 were associate pastors in Southern Baptist congregations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
