<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kitsch in Sync With Treasures</title>
    <meta content="19KIMM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nineteen Hundred (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Twentieth Century</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DB143AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kitsch in Sync With Treasures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman reviews Guggenheim Museum's survey show 1900: Art at the Crossroads; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Guggenheim's ''1900: Art at the Crossroads'' is a wacky exercise in historical simulation, the excuse being a new century. It is hard to remember the last time so many bad pictures were in one place at one time, unless you consider eBay a place. But the show no doubt will be as popular in New York as it was in London. There is no underestimating the public's taste for kitsch.</p>
        <p>There is a good deal of excellent art mixed in among the dogs, and sometimes what is best is not what you would expect, which is partly the show's point. It tries to conjure up the situation in art at the turn of the last century, when Picasso was a little-known young Spaniard, and a French painter named Paul Chabas won the gold medal at the 1900 Paris Exposition Universelle for a vaporous confection of soft-core bathing beauties called ''Joyous Frolics.'' We see Mondrian cheek by jowl with Albijn Van den Abeele, Renoir with Anders Zorn, Kandinsky with Pal Szinyei Merse. And if you think you know who comes out on top in each case, you are wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Guggenheim's ''1900: Art at the Crossroads'' is a wacky exercise in historical simulation, the excuse being a new century. It is hard to remember the last time so many bad pictures were in one place at one time, unless you consider eBay a place. But the show no doubt will be as popular in New York as it was in London. There is no underestimating the public's taste for kitsch.</p>
        <p>There is a good deal of excellent art mixed in among the dogs, and sometimes what is best is not what you would expect, which is partly the show's point. It tries to conjure up the situation in art at the turn of the last century, when Picasso was a little-known young Spaniard, and a French painter named Paul Chabas won the gold medal at the 1900 Paris Exposition Universelle for a vaporous confection of soft-core bathing beauties called ''Joyous Frolics.'' We see Mondrian cheek by jowl with Albijn Van den Abeele, Renoir with Anders Zorn, Kandinsky with Pal Szinyei Merse. And if you think you know who comes out on top in each case, you are wrong.</p>
        <p>We're meant to look anew at a moment 100 years ago, when it was not yet clear who would be the pioneers in the 20th century and who would be forgotten. Thus recapturing innocence, we can make connections between conservatives and avant-gardists, Americans and Finns, one generation and another, which for the sake of simplification or because of ignorance art historians have glossed over or ignored.</p>
        <p>That's the idea, anyway. The lesson is simply that ''history is messy,'' a phrase the catalog approvingly quotes, although it might be more precise to say that the present is messy while history, after historians have finished with it, is always too tidy.</p>
        <p>It is useful to be reminded of this. But we ought to be careful about taking ''1900'' too much at face value. This being a global age, imagine an exhibition of current art that mixed selections from the Venice Biennale with art made by members of the National Academy of Design; work by star graduates from art schools in Beijing, Los Angeles and Cairo; and examples by the leading Argentine and Portuguese portrait painters, whoever they are. An interesting cross section maybe, but would it fairly represent where we are now in art, or would it be a hodgepodge of the sort one could fabricate for any year during the last century or two?</p>
        <p>Here, for example, we find the young Picasso, Mondrian, Kupka and Kandinsky, who, had they stopped painting in 1900, we can presume would be ignored today. Kupka, soon to invent pure abstraction, was painting frothy lunching parties for the 1900 Paris fair, retrograde art for the marketplace by someone with more talent and imagination than what we see suggests (demonstrating that one should be careful before writing off a young artist).</p>
        <p>It is vaguely interesting to be reminded of how Kupka, Picasso and the others conformed to convention at the turn of the century. But hindsight is why they are here, and it's of limited historical value to note that at that instant they were outshone by more successful artists whom they would soon eclipse.</p>
        <p>The show, with 250 paintings and sculptures filling the whole museum, was organized by Robert Rosenblum, the art historian, now a Guggenheim curator, who has written widely about old and new art. His unconventional textbook on the 19th century puts many once-famous, now-forgotten figures into the story line. The exhibition extends this principle. Mr. Rosenblum assumes scholastic neutrality about whether, say, Carl Wilhelmson is as good a painter as Cezanne. They worked at the same time; they're both in the show. We decide.</p>
        <p>The decision is laughably easy, but detractors will call this an abdication of curatorial responsibility. You can bet that traditionalist critics are charging up their computers to fight the latest Armageddon of artistic standards at the Guggenheim.</p>
        <p>Never mind. The show provides compensatory rewards for its schlock quotient and whatever might be unclear about its inclusionary standards.</p>
        <p>There are discoveries, for example, and this is a reason to see any show. Eugene Jansson was painting luminous scenes in an Impressionist mode when Monet was painting London and the Seine, and Jansson holds his own in a single picture of Stockholm Bay. Ignacio Zuloaga, the flashy Spanish society portraitist, stands out for a bizarre homage to Velazquez in the form of a portrait of a dwarf, and he comes across as more daring than expected. Ferdinand Hodler, the important Swiss painter, can't be called a discovery, but he emerges as an even more refined, luminous innovator in this context. Likewise, Eugene Carriere, the Symbolist who painted misty spiritualistic monochromes with the quality of nighttime snapshots, proves to be a true original.</p>
        <p>Carriere, Zuloaga and others exemplify a widespread mood of paranoia, pessimism and general fin-de-siecle angst, cutting across nationalities, generations and styles. It isn't quite true that not a single picture in this exhibition depicts the sun shining through clear skies, but almost. These are literally dark works. Poverty, religious fear, loneliness, sexual anxiety including homosexual guilt, distrust of industrialization: they're the symptoms of a psychic havoc wrought by Freud, late Victorianism, urban sprawl, the reshuffling of social classes and so on.</p>
        <p>And who can deny that these artists had a reason to be glum? Two world wars later, after the bloodiest century in history, we should regard them as visionaries. Even the glassy world of the supremely retrograde academic William-Adolphe Bouguereau suggests a desperation to escape from reality. One of the show's surprises is simply reminding us that Bouguereau was still around when someone like Maurice de Vlaminck was painting ''The Bar,'' a brash and grotesque paean to modern night life, primed for hard times.</p>
        <p>This isn't the first exhibition to present a cross section of a year from a century ago. The Orsay Museum in Paris did something similar in 1993 about painting across Europe in 1893, a smaller show, less flashy. That was an underappreciated experiment because the time perhaps wasn't right. Exhibitions of old art, whatever they're about, are successful only if they speak to the present, and the value of ''1900,'' its drawbacks aside, is ultimately to hold up a mirror to now.</p>
        <p>The situation for art in 2000 seems as hard to parse as it clearly was 100 years ago. And 1900 was also an in-between moment, a creative no man's land, despite everything that was going on. Cezanne, Degas, Renoir and Monet were around, but they were no longer new. That goes double for Bouguereau. Cubism was still a few years off. Art has these difficult-to-define episodes, then moves ahead.</p>
        <p>The show also proves that bad art can sometimes get a second look, profitably. Because painting today encompasses camp without guilt, it wouldn't be surprising if Leon Frederic's triptych ''The Stream,'' with its Rubensian babies cascading through Alpine mist, caught some contemporary artists' attention, if only for its sheer hypnotic awfulness. I could imagine that John Currin, for example, a fashionable painter now, might be intrigued by Frederic or by Antonio Teixeira Carneiro, the Portuguese Symbolist, or even by Bouguereau.</p>
        <p>It takes fresh eyes to see art turned on its head. Jean-Leon Gerome, Bouguereau's conservative colleague, inspired Dali with his ''Optician,'' a trompe l'oeil curio painted for a 1902 Paris exhibition of advertising signs: a dog with a monocle is sandwiched between a pince-nez with disembodied eyes and the fractured word ''O PTI CIEN.'' It is a pun on ''Au petit chien,'' meaning ''oh, little dog'' or ''at the sign of the little dog.''</p>
        <p>Wordplay. Surrealism. No wonder Dali loved it. Mr. Rosenblum calls the work an instance of unwitting prophecy: ''Who would have expected the stuffy Jean-Leon Gerome, who railed against the Impressionists at the 1900 fair, to produce a strange painting that offered a preview of Dada and Surrealism?'' One might put it this way: that artists, who are trained to think unconventionally, often don't feel as constrained as the rest of us by the verdicts of art historians, so they may sometimes help us see what we dismiss too easily or refuse to consider.</p>
        <p>Patience is required. This show strains it. The weak-hearted and modern-day culture Pharisees may never get past the shock of confronting so much of the art that the abstractionists were rebelling against in a great museum created as a shrine to 20th-century abstraction. Heathens have taken over the temple again. Could there by any further blasphemy?</p>
        <p>Actually, yes. The traveling Norman Rockwell exhibition arrives at the Guggenheim soon.</p>
        <p>''1900: Art at the Crossroads'' remains at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 88th Street, (212) 423-3500, through Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
