<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Crisis, a Changed Man</title>
    <meta content="20RUDY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MAYOR'S DECISION: THE MAYOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED8133AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Crisis, a Changed Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani has often been called operatic, but little in his past prepared the audience for yesterday's performance. It was a new character on stage: vulnerable, affectionate, introspective, indecisive, apologetic to his enemies, more concerned with being ''better as a person'' than winning a political fight.</p>
        <p>His enemies may doubt his conversion. One of his promises yesterday, to reach out to disaffected New Yorkers, was reminiscent of the overtures he made to minority-group voters in his second inaugural speech.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani has often been called operatic, but little in his past prepared the audience for yesterday's performance. It was a new character on stage: vulnerable, affectionate, introspective, indecisive, apologetic to his enemies, more concerned with being ''better as a person'' than winning a political fight.</p>
        <p>His enemies may doubt his conversion. One of his promises yesterday, to reach out to disaffected New Yorkers, was reminiscent of the overtures he made to minority-group voters in his second inaugural speech.</p>
        <p>But whatever he does the rest of his term, there was no mistaking the change in Mr. Giuliani yesterday. He started off sounding a bit like Lou Gehrig in ''The Pride of the Yankees.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a very fortunate man,'' Mr. Giuliani said in response to the applause that greeted him. ''The reason I'm such a fortunate man is that I have people that love me and I love them.''</p>
        <p>He said there would not be ''a new Rudy,'' but then he promptly talked about about becoming ''somebody who grows from the fact you confront your limits.''</p>
        <p>''I think I understand myself a lot better,'' he said. ''I think I understand what is important to me better. Maybe I'm not completely there yet.''</p>
        <p>It wasn't surprising to hear that intimations of mortality made Mr. Giuliani reassess his life. But it was a shock to hear him confess to a new sensation. For the first time, he had met a decision he was having trouble making. For a moment he sounded almost like that classic Hamlet on the Hudson, Mario M. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>''I find myself unable to make, really make the treatment decision yet,'' he said referring to his prostate cancer. ''And about the decision to run, I was almost in the same position, not being able to make it, which has never really happened to me.''</p>
        <p>Thanks to his background as a prosecutor, Mr. Giuliani was accustomed to making difficult decisions based on imperfect information. Prosecutors, unlike politicians, are used to making people unhappy. Mr. Giuliani prided himself on acting quickly and not looking back.</p>
        <p>When he was asked near the end of his second year in office to name any mistakes he had made, he could barely come up with anything. He refused even to apologize for his endorsement of Mr. Cuomo, which left him politically isolated and unable to carry out some of the most important changes he had planned.</p>
        <p>''I never revisit it,'' he said in October 1995, a year after the endorsement. ''You don't get the benefit when you make a decision to know what you're going to know a year later. I made the right decision based on the things that I knew at the time. I'm actually proud of the decision, because it was an ability to take a risk for what I thought was the good of the city.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday he was having second thoughts about lots of things. He promised to try to overcome ''the barriers that maybe I placed'' between himself and New Yorkers who didn't feel a part of the city's good times. ''I'm going to dedicate myself to trying to figure out how we can get them to feel that, too, including maybe changes I have to make in the way I approach it, the way I look at it.''</p>
        <p>How will the mayor's new persona go over with the public? The reaction was mixed among an unscientific sample of people interviewed on the streets of Brooklyn. Ken DiPreta, a writer walking his dog in Cadman Plaza Park, was not impressed.</p>
        <p>''It's really pretty self-absorbed of him,'' Mr. DiPreta said, ''to suddenly realize, 'Gee, maybe I haven't exactly been nice to people as mayor.' All of us knew that he was like that. So to hear him discovering normal human kindness like it was some great new invention seems a little strange.''</p>
        <p>But others were willing to cut the mayor a break. ''He suddenly became human,'' said Quentin Arthur, a law student standing outside Federal District Court in Brooklyn. ''It's like tragedy had to strike before he could see what he was like. I don't think it's an act. I think he really probably does want to be a better person.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's new priorities have been obvious to city officials. ''There's been a lot of self-examination,'' said Nicholas Scoppetta, the commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services. ''What's quite remarkable is that he has done a good deal of this in public, and his declarations of where he finds himself have been public, too. I find it all very moving.</p>
        <p>''I feel for him,'' Mr. Scoppetta said. ''He is going through an extremely difficult time and doing it with the whole city watching him.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's aides and friends have always said there was a softer and gentler Rudy whom the public never saw, and journalists have always known that he can be charming when he sits down to dinner with a glass of Chianti. But even at his most relaxed, even when he was rhapsodizing about opera, he was not what you could call a touchy-feely guy.</p>
        <p>''What moves me about opera is that you can express emotions in a way that you can't when you just speak,'' he said one evening five years ago after watching ''Tosca,'' but the emotions that concerned him seemed to be mainly political. He said he liked ''Tosca,'' by Giacomo Puccini, because it featured a political struggle, like the operas of his favorite composer, Giuseppe Verdi.</p>
        <p>''Verdi was a great Italian patriot,'' he said that evening. ''I like his operas because they almost all have a political subplot. The themes are governmental and political and national. Puccini's operas tend to be much more personal. 'La Boheme' is a very personal, beautiful story, but it's never done it for me as a story.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday the mayor said he had  just learned that politics is actually not ''the core of me.''</p>
        <p>He did not discuss his operatic tastes, but perhaps ''La Boheme'' now has more appeal. A nonpolitical story about love and disease would seem to fit his current mood.</p>
        <p>THE MAYOR'S DECISION: THE MAYOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
