<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Culling Trophies Of a Boom</title>
    <meta content="19ANTI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDB163AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Culling Trophies Of a Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column on Sotheby's sale of antiques and art objects from collection of Saul Steinberg; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Enough years have passed since the roaring 1980's that it's probably time for a television mini-series on the decade. And what would furnish the sets better than the antiques in the collection of the swashbuckling tycoon Saul Steinberg and his wife, Gayfryd, who are selling most of their decorative arts collection at Sotheby's next Friday?</p>
        <p>Until very recently the collection was in the Steinbergs' 37-room Park Avenue triplex, possibly the largest apartment in New York, which they recently sold for about $35 million to Stephen Schwarzman, president of Blackstone Group, the investment firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Enough years have passed since the roaring 1980's that it's probably time for a television mini-series on the decade. And what would furnish the sets better than the antiques in the collection of the swashbuckling tycoon Saul Steinberg and his wife, Gayfryd, who are selling most of their decorative arts collection at Sotheby's next Friday?</p>
        <p>Until very recently the collection was in the Steinbergs' 37-room Park Avenue triplex, possibly the largest apartment in New York, which they recently sold for about $35 million to Stephen Schwarzman, president of Blackstone Group, the investment firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinberg acquired the triplex, built for John D. Rockefeller Jr., in the 1970's for $275,000, Mrs. Steinberg said. ''New York was in trouble then,'' she said, ''and no one wanted to pay the maintenance.'' The couple, working with the decorators Tom Collum and Mark Hampton, spent the 1980's and 90's filling it with English furniture, European artworks, silver and porcelain. The 293 lots in the sale are expected to bring $12 million.</p>
        <p>The couple, looking for a brownstone, are not selling everything, Mrs. Steinberg said. ''We are keeping things that work on a smaller scale,'' she said, including the furniture, Goya drawings and objets d'art from what she calls ''Saul's John Soane-looking library.'' Inspired by the British Neo-Classical architect John Soane, the black library was decorated, Mrs. Steinberg explained, ''with elements from the Grand Tour, such as casts of Roman temples, rondels with Roman gods, bas reliefs with ancient figures in procession, as well as some 200 drawings and 250 cartons' worth of antique books.''</p>
        <p>What the Steinbergs are selling are the grand, overscaled pieces that she calls ''palace furniture.''</p>
        <p>''It was a gutsy space that called for gutsy furniture,'' she said. ''The space demanded it. The apartment was splendid in scale, and after Mark Hampton's work there, it looked like it should: a very grand place so Saul's Old Master pictures could be hung properly.''</p>
        <p>The Steinbergs had different collecting interests. ''I loved English furniture, French chairs and Chinese export porcelain,'' Mrs. Steinberg said. ''Saul loved his pictures. He bought them without knowing if we had a spare wall. He could live in a plain white room if he had his pictures.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, they bought their antiques together, often in London. John Hobbs, a London dealer with offices in New York, sold them pieces and occasionally advised them on acquiring things at auction. To him, the most important piece in the sale is a George II rococo mahogany dressing and writing commode attributed to John Channon, circa 1765, which the Steinbergs bought at auction in London. A companion piece is in the Victoria and Albert Museum.</p>
        <p>Channon (1711-1783) was a member of a family that made furniture for the richest families in England. The commode is thought to be one of a pair commissioned for Fonthill Splendens, a Palladian mansion near Bath that was rebuilt after a 1755 fire by Alderman William Beckford, heir to an immense Jamaican sugar fortune.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hobbs recalled, ''When it came up for auction at Christie's 11 years ago, Gayfryd called me about it, and I told her to buy it because she would never have a chance to buy something categorically by Channon again.''</p>
        <p>Giles Hutchinson-Smith, one of the directors of Mallett, the London antiques shop, said he thought the two commodes would have been placed in ''the center of the room, back to back, to make a real statement.''</p>
        <p>Sotheby's said the commodes were probably made for either Mrs. Beckford's bedroom or the State Bedroom, where the King and Queen would stay at Fonthill Splendens.</p>
        <p>Peter Lang, Sotheby's specialist in English furniture, said, ''It's the best example of the rococo period of this model in England, where you really don't see such elaborate use of bronze mounts.''</p>
        <p>The commode has an exaggerated serpentine top with two sets of five drawers flanking a central niche, which has five smaller drawers. Above the central drawers is a larger drawer with a leafy bronze keyhole escutcheon. It is flanked by two large ormolu female heads. They are nereids, or sea nymphs. Above the keyhole is a bronze garland with different kinds of sea shells.</p>
        <p>The corners have winged satyr heads and front feet with elaborate roroco scrolls. Between them are two scaly winged ormolu dolphins, associated with the goddess Venus.</p>
        <p>''In my opinion Channon was the genius of his century,'' Mr. Hobbs said. ''In terms of design and workmanship he was in a class of his own. He was so innovative he left everyone else for dead. The commode is one of Channon's major pieces.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hobbs pointed out that the Steinberg commode had been ''toned down'' sometime in the past. When it came up for sale at Christie's in 1989, some of the mounts were missing.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Steinberg recalled: ''We were hiking in Arizona, and John Hobbs called to tell us to stay by the phone for the auction. We discussed a limit on how much we would spend. Saul ended up buying it for $:1 million, way above our limit. Then there was the challenge of restoring it, which took a year and a half.''</p>
        <p>The Steinbergs got permission to borrow the twin at the Victoria and Albert Museum and at enormous expense were able to recast its mounts to replace their missing ones. ''The commode is absolutely spectacular, even though half of it has been replaced,'' Mr. Hobbs said. The estimate at Sotheby's is $3 million to $4 million.</p>
        <p>Equally over the top are two pairs of Grimsthorpe Castle side chairs, circa 1755. Made of mahogany with some gilding, each has a delicate pierced back whose top rail is adorned with a Chinese pagoda and beautifully carved cabriole legs ending in scroll-carved toes. The four are part of a set of six; Mallett currently has the third pair.</p>
        <p>''They go to the extremes of luxury and fantasy,'' said Giles Hutchinson-Smith, one of the directors at Mallett.  ''The chairs were conceived as furnishings for a Chinese room and were meant to show off incredible prosperity and power. They were made purely for the drinking of tea. They are incredibly important in that they predate Thomas Chippendale's Chinese-influenced furniture. They show the beginning of a fantasy element, which blew away the restraint of the George II style. They are thought to have been made by William Hallett, whom George II called his 'Chinese mongrel.' '' Each pair at Sotheby's is estimated at $200,000 to $300,000.</p>
        <p>The Steinberg sale ''is extremely impressive,'' said Christopher Gibbs, the London antiques dealer. ''It's a very unboring collection of things. As a mixture, it was decidedly indigestible, not calming in any way, but there are a lot of things to be surprised by.''</p>
        <p>The collection goes on view tomorrow at Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
