<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flamboyant Owner Finds a Horse to Match</title>
    <meta content="19PEGA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sekiguchi, Fusao</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0D9153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flamboyant Owner Finds a Horse to Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE and HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe; French, Howard W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fusao Sekiguchi, flamboyant Japanese entrepreneur, was stranger to American sporting scene until his horse, Fusaichi Pegasus, scored overpowering victory in Kentucky Derby on May 6; horse is odds-on favorite to win Preakness Stakes May 20 at Pimlico Race Course in Baltimore; if he wins, he will have chance to become first horse in 22 years to capture racing's Triple Crown at Belmont Stakes in New York on June 10; Sekiguchi's unconventional career and colorful lifestyle detailed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In July 1998, Fusao Sekiguchi traveled from Japan to Lexington, Ky., with a horse on his mind: an extraordinary one listed as Hip No. 228 at Keeneland race track's annual yearling sales. This was a regally bred colt, the equine equivalent of a Rembrandt, and he was no secret; he was coveted by a group of bidders from the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>The group's members had banded together rather than risk driving up the price by bidding against one another. But Sekiguchi wanted it more. He outbid that group and everyone else, paying the extremely high price of $4 million for the colt that he later named Fusaichi Pegasus. He says now that he would have paid whatever he had to in order to get the horse -- and, in fact, he had financial backing from partners, whom he had to repay within 10 days, to ensure that he came out on top.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In July 1998, Fusao Sekiguchi traveled from Japan to Lexington, Ky., with a horse on his mind: an extraordinary one listed as Hip No. 228 at Keeneland race track's annual yearling sales. This was a regally bred colt, the equine equivalent of a Rembrandt, and he was no secret; he was coveted by a group of bidders from the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>The group's members had banded together rather than risk driving up the price by bidding against one another. But Sekiguchi wanted it more. He outbid that group and everyone else, paying the extremely high price of $4 million for the colt that he later named Fusaichi Pegasus. He says now that he would have paid whatever he had to in order to get the horse -- and, in fact, he had financial backing from partners, whom he had to repay within 10 days, to ensure that he came out on top.</p>
        <p>''I own it entirely now,'' he said. ''I am sure, though, that many others would like to come forward and offer to buy a piece of it.''</p>
        <p>For the moment, Sekiguchi has no plans on sharing the horse. Fusaichi Pegasus scored an overpowering victory in the Kentucky Derby 13 days ago, and is the odds-on favorite to win the Preakness Stakes tomorrow at Pimlico Race Course in Baltimore. If he wins, he will have a chance to become the first horse in 22 years to capture racing's Triple Crown at the Belmont Stakes in New York on June 10.</p>
        <p>It would be a dazzling payoff for Sekiguchi, the flamboyant Japanese entrepreneur.</p>
        <p>Only two weeks ago he was a stranger to the American sporting scene, but he prompted fascination at the Derby with his long ponytail and splashy entrance to the winner's circle at Churchill Downs, where he was accompanied by several incandescently powdered geisha.</p>
        <p>Sekiguchi, 64, won his prized colt the same way he has lived his life and built his businesses: with extravagance, daring and creativity. In Japan, he is a member of a loose class of men who are referred to as bubble gentlemen, a label attached to those who built dizzying individual fortunes in the booming 1980's. It also implies that the source of one's wealth is never quite clear, though signs of it are everywhere.</p>
        <p>He collects modern and vintage racing cars, and two of them grace the lobby of his new company, Venture-Safenet, near Tokyo Bay. He orchestrates spectacles to welcome company recruits, last year importing matadors from Spain and bulls from Mexico, another year renting a disco, piling 100 million yen (about $921,000 at today's rates) on the stage and exhorting his new charges to ''aim high and be a player.''</p>
        <p>''I am a rebel,'' he said of his style. ''It is true that I always take care of my appearance, but my attitude is not always appreciated by others.''</p>
        <p>In 1991 Sekiguchi wrote the book ''Challenge to Japan Dream,'' which became a best seller and offered a vision for success different from the country's traditional approach; he suggested that devoting a career to one company was not the only way to succeed, and that even the world's most formidable corporations sometimes needed help from outside problem solvers. In 1974 he started a business, called Meitec, that trained engineers and then leased them out to companies.</p>
        <p>''Entrepreneurs are not well received in Japan,'' said the retired General Bill Dyke, who first met Sekiguchi in 1987 when he was commander of the United States Army in Japan. ''People who sign on with a company and keep their head down are better regarded. He wanted to move people around, which is a pretty novel concept for Japan. He had this promoter's flair that also didn't go over well.''</p>
        <p>If this high-tech temp service seemed very American, it was, and for good reason. Sekiguchi says he has been fascinated by and appreciative of Western culture since the age of 10 when American G.I.'s occupied his hometown as World War II was coming to an end. They fed him. They told him stories about the States -- including one about the Kentucky Derby. In 1992, according to Dyke, Sekiguchi donated $2 million to the U.S.O.</p>
        <p>Sekiguchi followed up this extravagant gesture with a quieter one. At a dinner honoring Sekiguchi at the Madison Hotel in Washington, D.C., he insisted that a glass of milk and a Hershey bar be placed at each setting. When it was his turn to speak, he spoke of the American soldiers who confounded his and his community's expectations by bringing food and aid to his town. ''He said what he remembered most was the milk and chocolate,'' remembered Dyke, who was a U.S.O. board member. ''So he asked everybody to toast with the milk in thanksgiving for their kindness. There wasn't a dry eye in the place.''</p>
        <p>A year later, Sekiguchi headed down the high dollar horse path that cost him the business he built and launched him on this current Triple Crown campaign. He had been involved in horse racing in Japan since the early 1970's, but asked Dyke to find him a representative in Kentucky to establish a United States  presence. So Dyke introduced him to John Ward, a third-generation horseman from Lexington, who, with his wife, Donna, breeds and trains horses.</p>
        <p>The Wards showed Sekiguchi central Kentucky horse farms, the Kentucky Derby Museum and, most memorably, feted him at sundown with Japanese food on the lawn of the famed Calumet Farms.</p>
        <p>''He was moved,'' Ward said. ''He believes in history and tradition, but he also was able to say where he wanted his horse business to be in five years: the top.''</p>
        <p>In 1996, the year Sekiguchi won his first important race, the Japan Derby, with Fusaichi Concorde, the Meitec board did something seldom done in the staid Japanese business culture -- they ousted him.</p>
        <p>The reason? His love for expensive horses. The new president, Mitsuo Otsuki, told a leading newspaper, The Asahi Shimbun, that Sekiguchi had told him he wanted ''to invest one billion yen or more in the horse-racing business.''</p>
        <p>''They were afraid that I was becoming too powerful, that I was getting too big, and that they couldn't control me,'' said Sekiguchi, who denied he wanted the company to invest in his hobby,</p>
        <p>Last March, a Nagoya district court ruled that it was justified for the Meitec board to demote Sekiguchi -- though it ruled he was due back pay -- and cited the horses, as well as his lavish spending, as reasons. Both sides are appealing the ruling. A lawyer for Meitec, Jun-ichi Tsutsumi, said Sekiguchi was, in effect, draining the company of its resources.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Sekiguchi was earning 27,500,000 yen per month at the time he was ousted, in 1996,'' Mr. Tsutsumi said, which is about $253,000 a month at today's exchange rates and three quarters of what the entire board of directors was making at the time. The timing was awful. He had just bought seven yearlings for $5.75 million at the Keeneland sale. He was forced to return them for resale and promised Keeneland officials that he would make up any shortfall. It was substantial.</p>
        <p>''He handled transactions responsibly and expeditiously,'' said Anthony Bisceglie, his lawyer, who is based in Washington. ''It is why the people at Keeneland have welcomed him back.''</p>
        <p>Until Sekiguchi returned to Keeneland in July 1998, he had little profile on the American racing scene.</p>
        <p>That all changed when he forced a deep-pocketed and willing-to-use-it consortium -- Satish Sanan of Padua Stables in Florida; John Magnier of Coolmore Stud in Ireland; and Michael Tabor, a former betting shop owner in England -- out of the bidding for Fusaichi Pegasus. The name Fusaichi (pronounced foo-sah-eech-ee) is a combination of the first four letters of his given name and the Japanese phrase for ''No. 1.''</p>
        <p>Now, Bisceglie said, numerous inquiries about purchasing part of the colt have been made from the leading stud farms across the world. Sekiguchi shows no indication of selling. And so far he has allowed the trainer, Neil Drysdale, to make all decisions about his superhorse.</p>
        <p>But, as he demonstrated recently in Japan, he can be a strong-willed owner. He believed one of his trainers, Seiki Tabara, was appearing on television too often and threatened to take horses away from him. ''It is the owner's role to be out front,'' he said, and that is another against-the-grain notion in Japan.</p>
        <p>Sekiguchi also prefers to keep his own financial situation a mystery. He said he owed his entire fortune to a ''major capital gain'' when he sold the 38 percent of Meitec he owned for 18 billion yen, or about $166 million at today's exchange rates. He would not say how much he was worth. ''That might create tax problems,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he conceded that the company he started in 1997, Venture-Safenet -- in the same outsourcing niche he pioneered in Japan with Meitec -- had yet to soar to Pegasus heights. He acknowledged reports that the company was badly extended and losing money. ''We don't have any profits,'' he said of his 1,200-employee operation. ''This company lives from my own capital. I am spending my own money here.''</p>
        <p>Still, he is intent on putting on a good show, as he did at the Derby. To spend a couple of hours with a sole geisha, for example, can routinely cost $500 and extend as high as $3,000. In an interview in his office in Tokyo this week, however, Sekiguchi shrugged and said he had no idea what it cost to bring two geisha, a maiko (a trainee) and their oka-san, or ''mother,'' to Louisville.</p>
        <p>''I was nervous about what would happen if I lost,'' he said. ''The press would just be talking about the money I had spent. I had to think only of winning, and having the three women there was intended to be part of the performance.''</p>
        <p>He will not be in Baltimore at the Preakness tomorrow when his big horse tries to race one step closer to the Triple Crown. He is busy trying to build a business and, as appreciative as he is of America, he does not like to venture from home too often. His daughter-in-law, Yukari, who manages the 40 horses Sekiguchi currently races, will represent him.</p>
        <p>Sekiguchi says his Triple Crown run is as hard as it is glorious. ''In the U.S., when I won, everyone congratulated me,'' he said. ''Here, in Japan, people just turned their heads and looked away.''</p>
        <p>But this horse, he said, makes it all worthwhile. ''When I laid my eyes on the colt,'' he said, ''I knew he was going to be a Derby winner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
