<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Average Cost Of Apartments Hits $700,000</title>
    <meta content="19REAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Douglas Elliman</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4D6143AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Average Cost Of Apartments Hits $700,000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hevesi, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Douglas Elliman Manhattan Market Report, one of real estate industry's most comprehensive surveys, shows that average price for apartments in Manhattan jumped by almost a third over last year, breaking $700,000 mark for first time, and continuing a seemingly inexorable climb; shows that average price for an apartment south of West 116th Street and East 96th Street rose to $733,860 during first quarter of 2000, 31 percent rise from $559,204 average recorded in first quarter of 1999; $733,860 figures represents 77 percent increase over average price of $414,187 recorded in 1995--during bottoming out of last real-estate recession--and 62 percent over $453,909 average in 1990 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Continuing a seemingly inexorable climb, the average price for apartments in much of Manhattan jumped by nearly a third over the last year, breaking the $700,000 mark for the first time, according to one of the real estate industry's most comprehensive surveys.</p>
        <p>The average price for an apartment south of West 116th Street and East 96th Street rose to $733,860 during the first quarter of 2000, a 31 percent rise from the $559,204 average recorded in the first quarter of 1999, according to the study, the Douglas Elliman Manhattan Market Report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Continuing a seemingly inexorable climb, the average price for apartments in much of Manhattan jumped by nearly a third over the last year, breaking the $700,000 mark for the first time, according to one of the real estate industry's most comprehensive surveys.</p>
        <p>The average price for an apartment south of West 116th Street and East 96th Street rose to $733,860 during the first quarter of 2000, a 31 percent rise from the $559,204 average recorded in the first quarter of 1999, according to the study, the Douglas Elliman Manhattan Market Report.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time ever that the average has exceeded $700,000,'' said Jonathan Miller, president of Miller Samuel, the appraisal company that prepares the quarterly report. Mr. Miller said a major contributor to the jump in the overall average price was an increased proportion of larger apartments in the quarter's sales.</p>
        <p>The $733,860 figure represents a 77 percent increase over the average price of $414,187 recorded in 1995 -- during the bottoming-out of the last real estate recession -- and 62 percent over the $453,909 average in 1990.</p>
        <p>''Things are crazy, but it's still not the 80's in terms of percentage,'' Mr. Miller said, pointing out that between the fourth quarters of 1985 and 1986, the overall average price rose 49.1 percent, to $580,282 from $389,170. Adjusted for inflation, that 1986 average of $580,282 would be $906,458 today.</p>
        <p>Dr. James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University, put the current increases in perspective. ''We're in an era of setting economic records,'' Dr. Hughes said. ''Each month, we break the record for the longest economic expansion in history. Manhattan has become one of the major locomotives of this record-setting, and it would be shocking if this were not reflected in surging housing prices in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''This now rivals the boom of the 1980's in terms of a single year,'' Dr. Hughes said. ''The difference in the 80's was that the price surge was sustained over a seven-year period. This current boom has really only taken off the last two years. As long as the national economy keeps expanding, the price momentum in Manhattan will continue. And the national economy is still red hot, which is why we had the Federal Reserve interest rate hike on Tuesday.''</p>
        <p>Manhattan, to be sure, is not the only place in the country where price rises have been breathtaking. In Santa Clara County, Calif., which includes most of Silicon Valley, the local association of Realtors reported in April that the average price for a single-family home hit $702,165, a 37 percent increase from $513,085 in April 1999, and that the average price of condominiums and town houses had jumped 30 percent over the same period, to $341,167 from $262,139.</p>
        <p>The Elliman first-quarter report was based on 2,313 closed deals for both co-op and condominium apartments, representing about 75 percent of the market's volume. It does not include sales of less than $75,000, Mr. Miller said, because there are so few transactions below that mark ''that they are insignificant to the overall results.''</p>
        <p>Deborah Beck, executive vice president of the Real Estate Board of New York, expressing concern that the Elliman numbers might scare off potential buyers, pointed out that the report did not cover northern Manhattan and that prices for smaller apartments throughout the borough, while increasing significantly, were more reasonable.</p>
        <p>And placing the Manhattan numbers in geographical context, Kevin Thorpe, an economist with the National Association of Realtors, cited the median price for an existing single-family home in the Greater New York Region, which the association defines as the city and certain suburban areas. The median was $221,500 in the first quarter of 2000 -- a rise of 14.3 percent from the $193,800 median in the first quarter of 1999, and 6.5 percent above the median of $207,900 at the end of last year. The median price is the point at which half the sales were above that figure and half were below it.</p>
        <p>The Elliman Manhattan survey found that the average price for condominiums had increased 40 percent in a year, from $682,094 in the first quarter of 1999 to $952,761 this quarter. ''That's a staggering increase, since we have never seen the quarterly average for condos exceed $700,000,'' Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>Breaking down the condominium category by apartment size, the average price for a studio in the first quarter of 2000 was $243,667, up 38 percent from $175,986 in the first quarter of 1999. For one-bedrooms, the average was $387,961, a 7 percent increase from $361,397 a year ago. The two-bedroom average this year was $958,202, up 8 percent from $888,093.</p>
        <p>For three-bedrooms, the average price was $1,997,053, a 75 percent jump from $1,140,600 in the first quarter of '99. (Mr. Miller attributed that increase to great demand for the few available properties.) And for condos with four or more bedrooms, the average price in the first quarter of 2000 was $4,118,750, a 7 percent increase from $3,836,414 in the first quarter of '99.</p>
        <p>''My theory for the change in the overall average is that there has been a shift to larger units; a significant increase in the number of two-bedroom sales relative to the rest of the market,'' Mr. Miller said. ''The two-bedroom apartment is becoming a first-purchase preference.'' In the first quarter of '99, two-bedroom condominium sales represented 33 percent of the condominium market; this year, they represented 49 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Sicular, director of appraisal and consulting at Brown Harris Stevens, a major Manhattan real estate brokerage firm, concurred: ''The change in mix sounds like a very plausible explanation. The demand for one-bedrooms may be in relative decline because people may prefer to rent until they can buy a two-bedroom.</p>
        <p>''In the 80's,'' Mr. Sicular explained, ''people felt that every type of property went up, so anything they bought would provide leverage for their next purchase. Now they are viewing real estate less as a speculative investment than they did in the last real estate cycle. They're not going to trade up every one or two years, thinking they are going to make money.''</p>
        <p>In the co-op category, the Elliman survey reported the average price increased 24 percent over the year, to $576,596 from $464,692. ''That's the highest average ever recorded for co-ops in our study,'' Mr. Miller said. ''And like the condos, the co-ops also saw a gain in the two-bedroom market share, from 33 percent last year to 38 percent this year.''</p>
        <p>For co-ops, by apartment size, the average price for a studio was $142,060 in the first quarter of this year, up 19 percent from $119,444 in the first quarter of 1999. For one-bedrooms, the average was $291,675, a 28 percent increase over $227,229 in 1999. In the two-bedroom category, the average this year was $760,578, up 39 percent from $547,407. For three-bedrooms, it was $1,858,576, up 44 percent from $1,294,840. And for those with four or more bedrooms, the average price in the first quarter of 2000 was $3,565,625, a decrease of 24 percent from $4,690,833 last year. There are relatively few sales of apartments with four or more bedrooms, so prices in that category are particularly volatile.</p>
        <p>Asked about further price increases, Mr. Miller said his company's appraisals showed a continued rapid increase in prices in the last six weeks, the first half of the second quarter. ''I would expect it to continue at least through mid-June, when the kids are out of school and we usually see a lessening of activity.''</p>
        <p>Concerned about wary buyers, Ms. Beck of the real estate board noted that the board's report covered all of Manhattan, ''so that our figures aren't quite as euphoric, although they are wonderful.'' The median price for co-ops in all of Manhattan during the first quarter of this year was $397,500, the real estate board reported, up 14 percent from $350,000 in the first quarter of 1999. Condominium prices were not available.</p>
        <p>Ms. Beck pointed out that more than 80 percent of all apartments in Manhattan were studios, one-bedrooms or two-bedrooms. And the median price for those apartments, taken together, was $342,500 in the first quarter of this year, up 12 percent from $306,000 a year ago.</p>
        <p>''Some consumers would look at the Elliman numbers and say, 'I can't afford that,' '' Ms. Beck said. ''But if they look at the median price, particularly on studios, one- and two-bedroom units, they will find encouragement.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
