<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Time Warner and Disney Agree to End Dispute About Cable</title>
    <meta content="Y19CAB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levin, Gerald M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3DA153AF93AA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Time Warner and Disney Agree to End Dispute About Cable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time Warner chairman Gerald M Levin says Time Warner and Walt Disney Co have reached agreement in principle that will end their dispute over cable transmission of television channels owned by Disney, address to shareholders; neither Time Warner nor Disney executives will discuss specific details of agreement, saying that it needs to be committed to contractual language first (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Time Warner and the Walt Disney Company have reached an agreement in principle that will end their rancorous dispute over the cable transmission of television channels owned by Disney, the Time Warner chairman, Gerald M. Levin, told shareholders at the company's annual meeting yesterday.</p>
        <p>Neither Time Warner nor Disney executives would discuss the specific details of the agreement yesterday, saying that it needs to be committed to contractual language first. But one executive close to the negotiations said that it was ''completely an economic deal,'' meaning that it would not specifically address Disney's demands for assurances about the pending merger between America Online and Time Warner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Time Warner and the Walt Disney Company have reached an agreement in principle that will end their rancorous dispute over the cable transmission of television channels owned by Disney, the Time Warner chairman, Gerald M. Levin, told shareholders at the company's annual meeting yesterday.</p>
        <p>Neither Time Warner nor Disney executives would discuss the specific details of the agreement yesterday, saying that it needs to be committed to contractual language first. But one executive close to the negotiations said that it was ''completely an economic deal,'' meaning that it would not specifically address Disney's demands for assurances about the pending merger between America Online and Time Warner.</p>
        <p>Disney had raised concerns that the new company would deny access on the Internet or cable television to competitive providers of entertainment and information.</p>
        <p>In his remarks to the shareholders, Mr. Levin said that the deal was a result of direct negotiations between Robert A. Iger, the president of the Disney Company, and Richard D. Parsons, the president of Time Warner, and that they had reached what he called a handshake agreement. A Time Warner spokesman, Edward Adler, later labeled it a ''telephonic handshake.''</p>
        <p>Executives at each of the companies said that the refusal by senior executives to discuss the details was a result of the bitterness that has surrounded the negotiations. The tensions led to Time Warner's decision to take Disney's ABC stations off its cable systems on May 1. Time Warner had declined a Disney offer of a one-month extension in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>The move proved calamitous for Time Warner when the company was criticized by consumers, editorial writers and politicians in New York and Washington.</p>
        <p>Time Warner restored the service one day later, agreeing to an extension until July 15. Mindful of that fallout, Mr. Levin said in his remarks at the annual meeting that Time Warner had apologized to consumers and regulators for terminating access to ABC stations. Then he added that the companies had reached an agreement in principle to resolve what he called their commercial dispute.</p>
        <p>The executive close to the negotiations said that Mr. Levin's careful language was an indication that the resolution would deal solely with the financial details of Time Warner's agreement to continue carrying the ABC stations and would not specifically address Disney's concerns about the merger with AOL.</p>
        <p>''Obviously this agreement is an enormously positive step,'' the executive said. ''Whether it's the last step or not, time will tell.''</p>
        <p>Disney executives challenged some aspects of the merger in meetings with both Congressmen and representatives of the Federal Communications Commission last week. Though Disney did not ask the commission to block the merger itself, Disney did request that it issue certain directives that would ensure that competitors received the same full access to consumers that any AOL or Time Warner company received after the two companies merged.</p>
        <p>Disney's worries about whether a combined AOL and Time Warner would wield too much control over access to both the Internet and cable distribution became a factor in what had been longstanding negotiations over how Disney would be compensated for the transmission on Time Warner cable systems of the ABC stations that Disney owns.</p>
        <p>Disney had backed off a deal that was near completion when the AOL merger was announced. Time Warner contended that after the merger announcement, Disney greatly increased its financial demands, to a point where it would have cost Time Warner another $300 million over 10 years. Disney disputed that figure.</p>
        <p>The money was to come to Disney in fees for carrying cable channels that Disney owns, including the Disney Channel, the Soap Channel and Toon Disney.</p>
        <p>The rancor escalated into the showdown at the beginning of the month, when Time Warner pulled ABC off the air in a number of cities including New York, Los Angeles, and Houston. ABC reacted by placing advertisements in many papers urging consumers to purchase satellite dishes to circumvent Time Warner's cable service. ABC agreed to pay the cost of the dishes.</p>
        <p>That move greatly angered Time Warner officials, who said Disney was directly threatening their business.</p>
        <p>But there were indications early this week that the two sides were getting closer because the ads for ABC's satellite deal were pulled from newspapers starting Tuesday.</p>
        <p>And earlier this week, Time Warner reached agreement with NBC for transmission of that network's stations. ''That move sort of isolated ABC,'' a Time Warner executive said. ''It helped move things along.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
