<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Is No.1, but Parity Follows</title>
    <meta content="02USAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BY THE NUMBERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED6153DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Is No.1, but Parity Follows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States dominates Olympic Games, winning 97 medals in all, 39 gold, more than any other country; Russia wins second most, 88 medals, 32 gold, in 23 sports; China is third in medal tally with 59 total, 28 gold, in 12 sports; Australia has best showing ever, finishing fourth, with 58 total, 16 gold; (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American success began with a surprise, on a Saturday morning nearly 20 miles west of downtown Sydney in an agricultural area known as the Cumberland Plain. Nancy Johnson won the first gold medal of the 2000 Olympic Games, and did so in an upset at the 10-meter air rifle event.</p>
        <p>It ended 15 days later, with something preordained, even if it was startlingly close: an American victory in men's basketball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American success began with a surprise, on a Saturday morning nearly 20 miles west of downtown Sydney in an agricultural area known as the Cumberland Plain. Nancy Johnson won the first gold medal of the 2000 Olympic Games, and did so in an upset at the 10-meter air rifle event.</p>
        <p>It ended 15 days later, with something preordained, even if it was startlingly close: an American victory in men's basketball.</p>
        <p>The United States won 97 medals in all, 39 gold, more than any other country in either category. From baseball to beach volleyball, from swimming to softball, the Americans were dominant. In addition to Marion Jones's five track and field medals at these Games -- three gold and two bronze -- the United States team provided engaging stories and standout performances in unexpected places. The Greco-Roman wrestler Rulon Gardner might have provided the upset of the Games when he won the gold over Aleksandr Karelin, who had never lost in a major international competition.</p>
        <p>But these Games brought evidence that several national athletic programs are growing stronger. Russia won medals in 23 sports -- more than anyone -- and won the second most medals over all (88) and the second most gold medals (32). China, despite leaving behind 27 athletes suspended for drug testing problems, was third in the medal tally with 59, 28 of them gold.</p>
        <p>The Chinese won medals in a dozen sports, and had a stranglehold on diving, where they won five golds and five silvers. They won eight table tennis medals, including golds in all four categories. They also won their first men's team gymnastics gold medal.</p>
        <p>Australia had its best Olympic showing. In addition to putting on a good show, the Aussies wanted to perform well, having poured millions into nationwide sporting programs after a dismal medal count at the 1976 Montreal Olympics. For a nation of 18 million, the Australians kept up with the largest nations in the world, finishing fourth in the medal count with 58 and also finishing fourth in gold medals with 16. Germany was fifth with 57 medals, 14 gold.</p>
        <p>The countries of the former Soviet Union had an extremely strong showing. Excluding Russia, 12 countries formed by the breakup of the Soviet Union won medals in Sydney: Belarus, Uzbekistan, Georgia, Lithuania, Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan, Latvia, Estonia, Moldova, Armenia, Kyrgyzstan and Ukraine.</p>
        <p>If their totals were combined -- as if the Soviet Union were still together -- they would have won 48 gold medals, 48 silver medals and 67 bronze medals, or 163 medals over all. That figure dwarfs any other country's total.</p>
        <p>The American softball pitcher Lisa Fernandez, whose gold medal team had to win five consecutive games after losing three in a row, said these Games would be remembered for the high level of competition.</p>
        <p>''Just look at our story,'' Fernandez said. ''Here's a team that came in with a 110-game winning streak, and we got beat three in a row. It shows how far the other countries have come. The playing field is leveling. Maybe in most sports.</p>
        <p>''That's what was great about these Games. We had cable satellite feeds in our Olympic Village, and we would come back from a game or practice and watch all kinds of sports, just everything. The competition level was so high.''</p>
        <p>That proved to be true to the very end, with France, never an Olympic basketball power, testing the United States in the final minutes of the men's basketball final.</p>
        <p>An Olympic Games of surprises almost had one last one in it.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BY THE NUMBERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
