<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nader Assails His Exclusion From Debates</title>
    <meta content="Y02NAD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/politics/02NADE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barstow, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D8123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nader Assails His Exclusion From Debates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARSTOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barstow, David</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Green Party presidential candidate Ralph Nader accuses two major parties and their corporate supporters of stifling democracy by keeping him out of presidential debates; tells supporters in Boston that Republican and Democratic Parties are excluding him because they are determined to prevent him from asking questions about corporate influence before national television audience; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Staring out at a raucous audience of some 12,000 people, soaking up their insistent chants of ''Let Ralph debate,'' the Green Party presidential candidate, Ralph Nader, accused the two major parties and their corporate supporters today of stifling democracy by keeping him out of Tuesday night's presidential debate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader and those who shared the stage with him at the Fleet Center this afternoon repeatedly asserted that the Republican and Democratic Parties were excluding him from the debates because they were determined to prevent him from asking questions about corporate influence before a national television audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Staring out at a raucous audience of some 12,000 people, soaking up their insistent chants of ''Let Ralph debate,'' the Green Party presidential candidate, Ralph Nader, accused the two major parties and their corporate supporters today of stifling democracy by keeping him out of Tuesday night's presidential debate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader and those who shared the stage with him at the Fleet Center this afternoon repeatedly asserted that the Republican and Democratic Parties were excluding him from the debates because they were determined to prevent him from asking questions about corporate influence before a national television audience.</p>
        <p>The former talk-show host, Phil Donohue, the master of ceremonies at today's rally, said Mr. Nader had strong opinions about corporations that replace American workers with ''32-cent-an-hour'' workers in foreign countries.</p>
        <p>''You won't hear it on that stage because Ralph Nader won't be there,'' Mr. Donohue said of the debate. Underscoring the point, hundreds of people waved signs that depicted Mr. Nader with an American flag wrapped across his mouth.</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas said the candidates had nothing to do with Mr. Nader's failed efforts to join the debates.</p>
        <p>The criteria for debate participation, they said, was set by the Commission on Presidential Debates, a bipartisan group that decided to invite only candidates who had the  support of an average of at least 15 percent of those polled in five national surveys. Recent polls put Mr. Nader's support at 2 percent to 5 percent.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that there are over 200 people running for president,'' said Jano Cabrera, a spokesman for the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>In an interview after his speech, Mr. Nader made it clear that he intended to make his presence felt at Tuesday night's debate, which will be held at the University of Massachusetts campus in Boston.</p>
        <p>He said he was trying to get a ticket to the event, and he called on his supporters to converge on the debate site for an evening of protest.</p>
        <p>''I think we have to make a statement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Today's event was the fourth of what Mr. Nader's campaign staff called his ''super rallies.''</p>
        <p>He attracted 10,000 in Portland, Ore., 12,000 in Minneapolis and 10,000 in Seattle. A fifth rally was scheduled for Chicago on Tuesday, Oct. 10.</p>
        <p>The crowd at the Fleet Center was made up largely of young people, a mixture of college graduates, budding socialists, eager environmentalists and others who were carrying the banner for all manner of progressive causes.</p>
        <p>At times, the rally resembled less a political happening than a body piercing convention, with earrings sprouting from noses, eyebrows, tongues, lips and sometimes even ears. In interviews, dozens of people said they had voted for President Clinton in 1996 but had since become disenchanted.</p>
        <p>''Slackers can change this country,'' said the filmmaker Michael Moore, who has been touring with Mr. Nader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader pointed out that he was drawing the largest crowds of any of the candidates even though he  charged $7 for the first three events and $10 for today's event. ''It's about as clean money as you could ever imagine,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>But as a fund-raising tool, the rallies are not particularly effective. Nader's campaign aides said most of the money raised was spent covering the costs of rallies like the one at the Fleet Center, which charged $80,000 in rent.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Nader and his staff viewed the events as essential to giving him credibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader had promised to talk about the ''politics of joy and justice.'' But instead he mounted an unrelenting rhetorical assault on his nemesis, Corporate America.</p>
        <p>Again and again he described the nation's most serious problems as symptoms of unchecked corporate greed. Cancer? He blamed tobacco companies. Pollution? He blamed major oil companies. No money for antipoverty programs? He blamed defense contractors who lobby for costly weapons systems that do not work.</p>
        <p>The central issue of the election, he said, is whether the nation has the political will to wrest power from the ''oligarchy'' of ever-larger multinational corporations.</p>
        <p>Democrats and Republicans, he said, are beholden to corporate supporters who underwrite their political campaigns, and they have become almost indistinguishable on many policy issues.</p>
        <p>''They say things differently,'' he  said, ''but they don't do things differently.''</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Nader called Mr. Bush ''a corporation running for president disguised as a person.'' But his harshest attacks were reserved for the Democratic Party in general and Mr. Gore in particular.</p>
        <p>He accused President Clinton of presiding over a ''criminal injustice system'' that has ''turned drug addicts into criminals and sent them to corporate prisons.''</p>
        <p>He mocked Mr. Gore's pledge to fight big oil, major pharmaceutical companies and health maintenance organizations.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, yeah, and I've got a bridge in Brooklyn to sell you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
