<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Has New Stories to Tell, but Reality Lurks in the Wings</title>
    <meta content="02SEAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/arts/02SEAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Has New Stories to Tell, but Reality Lurks in the Wings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Television networks, set to open new season, will offer burst of new shows that lean heavily toward conventional, at least in format; virtually all shows sit within broad categories of sitcom or drama; host of new 'reality' shows is planned for later in season, but none are in fall lineup; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For network programmers the television season that begins tonight blooms with more promise than any since the mid-1990's; it also looms with just as much threat.</p>
        <p>The broadcast networks learned a vivid lesson last season: real hits are still possible. Not the niche successes they have come to accept in a cable-saturated era -- hits with teenagers, or women under the age of 35, or families with incomes over $75,000 -- but bona fide, the-whole-country-is-talking-about-them hits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For network programmers the television season that begins tonight blooms with more promise than any since the mid-1990's; it also looms with just as much threat.</p>
        <p>The broadcast networks learned a vivid lesson last season: real hits are still possible. Not the niche successes they have come to accept in a cable-saturated era -- hits with teenagers, or women under the age of 35, or families with incomes over $75,000 -- but bona fide, the-whole-country-is-talking-about-them hits.</p>
        <p>Starting last January, when ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' became a regular part of ABC's schedule, network television, caught in a long downward spiral of diminishing expectations based on diminished returns, found itself lifted by a whiff of revival. After CBS electrified the country for 13 weeks in the summer with ''Survivor,'' the window of opportunity blasted open.</p>
        <p>Given the right show, a network could still be what it used to be: the truly dominant entertainment source for the nation.</p>
        <p>But with opportunity comes risk, and as the 2000-1 television season gets off to a belated start -- thanks to two weeks of Olympics on NBC -- the executives who choose the shows find themselves wondering more than ever: what exactly do people want to see?</p>
        <p>Their answers, which will dribble out in bursts of new shows, spread over the next six weeks, lean heavily toward the conventional, at least in terms of format. Virtually every show sits within the broad categories of sitcom or drama. A host of new ''reality'' shows is planned for later in the season, but none are on the fall lineup. ''Millionaire.'' meanwhile, will expand to four nights a week.</p>
        <p>That leaves a group of new comedies and dramas, even though programmers acknowledge that those formats have all but worn out their welcome with many viewers, who seem to shrug and sigh when they see a comedy with a sofa stuck in the middle of a living room. From ''Yes, Dear,'' on CBS to ''The Geena Davis Show'' on ABC, to ''Normal, Ohio'' on Fox, sofa-based comedies are still in vogue, even if populated with characters who might be more unorthodox than those of the past. There is, for example, John Goodman, whose character in ''Normal'' returns to the family he abandoned for life as a gay man in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Tom Werner, a partner in the Carsey-Werner Company, which created ''Normal, Ohio,'' put his finger on the issue that seems of most network concern: ''It's going to be a tough year for story-form shows.''</p>
        <p>Television people did not use the term ''story form'' much in the past because just about everything but news magazines was story-form television, that is, entertainment shows based on actors performing a script.</p>
        <p>''Millionaire'' and ''Survivor'' have made that format vulnerable because nothing performed on Hollywood sound stages in the last five years came close to capturing their viewer interest. Garth Ancier, the president of NBC Entertainment, said, ''What happened with those two shows in being so different is that they broke the stranglehold of story-form television.''</p>
        <p>Story-form shows have continued to be successful, of course. ''The West Wing'' was the most talked about drama of last season and a strong enough rating performer. But it did not play in the same ratings league as ''Millionaire'' and ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>And the high quality of ''West Wing'' -- which won the Emmy as best drama on television in its first year -- is causing some pressure of its own. As an executive at a competing network put it: ''People watch a show like 'West Wing' because it is executed at such a high level. How many shows like that can you do?''</p>
        <p>ABC thinks it may have one in ''Gideon's Crossing,'' a medical drama dealing mainly with all but hopeless cases that boasts one of television's most admired actors, Andre Braugher. The network thinks so much of the show that it is broadcasting the pilot on Wednesday night without a single commercial interruption, a ploy it hopes will draw plenty of attention, and viewers.</p>
        <p>Fox is relying on the talents of David E. Kelley, who has devised two of the medium's most distinctive hours in ''Ally McBeal'' and ''The Practice.'' ''Boston Public'' places a host of quirky Kelley characters in a high school.</p>
        <p>NBC, which scored with the on-the-sleeve earnestness of political drama in ''The West Wing'' last season, is betting heavily on quirkiness itself in its most anticipated hour, ''Ed,'' a show that mixes the warmth of coming home with the premise of a lawyer who works out of his bowling alley.</p>
        <p>CBS is going in a slightly different direction with ''The Fugitive,'' a remake of a classic, which the network wants to make fresh for a new generation of viewers, with Tim Daly doing the weekly run from injustice.</p>
        <p>The main optimism at the networks seems to center on their dramas, a big shift from just a few years ago when prime time was glutted with comedies. Fox is banking on sci-fi thrillers like ''Dark Angel'' and ''Freakylinks'' as well as sex-drenched, glossy soap opera in ''The Street.'' CBS has hopes for two police dramas, ''C.S.I.'' and ''The District,'' and WB thinks it can score with ''Gilmore Girls,'' an hourlong family show with attitude,</p>
        <p>Quality and comedy have rarely worked their way into the same sentence in recent seasons. The exceptions -- like ''Everybody Loves Raymond'' and ''Will and Grace'' -- have emerged as reliable favorites, if not raging hits. But the misses have piled up so high that network programmers almost seem gun-shy about risking too many time periods on comedy.</p>
        <p>When they do, they are going back to star vehicles like ''Bette,'' on CBS, which brings a true comedic leading lady, Bette Midler, to the sitcom realm for the first time. (She sings, but she, too, has a living-room sofa.) ABC has both Geena Davis and Gabriel Bryne, whose ''Madigan Men'' is a multigenerational sofa show with an Irish accent. NBC is risking the most with ''The Michael Richards Show,'' with Mr. Richards, the first of the icons of ''Seinfeld'' to try a new comedy, as a bumbling private eye. After an initial pilot flopped in epic fashion, much rides on a totally remade show that only NBC executives have seen.</p>
        <p>Is there a hit in the bunch that will stoke the fires of the network comeback ignited by ''Millionaire'' and ''Survivor?'' No one is answering out loud, or even in a whisper. Instead the story-form shows can probably expect to spend the season looking over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>More and more reality show formats have been purchased by every network, with concepts ranging from a woman going around chained to men she may or may not want to date, to a contest among a group of pudgy aspirants based on who can lose the most weight.</p>
        <p>None of the reality shows made it onto the fall network schedules, but they are poised to plug the holes that always come when what had looked like great ideas die early deaths. By January one or more of these shows will probably be testing the audience's fascination with the reality format.</p>
        <p>But towering over everything else, and casting a shadow of both possibility and menace, will be ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' still expected to lead ABC single-handedly to network leadership.</p>
        <p>Unless CBS finds a way to stay close until January. Starting on Jan.  30 is a show called ''Survivor II.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
