<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABC tries to bring its longtime 'dot' logo into prominence with a new campaign.</title>
    <meta content="02ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/technology/02ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DoDots Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5D6153DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABC tries to bring its longtime 'dot' logo into prominence with a new campaign.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ABC television network is making its longtime logo focus of ambitious promotion to spur viewers to interact with its Web site; promotion uses technology developed by DoDots Inc to let visitors to Web site download small packages of Internet content, with network themes ranging from video clips and calendar to games and news ticker; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TELEVISION network is making its longtime logo the focus of an ambitious promotion to encourage viewers to interact with its Web site.</p>
        <p>Which network? Here's a hint: The effort, which is to begin today to mark the start of the 2000-2001 prime-time TV season, involves neither eyes nor peacocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TELEVISION network is making its longtime logo the focus of an ambitious promotion to encourage viewers to interact with its Web site.</p>
        <p>Which network? Here's a hint: The effort, which is to begin today to mark the start of the 2000-2001 prime-time TV season, involves neither eyes nor peacocks.</p>
        <p>The promotion, by the ABC unit of the Walt Disney Company, is emblematic of attempts by media giants to more closely integrate their offline and online operations. With convergence -- the buzzword for the eventual union of the TV set and the PC -- still seemingly as far off as a live Olympics on NBC, consumers are being offered various combinations of old-  and new-media content.</p>
        <p>For instance, during its broadcasts of the Summer Games that ended last night, NBC, part of the General Electric Company, lavishly promoted a Web site (www.nbcolympics.com) that was part of a joint venture with Quokka.com.</p>
        <p>''We're always trying to find new and different platforms to help people think about the ABC brand: our shows, our stars, our identity,'' said Alan Cohen, executive vice president for marketing, advertising and promotion at ABC in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The promotion uses a technology developed by a company named DoDots Inc. to offer visitors to the ABC Web site (www.abc.com) an opportunity to download directly to their desktops small packages of Internet content, called ABC Dots, with network themes ranging from video clips and a calendar to games and a news ticker. The effort is centered on the ABC logo, the disc carrying the initials of the American Broadcasting Company in lower-case letters.</p>
        <p>''The one thing we want more than anything,'' said Mike Benson, senior vice president for advertising and promotion at ABC, ''is that when people pick up the remote control, we want them to think of ABC first instead of just thinking 'What's on?' and surfing all over.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benson and other ABC executives refer to the logo -- rendered in black and yellow as well as black and white -- as the ABC ''dot,'' which of course also echoes the ''dot'' in ''dot-com.''</p>
        <p>The ABC dot -- designed by Paul Rand and introduced in 1962 -- is now being featured prominently in commercials running on ABC that promote the new prime-time lineup. Still, it is less of an icon than its more familiar counterparts, the CBS eye and the NBC peacock. Another challenge: many in the television industry call the ABC logo the ''meatball,'' after its round, compact shape.</p>
        <p>Indeed, a meatball logo offers few options for promotions apart from joint ventures with Chef Boyardee. But a dot logo -- well, ABC has already reached agreement with Hearst Entertainment, representing Harvey Entertainment, to use the comic book mainstay Little Dot as the spokescharacter for the ABC Dots promotion.</p>
        <p>Visitors to the ABC.com home page will be prompted by Little Dot to ''download the dot.'' That will deliver an ABC dot logo that flies around the computer screen, then settles at the bottom right corner. Click on the logo and a ''Hubdot'' appears, where there are links to the content packages.</p>
        <p>(The dot will start up automatically whenever the computer is started. For those not eager to have their screen permanently branded by ABC, the logo can be removed with some right-click mouse moves.)</p>
        <p>The promotion ''allows consumers to continue to interact with ABC when they're not watching TV,'' said Brian Bowman, vice president and general manager at ABC.com.</p>
        <p>''Alan and Mike came to us with this wacky idea that they wanted to communicate with viewers on the desktops of their computers,'' he added. ''We had some companies come in to pitch the technology and settled on DoDots.''</p>
        <p>The DoDots technology is being used by more than 40 companies that include, in addition to ABC, Bluelight.com, CNET, Excite @Home and ZDNET.</p>
        <p>''It's a way to package, brand and distribute your content across the Internet to your customers without them having to go find it,'' said George Kembel, chief executive at DoDots in Sunnyvale, Calif.</p>
        <p>''When you get the DoDots instead of surfing through Web pages,'' he added, ''it's more engaging.''</p>
        <p>The dots are the most recent in a lengthy list of nontraditional promotions for ABC that include ads on fruit stickers, coffee cups and even urinals in men's rooms. A plan to promote the fall lineup by leaving taped messages on the answering machines of viewers was canceled in July after news reports generated widespread disapproval.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen and Mr. Benson are already at work on additional ways to extend the dots promotion.</p>
        <p>''We're working with Tootsie Roll Industries, the maker of Dots candy, to customize a package of yellow and black Dots,'' Mr. Cohen said.</p>
        <p>And dot's the way it is, as a dotty Walter Cronkite might conclude.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
