<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even a Tycoon Has an Occasional Lapse at the Card Table</title>
    <meta content="02CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Bill (William H)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D6153DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even a Tycoon Has an Occasional Lapse at the Card Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on hand defended by Mircosoft Corp chairman Bill Gates at recent national tournament; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Millions know that Bill Gates is the chairman of Microsoft and, in spite of some recent misfortunes, the world's richest man. But fewer people know that he is a bridge enthusiast who recently played in his first national championship.</p>
        <p>For several years he has been taking instruction from Sharon Osberg of San Francisco, a top international player, reading books and playing in local tournaments and online. ''The game is so deep,'' he said. ''There is always something you can learn, and it rewards you when you use good judgment. And it's fun.'' His bidding preference is for Yellow Card, the straightforward method that is standard in online games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Millions know that Bill Gates is the chairman of Microsoft and, in spite of some recent misfortunes, the world's richest man. But fewer people know that he is a bridge enthusiast who recently played in his first national championship.</p>
        <p>For several years he has been taking instruction from Sharon Osberg of San Francisco, a top international player, reading books and playing in local tournaments and online. ''The game is so deep,'' he said. ''There is always something you can learn, and it rewards you when you use good judgment. And it's fun.'' His bidding preference is for Yellow Card, the straightforward method that is standard in online games.</p>
        <p>Six weeks ago in Anaheim, Calif., Gates competed in the Mixed Team Championship at the end of the American Contract Bridge League's Summer Nationals. In an interview he revealed, ''My desk is covered with books, half of them on bridge and the other half on world health.'' The latter is a reference to the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, to which he recently donated $5 billion.</p>
        <p>He was teamed with Osberg, Howard Weinstein of Chicago and Sheri Winestock of Toronto. Warren E. Buffett, chairman of Berkshire Hathaway Inc. and a frequent bridge partner of Gates, was expected to be a member of the team but was recovering from surgery. The foursome did well in the qualifying stage but slumped in the final in a field with many world-class players. Gates was quick to take the blame. ''We had several bidding misunderstandings that were primarily my fault,'' he said. ''It's really frustrating to get a play problem wrong. I feel I should always be able to work it out.''</p>
        <p>He did work out the solution to a difficult defensive problem on the diagramed deal. As West he did the right thing in the bidding after his partner opened one no-trump, persevering in hearts to the three-level and pushing his opponents to three spades. He led a heart, and his partner took two heart winners and shifted to a club. This was ducked, and the moment of truth arrived when he won with the king. The obvious return of a club would have allowed the declarer to succeed, since all the missing high-card strength was marked in the East hand. South would have won, crossed to the diamond king and finessed the spade queen. Then he would have cashed the spade ace and the remaining club winner. Finally a trump lead would endplay East, forcing a lead from the diamond queen or a ruff-and-sluff. In either case South would avoid the potential diamond loser and make his contract.</p>
        <p>Instead Gates hit on the crucial shift to a diamond. This did not help solve South's entry problems, and he had to lose two more tricks eventually. The result was down one.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
