<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beijing Protest By Falun Sect Brings Arrest Of Hundreds</title>
    <meta content="Y02CHI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/world/02CHIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Falun Gong (Spiritual Movement)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Li Hongzhi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DD123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beijing Protest By Falun Sect Brings Arrest Of Hundreds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of followers of banned Falun Gong spiritual movement are arrested in Beijing on October 1, China's National Day, after recent instructions from US-based leader Li Hongzhi to step forward and achieve consummation by facing imprisonment or death; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of followers of the banned Falun Gong spiritual movement were arrested at Tiananmen Square in Beijing today, China's National Day, after recent instructions from their United States-based leader to ''step forward'' and ''achieve consummation'' by facing imprisonment or death.</p>
        <p>In what has become a well-rehearsed ritual, plainclothes police officers sprinted from spot to spot in the crowded square, ripping down Falun Gong banners, pummeling followers and hustling the protesters into waiting police vans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of followers of the banned Falun Gong spiritual movement were arrested at Tiananmen Square in Beijing today, China's National Day, after recent instructions from their United States-based leader to ''step forward'' and ''achieve consummation'' by facing imprisonment or death.</p>
        <p>In what has become a well-rehearsed ritual, plainclothes police officers sprinted from spot to spot in the crowded square, ripping down Falun Gong banners, pummeling followers and hustling the protesters into waiting police vans.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people were arrested from among tens of thousands of holiday tourists, said witnesses and Western news reports. The police cleared and closed part of the square for nearly an hour at one point during the day to stop the protests.</p>
        <p>Falun Gong followers are arrested at the square almost daily after brief, largely unnoticed acts of protest -- usually attempts to unfurl a small banner or to sit in the lotus position to begin the discipline's yogalike exercises.</p>
        <p>The numbers of protesters has generally increased on national holidays or significant dates in the group's year-and-a-half-long struggle with the government.</p>
        <p>The protests today, on the 51st anniversary of the founding of the People's Republic of China, were the group's largest and best coordinated since Falun Gong was banned as an ''evil cult'' in July of last year. They came as the group's leader, Li Hongzhi, has been espousing an increasingly activist attitude.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy for those disciples who have stepped forward,'' Mr. Li said in comments that were recently posted on the group's official Web site, clearwisdom.net, and which the Web site says were transcribed from a talk he gave on Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>''Whether they are imprisoned or lose their human lives for persevering in dafa cultivation, they achieve consummation.''</p>
        <p>Dafa translates as great law and refers to the cosmology that Mr. Li lays out in his writings and to the discipline he prescribes for achieving enlightenment. Drawing from Buddhist and Taoist traditions, that cosmology describes multiple dimensions and alien beings, apocalyptic events and segregated paradises for the world's various races.</p>
        <p>It struck a chord with many people in China, where the Communists' once unifying ideology is now ignored and where a turn toward market economics has embittered those who feel disfranchised after decades of sacrifice.</p>
        <p>Falun Gong is also one manifestation of a growing desire for charismatic spiritual leadership in China during a period of rapid social change. While the Communist Party allows five state-sanctioned religions to operate, its requirement that religious leaders be approved by the state has kept those religions bland and passive.</p>
        <p>A steady stream of more dynamic spiritual leaders has appeared in recent years to fill the void, from self-styled spiritual masters like Mr. Li to mystical Buddhist monks, underground Christian preachers and a network of priests loyal to the pope rather than the Patriotic Catholic Church of China, which forbids fidelity to Rome.</p>
        <p>China's leaders, evidently fearful that true freedom of religion would increase pressure for political freedom and threaten the Communist Party's monopoly on power, have cracked down on any of the groups whose organization has grown too large. Falun Gong, which at its peak said it had tens of millions of followers, became a prime target of the crackdown after 10,000 adherents gathered outside the government's leadership compound in Beijing in April 1999.</p>
        <p>An ensuing propaganda campaign, together with widespread arrests and pressure from employers, stopped the movement's rapid growth and even shrank its numbers. But it also hardened a core of believers in China, won the movement international support and galvanized adherents abroad.</p>
        <p>The group has grown increasingly sophisticated in its challenge to China's government and its efforts to gather followers outside China. Its public face, for example, presented through Web sites, press releases and radio broadcasts, has been represented as a middle-class spiritual movement and human rights cause rather than a mystical movement from China.</p>
        <p>Web sites with ''falun dafa'' or ''falun gong'' in the Internet addresses now carry photographs of middle-class Westerners performing the movement's exercises instead of the spinning swastikas and portrait of Mr. Li that they carried earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Li's writings on alien invasions, levitation, mankind's destruction and the evils of racial intermarriage, meanwhile, have been moved to other Web sites that nonbelievers are less likely to stumble across. One of those sites carries Mr. Li's latest comments, in which he criticizes followers who are afraid to confront China's police.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
