<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supporter of 'Female Presence,' but No Boxing Fan</title>
    <meta content="02TEXT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale Daily News</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD8123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supporter of 'Female Presence,' but No Boxing Fan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from editorials Joseph I Lieberman wrote in The Yale Daily News (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Below are excerpts from editorials Joseph I. Lieberman wrote in The Yale Daily News.</p>
        <p>Boxing  April 1, 1963</p>
        <p>The most frequent defense of boxing is that it has given many individuals of humble background the chance of a decent life. It seems to us to be something of a condemnation of our society if the only way some men can come to a comfortable existence is through this ''barbaric'' sport. To defend boxing in this way is the equivalent of a statement such as ''Gangland killings may not be nice, but they certainly made it possible for many young Americans from poor families to enjoy the benefits this country has to afford.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Below are excerpts from editorials Joseph I. Lieberman wrote in The Yale Daily News.</p>
        <p>Boxing  April 1, 1963</p>
        <p>The most frequent defense of boxing is that it has given many individuals of humble background the chance of a decent life. It seems to us to be something of a condemnation of our society if the only way some men can come to a comfortable existence is through this ''barbaric'' sport. To defend boxing in this way is the equivalent of a statement such as ''Gangland killings may not be nice, but they certainly made it possible for many young Americans from poor families to enjoy the benefits this country has to afford.''</p>
        <p>It is the supreme irony that states such as New York outlaw ''cock-fighting'' but allow boxing.</p>
        <p>Professional boxing must be made illegal in every state in the nation.</p>
        <p>General Conduct  April 29, 1963</p>
        <p>The actions taken against two Yale students arrested in a raid on a house of prostitution last week raise a series of questions concerning the bounds of university authority over its undergraduates.</p>
        <p>Were the two gentlemen involved in the most recent incident punished because they were charged by public authorities with breaking a law? If this is so, would the university have taken similar action if the two students had been arrested for reckless driving? We believe this would be far more ''ungentlemanly conduct'' since it endangers the well-being of others, which is really not the case in frequenting a house of prostitution.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most annoying is the fact that there seems to be a strong correlation between the degree of publicity given an incident and the extent of punishment meted out to those involved in it. It is preposterous if the academic future of a student involved in a questionable situation depends on whether that incident is picked up by such papers as the Bridgeport Herald.</p>
        <p>Servus Servorum Dei  May 29, 1963</p>
        <p>Reports from Rome bring the saddening news that the health of Pope John XXIII continues to deteriorate. This should bring grief to all men.</p>
        <p>In his five years as pope, Angelo Giuseppe Roncalli has revivified the church and spoken an essential message to the world.</p>
        <p>It was altogether fitting that Pope John should address his recent encyclical, Pacem in Terris, to all men rather than simply to Roman Catholics. Throughout these five years, the spirit of the words he has spoken has held immense relevance to all peoples. The extension of his love and charity has not been confined within the walls of the church. More than any other great leader of men today he has continually conveyed the essential truths of the overriding unity of the human family and of the mysteries which rest well beyond many's capacities.</p>
        <p>Of all the titles of the Roman pontiff, he is said to prefer the simple servus servorum Dei -- servant of the servants of God. He feels common cause with ''anyone who does not call himself a Christian, but who really is so because he does good.''</p>
        <p>Awake, Arise!  Oct. 25, 1963</p>
        <p>Somewhere, Susan B. Anthony is smiling.</p>
        <p>For once more the women of America stand proudly together to fight the forces of discrimination and exclusion.</p>
        <p>Although Yale's admissions office continues to decline to comment substantively on the matter, the News has learned from unimpeachable sources that at least fifty girls -- and probably many more -- have applied this week for admission to Yale. We believe this is the most refreshing event to occur on the Yale campus in some time.</p>
        <p>We believe further that the presence of women undergraduates at Yale would bring about a healthier and more natural social climate. The wonders of the female presence are sorely lacking on the Yale campus.</p>
        <p>A Void  Nov. 27, 1963</p>
        <p>It is now more than 100 hours since the death of the president. The loss is personal and deep. There is a gnawing void.</p>
        <p>The president spoke with characteristic insight in his inaugural address when he said, ''The torch has passed to a new generation.'' This generation -- this man -- was best-suited to lead this nation today. President Kennedy was the man for our times. His tragic death has removed the torch from the generation and the man who should be carrying it. The period of his leadership now takes on the aura of an interlude when it could have been something more lasting. The spirit of elevation which resided in Washington the past three years is gone.</p>
        <p>It is inevitable that other men with a style of leadership similar to John Fitzgerald Kennedy's will come to the presidency in the future. But today his loss -- which was so unnecessary -- is difficult to bear.</p>
        <p>Church and School  Dec. 18, 1963</p>
        <p>The government's interest here should be in a better education for all students in this country regardless of whether they attend public, private or church-related schools. Those who oppose aid to private parochial schools are usually most concerned over the effect such support would have on the Catholic parochial schools which now educate more than six million young people in America. They fear that such aid would be, in some sense, an ''establishment of religion.'' But we see no good reason why the federal government should not help provide nonreligious facilities to church-related schools. Does this nation -- already plagued by masses of people ill-prepared -- not gain if laboratory facilities, libraries, and language labs are updated in church-related schools?</p>
        <p>Many argue that such aid to parochial schools -- although it is for nonreligious purposes -- nevertheless frees funds for religious purposes. But does not this theory of indirect aid carry itself to ridiculous conclusions? What of the municipality which puts up a traffic light at a busy intersection where a church-related school is located? Does not this traffic light aid the religious school or make it more appealing?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
