<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abera Resurrects a Proud Ethiopian Tradition</title>
    <meta content="02MARA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: MEN'S MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kenya</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abera, Gezahgne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wainaina, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tola, Tesfaye</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DE123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abera Resurrects a Proud Ethiopian Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gezahgne Abera of Ethiopia wins gold medal in men's marathon, Eric Wainaina of Kenya wins silver and Tesfaye Tola of Ethiopia wins bronze; Ethiopia's fourth gold medal in men's marathon is more than any other country; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With winds gusting to 40 miles an hour, Gezahgne Abera of Ethiopia tucked into a pack of 10 runners on the Olympic marathon course. At 10 1/2 miles, though, his feet became tangled and he fell down, scraping his knee and shoulder.</p>
        <p>This was his fifth international marathon, and two had ended in an adventure. Last December, Abera slowed at the Fukuoka Marathon in Japan, believing he had won the race, only to be told that he had a quarter of a mile left to run. Urgently, he sped up, caught a runner who had passed him and won anyway. Last April, he finished in a dead heat with Kenya's Elijah Lagat and took second in the closest Boston Marathon ever run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With winds gusting to 40 miles an hour, Gezahgne Abera of Ethiopia tucked into a pack of 10 runners on the Olympic marathon course. At 10 1/2 miles, though, his feet became tangled and he fell down, scraping his knee and shoulder.</p>
        <p>This was his fifth international marathon, and two had ended in an adventure. Last December, Abera slowed at the Fukuoka Marathon in Japan, believing he had won the race, only to be told that he had a quarter of a mile left to run. Urgently, he sped up, caught a runner who had passed him and won anyway. Last April, he finished in a dead heat with Kenya's Elijah Lagat and took second in the closest Boston Marathon ever run.</p>
        <p>Today, there would be no such suspense. When he fell, Abera climbed to his feet, sheltered behind his teammate Tesfaye Tola until the 25th mile and then burst into the lead to win the gold medal in 2 hours 10 minutes 11 seconds.</p>
        <p>Eric Wainaina, a Kenyan who trains in Japan and who won the bronze medal at the Atlanta Olympics, kept surging in an attempt to break the Ethiopians, but he finally had to settle for second in 2:10:31. Tola won the bronze in 2:11:10.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia has now won four men's marathons in the Olympics -- more than any other nation -- having established a tradition three decades ago by the victories of the great Abibe Bikila. Abera's visage is now certain to join Bikila's in a set of Olympic rings that adorn the national stadium in the capital, Addis Ababa.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't believe it,'' the 22-year-old Abera said. ''It's not only for me, but for the whole of Ethiopia, a new upsurge.''</p>
        <p>Running barefoot through the streets of Rome in 1960 as Italian soldiers held up torch lights, Bikila won the marathon and, as the first black African to win a gold medal, he started what became the East African running boom. He won again at the 1964 Tokyo Olympics, then did stretching exercises after he crossed the finish line as if to show that he could have maintained the pace long beyond the marathon distance of 26.2 miles. Five years later, Bikila was paralyzed in an automobile accident, and he died in 1973.</p>
        <p>At the 1968 Summer Games in Mexico City, Mamo Wolde won Ethiopia's third successive gold medal in the marathon. He won a bronze four years later in Munich, but Wolde has been imprisoned since 1993 in the shooting death of an antigovernment protester during the former brutal Communist regime in Ethiopia. Wolde has proclaimed his innocence, contending that he is essentially a political prisoner.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia has maintained its elite standing in the world of international distance running despite a national track and field federation that has been corrupt, incompetent and chronically short of money. At the Sydney Games, Ethiopians won 8 of the 18 available medals in distance running, including gold in the men's marathon, the men's and women's 10,000 meters and the men's 5,000 meters.</p>
        <p>As did the more renowned Haile Gebrselassie and Derartu Tulu, both two-time winners of the men's and women's 10,000-meter races, respectively, Abera grew up in the Arssi region of Ethiopia's southern highlands. He lived on a farm and ran great distances as a boy, and was discovered at the national cross-country championships in Addis Ababa.</p>
        <p>Abera ran patiently in today's marathon as Tiyapo Maso of Botswana made an early break and ran alone in front for the first 15 miles. But this was a suicidal tactic on such a blustery day. Abera, at 5-foot-6, 126 pounds, realized he was too slight to fight the wind, so he tucked into the pack that reeled Maso in.</p>
        <p>''It was terrible,'' Abera said of the wind. ''We wanted to start walking. It was blowing from the front, blowing from the side. Terrible.''</p>
        <p>At about 18 1/2 miles, the pack winnowed to four runners and then to Abera, Wainaina and Tola, two Ethiopians and a Kenyan. The medals were won. Only the order was left to be determined.</p>
        <p>Kenya had never won a gold medal in the Olympic marathon. Wainaina competed in Sydney only because three more renowned runners were kicked off the national team in a political battle, though the official explanation was a lack of fitness.</p>
        <p>Knowing the Ethiopians would be working together, Wainaina surged several times. Finally, just before the 25th mile, Tola could not hold the pace.</p>
        <p>''I am tired; you chase Wainaina,'' he told Abera.</p>
        <p>Abera took the lead fluidly and this time there was no confusion at the finish. He entered Olympic Stadium to the cheers of 100,000 people, his lead insurmountable, and Kenya would have to wait yet another four years to try to get its first gold medal, while Ethiopia claimed its fourth in the marathon.</p>
        <p>''I can't believe it,'' Abera said. ''It is almost 30 years since our last success.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: MEN'S MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
