<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turkish Parliament Convenes, But Generals Remain in Power</title>
    <meta content="Y02TUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/world/02TURK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frantz, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DD123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turkish Parliament Convenes, But Generals Remain in Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS FRANTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frantz, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>ANKARA, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turkish Parliament convenes; influence of military is evident on two of most significant items on legislative agenda, namely, dismissing civil servants suspected of Islamic sympathies and easing restrictions on freedom of speech; military, which regards itself as guardians of 77-year-old secular state, warns it will monitor Parliament's action on legislation necessary to carry out purge of Islamic fundamentalists (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For four centuries, the imperial council of the Ottoman Empire met in the divan at Topkapi Palace in Istanbul to debate the affairs of the far-flung realm. Shielded behind a grilled window above the exquisitely tiled chamber, the sultan observed the proceedings and dictated his instructions by summoning the grand vizier.</p>
        <p>The modern Turkish Parliament meets in a contemporary stone-and-wood office building in Ankara and, as befits the capital of the Turkish republic, no sultan oversees its deliberations. The ruler's role is occupied by the generals, who wield their power from behind the scenes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For four centuries, the imperial council of the Ottoman Empire met in the divan at Topkapi Palace in Istanbul to debate the affairs of the far-flung realm. Shielded behind a grilled window above the exquisitely tiled chamber, the sultan observed the proceedings and dictated his instructions by summoning the grand vizier.</p>
        <p>The modern Turkish Parliament meets in a contemporary stone-and-wood office building in Ankara and, as befits the capital of the Turkish republic, no sultan oversees its deliberations. The ruler's role is occupied by the generals, who wield their power from behind the scenes.</p>
        <p>When Parliament convened today amid pomp and speeches, the influence of the military was evident on two of the most significant items on the legislative agenda, one authorizing the dismissal of civil servants suspected of Islamic sympathies and the other easing restrictions on freedom of speech.</p>
        <p>Turkey's generals regard themselves as guardians of the 77-year-old secular state and a bastion against Islamic fundamentalism. Although the military engineered three coups in the last four decades, its leaders prefer to exercise their authority quietly.</p>
        <p>But the cloak fell away in late August when the senior commander, Gen. Huseyin Kivrikoglu, demanded at a public ceremony that thousands of Islamic government employees be dismissed. The general warned that the military would ''monitor'' Parliament's action on legislation necessary to carry out the purge.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats were not as surprised by the general's sentiments as they were by his decision to announce them in public. In recent interviews, diplomats cautioned that Turkey's application for membership in the European Union will founder unless the military's influence is checked.</p>
        <p>While the power of the armed forces in public affairs may disturb Westerners accustomed to a politically neutral military, it is no surprise to Turks. The country's military has a high degree of authority over civil matters and autonomy over military affairs under the Constitution, which was written in 1982 by the generals who had seized power two years earlier.</p>
        <p>In practical terms, the generals have interpreted their mandate as authority to set parameters of acceptable behavior for the government and remain in the barracks as long as the civilian leaders observe the boundaries.</p>
        <p>''The state is a bus, the people are the passengers and the politicians are the driver,'' said Dogu Ergil, a political science professor at Ankara University. ''When the reckless driver starts weaving, the army acts as the road barrier. Instead of rolling over the cliff, the bus hits the barrier.''</p>
        <p>From the military's vantage point, the inroads by Islamic-oriented civil servants constitute a dangerous weaving. When President Ahmet Necdet Sezer twice refused to sign a decree authorizing the mass dismissal of government employees this summer, General Kivrikoglu stepped in with the thinly veiled demand that Parliament pass a law allowing the purge.</p>
        <p>Human rights advocates argue that a witch hunt could result from the dismissal of thousands of employees without a hearing. Similar legislation has failed to pass the fractious Parliament in the past and the outcome this time will provide an intriguing test of the military's power.</p>
        <p>On a quieter level, Turkish politicians said the generals have also warned the governing coalition not to go too far in softening laws that make it a crime to make speeches and write articles that can be interpreted as inflaming ethnic or religious differences, advocating an Islamic leadership or insulting the military. Here again the interests of the military and other hard-liners will collide with legislators who favor more democracy and are concerned about winning membership in the European Union.</p>
        <p>The legislators will face other tough issues, particularly on the economic side. Under prodding from the International Monetary Fund, Turkey has been fighting to reduce inflation and sell more state-owned businesses to the private sector. Parliament must approve a stringent new budget and the sale of three state-owned banks.</p>
        <p>In addition, hundreds of laws and regulations must be changed to meet European Union standards. For the same reason, an effort is expected to abolish the death penalty, a proposal that has already generated dissension within the three-party governing coalition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
