<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Monday Morning Quarterback</title>
    <meta content="02MOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/sports/02MOND-QB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D7123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Monday Morning Quarterback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from weekend college football games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from the weekend.</p>
        <p>CHANGE AT THE TOP  Though it is rare for a No. 1 team to fall after winning, The Associated Press voters replaced Nebraska with Florida State at the top of the poll yesterday, apparently after judging the Seminoles' 59-7 victory over Maryland more impressive than the Cornhuskers' 42-24 defeat of Missouri.</p>
        <p>The Seminoles collected 42 first-place votes and 1,745 points from the 71 sportswriters and broadcasters on the A.P. panel, while the Cornhuskers had 28 first-place votes and 1,731 points after a third consecutive less-than-overwhelming victory. Nebraska gave up a season-high 492 yards to Missouri (1-3). (The Cornhuskers, however, remained No. 1 among the coaches in the USA Today/ESPN Top 25.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Highlights and lowlights from the weekend.</p>
        <p>CHANGE AT THE TOP  Though it is rare for a No. 1 team to fall after winning, The Associated Press voters replaced Nebraska with Florida State at the top of the poll yesterday, apparently after judging the Seminoles' 59-7 victory over Maryland more impressive than the Cornhuskers' 42-24 defeat of Missouri.</p>
        <p>The Seminoles collected 42 first-place votes and 1,745 points from the 71 sportswriters and broadcasters on the A.P. panel, while the Cornhuskers had 28 first-place votes and 1,731 points after a third consecutive less-than-overwhelming victory. Nebraska gave up a season-high 492 yards to Missouri (1-3). (The Cornhuskers, however, remained No. 1 among the coaches in the USA Today/ESPN Top 25.)</p>
        <p>Florida State Coach Bobby Bowden tried to play down the promotion and worried how it might affect his team heading into a showdown on the road with No. 7 Miami next Saturday.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't mean a thing at this time,'' he said. ''Especially when we're going to a place like Miami this week. It just gives them more fuel for the fire. Playing down at their place is always tough, and this will give them extra incentive. But our goal is to end up No. 1.''</p>
        <p>OOPS, WRONG GUY  Kansas quarterback Dylen Smith threw five interceptions, three of them to Oklahoma's J. T. Thatcher. Smith also fumbled once, and four of his turnovers led to scores as the Sooners won, 34-16.</p>
        <p>THEY AREN'T HERALDED, JUST PRODUCTIVE</p>
        <p>Ennis Haywood ran for 241 yards and 2 touchdowns as Iowa State beat Baylor, 31-17.</p>
        <p>Steve Campbell caught 19 passes for 218 yards and 2 touchdowns as Brown beat Rhode Island, 29-19.</p>
        <p>Damien Anderson ran for 219 yards and 2 touchdowns as Northwestern beat No. 18 Michigan State, 37-17.</p>
        <p>Jabu Powell rushed 40 times for 215 yards and 4 touchdowns in Bucknell's 35-14 victory over Duquesne.</p>
        <p>Tellis Redmon gained 299 yards from scrimmage and scored 2 touchdowns as Minnesota upset No. 24 Illinois, 44-10. He rushed for 183 yards and caught 3 passes for 116 yards.</p>
        <p>Ken Simonton ran for a career-high 234 yards and 3 touchdowns as Oregon State beat No. 8 Southern Cal, 31-21.</p>
        <p>Franklin and Marshall's Justin Salton caught 16 passes for 216 yards, breaking a school record for receptions in a game, in a 16-14 loss to Carnegie Mellon.</p>
        <p>SUPER FOOT  Billy Cundiff kicked three field goals, including a 62-yarder, as Drake beat San Diego, 52-12.</p>
        <p>IT'S MY FAULT  ''I can't tackle for them. But the communication on how to tackle is not getting taught. We'll look at every position from a standpoint that something is missing. I'm accountable for that.'' Florida's defensive coordinator, Jon Hoke, after Mississippi State amassed 517 yards against the Gators.</p>
        <p>IT'S THEIR FAULT  ''The first half was an embarrassment. One team came to fight, one team didn't. One team came to play with passion, one team didn't.'' Illinois Coach Ron Turner after a 44-10 loss to Minnesota.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
