<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equity Offerings Scheduled for Week</title>
    <meta content="02EQUI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/business/02EQUI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFD6153DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equity Offerings Scheduled for Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>Advanced Switching Communications, Vienna, Va., an initial public offering of 6.25 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>Advanced Switching Communications, Vienna, Va., an initial public offering of 6.25 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Albany Molecular Research, Albany, 4.1 million shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>Asia Global Crossing, Hamilton, Bermuda, an initial public offering of 53 million Class A shares. Goldman, Sachs and Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Coach Inc., New York, an initial public offering of 7.38 million shares. Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>Computer Network Technology, Minneapolis, 3.7 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Corinthian Colleges, Santa Ana, Calif., three million shares. Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Delcath Systems, Stamford, Conn., an initial public offering of two million shares. Whale Securities Co.</p>
        <p>InforMax, Rockville, Md., an initial public offering of five million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Introgen Therapeutics, Austin, Tex., an initial public offering of five million shares. SG Cowen.</p>
        <p>Kosan Biosciences, Hayward, Calif., an initial public offering of five million shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Natural MicroSystems, Framingham, Mich., two  million shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>New Skies Satellites, the Netherlands, an initial public offering of 28.5 million American depository shares, each share representing one ordinary share. Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>NVIDIA Corp., Sunnyvale, Calif., 1.4 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Oplink Communications, San Jose, Calif., an initial public offering of 13.7 million shares. Robertson Stephens.</p>
        <p>Radiance Medical Systems, Irvine, Calif., 2.8 million shares. Prudential Securities and Gruntal &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Shaw Group, Baton Rouge, La., four million shares. Merrill Lynch and Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Tality, San Jose, Calif., an initial public offering of 12.75 million Class A shares. Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>Thomson Multimedia, Boulogne, France, 41.66 million American depository shares, each share representing one ordinary share. SG Cowen.</p>
        <p>TNPC, Greenwich, Conn., an initial public offering of 21 million shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette and Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Ulticom, Mount. Laurel, N.J., 4.25 million shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
