<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Columnist Who Thinks He's a Cop</title>
    <meta content="02SALA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/arts/02SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Platt, Oliver</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Deadline (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DE123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Columnist Who Thinks He's a Cop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews premiere of new NBC series Deadline, with Oliver Platt; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonight's episode of ''Deadline,'' the new NBC series from Dick Wolf, creator of ''Law and Order,'' has a riveting opening. Clean-cut employees at a brightly lighted fast-food restaurant in Chicago agree to serve two ominous customers who appear just at closing time. The sense of impending doom is tautly fulfilled as gunfire and a witness's scream announce the killings.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wolf's usual heroes, the detectives and lawyers, leave the investigating this time to a chubby journalist named Wallace Benton, a foppish Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist for a New York tabloid. He sees a link between a crime he covered in New York and the Chicago killings, and he follows his instincts to Chicago, where he shows up wearing riot gear as police officers prepare to storm a building containing suspects. Then he's in the interrogation room with a couple of detectives and a man they have arrested. When Benton asks the officers to leave him alone with the suspect, they do, with ludicrous obedience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tonight's episode of ''Deadline,'' the new NBC series from Dick Wolf, creator of ''Law and Order,'' has a riveting opening. Clean-cut employees at a brightly lighted fast-food restaurant in Chicago agree to serve two ominous customers who appear just at closing time. The sense of impending doom is tautly fulfilled as gunfire and a witness's scream announce the killings.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wolf's usual heroes, the detectives and lawyers, leave the investigating this time to a chubby journalist named Wallace Benton, a foppish Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist for a New York tabloid. He sees a link between a crime he covered in New York and the Chicago killings, and he follows his instincts to Chicago, where he shows up wearing riot gear as police officers prepare to storm a building containing suspects. Then he's in the interrogation room with a couple of detectives and a man they have arrested. When Benton asks the officers to leave him alone with the suspect, they do, with ludicrous obedience.</p>
        <p>The busy columnist-sleuth gets help from his own little Scribe Squad, his students in a journalism seminar, who happen to be trim, attractive and racially diverse. They should get extra credit for having to endure their teacher's smug speeches about his personal code of journalistic ethics. Audiences will quickly drop out, though, if Mr. Wolf doesn't find a way to make reporting as compelling as he has made crime fighting. They really aren't the same thing, though you'd be hard pressed to tell from watching the first episodes of ''Deadline.''</p>
        <p>It doesn't help that Oliver Platt, the movie character actor who plays Benton and who usually is so appealing, treats his role as if it was really a spoof. Elsewhere he has proved that he has range, but his Benton always seems to be smirking, and never more than when he's trying to be earnest. Mr. Platt tries to look stricken when he reads over the fiery articles his character wrote that might have resulted in wrongful murder convictions for two men, who wait for imminent execution. Instead he looks flummoxed, and who can blame him? The solemn chords of sacramental music issue forth to signal a moral dilemma in the making, as though to explain the strange expression on the actor's face.</p>
        <p>The beauty of ''Law and Order,'' and the key to its longevity, has been its focus on cases. The justice system is the main character; the actors illuminate its different aspects, which has allowed the show to absorb so many cast changes (with the latest test being this season's substitution of Dianne Wiest for Steven Hill's district attorney).</p>
        <p>Neither of the first two episodes of ''Deadline'' provides much understanding of journalism, tabloid or otherwise, except for one enjoyable scene in an editorial meeting, at which the paper's publisher deftly composes lurid headlines on the spot. A story about metal pollution at a grammar school becomes ''Toxic Tots.''</p>
        <p>Tom Conti -- who in 1995 starred in another Wolf series, the short-lived ''Wright Verdicts'' -- brings a nice sense of cynical amusement to the publisher's role. At the editorial meeting, as a sports editor tells about a brawl at a strip club involving ballplayers, the publisher lifts his head from the newspaper he's been reading and offers: ''Hapless Hurlers in Topless Bar.'' Then he chuckles and dismisses his own idea. ''I think we've done that,'' he says. With that, the show is also done with wry humor, showing a preference for the arch vulgarisms that pass for wit in and out of the paper's newsroom.</p>
        <p>Working journalists may envy the absence of grunge at The New York Ledger, the show's newspaper, which is pointedly modeled after The New York Post, with the Scottish Mr. Conti standing in for the Post's Rupert Murdoch, an Australian. It's not surprising that The Ledger's publisher has a plush office. More unusual, perhaps, is his on-site masseuse -- a blond and sexy woman, of course -- who kneads his flesh while he consults with his star columnist.</p>
        <p>Even in the newsroom the decor and the female reporters are remarkably sleek, especially the managing editor, Nikki Masucci, played by Bebe Neuwirth, who in the second episode makes The Ledger's own gossip pages when a photographer captures her slithering into the back seat of a car with a political candidate the paper is covering.</p>
        <p>An absence of realism wouldn't be a problem if ''Deadline'' showed more emerging signs of a functioning internal life. This talented cast, which also includes the charming Lili Taylor as a gossip columnist, has potential. But right now, the drama is relying on stories that seem improbable, even if they happen to be based on fact. That could change, but in the first two episodes the characters are left to carry the show, and they aren't nearly strong enough yet for such heavy lifting.</p>
        <p>DEADLINE  NBC, tonight at 9  (Channel 4 in New York)</p>
        <p>Created by Dick Wolf; Dick Wolf and Robert Palm, executive producers; Don Scardino, Peter Jankowski and Arthur Forney, co-executive producers; produced by John L. Roman; Matt Pyken, Michael Berns and Chris Mundy, executive story editors; music composed by Mike Post. A production of Wolf Films in association with Studios USA Television.</p>
        <p>WITH: Oliver Platt (Wallace Benton), Bebe Neuwirth (Nikki Masucci), Lili Taylor (Hildy Baker), Tom Conti (Si Beekman), Hope Davis (Brooke Benton), Christina Chang (Beth Khambu) and Damon Gupton (Charles Foster).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
