<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investment Banks Rebound in 3rd Quarter</title>
    <meta content="02UNDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/business/02UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atlas, Riva D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DE123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investment Banks Rebound in 3rd Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RIVA D. ATLAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Atlas, Riva D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investment banks raise $459 billion in United States in third quarter in 3,321 stock and bond offerings; figures are strong, but down 10 percent from $512 billion and 4,194 offerings in 1999 period; Goldman, Sachs remains leading equity underwriter, raising $12.7 billion, or 28 percent of all stock deals; table of leading underwriters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock prices may be volatile, but somehow investor jitters have not had much impact on the underwriting business. After some rockiness in the spring, the market for debt and equity offerings rebounded in the third quarter, meaning brisk business for the investment bank that bring those offerings to market.</p>
        <p>Investment banks raised $459 billion in the United States the last three months, in 3,321 deals. That is down 10 percent from $512 billion and 4,194 offerings in the similar period a year ago, but the latest totals are still strong enough to make it the ninth-busiest quarter on record, based on money raised, according to Thomson Financial Securities Data in Newark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock prices may be volatile, but somehow investor jitters have not had much impact on the underwriting business. After some rockiness in the spring, the market for debt and equity offerings rebounded in the third quarter, meaning brisk business for the investment bank that bring those offerings to market.</p>
        <p>Investment banks raised $459 billion in the United States the last three months, in 3,321 deals. That is down 10 percent from $512 billion and 4,194 offerings in the similar period a year ago, but the latest totals are still strong enough to make it the ninth-busiest quarter on record, based on money raised, according to Thomson Financial Securities Data in Newark.</p>
        <p>The underwriting totals speak to strength in many segments of the business, particularly in the market for initial public offerings of stock, where $18 billion was raised in the United States, up 45 percent from last year. I.P.O.'s are the most lucrative business for investment banks, with underwriters typically taking a fee of nearly 6 percent of the money raised.</p>
        <p>''Generally speaking, the quarter was still very strong and deal backlogs are at record levels,'' says Richard Strauss, an analyst who follows the brokerage industry for Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>Goldman held onto its perch as the leading underwriter of equities over all, raising $12.7 billion, or 28 percent of all stock deals. That is more than twice as busy as Goldman was for the comparable period last year, although it got a big lift from its own $4.6 billion secondary offering on behalf of partners and other long-time shareholders, which was the largest equity financing done this quarter.</p>
        <p>The two mergers announced between investment banks in the last quarter would have altered the underwriting rankings a bit, if they had closed before the quarter's end. If Chase Manhattan and J. P. Morgan had already merged, the combined firm would have ranked 3rd in the overall debt-and-equity league tables, instead of their 7th and 10th place finishes, respectively.</p>
        <p>But for equity underwriting alone -- a far more lucrative business than bond financing -- Chase's standing barely budged. The combined firm would jump just two slots from Chase's actual standing, to eighth place, capturing only 2.8 percent of the stock deal volume.</p>
        <p>Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette outstripped its rivals as lead underwriter in the lucrative high-yield bond market, even before taking into account its planned merger with Credit Suisse First Boston. But that business is in the midst of a cyclical slump, with just $13 billion raised this quarter, down 25 percent from last year.</p>
        <p>Internet start-ups no longer dominated the I.P.O. market, but technology offerings still accounted for nearly three-quarters of the money raised, according to Thomson.</p>
        <p>''This is no longer an environment where every deal will fly,'' said Mark Tercek, global co-leader of equity capital markets at Goldman. ''Investors are more focused on the fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>Still, for the right deal, investors were enthusiastic: companies going public saw their shares jump 42 percent, on average, the first day. Some stocks leapt far higher: CoSine Communications, a telecommunications equipment company, raised $265 million in a deal underwritten by Goldman last week. CoSine's shares soared 136 percent on their first day of trading.</p>
        <p>The market for debt offerings was much more of a mixed bag. Investment-grade financings were in demand, with $106 billion raised this quarter, up 11 percent from last year. But other areas of the debt business, particularly high-yield bonds, remained soft.</p>
        <p>''The debt markets this year were definitely a study in contrasts,'' said William White, head of global debt syndication at Morgan Stanley.</p>
        <p>The corporate bond market benefited from investors seeking higher yields than could be found in the Treasury market, as there was less fear of further increases in interest rates from the Federal Reserve.</p>
        <p>The market for high-yield debt remained weak as investors worried about the increasing level of defaults, which accounted for 3.87 percent of the market for the 12 months ended Aug. 31, up from 1 percent two years ago, according to Donaldson. These so-called junk-bond underwritings are the most lucrative part of the bond market, with investment banks typically taking a 2 percent fee on underwriting such deals, versus 0.32 percent on investment-grade offerings, according to Mr. Strauss of Goldman.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, the worst of the credit issues are behind the market,'' said Tripp Smith, head of global high-yield capital markets at Donaldson. ''We have a lot of business going into the fourth quarter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
