<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parity, Equality or Mediocrity? It's Your Call</title>
    <meta content="02COLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/sports/02COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED9123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parity, Equality or Mediocrity? It's Your Call</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Drape</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses results of weekend's college football games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dictionary definition of parity and the one invoked in today's sport culture are rarely the same. In my edition of Webster's, the word means the state or condition of being the same in power, value, rank, etc.; equality. When commissioners of professional leagues, or their surrogates -- that is, television executives -- use the word, it's usually in response to dwindling fan interest, low ratings or the unexpected decline of a powerhouse or two.</p>
        <p>Neither definition is accurate, however, to explain what occurred over the weekend in college football. Nine teams ranked in the top 25 of the Associated Press poll were defeated; seven of them by unranked teams. It was as if a child played 52 pick-up with the ranking and left the deck scattered on the floor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The dictionary definition of parity and the one invoked in today's sport culture are rarely the same. In my edition of Webster's, the word means the state or condition of being the same in power, value, rank, etc.; equality. When commissioners of professional leagues, or their surrogates -- that is, television executives -- use the word, it's usually in response to dwindling fan interest, low ratings or the unexpected decline of a powerhouse or two.</p>
        <p>Neither definition is accurate, however, to explain what occurred over the weekend in college football. Nine teams ranked in the top 25 of the Associated Press poll were defeated; seven of them by unranked teams. It was as if a child played 52 pick-up with the ranking and left the deck scattered on the floor.</p>
        <p>Check this week's ranking to see how voters went about that task of assessing the ''state or condition of being the same in power, value, rank, etc.'' But judging by the reaction of those who scattered the cards, there's really no consensus. Two coaches of unranked teams declared their team's victories among the biggest in their careers.</p>
        <p>Coach Dennis Erickson of Oregon State, who won two national championships at Miami, choked with pride for his squad after the Beavers beat Southern California, 31-21, to end a 26-game losing streak to the Trojans, improve to 4-0 and enter the ranking for the first time since Jan. 4, 1969, at No. 23. Mississippi State Coach Jackie Sherrill, who has won big games at Pittsburgh and Texas A&amp;M, echoed those sentiments after his Bulldogs defeated No. 3 Florida, 47-35, and returned to the ranking at No. 20, after a week's absence.</p>
        <p>''It's as high as I've ever been,'' Erickson said. ''This was right up with any of them.''</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, Northwestern's Randy Walker, who has a right to be ecstatic, chose a tempered, if not blase, posture to laud his Wildcats after they followed an overtime upset of Wisconsin with a 37-17 rout of No. 18 Michigan State on Saturday. Sure, Walker left Miami of Ohio as the school's most successful coach before arriving in Evanston, Ill., last year, but really, coach, how about giving it up to your players?</p>
        <p>''We are a better football team this week than we were last week,'' he said of his team, which entered the top 25 at No. 22. ''I think over all we played pretty solid. It was a nice job by the offense, and I knew that it would be because of the optimism we had coming in. We came out of the blocks and got the job done.''</p>
        <p>Leave it to Coach Steve Spurrier of Florida, however, to speak, actually to hiss, on behalf of the once mighty.</p>
        <p>''Mississippi State ought to be embarrassed tearing down the goal posts after beating this team,'' Spurrier said of the Starkville fans' postgame celebration.</p>
        <p>Like much of what the irascible and antagonistic Spurrier says, there's a bit of truth in his putdown. He has stated repeatedly that his Gators are not that good. So far this year he has benched players for improper displays of invincibility, barred them from meeting members of the news media because he was tired of hearing their barely backed up trash-talk, and rotated quarterbacks in an attempt to get some traction on what he knew was a dangerously slippery season.</p>
        <p>His is not the only program struggling. How about unranked Penn State (2-4) upending Purdue, No. 22 last week? Or unranked Alabama, once as high as No. 3, defeating South Carolina to improve to 2-3 and make the return to the top 25 of Lou Holtz and the Gamecocks a brief one?</p>
        <p>Now, none of this means a state of equality has descended on college football. While Florida State supplanted Nebraska as the nation's No. 1 team this week, nobody can dispute that the two teams own five of the last 10 national titles. But the weekend's games do reflect that the gap has narrowed between, say, a No. 40 and a No. 10.</p>
        <p>Like new issues on the Nasdaq, college football teams can become ''movers'' in the polls. Unlike the professional leagues, with their advanced scouting of a limited pool of players, a solid college coach and an enthusiastic recruiting staff can unearth overlooked talent. Last year, Marshall, behind quarterback Chad Pennington, finished No. 10 in the final poll with a 12-0 record. This year it looks as if Texas Christian (4-0, No. 14 A.P.) may follow the powerful legs of LaDainian Tomlinson, a Heisman Trophy candidate, up the ranking.</p>
        <p>The tougher climb is from No. 10 to No. 1. Last year Virginia Tech played Florida State for the national championship and almost completed that feat. The Hokies are now No. 3. For the past three years, Kansas State has yo-yoed within that index. Now the Wildcats loom at No. 4. Still, college fans embrace upstarts.</p>
        <p>They root for teams because they represent their state or their alma mater or because their father or mother or brother or sister went there. They either spend Saturday afternoons with 50,000 to 100,000 like-minded folks in stadiums, or click to the games on television with a remote.</p>
        <p>Even the most ardent fans understand that it is hard to get disgusted, or even upset, with 18- to 22-year-olds whose mistakes on a football field can unplug a powerhouse. So Webster's definition of parity isn't true; and sports executives' use of the word isn't necessary. The fun is that next Saturday the deck of cards will be thrown to the ground once more, and for the rest of the week we'll discuss how to reorder them.</p>
        <p>ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
