<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Shot at Subway Station After Clash Over Camera</title>
    <meta content="02SUBW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/nyregion/02SUBW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gangs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cholos (Mexican-American Street Gang)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tellez, Ulises</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D7123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Shot at Subway Station After Clash Over Camera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ulises Tellez, member of Mexican-American street gang Cholos, angry because he thought a fellow subway rider had videotaped him, ignites desperate struggle inside N train early in morning that continues onto subway platform at East 59th Street in Manhattan, where three people are shot; victims are listed in stable condition; Tellez and four other gang members are arrested (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A member of a street gang, angry because he thought a fellow subway rider had videotaped him, ignited a desperate struggle inside an N train early yesterday that continued onto a platform at East 59th Street in Manhattan, where three people were shot, the police said.</p>
        <p>The gunshot victims, who the police said were revelers traveling from a party in Queens to their home in the Bronx, were in stable condition yesterday in Manhattan hospitals and were expected to recover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A member of a street gang, angry because he thought a fellow subway rider had videotaped him, ignited a desperate struggle inside an N train early yesterday that continued onto a platform at East 59th Street in Manhattan, where three people were shot, the police said.</p>
        <p>The gunshot victims, who the police said were revelers traveling from a party in Queens to their home in the Bronx, were in stable condition yesterday in Manhattan hospitals and were expected to recover.</p>
        <p>The police arrested six men immediately after the shootings -- three members of the Cholos, a Mexican-American street gang, and three others -- and held them  at the 17th Precinct station house pending arraignments today.</p>
        <p>The police said the confrontation began at 2:30 a.m. when Ulises Tellez, a Cholos member, confronted a group of about 12 friends and family members on the Manhattan-bound train just after it left the Queensboro Plaza station in Queens. Mr. Tellez, 25, was furious because he believed he had been videotaped by Roberto Tehuezeel, 25, who was carrying a video camera on a strap around his neck and filming the inside of the subway car, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tellez approached Mr. Tehuezeel, punched him in the face and tried to yank the camera from his neck, said Inspector John W. Cutter, commander of Manhattan North detectives. As many as five of Mr. Tehuezeel's friends stepped in to try to stop the fight, and the scuffle escalated as the car sped toward Manhattan, the police said.</p>
        <p>At the station at East 59th Street and Lexington Avenue, the fight continued onto the platform, where, the police said, another of the Cholos, Daniel Carinc, 17, pulled a .22-caliber semiautomatic pistol from his belt and shot three people in rapid succession.</p>
        <p>First, Mr. Carinc shot Mr. Tehuezeel in the chest, the police said. Next, he held the gun near the head of Tony Mani, one of Mr. Tehuezeel's friends, and pulled the trigger. Inspector Cutter said Mr. Mani flinched and the bullet grazed one side of his head.</p>
        <p>''He's extremely lucky,'' Inspector Cutter said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carinc then shot a woman, Irene Cuenca, 22, in the left thigh, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police said Ms. Cuenca, 22, was related to Mr. Mani, 32, but  were not sure how. All of the victims live together in the Bronx, the police said.</p>
        <p>The scene on the platform turned to bedlam after the shooting as the victims crawled for safety and the gang members ran.</p>
        <p>The police said three of the men involved in the shootings were arrested on Lexington Avenue after two transit officers in pursuit saw one of them throw a pistol near a parked car. The rest were caught in the station after the police sealed it. In the aftermath, a blood-stained sock and shoe were found at the foot of an escalator, and blood could be seen along a 30-foot section of the N line platform.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cuenca was being treated at Bellevue Hospital Center. Mr. Mani and Mr. Tehuezeel were at New York Weill Cornell Medical Center.</p>
        <p>The police and prosecutors were reviewing charges against the six men yesterday. Officer Joseph Cavitolo, a police spokesman, said the authorities expected to charge Mr. Carinc, of 146th Street in the Bronx, with multiple counts of attempted murder, assault and gang assault, as well as robbery and criminal possession of a weapon.</p>
        <p>The other five men in custody were Ulises Tellez; Christian Tellez, 23; Ruben Garciaza-Flores, 17; Luis Romero, 18; and Antonio Vasques, 22. They were expected to be charged with assault, gang assault and robbery, Officer Cavitolo said.</p>
        <p>Inspector Cutter said Mr. Carinc and the Tellezes are members of the Cholos, a small, loosely knit gang that has seen a number of its members arrested in the city recently.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
