<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How an Illinois County Cleared the Welfare Rolls</title>
    <meta content="14WELF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Workfare and Employment of Welfare Recipients</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Schuyler County (Ill)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DE103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How an Illinois County Cleared the Welfare Rolls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>RUSHVILLE, Ill., Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Schuyler County, Ill, is first county in state and one of first in nation to be 'welfare-free,' illustrating in microcosm some of profound changes that have transformed much of nation's welfare system since Pres Clinton signed landmark welfare-reform law in 1996; county's elimination of cash assistance resulted not just from strong economy, but from hard work by local welfare officials, who gave much personal attention to each case and became adept at matching welfare recipients with jo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Holly E. Cain, manager of the local welfare office, used to post job openings for welfare recipients just inside the front door of her agency here. She nearly put herself out of business. Welfare disappeared from this county. For more than a year, there have been no new cases, no old cases, no one on the rolls receiving cash assistance.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cain still clips and posts help-wanted advertisements from local merchants, schools and hospitals. But the notices are no longer intended for welfare recipients. All sorts of people stop by to check what jobs might be available.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Holly E. Cain, manager of the local welfare office, used to post job openings for welfare recipients just inside the front door of her agency here. She nearly put herself out of business. Welfare disappeared from this county. For more than a year, there have been no new cases, no old cases, no one on the rolls receiving cash assistance.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cain still clips and posts help-wanted advertisements from local merchants, schools and hospitals. But the notices are no longer intended for welfare recipients. All sorts of people stop by to check what jobs might be available.</p>
        <p>''That's new,'' said Mrs. Cain, who has run the four-person Schuyler County office of the Illinois Department of Human Services for 20 years. ''It's a very positive change.''</p>
        <p>Schuyler, on the prairie west of Springfield, Ill., was the first county in the state and one of the first in the nation to be ''welfare-free.'' As other counties have approached that status, they have found that the last cases are among the most difficult.</p>
        <p>This county, with a population of about 7,500, illustrates in microcosm some of the profound changes that have transformed much of the nation's welfare system since President Clinton signed a landmark welfare law on Aug. 22, 1996.</p>
        <p>The elimination of cash assistance here resulted not just from a strong economy, but also from hard work by local welfare officials, who gave lots of personal attention to each case -- and who have many lessons to teach the rest of the country. With practice, they became adept at matching welfare recipients with jobs.</p>
        <p>Virtually all the former welfare recipients in Schuyler County have kept their jobs or moved on to higher-paying jobs, Mrs. Cain said.</p>
        <p>But poverty has not disappeared here, and life is not easy for the former welfare recipients, some of whom take home less than $1,000 a month from their jobs. But they say they have more self-confidence and self-esteem because they are earning paychecks and not getting cash assistance any more.</p>
        <p>''It was scary,'' said Karen J. DeMoss, 46, describing her transition to work after 12 years on welfare. ''But I have more confidence now. And I wish I had gotten off public aid a long time ago.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DeMoss once held factory jobs, but in her years on welfare she got into a rut. Tears welled up as she recalled how she had to explain to her two teenage sons that the family was poor. That was three years ago. Now, she said, the boys are proud of her because she caters banquets and wedding receptions. ''They think it's nice their mom can cook for 300 people,'' Ms. DeMoss said.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Deanna D. Zeisler, 34, who now works in a restaurant and does cleaning, said: ''I didn't feel good when I was on public aid. I feel good about myself now. I'm working. It feels good to have a paycheck in my name. It may be a tiny paycheck, but I earned it. It wasn't just handed to me.''</p>
        <p>Life is still austere for Ms. Zeisler. ''I can't afford to go to the movies,'' she said. She volunteers at the local theater, taking tickets and selling popcorn, in return for the privilege of seeing a film with her three sons.</p>
        <p>The goals of the 1996 law and the intent of Congress are understood by Mrs. Cain and her colleagues at the welfare office here. Drawing on their experience and their contacts in the community, they devised a strategy to carry out the law by matching workers with jobs.</p>
        <p>''We didn't wave a magic wand,'' Mrs. Cain said of her effort to whittle down the welfare rolls. Her supervisor at the regional office in Springfield, Gregory Matarelli, said ''it's not happenstance'' that Schuyler County was the first to eliminate welfare, though that was never an explicit goal.</p>
        <p>The welfare office here went about its work methodically and systematically. Whenever a welfare recipient got a job, Mrs. Cain or her caseworkers would call the person every two or three weeks for five months, to make sure the person kept the job.</p>
        <p>''We pretty well know most of our clients, or their family members,'' Mrs. Cain said. (In 1995, the last year for which Census Bureau estimates are available, Schuyler County had a median household income of $27,370, about 80 percent of the comparable figure for the nation as a whole.)</p>
        <p>Of the 102 counties in Illinois, four others -- Cumberland, Hardin, Putnam and Washington -- had no welfare cases in July. A total of 53 had fewer than 20 cases each.</p>
        <p>State officials pay close attention to those counties. They receive a monthly report describing the circumstances of each family on welfare in any county with fewer than 50 cases. Supervisors like Mr. Matarelli want to know if the families are working, and if not, why not. They discuss each case with local officials, suggesting techniques that have proved effective in other counties.</p>
        <p>As the number of cases dwindled, Mrs. Cain formed a ''5 o'clock club'' for those who remained on welfare -- the cash assistance program officially known as Temporary Assistance for Needy Families. They met on Monday evenings to share their job-hunting experiences.</p>
        <p>''They gave support to one another,'' Mrs. Cain said. ''They listened to one another much more readily than they'd listen to me standing up there saying the same thing.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DeMoss said caseworkers prodded her to start looking for work. ''They made it sound like a positive thing, not like it was doomsday and we'd be out on the street with nothing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The number of families on welfare in Illinois has fallen below 100,000 this year for the first time in three decades. State officials say 86,600 families are receiving cash assistance, down from a peak of 247,800 in 1994. More than two-thirds of the cases are in Cook County, which includes Chicago, but even in that county the number of families receiving cash assistance has declined by 50 percent in the last three years.</p>
        <p>Illinois differed from many other states in one crucial respect. It encouraged people to hold on to Medicaid and food stamps after they took jobs and lost cash assistance.</p>
        <p>The number of people in Schuyler County receiving Medicaid or food stamps rose to 418 in July of this year from 368 in July 1997, even as the number of people on cash assistance dropped to zero.</p>
        <p>In many states, people were inadvertently dropped from Medicaid when they lost cash assistance. But in Illinois, state and local officials saw Medicaid as an indispensable form of assistance that could help tens of thousands of welfare recipients take low-wage jobs offering no health insurance benefits. Indeed, Mr. Matarelli and Mrs. Cain said they had audited the records of closed welfare cases to make sure families were receiving the medical and food assistance to which they were entitled.</p>
        <p>Linda Renee Baker, secretary of the Illinois Department of Human Services, said, ''We are aggressive about letting families know they may still be eligible for food stamps and Medicaid.'' In addition, she said, the state increased spending on child care by 30 percent this year, to $648 million.</p>
        <p>The staff at the Schuyler County welfare office has not been reduced, despite the absence of welfare recipients since April 1999. Mrs. Cain said the four employees still had plenty of work to do, arranging Medicaid, food stamps, child care, transportation and other services for needy county residents, including former welfare recipients. Mr. Matarelli said those services helped welfare recipients ''get some traction in the economic mainstream.''</p>
        <p>Cumberland County, in east central Illinois, had 143 welfare cases in September 1994 and has not had any in 8 of the last 12 months. Asked why the numbers were so low, Paul D. Marti Jr., manager of the local welfare office, said, ''It's a combination of good case work, a good economy and good follow-up.''</p>
        <p>If trends continue, Mr. Marti said, many more counties may become welfare-free. ''That would mean that everyone has gotten work or has been assisted in some way to get beyond welfare,'' he said. But, he added, ''State officials discourage talk of that goal,'' for fear that caseworkers might improperly limit access to welfare if they focused too much on caseload statistics rather than on serving clients.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cain and Mr. Marti said the last cases were the most difficult because these welfare recipients often had mental or physical disabilities, alcohol or drug abuse problems, little work experience, few job skills and limited education.</p>
        <p>''But,'' Mr. Marti said, ''because the numbers are so low, you have a lot more time to work with clients, and you can focus on them quite a bit. They're the toughest cases, but they're also the most gratifying when you're able to help them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
