<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORTH WATCHING</title>
    <meta content="Y14PRO$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DE103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORTH WATCHING</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the speakers on this evening's program:</p>
        <p>Dianne Feinstein  Barbara Boxer  Senators</p>
        <p>When it came to elections, 1992 was the year of the woman, and  California residents  made history by electing  Dianne Feinstein and Barbara Boxer. Ms. Feinstein, a native of California and the former mayor of San Francisco who was swept into office in a landslide, has quietly pushed anticrime legislation and issues close to home in her eight years in Washington. One of her biggest victories was attaching an assault weapons ban to the crime bill signed by President Clinton in 1994.  Ms. Boxer is a strong abortion rights advocate who has fought the ban on the late-term procedure that opponents call partial-birth abortion.  Ms. Boxer is linked to the Clintons by the marriage of Hillary Rodham Clinton's brother, Tony Rodham, to her daughter, Nicole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the speakers on this evening's program:</p>
        <p>Dianne Feinstein  Barbara Boxer  Senators</p>
        <p>When it came to elections, 1992 was the year of the woman, and  California residents  made history by electing  Dianne Feinstein and Barbara Boxer. Ms. Feinstein, a native of California and the former mayor of San Francisco who was swept into office in a landslide, has quietly pushed anticrime legislation and issues close to home in her eight years in Washington. One of her biggest victories was attaching an assault weapons ban to the crime bill signed by President Clinton in 1994.  Ms. Boxer is a strong abortion rights advocate who has fought the ban on the late-term procedure that opponents call partial-birth abortion.  Ms. Boxer is linked to the Clintons by the marriage of Hillary Rodham Clinton's brother, Tony Rodham, to her daughter, Nicole.</p>
        <p>Barbara A. Mikulski  Senator</p>
        <p>After organizing neighbors to protest the construction of a 16-lane highway through the historic Fells Point area of Baltimore,  Barbara A. Mikulski plunged into politics in the late 1960's. Then a social worker, Ms. Mikulski went on to serve as a  councilwoman in Baltimore before serving in the United States House from 1976 to 1986 and being elected to the Senate in 1986. She has helped write two mystery novels with a political twist that sketch the life of a freshman senator from Pennsylvania who Ms. Mikulski has called a ''somewhat younger, somewhat slimmer, but no less politically savvy'' version of herself.</p>
        <p>Mary L. Landrieu  Senator</p>
        <p>Senator Mary L. Landrieu of  Louisiana came to politics naturally as the oldest of nine children of Moon Landrieu, the mayor of New Orleans in the 1970's. In 1979, after graduating from Louisiana State University, she became, at 23, the youngest woman ever elected to the State Legislature. She was elected to the Senate in 1996.</p>
        <p>Blanche Lambert Lincoln  Senator</p>
        <p>Blanche Lambert Lincoln, 39, grew up on a rice farm in Helena, Ark., and was elected to the Senate two years ago. After serving in the House  from 1992 to 1996, she left politics to give birth to twin boys. When she ran for the Senate in 1998, she put their photographs on her campaign posters.</p>
        <p>Debbie Stabenow  Representative</p>
        <p>A Michigan Democrat who was elected to the House in 1996, Debbie Stabenow is involved in what is shaping up to be one of the nation's most bitterly contested Senate races. She is challenging Senator Spencer Abraham by highlighting her own legislative record that goes back to 1975, when she was a county commissioner fighting a proposal that would have shut down a local hospital that accepted Medicaid.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
