<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Hope Beefed-Up Convention Will Distinguish Them From G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="Y14STA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE AGENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DC103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Hope Beefed-Up Convention Will Distinguish Them From G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles is intended to be in look and feel brainier and meatier antidote to Republicans' feel-good Philadelphia spectacle; Democrats say Republicans were so consumed with banishing divisive demons of gatherings past that they missed opportunity to give American voters comprehensive sense of what they stand for in 2000, or of who their standard-bearer truly is; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the sea of see-through iMac computers on the convention floor to a center-stage program of prominent officials engaged in issue ''dialogues'' with ordinary people, the Democratic National Convention that opens on Monday is intended to be, in look and feel, a brainier and meatier antidote to the Republicans' feel-good Philadelphia spectacle.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, meeting in the Staples Center here through Thursday, say the Republicans had been so consumed with banishing the divisive demons of gatherings past that they missed the opportunity to give American voters a comprehensive sense of what they stood for in 2000 -- or of who their standard-bearer truly was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the sea of see-through iMac computers on the convention floor to a center-stage program of prominent officials engaged in issue ''dialogues'' with ordinary people, the Democratic National Convention that opens on Monday is intended to be, in look and feel, a brainier and meatier antidote to the Republicans' feel-good Philadelphia spectacle.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, meeting in the Staples Center here through Thursday, say the Republicans had been so consumed with banishing the divisive demons of gatherings past that they missed the opportunity to give American voters a comprehensive sense of what they stood for in 2000 -- or of who their standard-bearer truly was.</p>
        <p>''They spent a lot more time battling their 1996 convention than they did battling the Democrats,'' said Joe Andrew, chairman of the Democratic National Committee. ''Ultimately what people saw was the surface image. We are going to focus on issues, because we know the issue landscape is home turf for us.''</p>
        <p>As a result, viewers will not just get a refresher course on the accomplishments of the Clinton-Gore administration; the opening day is being devoted to discussions of the economy and the needs of working families. But they will also hear enough talk of weighty policy matters to fill a social studies textbook. Health care is to be a constant thread, introduced in several panel discussions and reinforced in addresses by the major speakers. The other big issues include education, retirement security and fighting crime.</p>
        <p>Even the sleek computers, made by Apple and supplied to each delegation on the floor, are intended subtly to reinforce the idea of the Democrats as the party of the future, and Vice President Al Gore as the candidate of innovation. (Computers were scarce on the floor of the First Union Center in Philadelphia.)</p>
        <p>''That's a message in and of itself: 'Think Different,' '' Mr. Andrew said, invoking the theme of the Apple computer advertising campaign. ''We think outside the box.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats promise a convention less overtly rehearsed than that of their rivals. The party is not well known for sticking to the script anyway, as was demonstrated over the weekend by the tussle over the plans by Representative Loretta Sanchez of California to stage a benefit at the Playboy Mansion, and Representative Jesse Jackson Jr.'s tepid expression of support for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Yet in other ways symbolic and substantive, the Democrats are taking pains to turn the Staples Center into a palace devoted to the art of rebuttal.</p>
        <p>The layout of the hall is an answer to the Republicans' goal of a four-day variety show: while the Philadelphia rostrum was modeled on an Oscar telecast, complete with wide steps leading to the stage, the Democrats have installed a more traditional-looking podium, with a 12-foot retractable wall between the speakers and the delegates.</p>
        <p>The approach to selling the message also is different. In Philadelphia, the Republicans came up with a slogan, ''Renewing America's Purpose. Together,'' that was used as the gathering's overarching theme. The Democrats chose not to adopt a slogan, using instead the blandly generic ''America 2000'' as a kind of campaign trademark. The party talks so much about how it wants to differentiate itself from Philadelphia that the motto could have been ''Not the Republican National Convention.''</p>
        <p>''The Republican convention made no mistakes, but it wasn't successful because it didn't leave people with anything,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York. ''I think what we're trying to do is focus on some issues, not abstract issues, that make people's lives better. I think that is going to be our theme, and that theirs was sort of all fluff.''</p>
        <p>To make this the convention of antifluff, the Democrats are putting bright party lights like Mr. Schumer, and celebrities like the actor Jimmy Smits, in major supporting roles. They will be moderators of talk-show-style panels early each day in the proceedings, which are called to order at 5 p.m. Eastern time, to accommodate prime time on the East Coast. The panels, called ''American Dialogues,'' will feature everyday Americans talking about the issues that affect their lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer's panel, on Wednesday, will examine crime and victims' rights. Among his ''guests'' will be the parents of Matthew Shepard, the young gay man who was murdered in Wyoming in October 1998. ''The challenge of our convention is going to be to stick to the message,'' the senator said. ''If it doesn't seem meaty in comparison, we've sure flunked.''</p>
        <p>The attempt at message discipline may not reach the levels of those at the Republican convention, where copies of media talking points nine pages long were placed each day on the seat of every delegate. In Los Angeles, the emphasis will be on a reiteration of Mr. Gore's positions on issues that have tested well. Across the board, for instance, candidates, officials and Gore surrogates will talk about the vice president's advocacy of adding a prescription drug plan to Medicare.</p>
        <p>The Democrats may find obstacles to delivering their message on television from a surprising source -- their own speakers. Addresses on the initial nights by President Clinton, Hillary Rodham Clinton and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut could be major media events unto themselves, and thus could be the kinds of distractions for Mr. Gore that Gov. George W. Bush of Texas largely did not have to deal with in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Marc Burstein, executive producer of special events for ABC News, said those speakers had the potential to be riveting. ''The fact that you're going to have the president and the first lady speaking, in light of his comments the other day, it's certainly going to be compelling television,'' Mr. Burstein said, referring to Mr. Clinton's talk in Illinois on Thursday about his adulterous affair. Gail Evans, executive vice president of CNN, added that Mr. Lieberman's nomination as the first Jew on a major national ticket is great talk show fodder.</p>
        <p>''It's wonderful for discussion because everyone's got an opinion about it,'' Ms. Evans said.</p>
        <p>Still, Democratic officials contend they have developed a strategy that ensures they will get their message out even if the national news media and the political talking heads are not cooperative. They say they have committed vast resources to the creation of their own Democratic News Service. It will deliver news feeds via satellite to more than 500 local television stations around the country, as well as provide sound bites for radio and content for Web sites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrew says this dimension of the convention may be the most important. ''Our money is being spent more on that than on the show,'' he said. And as for those iMacs, Mr. Andrew said they, too, are part of that mission.</p>
        <p>''The reason we have computers on the floor is not so the podium can communicate with the delegates,'' he said. ''It's for us to be able to track the officials in each delegation so we can send the message back home, 'Here's what's happening in your Indiana delegation.' ''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE AGENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
