<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bluesman at the Crossroads (on Seventh Ave.)</title>
    <meta content="14BLUE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tips and Tipping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, John W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Linen, Eugene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tips and Tipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFDD103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bluesman at the Crossroads (on Seventh Ave.)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, John W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses musician Eugene Linen playing for tips on Seventh Ave between 49th and 50th Streets in midtown Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blues flow with his fingers. The index, middle and third do all the work. Pressing skin to steel strings and wood, they make the city night wail with the music of the bluesman and his Manhattan blues band.</p>
        <p>His name is Eugene Linen. He is both man and band, with a curious ensemble of guitar, harmonica, and recorded backup band rolled into one, and powered by a car battery. Mr. Linen plays at a cozy spot most summer nights, just off Broadway. He plays the washboard to boot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blues flow with his fingers. The index, middle and third do all the work. Pressing skin to steel strings and wood, they make the city night wail with the music of the bluesman and his Manhattan blues band.</p>
        <p>His name is Eugene Linen. He is both man and band, with a curious ensemble of guitar, harmonica, and recorded backup band rolled into one, and powered by a car battery. Mr. Linen plays at a cozy spot most summer nights, just off Broadway. He plays the washboard to boot.</p>
        <p>Born in South Carolina, Mr. Linen, a chubby-cheeked 63-year-old with neatly trimmed salt-and-pepper beard, is not anyone blues enthusiasts would know. He is no less a bluesman. Sometimes a bricklayer by day, a ''one-man blues band'' by night. His stage is a slice of curb on the east side of Seventh Avenue, between 49th and 50th Streets, and halfway between the subway music circuit and the Manhattan club scene.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of musicians like Mr. Linen play on the streets on New York, out in the shadow of city lights. There is something that gets Mr. Linen's juices jangling, something that has led him each summer over the last four years to make the nightly drive from Harlem to star in his own Midtown sideshow. Is it the $20 bill here, the $10 there, or just the jingle of spare change that patrons dump into Mr. Linen's tin can?</p>
        <p>Or something else?</p>
        <p>When he connects and the licks fall like rain, when his fingers and the frets are in harmony, and the blues and the man are one, he sways.</p>
        <p>On a mild Thursday night, the bluesman sits in the glare, on a self-constructed, uncomplicated stage.</p>
        <p>It is late. The crowd on the street is a little thin.</p>
        <p>''Hardly anybody is out tonight,'' says Mr. Linen. ''But you can never tell, you know?''</p>
        <p>The bluesman cradles his guitar, Sally. His left hand caresses her neck.</p>
        <p>The melancholy melody rises in the wind at the edge of a Times Square night, a bluesy soundtrack to a life's story.</p>
        <p>But there are gaps in this life's song. Missing verses and dissonant chords, between the past and present, places and faces that a man omits when telling his life to a stranger.</p>
        <p>But within his seasons of picking potatoes on Southern plantations and his days of gambling before becoming a gospel preacher lies the story of who he is, and the reason he plays the blues.</p>
        <p>The conversation turns to the past.</p>
        <p>It was hours before the red sun rose on the white man's plantation on Wadmalaw Island, S.C. Half asleep, the little boy ambled toward the field, holding his mother's hand. He was the fourth of eight children. With his family, he plucked potatoes until long after sundown.</p>
        <p>He was in the fourth grade when full-time work in the fields beckoned, and had not yet learned to read. At 13, work made him a man. Back then, pubescent boys without a whisker suddenly matriculated to manhood. At week's end, he handed his earnings to his mother, Annie Linen, a God-fearing Methodist.</p>
        <p>By age 14, Mr. Linen had joined the migrant worker circuit with his older siblings, who worked and sent their money back home, his youngest brother, Leroy Linen, remembered.</p>
        <p>''Ever since I was a kid, they were traveling to and fro, trying to provide for the family,'' Leroy Linen said. ''Jobs were not as plentiful, so there was a great need.'' Especially after their father, Ernest Linen, died in 1959.</p>
        <p>Two years later, Mr. Linen moved to New York to work in construction, the beginning of the trip that led to the music.</p>
        <p>It's 10:20 p.m. The music is loud enough to draw attention, low enough to keep the police from calling it a disturbance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linen plays a range of blues, from the Mississippi Delta-born slow and mournful twang to spicy soul-stirrers reminiscent of gospel music, along with finger-snapping melodies. He might play John Lee Hooker. Or B.B. King. Sometimes even a little rock 'n' roll. But even when Mr. Linen is playing to a track of ''Johnny B. Goode,'' his rendition is slower, less fluid, less like rock, more like blues.</p>
        <p>His playing is not always clean. Sometimes his fingers seem sticky, sluggish. Sometimes the notes buzz, until Mr. Linen warms up like a car engine on a winter morning. Then Sally cries, and sometimes she talks. At other times, she sings.</p>
        <p>Over the years, their music has fallen on the ears of neighbors: the Federal Express deliveryman who stops by occasionally. The officers who know him as a regular and nod as they walk by. The roving street vendors with their cases of sunglasses and fake $10 Rolexes, who pause as they pass, if only to steal a peek into his tin can.</p>
        <p>''For years I've been hearing him,'' says Peter Petrucci, 26, a manager at the Sweet Factory candy store across the street. ''The tourists enjoy it. He's pretty good. Sometimes it's good for business. It makes people happy and they want to buy candy.''</p>
        <p>Mostly, Mr. Linen's listeners drift in from the crowds that flow up and down Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linen started playing the guitar at 18. How he learned to play is one story. How he learned to read is another.</p>
        <p>He was about 19, and at a Salvation Army center, staring at a Bible. A woman assumed he was reading and gave him the Bible to keep. That night, Mr. Linen placed it under his pillow. A few hours later, he says, the Lord roused him from bed and told him to read.</p>
        <p>But through the years, whenever Mr. Linen had trouble with words, his friends showed him the light. He committed each word to memory. He did the same with the lessons he found on the pages of the guitar and harmonica books.</p>
        <p>He says he first played the streets of New York about four years ago with a friend. Mr. Linen eventually took up the solo act, creating a more reliable blues companion in his ensemble. It is a simple act. ''I don't like to create no crowd,'' Mr. Linen says. ''I don't come around and take requests. Whenever I play, I just play.''</p>
        <p>Sitting now in a coffee shop on a gentrified corner of Harlem, he laughs and his eyes become slits as he recalls the way his relatives jump and scream, ''big Gene, big Gene,'' whenever they see him coming. But the laughter and words disappear inside his paper cup when his thoughts shift to his divorce, to the life he has since made with a woman he calls his fiancee, and to his days as a fire-and-brimstone preacher. It is not clear why he rarely ever plays gospel anymore, or why he has not been home to South Carolina in a few years. Half his siblings are dead now, and so is his mother, who died in 1983.</p>
        <p>''When she passed, it took a lot out of me,'' he says.</p>
        <p>He looks forward to going to Wadmalaw again soon, to driving up the road that leads to the house of his youngest brother, Leroy, a magistrate for the last 20 years who has a street named in his honor -- ''Judge Linen Lane,'' the bluesman says with pride.</p>
        <p>Leroy Linen wishes his brother would come home for good. ''I always wanted him to be able to come home and enjoy some of the fruits of his labor,'' he says. ''I always ask him, 'When you coming home?' '' But he never answers. ''It appears he's in love with the bright lights of the big city.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Linen figures he has his own special street and good reasons for playing the blues. It is for him life's most natural song.</p>
        <p>''I play it because it's freedom of expression,'' he says. Blues music ''deals more with the person, it deals with how you feel, how life treated you, how life is now with you.''</p>
        <p>''And when you play, other people, they feel it too,'' he added. ''And they get some kind of connection. You get some kind of connection with the people. And you can see it. You can look at their face.''</p>
        <p>And at his.</p>
        <p>Out on Seventh Avenue, an older woman approaches. ''All right now, all right now,'' she says. The woman slows, then passes by, sashaying, caught up in the rhythm. She turns and walks back, drops a fistful of coins into Mr. Linen's can. ''All right now,'' she says again, smiling, feeling the connection.</p>
        <p>''O.K. brother,'' she says, smiling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linen peeks up from his straw hat, his face spreading in a smile. ''O.K.,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The blues flow with his fingers. And Mr. Linen starts to sway.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
