<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Bill's Third Acceptance</title>
    <meta content="14SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED8133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Bill's Third Acceptance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Saafire Op-Ed column on significance of Pres Clinton's appearance at Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My Fellow Democrats:</p>
        <p>After that rousing eight-minute demonstration, I accept your love. I accept your appreciation for triangulating you out of the Carter-Mondale-Dukakis wilderness and back into the White House for eight glorious years. And were it not for that damnable two-term amendment the Republicans put through to get even with F.D.R., tonight I would be saying, ''I accept your renomination!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My Fellow Democrats:</p>
        <p>After that rousing eight-minute demonstration, I accept your love. I accept your appreciation for triangulating you out of the Carter-Mondale-Dukakis wilderness and back into the White House for eight glorious years. And were it not for that damnable two-term amendment the Republicans put through to get even with F.D.R., tonight I would be saying, ''I accept your renomination!''</p>
        <p>That's how I'd like to start my valedictory speech. And then there are a few other things I wish I could say.</p>
        <p>On the contrition business, I'd like to tell Bush and Cheney where to get off with all their barbs about ''restoring honor and dignity'' and other code words condemning my private life. But that line of attack from me would play into their hands.</p>
        <p>So I'll choke back my feelings and pretend to be grateful to Joe Lieberman for calling me to moral account on the Senate floor. That'll get a big hand; we can't let the Pat Robertson crowd out-God us. And at least Joe voted right on acquittal.</p>
        <p>I showed the other day how I can smother my detractors with gratitude. My best line to my pastor in Illinois: ''If I hadn't been knocked down the way I was, and forced to come to grips with what I'd done and the consequences of it in such an awful way, I might not ever have had to really deal with it 100 percent.'' Thank you, Ken Starr and Henry Hyde, for forcing me to deal with it. Beautiful.</p>
        <p>And the convention will tear the place apart if I thank the two-thirds of the American people for sticking by me in my toughest time. My personal purging process is not a subject Al wants me to touch on at a convention that is supposed to be all about him, but I know what's best for me. And what's best for me is best for him because this election is about me.</p>
        <p>I won't let on about that, of course; I have to say every election is about the future. But I'll look back, bragging on the good times, claiming my tax increase in '93 was responsible for all the prosperity and surpluses today. I'll blame the Democrats' loss of the House on that unpopular party-line vote, even though everybody in the hall who lost will know the reason was our health-care fiasco.</p>
        <p>My theme will be the tried-and-true ''You Never Had It So Good,'' backed up with a pile of facts and figures -- 22 million jobs! Crime down! Stock market up! -- followed by the fearsome ''Don't Let Them Take It Away.'' Look, maybe we had nothing to do with prosperity, but if we were in a depression, who would be getting the blame?</p>
        <p>Looking into my own soul, I confess I'm torn. The good part of me wants Al Gore to win because it would validate my eight years and show the American people saying, ''We want to give Bill Clinton a third term.'' On the other hand, the bad boy in me wants him to lose, to show the Democrats how much they needed me personally to drag them in and keep them in.</p>
        <p>Even more conflicted are my feelings about Hillary's New York bid. I want her to win because I owe her for all that forgiving and because she's a backup for my validation in case Al can't make it without me. But my bad side says if she loses, she'll realize who the only winner is in this family. Plus which, she wouldn't be able to get on her high horse and have all that fun in the Washington I brought her to.</p>
        <p>No -- get thee behind me, Satan -- I want Hillary to beat that pushover unknown, really I do. For six years, ever since her health-bill fiasco, we've been assuring everybody she hasn't been affecting presidential policy, especially about the Palestinians. But the new line is that the opposite was true, that she was deeply involved in all sorts of big decisions. Look, whichever she wants -- strictly first lady or co-president -- I can teach it either way.</p>
        <p>So I'll stand up there for my Third Acceptance and wow 'em by taking full credit for everything good that's happened in eight great years. Let Al play Mr. Nice Guy if he likes; I'll be that old lovable rogue who can make a centrist waffle look like red meat. I'll make the Democrats miss my charm. I'll scare the viewers with the prospect of Bush, backward economics and back-alley abortions, and I'll stupefy my enemies with great globs of gratitude.</p>
        <p>Clinton fatigue? Not when I'm finished. Tonight is the first night of Clinton nostalgia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
