<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RUSSIANS WONDER IF PUTIN ACCEPTS LIMITS TO POWER</title>
    <meta content="14RUSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDE103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RUSSIANS WONDER IF PUTIN ACCEPTS LIMITS TO POWER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia's Pres Vladimir V Putin has capitalized on voter mandate, high opinion poll ratings and economy buoyed by high oil prices since winning presidency five months ago to enact major economic and political reforms, but has raised questions among citizens and Westerners alike over whether country's weak democratic institutions are strong enough to resist undemocratic, authoritarian streak critics ascribe to him; many question whether he can meld freedom and discipline into new state structure for Russia, almost ungovernable land of 11 time zones and diverse ethnic populations, that avoids slide toward Soviet past; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Earlier this summer, the newly elected Russian president, Vladimir V. Putin, flew to Tatarstan to take part in the planting festival known as Sabantui. There he donned a Tatar hat, stuck his face in a vat of yogurt to bob for coins and then engaged a Tatar girl in arm wrestling.</p>
        <p>What happened next simply astounded Prof. Aleksandr B. Asmolov, a leading psychologist at Moscow State University, who watched on television as Mr. Putin, a black belt in judo, did not hesitate or politely feign a struggle, but simply slammed her arm to the table in a single overpowering motion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Earlier this summer, the newly elected Russian president, Vladimir V. Putin, flew to Tatarstan to take part in the planting festival known as Sabantui. There he donned a Tatar hat, stuck his face in a vat of yogurt to bob for coins and then engaged a Tatar girl in arm wrestling.</p>
        <p>What happened next simply astounded Prof. Aleksandr B. Asmolov, a leading psychologist at Moscow State University, who watched on television as Mr. Putin, a black belt in judo, did not hesitate or politely feign a struggle, but simply slammed her arm to the table in a single overpowering motion.</p>
        <p>''I looked at that and said, 'This man has a ton of ambition, a mountain -- no, a cosmos -- of ambition,' '' observed Professor Asmolov.</p>
        <p>From his office across from the Kremlin, the professor has written letters to the new president counseling him to rule with more tolerance and noted: ''We have a fighter who has come to power and whose nature is not to play, but to win. He not only is motivated to succeed, he is maniacally motivated to succeed.''</p>
        <p>The only thing many Russians do not yet fully understand is: succeed at what?</p>
        <p>In almost five months since he was elected, Mr. Putin has capitalized on a voter mandate, high opinion poll ratings and an economy buoyed by strong oil prices to begin putting Russia back in order after a decade of wild economic and political swings under Boris N. Yeltsin, the country's first democratically elected president.</p>
        <p>In the course of a summer, Mr. Putin, who will be 48 in October, has laid out an economic program that has won praise from Western governments and pushed a new tax code through a cooperative Parliament.</p>
        <p>He has begun a major reorganization of the country's unruly regions, dividing the country into seven large new administrative areas and installing his own men over them. He has humbled its autocratic governors by siphoning off their power and their tax revenues to the federal authorities and begun the process of separating a class of super-rich oligarchs from their influence over the Russian government.</p>
        <p>Next, it seems, is the military. After firing six senior generals at the beginning of the month, Mr. Putin closeted himself for four hours on Friday evening with his national security council -- men who would usually be on vacation this time of year -- to decide what may be the most significant restructuring of the Russian military in two decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin may be proving himself more adept at using the enormous powers of his office to consolidate central control than his often ailing predecessor.</p>
        <p>But the question that seizes many Russians and Westerners alike is whether Russia's weak democratic institutions -- a nascent business class, free press and ever-changing assortment of political parties and organizations -- are strong enough to resist the undemocratic, authoritarian streak that critics ascribe to the former K.G.B. official who is now president.</p>
        <p>Can he meld freedom and discipline into a new state structure for Russia -- an almost ungovernable land of 11 time zones and diverse ethnic populations -- that avoids a slide toward the Soviet past?</p>
        <p>Aleksandr I. Gelman, a writer who now works with the former Soviet President, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, on building a social democratic party in Russia, said in an interview that Mr. Putin had made mistakes but was correctly seeking the proper balance between freedom and order, a traditional feature of politics in a country where power has long proven indivisible.</p>
        <p>''It is very important to link freedom with discipline in this country,'' Mr. Gelman said. ''Russia is made in such a way that it either had a very strict discipline or it was anarchy. The most difficult task was always to combine these two things, so that freedom does not interfere with discipline and discipline does not interfere with freedom.''</p>
        <p>But others see freedom already being compromised.</p>
        <p>''The new team of our new president is energetically crushing freedom and democracy,'' said Sergei A. Kovalyov, the human rights campaigner and longtime protege of the Nobel laureate Andrei D. Sakharov. ''Putin is building a country that is neither a democratic nor federal state. He is building, in fact, a unitary state based on force and trying hard to create the good old Soviet idea: unbroken vertical power from top to bottom.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kovalyov's critical assessment, which is shared by a number of Russian intellectuals, including many former dissidents who suffered at the hands of the K.G.B., carries great weight inside and outside Russia.</p>
        <p>But it has not dented Mr. Putin's high popularity ratings at home, where many other Russian intellectuals, younger reformers and liberal members of the old Soviet establishment support him.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday, Mr. Gorbachev, the last leader to rule over a unified Russia within an even larger Soviet Union and a rare visitor to the Kremlin during Mr. Yeltsin's rule, emerged from a two-hour meeting with Mr. Putin and pronounced that his youthful successor was on the right path.</p>
        <p>''I support Putin's efforts to strengthen order and responsibility,'' Mr. Gorbachev said, warning that ''regionalism is threatening to lead to the country's disintegration.''</p>
        <p>More discipline lies ahead, Mr. Putin's advisers say. He is preparing legislation to reform the country's chaotic system of customs laws and their corrupt administration and, in the fall, a major overhaul of Russia's legal system: courts, prosecutors and law enforcement agencies.</p>
        <p>Next month, around the anniversaries of the terrorist blasts that killed nearly 300 Russians in apartment blocks in Moscow and other cities last year, Mr. Putin is expected to dedicate a new memorial to the victims. Aides say he will ask Russians to stay the course in the ''anti-terrorist campaign'' in Chechnya that has killed thousands, displaced 270,000 people and left much of the rebellious region in ruins.</p>
        <p>Internationally, especially in Europe, Mr. Putin's rise was viewed with skepticism and alarm as Russian tanks flattened Grozny, the Chechen capital, last winter. But the new president took an unexpectedly activist role in fanning European opposition to American plans for a national missile defense system that would not cover Europe and could ignite a new arms race in Asia.</p>
        <p>To the leaders of the largest industrial nations, he presented the face of an earnest problem solver, visiting North Korea and pressing its leader, Kim Jong Il to abandon his long-range missile program.</p>
        <p>Vladimir P. Lukin, former Russian ambassador in Washington and now a deputy speaker of Parliament from the liberal party Yabloko, said that because Russia today has only a weak hand to play as a world power, Mr. Putin is seeking a constructive role to complement his reform efforts at home. That, Mr. Lukin said, will require a Western orientation, though not necessarily close relations with the Americans.</p>
        <p>Still, he added, ''Putin and his staff understand that whether Russia finds its place in the international division of labor depends mostly on our relations with Europe and the United States.''</p>
        <p>At home, freedom has taken a few jolts that rattled even Mr. Putin's most ardent supporters, most notably the storming of the headquarters of Media-Most, the conglomerate that owns the NTV television network, a frequent critic of Mr. Putin.</p>
        <p>After seizing documents, prosecutors ordered the arrest of Media-Most's chairman, Vladimir A. Gusinsky, held him for four days and charged him with financial crimes related to assembling his media empire.</p>
        <p>The charges were dropped, but only after Mr. Gusinsky was summoned for a private meeting at the Kremlin with Mr. Putin's chief of staff, Aleksandr S. Voloshin. The contents of that conversation have yet to be made public.</p>
        <p>Since the meeting, the government-controlled natural gas monopoly, Gazprom, has been putting pressure on Mr. Gusinsky to sell a controlling stake in his media empire by threatening to call in the loans that the gas giant extended him in the salad days of 1995-96, when oligarchs like Mr. Gusinsky were helping Mr. Yeltsin win re-election.</p>
        <p>Yevgeny A. Kiselev, the general director of NTV and anchor of its popular news program Itogi, told an interviewer last week that Mr. Gusinsky would surrender control of his media properties only ''at gunpoint.''</p>
        <p>''I worked for the government-owned media for years, like many of my colleagues,'' Mr. Kiselev said, ''and I don't believe any wishful talk that government-owned media in Russia can be independent.''</p>
        <p>It may take months before the fate of Mr. Gusinsky's empire is settled, but many Russians already view the case as a profound test of press freedom.</p>
        <p>''It's a very serious mistake,'' said Irina M. Khakamada, referring to the government assault on Mr. Gusinsky.</p>
        <p>A deputy speaker of Parliament and leader of the pro-market Union of Right Forces party, Ms. Khakamada supports Mr. Putin, especially for his commitment to economic reform. But her optimism is leavened with reservations about what she calls Mr. Putin's ''enlightened authoritarianism.''</p>
        <p>''I think his personal dream is to demonstrate that a liberal and enlightened market economy with the help of civil institutions can be successfully combined with more strict and rigid authority in the system of power,'' she said. ''The idea is not to strengthen his own personal power, but to strengthen Russia.''</p>
        <p>Many influential Russians remain more skeptical.</p>
        <p>As the sirens wailed last week around Pushkin Square, where a bomb shattered the evening calm with an explosion that so far has killed 11 people and left more than 50 with serious or critical injuries, a group of prominent intellectuals and businessmen was issuing an ''appeal to society'' for a new political movement to counter any drift toward authoritarianism.</p>
        <p>''Russian democracy is young and too dependent on the recent totalitarian past,'' the appeal said. The Putin government reflex, of seizing power from oligarchs and regional governors alike, is endangering the ''main achievements of the last decade,'' especially intellectual freedom, the group said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because it is August, vacation season, the appeal failed to generate any groundswell of response from ordinary Russians, who anyway have a strong instinct for gravitating toward the existing power.</p>
        <p>For all his talk of reform and strengthening the power of the center, Mr. Putin has yet to dismiss a single governor or mayor, though new legislation will soon arm him with clearer authority to do so.</p>
        <p>Vladislav Y. Surkov, a deputy chief of staff under Mr. Putin, said in an interview that a full-fledged anti-corruption campaign was impossible, since it would be interpreted as a political purge and evoke images of 1937 and Stalin's terror.</p>
        <p>Mr. Surkov said reforming the functions of government was the only way to fight corruption for now.</p>
        <p>''We inherited a thick layer of problems that accumulated during decades,'' Mr. Surkov said. ''If you think they can be solved without a certain consolidation of power, as we say, then you are mistaken.''</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Putin was aware that many people do not see him as committed to democracy. ''I want you to believe me that the president is a democrat,'' he said. ''It's true. But I don't understand how the elementary desire to establish order, and I mean elementary order, is considered undemocratic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
