<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Author Seduced by Hollywood's Glimmer</title>
    <meta content="14AGEN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agents (Business)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morris, William, Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Artists Management Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clancy, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottlieb, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ovitz, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/Artists Management Group</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Talent Agencies/William Morris Agency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Professions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2D9133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Author Seduced by Hollywood's Glimmer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Decision by author Tom Clancy to end his 15-year relationship with William Morris agent Robert Gottlieb and be represented by Michael Ovitz is seen as highly visible test case for Ovitz's new business plan for his Artists Management Group: representing writers and stars as an adviser while simultaneously negotiating deals with them to produce movies and television; defection is not only aggravating already strained relations between Gottlieb and William Morris's top executives, who prefer cordial relations with Ovitz, but is also an awkward chapter in deep friendship between Clancy and Gottlieb; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Aug. 3, Robert Gottlieb, one of the most powerful agents in the book business and the head of the William Morris agency's New York literary group, received a letter from Tom Clancy, his old friend and biggest client. His message: he was ending their 15 years of business together. From now on, his book deals would be handled by Michael Ovitz.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb was angry. Just a few years before, his relationship with Mr. Clancy had been so close that Mr. Clancy occasionally referred to ''the two G's'' -- Mr. Gottlieb and God -- said Diana Patin, Mr. Clancy's former secretary. When both men had been divorced, Mr. Clancy even established a pied-a-terre in Mr. Gottlieb's building on the Upper West Side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Aug. 3, Robert Gottlieb, one of the most powerful agents in the book business and the head of the William Morris agency's New York literary group, received a letter from Tom Clancy, his old friend and biggest client. His message: he was ending their 15 years of business together. From now on, his book deals would be handled by Michael Ovitz.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb was angry. Just a few years before, his relationship with Mr. Clancy had been so close that Mr. Clancy occasionally referred to ''the two G's'' -- Mr. Gottlieb and God -- said Diana Patin, Mr. Clancy's former secretary. When both men had been divorced, Mr. Clancy even established a pied-a-terre in Mr. Gottlieb's building on the Upper West Side.</p>
        <p>Before the day was out, Mr. Gottlieb was on the phone to a New York Times reporter, fuming that Mr. Ovitz had ''raided'' his client and declaring ''open season'' on Mr. Ovitz. Mr. Clancy, Mr. Gottlieb insisted, had been ''bamboozled.''</p>
        <p>The episode has turned Mr. Clancy's jump into a highly visible test case for Mr. Ovitz's new business plan: representing writers and stars as an adviser while simultaneously negotiating deals with them to produce movies and television. And it has aggravated already strained relations between Mr. Gottlieb and William Morris's top executives in Los Angeles, who prefer cordial relations with Mr. Ovitz. William Morris is currently negotiating with Mr. Gottlieb to renew his soon-to-expire contract, raising questions about his future at the agency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clancy's defection is also an awkward chapter in a deep friendship between two sharply drawn characters -- Mr. Gottlieb, the streetwise deal maker with a penchant for hardball, and Mr. Clancy, the mercurial author who seals deals with handshakes and still harbors fantasies about commanding a tank.</p>
        <p>Their relationship began in May 1984, when Mr. Gottlieb stumbled across galleys of Mr. Clancy's first book, ''The Hunt for Red October,'' at a booksellers' convention. Mr. Gottlieb cold-called him at his home in Maryland near Chesapeake Bay.</p>
        <p>''Why do I need an agent?'' Mr. Clancy replied at the time. ''Rob came after me like a gigolo after an heiress,'' he later recalled.</p>
        <p>His military ambitions thwarted by vision problems, Mr. Clancy was selling insurance while plotting thrillers at his dining room table at night. He sold his debut novel on his own to the Naval Institute Press for an advance of just $5,000, inadvertently signing away the rights to use the story or its hero, Jack Ryan, in films.</p>
        <p>In December 1984, Mr. Clancy finally agreed to meet Mr. Gottlieb in New York, over corned beef sandwiches at a Midtown deli, and soon signed on as client. Together they turned Mr. Clancy's name into one of the most lucrative franchises in the book business. In all, Mr. Gottlieb negotiated deals with Mr. Clancy's publisher, Penguin Putnam, for 47 books, roughly 10 still to be published. Mr. Clancy has 10 best-selling hardcover novels to his credit, with another on the way this fall. His career has spawned a cottage industry of other projects -- military nonfiction, mass market paperbacks written with a collaborator and even his own video game company. Three of his novels have become movies.</p>
        <p>According to executives at William Morris, Mr. Clancy earned more than $300 million from its deals, although Mr. Clancy insists that he made far less. A recent book contract fetched an advance of about $19 million for each hardcover title. William Morris received a 10 percent commission on each deal. Mr. Gottlieb came to represent many other best-selling clients, including Dean Koontz and Janet Evanovich. But Mr. Clancy remained the foundation of his career.</p>
        <p>''Rob is a good guy,'' Mr. Clancy, 53, said in an interview last week. ''He made me a lot of money, and I made him a lot of money. We were pals, for crying out loud.'' Mr. Gottlieb, who is 46, attended not only Mr. Clancy's wedding but the weddings of both of his daughters, and Mr. Clancy attended Mr. Gottlieb's second wedding, too.</p>
        <p>But as time went on, Mr. Clancy said, he grew impatient that only three of his highly cinematic thrillers had been turned into films, the last one in 1994. ''Eight are out there hanging and flapping in the wind, and I think they are damn good enough to be made into movies,'' he said. ''I just wasn't terribly impressed with how the movies and TV things had worked out.'' He also denied comparing Mr. Gottlieb to God.</p>
        <p>People at the William Morris agency, however, point out that Mr. Clancy's exacting standards did not help. He frequently sparred with producers at Paramount Pictures, which had acquired the film rights to his Jack Ryan character from his first publisher. ''I just thought it was a bit of an exaggeration to say the movies were based on the books by Tom Clancy -- they should have followed the books a little more closely,'' he acknowledged last week. He has also publicly deprecated the casting of Harrison Ford, who played Jack Ryan in two films.</p>
        <p>Although already a millionaire, Mr. Clancy also complained about his earnings from the films. ''The money matters, if you can make money from it,'' he said. The Naval Institute's deal for ''The Hunt for Red October'' earned Mr. Clancy a total of just over $251,000, he said. He was not content with the two deals Mr. Gottlieb negotiated either. After a multimillion-dollar signing fee, he said, he still has not seen any royalties from ''Patriot Games.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clancy met Mr. Ovitz about five years ago. He had resigned his position as the head of the Creative Artists Agency to become president of the the Walt Disney Company. He proposed a ''vertically integrated partnership'' with Disney in books, television and movies, Mr. Clancy recalled. The deal was never consummated. Mr. Ovitz's tenure at Disney lasted just 14 months.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clancy liked the way Mr. Ovitz was thinking, and they stayed in touch. ''Friendship is important,'' Mr. Clancy said. ''He explains Hollywood to me, and I explain the national security stuff to him.'' When Mr. Clancy remarried, Mr. Ovitz, too, attended the wedding, and chatted politely with Mr. Gottlieb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ovitz began informally offering Mr. Clancy advice and about three years ago signed on as his manager. Unlike agents, managers cannot negotiate deals for clients, only advise. They usually collect 10 percent of their clients' revenue as a commission. As a result, over the last few years, Mr. Clancy has been paying two commissions on some of deals, according to people at William Morris and associates of Mr. Ovitz.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ovitz began wooing Mr. Clancy more aggressively about 18 months ago, when he founded his new firm, the Artists Management Group. The new firm is a talent management business that also seeks to produce its own films and television programs on the side. The arrangement has raised eyebrows in Hollywood because it puts Mr. Ovitz's firm in a potential conflict of interest, advising clients as manager while negotiating with them as producer. Agents are legally prohibited from playing such dual roles with clients they represent. Mike Burns, a spokesman for Artists Management, said that on its own productions, the company does not take a commission and its clients are represented by lawyers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clancy, however, disputes that he ever paid two commissions, nor does he know the difference between Mr. Ovitz's role as his manager and Mr. Gottlieb's role as his agent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ovitz told Mr. Clancy that Artists Management could start generating at least one movie or television program based on his novels each year, partly by taking a role as a producer or co-producer. That sounded good to Mr. Clancy. ''Ovitz knows Hollywood pretty well, or he certainly seems to,'' he said. ''I decided to give him a chance to show me if he is as good as he says he is.'' Artists Management's television and movie units are now co-producing with Paramount at several projects based on Mr. Clancy's books. In the next film, Ben Affleck will replace Harrison Ford.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ovitz officially took over from William Morris negotiations for all of Mr. Clancy's Hollywood dealings about 18 months ago, and he soon grew involved in Mr. Clancy's dealings with his publisher, too, calling with suggestions about publicity.</p>
        <p>Finally, opting for the formality of a letter, Mr. Clancy cut Mr. Gottlieb out completely, explaining that from now on Mr. Ovitz would manage his book deals, too. ''It was time to move on,'' Mr. Clancy said.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Gottlieb, the news was not unexpected, but it came at a sensitive time within William Morris. The venerable agency last year named a new co-chief executive, James A. Wiatt, a Hollywood agent and former vice chairman of International Creative Management. His relations with Mr. Gottlieb quickly soured, according to others at the firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiatt rapidly consolidated his power, beginning with a shake-up of the agency's East Coast film group that led to the departure of 10 agents last year. Mr. Wiatt told friends he intended to turn his attention to the New York book group this summer. Then, over strenuous objections by Mr. Gottlieb and others in New York, he removed Dan Strone, a friend and ally of Mr. Gottlieb, from his position in charge of turning the New York literary group's books into Hollywood films.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clancy's departure sparked a new confrontation. William Morris executives in Los Angeles immediately called Mr. Ovitz, who was about to leave for a two-week vacation in Italy and tried to mollify the situation, saying that on his return he would try to keep William Morris involved. Meanwhile, Mr. Gottlieb went public with his bitter feelings -- accusing Mr. Ovitz of blurring the line between manager and agent and poaching his client. (A spokesman for Artists Management said many of its clients also have agents, noting their commissions do not interfere with its own.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb's diatribe only underscored the tensions within the firm: Don DeMesquita, an agency spokesman, took the extraordinary step of disavowing Mr. Gottlieb's comments, explaining that Mr. Gottlieb spoke only for himself and not for William Morris. The incident quickly became the talk of the industry, fueling speculation about Mr. Gottlieb's place at the firm.</p>
        <p>Through Mr. DeMesquita, Mr. Gottlieb declined to comment further. Asked about Mr. Gottlieb's future at the firm, Mr. Wiatt issued a one-sentence statement: ''William Morris is not cutting back its East Coast book operations, and Robert Gottlieb remains in place as head of our New York literary department.'' People at the firm say Mr. Gottlieb's contract renewal remains under negotiation. Although he is one of William Morris's biggest earners, the firm could retain the revenue from his previous deals if he left.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Clancy expressed a mixture of sympathy and chagrin toward his old friend. ''I'm not a partridge; nobody poached me. But sometimes people let their anger get in the way of their brains, and that's what happened to Rob in this case. I just hope Rob didn't shoot himself in the foot.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
