<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Feels Time Is Short for Restarting the Mideast Talks</title>
    <meta content="Y14DIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D6133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Feels Time Is Short for Restarting the Mideast Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House is prepared to convene new summit between Israelis and Palestinians, but has concluded that effective deadline for final settlement during Clinton presidency is end of September; senior official says Pres Clinton is prepared to reconvene summit, but only if he is assured that Israelis and Palestinians are ready to settle all outstanding issues, including Jerusalem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House has calculated that the effective deadline for a final Middle East peace settlement during the Clinton presidency is the end of September, a senior administration official said today.</p>
        <p>President Clinton is prepared to reconvene a summit meeting -- intense, but shorter than last month's Camp David talks -- but only if he is assured that the Israelis and Palestinians are ready to settle all outstanding issues, including Jerusalem, the senior official said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House has calculated that the effective deadline for a final Middle East peace settlement during the Clinton presidency is the end of September, a senior administration official said today.</p>
        <p>President Clinton is prepared to reconvene a summit meeting -- intense, but shorter than last month's Camp David talks -- but only if he is assured that the Israelis and Palestinians are ready to settle all outstanding issues, including Jerusalem, the senior official said.</p>
        <p>The narrow time frame was dictated, the official said, by the start of the Jewish religious holidays, which stretch from late September into much of October, and by the return from a long recess of the Israeli Parliament at the end of October.</p>
        <p>The pressure to move quickly has intensified, the official said, because the administration has concluded that the Israeli government of Prime Minister Ehud Barak will not be able to survive very long after Parliament reconvenes.</p>
        <p>Recently published opinion polls in Israel suggest that Mr. Barak's popularity has dropped precipitously. If he is still in dire straits when Parliament returns, the rightist opposition party Likud is likely to succeed in maneuvering for new elections.</p>
        <p>''There is not a huge window of time that is available,'' the administration official said.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, has threatened to declare a Palestinian state on Sept. 13, the deadline set by both sides for a final peace agreement, if there is no such accord by then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat did not get much support for such a unilateral move during a recent trip to Europe and Russia, the senior administration official said. Mr. Arafat is expected to continue to seek support for statehood when he visits leaders of Pakistan, China and India.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has sent messages to both sides, but not in the same intense mode as at Camp David, the official said. There has also been a ''wide array'' of contacts between senior Israeli and Palestinian officials, although no direct contact between Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Since the Camp David talks ended, ''the Egyptians have made it clear to us that they are prepared to be helpful'' in persuading Mr. Arafat to make tough decisions, the official said.</p>
        <p>One indication of that, another administration official said, was the cool reception that President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt gave to Mr. Arafat's idea of an Arab summit meeting on Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the Camp David talks, the Egyptian leader infuriated senior White House aides with his outspoken statements discouraging Mr. Arafat from making a compromise on Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Mubarak has continued to sound a stern uncompromising note in public, saying in an interview published during the weekend that no Arab or Muslim state could relinquish the traditional claim to Jerusalem and its holy sites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubarak was briefed extensively about the Camp David talks by the assistant secretary of state for Near Eastern affairs, Edward S. Walker Jr., who has been touring Arab capitals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker, who took part only briefly in the negotiations at Camp David, has instructions to tell Arab leaders the broad outlines of what went on there and to urge them to help Mr. Arafat to compromise, American officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat returned to his headquarters in Gaza on Saturday to contemplate the results of his visits to European and Arab countries.</p>
        <p>France, which currently holds the chair of the European Union, encouraged Mr. Arafat to continue to talk to his ''partner,'' Mr. Barak, the senior official said. That was in contrast, he said, to the message that Mr. Arafat had received from the French when he was negotiating with the previous Israeli government under Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, whom Paris considered more of an obstacle to Middle East peace.</p>
        <p>In the Arab capitals, Mr. Arafat garnered expressions of support for his refusal to compromise on the question of Palestinian sovereignty over East Jerusalem. But there was no broad endorsement for an Arab summit meeting that would develop into a platform for Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>The White House is sending Dennis B. Ross, its senior Middle East negotiator, to Israel late this week. He is expected to travel in the region.</p>
        <p>The administration insists that Camp David created a new dynamic because issues that had never been dissected before -- especially the future status of Jerusalem -- were broached in a serious manner.</p>
        <p>Jerusalem remained the hardest hurdle, with the most intractable problems concerning sovereignty over what the Jews call the Temple Mount, known to Muslims as Haram al Sharif, and the status of the Old City and its immediately adjoining areas, the senior administration official said.</p>
        <p>At Camp David, the administration suggested that the Palestinians have sovereignty over the Muslim and Christian quarters and the Israelis over the Jewish and the Armenian quarters of the Old City. Another proposal revolved around the Palestinians having sovereignty over several of the neighborhoods surrounding the Old City and having administrative autonomy within the walls.</p>
        <p>A third notion was to defer the Jerusalem problem for some years.</p>
        <p>Neither the Israelis nor the Palestinians showed much enthusiasm for deferring the issue while completing a peace agreement on territory, security and the fate of Palestinian refugees, the official said.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Barak's declared objectives has been to secure an accord that would enable him to announce that it was a final agreement settling all Palestinian claims on Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat has argued that East Jerusalem must be the sovereign capital of the new Palestinian state. ''I wouldn't dismiss the possibility of getting the agreement on everything,'' the senior administration official said.</p>
        <p>The official said that the administration remained willing to do all it could, but that only the two sides could actually reach agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
