<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leiter Makes It Easy For the Soaring Mets</title>
    <meta content="14METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6DB103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leiter Makes It Easy For the Soaring Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat San Francisco Giants, 2-0 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Leiter spotted a photo of a pitcher a few days ago, and he looked it over with admiration. As the pitcher released the ball, his arm was like the minute hand on a clock at the top of the hour. That is impressive, said Leiter, who felt his release point was off in a sloppy outing at Houston last week.</p>
        <p>Leiter, the Mets' left-hander, knew his mechanics would have to be better. Yesterday, they were. Leiter reached out more with his arm, kept his fingers on top of his pitches and worked eight marvelous innings to beat the San Francisco Giants, 2-0, at Shea Stadium. He gave up only two hits and one walk while striking out 12, improving his record to 13-5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Leiter spotted a photo of a pitcher a few days ago, and he looked it over with admiration. As the pitcher released the ball, his arm was like the minute hand on a clock at the top of the hour. That is impressive, said Leiter, who felt his release point was off in a sloppy outing at Houston last week.</p>
        <p>Leiter, the Mets' left-hander, knew his mechanics would have to be better. Yesterday, they were. Leiter reached out more with his arm, kept his fingers on top of his pitches and worked eight marvelous innings to beat the San Francisco Giants, 2-0, at Shea Stadium. He gave up only two hits and one walk while striking out 12, improving his record to 13-5.</p>
        <p>Leiter left for a pinch-hitter in the eighth, when Robin Ventura's double and Mike Bordick's single brought in the only runs of the game to give the Mets their fifth straight victory. With Armando Benitez having pitched the last two days, John Franco worked the ninth inning for his fourth save.</p>
        <p>The Mets (69-47) pulled to a game and a half behind first-place Atlanta in the National League East, the closest they have been in five weeks, and they have won 16 of 19 games.</p>
        <p>Earlier in this four-game series, which the Mets can sweep with a victory tonight, Leiter talked with Dave Righetti, the Giants' pitching coach and his friend, about his Sunday opponent, Livan Hernandez. Righetti told him how sharp Hernandez had been, and Leiter knew that every pitch would count.</p>
        <p>''Any time I'm facing a guy who's quality, that kind of elevates my concentration, and realizing that the execution of a pitch is important,'' Leiter said. ''I even thought about that with Barry. I really wanted to throw a fastball in at some point in one of his at-bats, and I never did.''</p>
        <p>The wind was blowing in from center field, but Leiter feared Barry Bonds could turn on a pitch and drive it down the right-field line for a homer. So Leiter changed his approach to Bonds, a left-handed power hitter, and twice struck him out with curveballs.</p>
        <p>Leiter had all of his pitches working, even his changeup, which he used against Ellis Burks to set up the groundout that ended the seventh inning, just after Jeff Kent singled to end a stretch of 19 consecutive outs.</p>
        <p>Manager Bobby Valentine let Leiter hit with a man on third and one out in the seventh -- he struck out -- and Leiter fanned the side in the eighth. His high fastball was humming, his slider diving and his cutter boring in on the Giants' hands.</p>
        <p>When Leiter was younger, he would continue to try to make a nasty pitch when he fell behind in the count. While he struck out a lot of hitters, he usually walked a lot, too. Yesterday, Leiter said, he mostly tried to throw strikes without worrying that a hitter would put it in play.</p>
        <p>Leiter got several outs this way, and Righetti noticed how Ventura, the third baseman, would set up close to the line and Bordick, the shortstop, would set up in the hole. The wild rookie whom Righetti knew with the Yankees in the late 80's now has superior command of his cutter.</p>
        <p>''He had a good, rising fastball and a pretty good slider,'' said Righetti, who was the Yankees' closer when Leiter started his career there in 1987. ''But he never had that other pitch, that curveball and that efficient fastball he could spot; it was all over the place.</p>
        <p>''Now, he's got that cutter to go along with the other fastball that he has. He's using a pitch that right-handers have a tough time dealing with. Even if they hit it good, they have a tough time hitting it fair.''</p>
        <p>Leiter idolized Righetti, who taught him slider grips but whose professionalism made the most lasting impression. Leiter noticed how Righetti would sit in the bullpen all game long, even though he would not be called on until the end, and he said that commitment taught him respect for the team ideal.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's outing looked like Leiter's best this year, but he did not care to rank it.</p>
        <p>''Really I'm not proud anymore of whether it's a complete domination or not, so long as we win the game,'' he said. ''I don't want to give up five runs in my games, because after a while you realize you're playing with fire, but a win's a win. The organization, the G.M., owner, fans -- all they care about is whether you won the game.''</p>
        <p>Leiter would not have won without the offense finally getting to Hernandez (11-9). The Mets left seven runners on in the first seven innings -- they lead the N.L. in runners left on base, with 7.76 a game -- but Edgardo Alfonzo walked to lead off the eighth and scored when Ventura split the gap in right-center with a double that bounced to the wall.</p>
        <p>''He's really on the upward climb,'' Valentine said of Ventura, who was slowed at midseason by a shoulder injury. ''He's been very, very good in the dugout all year long, and very good with his preparation, but you could tell that he's felt he could contribute more. Now he's getting right on track.''</p>
        <p>So is Leiter, whose mechanics looked just fine to his mentor.</p>
        <p>''The best thing he's doing now is finishing his pitches,'' Righetti said. ''He attacks hitters better out front than he did before. He used to land and spin off the ball. Now, he's not doing that. He's finishing.''</p>
        <p>His forgettable Houston start behind him, Leiter's performance was picturesque again.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mets left fielder BENNY AGBAYANI, who forgot the number of outs on Saturday and gave a ball to a fan, which allowed two Giants runs to score, received a warm ovation before his first at-bat yesterday. ''It was unexpected, but I really appreciate that,'' said Agbayani, who was spared a negative reaction because the Mets won Saturday's game, 3-2. ''I guess the fans realize I'm human also. I make mistakes; everyone makes mistakes.'' . . . The right-hander PAT MAHOMES was not needed yesterday, so he will be rested today and start one of the games in tomorrow's doubleheader against Colorado. Mahomes has a 2.76 earned run average in three starts this year, though he has pitched only in relief since mid-May. . . . JOHN FRANCO struck out JEFF KENT looking to end the game with a runner on third. It was the 19th game in a row in which Franco had not allowed an earned run. ''I think he knows he still can save a lot of games, and I'd be very surprised if he doesn't save a whole lot more games before his career is over,'' Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said. It is not clear where Franco, who turns 40 next month, will get those saves. He has 420 in his career, second most behind Lee Smith's 478, but he is a setup man this year and can become a free agent this winter.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
