<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Says Firestone Was Aware of Flaw In Its Tires by 1997</title>
    <meta content="14TIRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DC103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Says Firestone Was Aware of Flaw In Its Tires by 1997</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co releases documents showing that in 1997 Bridgestone/Firestone began receiving numerous complaints of injuries and property damage involving certain Firestone tires that were not recalled until recently; discloses that some of recalled tires have rates of injury 100 times greater than for those not recalled; says many of claims were sent to Bridgestone by vehicle owners from 1997 to 1999 but that Ford was never informed; says it only learned of high rate of claims week ago, when it performed its own computer analysis of Bridgestone's data; Bridgestone reportedly resisted Ford's disclosure of information; Ford's new automobiles, particularly sport utility vehicles, are equipped with two-thirds of recalled tires (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company released documents today showing that in 1997 Bridgestone/Firestone began receiving numerous complaints of injuries and property damage involving certain Firestone tires that were not recalled until last Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some of the recalled tires have rates of injury and personal damage claims up to 100 times greater than for tires not recalled, Ford disclosed today. Many of those claims were sent to Bridgestone by vehicle owners from 1997 to 1999, but the tire maker did not tell Ford, the company said. Ford's new automobiles, particularly Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles, are equipped with two-thirds of the recalled tires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company released documents today showing that in 1997 Bridgestone/Firestone began receiving numerous complaints of injuries and property damage involving certain Firestone tires that were not recalled until last Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some of the recalled tires have rates of injury and personal damage claims up to 100 times greater than for tires not recalled, Ford disclosed today. Many of those claims were sent to Bridgestone by vehicle owners from 1997 to 1999, but the tire maker did not tell Ford, the company said. Ford's new automobiles, particularly Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles, are equipped with two-thirds of the recalled tires.</p>
        <p>The automaker said it only learned of the high rate of claims a week ago, when it performed its own computer analysis of Bridgestone's data. Bridgestone had resisted Ford's disclosure of the information, said a person briefed on the automaker's work on the issue.</p>
        <p>Ford said Bridgestone's factory in Decatur, Ill., had been the main source of the problem tires, and that the factory had experienced its biggest quality problems from 1994 through 1996. Those were the years when the factory was operated mainly by replacement workers because of a labor dispute between Bridgestone and its union, although Ford made no mention of that fact today.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone officials did not dispute Ford's data but said the problem had not caught their attention until Ford began reviewing Bridgestone's files two weeks ago. The overall rate of complaints on tires from all Bridgestone factories has not been unusually high, and Bridgestone did not conduct the detailed review of tire quality by factory that Ford undertook, said Bob Wyant, Bridgestone's vice president of quality assurance.</p>
        <p>Chris Karbowiak, a Bridgestone spokeswoman, said there was no evidence the labor dispute had affected quality in Decatur. She was also  quick to point out during a conference call with reporters this afternoon that Ford itself had given the Decatur factory a quality award.</p>
        <p>The two companies' mutual sniping was the clearest sign yet that the recall was causing a strain in one of corporate America's oldest relationships. Firestone, which was purchased by Bridgestone in 1988, has been supplying tires to Ford since 1906, when Henry Ford was still designing the first Model T.</p>
        <p>Ford and Bridgestone had presented a mostly united front since last Wednesday's recall of 6.5 million Firestone tires, which in addition to being included on some new Ford vehicles were sold as replacement tires for several manufacturers' sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks. Ford dealers have been flooded with customers seeking replacement tires, including for Firestone tires not covered by the recall, while buyers have been leery of purchasing new Ford Explorers equipped with Firestone tires.</p>
        <p>Ford released the data today partly in the hope of reassuring customers that Firestone tires not covered by the recall were safe, notably Wilderness AT tires made at factories other than in Decatur. But the data is unlikely to appease plaintiff lawyers and safety groups, who scheduled a press conference on Monday in Washington to call for Bridgestone to expand the recall to include far more Wilderness brand tires.</p>
        <p>Ralph Hoar, the founder of Safetyforum.com, a consulting firm that is coordinating many of the lawsuits against Bridgestone and Ford, said  Ford was trying to put all the blame on Bridgestone to draw attention away from what he described as design defects in the Ford Explorer's suspension that put strain on the tires. Ford officials have repeatedly denied this.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone and Ford have recalled a larger size of Wilderness tire used on Explorers in four foreign countries. The larger size is included on the more expensive Explorers in the United States, but has not been recalled here. Ford said the oversees recall reflected driving conditions seldom found here, so that a broader recall was unnecessary.</p>
        <p>People who have been briefed on  Ford's work on the tire problem said the automaker had been deeply disturbed to learn two weeks ago that Bridgestone had done little work to analyze the reliability of its tires in the United States despite growing complaints and a federal investigation that began in May. Jason Vines, a Ford spokesman, took pains today to mention that Ford had used very sophisticated programs and equipment to analyze the Bridgestone data. But another person briefed on Ford's work said the company's analysis was ''not rocket science'' and represented standard practice for automakers that try to identify quality problems.</p>
        <p>Ford faxed a 12-page summary of the data to reporters this afternoon and then held a conference call during which it discussed the material. Ford initially planned only to have its own executives take part, but Ms. Karbowiak and Mr. Wyant of Bridgestone decided to participate as well. They were mostly silent as Mr. Vines explained how Ford had asked for and been given Firestone's data on injury and property damage claims, and quickly discovered problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vines said Ford officials obtained the data on July 28 and spent eight days entering it into Ford's computers. Within several days, Ford had concluded that there was a problem with all Firestone ATX and ATX II tires of the P235/75R15 size, and with Firestone Wilderness AT tires of the same size that were produced in Decatur only. Firestone and Ford then decided on a recall.</p>
        <p>The federal investigation that began in May includes 300 complaints about Firestone tires, involving 46 deaths. The Ford data released today showed that there had been just one to six tread separation claims per million Wilderness AT tires from factories other than Decatur. Wilderness tires from other factories are being used to replace the Decatur tires and various ATX tires that are being recalled.</p>
        <p>For Wilderness AT tires from Decatur, the rate of injury and property damage claims was more than 50 per million tires produced in 1996 and close to that level for tires produced in 1997. While there have been very few claims for Decatur-made Wilderness tires produced since 1998, these have not been on the road long enough for many claims to be received, Mr. Vines said.</p>
        <p>The claims rate was far higher for ATX tires, all of which are being recalled in the P235/75R15 size regardless of where they were produced. For factories other than the Decatur plant, the rate approached 100 claims per million tires for tires produced from 1993 to 1995.</p>
        <p>At the Decatur plant itself, the claims rate soared to between 350 and 650 claims per million ATX tires produced in 1994, 1995 and 1996. There have been virtually no claims for any of the recalled tires in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, with almost all problems occurring in hotter states.</p>
        <p>Thomas F. Dasse, a Phoenix lawyer handling several lawsuits against Bridgestone, said in an interview on Friday that his litigation depended partly on testimony from former Bridgestone employees who had worked at the Decatur factory until the labor dispute and who had described quality problems there. The Washington Post reported today that some of the lawsuits against Bridgestone included testimony from former workers in Decatur who described manually piercing blisters in the rubber of flawed tires and sending them to a warehouse for sale, instead of scrapping them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Karbowiak described these comments as the views of ''disgruntled workers,'' and said that Bridgestone disagreed with them. She said Bridgestone believed that all of the replacement workers had performed their jobs as well as the union workers had before them.</p>
        <p>''We strongly believe there is no connection based on what we know of our training and operating procedures,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Decatur factory makes tires of various sizes for other automakers, and Ford has not analyzed the claims rates for these tires. Mr. Wyant said Bridgestone did not believe these tires had problems.</p>
        <p>The United Steelworkers of America went on strike against Bridgestone in Decatur in July 1994. After 10 months, the union ordered a return to work without a contract, but the company rehired only a few workers while continuing to rely on replacement workers. The company and the union did not reach an agreement until November 1996, when most of the remaining union workers went back to their jobs.</p>
        <p>The claims rate for Wilderness tires made in Decatur began to fall in 1997 and is now virtually equal to the claims rate for Wilderness tires made elsewhere, Mr. Vines, of Ford, said. But Bridgestone is recalling all Wilderness tires made in Decatur since 1996 as a precaution.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
