<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testaverde's Status Is Uncertain for Opener</title>
    <meta content="14JETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testaverde's Status Is Uncertain for Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde will miss at least next week of practice and will not play in final preseason game against New York Giants because of sprained big toe on his left foot; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde will miss at least the next week of practice and will not play in the final preseason game Friday against the Giants because of a sprained big toe on his left foot. But Jets Coach Al Groh remained hopeful that Testaverde, who was injured in the Jets' loss to the Baltimore Ravens on Saturday night, would be ready when the Jets open the regular season against Green Bay on Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>''I think it's too early to speculate on that right now,'' Groh said. ''But the indications I've gotten are that with aggressive treatment and with an aggressive approach on his part, he should be ready.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde will miss at least the next week of practice and will not play in the final preseason game Friday against the Giants because of a sprained big toe on his left foot. But Jets Coach Al Groh remained hopeful that Testaverde, who was injured in the Jets' loss to the Baltimore Ravens on Saturday night, would be ready when the Jets open the regular season against Green Bay on Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>''I think it's too early to speculate on that right now,'' Groh said. ''But the indications I've gotten are that with aggressive treatment and with an aggressive approach on his part, he should be ready.''</p>
        <p>Although turf toe is typically a nagging injury that can impair a quarterback's ability to push off comfortably on his affected foot, the Jets' quirky schedule should work in Testaverde's favor. After the game against the Giants, the Jets have a bye in the final week of the preseason, so Testaverde has three full weeks to receive treatment before a decision has to be made for the Green Bay game.</p>
        <p>If Testaverde cannot start, Ray Lucas, who was 6-3 as a starter after Testaverde was hurt last season, would open the season against the Packers.</p>
        <p>Much less hopeful is the prognosis for the rookie quarterback Chad Pennington. He will be out at least three weeks, Groh said, with a sprained left knee. Pennington would have almost certainly been inactive for the season opener anyway, so this injury merely impedes the progress he was making in what had been an impressive preseason.</p>
        <p>More troubling for the Jets, though, is that even if Testaverde is healthy enough to play Sept. 3, he will have had little live action preparation. Testaverde has been in on just 41 official plays, and until last night he had received no contact at all. Of the seven drives he has led, two of them were of just one play -- one a 75-yard touchdown pass to Wayne Chrebet against the Saints, the other an interception that was returned for a touchdown Saturday by the Ravens.</p>
        <p>For the preseason Testaverde has completed 11 passes in 21 attempts for 244 yards, one touchdown and 2 interceptions, both of which were returned for touchdowns. Testaverde indicated before Saturday's game that he had hoped to get more playing time in the preseason. Now, Lucas will get the bulk of the time against the Giants.</p>
        <p>''I can only deal with the reality of things as they've transpired,'' Groh said of Testaverde's game time. ''So now we have to get him ready in a different fashion.''</p>
        <p>In a twisted way, the rest of the Jets benefited from the injuries to Testaverde and Pennington.</p>
        <p>For at least a few hours, the injuries took the attention away from how poorly they performed against the Ravens.</p>
        <p>The Ravens' defense, one of the best in the league, ate up the Jets' offensive line with so many blitzes that it looked like the Super Bowl and not the preseason. That aggressiveness rendered the passing game -- which had looked hopeful in the first two games but which was missing Chrebet, who was ill -- anemic (149 yards passing from 4 quarterbacks, no touchdowns and 2 interceptions). It had looked hopeful in the first two games but was missing Chrebet, who was ill, in the third.</p>
        <p>''It needs to be a lot more effective than that,'' Groh said. ''It was on the opposite end of the spectrum from the first two games.''</p>
        <p>The defense, which struggled against Green Bay, did not fare much better against the Ravens, despite the limited Ravens scoring. The Ravens had 344 yards of total offense, including 215 passing. Despite some good individual performances -- the rookie linebacker John Abraham had four tackles and blocked a field goal late in the game, the rookie cornerback Tony Scott had an interception and Groh praised the rookie defensive end Shaun Ellis's progress -- the defense also gave up the play of the night.</p>
        <p>The Ravens' offensive line picked up a blitz by Kevin Williams and Tony Banks delivered a pass to a wide open Qadry Ismail, who ran away from Marcus Coleman and Victor Green for a 57-yard play that put the Ravens on the Jets' 18-yard line.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The unretired offensive tackle JUMBO ELLIOTT is expected in camp Monday, and Coach AL GROH said he could play as soon as Friday against the Giants. . . . Groh said WAYNE CHREBET should return to practice this week after missing the Ravens game while feeling sick and lightheaded. . . . There is still no timetable for the return of cornerback AARON GLENN, who has a sprained ankle. . . . Despite two bad snaps by long snapper DENNIS O'SULLIVAN, Groh indicated the Jets were not taking a look at that position. . . . Groh said nobody had set himself apart for the third wide receiver position. WINDRELL HAYES and LAVERANUES COLES each had two catches Saturday. But Groh said there were no veteran wide receivers available who sparked the Jets' interest. . . . DEDRIC WARD and TONY SCOTT will continue to return punts. . . . After each of the three contestants got a start, none of the free safeties has grabbed the job yet.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
