<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unusually Severe Crackdown On Political Dissent in China</title>
    <meta content="Y14SHA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000815T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D6133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unusually Severe Crackdown On Political Dissent in China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police activity has increased in several parts of China as country undergoes tightening of social controls ahead of October 1 National Day holiday; while summer sweep of discos and karaoke bars and detention of people voicing political dissent happen every year, current crackdown appears unusually harsh (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police activity has been increasing in several parts of China as the country undergoes a tightening of social controls ahead of the Oct. 1 National Day holiday.</p>
        <p>While the summer sweep of discos and karaoke bars and the detention of people voicing political dissent happen every year, the crackdown appears unusually harsh this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police activity has been increasing in several parts of China as the country undergoes a tightening of social controls ahead of the Oct. 1 National Day holiday.</p>
        <p>While the summer sweep of discos and karaoke bars and the detention of people voicing political dissent happen every year, the crackdown appears unusually harsh this year.</p>
        <p>It coincides with the annual gathering of Communist Party leaders in the northern seaside resort of Beidaihe, where growing social discontent and the economic challenges of China's planned entry into the World Trade Organization are expected to be high on the agenda.</p>
        <p>China is climbing out of an economic slump in which its overall economic growth rate dipped by close to 7 percent last year. Several regions of the country went into a deep recession, leading to scattered unrest in heavily industrialized regions. Now a severe drought has increased disquiet among much of the country's rural population.</p>
        <p>China's entry into the trade organization, expected later this year, will increase economic pressure on the bottom rung of the country's population as it struggles to compete with  multinational corporations.</p>
        <p>Following other reports of a crackdown on dissent in recent days, the  police detained a reporter in central China after he talked to an American journalist about unrest among local farmers, a human rights group said today.</p>
        <p>The Hong Kong-based Information Center for Human Rights and Democracy said that a Shaanxi Province television reporter, Ma Xiaoming, was picked up by the police after he met a journalist from an unspecified news organization to talk about farmers trying to sue the government. Mr. Ma was later released.</p>
        <p>Farmers in the province have complained of exorbitant taxes and beatings by the local authorities. And the residents of eight poor Shaanxi villages are trying to free their lawyer, jailed last year after he went to Beijing to appeal to the central government on their behalf.</p>
        <p>In Beijing, the police apparently continued to hold a poet and editor, Bei Ling, after they seized hundreds of copies of an independent literary journal he had edited, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bei disappeared Friday after telling friends he planned to hold a discussion forum that afternoon to review the August issue of his quarterly journal Tendency, which includes a photograph of the exiled Chinese dissident, Wang Dan, and a poem by a dissident literary critic, Liu Xiaobo.</p>
        <p>And in Shanghai, police officers shut down several discos and bars for minor infractions in what the police described as a national campaign to clean up China's night life. Several establishments crowded with foreigners and Chinese have been raided by vanloads of uniformed police officers for no clear reason, and some have been told not to reopen until after Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 15, 2000, Tuesday  Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about a crackdown on political dissent in China misstated the change in China's economic growth rate last year, when a slump contributed to unrest in parts of the country. The rate of growth dipped from about 8 percent to about 7 percent; it did not fall by 7 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 15, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about a crackdown on political dissent in China misstated the change in China's economic growth rate last year, when a slump contributed to unrest in parts of the country. The rate of growth dipped from about 8 percent to about 7 percent; it did not fall by 7 percent.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
