<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wacky, fake Web sites grab attention, while only slyly referring to their sponsors.</title>
    <meta content="14ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fass, Allison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4D9133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wacky, fake Web sites grab attention, while only slyly referring to their sponsors.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allison Fass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fass, Allison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New marketing trend on Internet is fanciful or fictional sites that only refer to actual products or companies in subtle ways; several sites described (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VISITORS to www.goblertoys .com can find cartoon versions of the toy inventions of Ira Gobler like Gobler's Wobblers, Rodeo Rover and Senor and Senorita Sandwich. The site also offers a scrapbook of the career of Mr. Gobler, president and founder of Gobler Toys, and links to animated commercials.</p>
        <p>But anyone doing research into the toy business will soon find there is no Gobler Toys and no toymaker named Ira Gobler. Rather, www.goblertoys.com is an example of an increasingly popular trend in marketing: fictional or fanciful Web sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VISITORS to www.goblertoys .com can find cartoon versions of the toy inventions of Ira Gobler like Gobler's Wobblers, Rodeo Rover and Senor and Senorita Sandwich. The site also offers a scrapbook of the career of Mr. Gobler, president and founder of Gobler Toys, and links to animated commercials.</p>
        <p>But anyone doing research into the toy business will soon find there is no Gobler Toys and no toymaker named Ira Gobler. Rather, www.goblertoys.com is an example of an increasingly popular trend in marketing: fictional or fanciful Web sites.</p>
        <p>The trend is meant to capitalize on the growing use of and fascination with the Internet as well as to take advantage of the capabilities of the Web to produce content at a low cost that appears to be genuine. In other words, on the World Wide Web, it can always be April Fool's Day.</p>
        <p>''The Internet allows you to be a little more out there in your approach,'' said Peter Capper, vice president and account supervisor at BVK/McDonald in Milwaukee. ''It's much more accepting of different ideas.''</p>
        <p>For one client, Sun Country Airlines in Mendota Heights, Minn., BVK/McDonald created a campaign centered on a fanciful Web site, www.heybill.com, which is separate from the airline's official site, www.suncountry.com.</p>
        <p>''Bill'' refers to the president and chief executive at Sun Country, Bill La Macchia Jr., who has appeared in quirky television, radio and print ads for the airline.</p>
        <p>''Many people looked at me as part of the brand,'' Mr. La Macchia said, adding that the silly site was meant to further the airline's goal of sponsoring ''relationship marketing'' instead of just traditional advertising.</p>
        <p>Heybill.com was built to resemble a friend's home page, featuring travel tips, a trivia game about famous people named Bill and opportunities to negotiate with Mr. La Macchia for low ticket prices. To put up the site, BVK/McDonald worked with Mark Net World in Milwaukee, which is owned by BVK/McDonald and a group of private investors.</p>
        <p>The fictional Web site for Gobler Toys was created by two toy lovers who met two years ago at the International Toy Fair in New York.</p>
        <p>''What we would love to have is our own Mattel, our own Hasbro,'' said Steve Fink, vice president for marketing at Bang Zoom Design in Cincinnati, describing the virtual company he concocted with Steve Casino, a toy inventor at Kiscom in Englewood, N.J. ''But obviously, we can't do that because we don't have the money.''</p>
        <p>''We thought the next best thing,'' he added, ''is to have a fake one.''</p>
        <p>Likewise, Web surfers who check out www.rentarelative.com will see information that appears to be about a company renting stand-in replacements for people unable to attend family functions because they are restricted from redeeming frequent-flier miles.</p>
        <p>The site presents what seems to be information about the company's staff, employment opportunities and a detailed price chart; for instance, if a meal is not served while a stand-in is working, the price goes up $25.</p>
        <p>Sound real? As if.</p>
        <p>The site was created as an advertising ploy for a company called WebMiles.com, which promotes itself as offering members ways to earn frequent flyer miles with fewer restrictions than conventional programs.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Case, vice president for marketing at WebMiles.com in Sandy, Utah, described the site as the ''creative concept by which we're going to get the message of Web Miles across.''</p>
        <p>A humorous television commercial by the WebMiles.com agency, GMO/Hill, Holliday in San Francisco, shows a laid-back young man turning up at a reunion of a family clearly not his own: The family is Asian-American and he is Caucasian. After the man explains he has been sent to stand in for a cousin who could not attend because of frequent flyer blackout dates, he spends the afternoon behaving badly.</p>
        <p>Making up a Web site is ''definitely an idea that has legs,'' said Terry Rietta, a creative director at GMO/ Hill, Holliday, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>To keep the spoof going, WebMiles.com sent out news releases and e-mail announcing the formation of RentaRelative.com that only briefly referred to WebMiles.com, calling the real company a ''strategic partner.''</p>
        <p>In the April issue of Esquire, published by Hearst Magazines, Ted C. Fishman wrote an article meant to parody the abundance of Web sites for products that seemed too good to be true. To ''take readers for a ride,'' Mr. Fishman said, he described a company offering free cars to people who agreed to have them plastered with ads, as if it were real. He and Esquire then actually put up a site at www.FreeWheelz.com, complete with impressive graphics and a section titled ''about us.''</p>
        <p>But the company may not have been fantastic enough. Mr. Fishman said he heard from advertisers who did not get the joke, asking for information about becoming sponsors, as well as from people who said he had been able to get a site up before they could.</p>
        <p>In June, Mr. Fishman sold the domain name www.FreeWheelz.com for $25,000 to an entrepreneur who said he was starting his own free-car ad company. Mr. Fishman said that he and Hearst split the money.</p>
        <p>It seems when it comes to fictional sites, the difference between fiction and fact can be slight.</p>
        <p>''We started this as a fake thing,'' said Mr. Fink of the make-believe Gobler Toys site, ''but it could end up being very real.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
