<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democratic Chairman Plays Humble Hoosier Effortlessly</title>
    <meta content="Y14LIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Joe Andrew</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Democratic National Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrew, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democratic Chairman Plays Humble Hoosier Effortlessly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles Joe Andrew, chairman of Democratic National Committee who will open Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Republicans on MSNBC's ''Equal Time'' were having a hard time painting the smiling, smooth-faced guy in glasses and a brown suit -- the one trying in vain to offer an opinion -- as in league with Al Gore's ''slaughterhouse killers.''</p>
        <p>Still, that nice Joe Andrew, the chairman of the Democratic National Committee, who will bring the gavel down to start his party's convention in Los Angeles on Monday, tried to enter into the spirit of the show, talking right over the hosts, Ollie North and Paul Begala, and exchanging ideas on the issues with Jim Nicholson, chairman of the Republican National Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Republicans on MSNBC's ''Equal Time'' were having a hard time painting the smiling, smooth-faced guy in glasses and a brown suit -- the one trying in vain to offer an opinion -- as in league with Al Gore's ''slaughterhouse killers.''</p>
        <p>Still, that nice Joe Andrew, the chairman of the Democratic National Committee, who will bring the gavel down to start his party's convention in Los Angeles on Monday, tried to enter into the spirit of the show, talking right over the hosts, Ollie North and Paul Begala, and exchanging ideas on the issues with Jim Nicholson, chairman of the Republican National Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson: ''Is Joe Lieberman going to work in the slaughterhouse?'' -- as Mr. Gore's wild-talking campaign manager, Donna Brazile, recently called their headquarters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrew: ''It's called the kitchen'' -- the Gore campaign's name for its ''war room.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicholson: ''No, it's killers in the kitchen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrew: ''The only killers in this process are Dick Cheney.''</p>
        <p>He's not quite as tame as he looks, but not entirely comfortable with the zingers, either. After the show, Mr. Andrew tried a little friendly chitchat on Mr. Nicholson: ''Hey, they didn't even need us in there, did they?''</p>
        <p>What he got back, though, was the tight smile of an airline passenger engrossed in a really good book and hoping to discourage instant intimacy without being totally rude.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrew whispered, ''I'm always the one who asks about his kids,'' not the other way around. He frequently sounds surprised by the brusqueness of life in the capital, having arrived here with his wife and two children just last year, ''plucked from the obscurity of the cornfields of Indiana,'' as he puts it.</p>
        <p>When George W. Bush was asked, not long ago, to respond to a charge Mr. Andrew had made, his response was, ''Who is Joe Andrew?''</p>
        <p>But then, Mr. Andrew did not get his job because he was a brand name. He got it -- O.K., in part because the heaviest hitters were not begging to take over when the national committee was going broke -- but also because he had turned around the state operation in Indiana.</p>
        <p>He loves to tell how, on his first day in Washington, he took some union officials to lunch and handed the waiter his new corporate credit card: ''They came back and said, 'I'm sorry, Mr. Andrew, but your card has been rejected.' We hadn't been able to pay Visa for six months.''</p>
        <p>Since then, he has excelled at the unsexy business of cutting costs, upgrading technology and taking care of candidates -- while the better known general party chairman, Edward G. Rendell, handles fund-raising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrew's ''boring, difficult, unpopular'' cuts helped get the operation back in the black last year, as one party operative put it. And Mr. Andrew has emerged as a favorite of unions and state parties, who like his regular-guyness and do not care if he fails to dazzle on cable.</p>
        <p>''Joe Andrew has been a shot of adrenaline,'' said Judith Hope, chairwoman of the New York  Democratic Party. ''It means a lot to those of us in the trenches that he's been there himself.''</p>
        <p>The humble Hoosier routine is no put-on. After an initial meeting with a reporter, in which he was correct in the extreme, he asked  an associate, ''Do you think I came on too strong?'' But he is also better-connected than his references to cornfields would suggest.</p>
        <p>One of those six-degrees-of-separation diagrams that showed all Hollywood linked to  Winona Ryder might work for Joe Andrew in Washington. Mr. Gore's new running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, had Mr. Andrew in class at Yale and recommended him for his current job.</p>
        <p>William M. Daley of Chicago, who is running Mr. Gore's campaign, once worked with him on a legal case. He got to know Jesse Jackson through Black Expo, a cultural festival in Indianapolis. He has worked for Senator Evan Bayh of Indiana.</p>
        <p>And that is how he met a bunch of people with ties to Mr.  Gore -- including Carter Eskew, Mr. Gore's top consultant. Ron Klain, Mr. Gore's former chief of staff, is a fellow Hoosier Mr. Andrew knows from Indianapolis -- a networking hot spot, it would seem. And Mr. Klain also had a hand in bringing him into Goreworld.</p>
        <p>In a long interview over dinner, Mr. Andrew, 40, said it was politics that had gotten him interested in the wider world back in his hometown of Poe, Ind., population 87, where he was one of nine children  in a Republican family.</p>
        <p>HIS father, a doctor, moved the family to ''an actual corn-and-soybean farm. His idea was to be a gentleman farmer, but when they divorced, it became a real farm.''</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a Newt Gingrich story,'' Mr. Andrew said, putting a partisan spin even on the story of how his father left the family.</p>
        <p>After that, his mother, a former teacher he described as ''a woman who likes a good glass of wine and a Shakespeare festival,'' had to learn how to farm. ''My entire adolescence was spent mowing weeds,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His escape, his entertainment, and probably his rebellion, was Democratic politics. At 12, his idea of fun was to go to the mall and slap bumper stickers for local Democrats on the cars of unsuspecting shoppers. The Allen County party headquarters became his hangout.</p>
        <p>Along about then, a ''very liberal'' teacher began encouraging him to shoot for Yale University, mostly because a local man had set up a scholarship to that school, Mr. Andrew said,  and that is how he went to college. He later graduated from Yale Law School.</p>
        <p>And, of course, he met Mr. Lieberman. ''But for Lieberman,'' he says, modestly, ''I would never had gotten involved in any of it.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
