<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holyfield Regains Part of Title but Goes Backward</title>
    <meta content="Y14FIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Boxing Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arkush, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holyfield, Evander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruiz, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFDC103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holyfield Regains Part of Title but Goes Backward</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ARKUSH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arkush, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Evander Holyfield wins World Boxing Association heavyweight championship bout with unanimous decision over John Ruiz, Las Vegas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A right hand late in the third round stunned his opponent, who began to wobble. A visit to the canvas seemed imminent. But at this pivotal moment in Saturday night's World Boxing Association heavyweight championship bout against the unheralded John Ruiz, 37-year-old Evander Holyfield could not do what he almost surely would have done during his best years. He could not put his opponent away.</p>
        <p>He could not do it the rest of the 12-round fight, either. In fact, he almost lost the bout, escaping with a narrow decision before about 8,500 fans at the Paris Las Vegas Casino Resort. Two judges scored it 114-113, and the other judge had it 116-112. Only by capturing the final round did Holyfield avoid defeat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A right hand late in the third round stunned his opponent, who began to wobble. A visit to the canvas seemed imminent. But at this pivotal moment in Saturday night's World Boxing Association heavyweight championship bout against the unheralded John Ruiz, 37-year-old Evander Holyfield could not do what he almost surely would have done during his best years. He could not put his opponent away.</p>
        <p>He could not do it the rest of the 12-round fight, either. In fact, he almost lost the bout, escaping with a narrow decision before about 8,500 fans at the Paris Las Vegas Casino Resort. Two judges scored it 114-113, and the other judge had it 116-112. Only by capturing the final round did Holyfield avoid defeat.</p>
        <p>But now that this close call is over, Holyfield may have an even tougher time avoiding the doubts. Doubts about whether he can regain the form that made him one of boxing's most admired warriors.</p>
        <p>He was not, after all, facing Lennox Lewis or Riddick Bowe or Mike Tyson, fighters of supreme skill or power. He was facing Ruiz, an underdog who had not beaten anyone of distinction and who once lost to David Tua in 19 seconds. Yet, except for the flourish in the third round and a few good shots later in the fight, Holyfield never had Ruiz in any real trouble.</p>
        <p>Holyfield, who weighed in at 221 pounds, does not believe in doubts. He never has. He has been counted out before, yet has always found a way to bounce back with victories  against the best in his sport. So in his postfight comments, he sounded as proud and confident as ever.</p>
        <p>''Every time I attempted to reach a goal, people told me I wouldn't make it,'' said Holyfield, who, by beating Ruiz, became the first fighter to win the heavyweight crown four times, although many say this one is tainted because Lewis, the former champion, lost his W.B.A. belt in the courts, not in the ring.</p>
        <p>''When I fought Buster Douglas, everyone said I won because he was out of shape,'' Holyfield added. ''He might have been out of shape, but that's not my problem. I did beat him. After fighting Bowe, I came back and won. My goal was to win again and I did.''</p>
        <p>As for his inability to put the 224-pound Ruiz away, Holyfield had an answer for that, as well.</p>
        <p>''He leads with his head,'' said Holyfield, who earned $5 million and improved his record to 37-4-1. ''I hit him with hard punches. He is an awkward fighter.''</p>
        <p>Awkward or not, Ruiz, who was attempting to make his own history -- the first Hispanic to capture the heavyweight championship -- had a different analysis.</p>
        <p>''I fought my heart out and I feel like I won the fight,'' said Ruiz, 28, of Chelsea, Mass. He lost for the first time in 12 bouts since the Tua fight, dropping his record to 36-4.</p>
        <p>''This was a big setback. This is something I've been dreaming about. But that's life. I will keep fighting on.''</p>
        <p>Immediately after the fight, Holyfield said that he would offer Ruiz a rematch but hoped to ultimately face Lewis in a bid to unify the titles. Lewis had been the undisputed champion until he was stripped of his W.B.A. belt by a federal judge who ruled that he had violated a contract by refusing to fight Ruiz, then ranked as the association's top contender. Lewis, who still owns the World Boxing Council and International Boxing Federation titles, instead fought Michael Grant, knocking him out in the second round on April 29 in New York.</p>
        <p>''I am not going anywhere. I am the W.B.A. champion,'' said Holyfield, who lost a unanimous decision to Lewis last November in their second, and most recent, fight. Their first match, in March 1999, ended in a controversial draw.</p>
        <p>''He has two belts and I have one,'' Holyfield said. ''I am very happy to be the first four-time world heavyweight champion, but this is just the first step.''</p>
        <p>It was a first step that almost went backward.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
