<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With All Eyes on Kane, Mallon Wins du Maurier</title>
    <meta content="14LPGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Du Maurier Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mickey, Lisa D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallon, Meg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DD103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With All Eyes on Kane, Mallon Wins du Maurier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA D. MICKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mickey, Lisa D</byline>
      <dateline>AYLMER, Quebec, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Meg Mallon wins du Maurier Classic golf tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While all of Canada was caught up in the drama of one of its own daughters trying to win the final du Maurier Classic, the veteran Meg Mallon saw her own long-awaited opening and lunged for it.</p>
        <p>Only three weeks ago, Mallon came up short at the United States Women's Open, tying for second. Earlier in the year, she finished third at the Nabisco Championship. For most golfers on the women's tour, such a strong season in the L.P.G.A.'s major tournaments would have been exceptional. For Mallon, it meant coming up short in a major once again since winning the L.P.G.A. Championship and the United States Women's Open in 1991.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While all of Canada was caught up in the drama of one of its own daughters trying to win the final du Maurier Classic, the veteran Meg Mallon saw her own long-awaited opening and lunged for it.</p>
        <p>Only three weeks ago, Mallon came up short at the United States Women's Open, tying for second. Earlier in the year, she finished third at the Nabisco Championship. For most golfers on the women's tour, such a strong season in the L.P.G.A.'s major tournaments would have been exceptional. For Mallon, it meant coming up short in a major once again since winning the L.P.G.A. Championship and the United States Women's Open in 1991.</p>
        <p>But today, Mallon charged into the lead with a birdie on the seventh hole and never let go. The 14-year veteran ended up dueling with Rosie Jones to win the tournament with a final-round 69 and an overall score of six-under-par 282. Jones, on the strength of a 68 today, leapt over the field to take second place at 283.</p>
        <p>Annika Sorenstam, who was tied for the lead with the Canadian favorite, Lorie Kane, coming into the final round, finished third at four-under-par 284, one shot ahead of the rookie Diana D'Alessio at 285. Kane and Juli Inkster tied for fifth at two-under-par 286.</p>
        <p>''I had such a heartbreak at the U.S. Open this year,'' said Mallon, who earned $180,000 for winning her third major championship. ''It's great to come out on top today.''</p>
        <p>All week, the buildup to today's final round had been a giant crescendo for Kane, who was trying to do what only one other Canadian had done before. Jocelyne Bourassa won at this event's predecessor, La Canadienne, in its first year, 1973. The tournament became a major in 1979.  Now, Kane wanted to become the last Canadian to win the event and appropriately close this final staging, which will most likely expire because of Canadian anti-tobacco advertising laws affecting the tournament's title sponsor, Imperial Tobacco. No other Canadian company has indicated a willingness to sponsor the tournament.</p>
        <p>Kane seemed to feel the pressure today, although she tried to play it down all week. She did and did not want to be the country's hero, but she did admit that she wanted to do her part to make Canadian companies pay attention to what could be the last L.P.G.A. tournament in Canada. In the end, it proved too much to bear. Carrying a nation's hopes and trying to win a major championship on the same weekend turned out to be more than the fifth-year player could handle.</p>
        <p>''I made the last putt,'' said Kane, who shot a final-round, four-over-par 76 and fought back tears on the 18th green. ''And the whole time I was thinking about this tournament ending. I told myself, 'Put the ball in the hole and then carry on.' ''</p>
        <p>Kane and Sorenstam both got off to rocky starts. Kane bogeyed the first hole, and Sorenstam bogeyed the second. Kane lost another shot on the third hole and Sorenstam took a one-stroke lead, but on the fourth hole, Kane birdied and Sorenstam bogeyed for a two-shot swing that gave Kane a one-stroke lead over Mallon and Sorenstam. That one-stroke margin was the opportunity Mallon needed to make a move.</p>
        <p>Hitting a 9-iron to within 10 feet of the cup before making a birdie on the seventh hole, the tournament was suddenly in Mallon's grasp. When both Kane and Sorenstam bogeyed the seventh, Mallon led by a shot. She added another birdie on the ninth to make the turn at three-under-par 33. By that point, she had a one-stroke lead over D'Alessio.</p>
        <p>Kane's hopes faded further when she hit her tee shot out of bounds on the par-five 14th hole. It was her second straight bogey. D'Alessio three-putted for double bogey on the 11th and Sorenstam, who was on the wrong side of the hole all day, played defensively down the stretch.</p>
        <p>''It was a tough day, that's all I can say,'' said Sorenstam, who shot a two-over-par 74.</p>
        <p>Jones, who started the day one under par, posted birdies on Nos. 3, 6 and 8 to play the front nine at three under par before adding another birdie on the 10th hole to trail Mallon by one stroke. But Jones never got any closer, and Mallon rolled in a 15-footer for a birdie on the 16th to take a two-shot lead.</p>
        <p>Mallon's only hiccup came with her lone bogey. It occurred on the 552-yard, par-five 18th hole, where her approach shot landed short and her sand wedge pitch to the green left a 12-footer for par. Mallon missed the up and down, but knew the one-shot lead was good enough.</p>
        <p>''After so many close calls,'' she said, ''I'm going to cherish this one for a long time.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
