<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hyundai Group Founder to Sell 6.1% Stake in Auto Company</title>
    <meta content="14AUTO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hyundai Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hyundai Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Len, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung Ju Yung</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2D9133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hyundai Group Founder to Sell 6.1% Stake in Auto Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL LEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Len, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hyundai Group says founder Chung Ju Yung will sell 6.1 percent stake in Hyundai Motor Co by end of year, ending months of defiance of government demands for reorganization and setting stage for Hyundai Motor to be spun off (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hyundai Group, South Korea's largest business group, said today that its founder, Chung Ju Yung, would sell a 6.1 percent stake in the Hyundai Motor Company by the end of the year, ending months of defiance of government demands for reorganization.</p>
        <p>The 85-year-old founder will cut his stake in Hyundai Motor to 3 percent from 9.1 percent, which is expected to raise about 216 billion won ($193.8 million), according to Kim Jae Soo, head of the Hyundai Group's corporate reorganization committee. Hyundai plans to use the money to buy three-year corporate bonds issued by the ailing Hyundai Engineering and Construction Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Hyundai Group, South Korea's largest business group, said today that its founder, Chung Ju Yung, would sell a 6.1 percent stake in the Hyundai Motor Company by the end of the year, ending months of defiance of government demands for reorganization.</p>
        <p>The 85-year-old founder will cut his stake in Hyundai Motor to 3 percent from 9.1 percent, which is expected to raise about 216 billion won ($193.8 million), according to Kim Jae Soo, head of the Hyundai Group's corporate reorganization committee. Hyundai plans to use the money to buy three-year corporate bonds issued by the ailing Hyundai Engineering and Construction Company.</p>
        <p>''We sincerely apologize for causing concerns to the people and shareholders,'' Mr. Kim said at a news conference. ''We will faithfully continue restructuring efforts to regain market trust.''</p>
        <p>The sale of the founder's stake sets the stage for Hyundai Motor to be spun off from the Hyundai Group, a crucial step in efforts to reorganize the huge business group while easing cash shortages at Hyundai Engineering and Construction, Mr. Kim said.</p>
        <p>The construction affiliate, South Korea's largest builder, owes creditors 5.4 trillion won ($4.8 billion) and has had severe difficulty in repaying its debts since May, setting off alarms that both the group and the nation's economy were in danger of another crisis.</p>
        <p>One of the characteristics of South Korean conglomerates has been the complex network of financing and loan arrangements among affiliates, which forced healthy companies to prop up the struggling units of the same business group. The government has been trying to untangle this complicated web. One of the most effective methods has been to sever the control wielded by the founders of the conglomerates and allow individual units to be run by professional managers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim added that Chung Mong Koo, the chairman of Hyundai Motor, would be forced to step down as part of the agreement. With the acceptance of a $167 million emergency loan from creditor banks in May, Chung Ju Yung ordered his sons, Mong Koo and Mong Hun, to give up their positions as the heads of several affiliates. While Mong Hun relinquished his control of the electronics affiliates, Mong Koo has refused to obey the order.</p>
        <p>Hyundai Motor officials could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim said Hyundai would not allow Chung Mong Koo to acquire his father's 6.1 percent stake.</p>
        <p>Korea Exchange Bank, one of Hyundai's main creditors, welcomed the announcement. ''The plan announced today will fundamentally resolve the liquidity problem at Hyundai Engineering and Construction,'' said Kim Kyong Rim, head of Korea Exchange Bank.</p>
        <p>Hyundai said it would also sell stock and real estate worth $4.9 billion, sell all or part of the Hyundai Elevator Company and focus on core businesses, including car making, shipbuilding and electronics.</p>
        <p>However, contrary to demands by creditor banks, the conglomerate decided to keep several high-level executives, who have demonstrated their loyalty to the founding family over decades, even at the cost of incurring losses to investors. Only Hyundai's board has the authority to oust them.</p>
        <p>''The problem will be whether these loyal executives would be able to discard old habits,'' said Yon Kang Heum, professor of international finance at Yonsei University. ''With major shareholders wielding the most power, it may take a consolidated effort by minority shareholders to oust these executives.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
