<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK: Snap! Kiss That Niche Market Goodbye; Nurtured by TV, Black Comics Are Breaking Boundaries at the Box Office</title>
    <meta content="14NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Box Office</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0DA133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK: Snap! Kiss That Niche Market Goodbye; Nurtured by TV, Black Comics Are Breaking Boundaries at the Box Office</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell Critic's Notebook article says huge box office success of recent spate of black-themed movies, particularly comedies, is evidence that genre is broadening its appeal to the young, white constituency that studios are always aiming for; says new audience, for which hip-hop is simply part of its grammar, is demolishing the ceiling for black movies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The slogan for the remake of 'Shaft'' -- ''Still the man'' -- turned out to be more than an idle boast. The picture topped the box-office charts in its first week of release, coming in at $21 million. ''Shaft'' was preceded by ''Big Momma's House,'' the Martin Lawrence comedy, which made $25 million its first week. Both were followed by ''Scary Movie,'' directed by Keenen Ivory Wayans, which hosed its competition with $54 million, the biggest opening ever for an R-rated movie. Then ''Nutty Professor II'' opened at $42 million, the largest first-weekend take for an Eddie Murphy movie.</p>
        <p>That all four topped the $15 million ceiling said by the studios to be the limit for black-themed movies means they are no longer just for a niche market; four times isn't just a fluke. Next up is ''The Original Kings of Comedy,'' a concert film featuring the stand-up comics Steve Harvey, D. L. Hughley, Cedric the Entertainer and Bernie Mac; it opens on Friday, and it will be interesting to see if it continues the winning streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The slogan for the remake of 'Shaft'' -- ''Still the man'' -- turned out to be more than an idle boast. The picture topped the box-office charts in its first week of release, coming in at $21 million. ''Shaft'' was preceded by ''Big Momma's House,'' the Martin Lawrence comedy, which made $25 million its first week. Both were followed by ''Scary Movie,'' directed by Keenen Ivory Wayans, which hosed its competition with $54 million, the biggest opening ever for an R-rated movie. Then ''Nutty Professor II'' opened at $42 million, the largest first-weekend take for an Eddie Murphy movie.</p>
        <p>That all four topped the $15 million ceiling said by the studios to be the limit for black-themed movies means they are no longer just for a niche market; four times isn't just a fluke. Next up is ''The Original Kings of Comedy,'' a concert film featuring the stand-up comics Steve Harvey, D. L. Hughley, Cedric the Entertainer and Bernie Mac; it opens on Friday, and it will be interesting to see if it continues the winning streak.</p>
        <p>This spate of black films may be the biggest sign yet of a new era. At the same time that young white kids -- 'N Sync, Britney Spears and Eminem -- are tearing up the pop charts by appropriating hip-hop and soul, black-themed movies have made a run at the audiences that are buying that music. In last year's ''Office Space,'' by the writer-director Mike Judge, the creative force behind ''Beavis and Butt-head'' and ''King of the Hill,'' a young, white software engineer drives along and raps furiously to a gangsta tune; shamefaced, he lowers the volume when he sees a black man walking within earshot. (I noticed the sea change in 1992 during a live call-in show on MTV during the Los Angeles riot, when Chuck D of Public Enemy took questions. Not a single call came from a black viewer; there was no ''Fear of a Black Planet'' among MTV viewers, many of whom probably had the album, and it made evident the fact that rap had a large white fan base.)</p>
        <p>The mainstream appetite for such material has been stimulated by television, whose young, white constituency -- the glowing red center of the target demographic that studios are always aiming for -- has been steadily growing. Mr. Murphy, Mr. Wayans and Mr. Lawrence fought their way up on the small screen, where they initially caused a stir.</p>
        <p>The new audience, for which hip-hop is simply a part of its grammar, has demolished the ceiling for black movies. John Singleton, who directed the remake of ''Shaft'' for Paramount, has said the reason MGM didn't put it into production was because that studio had no faith that there was an audience for it; apparently MGM is much choosier than it was in 1971 when the original ''Shaft'' saved it from bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>The financial glory of these films -- ''Scary Movie'' is the first by a black director to make $100 million -- proves that African-American talent has planted a flag right in the middle of the mainstream. Will Smith's three hits (he even brought viewers out for ''Wild, Wild West'') can no longer be shrugged off as an aberration, an exception that proves the rule.</p>
        <p>The groundswell probably got going 10 years ago, when ''In Living Color,'' the sketch comedy show of which Mr. Wayans was creator and host, made its debut on the Fox network. ''In Living Color'' provided a forum for thoughts generally voiced by black comics only in nightclubs. (That nightclub feel later became available when ''Def Comedy Jam,'' the all-the-way-live and raw stand-up comic showcase, ran on HBO and provided a home for Mr. Lawrence, Cedric the Entertainer, Mr. Hughley and Mr. Mac, among others.)</p>
        <p>''In Living Color'' limned the anger that many African-Americans felt while sitting through ''Driving Miss Daisy'' -- the throwback foot-shuffling melodrama that was officially certified with Oscars -- in a sketch where the chauffeur turned the tables on his demanding charge. ''In Living Color'' had a killer instinct in playing up a subject -- race comedy from the African-American perspective -- and folding in shrewd and swift references that had been given short shrift on network television.</p>
        <p>The show displayed its first-strike capability in pieces like ''The Wrath of Farrakhan,'' a ''Star Trek'' parody that blew up into something much bigger: Mr. Wayans's brother Damon was Farrakhan, the nemesis of a hammy, ineffectual Captain Kirk, played by Jim Carrey. (''In Living Color'' was the offshoot of the 1987 black culture film comedy ''Hollywood Shuffle,'' which was directed by its star, Robert Townsend, and written by Mr. Townsend and Mr. Wayans. The projects that Mr. Townsend later produced for television -- a short-lived sketch show ''Townsend Television'' and ''The Parent Hood'' -- were as gentle and optimistic as their star. The Wayans brothers' output is considerably more coldblooded.)</p>
        <p>During the series's four-year run -- it stalled out creatively after Mr. Wayans disagreed with Fox over the direction of the show and left, and was canceled soon after -- it was the home of more future movie stars than ''Saturday Night Live'' in the same period. Jamie Foxx was a cast member, and Jennifer Lopez bounced to the bumping segue as a Fly Girl, with moves choreographed by Rosie Perez. Mr. Carrey, who was bypassed when he auditioned for ''Saturday Night Live'' in the late 80's, got noticed on ''In Living Color'' and made ''Ace Ventura, Pet Detective,'' the stealth comedy that came from nowhere to crush its competition.</p>
        <p>The series often seemed like a Triple A training camp for the Wayans family, though they proved to be up to the challenge.</p>
        <p>Damon, with his heavy-lidded and placid face, took center stage in sketches, playing the surly convict who tossed off overripe malapropisms -- ''Allow me to flatulate my liquids,'' he would snarl, pleased with himself. Or Antoine, one of the soi-disant movie critics of the recurring ''Men on Film'' sketch, who happily meowed the virtues of ''big sweaty mens'' in a gay parody of thumbs-up, thumbs-down critique.</p>
        <p>The Wayans brothers Shawn and Marlon are the featured players in ''Scary Movie'' and co-writers of its script. (They're very canny about the branding of their surname; the title of their WB sitcom, ''The Wayans Brothers,'' plays on the jokey nepotism by treating the family name as if it were the most important part of their resumes.) The frenetic and scattershot film is in the tradition of attention-deficit comedies like ''Kentucky Fried Movie.''</p>
        <p>The picture has moments good enough to have been sketches on ''In Living Color'' in its heyday: at a movie theater showing ''Shakespeare in Love,'' a young African-American woman (Regina Hall) who prattles on her cell phone to her homey (''Brad Pitt's girlfriend is a freak!'') and eats food that's as loud as she is, is attacked first by the masked killer and finally by the theater audience.</p>
        <p>The success of ''Scary Movie'' is likely to stir the inevitable sequels and rip-offs that followed in the wake of ''Scream.'' That kind of reflexive moviemaking helped kill off the small renaissance of black film in the 1990's, a movement that included ''Boyz N the Hood,'' ''Straight Outta Brooklyn,'' ''South-Central'' and ''Menace II Society.'' The same film was getting made over and over.</p>
        <p>Black coming-of-age movies of that period took themselves too seriously; the melancholy note they sounded was unrelieved and sentimental. In real life, rappers displayed a gallows humor and short temper that those movies were never allowed to exploit. And after all the pathos had been wrung out of the genre, it was as if the urban experience had been all used up, because no one wanted to see those pictures anymore.</p>
        <p>The plea for understanding had a callow, well-meaning earnestness, which the Wayanses parodied in 1996's ''Don't Be a Menace to South-Central While Drinking Your Juice in the Hood.'' (This was a better sketch idea than a film; the title does all the work.) Black films about adult concerns, however, like ''To Sleep With Anger'' (1990) -- in which Danny Glover uses his soothing, honeyed voice for less than altruistic reasons -- lacked the easy sell of the other films.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately comedy is still the genre where black movies can score most. Even in ''Shaft,'' Samuel L. Jackson's black-avenger oppressiveness is so self-conscious that he might as well wink at the camera as he hauls his magnificence around. The laughs undercut the crude vigilantism in the current remake. The scene in which Shaft pulls a pistol on a drug dealer and beats him on the streets is troubling, but at least he has already quit the police force.</p>
        <p>It's far more insidious when, while still a cop, Shaft punches a suspect in front of a crowd and television cameras. That is meant to be a bravura gesture, but it debases the worldliness and aplomb that Shaft is meant to represent; he's supposed to be smarter than the Dirty Harrys who would beat the sweat off a criminal.</p>
        <p>Now the comics who have moved from television to film are starting to act like men. The maturity that Mr. Murphy is showing as an actor means he may be ready to ease into much more serious work. In ''Bowfinger'' he was Jif, the shy and eager-to-please brother of a megalomaniac movie star (he also played Kit, the paranoid brother, without the makeup he used in ''Professor''), and the character was so vulnerable it could have been painful. Jif's physical discomfort branded him a needy loner, more pathetic than the Julius Kelp that Jerry Lewis played in the original ''Nutty Professor'' and to whom Jif seems a loving tribute. Mr. Murphy has grown up without losing his enthusiasm for comedy.</p>
        <p>He was so poised and confident in ''48 Hrs.'' that it's easy to forget he was only 20 when he walked away with the picture and held his own against Nick Nolte, who made the mistake of trying to give his underwritten character some psychological depth. Mr. Murphy was so accomplished and appealing an entertainer that he could laugh at his own jokes and have the audience laugh along with him.</p>
        <p>He has also learned from his mistakes, and some of them, like ''Harlem Nights,'' cost him dearly. The vulgar display of egotism in that film -- its biggest laughs came at the number of times his name appeared in the credits -- showed how isolated he had become. Mr. Murphy's cockiness has burned away; he has the finesse of a grown-up and isn't worried about being upstaged anymore. Once he would look another performer in the eye only when a scene was being stolen; he is tickled and stunned by Bronson Pinchot's effrontery in purloining their scene together in ''Beverly Hills Cop.''</p>
        <p>Parts of ''Nutty Professor II'' show that Mr. Murphy is ready for a comedy with feeling. And the audiences that grew up with him -- and with Mr. Lawrence and the Wayanses -- could move along into that next phase without a hint of fuss. After all, this is the same audience that rented the ghetto stoner comedy ''Friday'' in droves and made a movie star of Chris Tucker; they followed him from Blockbuster and into movie theaters.</p>
        <p>It is obvious that these performers can attract the most desirable mainstream audiences with less demanding fare. These kids have matured with them, as well as the baby African-American comics Kenan and Kel on Nickelodeon. Film grosses indicate that this crowd feels that hip-hop culture belongs to them; it's in the air, part of the way they express themselves. That interest transcends race and can be translated into something bigger.</p>
        <p>Maybe the time is ripe for an alliance something along the lines of First Artists, the production company that the 60's stars Paul Newman, Barbra Streisand, Steve McQueen and Sidney Poitier created so they could make the movies they wanted. They were so powerful that no one could say no to them. (Sadly, First Artists fell into chaos, with bruised egos leading to the collapse of the company.)</p>
        <p>The most remarkable aspect of the black film renaissance is that the major television networks have totally missed the point. It was television that nurtured the audience that grew up with this welt of actors, writers and directors and trailed happily after them into the movies. It's unbelievable that while these pictures have made a mark at the box office, there are no television series capitalizing on that interest.</p>
        <p>After all the noise last summer, when the N.A.A.C.P. announced a campaign to press for more diversity on television, and the networks vowed to make changes, the prime-time schedules still look as white as a box of long-grain rice. The networks deserve to have viewers fleeing their bland fare in droves.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
