<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hefners' Record of Donations Reflects Their Liberal Ideology</title>
    <meta content="Y14PLA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE MONEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Playboy (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayne, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanchez, Loretta (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hefner, Hugh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hefner, Christie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DC103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hefners' Record of Donations Reflects Their Liberal Ideology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wayne, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on controversy stemming from plans by Democratic Repr Loretta Sanchez to stage fund-raiser at Playboy Mansion; controversy has drawn attention to donations of Playboy publisher Hugh Hefner and daughter Christie to coffers of Democratic Party over years that reflect their liberal ideology (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By most measures, Hugh Hefner and his daughter, Christie, are hardly the largest donors to the Democratic Party. But this week, as a controversy swirled around the use of the Playboy Mansion for a Hispanic fund-raiser, they became, for a moment, among the most visible.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Mr. Hefner, the founder and editor in chief of Playboy Enterprises, and Ms. Hefner, the company's chief executive, have given about $95,000 to Democratic candidates and committees, with a large portion of their donations going to female candidates and to liberals -- and at least $8,000 going to the Clinton and Gore campaigns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By most measures, Hugh Hefner and his daughter, Christie, are hardly the largest donors to the Democratic Party. But this week, as a controversy swirled around the use of the Playboy Mansion for a Hispanic fund-raiser, they became, for a moment, among the most visible.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Mr. Hefner, the founder and editor in chief of Playboy Enterprises, and Ms. Hefner, the company's chief executive, have given about $95,000 to Democratic candidates and committees, with a large portion of their donations going to female candidates and to liberals -- and at least $8,000 going to the Clinton and Gore campaigns.</p>
        <p>What is striking about the Hefners' contributions is how personal, consistent and targeted they are, reflecting mainly the Hefners' socially liberal ideology. Their publishing empire, which had sales of $348 million last year, has no political action committee, nor does it make the large, unregulated soft-dollar donations that many corporations do to gain political access in Washington. Few Playboy executives besides the Hefners give much money. And, if they do, it is not always to Democrats -- Libertarian candidates, too, have received money from Playboy employees.</p>
        <p>Yet the Hefners' brand of quiet and personal giving drew attention when the the Democratic National Committee pressured Representative Loretta Sanchez of California to move a fund-raiser for Hispanic candidates from the Playboy Mansion, fearing it would portray the wrong image for a party trying to distance itself from President Clinton's personal scandals.</p>
        <p>Female, feisty and Hispanic, Ms. Sanchez is exactly the kind of candidate the Hefners support. Mr. Hefner has given Ms. Sanchez $3,000, starting with a $1,000 donation when she was the underdog in her first race, in which she unseated the conservative incumbent, Robert K. Dornan.</p>
        <p>As givers, father and daughter are about equal; Mr. Hefner has given Democratic candidates about $43,000 since 1992 and Ms. Hefner has given them about $51,000. But what is most consistent is the pattern of giving, especially from Ms. Hefner, who has largely donated to to Democratic women and related committees. She is a major donor to Emily's List ($11,500), which raises money for Democratic women and has given to  Voters for Choice/Friends of Family Planning ($7,000), Woman Unite 2000 ($2,500) and PAC for Change ($1,000). Democratic women running for the House or Senate who have received contributions from Ms. Hefner include Hillary Rodham Clinton, Lynn H. Yaekel and Dianne Feinstein. Men who have received contributions from Ms. Hefner include Charles E. Schumer, Paul E. Tsongas and Charles S. Robb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hefner has a more mainstream approach to giving, primarily making large contributions to eading Democratic committees -- $20,000 in 1998 and $5,000 in 1996 to the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, $5,000 this year and $5,000 in 1998 to the Democratic National Committee and $5,000 to Leadership 98, Vice President Al Gore's leadership PAC, along with $1,000 to Gore 2000 in 1999.</p>
        <p>Except for Ms. Sanchez, who has received three four-figure donations from Mr. Hefner, he has not given directly to candidates other than Mr. Gore and Mr. Clinton. Mr. Hefner has, however, allowed the Playboy Mansion to be used for political fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>Scott Harshbarger, president of Common Cause, a nonprofit advocacy group, said the Hefners were ideologically motivated donors who were  being ''tainted unfairly'' by the Sanchez episode.</p>
        <p>''Many people who give do so because they believe in the cause or they believe in the candidate,'' Mr. Harshbarger said, ''but they get tainted in the same way as people who are giving for less noble reasons of gaining access and influence.''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE MONEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
