<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Park Arrives With Victory At the Glen</title>
    <meta content="14AUTO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Crossing (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Park, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DD103FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Park Arrives With Victory At the Glen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>WATKINS GLEN, N.Y., Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steve Park wins Global Crossing auto race at Watkins Glen, NY (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His boss left on an airplane late this afternoon without him. Steve Park would have to find a much slower way to get back to North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I'll hitchhike home if I have to,'' Park said, beaming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His boss left on an airplane late this afternoon without him. Steve Park would have to find a much slower way to get back to North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I'll hitchhike home if I have to,'' Park said, beaming.</p>
        <p>Park, who drives a Chevrolet owned by the fussy Dale Earnhardt Sr., was held up because he finally won his first Nascar Winston Cup race -- and earned the right to pose for photos, spray Champagne and jump up and down on the roof of his car.</p>
        <p>The 32-year-old native of East Northport, N.Y., moved into contention early, held his lead by virtue of a sensational pit stop, then held off a thrilling late charge by the veteran Mark Martin to win the grueling, temper-testing Global Crossing at the Glen by not much more than a car length.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Park received a thumbs-up from Martin and a visit in the victory circle from Earnhardt, for whom Park has driven for nearly three seasons.</p>
        <p>This was the same racetrack at which Earnhardt first made note of Park's driving talent a few years ago. Now, after 77 races, an accident that cost him half the 1998 season and some shuffling of his crew, Park had his first victory. He felt he had earned it.</p>
        <p>''A young guy like me is not used to the pressure of holding off a Mark Martin to win a race,'' Park said.</p>
        <p>This was an exasperating day for almost everyone but Park. Jeff Gordon, who had won a record six straight Winston Cup races on road courses, including the last three here, collided with Tony Stewart on the second of 90 laps and quickly fell from contention. Gordon finished 23rd.</p>
        <p>When Gordon pulled his mangled car next to Stewart's mangled car after the race, Stewart summoned him over, and the two drivers swapped accusations as if they were still banging into each other on the track.</p>
        <p>Stewart, pointing a finger and lacing each sentence with profanity, accused Gordon of reneging on his promise to avoid an accident early in the race.</p>
        <p>''You should practice what you preach,'' Stewart said.</p>
        <p>Later, Gordon said: ''I made a clean move, and I don't think he wanted me to pass him. Maybe I was trying to go too hard too early. But I think there could have been a little bit more consideration there.''</p>
        <p>Earnhardt. lost control of his Chevrolet and spun into the Styrofoam-lined fence on Lap 2. It was a costly accident for Earnhardt, who had been hoping to win his eighth Winston Cup championship.</p>
        <p>He finished 25th, with black tape holding the back of his car together, and fell 217 points behind Bobby Labonte, the leader in the points standing. Labonte finished fifth, two spots ahead of Dale Jarrett, and stretched his lead to a season-best 101 points over Jarrett, with 13 races remaining.</p>
        <p>''I thought the car was going to be pretty good today, but we'll just have to forget about it now,'' Earnhardt said.</p>
        <p>Good drivers began to drop out in a hurry. Ron Fellows, the road-course specialist who finished second to Gordon at the Glen last year, moved to 15th from 40th in only 13 laps but abruptly dropped back because of engine trouble.</p>
        <p>''It looks like last year was a lot more difficult than we thought,'' Fellows said. ''It's a shame.''</p>
        <p>Rusty Wallace spun into the gravel next to the track. Jerry Nadeau, after moving to third from 25th to third place, lost use of third gear. Ward Burton fell from the top five after he was penalized because his crew forgot to put all the lug nuts on his tire.</p>
        <p>Park told himself to keep his composure, and he moved up in the pack. He started 18th but was in the top five after 25 laps. He took the lead one-third of the way into the race and gave it up briefly on his last pit stop.</p>
        <p>But what a pit stop it was. His crew needed only 15.4 seconds to refuel his car and change his tires. Labonte's crew needed 17.2 seconds to do the same thing one lap later.</p>
        <p>Park found himself in the lead after everyone in the field had made his final stop, and soon the race boiled down to Park and Martin.</p>
        <p>Martin closed on Park's rear bumper and stayed there, as if his car had a magnet on it. Park said he tried to avoid the temptation to steal peeks in his rearview mirror to see where Martin was.</p>
        <p>Park bobbled twice in the final laps, once when his car appeared to be nudged by Jeff Burton's, but he kept the lead.</p>
        <p>When he crossed the finish line, Park remembered to stick his hand out of the car and wave to the crowd. He forgot to shift, though, and his car protested with a sudden pop. That was about the only thing that went amiss today for Park.</p>
        <p>He was asked after the race if he told his boss, now long gone, that he had won one more race at Watkins Glen than the great Earnhardt had. Park smiled again. The boss is still the boss.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't want to tell Dale Earnhardt anything that he wouldn't want to hear,'' Park said. ''He still signs my paychecks.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
