<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Days of Hope for Seton Hall Recruits</title>
    <meta content="14HALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seton Hall University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffin, Eddie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrett, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toney-El, Marcus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fray, Damion</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6D7133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Days of Hope for Seton Hall Recruits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Seton Hall basketball recruits Eddie Griffin, Andre Barrett, Damion Fray and Marcus Toney-El playing in summer basketball league to prepare for upcoming season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is 10 minutes past 8 o'clock last Wednesday night and all eyes are on the door to the gym at St. Rose's High School in Belmar, N.J. The task for Andre Barrett, Eddie Griffin, Marcus Toney-El and Damion Fray this night is not to lift Seton Hall University toward any basketball championship. It is to save the Jersey Shore Basketball League the embarrassment of pulling people out of the stands to play in a playoff game that was to begin at 8.</p>
        <p>The commissioner and coaches breathe a collective sigh of relief at 8:15 when the four Seton Hall recruits come through the door, having made the journey down the Garden State Parkway together. They put on their uniforms, and, in minutes, Griffin and Toney-El are on the floor for the opening tip, while Barrett is on the bench tightening his laces and Fray settles in to watch, a sprained ankle keeping him on the sideline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is 10 minutes past 8 o'clock last Wednesday night and all eyes are on the door to the gym at St. Rose's High School in Belmar, N.J. The task for Andre Barrett, Eddie Griffin, Marcus Toney-El and Damion Fray this night is not to lift Seton Hall University toward any basketball championship. It is to save the Jersey Shore Basketball League the embarrassment of pulling people out of the stands to play in a playoff game that was to begin at 8.</p>
        <p>The commissioner and coaches breathe a collective sigh of relief at 8:15 when the four Seton Hall recruits come through the door, having made the journey down the Garden State Parkway together. They put on their uniforms, and, in minutes, Griffin and Toney-El are on the floor for the opening tip, while Barrett is on the bench tightening his laces and Fray settles in to watch, a sprained ankle keeping him on the sideline.</p>
        <p>And it takes just minutes to see that it was worth the wait for the fans, who quickly take to the young players flying up and down the floor. Griffin, a 6-foot-9-inch forward from Roman Catholic High School in Philadelphia, posts up Fred Herzog, one of the longtime standouts of the league, a player who graduated from Fordham in 1992, when Griffin was 10, and has played in the Continental Basketball Association and overseas professionally. Griffin takes a dribble and turns, effortlessly rising above Herzog and dropping in a turnaround jump shot. The next time down, Griffin drops in a 3-point shot.</p>
        <p>If Griffin is effortless, Barrett appears out of control, a 5-8 bundle of speed. But the point guard from Rice High School in Manhattan is in control, even if his teammates are not quite up to speed with him yet. Toney-El, from Seton Hall Prep, is almost a cross between Griffin and Barrett. At 6-7, he is able to handle the ball with the skill of a point guard while joining Griffin in swatting away shots inside.</p>
        <p>Their team, the Allenhurst Barbers, races to a 32-22 lead at the end of the first quarter. And the Seton Hall fans who have come to see a preview of what is to come when the best recruiting class in the school's history takes the floor in the fall are almost giddy, pumping their fists along with the ebullient Toney-El.</p>
        <p>But slowly, the opposition, RKE Athletic, a team made up of players who come less heralded but with far more experience, grinds away, tying the score by halftime and then opening leads of nearly 20 points in the second half before settling for a 126-122 victory that ends the summer league season for the Seton Hall recruits.</p>
        <p>''It just helps us play together as a team,'' Barrett said afterward. ''Playing in this league, playing in camps together, we get to know each other much better. It's going to be a great start for us.''</p>
        <p>Even in defeat, the players had accomplished something that began when Toney-El and Barrett were in seventh grade and found each other in a summer camp. While other teams take time to mix personalities and skills, Seton Hall Coach Tommy Amaker, while having much to teach these young charges, will not have to waste time with introductions. These four recruited one another as much as they were recruited by the school.</p>
        <p>''I met Andre the summer of my seventh-grade year,'' said Toney-El, the most vocal of the four. ''We met at the UMass basketball camp. He was on the team with one of my high school teammates, Mark Curry. I remember thinking, 'Who is this little kid doing all this stuff?' Then I learned who it was and since then we've been playing in tournaments together.</p>
        <p>''Then, Eddie, I met during the summer of my junior year. I went to see him play once and then he came to see me, and then we ended up on the same A.A.U. team. Then we all saw Damion at the Five-Star Camp and we all agreed, he was the one for the final scholarship at Seton Hall. He liked what he saw and we made a bond.''</p>
        <p>Griffin, who finished with 37 points and 21 rebounds in that playoff finale, added: ''I think it was me and Marcus that played together in A.A.U. and liked how we played together. Then I played with Andre in the A.B.C.D. Camp and he was the best point guard I'd ever played with. Marcus and I had already decided we wanted to go together and I said, 'Andre is the guy I want to go to school with.' It was like we recruited each other.''</p>
        <p>Griffin, Barrett and Fray are already on campus at Seton Hall, and Toney-El is a short ride away, still at home during the summer. Just like Wednesday night, when they tumbled into the gym together, their days are spent getting acquainted with their new hometown. ''Marcus is the leader off the court,'' said Fray, who attended Walt Whitman High in Huntington Station, N.Y. ''He knows the area and he's a funny guy. We go and eat together probably every night. We do everything together.''</p>
        <p>Toney-El added: ''I'm down for whatever. I like adventures. You might catch Andre sleeping, Eddie just laying around, Damion on the phone. Then I come over and it's like: 'Let's go do something. Let's get out.' We go to the movies, go eat, or just chill. I'm just getting them used to Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Their willingness to learn is what Amaker is counting on.</p>
        <p>''I went down and saw them in July,'' he said. ''I probably saw them on their worst night, and that was good because we're not evaluating them. We know who they are. But I wanted to see how they handle the speed bumps. The main thing is to give them a chance to grow, to be a part of something. We believe they're all willing to fit in, and that's so important. It's important for them to realize that we have a nucleus coming back from a team that went to the Sweet 16. These kids all played on successful teams that were bigger than they were, and we think they'll fit in together here.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
