<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Floridians Take Grand National Team Title</title>
    <meta content="14CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000816T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DA133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Floridians Take Grand National Team Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on Florida's defeat of California to capture Grand National Team title at American Contract Bridge League's Summer Nationals; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a battle of world champions, Florida defeated California to capture the Grand National Team title at the American Contract Bridge League's Summer Nationals here on Saturday night. The Floridians were Jeff Meckstroth, Eric Rodwell and Robert Levin, whose many honors include the World Bridge Federation's Bermuda Bowl, as well as Michael Seamon and Joseph Shay.</p>
        <p>They repeated their success last year in San Antonio, winning the final by 68 against the Californians, Chip Martel, Lew Stansby and Peter Weichsel, who have also won the Bermuda Bowl, plus Ron Smith, Kyle Larsen and Rose Johnson Meltzer. The event began nine months ago at grass-roots level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a battle of world champions, Florida defeated California to capture the Grand National Team title at the American Contract Bridge League's Summer Nationals here on Saturday night. The Floridians were Jeff Meckstroth, Eric Rodwell and Robert Levin, whose many honors include the World Bridge Federation's Bermuda Bowl, as well as Michael Seamon and Joseph Shay.</p>
        <p>They repeated their success last year in San Antonio, winning the final by 68 against the Californians, Chip Martel, Lew Stansby and Peter Weichsel, who have also won the Bermuda Bowl, plus Ron Smith, Kyle Larsen and Rose Johnson Meltzer. The event began nine months ago at grass-roots level.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal, the last of the 64-deal match, demonstrates the concentration and effort that top players can summon at the end of a tiring day. Levin and Seamon were East and West, defending four hearts after East had opened the bidding with one club.</p>
        <p>A routine opening lead of a club would have allowed the contract to succeed, but West diagnosed the possibility of spade ruffs in the dummy and gave the defense a chance by leading a trump. South won in his hand and played three diamond winners, discarding a club from his hand. He then led the singleton spade, and Levin resisted the temptation to put up a winner. Seeing the importance of allowing his partner to win, he played low and was happy when West produced the queen. A second trump lead duly hit the table, and South won in this position:</p>
        <p>Diagram</p>
        <p>South did the best he could by leading the spade 10 and discarding a club from the dummy. Levin won with the king and administered the coup de grace by underleading his top clubs. Seamon won with the queen and led his last trump.</p>
        <p>South had no way to avoid the loss of a fourth trick for down one and a loss of 10 imps. The game succeeded easily in the replay, where North was the declarer in four hearts, and East led the spade king. Levin and Seamon now have a candidate for the International Bridge Press Association's Defense of the Year Award.</p>
        <p>The first world charity game, organized by the World Bridge Federation, will be played tomorrow and Wednesday evenings. These are the New York region locations:</p>
        <p>Manhattan: Culbertson, 24 Fifth Avenue</p>
        <p>Honors, 115 East 57th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan, 27 West 72nd Street</p>
        <p>Long Island: FrankLin, 340 Dogwood Avenue, Franklin Square</p>
        <p>Jack and Carol (tonight only), 1 Norwood Avenue, Malverne</p>
        <p>Smithtown, 738 Smithtown Bypass, Smithtown</p>
        <p>Westchester: Bridge Deck, 313 Central Avenue, Scarsdale</p>
        <p>New Jersey: Essex, (tonight only) 95 West Mount Pleasant Avenue, Livingston</p>
        <p>Glen Rock, 230 West Passaic Street, Maywood</p>
        <p>Plaza, Prospect and Eagle Rock Avenue, West Orange</p>
        <p>BRIDGE  Correction:  August 16, 2000, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, the Bridge column on Monday misstated the dates for the first world charity game organized by the World Bridge Federation. It is Aug. 22 and 23, not this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 16, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the Bridge column on Monday misstated the dates for the first world charity game organized by the World Bridge Federation. It is Aug. 22 and 23, not this week.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
