<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sampras Makes Early Exit Again in Paris</title>
    <meta content="30TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philippoussis, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampras, Pete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D9163CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sampras Makes Early Exit Again in Paris</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Philippoussis defeats Pete Sampras in opening round of French Open tennis tournament; other first round results noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is hardly a surprise to see Pete Sampras bid farewell to the French Open long before the last blow has been struck. At this stage of his otherwise brilliant career, it is only a question of how he will be eliminated, and who will do the eliminating.</p>
        <p>The answers came particularly early this year. They came today on the first day of play, and they came under an ever-changing sky against a younger and more powerful opponent, Mark Philippoussis, who has given him trouble in the past on surfaces much more conducive to Sampras's game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is hardly a surprise to see Pete Sampras bid farewell to the French Open long before the last blow has been struck. At this stage of his otherwise brilliant career, it is only a question of how he will be eliminated, and who will do the eliminating.</p>
        <p>The answers came particularly early this year. They came today on the first day of play, and they came under an ever-changing sky against a younger and more powerful opponent, Mark Philippoussis, who has given him trouble in the past on surfaces much more conducive to Sampras's game.</p>
        <p>But this was European clay, the red and gritty stuff that sticks to Sampras's sneakers and sticks in his craw. And though the second-seeded American performed and served quite well in stretches on the refurbished center court, he did not play well enough when it mattered to avoid another bitter five-set experience in Paris.</p>
        <p>Philippoussis prevailed, 4-6, 7-5, 7-6 (4), 4-6, 8-6, in a match that required 3 hours 39 minutes and ended with Sampras losing his serve at love on a double fault.</p>
        <p>''In the fifth set it comes down to nerves, and he had the better nerve,'' said Sampras, who also lost the second set and the sixth game of the final set on double faults.</p>
        <p>Though Sampras has won 12 Grand Slam singles titles -- tying him for the most ever with Roy Emerson -- he has never advanced past the semifinals at Roland Garros Stadium. He got that far only in 1996, negotiating a brutal draw before running out of resources on a very hot day against the eventual champion, Yevgeny  Kafelnikov. But with Sampras approaching his 29th birthday, that memorable run now looks increasingly like an anomaly. In 1997, he lost to Magnus Norman in the third round. In 1998, he lost to Ramon Delgado in the second round, and last year, he was beaten in the second round by Andrei Medvedev, who went on to reach the final against Sampras's compatriot Andre Agassi.</p>
        <p>All three of Sampras's recent losses came on the Suzanne Lenglen court, one that he dislikes and contends is considerably slower than the other show courts here. But this time, he was beaten on the center court he prefers, and beaten at his own game by a big server who likes to push forward to the net and take risks from the baseline.</p>
        <p>''I felt I had some chances, but Mark, I give him all the credit, he served huge,'' Sampras said after watching 23 aces go by.</p>
        <p>Two other Americans fared better today. First, Meghann Shaughnessy upset the No. 12 women's seeded player, Julie Halard-Decugis of France by 7-5, 6-4. Then Jan-Michael Gambill ousted eighth-seeded Nicolas Kiefer of Germany, 6-3, 7-5, 6-1, although it might have been more satisfying if the clearly off-form Kiefer had not missed most of the last two months because of ankle surgery. But Jennifer Capriati, still struggling since her split from her former coach Harold Solomon, fell to Fabiola Zuluaga of Columbia, 6-3, 7-5.</p>
        <p>Though Sampras holds a 7-3 career edge over Philippoussis, Sampras has lost to him twice in Grand Slam events: the first time in straight sets at the 1996 Australian Open when Philippoussis was still a relative unknown. But if Philippoussis, with his short attention span and penchant for the unforced error, has not managed to succeed consistently on tour, he has clearly improved his ability to handle pressure (not to mention short, low balls). He was the key figure in Australia's Davis Cup victory over France last year on indoor clay, and if not for a serious knee injury that forced him to retire with a one-set lead over Sampras in the Wimbledon quarterfinals last year, he might have eliminated the American there as well.</p>
        <p>''Playing Mark in the first round is certainly a tough draw,'' Sampras said. ''I certainly haven't got the breaks at this event over the years, but one year hopefully I'll get those breaks.</p>
        <p>''In a perfect world, a perfect career, you'd like to win all the majors, do everything in the game. I have a very high bar that I've raised. It kind of would be disappointing if I would not win it, but, you know, life will go on.''</p>
        <p>Martina Hingis would agree and has a great deal more time left to do so. Traditionally, it is the defending champion who opens play on center court at Roland Garros, but this year, the defending champion has retired, which means that Hingis, whom Steffi Graf beat in last year's final, got the honor of walking on court at 11 a.m. with only a few hundred fans in attendance.</p>
        <p>There was not much suspense surrounding the outcome. Hingis had beaten Sabine Appelmans of Belgium in all five of their previous matches, and she beat her again, 6-0, 6-4, in less than an hour.</p>
        <p>But what was in doubt was how the Parisian fans would react to Hingis after her histrionics in last year's final, when she contravened tennis etiquette by crossing the net to question a line call and later lost her composure and served underhand twice out of frustration.</p>
        <p>Though she may yet have some public relations work to do over the next two weeks, the response to Hingis's arrival today was restrained: light applause and a few scattered whistles. Hingis, as usual, is choosing to accentuate the positive.</p>
        <p>''I'm here since Tuesday, and I never had so many people recognize me walking on the streets in regular clothes, never,'' she said. ''So it was real nice.''</p>
        <p>Capriati, visibly heavier than she was during her resurgence from last summer to March of this year, has now lost both her matches without Solomon in her corner, first to Anne-Gaelle Sidot in the opening round at the Italian Open and to Zuluaga today.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
