<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joseph Heller's Valedictory Holds a Mirror to Himself</title>
    <meta content="30KAKU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heller, Joseph (1923-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Portrait of an Artist, as an Old Man (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DD163CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joseph Heller's Valedictory Holds a Mirror to Himself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Joseph Heller's Portrait of an Artist, as an Old Man; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PORTRAIT OF AN ARTIST, AS AN OLD MAN  By Joseph Heller  233 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>Like such embarrassing Hemingway works as ''The Garden of Eden'' and ''True at First Light,'' Joseph Heller's ''Portrait of an Artist, as an Old Man'' is one of those posthumously published books that form a sad coda to a distinguished career. Fans of ''Catch-22'' and ''Something Happened'' can only regret that ''Portrait'' was ever published.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PORTRAIT OF AN ARTIST, AS AN OLD MAN  By Joseph Heller  233 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>Like such embarrassing Hemingway works as ''The Garden of Eden'' and ''True at First Light,'' Joseph Heller's ''Portrait of an Artist, as an Old Man'' is one of those posthumously published books that form a sad coda to a distinguished career. Fans of ''Catch-22'' and ''Something Happened'' can only regret that ''Portrait'' was ever published.</p>
        <p>Completed before Heller's death last December at 76, ''Portrait'' tells the story of an aging novelist named Eugene Pota who is having difficulty writing another novel. It reads like one of those magazine profiles in which a reporter never manages to get an interview with his subject and so resorts to recounting his own travails in trying to get the story. The entire book consists of Pota's complaints about not being able to write, intercut with outtakes from novels he has decided, for good reason, to abandon.</p>
        <p>Most of these abortive efforts are simple testaments to Pota's failure of imagination. There are weary attempts to rewrite classic works of literature: Tom Sawyer as a would-be novelist, Tom Sawyer as rich yuppie with a law degree from Yale, Gregor Samsa as a Wall Street accountant. Pota contemplates rewriting ''The Iliad'' from the point of view of the Trojans, toys with writing the biography of a human gene as a witness to history and proposes a novel organized as a ''biological map'' of the human body. He has Hera, the Greek goddess, do a monologue about her philandering husband, Zeus; and he has Zeus recount a practical joke he played on Hera.</p>
        <p>There is something perfunctory about each of Pota's efforts, as though he couldn't really be bothered fleshing out his characters or stories. ''Descriptive details of place and character take time, deplete energy, aren't always necessary,'' Heller writes. ''Worst of all, we have never been much good with them. Or much good with intricate plots propelled by swift-paced action.''</p>
        <p>In another chapter he writes of Pota's wife: ''I could develop her easily, but it's much too hard. It's painstaking and time consuming, and Pota was short of patience. The generation of writers after him, and the generation of newer novelists and short story writers following that one are better at it now and have the gusto and the time. Let them do it. They can have it.''</p>
        <p>The skills Heller did possess in abundance at the height of his career are also sorely lacking in this novel. There are few glimpses in ''Portrait'' of his bravura satire or zany, improvisational humor, and while familiar preoccupations surface in this volume, they are addressed with none of Heller's old ferocity and swagger. For instance, the obsession with mortality that animated so many of his books from ''Catch-22'' through ''Closing Time'' lies very much at the heart of this novel, but as filtered through Pota's story it feels less like a terrifying reality or great existential dilemma, than an old man's narcissistic rant against declining book sales and a diminished sex life.</p>
        <p>Pota goes on at tiresome length about wanting to recapture the success of his youth: how he wants to write another best seller that will be ''a natural for the movies,'' how he has a sure-fire title for a novel (''A Sexual Biography of My Wife'') but doesn't want to go through the hassle of actually writing it. Though some of Pota's complaints are vaguely amusing -- he's angry that Nabokov already wrote ''Lolita,'' instead of leaving the field to him -- his remarks too often devolve into rationalization or self pity.</p>
        <p>He writes a dreary story about the unhappy lives of American authors -- how the likes of Mark Twain, Jack London, Bret Harte and Stephen Crane were all beset with financial or medical woes -- and then delivers an equally dreary, listlike speech about the declining years of writers like Hemingway, Tennessee Williams and Truman Capote.</p>
        <p>Pota's own name, the book baldly points out, is an acronym for Portrait of the Artist, and he clearly bears more than a passing resemblance to his creator. Like Heller, he wrote a memoir about ''his childhood and family life in Coney Island and had interwoven segments of his war and life experiences afterward into almost all his novels.'' Like Heller, he achieved fame with a novel based on his service in World War II. And like Heller, he later wrote a novel based on King David. No doubt the reader is also meant to take Pota's difficulties in writing another novel as a kind of comment on the difficulties Heller faced himself: always worrying about repeating himself, always being compared to his younger self.</p>
        <p>There is something sad about Pota's dilemma, -- ''a well-known, aging author'' struggling so painfully ''to close out his career with a crowning achievement, with a laudable bang that would embellish his reputation rather than with a fainthearted whimper.'' Unfortunately it's even sadder that Mr. Heller should cap his own inspired -- and sometimes brilliant -- career with ''Portrait of an Artist, as an Old Man,'' an anticlimactic book that is, at best, a poor imitation of a novel.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
