<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Lose Ordonez for Six Weeks and Then the Game</title>
    <meta content="30METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDE173CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Lose Ordonez for Six Weeks and Then the Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Dodgers defeat New York Mets, 4-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo said it was a play only Rey Ordonez could make. But it was also a risk only Ordonez could take.</p>
        <p>Ordonez, the Mets' shortstop, is expected to miss six weeks after breaking a bone in his left forearm today during the Mets' 4-1 loss to the Los Angeles Dodgers. The infielder/outfielder Melvin Mora will be activated from the disabled list when Ordonez goes on it Tuesday, and Kurt Abbott will probably get the bulk of the starts in Ordonez's absence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo said it was a play only Rey Ordonez could make. But it was also a risk only Ordonez could take.</p>
        <p>Ordonez, the Mets' shortstop, is expected to miss six weeks after breaking a bone in his left forearm today during the Mets' 4-1 loss to the Los Angeles Dodgers. The infielder/outfielder Melvin Mora will be activated from the disabled list when Ordonez goes on it Tuesday, and Kurt Abbott will probably get the bulk of the starts in Ordonez's absence.</p>
        <p>Ordonez sustained a nondisplaced fracture of the left ulna in the first inning, completing the tag on a pickoff play. Al Leiter, who later gave up a grand slam to Shawn Green to account for all the Dodger runs, walked the leadoff batter, F. P. Santangelo, after third baseman Robin Ventura made an error on a foul pop. Before throwing a pitch to the next batter, Leiter threw to first baseman Todd Zeile as Santangelo broke for second.</p>
        <p>But Zeile's throw to second sailed, and Ordonez leaped for the ball with his glove hand outstretched. The three-time Gold Glove shortstop caught it, whirled and, in one motion, swiped a backhanded tag on Santangelo.</p>
        <p>Santangelo's helmet plowed into Ordonez's left arm, and Ordonez fell to the ground in pain. He was examined by team trainers and was able to squeeze his hand into a fist. Ordonez wanted to stay in the game, but when he could not lift his arm to put his glove in position for a catch, it was obvious he could not continue.</p>
        <p>Zeile said he was hoping Ordonez would not attempt to make a tag the way he did; the safer play, Zeile said, would have been to catch the ball, then get back in normal position for a tag that would not have left Ordonez's arm in the path of the sliding runner.</p>
        <p>''I've seen him do it; it's something that he chooses to do,'' Zeile said. ''When I saw it happen today, I thought he was hurt. When I first saw it, I thought that he broke his hand, or he broke his wrist. He was swiping full-speed as the runner's coming in full-speed with the helmet on. I knew there was a lot of impact.''</p>
        <p>The play was classic Ordonez: acrobatic, balletic and, perhaps, a little reckless. Ordonez, who will fly back to New York on Tuesday to meet with Mets doctors, declined to speak with reporters. But Abbott, who replaced him today and went 1 for 4, was amazed at the play.</p>
        <p>''That play was unbelievable,'' Abbott said. ''Just to have the instincts and be able to catch the ball and just totally flip your body around and 180-it and boom -- that was pretty impressive. The outcome of it wasn't too good.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Steve Phillips said the Mets would keep their ''eyes open'' for possible replacements at shortstop from outside the organization, but he said the preference would be to fill the position from within. Phillips did not seem interested in the veteran Kevin Stocker, who was released last week by Tampa Bay, saying he was not sure whether Stocker would be an upgrade over the Mets' potential replacements.</p>
        <p>Besides Abbott -- who has 5 hits in his last 40 at-bats but was encouraged by two of his at-bats today -- Manager Bobby Valentine said he could use Mora and Joe McEwing at shortstop.</p>
        <p>For Leiter, it took only a three-pitch span to ruin his season of perfection. The Mets had won all nine of Leiter's starts before today, and they were tied in the sixth. No Dodger had batted with a runner in scoring position until Santangelo came up with a man on second and one out. That is when Leiter's trouble began.</p>
        <p>Leiter, who thrives by pitching inside, drilled Santangelo in the backside. The Dodger Stadium crowd stirred. One pitch later, Leiter plunked Mark Grudzielanek just above the elbow. The crowd hollered. On Leiter's next pitch, Green rocketed a grand slam over the wall in right-center. The crowd erupted.</p>
        <p>All three pitches were sliders, said Leiter, who had struck out Green on the pitch in the first inning. But with the bases loaded, Leiter said, there was probably a thought in his mind that the pitch should be a strike, and his location just missed.</p>
        <p>''I probably overthrew it a little bit,'' said Leiter, who dropped to 5-1. ''Even though it was on the outer half and was going down, Shawn was looking for it.''</p>
        <p>Green, who became baseball's highest-paid position player when he signed a six-year, $84 million contract after being traded from Toronto last winter, hit his 10th homer of the year and his second grand slam.</p>
        <p>The shot provided more than enough support for the right-hander Chan Ho Park, who held the Mets to two hits over seven shutout innings by changing speeds effectively and throwing his slider for strikes.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored once off the reliever Jeff Shaw in the ninth, but Alfonzo grounded to second with two on to end the game.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>It is only May, but the Dodgers have broken their Los Angeles record for grand slams in a season. The one by SHAWN GREEN was their seventh this year, the most they have hit since moving to the West Coast in 1958. The franchise mark is eight, set by the pennant-winning Brooklyn Dodgers in 1952. . . . Dodgers second baseman MARK GRUDZIELANEK left the game with a contusion on his left elbow. Grudzielanek was hit by a pitch from AL LEITER in the sixth and was removed for a pinch-hitter in the seventh. . . . The Mets are making their third separate visit to California this month as they ping-pong across the country. They started this road trip with three games in San Diego, then went to St. Louis before returning to Southern California.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
