<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y30BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DE173CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: BARAK BACKS PERES -- Shimon Peres, a former prime minister, was endorsed by Prime Minister Ehud Barak to succeed President Ezer Weizman, who is resigning in the wake of a corruption scandal. In a secret ballot in Parliament scheduled for July 31, Mr. Peres, left, who now holds the regional cooperation portfolio in Mr. Barak's cabinet, is expected to face Moshe Katzav of the opposition Likud Party.</p>
        <p>William A. Orme, Jr. (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: LESBIANS' LANDMARK VICTORY -- An Israeli-American lesbian couple won the right here to register as the two mothers of their 4-year-old son, Matan, provoking outrage from the religious right. Nicole Berner-Kadish adopted Matan, the biological son of her partner, Ruti Berner-Kadish, in California. But Israel fought their petition to have Matan recognized as Nicole's child until the High Court, in a groundbreaking ruling for gay couples, said a child may indeed have two mothers.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: BARAK BACKS PERES -- Shimon Peres, a former prime minister, was endorsed by Prime Minister Ehud Barak to succeed President Ezer Weizman, who is resigning in the wake of a corruption scandal. In a secret ballot in Parliament scheduled for July 31, Mr. Peres, left, who now holds the regional cooperation portfolio in Mr. Barak's cabinet, is expected to face Moshe Katzav of the opposition Likud Party.</p>
        <p>William A. Orme, Jr. (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: LESBIANS' LANDMARK VICTORY -- An Israeli-American lesbian couple won the right here to register as the two mothers of their 4-year-old son, Matan, provoking outrage from the religious right. Nicole Berner-Kadish adopted Matan, the biological son of her partner, Ruti Berner-Kadish, in California. But Israel fought their petition to have Matan recognized as Nicole's child until the High Court, in a groundbreaking ruling for gay couples, said a child may indeed have two mothers.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: PLEA ON WALL RULING -- The Justice Ministry said it would ask the Supreme Court to review a ruling last week that permitted women to hold services at the Western Wall while wearing prayer shawls and chanting from the Torah. Asserting that the ruling had changed longstanding tradition at the site, which limits such services to men, the ministry said the women could hold prayers at an adjacent location that would not offend Orthodox worshipers.</p>
        <p>Joel Greenberg (NYT)</p>
        <p>KUWAIT: WOMEN AND THE VOTE -- A court referred to the nation's highest tribunal, the Constitutional Court, the question of whether women should vote and run for office, a decision women's rights activists hailed as a victory. Kuwait's 1962 Constitution gives equal rights to men and women. But an election law bars women from voting or running for office. Activists want the Constitutional Court to make a definitive ruling.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: JOINT GOVERNMENT -- The government that divides authority between the province's Catholic and Protestant political parties has resumed, with Britain formally restoring powers suspended in February. The Irish Republican Army has agreed to open its hidden arms dumps to international inspectors, and the Ulster Unionists, the largest Protestant party, voted by a narrow margin on Saturday to accept that move as reason to return to government with Sinn Fein, the political allies of the I.R.A.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>POLAND: RESIGNATIONS REJECTED -- Prime Minister Jerzy Buzek rejected the resignations of five cabinet ministers, demanding new talks to keep his government from falling and facing elections it would probably lose. The ministers are members of the Freedom Union, the Solidarity-led government's junior coalition partner, which says Mr. Buzek must step down if the alliance is to survive.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: BERIA PLEA TURNED DOWN -- The Supreme Court rejected a request by relatives to posthumously pardon Lavrenty Beria, the reviled chief of the N.K.V.D. who sent millions of people to their deaths under Stalin's dictatorship in the 1930's and 40's. The N.K.V.D. later became the K.G.B. Mr. Beria was executed after Stalin's death in 1953 on trumped-up charges, including rape and espionage.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: REBELS ATTACK -- Chechen rebels have apparently begun a broad offensive against Russian troops, and, by their accounts, killed 40 soldiers in an ambush in the Grozny suburb of Aldi. Russian forces stand accused of conducting a killing and looting rampage in Aldi last February that residents say left at least 80 civilians dead. Russian officials denied rebel casualty reports, but said the situation in Chechnya is ''tense and difficult.''</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: FOX SPURNED -- Vicente Fox, the leading opposition presidential candidate, appeared to abandon attempts to enlist the campaign support of Cuauhtemoc Cardenas, the other major opposition contender who is running a distant third. Mr. Cardenas spurned a request to step down to help defeat the governing party. Mr. Fox called Mr. Cardenas ''a traitor'' to Mexico's democratic movement.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: ELECTION BOARD QUITS -- The directors of the National Electoral Council resigned, said the council's vice president, Eduardo Semtei. Last week the Supreme Court postponed elections for president and thousands of other jobs after the council said it could not ensure an accurate, timely and fair vote count. No new date has been set for the elections.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>HAITI: ARISTIDE PARTY GAINS -- The Lavalas Family Party of former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide has won control of the Senate, according to partial returns from elections on May 21. The returns showed that Lavalas had won at least 14 of the 27 Senate seats. The remaining 13 have not been fully tallied. Lavalas also won 10 of the 30 Chamber of Deputies seats counted so far, and its candidates were leading in the other 20 races.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: EX-PRESIDENT JAILED -- Former President Canaan Banana lost an appeal of his conviction on sexual assault charges and homosexual sex offenses and was ordered to serve a year in jail. Mr. Banana, 64, was convicted last year of 11 counts of sodomy and abusing his power to sexually assault men. Homosexual acts are illegal in Zimbabwe. Mr. Banana contended that the convictions violated privacy rights in the Constitution.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: TAX PROTEST -- As teams of soldiers and revenue officers fanned out in marketplaces seeking to document how much businesses owe in taxes, shopkeepers closed their doors in protest. Only 17,500 of the 2.5 million business owners in Pakistan collect sales tax, the government says.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
