<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Peaceful Death Without Tubes</title>
    <meta content="30TUBE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finocchio, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grady, Denise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alzheimer's</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3D7133DF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Peaceful Death Without Tubes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grady, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phyllis Finocchio dies at home in Queens, cared for by her family through a long battle with Alzheimer's disease; family opted against tube feeding when she could no longer eat, having learned from support groups that dying people who can no longer eat do not suffer from hunger and thirst and can be kept comfortable with ice chips and swabs to moisten the mouth and lips; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a crisp, sunny morning a year ago, in the Queens apartment that had been her home for more than 40 years, death came gently for Phyllis Finocchio. Gazing into her husband's eyes, she squeezed his hand, and then let go of it for the last time.</p>
        <p>''She died very peacefully, the way we wanted it,'' said her daughter, Bettina, who had helped care for her since 1988, when the family first learned that Mrs. Finocchio had Alzheimer's disease. ''And so as a family, we're at peace.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a crisp, sunny morning a year ago, in the Queens apartment that had been her home for more than 40 years, death came gently for Phyllis Finocchio. Gazing into her husband's eyes, she squeezed his hand, and then let go of it for the last time.</p>
        <p>''She died very peacefully, the way we wanted it,'' said her daughter, Bettina, who had helped care for her since 1988, when the family first learned that Mrs. Finocchio had Alzheimer's disease. ''And so as a family, we're at peace.''</p>
        <p>In an era of high-tech medicine, a quiet death like Mrs. Finocchio's may be harder to arrange than one encumbered by tubes and machinery, and attended by strangers.</p>
        <p>After their decision to care for her at home, one of the family's most important and most difficult choices came when Mrs. Finocchio began to have trouble eating, like many people with Alzheimer's. Four million Americans have dementia, and most lose the ability to feed themselves and eventually cannot eat at all, because of difficulty swallowing.</p>
        <p>They begin wasting away, and some doctors and many nursing homes recommend feeding tubes, which are inserted through the nose or through an incision in the abdomen.</p>
        <p>Families are sometimes pressured into consenting because they are told that without a tube, their loved ones will die painfully, from thirst, starvation or choking.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Finocchio learned from the Alzheimer's Association, other medical groups and a hospice program that dying people who can no longer eat do not suffer from hunger and thirst, and can be kept comfortable with ice chips and swabs to moisten the mouth and lips.</p>
        <p>The cessation of eating is often a natural part of the process of dying, and most patients are more comfortable without fluids, which can cause nausea and increased lung secretions. Dehydration, described by one doctor as ''nature's anesthetic'' in dying patients, leads them to lapse into comas and die peacefully.</p>
        <p>By contrast, tube feeding can cause suffering in dementia patients. It has not been proved to prolong their lives, and it can cause diarrhea, bloating and infections. It does not prevent choking, because patients still choke on their own secretions.</p>
        <p>In addition, demented patients often try to yank out the tubes, leading to the patients' being placed in restraints. Most then find the restraints so upsetting that they become agitated and wind up being sedated.</p>
        <p>Ms. Finocchio had seen her mother try to pull out intravenous lines when she was hospitalized, and knew she would pull out a feeding tube.</p>
        <p>The family decided there would be no tube. They fed Mrs. Finocchio when she could no longer feed herself, and froze broth into cubes to help keep her mouth from becoming parched when she had trouble swallowing.</p>
        <p>''This was not a selfish act,'' Ms. Finocchio said. ''It was not an easy way out. It's very painful to watch someone die like that. But we just felt it was the best thing for her. I think she would have wanted it that way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
