<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Condemns Peru Election And Fujimori Rule as Invalid</title>
    <meta content="Y30REA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000531T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peru-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Organization of American States</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toledo, Alejandro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DE173CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Condemns Peru Election And Fujimori Rule as Invalid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US and allies issue stern warnings to Peru that re-election of President Alberto K Fujimori without opposition risks serious harm to country's standing in international community; call handling of election undemocratic and its result illegitimate; election was boycotted by opposition and carried out despite objections from Organization of American States (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States and its allies issued stern warnings to Peru today, saying that the re-election of President Alberto K. Fujimori without opposition risked serious harm to Peru's standing in the international community.</p>
        <p>As President Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright prepared for consultations with their counterparts in Europe and the Americas, United States officials called the handling of the election undemocratic and its result illegitimate. The election was boycotted by the opposition and was carried out despite objections from the Organization of American States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States and its allies issued stern warnings to Peru today, saying that the re-election of President Alberto K. Fujimori without opposition risked serious harm to Peru's standing in the international community.</p>
        <p>As President Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright prepared for consultations with their counterparts in Europe and the Americas, United States officials called the handling of the election undemocratic and its result illegitimate. The election was boycotted by the opposition and was carried out despite objections from the Organization of American States.</p>
        <p>A State Department official called the handling of the voting ''a serious threat to the inter-American system and its commitment to democracy.''</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters, the official said that ''no president emerging from such a flawed process can claim legitimacy'' and that ''we do not see the election as being valid.'' But later, the official said in an interview that the comments were intended as ''guidance'' rather than as a formal statement of United States policy. The official spoke on condition of not being identified. Richard Boucher, the department's top spokesman, was traveling with Dr.  Albright to a meeting in Europe and could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>On Friday, President Clinton said  he regretted Peru's insistence on not delaying the election and added that ''we are consulting with our partners  in the hemisphere and the international community to determine appropriate next steps.''</p>
        <p>The first opportunity for consultations comes in Portugal, where European leaders are meeting this week. Mr. Clinton is leading the United States delegation before going on to Moscow.</p>
        <p>European nations joined in the criticism today.</p>
        <p>In France, the foreign ministry spokeswoman, Anne Gazeau-Secret, said that ''conditions under which the balloting was held were not satisfactory.'' In Spain, Foreign Minister Josep Pique said there had been ''no guarantees of fairness.''</p>
        <p>The Organization of American States is to meet in Canada on Wednesday to hear a report from election observers, who backed out after Mr. Fujimori's government refused to delay the election.</p>
        <p>The election, which brought him his third term, was criticized for numerous irregularities including state support for his campaign and questions about the computerized system for counting votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori said today that the date of the election could not be legally changed, and defended it.</p>
        <p>''This is a result of an election which is just, fair, transparent,'' he said on the CNN program ''Worldview.'' ''And unfortunately we couldn't have these international observers as we wanted to.''</p>
        <p>He said Peru's foreign minister would attend the meeting of American states in Canada to defend the election process.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 31, 2000, Wednesday  An article yesterday about American officials' criticism of the presidential election in Peru on Sunday misstated the site of a report from election observers to the Organization of American States set for today. It is in Washington; the organization is to meet in Canada next week and will also discuss the issue there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 31, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about American officials' criticism of the presidential election in Peru on Sunday misstated the site of a report from election observers to the Organization of American States set for today. It is in Washington; the organization is to meet in Canada next week and will also discuss the issue there.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
