<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>42 Years Later, a Troupe Finds Itself in Oz Again</title>
    <meta content="30PLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Monte</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wizard of Oz, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFD7163CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>42 Years Later, a Troupe Finds Itself in Oz Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONTE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Monte</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at reunion of cast and stage crew of 1958 production of The Wizard of Oz by fifth graders at Public School 100 in Brighton Beach section of Brooklyn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tin Man grew up to be a psychiatrist, and the Scarecrow became a musician. Dorothy works in a boutique. They were fifth graders in 1958, all ponytails and bobby socks and cardigans, when they staged ''The Wizard of Oz.''</p>
        <p>They and 28 classmates had performed the play at Public School 100 in Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, and on the evening of May 17, seven cast members turned out for a reunion almost 42 years to the day. Now in their early 50's, they gathered at Cajun, a New Orleans-style restaurant in Chelsea where one of the owners is Arlene Lichterman, their former teacher and the play's director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Tin Man grew up to be a psychiatrist, and the Scarecrow became a musician. Dorothy works in a boutique. They were fifth graders in 1958, all ponytails and bobby socks and cardigans, when they staged ''The Wizard of Oz.''</p>
        <p>They and 28 classmates had performed the play at Public School 100 in Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, and on the evening of May 17, seven cast members turned out for a reunion almost 42 years to the day. Now in their early 50's, they gathered at Cajun, a New Orleans-style restaurant in Chelsea where one of the owners is Arlene Lichterman, their former teacher and the play's director.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lichterman, now retired, was visibly moved by the assembly of former pupils. ''On the last day of school, I stood at the door and kissed every one of these students with tears in my eyes,'' she said.</p>
        <p>There was little crying at the reunion. Instead, there was plenty of laughter and hugs and poring over old photos and reminders of things past. There was the typical catching up: who married whom, what professions they entered, how their children were faring. But mostly, Oz took center stage; in this case, the small one in the back of Cajun, which had a piano.</p>
        <p>There were no costumes, but Mitch Margo, the Scarecrow, played the piano, and the old classmates did a medley, including: ''We're Off to See the Wizard,'' ''If I Only Had a Heart,'' ''Ding-Dong! The Witch Is Dead'' and ''Over the Rainbow.''</p>
        <p>At 12, Mr. Margo became the only professional performer in the group. He joined the Tokens, a singing group best remembered for their hit, ''The Lion Sleeps Tonight.'' A musician who plays guitar, keyboard, bass and drums, Mr. Margo flew in from Los Angeles for the reunion.</p>
        <p>He had fond memories of two cast members in particular. He told Helen Zegerman Schwimmer (Glinda the Good Witch): ''You were my first crush.'' Then he gazed at Nancy Kornspan Aufrichtig (Dorothy) and said: ''And you were my first kiss.'' The three laughed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Margo's mother, Ruth, 80, flew in from Fort Lauderdale, Fla., for the reunion. She designed the sets for the school musical. ''She wasn't paid a cent,'' said Ms. Lichterman, who used her for subsequent plays. ''All voluntary.''</p>
        <p>The reunion resulted from a meeting between Ms. Schwimmer and Ms. Lichterman.</p>
        <p>Last year, Ms. Schwimmer sat on the board of the Brooklyn College Alumni Association. She went to many meetings, unaware of the last name of the woman sitting next to her. It was Ms. Lichterman.</p>
        <p>Once, when Ms. Schwimmer read the minutes, she came across the name. She had thought there was something familiar about the woman, and at the end of the meeting, she asked her whether she had ever taught at P.S. 100. She said she had.</p>
        <p>The next meeting, Ms. Lichterman brought pictures, Ms. Schwimmer recalled, ''and I said wouldn't it be great if we had a reunion.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schwimmer had written the script for the class's production of ''Oz.'' Now a freelance writer and publicist, she said writing the script inspired her choice of career.</p>
        <p>She set about finding cast members, using telephone directories, the Internet, friends and friends of friends. Several years ago, she had run into Ms. Aufrichtig, a fashion coordinator at a Long Island boutique, and exchanged numbers.</p>
        <p>She had also encountered Saul Gorman (the Tin Man) at a class reunion at Brooklyn College, so she had his number as well. Mr. Gorman, a psychiatrist who lives in Marlboro, N.J., had what Ms. Lichterman considered a great voice.</p>
        <p>''I watched him in the third grade sing 'The 12 Days of Christmas,' '' Ms. Lichterman said. ''I said, 'I can't wait to get him and that class.' They've all gone on to great things. That makes it all worthwhile.''</p>
        <p>One of the brightest classes in the school at the time, the yellow-brick-road crew had been kept together from kindergarten through eighth grade. ''There's a sense of family,'' Ms. Aufrichtig said.</p>
        <p>Two others at the reunion had gone on to become teachers. Estelle Shavitz Ross (a munchkin), described in the reunion journal as the girl who had the most beautiful blue eyes, is teaching a prekindergarten class at P.S. 153 in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn. And Perry Blonder (a palace guard) teaches kindergarten through second grade at a Crown Heights elementary school.</p>
        <p>''This is bizarre to me,'' he said, appearing a little overwhelmed. He found out that for years he has lived just a block away from Ms. Schwimmer in Manhattan Beach, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Maxine Levy Roseman (a munchkin) works in finance and lives in Marlboro, N.J. ''It was almost like a professional production,'' she said. ''We poured our hearts and souls into it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
