<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Camera in a Pill' Views Digestive Tract</title>
    <meta content="30PILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Digestive Tract</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Light-Emitting Diodes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Given Imaging (Israeli Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Digestive Tract</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Digestive Tract</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DC163CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Camera in a Pill' Views Digestive Tract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Given Imaging, an Israeli company, creates a pill-size videocamera that can travel through the digestive tract and transmit pictures along the way, providing a less invasive way to examine the small intestine; it uses CMOS video imaging chip and white-light emitting diode as light source; photo; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They haven't figured out how to squeeze Raquel Welch into it, but scientists with an Israeli company have made a pill-size videocamera that takes a fantastic voyage of its own, traveling through the digestive tract and transmitting pictures along the way.</p>
        <p>The device, which consists of the camera and light source, radio transmitter and batteries within a sealed capsule slightly more than an inch long and less than half an inch wide, is intended as a less invasive way to examine the small intestine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They haven't figured out how to squeeze Raquel Welch into it, but scientists with an Israeli company have made a pill-size videocamera that takes a fantastic voyage of its own, traveling through the digestive tract and transmitting pictures along the way.</p>
        <p>The device, which consists of the camera and light source, radio transmitter and batteries within a sealed capsule slightly more than an inch long and less than half an inch wide, is intended as a less invasive way to examine the small intestine.</p>
        <p>The capsule has been successfully tested in animals and 10 healthy human volunteers. More human trials will be conducted as the company, Given Imaging of Yokneam, Israel, seeks approval from the United States Food and Drug Administration. Company officials said that the cost of an examination using the capsule should be about the same as a conventional endoscopic procedure.</p>
        <p>But the new device may be more effective, and will certainly be more comfortable. Examination of the small intestine, particularly the lower two-thirds, is difficult using fiber-optic or video scopes that have long cables that must be snaked into the digestive tract through the mouth or nose. The procedure usually requires that the patient be sedated.</p>
        <p>The camera-in-a-pill ''can go some places we have trouble going,'' said Dr. James T. Frakes, a gastroenterologist in Rockford, Ill., and president of the American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, who saw a demonstration of the device last week.</p>
        <p>The camera takes and transmits several images per second, which are picked up by an array of flexible antennas and a receiver about the size of a personal stereo that are attached to a special belt. The images are stored in memory chips and then downloaded to a computer for viewing, either as still pictures or as a kind of home movie.</p>
        <p>The system uses the strength and phase of the signal received by the antennas to track the pill so that the doctor can know approximately where in the digestive tract a particularly image was taken. So a surgeon, for example, would know where along the small intestine to operate to repair or remove a source of bleeding, a common and often vexing gastrointestinal problem.</p>
        <p>The batteries last for about six hours, enough time for the capsule to make it through the small intestine, propelled by the natural contractions known as peristalsis. Patients do not have to interrupt their daily routines during the 24 to 48 hours the pills are in their digestive tracts until excretion.</p>
        <p>''Once it's gone down, you don't feel it at all,'' said Dr. Paul Swain, a gastroenterologist at the Royal London Hospital, who conducted the initial trials of the device. The results were reported last week in the journal Nature. The capsule is designed to be disposable, said Dr. Swain, who has tried it himself.</p>
        <p>While Dr. Frakes said the images from the pill were not of the quality that could be obtained with the latest generation of video scopes, he described the demonstration, at a conference in San Diego, as a ''landmark event.''</p>
        <p>''It demonstrated that you could, in fact, do this,'' Dr. Frakes said. ''The possibilities are limitless.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the device offers a taste of a future in which molecular-scale sensors, pumps and other devices travel through the body, diagnosing and repairing problems, something like the shrunken submarine in the 1966 film ''Fantastic Voyage.'' The sub, with Ms. Welch and others aboard, was injected into the bloodstream of a gravely ill person, removed a blood clot with a laser and exited through a tear duct (at the last second, in cliffhanger fashion).</p>
        <p>The camera-in-a-pill is not quite the stuff of Hollywood dreams, obviously, and one drawback, as Dr. Swain pointed out, is that it cannot do biopsies, cauterizations or other procedures that a conventional endoscope can.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Richard W. Siegel, chairman of the materials science and engineering department at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., said the device was ''a very nice indication of where things are beginning to go.''</p>
        <p>''Once you've had success, you're going to want to go on to the next smaller thing, and the next smaller thing,'' said Dr. Siegel, who headed a major study that helped lead to a recent proposal by the Clinton administration to double federal spending on research into molecular-scale devices, or nanotechnology.</p>
        <p>The new device is a descendant of swallowable capsules with sensors and tiny radio transmitters that have been used for several decades to diagnose stomach problems. Known as Heidelberg capsules, they provide a record of stomach acidity during digestion.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arkady Glukhovsky, vice president for research and development with Given Imaging, said the new device was made possible by several technological advances, including the development of CMOS (pronounced SEE-moss) video imaging  chips. CMOS, or complementary metal-oxide semiconductor, chips, use far less power than more conventional charge-coupled device chips. The capsule also uses white-light emitting diodes as its light source. Previously, L.E.D.'s only produced colored light.</p>
        <p>The company is working to improve the image quality and the battery life of the capsule, and to develop a model that will work in the large intestine and colon, where more light is needed. Researchers have also tested in animals a rudimentary method of propulsion, in which a capsule with tiny electrodes fires a small charge into the intestinal wall, prompting a contraction that pushes the capsule up or down the tract.</p>
        <p>While it may be a forerunner of molecular-size devices, this device probably will not get much tinier, Dr. Glukhovsky said. ''There's no point to make it smaller,'' he said. ''It should fit the intestine.'' What is more likely is that the capsule will eventually be able to repair problems as well as view them.</p>
        <p>That would reflect another trend in the development of nanotechnology, Dr. Siegel said. ''The total package may not want to be small,'' he said, ''but it may be packed with more and more power to do things.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps, but Dr. Glukhovsky stressed that such multipurpose micromachines were far in the future. As for his company's pill, he said, ''If it's a beginning in that direction, it's a very early beginning.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
