<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Banks Scores Six Goals As Syracuse Wins Title</title>
    <meta content="30LACR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LACROSSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Syracuse University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D9163CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Banks Scores Six Goals As Syracuse Wins Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <dateline>COLLEGE PARK, Md., May 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Syracuse defeats Princeton, 13-7, to win men's NCAA Lacrosse championship (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liam Banks, a Syracuse attackman, lurked by the Princeton goal as Tigers bustled by him on their defensive assignments. They should have paid more attention to Banks.</p>
        <p>Banks, a sophomore, scored six goals and had one assist, powering top-seeded Syracuse past No. 3 Princeton, 13-7, and giving the Orangemen (15-1) their sixth men's national lacrosse championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Liam Banks, a Syracuse attackman, lurked by the Princeton goal as Tigers bustled by him on their defensive assignments. They should have paid more attention to Banks.</p>
        <p>Banks, a sophomore, scored six goals and had one assist, powering top-seeded Syracuse past No. 3 Princeton, 13-7, and giving the Orangemen (15-1) their sixth men's national lacrosse championship.</p>
        <p>''I had a lot of easy looks at the goal today,'' said Banks, whose 13 points in the final two postseason games earned him the tournament's most outstanding player award. ''I was right on the doorstop, and it's really hard for a goalie to make a save right there.''</p>
        <p>It was the first title for the second-year coach, John Desko, and left Princeton 5-1 in games for the national title. In front of 22,880 at the University of Maryland, the Tigers never made a serious run and fell to 12-3.</p>
        <p>''I'm very proud of these guys,'' Desko said. ''There aren't any words to express how they feel, how I feel, how I feel for them. I'm extremely happy. Today just couldn't be better.''</p>
        <p>Syracuse's domination -- Princeton could not get closer than four goals after early in the game -- transferred the spotlight to Ryan Powell, a senior attack for the Orangemen, as he tried to tie his brother Casey's school record of 287 career points.</p>
        <p>Late in the fourth quarter, it seemed as if Powell would not do it. He had 4 of the 5 points he needed to tie the record when he clanged a shot off the crossbar.</p>
        <p>But with 18 seconds left, Powell darted behind the goal and curled forward, covered closely by Ryan Mollet, who clogged the path to the goal. Powell dumped a pass to Ethan Mills, who dropped the ball in over the second-string goalie Willis Wu.</p>
        <p>''It's a great day for our family,'' Powell said, adding that his brother was happy about the tie. ''I think that's what I wanted to do all along. I mean, if I could write a storybook ending, that's how I wanted it to be.''</p>
        <p>Desko described the scene. ''Casey was behind the bench yelling, 'Coach, take him out!' '' Desko said, grinning. ''I'm glad it ended this way.''</p>
        <p>At the postgame news conference, Banks slipped Powell his hand. Not looking at each other, they shook hands under the table.</p>
        <p>''It's the greatest feeling that I've ever had in my lifetime,'' Powell said. ''I'm just a small-town kid who lives on a farm, then I come here and there are all these cameras in my face -- it's been an unbelievable ride.''</p>
        <p>''We're awfully proud of these young men,'' Princeton Coach Bill Tierney said of his team. ''They did what everyone said they couldn't do, won the games people said they couldn't win, and lost the championship game to a champion.''</p>
        <p>LACROSSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
