<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lazio Falls and Splits His Lip, But Keeps Marching at Parade</title>
    <meta content="30LAZI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memorial Day</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Babylon (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorial Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF173CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lazio Falls and Splits His Lip, But Keeps Marching at Parade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>BABYLON, N.Y., May 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Representative Rick A Lazio, campaigning for United States Senate, trips and falls face down onto pavement at Memorial Day parade in Babylon, NY, splitting his lip; he dusts himself off and finishes route before going to hospital, getting eight stitches and then marching in second parade in Queens; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio tripped and fell face down onto the pavement today at a Memorial Day parade here, splitting his lip. But he dusted himself off and finished the route before going to the hospital, getting eight stitches and then marching in a second parade in Queens alongside the man he replaced in the race for the Senate, Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The injury means that Mr. Lazio will most likely have a swollen lip on Tuesday afternoon, when he is expected to formally accept the Republican nomination for the Senate at the Republican convention in Buffalo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick A. Lazio tripped and fell face down onto the pavement today at a Memorial Day parade here, splitting his lip. But he dusted himself off and finished the route before going to the hospital, getting eight stitches and then marching in a second parade in Queens alongside the man he replaced in the race for the Senate, Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The injury means that Mr. Lazio will most likely have a swollen lip on Tuesday afternoon, when he is expected to formally accept the Republican nomination for the Senate at the Republican convention in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The candidate and his supporters quickly seized upon the accident and sought to turn it to their advantage, both with humor and by using it to try to illustrate Mr. Lazio's perseverance, before it could become the wrong kind of political metaphor about missteps or stumbling on the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>And like Bob Dole, who fell off a stage at a campaign stop in California during the 1996 presidential race, Mr. Lazio quickly poked fun at his mishap. ''I was so happy to be home that I had to kiss the ground,'' Mr. Lazio, who fell in his own district, said after leaving the hospital. ''I didn't know that it would kiss back.''</p>
        <p>It was indeed a hometown parade for Mr. Lazio, one he said he has marched in since childhood. Along the way, he greeted many spectators by name, shook many hands and kissed many babies. Then, his jacket and tie and leather dress shoes notwithstanding, he would sprint back to the head of the parade, literally running for office. It was during one of these sprints that he slipped and fell onto Deer Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>Dabbing at his mouth with a bloodied handkerchief and a bag of ice from a nearby deli, Mr. Lazio finished the parade.</p>
        <p>Some spectators were confused at the sight of him, as shouts of ''Good luck, Rick!'' and ''Keep her out of New York!'' were replaced by cries of ''You've got lipstick on you,'' and, more accurately, ''Your lip is bleeding!'' When Mr. Lazio finished the route, his aides looked on nervously as he paused to talk to reporters before driving back to his home in nearby Brightwaters for help.</p>
        <p>Aides said that once he got home, Mr. Lazio got prompt advice from his wife, Patricia, a nurse, who took one look at his lip and recommended a trip to the hospital.</p>
        <p>So he got stitches at the Long Island Jewish Medical Center, changed into a pair of rubber-soled boat shoes for better traction, and went back onto the hustings to campaign with Mr. Giuliani at the Little Neck-Douglaston Memorial Day parade along Northern Boulevard.</p>
        <p>It was the first time Mr. Giuliani had campaigned with Mr. Lazio since deciding not to seek the Republican nomination for Senate himself.</p>
        <p>This parade was not without chaos either. The mayor and the injured congressman soon found themselves facing a crush of reporters so unruly that police reinforcements were called in to restore order, and trying to talk about campaign issues and economic opportunities over the din of the roaring mufflers of Rolling Thunder, a motorcycle club made up of Vietnam veterans who were riding in the parade.</p>
        <p>The mayor seized on all this as evidence of Mr. Lazio's grit. ''Look at him, he's a real New Yorker,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''He's got a fat lip, he can talk over the worst kinds of noises, it doesn't bother him and he's out here answering all your questions.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's comments were a not-so-veiled allusion to Mr. Lazio's Democratic opponent, Hillary Rodham Clinton, who, as first lady, is often kept from the press by the Secret Service.</p>
        <p>But if the morning parade was in the heart of Lazio country, the afternoon parade was clearly in Mr. Giuliani's territory. The mayor got the loudest cheers from the crowd.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Lazio, while warmly greeted, was not always recognized. ''Who's that with the mayor?' '' one spectator asked.</p>
        <p>But there were plenty of well-wishers. Joe Martino, 73, who served in the Pacific in World War II, said, ''I was sorry to see Rudy Giuliani get out of the race, but we're for Lazio.''</p>
        <p>And Linda Delligatti, 65, who goes to the parade every year and gets a kiss from the mayor, got a kiss from Mr. Lazio, stitched lip and all, this year. ''On the cheek,'' she said. ''The mayor kissed me too. I hope he gets better.''</p>
        <p>Still, for all the spectacle of Mr. Giuliani's endorsing his onetime rival for the Republican nomination and actively stumping for him, many eyes remained on Mr. Lazio's sutured mouth. As the parade continued along Northern Boulevard toward 251st Street, a member of the mayor's staff might have averted another accident when he noticed that Mr. Lazio's shoelaces were untied. ''Sir, your shoes,'' he cried out.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lazio knelt down to tie them, he was instantly surrounded by photographers seeking to capture the moment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
