<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A CONVERSATION WITH: Geoffrey Miller; Author Offers Theory On Gray Matter of Love</title>
    <meta content="30MILL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Geoffrey F (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mating Mind, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Conversations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDE1F3DF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A CONVERSATION WITH: Geoffrey Miller; Author Offers Theory On Gray Matter of Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATALIE ANGIER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Geoffrey F Miller, author of The Mating Mind, discusses his theory that the most outstanding features of the human mind--creativity, consciousness, moral sense, artfulness and humor--were shaped not by natural selection but by sexual selection; notes that natural selection is surviving long enough to reproduce, while sexual selection is about convincing others to mate with you; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Look around a human-wrought landscape like Manhattan, and the term Homo manipulens might spring to mind. People are irrepressible toolmakers, slapping down grid systems and trumping up towers, and braking for nothing but the occasional Starbucks. Surely the human mind evolved to wrest from the environment every possible survival advantage, including a cell phone that works in the subway.</p>
        <p>But think again about Manhattan, and the things that make it livable: the museums, ballet corps, jazz clubs, comedy acts, drag shows. What good are they, really? More precisely, how can humanity's boundless thirst for the arts be explained in Darwinian terms as the product of natural selection -- the evolutionary process most commonly soundbitten as ''survival of the fittest?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Look around a human-wrought landscape like Manhattan, and the term Homo manipulens might spring to mind. People are irrepressible toolmakers, slapping down grid systems and trumping up towers, and braking for nothing but the occasional Starbucks. Surely the human mind evolved to wrest from the environment every possible survival advantage, including a cell phone that works in the subway.</p>
        <p>But think again about Manhattan, and the things that make it livable: the museums, ballet corps, jazz clubs, comedy acts, drag shows. What good are they, really? More precisely, how can humanity's boundless thirst for the arts be explained in Darwinian terms as the product of natural selection -- the evolutionary process most commonly soundbitten as ''survival of the fittest?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Geoffrey F. Miller, an evolutionary psychologist at University College, London, says it cannot. As Dr. Miller sees it, the most outstanding features of the human mind -- its creativity, its consciousness, its moral sense, its artfulness and its love of a good punch line -- were shaped not by natural selection but by the other strong evolutionary force called sexual selection.</p>
        <p>In this view, which he lays out in his new book, ''The Mating Mind'' (Doubleday), humans are imaginative, artistic, humorous and relatively amiable for the same reason that peacocks fan their fancy tails and cicadas thrum through the summer:  to attract mates and increase their so-called reproductive success.</p>
        <p>Born in 1965 in Ohio and educated at Columbia, Dr. Miller has lived in England for seven years, long enough to say things like ''cheerio'' and to assume the lanky, languid air of British film charmers like Ralph Fiennes or Ben Chaplin. He talked about his book and the underappreciated power of sexual choice, in a recent stop in New York.  Q. Give me a quick-and-dirty explanation of the difference between natural selection and sexual selection.  A. Natural selection is about living long enough to reproduce. Sexual selection is about convincing others to mate with you. It's about animal minds, our ancestors' minds, influencing other minds, which is why it appealed to me as a way of understanding the evolution of the human mind.  Q. So what's wrong with the idea of the mind as problem solver, or of humans as the best of all handymen?  A. When you think of what makes humans unique, you think of art, music, our sense of humor, our creativity. For 140 years, biologists have attempted to explain these traits by means of natural selection, and survival of the fittest, and they have completely failed to make the connection between Darwinism and the humanities. And as I read the standard evolutionary psychology stuff on mate choice, I thought there were several pieces of the puzzle that were missing here. I thought it was quite possible that art and music and creativity have quite a lot to do with somebody's psychological attraction.  Q. One of your premises is the idea that technological innovation was at a standstill during most of our brain evolution, suggesting that the brain was evolving for reasons other than to make better tools. Why do you think that was so?  A. Two million years ago, our ancestors were making and using hand-axes and other stone tools. Their brains tripled in size over the following 1.75 million years. By the time brain size increase stopped, the hand ax and similar tools were still in use around the world. Only in the last 100,000 years have we had all the increase in technological complexity. So you've got brain size increase first, and that stops, and then the tool use increases, very, very recently in evolutionary terms. You couldn't ask for a worse correlation in terms of evolutionary trends. The traditional story that brains are technophilic, tool-producing machines just doesn't match the archaeological evidence.</p>
        <p>Q. Let's talk about why early humans focused on the brain and mental traits when selecting their mates.  A. We must bear in mind that brains were already important to great apes generally by the time we started to diverge from chimps five million years ago.</p>
        <p>There's a consensus now that selection for social intelligence is extremely important in the emergence of great apes compared to other primates, like monkeys. If social intelligence in a general sense was crucial to survival and reproduction among these relatively big-brained primates like proto-chimps, then sexual choice has a powerful incentive to look for evidence of social intelligence when choosing a mate.</p>
        <p>Second, the bigger and more complex the brain gets, the larger the proportion of genes in the genome are involved in brain development. If you're choosing a mate for his or her genetic quality, what you want to focus on are the traits that give you the best window on the quality of the individual's genome.  Q. But we went further than chimpanzees did in attending to mental traits. Why is that?  A. I'm afraid I'll have to invoke Stephen Jay Gould here, and say there is a strong component of contingency in sexual selection, much more so than in natural selection. I think that most theoretical biologists recognize that sexual selection is evolution's wild card.  Q. Talk about the handicap principle here, which is so important to sexual selection theory, and to your book.  A. I didn't really understand the handicap principle until I read Thorstein Veblen talking about conspicuous consumption in his classic, ''Theory of the Leisure Class.'' I think there are close analogies between luxury goods that we acquire and sexual ornaments. What makes a good a luxury good is simply the cost. The more something costs, and the more reliably it can say ''I'm expensive,'' then the better an indicator it makes of wealth.</p>
        <p>Amotz Zahavi reinvented Veblen's principle and applied it to sexual selection. The peacock's tail is not just an arbitrary outcome of sexual selection. It's there because it's costly, which means only those fit, healthy, strong peacocks can afford to carry around those tails.  Q. It's easy to see the handicap principle as applying to the peacock's tail, but to human intelligence?  A. It's important to distinguish between the mental traits that I think really are handicaps from those that aren't. Our brighter ancestors would have survived better and attracted more mates.</p>
        <p>So the handicap principle doesn't apply to intelligence per se. But I think it does apply to behaviors like art, music and humor, or poetic uses of language, or the production of fictional stories. In those instances, nobody has been able to find any possible survival function. And yet, for the people that do these things, the traits consume enormous amounts of time and energy, not only to produce them, but to learn the skills necessary to produce them.  Q. So creativity becomes a ''fitness indicator,'' a way to strut one's quality, precisely because it is so wasteful and expensive?  A. Once mate choice identifies a trait as informative about something, that trait is going to be under strong selection to amplify its appearance. Those who invest the most energy, the most maintenance time, the most genes, into growing the trait, will attract the most mates. One of the book's main ideas is that the human traits of art, music and creativity are in there by design, as fitness indicators.  Q. You also propose that a father's devotion to his children, and his willingness to care for them, may be an unconscious courtship display, an extension of an ancestral man's willingness to show a woman that he is a kind and gentle guy who will treat her kids well, even if they were fathered by the fellow who came before him. What's the evidence?  A. One valid bit of evidence is simply the behavior of modern fathers across cultures. A typical problem with divorce is that divorced men seriously reduce their investment in their children. If paternal instincts had evolved simply for the good of their children, fathers shouldn't care whether they're sleeping with the mother. These are their kids, they should be supporting them, investing in them, acting like they recognize that the kids are vehicles carrying their genes. But the sad truth is that it's very hard to get a lot of men to pay child support.</p>
        <p>But I feel a bit humble about making predictions about what's testable in my book and what's not, given the rate of advance in genetics. A good theory should go in advance of the evidence. It shouldn't be circumscribed by the evidence. It should stick its neck out and say, this is how I think the world is, and leave it to other people to test it.  Q. One of the refreshing things about your book is that you discuss mutual mate selection for mental traits, and the idea that the female mind isn't just a consolation prize -- that intelligence, wittiness, creativity may have been sexually selected in women just as it was in men.  A. Absolutely. Darwin got almost everything right, except that he did view the human female brain as riding along on the evolutionary coat-tails of the male brain. I think that's wrong. And a lot of my colleagues still have this fixed idea that sexual selection always implies sex differences. They know in their hearts that we're a species with mutual choice, but they tend to ignore it.  Q. What about your own mate choice?  A. She's a television producer, and, as a psychologist, I introspected quite a bit as we were falling in love.  I think I was drawn to her because she was very witty and funny and a woman I thought I could learn a lot from. You look for somebody who you feel you could talk to for years without getting bored, and when you find that person it's a very exciting event.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
