<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="30FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DE173CF933A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Indonesia Places Suharto Under House Arrest  The Indonesian government, under intense public pressure to get tough, placed former President Suharto under house arrest as it sought to try him on charges of corruption and abuse of power. The house arrest does not materially change Mr. Suharto's living conditions.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Indonesia Places Suharto Under House Arrest  The Indonesian government, under intense public pressure to get tough, placed former President Suharto under house arrest as it sought to try him on charges of corruption and abuse of power. The house arrest does not materially change Mr. Suharto's living conditions.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Rejects Peru Vote  The State Department rejected the re-election of President Alberto K. Fujimori as invalid, saying it had resulted from a ''flawed process.''</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Decision on Lebanese Delayed  An Israeli court delayed a decision on whether to release two abducted Lebanese guerrilla leaders whose freedom was demanded by Hezbollah as a condition for halting anti-Israeli hostilities. The judge said he would issue a ruling on July 12.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The leader of the Hezbollah group said its guerrilla fighters would not disarm despite the Israeli Army's withdrawal from southern Lebanon. The Lebanese Army reinstated measures requiring travel permits to try to control the movement of people to the border area and the flow of weapons seized by guerrillas from Israel's allied militia.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Kosovo Town Remains Torn  Foreigners working in the volatile town of Mitrovica complain that the international security force there still does not control the Albanian-dominated southern part or the northern Serbian enclave.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Clinton Begins Europe Tour  President Clinton began a weeklong trip expected to be dominated by a stalemate with Russia over an American missile defense system and trade disputes with Europe.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Military Takes Over Fiji  Commodore Frank Bainimarama, head of the armed forces, declared martial law, stepping into a crisis in which the prime minister has been held hostage by gunmen since May 19.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Ethiopia Bombs Eritrea  Ethiopian warplanes bombed the airport outside Asmara, Eritrea, in the first air raid on the capital since the war's opening blows in 1998. The raid occurred as the nations prepared for peace talks in Algeria.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-20</p>
        <p>U.S. Working on Plan To Lessen Wildfire Risks  Congress and the Clinton administration are developing an emergency plan to try to ease the risk from wildfires faced by ever growing numbers of Americans with homes in wooded areas, especially in the mountain West. The emergency plan would nearly double, to $115 million, the amount of money available to the government this year for efforts intended to prevent wildfires from starting. Already this year, more than 40,000 wildfires have consumed more than a million acres, including the land scorched by the blaze in Los Alamos, N.M., which was a case of a pre-emptive fire gone awry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Labor's Resurgence  Union supporters and opponents say that despite the American labor movement's loss in the battle over the China trade bill, labor has once again become a powerful political player and will probably be a major force for the Democrats this fall. Much of the rebound has been engineered by John J. Sweeney, who was elected president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. in 1995 on a platform of reviving labor.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Remembering Normandy  Part of the National D-Day Memorial was unveiled in Bedford, Va., a community of 3,200 people in 1944 that lost more men per capita -- 19 in the first 15 minutes of the invasion and 4 more within days -- than any other place in the United States.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Paying Tribute to War Dead  Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush commemorated the nation's war dead in speeches that mostly avoided politics. Mr. Gore recounted some of his own military experiences in Vietnam and discussed reasons behind his enlistment.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Cleaning Up After Derailment  Hazardous-chemical specialists plan to put out fires still burning in two tank cars in Eunice, La., today and begin moving the 30 freight cars that derailed on Saturday, forcing 2,500 people from their homes.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Vigil for Slain Teacher  More than a thousand people gathered in Lake Worth, Fla., for a Memorial Day ceremony in honor of Barry Grunow, 35, a teacher killed by a student on Friday.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>2 Candidates Join Parades, And One Takes a Tumble  Representative Rick A. Lazio received eight stitches to close a split lip he sustained when he fell on his face during a Memorial Day parade in Babylon, in his home district on Long Island. After treatment, he marched in a parade with Mayor Giuliani, in Queens.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton joined a parade in Chappaqua, her adopted hometown, and indirectly criticized Mr. Lazio's opposition to handgun registration by emphasizing her support of it.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Breaking Speed Limit of Light  Researchers have produced light beams in the laboratory that appear to travel much faster than the normal speed of light. As such, the main part of the light pulse exits the chamber even before it enters it.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Night Landing for Shuttle  Atlantis and its seven-member crew landed at 2:20 a.m. at Cape Canaveral, Fla., after a 10-day mission to the International Space Station.</p>
        <p>F10</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Samuel Taylor  The playwright who wrote Broadway confections like ''Sabrina Fair'' and ''The Pleasure of His Company'' and who also worked on the script for Hitchcock's ''Vertigo'' was 87.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Knicks Even Series, 2-2  The Knicks beat the Pacers, 91-89, to pull even with Indiana in the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Early Exit in Paris for Sampras  Pete Sampras, the No. 2 seed in the French Open, lost in the first round to Mark Philippoussis, 4-6, 7-5, 7-6 (4), 4-6, 8-6.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-15</p>
        <p>Bypassing Windows and Intel  Gateway and America Online are expected to announce today that they will use a processor from an upstart Silicon Valley chip maker, Transmeta, and a version of the Linux operating system in a new Internet device for home use scheduled to go on sale later this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>$5 Billion China Stock Offering  China's second-largest telecommunications company, China Unicom, said it would seek to raise as much as $5.26 billion in an initial public offering in Hong Kong and New York.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>S.U.V. Makers Hold Advantage  Law professors and plaintiff lawyers say it remains difficult to win lawsuits based on the damage that sport utility vehicles inflict in crashes, despite Ford's recent acknowledgment that the vehicles can be hazardous to other motorists. The legal issue is not whether the vehicles are particularly deadly to other motorists, but whether that deadliness results in legal liability for automakers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>In Pursuit of a Wireless System  People close to the talks between Worldcom and the Justice Department on Worldcom's pending $115 billion acquisition of Sprint said the discussions could lead to the sale of the Sprint brand and its long-distance service. That is because Worldcom's primary focus is on Sprint's nationwide wireless operation.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Senate primary in New Jersey; another gain for Irish peace; a gift for the credit card industry.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
