<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last Manager Set to Leave Soros Fund</title>
    <meta content="YH09HE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Soros Fund Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Soros, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bessent, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Druckenmiller, Stanley F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roditi, S Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D6103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last Manager Set to Leave Soros Fund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Bessent, who oversees European investments for Soros Fund Management, says he will leave firm to start his own private investment group; he is last of three money managers to annouce his departure from Soros's dwindling investment empire; other top managers to leave were Stanley F Druckenmiller and S Nicholas Roditi (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last of three top money managers announced his departure from the dwindling investment empire of George Soros yesterday. Scott Bessent, who oversees European investments for Soros Fund Management, said he would leave to start his own private investment group.</p>
        <p>The move lowers the curtain on Mr. Soros' run as one of the world's most daring money managers. In late April, after sustaining bracing losses, Mr. Soros, 69, said he would reorganize his investment group and abandon many of the risky strategies that made him a multibillionaire. But it was unclear then just how thorough an overhaul his firm would undertake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last of three top money managers announced his departure from the dwindling investment empire of George Soros yesterday. Scott Bessent, who oversees European investments for Soros Fund Management, said he would leave to start his own private investment group.</p>
        <p>The move lowers the curtain on Mr. Soros' run as one of the world's most daring money managers. In late April, after sustaining bracing losses, Mr. Soros, 69, said he would reorganize his investment group and abandon many of the risky strategies that made him a multibillionaire. But it was unclear then just how thorough an overhaul his firm would undertake.</p>
        <p>By yesterday, the extent of the transformation was apparent. Mr. Bessent, 37, the last of the money managers that oversaw Soros Fund Management's global investment strategies, will take nine Soros staff members with him to his new firm. The other top managers, Stanley F. Druckenmiller and S. Nicholas Roditi, announced their retirements in late April, after the firm's flagship Quantum Fund had fallen 22 percent through the first four months of the year.</p>
        <p>All three executives will depart at the end of the month and will not be replaced. Instead, Mr. Soros will reduce his staff and farm out much of the management of his fund group to outside managers like Mr. Bessent, in an attempt to greatly reduce risk and make his investment group a more suitable launching pad for his charitable endeavors.</p>
        <p>Some investors, preferring the old Soros to the new, tamer Soros, have withdrawn their money. Because of withdrawals and performance setbacks, assets in the five Soros funds currently stand at $13.3 billion, down from $17 billion at the end of last year. In addition, Duncan Hennes, the chief executive of Soros Fund Management who indicated in April that he would stay on to help rebuild, said last week that he would also depart at the end of the month.</p>
        <p>The departures and the more conservative philosophy will leave Soros Fund Management a much different organization from the one that managed more than $22 billion in 1998 and rattled markets with big bets on the directions of global currencies, stocks and bonds. Mr. Soros was nicknamed ''the man who broke the pound'' in 1992 for betting millions of dollars against the British pound, but Mr. Bessent wrote in a recent letter to friends and associates that the environment that made these so-called 'macro' strategies successful in the past had changed.</p>
        <p>Both a Soros spokesman and Mr. Bessent said his departure was amicable. Mr. Bessent will use $150 million of his own money to start two private funds and Mr. Soros will add another $150 million. Mr. Bessent said he would keep some of his own money in Soros's $3.5 billion venture capital fund and sit on a Soros advisory board.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Russia Impresses Soros</p>
        <p>MOSCOW, June 8 (By The New York Times) -- George Soros, who owns one of the biggest failed investments in Russia, said today that he was impressed with the country's economic improvement and the new administration's apparent willingness to protect investors.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready to invest more in Russia,'' he said at a news conference here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Soros has sunk more than $1 billion into commercial investments in Russia. Most of that is stuck in an ill-fated purchase of a stake in the main state telephone holding company he has called ''the worst investment decision of my career.'' The 25 percent stake is currently worth less than half of what it was in 1997 when he purchased it through a group called Mustcom Ltd. Now, he said, he is not ruling out further purchases in the company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
