<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Muted Reaction of Admiration and Disbelief</title>
    <meta content="Y09GLO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. VS. MIRCROSOFT: THE VIEW ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DD113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Muted Reaction of Admiration and Disbelief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reaction in Europe and Asia to news of court order to break up Microsoft Corp is one of admiration mixed with disbelief that a government would take such step; neither Europe nor Japan has ever seen comparable effort to break up large company; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Windows and Word may be ubiquitous across Europe and Asia, but news of the court order to break up Microsoft generated a muted reaction outside of the United States today.</p>
        <p>There was a sense of admiration -- mixed with disbelief -- among many commentators that a government would take such a step. Neither Europe nor Japan have ever seen a comparable effort to break up a large company, though European regulators have become much more aggressive about imposing big fines on companies for anticompetitive activities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Windows and Word may be ubiquitous across Europe and Asia, but news of the court order to break up Microsoft generated a muted reaction outside of the United States today.</p>
        <p>There was a sense of admiration -- mixed with disbelief -- among many commentators that a government would take such a step. Neither Europe nor Japan have ever seen a comparable effort to break up a large company, though European regulators have become much more aggressive about imposing big fines on companies for anticompetitive activities.</p>
        <p>''The breakup of a company is impossible under German law,'' said Stefan Siebert, a spokesman for Germany's cartel office in Bonn. ''All we can do is prohibit abuses and impose fines.''</p>
        <p>In Rome, La Republica captured the sense that the breakup was something that could happen only in the United States.</p>
        <p>''A Washington judge with the deceptively good-natured image of a western actor has with almost hate-filled words ordered the breakup of Microsoft into two separate parts,'' the newspaper said in an editorial today. ''The century of the New Economy begins exactly where that of the old economy began: with an America that breaks up the monopoly of the 'new oil.' ''</p>
        <p>Mario Monti, head of the European Commission's competition ministry, said through a spokeswoman today that he ''congratulates'' the United States government for its work but said it was too early to know whether the court order would affect European investigations into Microsoft.</p>
        <p>Mr. Monti has raised questions about the Windows 2000 operating system, suggesting that it may hinder the abilities of computers linked over networks and over the Internet.</p>
        <p>His office is also scrutinizing Microsoft's plan to acquire 29.7 percent of Telewest Communications P.L.C., the British cable television operator.  Microsoft has teamed up with the Liberty Media Group to buy a controlling stake in Telewest from the Media One Corporation.</p>
        <p>''We understand that there will be an appeal,'' said Amelia Torres, a spokeswoman for the competition ministry. ''We will have to see what the final ruling is.''</p>
        <p>Though most European software companies said they would not be affected by the Microsoft case, several welcomed the order.</p>
        <p>''We welcome the recognition that monopolies have never been successful or sensible,'' said Reiner Jung, a spokesman for Brokat Infosystems A.G. of Stuttgart, a fast-growing developer of encryption programs and other software used in online banking systems. ''That doesn't mean we want a weaker Microsoft,'' he added. ''Quite the contrary, we want a strong Microsoft. But what we don't want is a monopoly.''</p>
        <p>Suse A.G., in Nurenberg, which produces software that runs on the Linux operating system, a competitor to Windows, argued that a court-ordered breakup of Microsoft might do little to break the Windows monopoly unless the company makes its code available to rivals.</p>
        <p>''Microsoft will have the ability after the breakup of making available applications for other platforms,'' said Carsten Fischer, a spokesman for Suse. ''But Microsoft has to adhere to the rules of open-source software, which includes opening up its documentation.''</p>
        <p>The biggest effect of the Microsoft case in Europe could prove to be on its many alliances and partnerships.  Microsoft has struck technology deals with scores of European media and telecommunications companies, and it sought to invest in both cable television and wireless networks.</p>
        <p>Microsoft officials say their goal is a foothold in new media, from interactive digital television to advanced wireless data communications.</p>
        <p>For the moment, companies involved with Microsoft are waiting to see what happens. ''We have consistently made it clear that we welcome Microsoft as a potential corporate shareholder, and that remains our position,'' said Rachel Turner, a spokeswoman for Telewest.</p>
        <p>U.S. VS. MIRCROSOFT: THE VIEW ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
