<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Kind of Remedy</title>
    <meta content="09PRIE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Netscape Communications Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Priest, George L (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4D7103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Kind of Remedy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George L. Priest</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Priest, George L (Prof)</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by George L Priest, law professor at Yale University and a consultant to Microsoft, says Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson's decision to break up an enterprise that was not itself the product of a merger is unprecedented in antitrust law, and ordering dissolution of flagship firm of software industry without hearings on the implications is bizarre; says if Judge Jackson gets his way, he will likely be forced to tie together a million loose ends created by this sweeping but casually constructed divestiture plan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson's decision to throw the book at Microsoft was not unexpected: his formal ''findings of law'' issued earlier made very clear that he viewed the company's alleged transgressions in the harshest light. Nonetheless, it was still a jolt to see the decision -- dividing Microsoft into an operating systems company and an applications company -- written in black and white.</p>
        <p>Breaking up an enterprise that was not itself the product of a merger is unprecedented in antitrust law. And ordering the dissolution of the flagship firm of the software industry without hearings on the implications approaches the bizarre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson's decision to throw the book at Microsoft was not unexpected: his formal ''findings of law'' issued earlier made very clear that he viewed the company's alleged transgressions in the harshest light. Nonetheless, it was still a jolt to see the decision -- dividing Microsoft into an operating systems company and an applications company -- written in black and white.</p>
        <p>Breaking up an enterprise that was not itself the product of a merger is unprecedented in antitrust law. And ordering the dissolution of the flagship firm of the software industry without hearings on the implications approaches the bizarre.</p>
        <p>Much has been written recently about the glorious history of big antitrust divestitures, with Standard Oil and AT&amp;T as case studies. But neither example goes to the point. Standard Oil was a loose trust of some 30 oil companies, assembled with the goal of reducing competition. The court simply ordered that the trust be taken apart the way it had been put together.</p>
        <p>For its part, AT&amp;T was a government-sanctioned monopoly with semi-autonomous local companies and other divisions, like a manufacturing arm, for which there was no justification for government regulation. Dividing the company into regulated local phone companies and an unregulated company to do everything else is more like deregulation than the breakup of a monopoly.</p>
        <p>And for the record, a court did not force the divestiture: it was the product of a mid-trial settlement in 1982, in which the Justice Department granted the deregulated AT&amp;T long-distance company the right to go into the computer business.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson dismissed Microsoft's request for weeks (or even days) of hearings on the proposed breakup, stating that ''the Court has found testimonial predictions of future events generally less reliable even than testimony as to historical fact.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to know what to make of a judge's rejection of expert comment. Witnesses from the two sides would no doubt be at odds, but the judge's unwillingness to assemble a record for both his own information and that of appellate courts is jaw-dropping.</p>
        <p>No one is quite sure, for example, how the copyrights to code now used by both Windows and other Microsoft software would be divided between the new operating system company and the applications company. No one knows how the heavily regulated Windows company could keep important employees, who would have the option to jump to the virtually unregulated Microsoft software applications company.</p>
        <p>No one knows whether (or how much) the independent Windows company would raise the price of the operating system, once it no longer had an interest in increasing sales of Office and other profitable Microsoft applications. Perhaps most troubling, no one knows how the breakup would affect investment in software. It is far from clear, for example, that the owners of the regulated Windows company would be willing to pay the billion-dollar bill for the next version of Windows.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson, like everyone else associated with this case, was no doubt impatient to rid himself of arcane talk of ''middleware'' and ''porting'' and ''elasticities of demand.'' The sad paradox here is that if he gets his way on the remedy, he will likely be forced to tie together a million loose ends created by this sweeping, but casually constructed, divestiture plan.</p>
        <p>In the AT&amp;T case, Federal District Court Judge Harold Greene spent more than a decade regulating the remnants of the national phone company. And in that case, you will remember, the division was voluntary.</p>
        <p>George L. Priest, a law professor at Yale, is a consultant to Microsoft.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">George L. Priest, a law professor at Yale, is a consultant to Microsoft.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
