<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ancient Pots As Storytellers</title>
    <meta content="09ANTI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greek Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borowski, Elie (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2DF103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ancient Pots As Storytellers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column on Christie's auction of 157 ancient Greek vases from collection of Dr Elie Borowski; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as medieval Christians learned their Bible by looking at stained glass windows and church sculptures, ancient Greeks had their mythology illustrated on painted pots.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the late Bronze Age (circa 2900 to 2000 B.C.), Greeks decorated all kinds of pots: kraters, amphorae, kylixes and vases. The pots (or the stories they told) must have been appreciated, because they have been passed down, even when broken and repaired, for more than 4,000 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as medieval Christians learned their Bible by looking at stained glass windows and church sculptures, ancient Greeks had their mythology illustrated on painted pots.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the late Bronze Age (circa 2900 to 2000 B.C.), Greeks decorated all kinds of pots: kraters, amphorae, kylixes and vases. The pots (or the stories they told) must have been appreciated, because they have been passed down, even when broken and repaired, for more than 4,000 years.</p>
        <p>On Monday Christie's New York is auctioning 157 ancient Greek vases that were formerly in the collection of Dr. Elie Borowski, a connoisseur of ancient Greek and Near Eastern art. ''This may be the best vase sale since 1980,'' said G. Max Bernheimer, the head of antiquities at Christie's. ''It is encyclopedic in scale and comes from one of the best private collections ever assembled.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Borowski, who was a curator of antiquities at the Royal Ontario Museum in Toronto, resigned in the 1950's to become a full-time collector of ancient Greek and Near Eastern art. About 10 years ago he sold his collection of Greek vases to finance the construction of the Bible Lands Museum in Jerusalem, which he built to display his second collection: ancient art that chronicles the Bible.</p>
        <p>The vases in the sale date from the Minoan era (circa 16th century B.C.) to the Hellenistc period (323 to 31 B.C.) and include examples of the Geometric, Archaic and Classical ceramic styles, some of whose painters have been identified.</p>
        <p>Some pots tell old tales. Lot 32, for example, is an Attic krater from around 560 B.C. that illustrates the battle between the Lapiths and Centaurs. Two Lapith warriors are seen in the heat of combat with three centaurs. The fierce Lapiths hurl spears at the centaurs, who are half man and half beast. The centaurs pick up rocks and throw them at the Lapiths.</p>
        <p>According to legend, the kind and generous Lapith king Peirithous invited the centaurs to his wedding. The centaurs got very drunk and repaid their host by trying to rape the Lapith women, so the Lapiths attacked the centaurs and sent them packing.</p>
        <p>The story is illustrated on a 17-inch-tall column krater designed to hold wine. ''Can you imagine how much wine it must hold?'' Mr. Bernheimer asked. Attributed to the painter Lydos, the krater is an example of the ancient Greek black-figure technique, in which figures appear in black silhouette against the natural red clay ground of the vase, with details incised.</p>
        <p>The technique, perfected in the seventh century B.C. in Corinth, was adopted in Athens in the sixth century B.C. and became the predominant style of the day. ''This one is quite early, when painters show a lot of influence of the Corinthian vase painting tradition,'' Mr. Bernheimer said, discussing the high quality of the draftsmanship.</p>
        <p>Lot 38, an Attic black-figure amphora from about 550 B.C., depicts Zeus fighting the giants. Dressed in a short white tunic, Zeus drives a four-horse chariot and wields his thunderbolt as his sons Ares and Herakles come to his aid. Ares, wearing a crested helmet and cuirass, crouches, sword in hand while Herakles, with his signature Nemean lion skin, launches an arrow from his bow. One helmeted giant has fallen at the feet of Zeus's horses, while another hides behind a shield decorated with a palmette.</p>
        <p>The black is gone from some of the figures. ''The pot is finished but misfired,'' Mr. Bernheimer said. ''In the kiln the glaze didn't reduce to black the way it is supposed to.''</p>
        <p>''It cost an enormous amount to fire up a kiln, and several pots were done together,'' he said. ''This pot shows the imprint where the foot of another vessel sat on its side.''</p>
        <p>The obverse side offers one of the earliest Attic renderings of a rare myth: the capture of the wise old centaur Silenos. The god Hermes brings the prisoner Silenos to the Phrygian king Midas, who is seated on his throne. Hermes has bound Silenos' hands and tied a rope to one foot, which he holds like a leash. His right hand is raised in greeting to a winged goddess, perhaps Iris, who stands behind the king. Here the exuberance of triumph and dejection of defeat are captured in one graphic moment. The pot does not give the punch line: according to some accounts, Silenos, in his wisdom, was able to talk himself out of trouble. The estimate is $50,000 to $70,000.</p>
        <p>After Athenian vase painters had mastered the black-figure technique, they developed the red-figure technique around 530 B.C. The vase was painted black except for the figures, which were left natural red. Fine details were applied by brush. A vase that combines black and red-figured techniques is called bilingual.</p>
        <p>Lot 81 is a finely painted red-figure vase from the Classical period, fifth century B.C. It is a kylix, a shallow cup that has a frieze on the underside. The painting has been attributed to Douris, and the pot to Python.  The underside shows the women of Thebes dismembering King Pentheus, who had forbidden them to worship Dionysus. The women persisted, and when they discovered the king spying on them, literally tore him to bits. The drama is as striking as the technique.</p>
        <p>Sotheby's antiquities sale on Wednesday in New York features an exceptional bronze Roman head from about the first century. Consigned by the heirs of an Englishman, Hans Calmann, it is thought to be a copy of a lost Greek original by the sculptor Lysippos, the court portraitist of Alexander the Great, or by one of his contemporaries.</p>
        <p>Dick Keresy, the head of antiquities at Sotheby's, praised the piece as ''the most important classical bronze to come on the market in decades.'' It may have been cleaned in the 16th century and lacquered later, he said, but the original patina remains.</p>
        <p>''It is so lifelike it may be a portrait of a famous athlete in the fourth-century B.C,'' he said. The bronze has been known to collectors since it was acquired in the 18th century by the Venetian senator Bernardo Nani and is expected to fetch more than $1 million.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Show</p>
        <p>The summer antique fairs in the region outside New York City begin this weekend, with the Litchfield County Antiques Show in Connecticut. It opens tonight with a $75 benefit cocktail and buffet from 6:30 to 9:30 p.m. at the Goshen Fair Grounds on Route 63 and continues through Sunday.</p>
        <p>The 37 dealers include several top Americana specialists, like the Philadelphia textiles dealer M. Finkle &amp; Daughter and the furniture dealers Wayne Pratt, Thomas Schwenke, Anthony S. Werneke, Nathan Liverant &amp; Son, and Jeffrey Tillou. Tickets are $8. Information: (860) 567-0300.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
