<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sotheby's Plans Web Auction</title>
    <meta content="09INSI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000614T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Doyle, William, Galleries</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bonhams (London Dealer)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boisgirard (Paris Dealer)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frick Collection</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olsoff, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bailey, Colin D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DD103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sotheby's Plans Web Auction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; Sotheby's will hold annual February auction of contemporary art on Internet, rather than in Manahattan headquarters, to capitalize on recent success in selling lower-priced works online; dealers like Wendy Olsoff say bidders should have chance to see work in advance; photo; William Doyle Galleries and London partner Bonhams set up arrangement with Boisgirard of Paris, hoping that French government will eventually allow foreign auction houses to conduct sales in France; merger of firms started by former Sotheby's experts noted; Colin B Bailey of National Gallery of Canada is named chief curator of Frick (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sotheby's has decided not to hold its annual February auction of contemporary art in its York Avenue headquarters next year but instead to put it on Sothebys.com, its Internet site.</p>
        <p>This move allows the house to capitalize on its recent success in selling lower-priced contemporary art online. It is also a way of bolstering Sotheby's online business, as the company has had trouble obtaining enough art and objects to fill its dot-com sales, people close to the Internet business have said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sotheby's has decided not to hold its annual February auction of contemporary art in its York Avenue headquarters next year but instead to put it on Sothebys.com, its Internet site.</p>
        <p>This move allows the house to capitalize on its recent success in selling lower-priced contemporary art online. It is also a way of bolstering Sotheby's online business, as the company has had trouble obtaining enough art and objects to fill its dot-com sales, people close to the Internet business have said.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to get our customers to regularly check the Web,'' said Wendy Cromwell, a specialist in Sotheby's contemporary art department in New York. ''While they may begin looking at the site during sale times, they should be hunting for art there all year around.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cromwell said that since 30 percent of Sotheby's Internet buyers were new to the house, holding its February sale online would help tap a new and broader market.</p>
        <p>That sale has traditionally featured works valued at $20,000 and below, which happens to be the price range online buyers feel comfortable with, Ms. Cromwell said. But rather than offering art that can be seen only online, Sotheby's will put highlights from the February sale on view in its Manhattan galleries.</p>
        <p>The idea of buying art online without the opportunity to view it troubles many people in the art world. Jason Murison and Wendy Olsoff, owners of P.P.O.W., a 17-year-old SoHo gallery, for example, say that bidders should have an opportunity to view art before they buy it.</p>
        <p>So Ms. Olsoff proposed that Sothebys.com try something new: offer  work by a group of emerging artists that could also be viewed directly in  their studios. ''@ the Artist's Studio'' -- works on paper by 20 young artists -- will be on view at P.P.O.W., 476 Broome Street, through July 7. The exhibition and sale is also online through June 29 at Sothebys.com.</p>
        <p>''I've been looking at all the e-commerce sites, and they're more like stores with stuff than organized, curated shows,'' Ms. Olsoff said. ''I approached Sotheby's to see if we could collaborate on a project, since they have the brand-name recognition on the Web and we'd like to try to sell art online.''</p>
        <p>''These are all young artists coming out of places like Yale and Columbia,'' Ms. Olsoff said. ''While we don't represent any of them, we always show young artists in the gallery since everyone loves to discover new talent.''</p>
        <p>Limiting the sale to works on paper was a way of keeping prices down, Ms. Olsoff added. Prices range from about $300 to $4,500. The Web site will include shots of each artist's studio along with comprehensive images of the work offered and artists' biographies.</p>
        <p>Why isn't Sotheby's showing the art in its newly expanded galleries instead of at P.P.O.W., especially since it has little to exhibit during the summer? Ms. Cromwell said, ''This is a curated show and it should be in a gallery setting.''</p>
        <p>Art from that sale that is not bought through the Web site by June 29 will be for sale at P.P.O.W. until the gallery show closes on July 7.</p>
        <p>Alliances With French</p>
        <p>Bargaining that the French government will eventually change its laws to allow non-French auction houses to conduct sales in France, American and English houses are forming alliances with Paris-based companies.</p>
        <p>William Doyle Galleries, based in Manhattan, and its London partner, Bonhams, announced this week that they had entered into an arrangement with Boisgirard, the Paris house.</p>
        <p>Doyle and Bonhams have worked together for several years conducting joint sales, promoting each other's auctions and pooling resources to attract business. With Boisgirard in the group, they will offer art and antiques through the French company both in New York and in London. Works of art from Paris will be offered at Doyle and Bonhams.</p>
        <p>The three companies also plan to link their Web sites. ''It's what every company has to do these days to broaden its base of both buyers and sellers,'' said Kathleen M. Doyle, chairwoman of William Doyle Galleries.</p>
        <p>Doyle and Bonhams are not the first to make inroads in Paris. Francois Pinault, the French investor who bought Christie's, acquired Paris-based Piasa in February. Last year Bernard Arnault's LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton bought the auctioner Phillips, which in turn acquired Tajan, France's largest auction house, this year.</p>
        <p>Combining Strengths</p>
        <p>Two powerful companies started by former Sotheby's experts -- Simon de Pury &amp; Daniella Luxembourg in Geneva and Lucy Mitchell-Innes &amp; David Nash in New York -- are joining forces. While the two are not formally merging, they will work together to buy and sell Impressionist, modern and contemporary art.</p>
        <p>The two firms handle art purchases and sales for some of the world's biggest collectors, including Ronald Lauder, the cosmetic's heir; David Geffen, the entertainment industry billionaire; the publisher S. I. Newhouse Jr.; and Paul Allen, the co-founder of Microsoft.</p>
        <p>''Our combined strengths have great advantages,'' Mr. de Pury said. ''When we started de Pury &amp; Luxembourg, I said I hoped one plus one would make more than two; now I hope two plus two will be more than four.''</p>
        <p>He and Ms. Luxembourg have worked with Ms. Mitchell-Innes and Mr. Nash for a long time, he said, adding: ''We have great mutual trust.''</p>
        <p>Appointments at Frick</p>
        <p>News of appointments are rare at the Frick Collection, whose staff is small and has little turnover. But this week the museum announced  that Colin B. Bailey, deputy director and chief curator of the National Gallery of Canada, would become the Frick's chief curator. He replaces Edgar Munhall, who has retired.  Barbara O. Roberts, an independent conservator, will become the Frick's conservator, replacing Sveteslao Hlopoff, who also retired.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART  Correction:  June 14, 2000, Wednesday  The Inside Art column in Weekend on Friday misstated the position of Jason Murison at P.P.O.W. Gallery in SoHo and omitted the name of one owner. Mr. Murison is a curator; the co-owner, with Penny Pilkington, is Wendy Olsoff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 14, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The Inside Art column in Weekend on Friday misstated the position of Jason Murison at P.P.O.W. Gallery in SoHo and omitted the name of one owner. Mr. Murison is a curator; the co-owner, with Penny Pilkington, is Wendy Olsoff.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
