<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Review Initial Handling of Stabbing Case</title>
    <meta content="09STAB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ortiz, Cesar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DB113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Review Initial Handling of Stabbing Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police officials are reviewing whether a sergeant who responded to a report of a stabbing in a Bronx apartment failed to properly investigate the case by deciding not to force open the door of the apartment; Cesar Ortiz was found dead in apartment 16 hours later (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police officials are reviewing whether a sergeant who responded to a report of a stabbing in a Bronx apartment failed to properly investigate the case by deciding not to force open the door of the apartment where, 16 hours later, a man was found dead.</p>
        <p>Although there were bloody footprints in the hallway outside the apartment in the Bronx River Houses, the sergeant who responded early Tuesday morning to an anonymous 911 call decided not to force the door, officials said, because he was not sure the substance was blood, the neighbors said they had not heard any commotion and one said the family was away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police officials are reviewing whether a sergeant who responded to a report of a stabbing in a Bronx apartment failed to properly investigate the case by deciding not to force open the door of the apartment where, 16 hours later, a man was found dead.</p>
        <p>Although there were bloody footprints in the hallway outside the apartment in the Bronx River Houses, the sergeant who responded early Tuesday morning to an anonymous 911 call decided not to force the door, officials said, because he was not sure the substance was blood, the neighbors said they had not heard any commotion and one said the family was away.</p>
        <p>But at 4:40 the next afternoon, the body of the man, Cesar Ortiz, 36, was found face down on the kitchen floor when his brother returned to the apartment, 6B at 1440 Bronx River Avenue. He had been stabbed in the head, neck and torso, and his arms and legs had been bound with duct tape, the police said. The apartment had also been ransacked, they said.</p>
        <p>Officials said the Bronx Investigations Unit, which reviews how officers follow procedures, is examining the actions of the sergeant, who was not identified. They said the unit has not determined whether the officer, who is with the 43rd Precinct, made any mistakes.</p>
        <p>The authorities said it was unclear whether Mr. Ortiz was still alive when officers first went to the apartment. A neighbor told investigators that footprints were in the hallway as early as 10 p.m. Monday, nearly three hours before 911 was called, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said they believed that Mr. Ortiz was apartment sitting for his mother, who they said was in the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>Officials said part of the confusion was caused by the incorrect address the caller initially gave to 911. The police said dispatchers later clarified the address.</p>
        <p>When the police went to the apartment just before 1 a.m., the sergeant was not sure whether the markings on the floor were blood stains, and neighbors said they had not heard a struggle, said Lt. Stephen Biegel, a police spokesman. One neighbor also told the police that the family who lived in the apartment was away, so the sergeant decided the evidence was insufficient to warrant forcing the door, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
