<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Duty for the Democrats' Main Money Man: Running the Convention</title>
    <meta content="Y09DEMS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONFIDANT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Natta, Don Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcauliffe, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D6103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Duty for the Democrats' Main Money Man: Running the Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON VAN NATTA Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Natta, Don Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terry McAuliffe, Democratic Party's most prodigious fund-raiser, after personal appeal by Vice Pres Al Gore, agrees to serve as chairman of Democratic National Convention, which is struggling to overcome fund-raising difficulties and bickering among its organizers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a personal appeal by Vice President Al Gore, Terry McAuliffe, the Democratic Party's most prodigious fund-raiser, has agreed to serve as chairman of the Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles, which has struggled to overcome fund-raising difficulties and bickering among its organizers.</p>
        <p>Several Democratic officials said Mr. Gore phoned Mr. McAuliffe on Wednesday morning to ask him to succeed Roy Romer, the former Colorado governor, who was appointed superintendent of the Los Angeles school system on Tuesday. Mr. McAuliffe instantly agreed to the request, the officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a personal appeal by Vice President Al Gore, Terry McAuliffe, the Democratic Party's most prodigious fund-raiser, has agreed to serve as chairman of the Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles, which has struggled to overcome fund-raising difficulties and bickering among its organizers.</p>
        <p>Several Democratic officials said Mr. Gore phoned Mr. McAuliffe on Wednesday morning to ask him to succeed Roy Romer, the former Colorado governor, who was appointed superintendent of the Los Angeles school system on Tuesday. Mr. McAuliffe instantly agreed to the request, the officials said.</p>
        <p>For months, senior party officials have worried that this summer's convention could turn out to be a dud, now that Mr. Gore has the nomination wrapped up. Several party activists had quietly lobbied for Mr. McAuliffe's appointment, saying they needed his enthusiasm to help energize the four-day nominating convention scheduled to begin  Aug. 14 at the Staples Center in downtown Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''Terry's commitment to the Democratic Party is unprecedented,'' Lydia Camarillo, the convention's chief executive, said today. ''Time and again he has demonstrated his deep devotion to our party's goals and efforts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McAuliffe is the most prolific fund-raiser in the history of American politics. He is also one of President Clinton's closest friends. Most recently, Mr. McAuliffe was chairman of the Democratic National Committee's gala at the MCI Sports Center here on May 23. The event, a tribute to Mr. Clinton, attracted a sell-out crowd of 13,625 people and raised a record $26.5 million for the Democratic Party. Most of that money will benefit Mr. Gore's presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. McAuliffe estimated that he had personally raised at least $300 million for Mr. Clinton and Democratic causes, including the president's 1997 inaugural, the White House millennium celebration, the president's legal defense fund, Mr. Clinton's library in Little Rock, Ark., and the current campaigns of Mr. Gore and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McAuliffe expects his convention duties, unlike those earlier assignments, to require spending very little time raising money. Democratic Party officials hope that Mr. McAuliffe can bring to the Staples Center the pep-rally ambience that existed at last month's gala here.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy to be joining a terrific convention team,'' Mr. McAuliffe said today. ''And I'm looking forward to working with them to make this the greatest convention in the history of American politics.''</p>
        <p>Last winter, senior party officials and Gore allies were concerned that the convention could turn into a disaster. Fund-raising was -- and still is -- behind schedule; $7 million still needs to be raised by the host committee. The billionaires who had helped lure the convention to Los Angeles have complained among themselves. Unions facing contract negotiations had warned of possible labor unrest.</p>
        <p>And to top it off, the city's public officials were reeling earlier this year from the ugly headlines generated by the worst police corruption scandal to hit the city in decades. There was widespread worry that the convention would not be a worthy successor to the last Democratic convention in Los Angeles: the 1960 party gathering that nominated John F. Kennedy for president amid great excitement.</p>
        <p>But today, Democratic officials said the convention team had made great organizational strides in the past two months. Convention officials said they were looking forward to working with Mr. McAuliffe.</p>
        <p>''His stock is trading at an all-time high,'' said James Carville, the Democratic consultant. ''He brings some panache and a lot of enthusiasm to the convention.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONFIDANT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
