<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazil Opens Files on Region's Abuses in Age of Dictators</title>
    <meta content="Y09BRA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Operation Condor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardoso, Fernando Henrique (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DF113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazil Opens Files on Region's Abuses in Age of Dictators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Military dictatorships of South America during 1970's organized secret program, known as Operation Condor, to kidnap and kill one another's opponents; now the democratic governments that succeeded them are joining together, albeit tentatively and somewhat reluctantly, in effort to determine true extent and toll of that collaboration; Brazil's high court recently ordered that all documents relating to Operation Condor and to case of three Argentinians who disappeared in Brazil when both countries were under military rule be released to Argentinian authorities; rights group say that government of Brazilian Pres Fernando Henrique Cardoso is being too slow in producing documents (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Throughout the 1970's, the military dictatorships of South America organized a secret program, known as Operation Condor, to kidnap and kill one another's opponents. Now the democratic governments that succeeded them are joining together, albeit tentatively and somewhat reluctantly, in an effort to untangle the true extent and toll of that sordid collaboration.</p>
        <p>The sudden burst of activity is the result of an Argentine judge's request, made last year, for information about three Argentine citizens who disappeared here when both countries were under military rule. To the surprise of almost everyone, Brazil's highest court recently ordered that all documents relating to the case and to Operation Condor be supplied to Argentine authorities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Throughout the 1970's, the military dictatorships of South America organized a secret program, known as Operation Condor, to kidnap and kill one another's opponents. Now the democratic governments that succeeded them are joining together, albeit tentatively and somewhat reluctantly, in an effort to untangle the true extent and toll of that sordid collaboration.</p>
        <p>The sudden burst of activity is the result of an Argentine judge's request, made last year, for information about three Argentine citizens who disappeared here when both countries were under military rule. To the surprise of almost everyone, Brazil's highest court recently ordered that all documents relating to the case and to Operation Condor be supplied to Argentine authorities.</p>
        <p>According to historians and human rights groups, Operation Condor was a cooperative effort that involved the military, the police and intelligence forces of Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Paraguay and Uruguay. Each nation's ''apparatus of repression'' exchanged information with its counterparts in neighboring countries and kidnapped, tortured and killed guerrillas and other exiles from those countries on behalf of its colleagues.</p>
        <p>In Argentina, for example, at least 118 exiled Uruguayans, 51 Paraguayans, 49 Chileans and 9 Brazilians were ''disappeared,'' according to tallies compiled by human rights groups.</p>
        <p>Operation Condor, named for the large bird that flies above the peaks of the Andes, appears to have been a Chilean initiative, and interest in its activities has heightened as a result of the judicial case against Gen. Augusto Pinochet, that country's former dictator.</p>
        <p>Fewer exiles were killed here than in Chile or Argentina. But Brazil's military dictatorship began much earlier, in 1964, and recently unearthed documents indicate that Brazil's security apparatus began training police and military intelligence from neighboring countries as early as 1969.</p>
        <p>The issue is one of particular interest to President Fernando Henrique Cardoso and his cabinet. As Georges Lamaziere, the president's press secretary, noted recently of the current administration, ''a good number of its members were victims of previous governments,'' including Mr. Cardoso himself, who spent several years in exile in Chile and France.</p>
        <p>''Fortunately, even though the memories are painful, we can regard this as a page that has been turned but should not be forgotten,'' Mr. Cardoso said last month in his first public comment on the matter. His government has also said that Brazil would pay a $72,500 indemnity to the families of the three missing Argentine leftists, who are said to have been executed here.</p>
        <p>Rights groups, however, have complained that the Cardoso government has been slow to produce documents that would clarify other incidents still being investigated. Brazil's armed forces, backed by the minister of defense, Geraldo Quintao, have said variously that requested documents never existed, that they appear to have been destroyed, or that to make them public would violate a law requiring that such records be kept secret for 30 years.</p>
        <p>''I don't see why they should be opened,'' Mr. Quintao, a civilian, said last week. ''No country opens its intelligence archives immediately after the fact.''</p>
        <p>The inability of the armed forces to produce relevant records is surprising in view of the spate of investigative reports that in recent weeks have filled the pages of Brazilian newspapers and magazines. All of the accounts are based on official documents that have been leaked to reporters, and some include detailed interviews with former military officers who remember specific episodes of cooperation with Argentine, Paraguayan and Uruguayan authorities.</p>
        <p>None of the material that has come to light thus far indicates the direct involvement of any American government agency in Operation Condor. But the United States was clearly aware of the effort: the first known mention of Operation Condor came in a 1976 cable from the American Embassy in Buenos Aires, and American agents worked closely with security officials in the region, many of whom had studied at the United States-run School of the Americas.</p>
        <p>Lawyers and human rights groups, along with relatives of the disappeared who want to make peace with the past, are eager to examine the Brazilian records.</p>
        <p>Though Paraguay made public thousands of pages of police files in 1992, no country involved in Operation Condor has yet opened its military archives for inspection, and the originals of many documents are believed to have vanished.</p>
        <p>Inspired by the Pinochet case and using the Paraguayan records and material recently uncovered here, Brazilian and Paraguayan lawyers and human rights groups are seeking to bring Gen. Alfredo Stroessner, Paraguay's former dictator, to justice. Overthrown in 1989 after 35 years in power, General Stroessner now lives in exile in Brazil, but an effort is under way here to have him expelled or extradited to Paraguay.</p>
        <p>The flurry of investigations has also revived speculation about the death of Joao Goulart, who was president when the military seized power here in 1964.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goulart died in exile in Argentina in December 1976 of what was officially said to be a heart attack, but no autopsy was performed, and his family had only limited access to his body when it was returned to Brazil for burial.</p>
        <p>The Goulart family has always suspected that the former president may have been poisoned or that someone tampered with his medicine, fears that have been fed by the recent publication of a September 1976 document that shows the military here was convinced that he was about to return to Brazil. In an effort to clarify the circumstances of Mr. Goulart's death, a congressional inquiry has just begun, and family members this week authorized the exhumation of his remains.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
