<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faithful Homage (Crash! Kapow!)</title>
    <meta content="09GONE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sena, Dominic</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckheimer, Jerry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cage, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jolie, Angelina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gone in 60 Seconds (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDF103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faithful Homage (Crash! Kapow!)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews Jerry Bruckheimer's remake of 1974 movie Gone in 60 Seconds; Dominic Sena directs and Nicolas Cage and Angelina Jolie star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Apparently because the rights to good films were unavailable, the producer Jerry Bruckheimer decided to remake the underwhelming auto theft spectacular ''Gone in 60 Seconds'' instead. By cranking up the action and adding a cast of magnetic, capable actors -- the Bruckheimer treatment -- he almost achieves alchemy. It's only gold-filled instead of pure gold, but that's quite an accomplishment. This new version is mindless hot-rodding fun, especially for those with a weakness for vintage cars hurtling down city streets, a group whose members include -- sigh -- me.</p>
        <p>The original ''Gone'' (1974) was so slender a conception that the title seemed to refer to the amount of time it might linger in a viewer's memory. It was literally a redneck car-crash spectacular written and directed by its ''star,'' H. B. Halicki, whose role consisted of stealing cars and spending the refreshingly plot-free last half-hour outdriving every law enforcement officer in the contiguous United States during a lead-foot pursuit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Apparently because the rights to good films were unavailable, the producer Jerry Bruckheimer decided to remake the underwhelming auto theft spectacular ''Gone in 60 Seconds'' instead. By cranking up the action and adding a cast of magnetic, capable actors -- the Bruckheimer treatment -- he almost achieves alchemy. It's only gold-filled instead of pure gold, but that's quite an accomplishment. This new version is mindless hot-rodding fun, especially for those with a weakness for vintage cars hurtling down city streets, a group whose members include -- sigh -- me.</p>
        <p>The original ''Gone'' (1974) was so slender a conception that the title seemed to refer to the amount of time it might linger in a viewer's memory. It was literally a redneck car-crash spectacular written and directed by its ''star,'' H. B. Halicki, whose role consisted of stealing cars and spending the refreshingly plot-free last half-hour outdriving every law enforcement officer in the contiguous United States during a lead-foot pursuit.</p>
        <p>The phrase ''influential genre film'' was appended to the original ''Gone,'' and that usage might be as entertaining as anything in the movie. Ron Howard began his directing career in 1977 with a rip-off homage called ''Grand Theft Auto,'' in which he also starred, and the climactic chase in the 1980 ''Blues Brothers'' also stands in Mr. Halicki's shadow.</p>
        <p>Time was that actors would begin in movies like ''Gone,'' or ''Grand Theft Auto,'' and then go on to much more substantial work, like pictures with a plot and a budget. The original ''Gone'' belonged to that vanishing breed of exploitation picture in which you may have spent more to get in to see it than the filmmaker spent creating it. Now actors start their careers in beguiling low-budget films and leap into big-budget movies that have less narrative than a Gap ad.</p>
        <p>Nicolas Cage, whose hammy intensity and baleful, unpredictable presence was a godsend for directors looking to bring power and presence to their films, is just one of those actors. But he's not alone in the ''Gone in 60 Seconds'' remake. The cast also includes Angelina Jolie, Robert Duvall -- so far, more Oscar winners than you'd see at a Democratic fund-raiser -- Delroy Lindo, Giovanni Ribisi, Will Patton, Christopher Eccleston and Chi McBride.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cage -- who, like Ms. Jolie, has gone prematurely blond here -- has the tough-guy moniker Memphis Raines. And although the name sounds like something you'd expect from a roadie for Willie Nelson, Memphis is the world's best car thief, retired. He's pulled back into the game when his kid brother, Kip (Mr. Ribisi), botches a huge car theft he'd been hired to pull off by the mobster Raymond Calitri (Mr. Eccleston). So Memphis has to give up his lucrative go-cart business and head back to L.A. to steal 50 rare cars in less than four days or Calitri will bust a cap in Kip.</p>
        <p>''He's a jackal tearing at the soft underbelly of our fair town,'' one of Memphis's pals says of Calitri.</p>
        <p>Now, you might ask yourself, would a seasoned veteran like Memphis take the word of a violent thug like Calitri about not killing his brother? Why would Kip be dumb enough to get involved with such a guy? Those questions will have to be answered in the DVD director's cut or the sequel because ''Gone'' never gets around to them.</p>
        <p>Memphis calls up his old buddies Otto (Mr. Duvall) and Donny (Mr. McBride) for help. ''Can't be done,'' Otto growls when approached, before jumping aboard to help out and barking out that laugh that's ready to be put under glass at the Smithsonian.</p>
        <p>There are other complications. When Detective Castlebeck (Mr. Lindo) sees Memphis back in town, the cop knows something's afoot -- or acar -- so he tails the returning master car thief. A rival gangster, played in an unbilled cameo by Master P, whose performance is the most riveting thing he's done on screen since ''I Got the Hook Up,'' also wants to break off a piece of Memphis. And when Kip's boys -- the comic TJ Cross, the indie actor James Duval and Scott Caan, who's on his way to becoming a regular member of the Bruckheimer repertory company -- decide to help Memphis's old-school crew, things really get nutty.</p>
        <p>Like all of Mr. Bruckheimer's other films, ''Gone'' looks as if it were filmed on alternate Earth, where it's perpetually dusk, so that the warming golden-red rays of the sun can light the concaves of his characters' cheekbones.</p>
        <p>''You look so good,'' Memphis's mother (Grace Zabriskie) tells him, and she's right. Everyone looks good in this movie. The skies seem sepia-toned, even at night. All the smog from the speeding autos may make the air in Southern California unsafe to breathe, but it is being used to good effect: a filter for the cinematographer Paul Cameron's lighting scheme.</p>
        <p>This may be the most mannered over-the-top cast in a movie in some time; Mr. Ribisi draws attention to this by offering a very funny imitation of Mr. Cage's Northern California stoner's drawl. Mr. Eccleston's turn as the roiling supervillain is reminiscent of the kind of thing that Mr. Cage used to do in his younger days.</p>
        <p>The grandiose riffing and shiny machismo of Mr. Bruckheimer's work can be engaging, as in ''The Rock,'' and is occasionally here. All of the talent he manages to assemble can be impressive, but in ''Gone'' it seems like a trial run for a feature film version of ''The A-Team.'' Just like that old action series, the astonishing stunts in ''Gone'' become abstractions that result in injuries that could be fixed with a little Bactine and a Band-Aid.</p>
        <p>The director Dominic Sena layers the picture in the kind of posh lacquer that one comes to expect from a Bruckheimer production; some may find the subject matter appropriate, since his movies gleam as if they'd been buffed with 25 coats of Turtle Wax.</p>
        <p>For those who might look to the cars as the real stars of the picture, even this selection is smart but impersonal, a pricey lineup you might encounter in front of Puffy Combs's place in the Hamptons. Some of the choices will seem questionable and may provoke discussion about the classic cars that have been left out of the picture.</p>
        <p>Yet the characters have so little personality that the only emotional reaction ''Gone'' got from the audience members I saw it with was when the side-view mirror had been knocked off a 1967 Shelby Mustang. They gasped as if Bambi's mother had been shot again.</p>
        <p>''Gone in 60 Seconds'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes an onslaught of car chases and wreckage.</p>
        <p>GONE IN 60 SECONDS</p>
        <p>Directed by Dominic Sena; written by Scott Rosenberg; director of photography, Paul Cameron; edited by Tom Muldoon and Chris Lebenzon; music by Trevor Rabin; production designer, Jeff Mann; produced by Jerry Bruckheimer and Mike Stenson; released by Touchstone Pictures. Running time: 119 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Nicolas Cage (Memphis Raines), Giovanni Ribisi (Kip Raines), Angelina Jolie (Sara Wayland), TJ Cross (Mirror Man), William Lee Scott (Toby), Scott Caan (Tumbler), James Duval (Freb), Will Patton (Atley Jackson), Delroy Lindo (Detective Roland Castlebeck), Robert Duvall (Otto Halliwell), Christopher Eccleston (Raymond Calitri), Chi McBride (Donny Astricky), Timothy Olyphant (Detective Drycoff), Grace Zabriskie (Helen Raines) and Master P (Johnny B.).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
