<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commencement; Hold On to Individuality, Levy Advises</title>
    <meta content="09COMM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">College of Staten Island</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DE113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commencement; Hold On to Individuality, Levy Advises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O Levy addresses graduates of College of Staten Island (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy told graduates at the College of Staten Island yesterday to take advantage of the growing globalization of the economy and the increasing interconnectedness of the world's people. But he warned them not to relinquish their privacy and individualism.</p>
        <p>''The world has become smaller, the Internet has pulled us all together and our economies have all become one,'' Mr. Levy told the roughly 1,800 graduates gathered on a broad lawn at the college, which is part of the City University of New York. ''How do we protect our spiritualism from the relentless march of the logical force of the future? How do we stand up and be ourselves?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy told graduates at the College of Staten Island yesterday to take advantage of the growing globalization of the economy and the increasing interconnectedness of the world's people. But he warned them not to relinquish their privacy and individualism.</p>
        <p>''The world has become smaller, the Internet has pulled us all together and our economies have all become one,'' Mr. Levy told the roughly 1,800 graduates gathered on a broad lawn at the college, which is part of the City University of New York. ''How do we protect our spiritualism from the relentless march of the logical force of the future? How do we stand up and be ourselves?''</p>
        <p>One way, Mr. Levy said, is to continue pursuing a ''moral education'' after leaving school.</p>
        <p>''It means intellectual honesty,'' he said. ''It means having a sense of vision. It means having a sense of creativity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, whose goals as chancellor include recruiting hundreds of qualified teachers to help turn around the city's failing schools, also stressed the importance of teaching in urban schools and compared it to volunteering in the civil rights movement or the Peace Corps. ''Education, in my judgment, is the key social issue of the day,'' Mr. Levy said. ''Education and teachers generally are the vessels by which we convey civilization.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy thanked the dozens of  graduates who had majored in education, and in particular, Maria Gusenfitter, the valedictorian of the college's class of 2000. In a speech to her classmates, Ms. Gusenfitter told of her struggles raising her son Jack, who was born deaf, on her own as she worked toward her bachelor's degree.</p>
        <p>''Despair can whisper lies about what will become of you,'' Ms. Gusenfitter said, describing her depression when her husband abandoned her after their son's birth. But Ms. Gusenfitter's family rallied around her, she said, baby-sitting for her son while she attended class and making sure she had transportation to get there.</p>
        <p>''Somehow this love, if you let it in, can pierce the darkness and the coldness,'' she said, her voice breaking.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gusenfitter, who plans to pursue a master's degree in elementary or special education, said she wanted to teach partly to help troubled students through tumultuous times.</p>
        <p>''I will remind them that darkness is but for a while,'' she said, ''and light will come again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
