<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin to Visit North Korea; U.S. ABM Plan May Be Target</title>
    <meta content="Y09PUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D7103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin to Visit North Korea; U.S. ABM Plan May Be Target</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin plans to visit North Korea next month, move that underscores his active foreign policy and seems calculated to counter Clinton administration's plan for a national missile defense; announcement comes on heels of Putin's meeting with Pres Clinton in Moscow, in which the two leaders found themselves at odds over administration's plan for a limited antimissile system; Korea visit is expected to provide Putin with opportunity to make case that diplomacy, not missile defense, is the way to cope with emerging missile threat from North Korea and to challenge idea that North Korea is a 'rogue state,' description that US has used to justify its antimissile plans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin plans to visit North Korea next month, a move that underscores his active foreign policy and seems calculated to counter the Clinton administration's plan for a national missile defense.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said today that it would be the first trip by a Russian leader to the North Korean capital, Pyongyang.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin plans to visit North Korea next month, a move that underscores his active foreign policy and seems calculated to counter the Clinton administration's plan for a national missile defense.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said today that it would be the first trip by a Russian leader to the North Korean capital, Pyongyang.</p>
        <p>''This is an unprecedented event, a bold step, as no head of state from our country has ever been in North Korea, neither in Soviet nor in Russian times,'' Georgi Toloraya, an official in the Foreign Ministry, told the newspaper Vremya Novostei.</p>
        <p>The announcement comes on the heels of Mr. Putin's meeting with President Clinton in Moscow, in which the two leaders found themselves at odds over the administration's plans for a limited antimissile system.</p>
        <p>The Korea visit meeting will provide Mr. Putin with an opportunity to make his case that diplomacy, not missile defense, is the way to cope with an emerging missile threat from North Korea.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin can also use the visit to challenge the idea that North Korea is an irrational ''rogue state,'' a description the United States has used to justify its antimissile plans.</p>
        <p>Those Russian themes are likely to resonate in Western Europe, where the Western allies remain very anxious that the administration's plan will start an arms race and leave them unprotected.</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mr. Putin took his campaign to Italy, where he urged Europeans to support a Russian alternative to the American plan.</p>
        <p>American officials were caught by surprise by the Russian announcement. They said they welcomed the visit as way to end North Korea's  isolation.</p>
        <p>''We continue to believe that dialogue among all countries in the region contributes to peace and security on the Korean peninsula and beyond,'' a State Department spokesman said.</p>
        <p>According to the Japanese media, Mr. Putin's visit is scheduled to take place in mid-July, just before the summit meeting of the leading industrial democracies in Okinawa, Japan, from July 21 to 23.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said Moscow had become more interested in the situation on the Korean peninsula as a result of the summit meeting between North and South Korea scheduled for early next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toloraya, who is deputy director of the Foreign Ministry's Asia department, said that the Kremlin had proposed the visit and that the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il, had issued a formal invitation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toloraya said Moscow wanted to assure the North Koreans that Moscow did not favor a unified Korea dominated by Seoul. Such fears have grown in Pyongyang, he said, as Russia has developed economic and political ties with South Korea.</p>
        <p>''That is not the case,'' Mr. Toloraya said in his newspaper interview. ''We consider it necessary for the two Korean states to coexist for a long time.''</p>
        <p>The American antiballistic missile plan is very much on the agenda, according to the Russians. Mr. Toloraya said the Russians and North Koreans would have a general discussion on ''how we can act together in the world situation, including in connection with U.S. plans for ABM.''</p>
        <p>In an indirect swipe at Washington, he said Russia's new assertive role in foreign policy had the potential to upset ''somebody else's cards.''</p>
        <p>Russia fears that the limited defense the United States is planning is just the first phase in a larger system that will eventually counter Russia's strategic forces. Washington's goal has been to overcome Russian suspicions and persuade the Kremlin to amend the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty.</p>
        <p>That would enable the United States to develop a limited defensive system, which could include the deployment of 100 interceptors and the construction of radar in Alaska.</p>
        <p>At the summit meeting between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Putin, Russia acknowledged that there was an emerging missile threat from nations like North Korea. Still, the Russians insist that the threat is not as worrisome as the United States says.  And while the Americans have insisted that an antimissile system is needed, the Russians have urged diplomacy.</p>
        <p>The United States has persuaded North Korea to accept a moratorium on the test-firing of long-range missiles. That has precluded Pyongyang from testing its Taepo Dong-2, a two-stage missile that Washington fears might eventually be developed as an intercontinental missile.</p>
        <p>There have been several indications of growing ties between Russia and North Korea. The Russian foreign minister, Igor S. Ivanov, paid a recent visit to North Korea. And a North Korean delegation arrived at Sakhalin Island in Russia's Far East to discuss joint construction projects, the Russian news agency Itar-Tass said today.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Pyongyang Reports New Drought</p>
        <p>SEOUL, South Korea, June 8 (Reuters) -- North Korea, now dependent on food aid for survival, today reported that another drought had hit all parts of the country, devastating spring crops.</p>
        <p>The official Korean Central News Agency said ''drought and heat persist in all parts'' of the country. ''Because of a long spell of drought and heat, paddy fields are parched and rice-transplantation is suspended in some areas,'' it said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
