<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agreement to Balance Budget Eludes Officials in Nassau</title>
    <meta content="09NASS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3DA113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agreement to Balance Budget Eludes Officials in Nassau</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County officials fail to reach final agreement on $50 million in recurring spending cuts and new revenues needed to help balance this year's budget (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite negotiations that continued into the early morning hours, Nassau County officials failed to reach a final agreement today on $50 million in recurring spending cuts and new revenues needed to help balance this year's budget.</p>
        <p>Nassau County's leaders had hoped to have a deal by the time they met here this afternoon with Frank G. Zarb, who is Gov. George E. Pataki's special adviser on the county's fiscal crisis. But officials said that while they had reached a tentative agreement on $50 million in cuts and revenues, some of them will not recur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite negotiations that continued into the early morning hours, Nassau County officials failed to reach a final agreement today on $50 million in recurring spending cuts and new revenues needed to help balance this year's budget.</p>
        <p>Nassau County's leaders had hoped to have a deal by the time they met here this afternoon with Frank G. Zarb, who is Gov. George E. Pataki's special adviser on the county's fiscal crisis. But officials said that while they had reached a tentative agreement on $50 million in cuts and revenues, some of them will not recur.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zarb asked the parties to keep working and scheduled another meeting for Monday.</p>
        <p>County leaders said they remained optimistic.</p>
        <p>''The meeting today has clearly indicated that a tremendous amount of progress has been made,'' said Thomas S. Gulotta, a Republican who is the county executive. ''We have more work to do. We have committed to continue work throughout the weekend and it is our objective to have the final resolution in place sometime Monday.''</p>
        <p>And the usually warring factions of the county's divided government -- Mr. Gulotta, Judith A. Jacobs, a Democrat and the presiding officer of the county Legislature, and John Ciotti, the deputy minority leader on the Legislature -- made a rare move by appearing together afterward and praising one another.</p>
        <p>The hitch in the proceedings stems from two problems. One is  that the parties are still arguing over several cost-cutting proposals, including a Democratic plan to lay off nonunion county workers and a Republican counter-plan to offer early retirement incentives. The other problem is that many of the $50.2 million in savings and revenues agreed on so far are one-shot deals that will not recur.</p>
        <p>The county can use nonrecurring measures to plug its hole this year, officials said, but it must balance them with recurring savings and revenues next year.</p>
        <p>All told, Ms. Jacobs said, county officials have agreed on roughly $43 million in recurring items for 2001. The county faces a tough road ahead. Once its leaders agree on the $50 million in cuts and revenues for this year, they must find $70 million more in recurring cuts and revenues for each of the next three years. Officials warn that the cuts could be painful.</p>
        <p>And a June 30 deadline is looming. Standard &amp; Poor's, the credit rating agency, has threatened that if the county does not show significant improvement by then, it will downgrade the county's bond rating to junk status.</p>
        <p>County officials said they were confident that they could agree on cuts by Monday. Ms. Jacobs said she got a good omen while taking a break from the budget talks on Wednesday for some chicken lo mein. Her fortune cookie read: ''Negotiations move along smoothly. The outcome is favorable.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
