<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Agrees On Plan to Aid Nassau County</title>
    <meta content="09ALBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buffalo (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Buffalo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DA113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1198" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Agrees On Plan to Aid Nassau County</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George E Pataki and State Legislature agree to spend $105 million to bail out Nassau County and impose state oversight of county spending; lawmakers also agree to let New York City increase its borrowing by $4 billion, skirting a legal restriction that could have put a halt to city's construction projects by end of year; overall agreement also provides $45 million in aid to schools in Buffalo and $10 million to schools in Yonkers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After weeks of brinkmanship, Gov. George E. Pataki and the Legislature have agreed to spend $105 million to bail out Nassau County and impose state oversight of county spending, in an effort to avert financial collapse in one of the nation's wealthiest regions.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers also agreed to let New York City increase its borrowing by $4 billion, skirting a legal restriction that could have put a halt to the city's construction projects by the end of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After weeks of brinkmanship, Gov. George E. Pataki and the Legislature have agreed to spend $105 million to bail out Nassau County and impose state oversight of county spending, in an effort to avert financial collapse in one of the nation's wealthiest regions.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers also agreed to let New York City increase its borrowing by $4 billion, skirting a legal restriction that could have put a halt to the city's construction projects by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Both the New York City and Nassau County measures were part of a broad package to aid local governments, including the troubled school systems in Buffalo and Yonkers, that had been linked to each other in the annual frenzy of horse-trading as the Legislature nears the end of its session.</p>
        <p>Having racked up huge deficits in a booming economy, and threatened with having its bonds downgraded to junk status, Nassau County will have to make deep budget cuts in return for the state aid. It also faces the continued threat that the state will take absolute control of the county's finances. The conditions of the deal will force Nassau to pare back one of the most generous arrays of public services -- in schools, parks, police protection, among others -- anywhere in the country.</p>
        <p>''They should be able to do it,'' said State Senator Dean G. Skelos, a Republican from Nassau. ''They have no choice. Albany has forced the local officials to end the political gridlock that existed in Nassau County, and to start meaningful, structural reform.''</p>
        <p>The county's financial troubles, and attempts last year to deal with them by imposing a tax on real estate sales, prompted a backlash against County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta and the Republican machine that has governed Nassau almost uninterrupted since the county was created in 1898. Last November, Democrats took control of the County Legislature for the first time, and Republican state legislators from the county fear that the rebellion could spread to their races.</p>
        <p>The bailout is essentially the one proposed last month by Mr. Pataki, with minor revisions. Winning approval for it is a victory for him, but it comes with potential perils. As the author of the plan and the person who appoints most of the oversight board, he stands to collect much of the credit if the county gets back on its feet, and much of the blame if it does not.</p>
        <p>Under the deal, the state will give the county $105 million outright over the next five years, including $30 million this year. It is an extraordinary step -- New York City received only loans, not gifts, from the state during its fiscal crisis, and when Orange County, Calif., went bankrupt in 1994, it pulled itself out of its troubles with no state aid of any kind.</p>
        <p>The state will create a Nassau Interim Finance Authority both to oversee the county's finances and to sell bonds on better terms than the county would be able to get on the market. In recent weeks, the Democrats who control the Assembly had called for two agencies, one for oversight and one to sell bonds, but in the end, they dropped that demand.</p>
        <p>In return for the state aid, Nassau must make $50 million in budget cuts this year, and $70 million in each of the next three years. If it does not, the state will impose a financial control board, essentially stripping Mr. Gulotta and the County Legislature of much of their power.</p>
        <p>''That's the very serious threat in this package,'' said Assemblyman Thomas P. DiNapoli, a Nassau Democrat. ''It enforces a level of discipline that the local people have not been able to enforce.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta said that he welcomed the bailout package and that as soon as he had the bill in hand, would ask the County Legislature for a ''home rule message,'' which is needed for the State Legislature to act.</p>
        <p>In talks over the last few weeks, the State Senate's Republican majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, had said his house would raise New York City's debt ceiling by $2.5 billion, and the Senate passed a bill to that effect. But that figure would get the city through barely two more years, meaning that the next mayor, most likely a Democrat, would hit the limit in his first year in office.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, threatened to block the Nassau bailout unless Albany increased the city's borrowing authority by $4 billion and delivered aid to Buffalo schools.</p>
        <p>Several Assembly members said that Mr. Silver's stance, weeks after he beat back a coup attempt by fellow Democrats, would help shore up his support among members from New York City and Erie County.</p>
        <p>While all sides wanted a deal, lawmakers had begun to worry that the Legislature could adjourn for the year next Wednesday without a compromise.</p>
        <p>In the end, both sides backed down, with Mr. Bruno agreeing to the $4 billion figure. Mr. Silver dropped the insistence on two Nassau agencies and compromised on his demand for more Democratic representation on the oversight board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki had proposed that the board have three members appointed by him, one by Mr. Bruno and one by Mr. Silver. Today, they agreed to add two more members, one named by the governor and one by Comptroller H. Carl McCall, a Democrat. All seven must live in the county.</p>
        <p>New York City's borrowing problem lies with a Depression-era state law that put a ceiling on borrowing, through a formula based on property assessments.</p>
        <p>The law is a relic of an era when the primary source of local revenue was property taxes; today, for New York City, it is the personal income tax, making the worth of real estate far less relevant to city finances. Also, the assessments tend to lag behind real-world prices, so that in good times, the debt limit rises more slowly than city revenues and the demand for borrowing.</p>
        <p>State lawmakers raised the city's borrowing limit in 1996, but the city is rapidly approaching the new cap. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, City Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone and other officials have warned that without another increase, within months the city would be unable to embark on new capital projects.</p>
        <p>''It would have been impractical for them to undertake any kind of long-term projects,'' Mr. Silver said. ''This gives them the ability pay for roads, bridges, schools and the like.''</p>
        <p>The city had asked for a change in the way its debt ceiling is calculated, which would require a change in the State Constitution, but that proposal went nowhere. Still, it won a reprieve of about four years until it has to ask the state to raise the cap once again.</p>
        <p>The overall agreement reached today includes $45 million in aid to Buffalo's schools, and $10 million to Yonkers's. In each case, it is a mix of outright aid and zero-interest loans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
