<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serving the Empire, One After Another After . . .</title>
    <meta content="09SUNS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehle, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frain, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fiennes, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horovitz, Israel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Szabo, Istvan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sunshine (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DB103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serving the Empire, One After Another After . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie Sunshine, directed by Istvan Szabo, who co-wrote script with Israel Horovitz; Ralph Fiennes, Jennifer Ehle and James Frain star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About half an hour into ''Sunshine,'' the first of three characters played by Ralph Fiennes raises a glass to toast the passage of time. ''Long live the 20th century!'' he cries, which is, when you think about it, a profoundly illogical thing to say.</p>
        <p>Not that he's entirely wrong: the century, or at least one Hungarian Jewish family's experience of it, from the twilight of empire to the fall of Communism, is the subject of Istvan Szabo's churning, sometimes clumsy, often thought-provoking -- and decidedly long -- film. It follows in the footsteps of movies like Visconti's ''Leopard'' and Bertolucci's ''1900,'' epics that aspired to match the sprawl and capaciousness of classic novels and to show, at once panoramically and intimately, the process of historical change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About half an hour into ''Sunshine,'' the first of three characters played by Ralph Fiennes raises a glass to toast the passage of time. ''Long live the 20th century!'' he cries, which is, when you think about it, a profoundly illogical thing to say.</p>
        <p>Not that he's entirely wrong: the century, or at least one Hungarian Jewish family's experience of it, from the twilight of empire to the fall of Communism, is the subject of Istvan Szabo's churning, sometimes clumsy, often thought-provoking -- and decidedly long -- film. It follows in the footsteps of movies like Visconti's ''Leopard'' and Bertolucci's ''1900,'' epics that aspired to match the sprawl and capaciousness of classic novels and to show, at once panoramically and intimately, the process of historical change.</p>
        <p>This is never an easy thing to do, and Mr. Szabo, working from a script he wrote with the American playwright Israel Horovitz, attempts it with minimal subtlety, priming his enormous canvas with big, cartoonish sketches.</p>
        <p>''I predict this will be a century of love, justice and tolerance,'' Mr. Fiennes's character, a rising star of the Austro-Hungarian judicial system named Ignatz Sonnenschein, declares after his toast. You don't need to know much about the last hundred years -- just that they were characterized by an awful lot of hatred, injustice and intolerance -- to grasp the irony. But fortunately, and thanks largely to Mr. Fiennes, Jennifer Ehle and Rosemary Harris, the film pulls away from such obviousness and views the lethal unreason of the past hundred years with gravity, humor and, most remarkably, with something like sanity.</p>
        <p>The first third of the film, which sprints from Ignatz's 19th-century childhood to his death in 1930, doesn't have much time for nuance. Most of the action takes place at the Sonnenschein dinner table, which stoically endures being pounded and stormed away from during the passionate arguments that seem to erupt at every meal.</p>
        <p>Most of the tsoris is caused by the smoldering passion between Ignatz and his adopted sister Valerie (Ms. Ehle), who is really his cousin and who will eventually be his wife (and then, since Mr. Fiennes plays both their son and grandson, his mother and his grandmother). When they aren't provoking family fights, Ignatz and Valerie steal away for dreamy, heavy-breathing, soft-focus sex, followed by earnest pillow talk. ''When I'm lying in your arms, I feel like I've come home,'' Ignatz whispers. No kidding.</p>
        <p>The Sonnenschein household, overseen by plump, good-hearted parents who migrated to Budapest from the countryside and made a fortune selling an herbal elixir called Sunshine, is dominated by a quasi-incestuous love triangle involving Valerie, Ignatz and his younger brother Gustave. Their relationship is further complicated by political differences that erupt, all of a sudden, in a scene of speechifying melodrama shortly before the assassination of Archduke Ferdinand. Gustave is a socialist, his brother a steadfast believer in the empire's brand of liberal multiculturalism, while their sister turns out to be a budding Hungarian nationalist.</p>
        <p>This scene, and many others in the film, is both underdeveloped and overdone, as though Mr. Szabo, in his rush to interpret the history of Central Europe, couldn't be bothered to dramatize it. The sets are there -- the complacent bourgeois opulence of the Sonnenschein apartments, the haughty grandeur of Budapest's cafes and governmental palaces -- but he never slows down enough to capture the texture and rhythm of daily life. For all the shouting and panting, the Sonnenschein family story feels more like a collage of ideas, events and metaphors than something lived.</p>
        <p>But it must be said that the ideas are interesting, the metaphors occasionally inspired and some of the events unforgettably powerful. Just as history, properly understood, is more than just one darn thing after another, so ''Sunshine'' manages, as a whole, to transcend the crude melodrama of its individual scenes. The stagy political shouting match on the eve of World War I turns out to be the key to Mr. Szabo's understanding of the 20th century. He imagines socialism, nationalism and imperial liberalism as siblings, born out of an essentially decent, meliorist 19th-century impulse, and all vulnerable to horrifying moral corruption.</p>
        <p>Several of this Hungarian director's earlier films -- notably ''Mephisto'' (1981) and ''Colonel Redl'' (1985) -- dealt with the exemplary modern agonies, especially acute in Central Europe in the middle decades of the 20th century, of decent men driven to compromise with evil. ''Sunshine'' is a triptych of such stories, each one displaying Mr. Fiennes, with different facial hair and altered ideological coloration, caught in the pincers of history.</p>
        <p>Small compromises lead to big disasters: Ignatz, anxious to advance his career, changes the family name from Sonnenschein to the more Hungarian-sounding Sors . His son Adam converts to Christianity to gain admittance to Budapest's most exclusive fencing club. He becomes the national fencing champion and leads his team to the 1936 Olympics but succumbs to the temptations of snobbery, anti-Semitism and acquiescence to dictatorship. As it follows Adam's rise and fall, the film begins to breathe a little more, and Mr. Fiennes comes out of himself, acting with the fierce insouciance that is his best, and often neglected, attribute.</p>
        <p>In the next generation Mr. Fiennes's flair turns into rage, as he portrays Adam's son Ivan, who becomes, after World War II, a member of the Communist secret police out of blind, vengeful rage at the fascists who destroyed his family. The contours of Hungarian history from 1939 to 1956, when Soviet tanks crushed an incipient revolution, is well known, but I'll refrain from revealing the particulars of the Sors-Sonnenschein family saga.</p>
        <p>By the time Ivan confronts his own crisis of conscience, the movie has accumulated sufficient power and momentum to erase the memory of its earlier awkwardness. It shows such sympathy for its characters, and approaches its subject with such intelligence, that it's easy to forgive the clumsy editing, the haphazard insertion of black-and-white newsreels, and the hyperventilating sexual ardor that seems to be a Sors family curse.</p>
        <p>In spite of it all, the film leaves you with a sense of quiet, chastened grace, as embodied by the older Valerie, played by Ms. Harris, who is Ms. Ehle's real mother (the two actresses might share an Oscar, just as Mr. Fiennes might have to compete against himself). ''She was the only one of us who had the gift of breathing freely,'' her troubled grandson remarks, and ''Sunshine,'' at last, honors that gift.</p>
        <p>''Sunshine'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has a number of feverish sex scenes, a scattering of strong language and a horrific depiction of torture and murder.</p>
        <p>SUNSHINE</p>
        <p>Directed by Istvan Szabo; written by Mr. Szabo and Israel Horovitz; director of photography, Lajos Koltai; music by Maurice Jarre; produced by Robert Lantos and Andras Hamori; released by Paramount Classics. Running time: 180 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ralph Fiennes (Ignatz Sonnenschein/ Adam Sors/Ivan Sors), Jennifer Ehle (Valerie Sonnenschein), Rosemary Harris (Valerie Sors), James Frain (Gustave Sonnenschein), John Neville (Gustave Sors) and William Hurt (Andor Knorr).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
