<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Boy-and-His-Dog Story In a More Innocent Era</title>
    <meta content="09TVWK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewitt, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Trial of Old Drum, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Invisible Man, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DE103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Boy-and-His-Dog Story In a More Innocent Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David DeWitt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewitt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David DeWitt reviews television movie The Trial of Old Drum, on Animal Planet channel, and The Invisible Man on Sci Fi Channel (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only the most hard-hearted can resist the sight of a boy crying when his dog faces death. Why else is ''Old Yeller,'' an iconic American movie, recalled when filmmakers want a hard character to reveal a heart?</p>
        <p>Fair warning: I'm a dog owner myself, and the harder parts of my heart turned to mush during moments in ''The Trial of Old Drum,'' an original movie having its premiere tonight on Animal Planet. When the golden retriever Old Drum whimpers after a gunshot wound, when he howls as he is separated from his young master, when he offers a peacemaking paw to the town villain -- O.K., everyone, a collective ''aaw.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only the most hard-hearted can resist the sight of a boy crying when his dog faces death. Why else is ''Old Yeller,'' an iconic American movie, recalled when filmmakers want a hard character to reveal a heart?</p>
        <p>Fair warning: I'm a dog owner myself, and the harder parts of my heart turned to mush during moments in ''The Trial of Old Drum,'' an original movie having its premiere tonight on Animal Planet. When the golden retriever Old Drum whimpers after a gunshot wound, when he howls as he is separated from his young master, when he offers a peacemaking paw to the town villain -- O.K., everyone, a collective ''aaw.''</p>
        <p>''The Trial of Old Drum'' is manipulative and awkward, and it features spotty acting, washed-out landscapes, wince-inducing dialogue, leaps of reason and a load of bathos. Its fans won't care. At its best, ''Old Drum'' relates a classic story of a boy and his dog.</p>
        <p>In fact, ''The Trial of Old Drum'' is based on a true story from the western Missouri of 1870, when a rhetorically gifted lawyer, George Vest, delivered a closing statement that popularized the line, ''A man's best friend is his dog.''</p>
        <p>''The Trial of Old Drum'' streamlines the facts and plants a happy ending on the tale, in a movie clearly geared toward children.</p>
        <p>The writer, Ralph Gaby Wilson, has moved the story to an invented Eisenhower-era village that retains the innocence of a far earlier time. ''This is God's country,'' says the adult Charlie (the singer Randy Travis), whose narration describes the town as a place where your word is your good name and you don't need to lock your doors. (That's not the last of the cliches.)</p>
        <p>Young Charlie (Bobby Edner) is an only child whose mother has died, leaving him lovingly attached to Old Drum, a sweet, devoted and heroic dog. Old Drum is accused by gruff Uncle Lon (John Schuck) of killing sheep, a high crime in this livestock-centered economy. Lon wants the dog destroyed. Despite Charlie's objections, Old Drum is jailed until the truth can come out in a trial.</p>
        <p>Charlie's father is played by big Ron Perlman, whose muted performance is quietly charming. It's touching to watch Mr. Perlman wrap his large frame around the small boy in an attempt to comfort him, but the threat to Drum calls for further help: a well-known city lawyer,  played by Scott Bakula, a fine actor best-known for his Emmy-nominated performances in ''Quantum Leap.'' The trial pits Mr. Bakula's George Vest against the prosecutor Thomas Crittenden (well-played by Tom Duggan). Not surprisingly, this is the most involving part of the movie, so it's a shame that the case zips along so quickly and Vest's climactic tribute to dogs is so disappointing. Mr. Bakula's big moment, Vest's history-making summation, fails to fulfill its potential.</p>
        <p>Most children will feel suspense during the trial and sympathy for all the movie's characters (aside from Uncle Lon, who remains an unredeemed villain). But even children will puzzle over some of the script's odder choices, in particular Charlie's alternating references to Drum as ''good girl'' and ''good boy.'' Is this a strange attempt at gender equity? If so, it is misguided; just after Drum is proven capable of fatherhood, Charlie again refers to his dog as ''girl.'' Huh?</p>
        <p>But there's no point quibbling over the movie's flaws. ''The Trial of Old Drum'' proclaims the worthy soul of a pet, a sentiment that Animal Planet is wise to embrace -- and that no pet owner would dispute.</p>
        <p>THE INVISIBLE MAN  Sci Fi Channel, tonight at 9</p>
        <p>Any show about an invisible man has a built-in challenge: a person who can't be seen is not too interesting to watch. The Sci Fi Channel's ''Invisible Man'' dispenses with that problem by providing solid acting, smart storytelling and classy visuals that should bring approving nods from sci-fi fans both casual and sophisticated.</p>
        <p>The title character, Darien Fawkes, is made invisible by his implanted ''quicksilver gland,'' which to viewers means the actor Vincent Ventresca's body morphs into a sleek, silver shell before blipping out of sight. It's an elegant effect, far more appealing than the moments when Darien is actually invisible -- moments that look silly but are, thankfully, limited.</p>
        <p>Tricks are vital to ''The Invisible Man,'' but they are not all the series has to offer. The two-hour premiere is a well-directed, well-scored and well-told tale that mixes a little drama, a little adventure and a lot of character. Mr. Ventresca has just the right touch with the central role, that of a ne'er-do-well who becomes a reluctant servant of the government after he is the subject of a sabotaged experiment. Darien has an intensity that is undercut by wisecracks, yet he seems neither anxious to charm nor doomed to irritate.</p>
        <p>Darien's talent carries with it a problem: the ''quicksilver effect'' is addictive and each episode of invisibility is a fix of a potent drug. Too many fixes in too short a time and Darien's id becomes unleashed. It's a dandy central conflict that gives the series welcome range.</p>
        <p>Matt Greenberg's script handles the science well and the fiction better; the ''Invisible Man'' pilot is a nicely layered tale, with parallel sets of brothers, a miserly government bureaucracy and witty supporting characters. Especially appealing is Paul Ben-Victor as Darien's partner, a longtime government operative who wants nothing more than a higher pay classification.</p>
        <p>The show feels a touch formulaic in its first regular episode, scheduled for June 16; at worst, the series could lose its ''X Files'' sophistication and trot out weekly problems for its hero to solve. But that seems unlikely. ''The Invisible Man'' is worth watching.</p>
        <p>THE TRIAL OF OLD DRUM  Animal Planet, tonight at 8.</p>
        <p>Sean McNamara, director; Joe Broido and David Brookwell, producers. A production of Porchlight Entertainment for Animal Planet. Bruce D. Johnson, executive producer for Porchlight; David E. Gerber, vice president of production, and Ross Hammer, executive producer, for Animal Planet.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ron Perlman (Charles Burden Sr.), Scott Bakula (George Vest), Bobby Edner (Charlie Burden), John Schuck (Uncle Lon) E. J. Callahan (Lyle Snelling), Alexis O'Keefe (Ann) and Randy Travis ( voiceover for Charlie Burden).</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
