<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panama Still Failing to Stem Narcotics Traffic, U.S. Report Asserts</title>
    <meta content="Y09PAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Customs Service (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDE113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panama Still Failing to Stem Narcotics Traffic, U.S. Report Asserts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States Customs intelligence report says Panamanian government has made little progress this year in its fight against drug trafficking and money laundering; says Panama continues to be major transshipment point for cocaine and increasingly for heroin; notes that drug seizures in 1999 declined 80 percent from 1998 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Panamanian government has made little progress this year in its fight against drug trafficking and money laundering, according to a United States Customs intelligence report.</p>
        <p>The report, which is expected to be discussed at a Congressional hearing on Friday, said Panama continued to be a major transshipment point for cocaine and increasingly for heroin, which are smuggled through weakly patrolled borders and ports. The reported noted that in 1999 drug seizures declined 80 percent from 1998 and no major drug arrests were made.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Panamanian government has made little progress this year in its fight against drug trafficking and money laundering, according to a United States Customs intelligence report.</p>
        <p>The report, which is expected to be discussed at a Congressional hearing on Friday, said Panama continued to be a major transshipment point for cocaine and increasingly for heroin, which are smuggled through weakly patrolled borders and ports. The reported noted that in 1999 drug seizures declined 80 percent from 1998 and no major drug arrests were made.</p>
        <p>A preliminary version of the report, which was provided to a House subcommittee on criminal justice and drug policy, originally had harsh words for Panama's law enforcement agencies, saying they were ''corrupt and ill trained'' and ''overwhelmed'' by drug traffickers. The final version softened that criticism, saying they faced ''difficulties dealing with sophisticated trafficking organizations.''</p>
        <p>The report said that Panama's sprawling Colon Free Trade Zone was used by traffickers not only to hide drugs in cargo containers but also to launder profits. It cited serious security problems at Tocumen International Airport, where there have been allegations that cargo and ramp workers are helping to move drug shipments.</p>
        <p>Customs officials would not comment on the report, which they said was classified.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the report's observations are sure to be used by Congressional critics and others who have expressed grave concerns about Panama's inability to secure its border with Colombia less than six months after the United States withdrew all its troops.</p>
        <p>''The situation in Panama has taken a dramatic turn for the worse,'' said Representative John L. Mica, a Florida Republican who is the subcommittee chairman. ''The information we have is pretty damaging, especially since the United States exited six months ago.''</p>
        <p>With increased unrest and violence in Colombia, more traffickers have been seeking a safe haven in Panama. At the same time, the country's lax banking laws and dollar economy have proved as much of a lure to them as the high-rise buildings they have settled into.</p>
        <p>''It's not all about drugs,'' a diplomat said. ''The country is built on dodging taxes, dodging bizarre exchange rates and evading court settlements.'' He added, ''The narcos have grafted right on.'' As a result, the diplomat said, efforts to crack down on money laundering have been unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>''Basically, about the entire economic elite of this country is involved in some form of money laundering, and the government is not going to crack down on that,'' he said. ''Money is a morally neutral item in this country. It does not matter where it comes from.''</p>
        <p>Part of the problem has been that the government of President Mireya Moscoso assumed power only last September and is still feeling its way. Some critics have faulted her for not having enough of a vision for the country's future and say that she has been more preoccupied with petty politics and deciding which supporters get which government posts.</p>
        <p>At the same time, her government has been ambivalent about what kind of relationship it wants with the United States after nearly a century of American influence on Panamanian  affairs. It is also about to sign a long-awaited national security plan that will, for the first time, outline its strategy for securing its borders and the canal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
