<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calgary Journal; In the Catbird Seat (or the Hot Seat, Like Seattle?)</title>
    <meta content="Y09CAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Calgary (Alberta)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alberta (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Petroleum Congress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta/Calgary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3D8103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calgary Journal; In the Catbird Seat (or the Hot Seat, Like Seattle?)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>CALGARY, Alberta</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Calgary, most prosperous city in Canada's prosperous Alberta province; modern city of steel-and-glass skyscrapers balanced with historic buildings enjoys both a squeaky-clean image and a booming economy that has diversified well beyond its traditional dependence on oil; but oil will become focus on June 11, when this showcase metropolis will be thrust into world spotlight with arrival of 3,000 delegates from 80 countries and some 200 journalists for World Petroleum Congress; protesters are already gearing up for a series of high-profile demonstrations reminiscent of antitrade protests that shook Seattle six months ago; map; photo (Calgary Journal) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Playing on Americans' fear of the unknown, a Best Western Hotel television ad last winter showed business executives bucking an unpopular travel request down the corporate ladder. Finally, the request stopped at a hapless underling, standing wide-eyed by a photocopier as a colleague asked, ''Have you ever been to -- Calgary?''</p>
        <p>Calgarians complained and the hotel chain pulled the commercial. But many others here in the most prosperous city in Canada's most prosperous province just shrugged it off, attributing it to the provincialism of an American ad copy writer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Playing on Americans' fear of the unknown, a Best Western Hotel television ad last winter showed business executives bucking an unpopular travel request down the corporate ladder. Finally, the request stopped at a hapless underling, standing wide-eyed by a photocopier as a colleague asked, ''Have you ever been to -- Calgary?''</p>
        <p>Calgarians complained and the hotel chain pulled the commercial. But many others here in the most prosperous city in Canada's most prosperous province just shrugged it off, attributing it to the provincialism of an American ad copy writer.</p>
        <p>With the highest household Internet connection rate in Canada, the country's largest concentration of corporate headquarters outside of Toronto, and a brand new venture capital stock exchange incubating hundreds of new companies, people in this steel and glass city on the edge of the Canadian Rockies are too busy making money to lose sleep over outdated stereotypes. In fact, a little negative publicity might cool off a city whose population has grown by two-thirds since 1975, to 860,000 today, pushing up housing prices by one third since 1995, the fastest rate of any city in Canada.</p>
        <p>''The traffic,'' groaned Alnisha Haji, a hairdresser who moved here from Winnipeg a few years ago. ''Places that used to take half an hour to get to, now take an hour.''</p>
        <p>But with the lowest unemployment rate of a major Canadian city, 4.7 percent, migrants still flock here at the rate of 50 a day.</p>
        <p>''One of the first things I noticed here were the help wanted ads,'' said Michelle Simick, 27, a newspaper reporter who moved here this spring from her native Vancouver. ''They have signs everywhere -- in front of the 7-Elevens, in front of the restaurants, even a board up in the mall. I have never seen that in Vancouver.''</p>
        <p>''People my age here seem to be a lot further along than people in Vancouver,'' she said. ''People in Vancouver seem to be slogging away at service jobs, waiting for jobs that never open up.''</p>
        <p>With Canada's tallest building west of Toronto, this modern city of high-rises enjoys its image of a sunny, squeaky clean city, even serving as ''Metropolis'' for the filming of all three modern Superman movies. But  on June 11, this showcase metropolis will be thrust into the world spotlight when 3,000 delegates from 80 countries converge here for the World Petroleum Congress, a five-day event that takes place every three years.</p>
        <p>The biggest event to hit Calgary since the 1988 Winter Olympics, the congress may not capture wide attention despite high gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>But protesters, noting the expected attendance of 200 journalists, are gearing up for a series of photogenic protests, promising a miniature version of the antitrade protests that shook Seattle six months ago. In a genteel city where parking meter attendants wear cowboy hats to charm the tourists, it is unclear how Calgary will cope if violence breaks out.</p>
        <p>Targets will be easy to find. Penthouse floors of downtown skyscrapers proudly bear the names of oil companies: Gulf, Husky, Mobil, Shell and Petro-Canada. But while energy sector companies occupy half of downtown's office space, appearances are deceiving in a city long labeled Canada's ''energy capital.''</p>
        <p>Whipsawed by a series of oil price shocks, Alberta has diversified. The energy industry's part of the provincial economy has dropped to 20 percent today from 35 percent 15 years ago. In the near suburbs, before housing developments sprawl across shortgrass prairie to the Rockies, about 1,200 new high technology companies have sprung up in recent years, now employing 50,000 people.</p>
        <p>Professors at a University of Calgary high technology center have licensed 300 technologies in the last decade. To lessen economic dependence on oil, Alberta's government has set up two $700 million funds, one for engineering research, the other for medical research. Last year, of Alberta's 10 fastest-growing companies, 6 were high-tech companies based in Calgary.</p>
        <p>''People have learned,'' said Ralph Klein, Alberta's premier, who was Calgary's mayor during the energy downturn of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>This year, Alberta expects to record the highest growth rate, 5 percent, of Canada's 10 provinces. The premier placed much of the credit on low taxes. Alberta has no sales tax, Canada's lowest gasoline tax and, starting Jan. 1, will have Canada's first flat provincial tax.</p>
        <p>''When people come out here, they are amazed,'' said William L. Hess, a Montreal native who runs Calgary's new Canadian Venture Exchange. ''The entrepreneurial drive, the quality of work available to professionals are unparalleled.''</p>
        <p>Since opening six months ago as a fusion of two old exchanges in Calgary and Vancouver, this national exchange has quadrupled its daily trades, to an average of about 28,000 today. With 2,800 small capital companies listed, it is now moving east, opening branches this summer in Winnipeg and Toronto. The new exchange replaces the Vancouver Stock Exchange, which lost credibility over stock manipulations of mining companies.</p>
        <p>The downside of Calgary's boom has been an affordable housing squeeze. In the last year, the minimum income needed to buy the average house here jumped by one-quarter, knocking 45,000 families out of the market, according to mortgage analysts. ''Homelessness has grown incredibly here,'' said David W. Lewry, who runs the Inn From the Cold Society, a network of homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>But in general Calgary's success has provoked mostly envy, starting in neighboring British Columbia. Alberta, with only three-quarters of British Columbia's population of four  million, expects its gross provincial product to surpass its western neighbor's this year, hitting $75 billion.</p>
        <p>''No wonder the new Canadian Venture Exchange will headquarter in Calgary and not Vancouver,'' Mark Milke, British Columbia director of the Canadian Taxpayers Federation, complained in an essay in The Calgary Herald. ''The stockbrokers are simply following the moving vans of other enterprising British Columbians.''</p>
        <p>In Edmonton, Alberta's capital, Don Ghermezian, manager of the West Edmonton Mall, the world's largest shopping mall, sniffed in an interview: ''Calgary has nothing. O.K., it has a tower with a revolving restaurant. Big deal.''</p>
        <p>In Toronto, newspapers like to paint Calgary and Alberta as weird bastions of reactionary politics and lifestyles. In reality, Calgary is middle of the road by American standards. Last fall, a Calgary judge established the right for local lesbian couples to adopt children legally.</p>
        <p>A yuppie haven in reality, Calgary has a household Internet connection  rate of 60 percent, and a population that, surveys indicate, prefers skiing over hockey and bicycling over fishing. With the local National Hockey League team, the Calgary Flames, losing money, The Calgary Herald is campaigning to expand the sales of season passes with scare headlines like ''No Bucks, No Pucks.''</p>
        <p>In this city of migrants, social mobility is often greater than in blue-blooded Eastern Canada. In May, Mayor Al Duerr bestowed Calgary's Citizen of the Year Award on Mitzie Wasyliw for her work preserving an old ranching homestead. A newspaper report noted that Mrs. Wasyliw got her start here in the 1970's when she blew into town and became one of the city's first ''exotic dancers.''</p>
        <p>''I am sure there is a bit of  Toronto looking down their noses at the West,'' Mr. Hess, the stock exchange president, said of intercity rivalries. ''But, frankly, there is a bit of the West looking down its nose at Toronto.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
