<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>National Semiconductor's Fourth-Quarter Earnings Exceeded Expectations</title>
    <meta content="Y09CHIP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Semiconductor Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D6103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>National Semiconductor's Fourth-Quarter Earnings Exceeded Expectations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Semiconductor Corp reports fourth-quarter earnings that exceed Wall Street analysts' estimates as sales increase 22.5 percent; says for quarter ended May 28, profit from operations was $134.2 million, or 68 cents on a diluted share, compared with loss from operations of $40 million in same period year earlier; analysts had expected company to earn 62 cents a share (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Semiconductor Corporation reported fourth-quarter earnings today that exceeded Wall Street analysts' estimates as sales increased 22.5 percent. Executives raised their predictions for revenue growth in the next fiscal year to about 30 percent from 25 percent.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended May 28, profit from operations was $134.2 million, or 68 cents a diluted share, in contrast to a loss from operations of $40 million, or 24 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $595.3 million from $486 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Semiconductor Corporation reported fourth-quarter earnings today that exceeded Wall Street analysts' estimates as sales increased 22.5 percent. Executives raised their predictions for revenue growth in the next fiscal year to about 30 percent from 25 percent.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended May 28, profit from operations was $134.2 million, or 68 cents a diluted share, in contrast to a loss from operations of $40 million, or 24 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose to $595.3 million from $486 million.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected the company to earn 62 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Special items for the most recent quarter included an $18 million credit related to the sale of Fairchild Semiconductor in 1997 and a $1.7 million credit related to restructuring financial reserves. With the gains, net income was $153.9 million, or 78 cents a share. In the period a year earlier, the company posted a net loss of $783.5 million, or $4.65 a share, because of reorganization costs.</p>
        <p>National's strong results partly reflect its exit last year from the computer chip business, where it had been bloodied in the price wars between the Intel Corporation and Advanced Micro Devices Inc. They also reflect the large part of the company's revenue that comes from analog chips, which are used in cellular telephones, wireless computers and consumer electronics products. Analog sales are growing more rapidly than digital sales.</p>
        <p>National ''was certainly a mess a couple of years ago because they had significant assets that were losing a fortune, and the semiconductor industry was in the doldrums,'' said Drew Peck, an analyst with SG Cowen. ''Now they're divested those assets and they're in the right place at the right time. The analog market is booming and will be booming for a number of years.''</p>
        <p>In a conference call with analysts, Brian Halla, National's chairman, president and chief executive, said he was confident the company's growth could outpace the 31 percent rate forecast by the Semiconductor Industry Association for fiscal 2000. ''For us it looks like a walk in the park,'' he said. ''Now we know we are in the right markets, with the right products and the right customers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
