<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Call Him Ishmael: The Young (Heartbroken and Lonely) Man and the Sea</title>
    <meta content="09BOOK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patterson, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Water in Between, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0D6133FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Call Him Ishmael: The Young (Heartbroken and Lonely) Man and the Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews book The Water in Between by Kevin Patterson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WATER IN BETWEEN</p>
        <p>A Journey at Sea</p>
        <p>By Kevin Patterson</p>
        <p>289 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Near the end of Kevin Patterson's smart and exciting narrative of maritime adventure, he admits something that travel writers rarely do:  the issues that drove him to brave the dangers of faraway places were not resolved by virtue of his travels.</p>
        <p>This is an age in which travel writing is seen romantically, as a kind of religious redemption, with the road and its hardships as elements in a ritual of purification or, at least, self-discovery. Mr. Patterson, a 29-year-old doctor who goes to sea after experiencing the chagrin of a failed love affair, did learn things -- among them that home is where he wanted to be. But the author's admission that he did not find any ''obvious resolution'' to his problems during his months in a sailboat on the Pacific illustrates the clear-headedness that elevates this journey above the level of mere adventure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WATER IN BETWEEN</p>
        <p>A Journey at Sea</p>
        <p>By Kevin Patterson</p>
        <p>289 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Near the end of Kevin Patterson's smart and exciting narrative of maritime adventure, he admits something that travel writers rarely do:  the issues that drove him to brave the dangers of faraway places were not resolved by virtue of his travels.</p>
        <p>This is an age in which travel writing is seen romantically, as a kind of religious redemption, with the road and its hardships as elements in a ritual of purification or, at least, self-discovery. Mr. Patterson, a 29-year-old doctor who goes to sea after experiencing the chagrin of a failed love affair, did learn things -- among them that home is where he wanted to be. But the author's admission that he did not find any ''obvious resolution'' to his problems during his months in a sailboat on the Pacific illustrates the clear-headedness that elevates this journey above the level of mere adventure.</p>
        <p>In 1994 the heartbroken Mr. Patterson bought a 37-foot ferro-concrete sailboat from a broker on Vancouver Island with a plan to sail it to Tahiti and back. It is important to note here that at the time he became a boat owner, Mr. Patterson had never sailed. Surprisingly, and also refreshingly, he treats this fact with self-deprecating humor, never considering it much more than an inconvenience.</p>
        <p>''All the books I'd bought made it clear to me that I had immersed myself in a pursuit where there was a great deal to know,'' Mr. Patterson writes of this early stage of his trip.  ''I knew none of it.'' Within a few days, however, he had found a companion for the journey to Tahiti, a quiet man named Don Lang who rivaled Mr. Patterson in broken-heartedness and, unlike Mr. Patterson, had done a good deal of sailing. They outfitted Mr. Patterson's clunky but seaworthy ketch with food and spare parts and a wind vane to keep the boat on course when the two men were sleeping. Before too long, Mr. Patterson was heaving to and dousing sails and running storm jibs with the best of them.</p>
        <p>But while he has not written a book about learning how to sail, Mr. Patterson writes a great deal about loneliness and the voyage, sadness and civilization. ''You could argue that the road selects for malcontents and wobbly psyches and you will find nothing to refute that argument in the bus terminal snack bars of my experience,'' he writes. He recognizes in that passage that he belongs to a history that has produced a considerable body of knowledge and thought.</p>
        <p>During his long and event-filled journey to Tahiti and back, he reflects on the literary tradition that grew out of the arduous escape from the tedium of home, measuring his own experience against the words and passages of writers who came before him.</p>
        <p>''The Water in Between,'' in this sense, is good travel writing and also good literary criticism. As he sailed the seas, Mr. Patterson developed as good an eye for authorial success and failure as he did for the distant darkening of the sky that foretells a squall.</p>
        <p>His main companions in this regard were the men whom sadness propelled to the planet's farther reaches, men like Richard Henderson, author of ''Singlehanded Sailing,'' Joshua Slocum, the grand progenitor of solo global circumnavigation, and several others. From these writer-traveler forebears, Mr. Patterson gets ideas about the land and home as places of restriction and false comfort as well as about solitude, the vastness of the sky, the immensity of nature.</p>
        <p>There is a moment in his own experience when his boat is becalmed in the middle of the ocean near the equator, and he and Mr. Lang swim away from it, trusting that it will go nowhere. ''For long seconds I had the illusion of being entirely alone,'' he writes. ''A thousand miles from anyone. It should have been more satisfying. I started to lose my breath.'' He does not say so, but it is hard to imagine that as well-read a sailor as Mr. Patterson did not think at that moment of Melville's Pip, the cabin boy of ''Moby-Dick'' who loses his mind when he has a similar experience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson has a number of mishaps, like losing his anchor and letting his battery go dead. As he sails, he recounts a few adventures and misadventures in his past life, including his experiences as a young doctor in the Canadian army, his encounters with the Inuit of northern Canada and his long-distance love affair with a delicately difficult woman escaping her French husband.</p>
        <p>He gets to Tahiti. He encounters other lonely sailors, including some with a striking literary bent. Generally, he is impressed more by their psychological disarray than their bravery in the face of the elements. He sails from Hawaii to Vancouver alone, at one point running into a two-day storm like nothing he had ever imagined. ''But my God, alone on a small boat, listening to wind like that, there is nothing so full of what sounds like unstoppered human rage, loneliness and malignancy,'' he writes.</p>
        <p>The figure he comes back to again and again, his chief foil and inspiration, is Bruce Chatwin, author of ''Songlines'' and ''In Patagonia'' and other travel books that for Mr. Patterson, gave expression to an especially romantic and ascetic philosophy of travel as redemption. Chatwin in Mr. Patterson's sharp and critical reading, saw sedentariness as spiritual death and self-sufficient, untrammeled nomadism as happiness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson's long days alone on the sea lead him to see the Chatwinian philosophy as a pose, a literary device, a kind of cynicism. Ever since the modern world created the ideal of individualism, he writes, people have lived out the fantasy of isolation as a response to alienation, but that is what it is, a fantasy.  Whatever our troubles may be, ''being awake at night, alone and cold, severed from others, does not have a patch on home.''</p>
        <p>That's not a bad lesson, and it is all the more persuasive because of Mr. Patterson's absence of self-dramatization.</p>
        <p>This is a writer more interested in the truth than in heroics. He has written an old-fashioned story of personal adventure that probes its own themes with subversive intelligence and ends in a lucidity that distilled into hard, honed prose is a pleasure to read.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
