<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Future of Collector Cars: On the Auction Block, or Online?</title>
    <meta content="09CARS$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monte Carlo (Monaco)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDB103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Future of Collector Cars: On the Auction Block, or Online?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>MONACO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three recent auctions in Monte Carlo demonstrate continuing strength of collector-car market; potential challenge from Internet sales discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THREE recent auctions here demonstrated that the collector-car market continues to gain strength. Yet the beneficiaries, the old-line auction companies that exhilarate crowds by sending multimillion-dollar Bugattis over the block, where they are subject to feverish bidding by celebrity collectors, are looking warily over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>Just as the Internet is changing the ways that multinational conglomerates and neighborhood pizzerias do business, it looms as a potential threat to the auction houses that could lose millions of dollars in commissions if buyers and sellers move online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THREE recent auctions here demonstrated that the collector-car market continues to gain strength. Yet the beneficiaries, the old-line auction companies that exhilarate crowds by sending multimillion-dollar Bugattis over the block, where they are subject to feverish bidding by celebrity collectors, are looking warily over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>Just as the Internet is changing the ways that multinational conglomerates and neighborhood pizzerias do business, it looms as a potential threat to the auction houses that could lose millions of dollars in commissions if buyers and sellers move online.</p>
        <p>The online auction formula is simple: Put a desirable car before millions of potential bidders and charge a minimal commission to reflect the site's low overhead. EBay has proved that the process works well for old books, Beanie Babies and tens of thousands of other low-cost, easy-to-describe items.</p>
        <p>Last August, eBay established a category specifically for cars and auto-related products. Now, with the formal introduction next Monday of eBayMotors.com, the online auctioneer is moving to set up a one-stop resource center for car shoppers, from commuters seeking rusty ''station cars'' to connoisseurs of custom-body Duesenbergs.</p>
        <p>Even an old-guard competitor credits eBay with increasing the public's awareness of the auction process. ''Now, someone who has a dusty old Pez dispenser knows they have an alternative to selling it at a garage sale,'' said David Gooding, managing director of Christie's International Motor Cars in Beverly Hills, Calif.</p>
        <p>In addition to its sales listings, eBayMotors.com will provide an array of services to aid in online sales, including presale inspections by authorized personnel, with results posted on the Web site; financing options; access to collector-car insurance; instant estimates of the costs of transporting a vehicle; and an escrow service that will hold money until a car's condition is verified.</p>
        <p>But none of these services are required. While any car entered at a Christie's or Brooks auction is researched and evaluated by specialists, eBay leaves the due diligence to the buyer and the seller.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for eBayMotors say that cars receiving presale inspections are more likely to sell, and for a higher price.</p>
        <p>For prospective buyers, eBayMotors promises to put a dizzying variety of cars within mouse-click range. Only 153 cars were offered, in total, at the three Monaco auctions. In contrast, eBay had 3,649 cars listed for sale this week, said Simon Rothman, vice president and general manager of eBay's automotive division; most were in a range of $10,000 to $50,000. Mr. Rothman projected that car listings on eBayMotors could total as much as $2 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The eBay bidder can also buy without paying a commission, although sellers pay $25 to list a car and just $25 more if the car sells. In contrast, most auto-auction houses charge up to 10 percent for consignors and 5 to 17.5 percent for buyers -- for total premiums of $60,000 or more on a $300,000 car.</p>
        <p>Still, it takes a leap of faith to spend a substantial sum to buy a car that one has not actually seen. Does its condition match the representation made by the seller? Is it authentic? Did it really once belong to Joan Crawford? Are competing bids being made by legitimate buyers, or is the price being driven artificially higher?</p>
        <p>Such questions apply to any big-ticket item offered online, as made obvious recently by the $135,805 eBay sale, later canceled, of a painting amid speculation that it was by a noted artist. It was discovered that the seller and some acquaintances had driven up the price by bidding on it themselves.</p>
        <p>Misrepresentation is possible at live auctions, as well, but bidders are less likely to be fooled if they examine a car and question the auction company's representatives. Further, the big auction houses work to resolve disputes between buyers and sellers.</p>
        <p>''EbayMotors won't attempt to authenticate items being listed, but we provide services for those who wish to do so,'' Mr. Rothman said. He depicted eBayMotors as ''a marketplace where automotive transactions take place.'' By playing the role of a feisty, no-frills newcomer challenging a full-service institution, eBay is to Christie's as E*Trade has been to Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>While live auctions are far more expensive for both buyer and seller, they offer more presale services. ''Christie's, along with other specialist auction houses, really add value to an item, especially for the ultra-exotic, whether painting, jewelry or automobiles,'' Mr. Gooding said. ''We research the cars being offered, inspect and drive them where possible and provide educated opinions for our clients.''</p>
        <p>Questions have also been raised about the technological reliability of online auctions. Robert Brooks, chairman of Brooks Specialist Auctioneers and Valuers, asked: ''If a customer is bidding online on a million-dollar Duesenberg and the computers go down, what's the bidder to do? Does he lose the car? Do we miss a chance to get the seller the highest price? At a live auction, there is always a way to keep the sale going.''</p>
        <p>Last summer, at the Meadow Brook collector-car sale in Michigan, a windstorm cut the power. The audience urged the auctioneer to continue, which he did, selling cars in a hall lighted by a backup generator.</p>
        <p>EBay can point to its own success as an indicator of future growth. ''We have had strong double-digit growth in our automotive sector every month since we began informally in August of 1999,'' Mr. Rothman said. ''We also have 10,000 listings for automotive memorabilia and over 46,900 parts listings. And we have tens of thousands of new listings each week, as auctions end and new ones begin.''</p>
        <p>To compete with online auctions, the live auction companies will stress quality over quantity, professional services over low commissions and the thrill of a live event. ''Especially at the high end, buyers and sellers want to enjoy the drama and spectacle of a live auction,'' Mr. Gooding said. ''After all, it's surely more fun to be in Monte Carlo watching someone bid on a million-dollar Maserati Grand Prix car than it is to sit in front of a computer terminal clicking away with your mouse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
