<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCall Says Giuliani Administration Is Defying Court Order to Assist State Audits</title>
    <meta content="09AUDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Administration for Children's Services (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7DF113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCall Says Giuliani Administration Is Defying Court Order to Assist State Audits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>H Carl McCall, state comptroller, says Giuliani administration is continuing to defy court order to cooperate fully with state audits of New York City agencies; releases three audits that reveal weaknesses in financial management and record keeping--but no improprieties--at Administration of Children's Services and Department of Health; Mayor Giuliani restates his disagreement with court ruling, but says he recognizes that city needs to comply with it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state comptroller said yesterday that the Giuliani administration was continuing to defy a court order to fully cooperate with state audits of city agencies.</p>
        <p>The comptroller, H. Carl McCall, made the charge as he released three audits that found weaknesses in financial management and record keeping at two New York City agencies, the Administration for Children's Services and the Department of Health. Mr. McCall said that both agencies had already begun to address the problems that were uncovered. He acknowledged that his auditors found no indication of any improprieties at the agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The state comptroller said yesterday that the Giuliani administration was continuing to defy a court order to fully cooperate with state audits of city agencies.</p>
        <p>The comptroller, H. Carl McCall, made the charge as he released three audits that found weaknesses in financial management and record keeping at two New York City agencies, the Administration for Children's Services and the Department of Health. Mr. McCall said that both agencies had already begun to address the problems that were uncovered. He acknowledged that his auditors found no indication of any improprieties at the agencies.</p>
        <p>The audits are the first completed by the state comptroller's office since 1997, when the Giuliani administration challenged Mr. McCall's right to investigate basic management matters at city agencies. Even after the State Court of Appeals ruled in April 1999 that the city had to cooperate with the audits, the Giuliani administration refused to provide everything that Mr. McCall said he requested.</p>
        <p>''It is troubling,'' Mr. McCall said yesterday. ''It could lead to a conclusion that maybe something is being covered up.''</p>
        <p>In early 1997, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, a Republican, ordered city agencies to stop sharing most of the information requested by the state comptroller's office because he said Mr. McCall, a Democrat, had begun several audits solely to embarrass his administration. But the State Supreme Court and the Court of Appeals both ruled for Mr. McCall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said yesterday that he still disagreed with the Court of Appeals ruling, but he indicated that he recognized that the city needed to comply with the court decision.</p>
        <p>''It was a matter of principle about what the scope of the state comptroller's function is and whether it duplicates the function of the city comptroller and about six other entities,'' Mr. Giuliani said during a news conference on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>At the child welfare agency, state auditors examined the way the city pays 260 private, nonprofit contractors for subsidized day-care services. A second audit examined the way the city reviews and approves $575 million a year in payments for more than 60 foster-care service providers.</p>
        <p>The state found that the city was not doing enough to ensure that the service providers are being paid only for work they delivered. By reviewing a year's worth of payments to four foster-care contractors, for example, the auditors found that in three of the four cases, the contractors had been paid $1 million more than their expense records indicated was justified.</p>
        <p>In a written response, Nicholas Scoppetta, the child welfare commissioner, thanked Mr. McCall's staff for the suggestions and gave details about the steps the agency planned to strengthen its oversight of payments.</p>
        <p>The review of day-care billing was hampered, Mr. McCall said, because even after the April 1999 court ruling, the city would not provide his auditors with all of the requested payment records or with information giving details on how the agency monitored its payments.</p>
        <p>At the Health Department, Mr. McCall examined how the city processed vital records, like birth certificates. His auditors found that city birth records were inconsistent with information provided by local hospitals. For example, hospitals reported 239 fewer births than city records indicated had occurred in April 1998. The city also often took too long to register births. And it had poor fire prevention control measures at buildings in Brooklyn and Queens where records are stored.</p>
        <p>The city health commissioner, Neal L. Cohen, disputed suggestions that the agency's birth and death records might be inaccurate, but the department agreed to take steps to strengthen its recordkeeping. It also installed 10 new fire extinguishers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
