<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stakes Will Still Be High at Belmont</title>
    <meta content="09BELM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0D9103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stakes Will Still Be High at Belmont</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coming weekend of racing at Belmont Park has much to offer beside the Belmont Stakes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There may not be a Triple Crown at stake at Belmont Park this weekend. But three days of major racing with $2.5 million in purses will be staged, starting today with the Acorn Stakes, the first event in the Triple Tiara series for fillies, and closing on Sunday with the 112th running of the Brooklyn Handicap.</p>
        <p>In between, the 132nd Belmont Stakes, the main event of the year in New York racing, will be run. True, it will be run without the two top 3-year-old colts in the country, the injured Fusaichi Pegasus and the resting Red Bullet. But it will feature 11 other horses searching for the 3-year-old championship the two colts are still expected to pursue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There may not be a Triple Crown at stake at Belmont Park this weekend. But three days of major racing with $2.5 million in purses will be staged, starting today with the Acorn Stakes, the first event in the Triple Tiara series for fillies, and closing on Sunday with the 112th running of the Brooklyn Handicap.</p>
        <p>In between, the 132nd Belmont Stakes, the main event of the year in New York racing, will be run. True, it will be run without the two top 3-year-old colts in the country, the injured Fusaichi Pegasus and the resting Red Bullet. But it will feature 11 other horses searching for the 3-year-old championship the two colts are still expected to pursue.</p>
        <p>The weekend will be anchored by four Grade I stakes, beginning with the Acorn and its undefeated star, Roxelana, who has won all four of her starts by a combined total of 29 lengths. A month ago, she scored big time in the La Troienne Stakes at Churchill Downs by nearly 12 lengths. ''She amazes me each time she runs,'' said her trainer, William Huffman. ''The Acorn is never an easy race. It's a Grade I in New York. So, we're going to run her and see if she fits in with that group. She's passed every test so far.''</p>
        <p>Roxelana will be surrounded by nine other fillies in the one-mile run, including Darling My Darling, Finder's Fee, Circle of Life and Tugger. The second race in the Triple Tiara series, the Mother Goose, at a mile and an eighth, will be run at Belmont on July 1, and the third, the Coaching Club American Oaks, at a mile and a half, on July 22. Only eight fillies have swept all three, most recently Sky Beauty in 1993.</p>
        <p>Racing reaches a peak tomorrow when four other stakes support the Belmont on a day festooned by parachute jumping, world-class buglers and marching bands. The cast for the $1 million Belmont includes several candidates for the 3-year-old championship, including the favored Aptitude, who ran second to Fusaichi Pegasus in the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>''The Belmont is a great race for the pedigree,'' said Bobby Frankel, who trains Aptitude, ''and the money isn't bad, either.''</p>
        <p>Supporting the mile-and-a-half Belmont will be the $400,000 Manhattan Handicap at a mile and a quarter on the inner turf course; the $150,000 Riva Ridge at seven furlongs; the $150,000 True North at seven furlongs; and the $150,000 Just a Game Breeders' Cup at one mile on the turf. The Manhattan will be contested by five Grade I winners, notably Yagli, who won the race last year, but has struggled since then.</p>
        <p>The weekend's run of races will close with flourishes on Sunday with the Brooklyn Handicap at a mile and an eighth, a race that has been won by such stars as Exterminator, Whirlaway, Assault and three straight times by Discovery in the 1930's and by Forego in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>The horse with a cause this year is Running Stag, who won the race last year and who campaigns as relentlessly as a political candidate. He is an international traveler who has raced in England, America, Dubai and Hong Kong in the last six months.</p>
        <p>For Running Stag, who is 6 years old, this will be his 38th start and his third in three weeks. He won an allowance at Belmont on May 24, won the Massachusetts Handicap at Suffolk Downs last Saturday and will be back in action Sunday at Belmont Park.</p>
        <p>Isn't that a lot? Roger Teal, the assistant trainer, said the horse got back to Belmont last Sunday and took life rather easy this week. ''We can't see any problems in running back on Sunday,'' he said.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
