<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through the Looking Glass: Europe Raises Interest Rates</title>
    <meta content="Y09NORR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Central Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3D6103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through the Looking Glass: Europe Raises Interest Rates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris article discusses decision by European Central Bank to raise interest rate by half-point at time when European inflation, in this case figures are for Germany, is running at about 2 percent and unemployment rate is 9.6 percent; says bank, eager to prove its credibility as inflation fighter, has confounded forecasters by its action; says sad thing about Europe now is that it seems to have accepted high unemployment as virtually permanent thing; notes latest report for countries in eruo zone is 9.2 percent; says conventional wisdom is that unemployment is high because of structural problems like high wages and restrictive labor laws and that stimulative monetary policy will only revive inflation without doing much for growth; graph on German unemployment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT would the Federal Reserve do if American inflation was running about 2 percent a year and the unemployment rate was 9.6 percent? Would Alan Greenspan have the nerve to raise rates by half a percentage point?</p>
        <p>If that idea sounds crazy to you, then you're not in touch with reality, European style. For that is exactly what happened yesterday to Germans, for whom the above statistics apply. The European Central Bank, eager to prove its credibility as an inflation fighter, decided to confound forecasters and impose a half-point interest rate increase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT would the Federal Reserve do if American inflation was running about 2 percent a year and the unemployment rate was 9.6 percent? Would Alan Greenspan have the nerve to raise rates by half a percentage point?</p>
        <p>If that idea sounds crazy to you, then you're not in touch with reality, European style. For that is exactly what happened yesterday to Germans, for whom the above statistics apply. The European Central Bank, eager to prove its credibility as an inflation fighter, decided to confound forecasters and impose a half-point interest rate increase.</p>
        <p>In this country, an unemployment rate that high would have long since become the major national economic issue -- the actual United States rate is now 4.1 percent -- and politicians would be screaming for easier monetary policy. It would take an inflation rate far higher than 2 percent to persuade anyone that tightening credit was a good idea.</p>
        <p>But in Europe, things are different. Wim Duisenberg, the central bank's president, explained that they were worried about inflation that can be traced in part to high oil prices and a weak euro, and that the European economy was growing at 3 percent anyway.</p>
        <p>The sad thing about Europe now is that it seems to have accepted high unemployment as a virtually permanent thing. It is coming down, but the latest reported rate for the countries in the euro currency zone is 9.2 percent. The conventional wisdom is that unemployment is high because of structural problems like high wages and laws making it difficult for employers to hire and fire at will, and that a stimulative monetary policy would only revive inflation without doing much for growth. Anyway, the European Central Bank is supposed to keep inflation from going above 2 percent.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Solow, the Nobel Prize-winning economist, has suggested that idea is simply wrong. ''European central banks kept the squeeze on for a long time'' when fighting the inflation of the 1970's, he wrote a few years ago. ''Suppose,'' he added, ''there is a tendency for prolonged 'cyclical' unemployment to turn into something that looks like 'structural' unemployment. It is not hard to imagine how that might plausibly happen as the unemployed adapt to the unavailability of jobs.'' Eventually, he said, central banks wrongly convinced themselves that high unemployment was there to stay and the banks could not ''afford to expand aggregate demand'' by loosening monetary policy.</p>
        <p>It is perfectly true that Europe needs structural reform, but as Mr. Solow noted, ''it would be bad news indeed if this apparently structural unemployment really would not yield to the revival of demand for goods and labor.'' He suggested that history indicated it would. The European Central Bank should find out if he is right.</p>
        <p>In the United States, there has been good reason to think the economy was overheating, and the Fed has been right to tighten. But the Fed's action makes it all the more regrettable that the Europeans seem scared of growth. ''From the world's perspective, a surprising strength coming out of Europe gives us the best chance to survive a necessary sharp slowing in the United States,'' said Robert Barbera, the chief economist of Hoenig &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The euro has been weak because investors have viewed the rapidly growing United States as a much more attractive place to put money. The euro is cheap, and will recover eventually. But efforts to slow European growth are not going to help the beleaguered currency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
