<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Carmakers Extend Benefits To Gay Couples</title>
    <meta content="Y09AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DF113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Carmakers Extend Benefits To Gay Couples</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>sGeneral Motors, Ford and DaimlerChrysler's Chrysler division announce they will extend medical, dental and prescription drug benefits for same-sex partners of their 466,000 hourly and salaried employees; move is largest yet by corporate America to provide such benefits for gay and lesbian couples; gay and lesbian advocates say car makers' decisions dwarfs previous corporate moves and are particularly welcome because Midwestern companies have been slow to move on such benefits; Catholic Archdiocese of Detroit expresses dismay at automakers' decision (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors, Ford and DaimlerChrysler's Chrysler division announced today that they would begin offering medical, dental and prescription drug benefits for same-sex partners of their 466,000 hourly and salaried employees in the United States, the largest move yet by corporate America to provide such benefits for gay and lesbian couples.</p>
        <p>Many companies in the financial, media, entertainment and airline industries and some state and local governments have offered same-sex benefits in the last several years. But gay and lesbian advocates said the automakers' decisions dwarfed previous corporate moves and were particularly welcome because Midwestern companies have been slow to provide such benefits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>General Motors, Ford and DaimlerChrysler's Chrysler division announced today that they would begin offering medical, dental and prescription drug benefits for same-sex partners of their 466,000 hourly and salaried employees in the United States, the largest move yet by corporate America to provide such benefits for gay and lesbian couples.</p>
        <p>Many companies in the financial, media, entertainment and airline industries and some state and local governments have offered same-sex benefits in the last several years. But gay and lesbian advocates said the automakers' decisions dwarfed previous corporate moves and were particularly welcome because Midwestern companies have been slow to provide such benefits.</p>
        <p>''When the Big Three come together as a group to announce domestic benefits for same-sex couples, it's really a sea change,'' said Kim I. Mills, the education director of the Human Rights Campaign, a group that represents gay, lesbian and transgender Americans. ''We have not seen this kind of movement in the manufacturing sector.''</p>
        <p>The two largest American companies offering same-sex benefits until now have been I.B.M. and Citigroup, she said. Both companies are based in the New York area, where gays and lesbians are more influential than in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The Catholic Archdiocese of Detroit expressed dismay at the automakers' decision. The Catholic Church favors open and equal access to health care, but ''anything that compromises or erodes the traditional shape of the family tears at the very fabric of moral relationships that the church seeks to uphold,'' said Ned McGrath, a spokesman for the archdiocese.</p>
        <p>The federal government does not provide same-sex benefits for its employees. In the private sector and among state and local governments, such benefits are offered to 18 percent of workers, according to a study last year by the Kaiser Family Foundation, a nonpartisan group in Oakland, Calif. The companies and governments offering the benefits are most likely to be in the Northeast, on the West Coast or in Minnesota and Wisconsin, two states with a liberal tradition, said Kenneth McDonnell, a research analyst at the Employee Benefit Research Institute in Washington.</p>
        <p>David L. Murphy, Ford's vice president for human resources, said that the U.A.W. had demanded same-sex benefits during contract negotiations last autumn. Ford concluded that the benefits would add less than $5 million a year to Ford's $2 billion in annual health care costs. G.M. and DaimlerChrysler also calculated that the costs would be small, Mr. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>When automakers provide a new benefit to their hourly workers, they usually offer it to salaried employees, too, as they are now. Companies in other industries have found that less than 1 percent of their employees register for same-sex benefits, and Mr. Murphy predicted that this would hold for the auto industry.</p>
        <p>The automakers will not offer the benefit to retirees, but same-sex partners of current employees can retain their benefits after these employees retire. Those seeking the benefits must provide an affidavit and evidence of shared financial responsibilities. Unmarried heterosexual partners of employees will remain ineligible for benefits.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W. has been under mounting pressure from its gay and lesbian members to win better legal protections and benefits for them. The Canadian Auto Workers union had made the issue a priority, winning same-sex benefits from G.M. in Canada in 1993. Chrysler resisted in Canada until it lost an arbitration case in 1997, and Ford held out in Canada until last year.</p>
        <p>''It became kind of a personal thing, that people had objections to gays and lesbians and couldn't get past that to see them as workers,'' said Basil E. Hargrove, the Canadian union's president.</p>
        <p>U.A.W. leaders declined to comment on the same-sex benefits, which will take effect on Aug. 1.</p>
        <p>Chrysler drew national attention in 1997 when it chose not to advertise on the episode of ''Ellen,'' a television sitcom in which the lead character, Ellen DeGeneres, made clear that she was a lesbian. Chrysler executives further antagonized gay and lesbian groups then when they compared the show with the murder trial of O. J. Simpson, saying that they did not buy advertisements on socially polarizing shows. Chrysler resumed advertising on subsequent episodes that included lesbian themes.</p>
        <p>The controversy caused some gay and lesbian employees at Chrysler to organize as People of Diversity, an advocacy group that now has about 100 members. Only a quarter of them are in the U.A.W., but they tried hard to enlist the U.A.W.'s support, said Michelle Walters, the group's co-chairwoman.</p>
        <p>Virtually all of Chrysler's top leadership has turned over since Daimler-Benz took over the company in November 1998. Kathleen Oswald, Chrysler's senior vice president for human resources, said that by stressing diversity, the company wanted to ''make sure we would continue to get the best and brightest.''</p>
        <p>She declined to comment on Chrysler's previous policies, other than to say, ''The 'Ellen' program certainly helped raise awareness.''</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler's other divisions, Mercedes cars and Freightliner heavy trucks, are not unionized except for one Freightliner factory that has a separate labor contract. Both divisions said today that they had no plans to offer same-sex benefits.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters said that two executives had played a large role in changing industry attitudes: Thomas T. Stallkamp, who was Chrysler's president in 1998 and 1999, and Jacques Nasser, who has been Ford's chief executive since the beginning of last year. Mr. Stallkamp was instrumental in persuading Chrysler to recognize People of Diversity, and he oversaw the negotiation of Chrysler's pattern-setting labor contract with the U.A.W. before leaving in a conflict with Daimler's German leaders, Ms. Walters said.</p>
        <p>The four-year labor contract signed last autumn, which G.M. and Ford adopted after Chrysler, not only called for the union and the companies to study same-sex benefits but also barred workplace discrimination based on sexual orientation. Ms. Walters, an auto parts procurement manager at Chrysler's headquarters in Auburn Hills, Mich., said that this was mostly an issue in auto factories rather than in offices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
