<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Held in Killing of Police Chief's Relative</title>
    <meta content="Y09CHI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1205920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gangs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parks, Bernard (Police Chief)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shabazz, Samuel Sharad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, Lori</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2D6103FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Held in Killing of Police Chief's Relative</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chief Bernard Parks of Los Angeles police announces arrest of Samuel Sharad Shabazz in fatal shooting of Parks's granddaughter Lori Gonzalez; investigators believe Gonzalez was unintended victim of gang-related violence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chief Bernard Parks of the Los Angeles police announced today the arrest of an 18-year-old man in the fatal shooting of his granddaughter.</p>
        <p>''I never thought that I would be talking about my granddaughter in this fashion,'' Chief Parks said at a morning news conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chief Bernard Parks of the Los Angeles police announced today the arrest of an 18-year-old man in the fatal shooting of his granddaughter.</p>
        <p>''I never thought that I would be talking about my granddaughter in this fashion,'' Chief Parks said at a morning news conference.</p>
        <p>He encouraged city residents and officials to continue working with the police to bring an end to the violence plaguing some communities.</p>
        <p>''If we unite together as a department, city and community, we can fight this violence,'' he said. ''Enough is enough.''</p>
        <p>Samuel Sharad Shabazz was arrested early Wednesday and charged with killing Chief Parks's 20-year-old granddaughter, Lori Gonzalez. Mr. Shabazz had been picked up the day before in southwest Los Angeles for drinking in public. Based on tips, a warrant had already been issued for his arrest in the killing.</p>
        <p>Investigators say they believe that Ms. Gonzalez was the unintended victim of gang-related violence. A 20-year-old passenger in her car, identified as Ernest Thomas Gray, is said to have been the target.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray has been described as a gang member with a felony record. He was apparently wounded about three weeks before the killing, which took place about 10:15 p.m. on May 28 as he and Ms. Gonzalez were leaving a Popeyes chicken restaurant. He ducked as a gunman approached the car and shot. Ms. Gonzalez was struck several times.</p>
        <p>No weapon has been recovered, and police officials said they were looking for additional suspects. But in announcing the arrest, Detective Brian Carr said investigators were confident that they had found the gunman based on evidence and witness identifications.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shabazz was charged with one count of street-gang murder, which carries a possible death penalty or life without parole. A law making gang-related killings a capital offense went into effect earlier this year. The district attorney's office said it had not yet decided how to proceed in the case.</p>
        <p>At the request of Mr. Shabazz's public defender, arraignment was pushed back to June 23. Asked in a court appearance whether he supported the delay, Mr. Shabazz vehemently opposed the move.</p>
        <p>The shooting occurred in the Jefferson Park neighborhood of South-Central Los Angeles, where gang-related violence and drug dealing have been persistent problems.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gonzalez lived with her father in Mission Viejo, about 50 miles south of downtown Los Angeles, and was a student at Saddleback College there. She was in Los Angeles visiting her mother when she was shot. She was described as a vibrant young woman who worked two jobs and volunteered in her church.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
