<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McMullen Moves On And Devils Stay Put</title>
    <meta content="09SAND$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nashville (Tenn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcmullen, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Nashville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D8113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McMullen Moves On And Devils Stay Put</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir column recalls when John McMullen threatened to move New Jersey Devils to Nashville in 1995 because of the way the team was treated at Byrne Meadowlands Arena (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils' second appearance in the Stanley Cup finals since 1995 lacks the unmistakable whiff of carpetbagging. Remember 1995? With Lord Stanley's trophy in hand, the Devils were threatening to move to Nashville to collect a $20 million relocation bonus and every cent in revenues at a new arena.</p>
        <p>In a dispute that simmered all season, but erupted during the playoffs, the owner, John McMullen, fulminated about his team being mistreated at Byrne Meadowlands Arena (it hadn't been renamed for Continental Airlines) and the 13 lease disputes that amounted to an ''affront to the ownership.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils' second appearance in the Stanley Cup finals since 1995 lacks the unmistakable whiff of carpetbagging. Remember 1995? With Lord Stanley's trophy in hand, the Devils were threatening to move to Nashville to collect a $20 million relocation bonus and every cent in revenues at a new arena.</p>
        <p>In a dispute that simmered all season, but erupted during the playoffs, the owner, John McMullen, fulminated about his team being mistreated at Byrne Meadowlands Arena (it hadn't been renamed for Continental Airlines) and the 13 lease disputes that amounted to an ''affront to the ownership.''</p>
        <p>Today, all is quiet. McMullen is in his final days as the owner, having agreed to sell his team for $175 million to YankeeNets. He didn't want to sell, but once he recognized that Gov. Christine Todd Whitman would not approve his plan to build his dream arena with Cablevision in Hoboken, he gave up.</p>
        <p>Except for some seller's regrets, the cantankerous McMullen is quiet.</p>
        <p>But 1995 was different and stormy. The National Hockey League had locked out its players, shortening the regular season to 48 games. The playoffs started late and the finals did not end until June 24, when the Devils completed their sweep of Detroit.</p>
        <p>Three days later -- a day before the team's gala celebration in the arena's parking lot -- the Devils threatened to terminate their lease on July 6 and bolt to Opryland. The New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority promptly sought a temporary restraining order in a state court to block the move to Nashville.</p>
        <p>The Devils issued a six-page news release detailing their case against the sports authority and noted that in 1991 and 1994 officials of the authority responded to the team's claims of financial difficulties by suggesting it could move.</p>
        <p>And Nashville was beckoning, with a financial giveaway that would have fulfilled McMullen's desire to make more money than the sweetest lease he could get in East Rutherford.</p>
        <p>McMullen's threat to move presaged by five months Art Modell's emotionally wrenching uprooting of the Cleveland Browns for Baltimore. The Baltimore and Nashville deals were prime examples in the debate over how much a state, city or county should give up to lure a team.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the Devils and the sports authority agreed to a truce, and in November 1995, they signed a 12-year lease that juiced up team revenues, which are still puny compared to what would have awaited the team in Nashville. But McMullen, New Jersey born and bred, let sentiment win over his wallet.</p>
        <p>The National Hockey League expanded to Nashville and the Predators began play at the Gaylord Entertainment Center in 1998.</p>
        <p>Had McMullen moved to Nashville and begun to collect 100 percent of all revenues from tickets, media, hockey advertising, naming rights, game day parking and luxury suites, he might never have contemplated selling. Importing a winning team (rather than one that has posted two seasons with 28-47-7 records), might have made him more beloved in Nashville than Minnie Pearl.</p>
        <p>But by getting $175 million from YankeeNets, McMullen will undoubtedly capture some of what he lost by not moving his Devils.</p>
        <p>Throughout McMullen's tenure, he has usually been more renowned than his players. Lou Lamoriello, the president and general manager, built teams on sane payrolls and relatively little publicity and promotion of the players.</p>
        <p>The formula has worked on the ice, but will get some alterations under YankeeNets, which will spend where McMullen chose not to. Yet YankeeNets will still have to struggle against the perception that despite its success, the team doesn't have a city to call its own and lacks the historic profile of entrenched teams like the Yankees, Mets, Knicks, Rangers, Giants and Jets.</p>
        <p>The N.H.L remains hurt by bad ratings for the finals. Low viewership won't help raise the national profile of Devils like Scott Stevens, Martin Brodeur and Jason Arnott.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to help a team whose light has been under a bushel to get the recognition it deserves,'' said John Krimsky, chief marketing officer of YankeeNets. ''America doesn't know our players. Some companies are coming forward and saying to us, 'We didn't know you had such great players.' ''</p>
        <p>Airwaves</p>
        <p>NBC generated a 10.5 Nielsen rating Wednesday night for Game 1 of the National Basketball Association finals between the Lakers and the Pacers, down 9 percent from an 11.5 last year for the Knicks-Spurs series. Each rating point represents about 1.08 million TV households. Through the conference finals, NBC averaged a 5.7 rating, down 12 percent from last year.</p>
        <p>Steve Young's impending retirement from the San Francisco 49ers will renew speculation about his joining ABC's ''Monday Night Football.'' Young auditioned last month, his agent Leigh Steinberg said, calling part of a taped game with Al Michaels. ''That's all that's happened,'' said Steinberg. ''Obviously, Steve's a neophyte.'' Precisely why he is unlikely to get the job. ESPN's Paul Maguire remains the best choice.</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
