<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets at Yanks: A Lot of Shakin' Going On</title>
    <meta content="09YANK$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D8113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets at Yanks: A Lot of Shakin' Going On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coming series of games between Mets and Yankees will not be inflamed by any personal animosity between the players, but they do feel the zest emanating from the fans; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There will be no angry men taking the field at Yankee Stadium tonight. The Mets and the Yankees don't harbor hatred, not in the way the Dodgers despised the Giants' Sal Maglie and Leo Durocher. The extra passion Derek Jeter and Mike Piazza and others will play with this weekend is not fueled by an inherited feud.</p>
        <p>The zest comes from the fans, from the enthusiasm emanating from the packed stands, tens of thousands of folks screaming and yelling and chanting, demanding more. Players on both teams smirk at the supposed significance of Yankees versus Mets -- these are just a handful of games in a 162-game schedule -- but they love the atmosphere of these games. ''When it gets to the first pitch, it makes you feel like all your blood is flowing so fast you could stay and play the game the whole day,'' said Ricky Ledee, the Yankees' left fielder. ''It's such a great feeling to play with a lot of fans.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There will be no angry men taking the field at Yankee Stadium tonight. The Mets and the Yankees don't harbor hatred, not in the way the Dodgers despised the Giants' Sal Maglie and Leo Durocher. The extra passion Derek Jeter and Mike Piazza and others will play with this weekend is not fueled by an inherited feud.</p>
        <p>The zest comes from the fans, from the enthusiasm emanating from the packed stands, tens of thousands of folks screaming and yelling and chanting, demanding more. Players on both teams smirk at the supposed significance of Yankees versus Mets -- these are just a handful of games in a 162-game schedule -- but they love the atmosphere of these games. ''When it gets to the first pitch, it makes you feel like all your blood is flowing so fast you could stay and play the game the whole day,'' said Ricky Ledee, the Yankees' left fielder. ''It's such a great feeling to play with a lot of fans.''</p>
        <p>Players feel the adrenaline absorbed from the crowds can help them, and in some cases might hurt them. The Mets' Al Leiter and the Yankees' Roger Clemens, pitchers who often fight to contain their emotions, will pitch in the first game of the three-game interleague series. The Yankees are 32-23 and leading the American League East, the Mets 32-26 and in third place in the National League East going into last night's game against Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch, the Yankees' second baseman and leadoff hitter, might play this weekend. He had an M.R.I. on his left forearm yesterday, which confirmed the diagnosis of inflammation, and he received a shot of cortisone. The Yankees are hoping they won't have to place Knoblauch on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Jeter will run onto the field about 15 minutes before tonight's game, with a pinstriped uniform and No. 2 stitched to the back of his jersey, and will stretch and do a few sprints and absorb the emotions from the crowd, look around the stands and feel the excitement. It's part of his routine to prepare for every game. He believes large and intense crowds can improve his play. ''It makes you focus on the little things,'' Jeter said, ''especially in postseason games, when you really pay attention to detail -- one pitch, one play, one at-bat could affect the game.</p>
        <p>''I just think you may have better at-bats. It shouldn't make any difference; you should have good at-bats every time up. But you may tend to swing at better pitches. If you try too hard, try to do too much, it hurts you.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' Matt Franco had the game-winning hit with two outs in the bottom of the ninth against the Yankees last July 10, a two-run single off Mariano Rivera, ending perhaps the most memorable game between the two teams. He was aware of the crowd as he batted, aware of its intensity. ''But it didn't make me nervous or scared,'' he said. ''I felt fine; I don't know if it made me focus or concentrate more. I'd like to think not, that I'm 100 percent concentrating on every pitch, regardless of the situation. But I don't think it can help but affect you in a positive way.''</p>
        <p>There are ''probably some players'' who might be hurt by an intense collection of fans, Franco added. ''But I think most of us are pretty much showoffs, and that's a time to do something really good in front of a lot of people. It's kind of like you're on stage, and the more people who are watching you, the more pumped up you get to do something good.''</p>
        <p>Ledee played extraordinarily in the 1998 World Series against San Diego, collecting 6 hits in 10 at-bats, including a key double against Kevin Brown. He could hear the buzz of the fans between pitches at Yankee Stadium, he said. Their feelings became his; their energy became his. When Ledee stood at second after the double, his adrenaline racing, ''I really felt like crying,'' he said. ''The whole stadium for me felt like it was shaking. Probably it was me who was shaking. It was just incredible.</p>
        <p>''Every time you play in the Stadium, people get into it. The crowds in some places give up, they get tired, they don't cheer. When we played in Atlanta in the World Series, you could see it was like their fans were acting; they were trying to be rough. And when we were playing San Diego, too, they were trying to be rough, but that's not the way they are; they kind of get tired. At home, they never get tired.''</p>
        <p>Ledee recalled a game last July 24, when the Yankees destroyed Cleveland, 21-1, at Yankee Stadium. Playing right field late in the game, Ledee played a line drive conservatively and did not try to throw out the Indian who scored Cleveland's only run. ''They booed like crazy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dave Mlicki was helped by the adrenaline rush from the stands in 1997, when he pitched a shutout against the Yankees in the first interleague game between these two teams. His fastball had a little extra zip, he thought, his curveball was sharp. Hard-throwing pitchers like Clemens can use the extra emotion as well: Rocket fuel. He usually throws 93 to 95 miles an hour, and a big crowd can push those readings to 97 or 98 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>But pitchers can be hurt by the adrenaline push from the stands. Clemens and Leiter can suddenly lose their rhythm of their mechanics, like a speeding car going out of control. ''The first couple of innings are critical because, If you can get through the first couple of innings, your intensity elevates, your concentration increases and you can feed off the crowd,'' Leiter said. ''If you start out poorly and you're down a couple of runs, then the crowd can work against you.''</p>
        <p>Andy Pettitte, who starts Saturday, relies on his control and movement on his fastball to get hitters out. If he throws too hard, he loses control and movement. ''Whenever I get pumped up and am getting juiced up with my fastball,'' Pettitte said, ''that's when I start getting shellacked.''</p>
        <p>Pitching in Boston in Game 5 of the American League Championship Series last Oct. 18, Mike Stanton entered the game to face Boston's Troy O'Leary, and walked him; Stanton was immediately replaced.</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt it affects you. A lot of times it doesn't matter which stadium you're in, home or road. You've got to take a step back and tell yourself, 'I'm trying to get people out.' ''</p>
        <p>Stanton and the rest of the Yankees and Mets will be trying to find a place of peace -- peace of mind -- in a chaotic Yankee Stadium this weekend.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
