<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Donald Judd</title>
    <meta content="RV234904" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judd, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EED9113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Donald Judd</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews Donald Judd's sculpture at Dia Center for the Arts; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dia Center for the Arts</p>
        <p>545 West 22nd Street, Chelsea</p>
        <p>Though June 18</p>
        <p>Although the sculptor Donald Judd is considered a leader of Minimal art, he had little use for art movements and considered his own work more than ''sufficiently complex,'' to use one of his favorite crypticisms. Nonetheless the untitled Judd sculpture from 1976 that is finishing its sojourn at the Dia Center for the Arts is a classic of the genre. Consisting of 15 largish plywood boxes, it has all the telltale signs -- repeating forms, unadorned surfaces and, well, boxes -- but also manages to transcend its category.</p>
        <p>The piece represented both a departure and return to basics for Judd, best known by 1976 for luxe sculptures made of sleek metals and opaque Plexiglas. Plywood had been the staple of his art a dozen years earlier, but never unpainted. Another staple was the floor box, made in several variations and endlessly considered in his drawings. But never had he laid out so many variations at once or considered them as a single work. As much three-dimensional drawing as sculpture, the Dia piece has a speculative, handmade, down-home quality. Each box is a variation on a volumetric theme achieved by one or two adjustments to a container that is usually open at the top and always measures three feet high and five feet across and deep. (These dimensions create an important proportional contrast of rectangular elevation to square footprint.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dia Center for the Arts</p>
        <p>545 West 22nd Street, Chelsea</p>
        <p>Though June 18</p>
        <p>Although the sculptor Donald Judd is considered a leader of Minimal art, he had little use for art movements and considered his own work more than ''sufficiently complex,'' to use one of his favorite crypticisms. Nonetheless the untitled Judd sculpture from 1976 that is finishing its sojourn at the Dia Center for the Arts is a classic of the genre. Consisting of 15 largish plywood boxes, it has all the telltale signs -- repeating forms, unadorned surfaces and, well, boxes -- but also manages to transcend its category.</p>
        <p>The piece represented both a departure and return to basics for Judd, best known by 1976 for luxe sculptures made of sleek metals and opaque Plexiglas. Plywood had been the staple of his art a dozen years earlier, but never unpainted. Another staple was the floor box, made in several variations and endlessly considered in his drawings. But never had he laid out so many variations at once or considered them as a single work. As much three-dimensional drawing as sculpture, the Dia piece has a speculative, handmade, down-home quality. Each box is a variation on a volumetric theme achieved by one or two adjustments to a container that is usually open at the top and always measures three feet high and five feet across and deep. (These dimensions create an important proportional contrast of rectangular elevation to square footprint.)</p>
        <p>The piece is laid out in three rows of five and the ensemble effect is of a Ping-Pong game with several balls in play, ideas bouncing all over the place. A couple of boxes have bottoms tilted on the diagonal in ways that are different, if equally startling upon approach. Several others are doubled by interior boxes but have little discrepancies. Often you realize that two boxes have an identical variation that has had a further adjustment in one case, like a slightly raised bottom plane.</p>
        <p>The Dia piece laid the groundwork for one of the crowning achievements of Judd's career, the series of 100 milled aluminum boxes that fill two giant rehabilitated artillery sheds at the Chinati Foundation in Marfa, Tex. But I like its precursor as much, if not more. For one thing it shows Judd thinking out loud. Not all the ideas made the final cut: a box with four sides pushed in a few inches, for example, that resembles an awkward, square spool. Another has a top plane that seems to levitate -- an aberrant moment of illusion from an artist who hated it.</p>
        <p>But the main point about this piece is that it is all emphatically there to be seen. The ideas are there for the looking, which is generous, and they are not systemic or predictable, which is fun. Judd's love of visible space and declarative structure and his exaltation of the powers of human perception -- the main themes of his art -- are fully evident. And countering such high-mindedness is the plywood, which just gets crazier and crazier. Its warm glow and moire patterns even start to resemble a flat-footed, diagrammatic send-up of the reflective surfaces of Judd's svelte metal and Plexiglas pieces.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
