<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paulson Hopes Fast Start Leads to Successful Finish</title>
    <meta content="09GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buick Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paulson, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD9113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paulson Hopes Fast Start Leads to Successful Finish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISON, N.Y., June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dennis Paulson leads field by one stroke after first round of Buick Open at Westchester Country Club; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After another strong start at the Buick Classic, Dennis Paulson was hoping for a happier finish.</p>
        <p>In last year's tournament, Paulson was defeated by Duffy Waldorf on the first hole of a sudden-death playoff. Instead of capturing his first PGA Tour victory, Paulson saw Waldorf birdie the final three holes, a sudden turn of events that would be difficult for any player to stomach. Paulson, however, took the philosophical approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After another strong start at the Buick Classic, Dennis Paulson was hoping for a happier finish.</p>
        <p>In last year's tournament, Paulson was defeated by Duffy Waldorf on the first hole of a sudden-death playoff. Instead of capturing his first PGA Tour victory, Paulson saw Waldorf birdie the final three holes, a sudden turn of events that would be difficult for any player to stomach. Paulson, however, took the philosophical approach.</p>
        <p>''I didn't lose the golf tournament, he won it,'' Paulson, who shot a 67 in his final round last year, said. ''I have not lost one bit of sleep over what happened last year at this tournament.''</p>
        <p>Paulson will not lose any sleep over today's round either. Shooting a six-under-par 65, his third consecutive round in the 60's at Westchester Country Club, Paulson held a one-stroke lead on a tightly-bunched leader board after 18 holes. Three players were tied at 66 including the defending champion Waldorf (66), who was tied with Davis Love III and Miguel Angel Jimenez of Spain.</p>
        <p>Gabriel Hjertstedt, Skip Kendall and John Maginnes were another stroke back.</p>
        <p>But the rest of the field was chasing Paulson, a 37-year-old California native who spent years playing on the Asian Tour and the Nike Tour before finally making golf's elite level. Paulson had a breakthrough 1999, finishing 27th on the money list and winning more than $1.56 million. But this year has been a struggle; in 14 starts, he has not had a top 10 finish.</p>
        <p>The high point of Paulson's 2000 campaign occurred on Thursday of Masters week, when he shot 68 to take the first-round lead. But even that boost of confidence did not last, as he ballooned to a second-round 76 and settled for a tie for 14th.</p>
        <p>But something clicks when Paulson arrives at Westchester. Today, he sounded like a player who believed he could win.</p>
        <p>''Probably the most solid round I played all year,'' said Paulson, after a bogey-free round that included six birdies. ''I drove the ball well when I had to and I hit a lot of good iron shots.</p>
        <p>''I've been shooting 73, 74, 75 the first day and shooting myself out of the tournament. But I've seen a lot of improvement in the last month or so. I only had one bad iron shot all day.''</p>
        <p>All the leaders followed the same game plan, avoiding the gnarly four-inch rough at Westchester, which punished anyone who did not drive the ball accurately. The best way to deal with the rough was to stay out of it. And Waldorf, trying to become only the second player to win in consecutive years at Westchester, let his accurate driving set the tone for his lowest round ever at the Buick Classic.</p>
        <p>Teeing off on No. 10, Waldorf ended the day in style, making an eagle on the par-5, 505-yard ninth hole, reaching the green in two shots and making a 20-foot putt.</p>
        <p>''As my game has gotten better, I've learned to appreciate the course a lot more and it's starting to play into my strengths,'' said Waldorf, trying to join Ernie Els (1996, 1997) as Westchester's only back-to-back winners.</p>
        <p>''You have to be very precise off the tee and really plan your position on the second shots. I only missed a couple of fairways, so that was a real important key to the round. As you know, the rough is really tough out here.''</p>
        <p>Jimenez knew the rough was tough, but his ball was never in it. He never missed a fairway, displaying the consistency off the tee that helped him earn a place on last year's European Ryder Cup team and boosted him to No. 20 in the world.</p>
        <p>As part of the overseas contingent that has added strength to this week's field, Jimenez arrived in New York on Sunday night and got his first look at the course on Monday. Apparently, Jimenez learns quickly. And for the other European players, this week's tournament provided a perfect stopover point on the way to next week's United States Open at Pebble Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>''It's always nice to play the week before a major, and it's three hours difference here,'' said Jimenez, referring to the time change between New York and California. ''Better to have three hours than nine.''</p>
        <p>For Love, today was another opportunity to take advantage of his length off the tee. He birdied two of the three par-five holes and his putting was solid, which is a good sign for next week.</p>
        <p>Love has been criticized for not winning since April 1998. In 13 starts this year, he has seven top 10 finishes, six top 5 finishes and three second-place finishes. This week, Love hoped to save his best round for the last round.</p>
        <p>''A win this week and a win next week and it would be a huge year,'' said Love, who enjoys coming to New York after winning the 1997 P.G.A. Championship at Winged Foot Country Club in Mamaroneck, N.Y. ''A great year would be winning one of the next three majors. And if I'm in the running this week, it will help me next week.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Among other players, PHIL MICKELSON and FRED COUPLES both shot 69; DAVID DUVAL, ERNIE ELS, JOSE MARIA OLAZABAL, VIJAY SINGH and CRAIG STADLER were at 70; JESPER PARNEVIK and GREG NORMAN were at 71; STEVE ELKINGTON and TOM LEHMAN shot 72; and SERGIO GARCIA shot 74.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
