<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CBS's 'Early Show' Draws Complaints, Not Crowds</title>
    <meta content="09EARL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">General Motors Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brozan, Nadine</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Early Show, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDA113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CBS's 'Early Show' Draws Complaints, Not Crowds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADINE BROZAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brozan, Nadine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People living near 59th Street and Fifth Avenue sue CBS in effort to stop live performances and other noise generated by The Early Show in plaza in front of General Motors Building; complaints are another embarrassment to a program that has been a ratings disappointment since its debut in November; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When ''Today'' began broadcasting from a street-level studio in the early 1990's, using Rockefeller Plaza as its backdrop, it helped propel the show to first place in the ratings. The tactic was so successful that it was copied by ''Good Morning America,'' which opened a glass-walled studio in Times Square last year.</p>
        <p>But when ''The Early Show,'' the CBS program with Bryant Gumbel, tried the same tactic, there was one problem: the studio at Fifth Avenue and 59th Street is next door to one of the more expensive residential properties in New York, and the neighbors did not appreciate waking up to rock bands and other musical acts early in the morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When ''Today'' began broadcasting from a street-level studio in the early 1990's, using Rockefeller Plaza as its backdrop, it helped propel the show to first place in the ratings. The tactic was so successful that it was copied by ''Good Morning America,'' which opened a glass-walled studio in Times Square last year.</p>
        <p>But when ''The Early Show,'' the CBS program with Bryant Gumbel, tried the same tactic, there was one problem: the studio at Fifth Avenue and 59th Street is next door to one of the more expensive residential properties in New York, and the neighbors did not appreciate waking up to rock bands and other musical acts early in the morning.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, as the ethereal sounds of the liturgical cantata ''Dona Nobis Pacem'' were sung by a high school choir from Peoria, Ariz., Frederick A. Klingenstein, president of the co-op board of the Sherry-Netherland Hotel, was not pleased. He and residents of the 164 other co-op apartments in the building, 70 of which are rented out as luxury hotel suites, say they have also had to contend with morning appearances by Martha and the Vandellas, Little Anthony and the Imperials and other groups.</p>
        <p>The residents are so disgruntled that they have gone to court to block the outdoor performances outside the program's shiny glass home in the General Motors Building.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the hotel asked the New York State Supreme Court to ban the outdoor concerts during the program's hours, from 7 to 9 a.m. They also want to ban the use of amplifiers, six of which are permanently affixed to the exterior of the studio.</p>
        <p>For CBS, the complaints are another embarrassment to a program that has been a ratings disappointment since its debut in November. The network had hoped that Mr. Gumbel's star quality would give it a challenger to ''Good Morning America'' and ''Today.''</p>
        <p>Reacting to the complaints from neighbors, a lawyer for CBS, Richard Davis of Weil, Gotshal &amp; Manges, contended that city agencies, and not the court system, have jurisdiction over application of the noise code.</p>
        <p>At a hearing on the issue yesterday, Justice Barbara R. Kapnick in Manhattan conceded that ''I wouldn't appreciate people screaming or yelling at 7 a.m. in front of my apartment.'' But she postponed her decision on the residents' request for a preliminary  injunction.</p>
        <p>Although musical acts occasionally perform for the program, there is not much screaming or yelling in the plaza because there are few spectators, other than curious stragglers and people en route to work.</p>
        <p>By contrast, ''Today'' has throngs of people waving banners reading ''Hi, Mom'' for the folks back home, and ''Good Morning America'' is drawing growing numbers of spectators outside its Times Square studio.</p>
        <p>So it is not crowds that disturb the residents of this bastion of Old World civility, but the liturgical compositions, rock 'n' roll or any other form of music that threatens their sleep.</p>
        <p>''If they had 2,000 people praying on the plaza, I don't think it would be a major concern,'' said Mr. Klingenstein, former chairman of the Mount Sinai Medical Center. ''We have no objection to them utilizing the studio internally, but we would like to see them stop utilizing the plaza to create noise and disturbance.</p>
        <p>''We have had numerous complaints at the front desk,'' he added. ''Clearly a person renting a room -- and the average room rate is $370 a night -- doesn't want to be awakened at 7 or even 8 a.m. by this intrusion.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klingenstein said that he was able to hear the music even though he lives above the 30th floor and the hotel has double-hung windows.</p>
        <p>Steve Friedman, senior executive producer of ''The Early Show,'' responded, ''We're mindful of where we're at. We've been good neighbors for the past seven months, and we're doing a terrific job in keeping everything we do in the bounds of the law.''</p>
        <p>Although the hearing yesterday was limited to issues of sound, Eva Talel, a partner at Stroock &amp; Stroock &amp; Lavan, who represents the Sherry-Netherland, said before the hearing, ''The court appearance today involves just a piece of the case. The rest of it says that they shouldn't be out there at all. They are taking over a public plaza for their own commercial purposes. NBC is in a privately owned area, Rockefeller Center, and ABC brings its crowds into the studio and does its concerts in Bryant Park.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
