<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Belfour's Efforts in Goal Keep the Stars in the Game</title>
    <meta content="09STAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STANLEY CUP FINALS: DEVILS VS. STARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belfour, Ed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3D8113FF93AA35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Belfour's Efforts in Goal Keep the Stars in the Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Friday, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ed Belfour, Dallas Stars goalie, holds New Jersey Devils scoreless in Game 5 of Stanley Cup finals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If it were not for Ed Belfour, the Dallas Stars would never have had a chance today.</p>
        <p>And when his teammate Mike Modano scored in the third overtime for a 1-0 victory this morning, Belfour's effort ensured the Stars of a Game 6 in Dallas. Belfour finished with 48 saves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If it were not for Ed Belfour, the Dallas Stars would never have had a chance today.</p>
        <p>And when his teammate Mike Modano scored in the third overtime for a 1-0 victory this morning, Belfour's effort ensured the Stars of a Game 6 in Dallas. Belfour finished with 48 saves.</p>
        <p>The game was scoreless after regulation and two overtimes because both Belfour and the Devils' Martin Brodeur, who stopped 40 shots,  took turns standing on their heads.</p>
        <p>After two periods alone, the Devils could easily have had a 3-0 lead. That is how good Belfour was. Through two overtimes, he had 45 saves.</p>
        <p>Belfour's performance earned him a small measure of redemption. It was his Game 1 performance, in which he allowed six goals on 18 shots before being pulled, that put the Stars in an early hole in the series. Though Dallas rebounded to win Game 2, the Stars lost Games 3 and 4 at home. Belfour had something to prove.</p>
        <p>The Dallas goaltender faced five odd-man rushes in the first period alone this evening. Jay Pandolfo (two and a half minutes in) and Patrik Elias (with just over four minutes left) each broke in on Belfour on breakaways. Belfour stopped both tries.</p>
        <p>With a half a minute left in the first, in the midst of a line change, Elias and Bobby Holik broke in on Belfour on a two-on-one. Elias fed Holik with a pass across the slot, and Holik was looking at nothing but net. He fanned.</p>
        <p>On the same play, the puck eventually slid out to Scott Stevens at the top of the slot. Belfour was way out of position. Stevens fanned, too.</p>
        <p>So what if Belfour had a little luck. He had earned it. The Devils were credited with seven shots on goal in the first period. They had as many scoring opportunities.</p>
        <p>But with his team a game away from relinquishing the Stanley Cup to New Jersey, Belfour came up big. Time and time again.</p>
        <p>The Devils, sensing the series was theirs, turned their game up a notch in the second period. New Jersey was credited with 11 shots on goal in the period, but Belfour was there every time. And when he wasn't, his luck had not run out.</p>
        <p>Holik had a particularly good period -- and nothing to show for it. He nearly scored a minute into the second when his bad-angle shot from off the left post nearly ricocheted in off Richard Matvichuk's skate. Midway through the period, Holik deked Belfour out of position, only to have his shot hit the outside of the right post with Belfour down.</p>
        <p>Finally, with just over two minutes left in the period, Belfour stoned Holik twice, beating the Devils' center to the left post with his right pad to stop Holik's initial shot, then stopping Holik's backhanded attempt on the rebound. After Holik had gone off on a change, he could be seen shaking his head on the bench.</p>
        <p>The Devils opened the third period the way they had the first two: on the attack. They had at least four more scoring opportunities in the first four minutes of the period. In the last four, they had at least three more. Holik was positively snakebit. With just over three minutes in regulation, Belfour closed his five-hole on a Holik backhander from the right post. Twenty seconds later, Belfour somehow stopped a Petr Sykora one-timer from the left circle on a puck that had taken a strange bounce off the door along the backboards from which the Zamboni enters and exits the ice.</p>
        <p>Midway through the second overtime, Belfour came up with his biggest save yet. With the Stars caught on a line change, Ken Daneyko led Alexander Mogilny in on a breakaway. Mogilny elevated a wrist shot from the top of the slot, but Belfour knocked it down with his glove then tucked the puck back into his body with the stick for his 43rd save. The Stars were still clinging for life.</p>
        <p>STANLEY CUP FINALS: DEVILS VS. STARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
