<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Your Mother's Mayonnaise: A Great French Sauce for Summer</title>
    <meta content="02DRES$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayonnaise</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0DA113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Your Mother's Mayonnaise: A Great French Sauce for Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amanda Hesser article on preparing homemade mayonnaise; photos; recipes (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was 1993, and I had my first kitchen job, at a restaurant in Boston. I listened in as the sous-chef and a cook bent over a blender, the sous-chef slowly giving instructions. With the machine whirring, egg yolks were dropped in. Then oil, in an erratic, drippy stream. A sunny yellow sauce rapidly formed. I asked what it was.</p>
        <p>''Mayonnaise,'' the sous-chef said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was 1993, and I had my first kitchen job, at a restaurant in Boston. I listened in as the sous-chef and a cook bent over a blender, the sous-chef slowly giving instructions. With the machine whirring, egg yolks were dropped in. Then oil, in an erratic, drippy stream. A sunny yellow sauce rapidly formed. I asked what it was.</p>
        <p>''Mayonnaise,'' the sous-chef said.</p>
        <p>I almost fell over.</p>
        <p>Although I grew up with a mother who baked bread, made her own jam and never once bought a cake, I thought mayonnaise was something from a jar. I knew what it should taste like, but I never really knew what it was, and certainly not what it could be: something silky, pronounced, a delicacy all its own.</p>
        <p>Since I tasted that soft, buttery sauce, I have rarely gone back to the commercial kind. Watching that mayonnaise whirl together in what seemed seconds was one of those revelatory moments people new to cooking have, and it changed me. If you could make something so splendid from ingredients so ordinary, so unlikely, cooking must be full of many more unearthed secrets. (It is.)</p>
        <p>And though most of America still depends on the stiff, oily mayonnaise in jars, to serious cooks making their own has become as fundamental as whisking together vinaigrette. As eggs have grown safer in recent years, many home cooks have been emboldened to make it a part of their regular repertory. Hellmann's is a fine product, sweet and tangy as it is. But homemade mayonnaise is something entirely different.</p>
        <p>It is perfectly delicious spread on sandwiches or dressing a salad, but it can also become the foundation of a more complex dipping sauce or dressing. Though there is no reason to improve basic mayonnaise, there seem to be an infinite number of ways to enhance it. Eggs and oil welcome almost anything into their realm, including spicy greens like watercress and also horseradish, avocados, chipotle peppers and mustard.</p>
        <p>In the summer, when I don't feel like cooking an entire meal, I often gather a few vegetables from my neighborhood market, blanch them in boiling salted water, whisk together a mayonnaise and break a baguette into pieces. I dunk the artichokes, asparagus, carrots or whatever into the mayonnaise and sop up whatever is left with the bread. It is a perfect supper, easy, restorative and adequately indulgent. In Provence, cooks have been doing that forever, but  they make the mayonnaise with garlic and call it aioli.</p>
        <p>Making mayonnaise is meditative. You can whip it up in a blender or food processor -- and there are times, as with an herb mayonnaise, when you need a machine to chop as well as to emulsify -- but I always do it by hand.</p>
        <p>I have a small French whisk with many, many loosely layered wire loops and a stainless steel bowl. The egg yolk falls into the bowl like a thick drop of paint, and I loosen it with vinegar or lemon juice, a pinch of coarse sea salt and a little Dijon mustard. It smooths out with a few strokes of the whisk, and then I add the oil, usually peanut or vegetable, whisking steadily, almost frantically at first, to break up the oil. When it is incorporating correctly, it seems to melt into the folds of the liquid, disappearing until no drops of oil can be seen on the sides.</p>
        <p>Gradually, I add the oil more quickly, whisking, whisking, until the oil and mayonnaise are no longer at odds, blending as fluidly as vermouth and gin in a martini. The smooth, yellow emulsion clings to the sides of the bowl. I taste, add a little salt and whisk again, and in a few minutes -- no more -- it is ready.</p>
        <p>You can do this faster in a blender or food processor, but I have found I have more control with a whisk, and it is just as easy.</p>
        <p>I use a mildly flavored oil so that the richness of the egg comes through. Many people use olive oil and are disappointed. The result is often heavy and bitter. I use stronger, similar oils to flavor the mayonnaise. I might whisk in a few tablespoons of extra virgin olive oil, walnut oil or Asian sesame oil at the end. So small an amount can scent the entire sauce without overwhelming it.</p>
        <p>Choosing a liquid is perhaps the most difficult decision. The oil needs a liquid to emulsify and stabilize the sauce. You can use just water. But some kind of acid is typically preferred. Almost any will work: red wine vinegar, rice vinegar, Champagne vinegar, sherry vinegar, apple cider vinegar, lime juice, grapefruit juice, lemon juice, Meyer lemon juice, too.</p>
        <p>Beyond these basic components you are free to roam, within reason. Garlic in particular does good things to oil and eggs. I add at least a sliver to most mayonnaise recipes as a gentle background flavor.</p>
        <p>If you keep adding garlic, you'll get aioli. I have read recipes for 16 cloves to a cup of oil. If you plan to carry on any conversations in person for the rest of the week, three might be a better start.</p>
        <p>But garlic is unpredictable. Some is wickedly strong, and some is subtle. Crush it with the side of a knife, chop it to a paste and add it at the beginning.</p>
        <p>If you want the aioli stronger, whisk in more garlic later. Aioli, like most flavored mayonnaises, needs to sit a few hours (in a refrigerator) before serving, to mellow.</p>
        <p>Last week, I added a few crushed anchovy fillets with garlic cloves to a mayonnaise. It became a decadent cousin to anchoide, the French anchovy dressing, and seemed destined for a steak sandwich.</p>
        <p>Then I charred a red pepper and pushed it into a blender with a mayonnaise made with a whisk and a bowl. It turned a pretty salmon pink and tasted sweet, smoky and only vaguely of red pepper.</p>
        <p>Another time, I packed the blender with arugula and pureed the fresh leaves into mayonnaise until it was smooth, pale green and peppery. I spread it on day-old bread, rubbed with a tomato, and covered it with a piece of serrano ham. You could substitute basil and watercress for the arugula.</p>
        <p>Herbs can be added in the blender, or you can chop them up and stir them in at the end. In the blender, you will get a delicate, uniform sauce. By hand, you will get something more eventful. Some tastes will be smooth as a pastry cream, others enlivened with bursts of flavor from the herb.</p>
        <p>Mayonnaise, of course, is the basis of many salad dressings and sauces. Tartar sauce is just mayonnaise loaded with salty bits of gherkins, shallots or onion and capers. Sour cream is sometimes added to mayonnaise to make a creamy and tangy dressing on wedges of lettuce.</p>
        <p>I tried whole milk yogurt to see what would happen. The two allied beautifully. The yogurt added a sharper tang and creaminess without weighing down the sauce. A little heavy cream stirred into a bowl of mayonnaise turned up a gentle, light sauce that could be eaten by the spoonful. I folded it into a salad of smoked mackerel, red potatoes and celery. The cream in the mayonnaise tempered the smoke in the fish and thinly washed its flavor over everything as a shadow softens a landscape.</p>
        <p>A standard mayonnaise would have been too thick for this salad. The cream stretched it out and made it easier to pour. You can also loosen mayonnaise by adding yogurt or even water. A tablespoon or so is usually plenty.</p>
        <p>Once the egg yolk and oil emulsify into mayonnaise, it is a fairly stable concoction. A little water, a little more acid or a lot of mustard is not going to shake its foundation. Getting it to coalesce in the beginning is the challenge.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a mayonnaise will start thickening and then suddenly turn liquid, or break. It could be caused by anything from the temperature of the ingredients to the speed at which the oil is being added.</p>
        <p>To avoid this hazard, make sure all ingredients are at room temperature, and when you first add oil, do it a few drops at a time and no faster. If you add the oil too quickly, it is like flooding an engine. The emulsifiers in the yolks are overwhelmed by the oil.</p>
        <p>If your mayonnaise breaks, don't throw it out. Get a fresh bowl and a new egg yolk. Begin mixing the yolk with the acid, salt and whatever else you put in the first batch and then treat the broken batch as if it were the oil, whisking it in drop by drop. Once this emulsifies, you can add oil until the sauce is like your original vision for the mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>By now, I have broken many mayonnaises. But I have yet to make one that has disappointed me. One with lots of lemon juice and lemon zest folded into chopped eggs changed my opinion of egg salad. I used another, flecked with coriander and cumin, to dress red and savoy cabbage, but it made me consider roasting lamb, just so I could make a sandwich with it.</p>
        <p>A lime mayonnaise with sieved avocado stirred in on a whim was as green as a baby leaf and startlingly rich. It ended on chicken and fennel. But it may end up with potatoes next time.</p>
        <p>One of the best consequences of making mayonnaise is that you have to make more than you need for a meal. A cup is about the least you can make, so there is always some left over.</p>
        <p>The next day when you pull it from the refrigerator, you can congratulate yourself and choose its next fate. A basil mayonnaise for burgers one day has renewed vitality in a chicken salad the next.</p>
        <p>None of this means that I have turned my back on what I first knew as mayonnaise. My mother makes a chicken salad with almonds, grapes and celery. Commercial mayonnaise holds it together and asserts itself sharply, sweetly. I would never try to make her salad with homemade mayonnaise. Both have their place.</p>
        <p>STANDARD MAYONNAISE  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1 egg yolk  Sliver of a garlic clove, crushed  1 teaspoon Dijon or English mustard  2 teaspoons lemon juice  Sea salt  1 cup peanut oil or vegetable oil.</p>
        <p>In a small bowl, whisk together egg yolk, garlic, mustard, lemon juice and a large pinch salt. Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in oil. As it emulsifies, add oil a little faster, in a slow steady stream. When mixture is thick, taste and adjust seasoning. It should be highly seasoned.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 1 1/4 cups.</p>
        <p>Variation 1: Add  1/4 cup walnut oil.</p>
        <p>Variation 2: Reduce lemon juice to one teaspoon, and add truffle oil to taste.</p>
        <p>Variation 3: Add 3 tablespoons heavy cream.</p>
        <p>ARUGULA MAYONNAISE  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1 egg yolk  2 teaspoons Dijon mustard  1 tablespoon white wine vinegar  Sea salt</p>
        <p>3/4 cup vegetable oil</p>
        <p>1/4 cup extra virgin olive oil  2 1/2 cups tightly packed arugula.</p>
        <p>1. In a small bowl, whisk together egg yolk, mustard, vinegar and large pinch of salt. Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in oils. As it emulsifies, add oil a little faster in a slow, steady stream. When mixture is thick, taste, and adjust seasoning. It should be highly seasoned.</p>
        <p>2. Transfer mixture to a blender or food processor, add arugula, and puree. (Add a tablespoon of water, if necessary, to get arugula flowing.) Taste, and adjust seasoning before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 1 1/4 cups.</p>
        <p>ROASTED RED PEPPER MAYONNAISE  Time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>1 large red pepper  1 egg yolk  1 teaspoon Dijon mustard</p>
        <p>1/2 tablespoon white wine vinegar  Sea salt</p>
        <p>3/4 cup vegetable oil</p>
        <p>1/4 cup extra virgin olive oil.</p>
        <p>1. Heat broiler. Place pepper under broiler, and roast until blackened on all sides. Remove, and let cool. Peel away skin and seeds, and discard. Pull pepper into 3 or 4 long pieces and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. In a small bowl, whisk together egg yolk, mustard, vinegar and a large pinch of salt.  Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in oils. As they emulsify, add oils a little faster, in a slow steady stream. When mixture is thick, taste and adjust seasoning. It should be highly seasoned.</p>
        <p>3. Transfer the mixture to a blender or a food processor, add the pepper and puree. Taste, and adjust the seasoning before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 1 1/4 cups.</p>
        <p>POTATO AND SMOKED MACKEREL SALAD WITH CREAMY MAYONNAISE  Time: 35 minutes, plus 1 hour's refrigeration</p>
        <p>1 1/4 pounds (about 15) baby red-skinned potatoes, washed  Sea salt and freshly ground grains of paradise (see note) or black pepper</p>
        <p>1/4 peeled red onion, thinly sliced  1 stalk celery, thinly sliced on the diagonal  1 smoked mackerel fillet, skin discarded  1 large egg yolk</p>
        <p>1/2 tablespoon Dijon mustard  1 tablespoon red wine vinegar, more to taste  1 cup peanut oil  3 tablespoons heavy cream.</p>
        <p>1. Place potatoes in a medium pan, cover with water and season generously with salt. Bring to a boil, reduce to a simmer and cook until tender, about 15 minutes. Drain. When cool enough, slice into  1/4-inch rounds.</p>
        <p>2. In a large bowl, combine potatoes, red onion and celery. By hand, shred mackerel into pieces no larger than a raspberry; there should be about 1 cup. Add to salad.</p>
        <p>3. Prepare mayonnaise: In a small bowl, whisk together the egg yolk, mustard, vinegar and large pinches of salt and grains of paradise. Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in oil. As it emulsifies, add oil a little faster, in a slow, steady stream. When mixture is thick, whisk in heavy cream.</p>
        <p>4. Fold  1/3 cup mayonnaise into potato mixture. There should be just enough mayonnaise to coat ingredients; add more if necessary. Cover, and refrigerate for at least an  hour. Adjust seasonings before serving, adding more salt or vinegar as needed.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: Grains of paradise are at Adriana's Caravan in Grand Central Terminal, (212) 972-8804 ($6.50 for 2 ounces), and Kalustyan's, 123 Lexington Avenue, at 28th Street, (212) 685-3451 ($3.49 an ounce).</p>
        <p>CABBAGE SALAD WITH TOASTED CORIANDER AND CUMIN MAYONNAISE  Time: 20 minutes, plus 1 hour's refrigeration</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon coriander seeds  1 teaspoon cumin seeds  3 cups thinly shredded savoy cabbage  2 cups thinly shredded red cabbage  1 large egg yolk  2 tablespoons apple cider vinegar, or more to taste  1 shallot lobe, minced  1 tablespoon thinly sliced chives  Sea salt and ground black pepper  1 1/4 cups vegetable oil.</p>
        <p>1. In a small skillet over high heat (or in a microwave oven at full power), toast coriander seeds and cumin seeds just until fragrant. Grind together using a mortar and pestle, and set aside. In a large bowl, combine savoy cabbage and red cabbage, and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Prepare mayonnaise: In a small bowl, whisk together egg yolk, vinegar, shallot, chives, reserved coriander and cumin and large pinches of salt and pepper. Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in oil. As it emulsifies, add oil a little faster, in a slow steady stream. When mixture is thick, whisk in more vinegar to taste; mayonnaise should be highly seasoned.</p>
        <p>3. Fold  1/3 cup mayonnaise into cabbage.  There should be enough to coat cabbage generously; add more if necessary. Cover, and refrigerate for at least an hour. Before serving, adjust seasonings, adding more salt or vinegar as needed.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>CHICKEN AND AVOCADO SALAD WITH LIME MAYONNAISE  Time: 65 minutes, plus 1 hour's refrigeration</p>
        <p>1 2 3/4 pound chicken, with neck, rinsed and patted dry  1 teaspoon black peppercorns  8 cloves of whole unpeeled garlic, plus  1/2 clove garlic, peeled and chopped  1 medium bulb fennel, with leaves  Coarse sea salt  2 scallions, thinly sliced  1 1/2 avocados  3 tablespoons fresh lime juice, or more to taste  1 large egg yolk  1 tablespoon Dijon mustard</p>
        <p>3/4 cup vegetable oil</p>
        <p>1/4 cup, plus 2 tablespoons whole milk yogurt.</p>
        <p>1. In a large soup pot, combine chicken, chicken neck, peppercorns and whole garlic cloves. Cut fennel bulb into  1/4-inch dice, and reserve  1/2 cup; add remainder to pot. Chop  fennel leaves, and reserve 2 tablespoons; add remainder to pot. Add just enough water to cover chicken, and season generously with sea salt. Bring to a boil, then reduce to a simmer. Cook until chicken juices run clear when sliced at a joint, 20 to 25 minutes.  Transfer chicken to a plate and allow to cool completely. Reserve broth for another use.</p>
        <p>2. Remove meat from chicken, discarding skin and bones. Cut meat into  1/2-inch pieces.  Place in a large bowl with reserved fennel bulb, reserved fennel leaves and scallions.  Peel and cut one avocado into  1/2-inch cubes, and add to bowl. Sprinkle with 1 tablespoon  lime juice, and toss gently to mix.</p>
        <p>3. Prepare mayonnaise: In a small bowl, whisk together egg yolk, 1 tablespoon lime juice, mustard, chopped garlic and a large pinch of salt and pepper. Beginning a drop at a time, whisk in vegetable oil. As it emulsifies, add oil a little faster in a slow, steady stream. When all oil is incorporated and mixture is thick, press remaining half of avocado through a sieve into mixture.  Add remaining tablespoon lime juice and  yogurt, and whisk to blend. Season to taste with salt and pepper; it should be highly seasoned.</p>
        <p>4. Fold  1/3 cup mayonnaise into chicken.  There should be just enough mayonnaise to coat ingredients; add more if necessary.  Cover and refrigerate for at least an hour.  Adjust seasonings before serving, adding more lime juice as desired.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
