<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>W.H.O. Says Files Show Tobacco Companies Fought Antimsoking Efforts</title>
    <meta content="Y02TOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/02/world/02TOBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Health Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philip Morris Cos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meier, Barry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bible, Geoffrey C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DD1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>W.H.O. Says Files Show Tobacco Companies Fought Antimsoking Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meier, Barry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Health Organization report says tobacco industry documents show industry took part for years in sweeping campaign to influence and undermine WHO's anti-smoking efforts worldwide; holds industry used network of front groups and groups with industry ties to thwart WHO; says industry consultants got posts at WHO-affiliated groups and that new rules are probably needed to require agency employees, consultants and advisers to disclose industry ties; report sheds new light on role played by Philip Morris chairman Geoffrey Bible, then head of company's international tobacco division, in 1988 in devising ways to undercut WHO; company says it has changed policies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tobacco industry documents show that cigarette makers took part for years in a sweeping campaign to influence and undermine the World Health Organization's anti-smoking efforts worldwide, the agency contends in a new report.</p>
        <p>The report also accuses the leading tobacco companies of using a network of front organizations and groups with industry ties to thwart W.H.O. The study adds that industry consultants obtained positions at W.H.O.-affiliated groups and that new rules are probably needed that would require the agency employees, consultants and advisers to disclose their industry ties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tobacco industry documents show that cigarette makers took part for years in a sweeping campaign to influence and undermine the World Health Organization's anti-smoking efforts worldwide, the agency contends in a new report.</p>
        <p>The report also accuses the leading tobacco companies of using a network of front organizations and groups with industry ties to thwart W.H.O. The study adds that industry consultants obtained positions at W.H.O.-affiliated groups and that new rules are probably needed that would require the agency employees, consultants and advisers to disclose their industry ties.</p>
        <p>The special report, a copy of which the World Health Organization provided to The New York Times in advance of its release today, is based on industry documents, including those uncovered by states during lawsuits against the tobacco industry. Some have been previously cited in news reports. But others shed new light on the biggest cigarette maker, Philip Morris, and the role apparently played a decade ago by its chairman in devising ways to undercut the World Health Organization. The report includes some documents and citations to others.</p>
        <p>The report is being issued as international health groups like the World Health Organization are trying to keep attention focused on smoking after settlements in lawsuits under which major cigarette makers agreed to restrict advertising and finance anti-smoking campaigns. Those accords do not extend outside the United States, and antismoking groups have maintained that producers will operate under different rules abroad.</p>
        <p>''Nobody who is working in the area of tobacco control is surprised that tobacco companies are trying to limit our influence,'' said Dr. Thomas Zeltner, a top Swiss public health official who headed the panel that oversaw the report. ''But,'' Dr. Zeltner said, ''the surprise is how elaborate and well financed this whole activity was.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, an official of Philip Morris, David Davies, did not dispute the report's contents but said that the decade-old documents that it cited reflected a different time in the company's history and that the company has changed its practices.</p>
        <p>''Our goal today is to create a different environment, one of less rancor, where there can be real progress in resolving important issues relating to the regulation of tobacco,'' said Mr. Davies, a vice president of the international tobacco subsidiary.</p>
        <p>Michael Prideaux, a spokesman for British-American Tobacco, another company cited in the report, was more critical. ''It is very sad that the W.H.O., of all people, have succumbed to the plaintiffs' obsession with old documents,'' Mr. Prideaux said, ''rather than how we might work together constructively to move things forward.''</p>
        <p>The report is based on documents that extend from almost a decade ago, when the suits were filed, and is thus largely focused on the manufacturers' activities at a time when producers felt little pressure from the threats of suits or public condemnation. In 1988, top officials of Philip Morris gathered in Boca Raton, Fla., to develop a broad strategy for undermining antismoking efforts and other threats to the industry, the report states.</p>
        <p>The meeting was overseen by Geoffrey Bible, who was then head of the company's international tobacco division and is now its chairman. Executives at the meeting identified 26 threats to tobacco, foremost of which was international health agencies like the World Health Organization.</p>
        <p>The report says officials then devised a set of ''redirection/containment strategies,'' though it said it was difficult to determine how many of them Philip Morris carried out because company documents were incomplete. But in one memo sent to Mr. Bible, a subordinate wrote, ''The antismoking movement is now so intertwined and interrelated that chopping off one arm, or the head, should not be viewed as a quick fix to containment.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the company, Elizabeth Cho, said Mr. Bible was not available for comment.</p>
        <p>Other parts of the report say the industry tried to use front organizations or surrogates to influence the World Health Organization. One section details industry dealings with Paul Dietrich, a lawyer who is also head of the Institute for International Health and Development, a research group in Alexandria, Va. According to the report, Mr. Dietrich attended the meeting in Boca Raton and subsequently wrote opinion pieces for The Wall Street Journal and The International Herald Tribune that attacked W.H.O. without disclosing that he and the institute had received money from the tobacco industry. In 1990, Mr. Dietrich was appointed to a committee of the Pan American Health Organization, a group that is a W.H.O. regional office, and sought to lower tobacco as a priority for the agency, the report asserted.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Dietrich disputed the findings, calling them ridiculous. He said he had been critical of W.H.O. because he believed that the agency was wasting its money on ineffective anti-smoking efforts rather than concentrating on major health initiatives in the developing world.</p>
        <p>''In my speeches, I talked about vaccination programs and childhood health,'' Mr. Dietrich said. ''I never mentioned tobacco. My mantra was we have 'x' amount of dollars, and that needs to be spent on the diseases that were killing children.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dietrich has denied that the industry financed his writings. But he acknowledged that British-American Tobacco hired him as a consultant in the mid-1990's, when he was also an official of the Pan American organization. Mr. Dietrich said he agreed to prepare a report for the company that would be an overview of the World Health Organization and the issues it confronted.</p>
        <p>Asked about disclosing his work to the Pan American organization, Mr. Dietrich said he had not and added: ''I didn't feel like it related to anything we were doing with tobacco. So there was no conflict.''</p>
        <p>An official of the World Health Organization, David Nabarro, said some of the report's findings raised concerns that the agency and related United Nations units needed better safeguards from industry interests, including a review of guidelines on disclosing possible conflicts of interest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
