<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Columbia Sets Pace In Profiting Off Research</title>
    <meta content="02COLO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royalties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7DA1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Columbia Sets Pace In Profiting Off Research</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University moves to forefront of universities that are profiting commercially from the knowledge, research and teaching of their faculties, collecting more in patents and royalties than any other university; is reinvesting much of its money in further research to expand scientific discoveries and the money it makes from them; faculty is not alarmed by commercial ventures, but there are concerns; Columbia's success has become the focus of concern and envy among other universities (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Fredric D. Price, the president of a nutritional-supplements company, sought a partner to create an online information company, NutritionU.com, he approached a Columbia University professor, Dr. Richard J. Deckelbaum.</p>
        <p>He hit pay dirt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Fredric D. Price, the president of a nutritional-supplements company, sought a partner to create an online information company, NutritionU.com, he approached a Columbia University professor, Dr. Richard J. Deckelbaum.</p>
        <p>He hit pay dirt.</p>
        <p>Some academics might have run the other way, concerned about the motives and standards in the emerging commercial market for cybereducation. But Dr. Deckelbaum, director of Columbia's Institute of Human Nutrition, viewed the Internet as a way to reach a wider population.</p>
        <p>Columbia was interested, too. The venture fit its strategy of turning more of its intellectual capital -- its professors' knowledge, research and teaching -- into financial capital. It quickly forged an agreement with Mr. Price for fees and a share of the company.</p>
        <p>Columbia's eagerness to join forces with a start-up Internet venture reflects a shift in an academic culture that once saw itself driven only by intellectual curiosity and far removed from commerce. While the change is occurring throughout the academic world, few universities have tried to cash in as aggressively as Columbia, which has a research capacity similar to that of Harvard and Yale but without their endowments.</p>
        <p>As Columbia ventures further and faster than its peers -- it is collecting more in patents and royalties than any other university -- it is the focus of concern and envy.</p>
        <p>''There's been a paradigm shift,'' said Cornelius W. Sullivan, vice provost for research at the University of Southern California, who is trying to point his university in a similar direction. ''There was a time that this kind of work -- and the idea of making money from your research -- was not acceptable at universities, including ours.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Columbia earned nearly $100 million of its $1.5 billion budget from patents and royalties. This year it will collect more than $144 million from patents, like one on a technique that allows animal cells to be used to manufacture proteins used as drugs, and one on a discovery that paved the way for eye drops used in treating glaucoma.</p>
        <p>The University of California, among the universities that has earned the most patent income in recent years, earned $89 million for the fiscal year that ended in June. Stanford University, another leader in patent income, expects to earn $35 million for the fiscal year that ends this month.</p>
        <p>Columbia is reinvesting much of its money in further research to expand scientific discoveries and the money it makes from them.</p>
        <p>Generally, the faculty has not raised a fuss. The benefits of collecting more money from research and other academic activities are clear: more money to advance their work and less dependence on the government. But there are concerns.</p>
        <p>Dimitris Anastassiou, a professor of electrical engineering at Columbia, said he worried about the perception among some faculty members that the university increasingly ''appears to be a for-profit enterprise.'' He would like it to put more of a wall between decisions about how the campus can make money, and decisions about what research the university should support. Currently, both sets of decisions are vested in the executive vice provost, Michael M. Crow, who receives the university's income from patents and royalties and decides how to spend it.</p>
        <p>Sheldon Krimsky, a science policy specialist at Tufts University, said he was concerned about the impact on research when professors or universities have a stake in the outcome of their work. ''It is a question not just of how many relationships you have with business, but the nature of those relationships,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Eli M. Noam, a Columbia business professor who said he thought that generating more revenue from intellectual property was legitimate, said he still worried that ''long term, it will reduce the credibility of universities and will probably reduce the willingness of society to take care of these institutions.''</p>
        <p>''Universities have benefited from the perception that they are outside the marketplace and have credibility because they are seen as disinterested parties,'' Mr. Noam said.</p>
        <p>Columbia's provost, Jonathan R. Cole, acknowledges that there is a revolution taking place in what he calls the ''means and modes'' of producing knowledge, but argues that it will be possible to safeguard the underlying values of the university.</p>
        <p>''I think the dominant values are predominantly the same as they used to be,'' he said. ''The income is only a means to continue to pursue our mission.''</p>
        <p>''Our motivation is to be entrepreneurial,'' Mr. Cole said. ''We've been giving it away for generations. Now we want to get a fair return, always so we can reinvest it.''</p>
        <p>The change began two decades ago. To spur technological progress, the Bayh-Dole Act of 1980 encouraged universities to commercialize the research they conducted with support from the federal government. Columbia, like other research universities, set up a technology licensing office.</p>
        <p>Spinning academic discoveries into commercial riches, however, turned out to be a slow, uncertain process. Even if a university can find a company willing to license its discoveries, the odds are only one in 20 that the company will make it pay off commercially, said Lita Nelsen, director of the Technology Licensing Office at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. She said that M.I.T. typically earned $15 million to $20 million a year in patent and royalty fees, and that most university licensing offices did not break even.</p>
        <p>But the Internet, which traffics in information, has jolted university officials into action. They see the Internet as a gold mine -- providing a faster, larger payback than traditional research in areas like biology -- if only they can figure out how to package what their professors know.</p>
        <p>Internet companies with deep pockets are already buzzing around campuses, eager to enlist professors  like Dr. Deckelbaum or Arthur R. Miller, a widely known Harvard law professor who agreed to work with a new online law school while he remained at Harvard.</p>
        <p>Mindful of the competition, universities are trying to create their own opportunities that will allow professors to expand their reach and their incomes, and permit the universities to share in the bounty.</p>
        <p>Columbia has been well ahead of the pack. The partnership with NutritionU.com is just one of the deals it has announced in recent months. In April, it announced the creation of Fathom.com, a commercial online partnership with other prestigious institutions, including the New York Public Library, the British Library and the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of Natural History; those institutions and others will offer information and classes on the Web site. In May, the university announced that it was teaming up with Cognitive Arts, a software designer, to offer continuing education on the World Wide Web.</p>
        <p>Columbia was the first university to join forces with UNext.com, a start-up backed by Michael Milken, the former junk-bond king, that is offering Internet college courses created by elite universities. Columbia has already collected $2 million.</p>
        <p>Dr. Crow, Columbia's executive vice provost, has been directing the university's efforts to cash in on its intellectual property. He has easy access to the provost and the president. And he has a hefty bankroll: more than $40 million this year, money not subject to the normal budget process or any faculty oversight.</p>
        <p>One sign of the university's seriousness was its decision seven years ago to give Dr. Crow the income from the university's research royalties as his budget, rather than contribute it to the university's general fund. At the time, the amount was small, about $1 million. Today, it is about $42 million.</p>
        <p>Dr. Crow thinks of the money, he said, as venture capital to be spent both on academically promising projects and economically promising ones. In recent years, his office has contributed $800,000 in seed money for a child and family policy center, and $600,000 into the development of an urban extension service.</p>
        <p>This year, he said, about $10 million went into various academic initiatives. Another $20 million went into building new institutions, like a campus connected with Biosphere 2 in Arizona, and the rest into various projects, including digital media.</p>
        <p>The university has created Columbia Media Enterprises to nurture  digital projects. Although modeled on Columbia's technology licensing office, Columbia Innovation Enterprise, there is a key difference: it is a profit-making company, albeit one wholly owned by Columbia. Columbia Media Enterprises started last fall with one employee; today there are 15, including 7 student ''sweepers'' who comb the university for content to put on the Web.</p>
        <p>In anticipation of increased activity over the Internet, Columbia pushed its faculty to consider how their interests should be treated. Professors traditionally own the rights to the books and articles they write, and their royalties represent perhaps 10 to 15 percent of book sales. Universities typically own patents from research, and professors may get a quarter of the revenue. (Each university's policy differs.)</p>
        <p>Columbia's Senate approved a new intellectual property policy in June that gives the university rights to Internet projects that are supported by university money or commissioned by the university, or that make ''substantial'' use of university equipment and labor. In these cases, professors share in the revenue, receiving anywhere from a quarter to a half of the revenue after expenses.</p>
        <p>Columbia says it has no plans to compel faculty members to cooperate with its own ventures, but hopes to offer them as an alternative to working with outside companies.</p>
        <p>''The faculty are independent spirits, and we can't make them do anything,'' Dr. Crow said. ''Their primary benefit is to create new knowledge. The secondary benefit is to collect licensing income. But it's a wondrous secondary benefit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
