<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Past Rivalries Color Present</title>
    <meta content="02MEMO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0DA1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Past Rivalries Color Present</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Both former Pres Bush and Pres Clinton are overshadowing process by which their political heirs, Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore, are supposed to be coming into own by giving newly candid, newly bracing glimpses into how much they apparently dislike each other; rivalry is also shaping how their would-be successors see each other and sell themselves; Bush threatens more direct intervention if Clinton continues to belittle son, television interview; Clinton repeatedly denigrates former president to rally Democratic faithful at fund-raisers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former president had been biting his tongue, sacrificing his anger to his heir's ambitions. The current president had been rocking on his heels, letting his disciple fight his own battles.</p>
        <p>But now, with a volley of words that unearthed genuine emotion amid a contrived spectacle, two leaders who had pledged to let the 2000 election be about the future are demonstrating how much of it is about the past -- about lingering animosities, dueling legacies, competing claims to vindication and rivals with the names Bush and Clinton, not Bush and Gore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former president had been biting his tongue, sacrificing his anger to his heir's ambitions. The current president had been rocking on his heels, letting his disciple fight his own battles.</p>
        <p>But now, with a volley of words that unearthed genuine emotion amid a contrived spectacle, two leaders who had pledged to let the 2000 election be about the future are demonstrating how much of it is about the past -- about lingering animosities, dueling legacies, competing claims to vindication and rivals with the names Bush and Clinton, not Bush and Gore.</p>
        <p>In an interview broadcast on NBC's ''Today'' show this morning, George Bush put President Clinton on warning, telling him that if he persisted in belittling Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the former president's eldest son, he would be sorry.</p>
        <p>''I'm tempted to get off the reservation,'' Mr. Bush told Jamie Gangel,  as he took at least a half step across the line. ''But I'll tell you what I'm going to do: I'm going to wait a month. Now, you give me a call; I'll give you the home number.''</p>
        <p>''And if he continues that,'' he went on, referring to the president who usurped him, ''I'm going to tell the nation what I think about him as a human being and a person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was responding to a swipe that Mr. Clinton had taken at the Texas governor last week, when Mr. Clinton said: ''The message of the Bush campaign is just that, 'How bad could I be? I've been governor of Texas. My daddy was president'.''</p>
        <p>But President Bush was also proving how thoroughly he had come to hover over this race in recent weeks, pulled back into it by those who think his memory will do them good and by those who think his memory will do their opponent harm.</p>
        <p>His son's choice of Dick Cheney, the former defense secretary, as a running mate seemed to mark a kind of turning point in the Texas governor's campaign. While Governor Bush had for months kept his father at a political distance, he now seems to be hugging him tight. In interviews and conversations with reporters in the days after he formally announced the selection of Mr. Cheney, Governor Bush gushed and gushed about Dad.</p>
        <p>And Dad himself loped back into the picture, sitting down with Ms. Gangel and sitting front and center at the convention on Monday night. Nearby was Mr. Cheney, who served in his administration. Up on stage was Gen. Colin L. Powell, another member of the Beltway brigade who waged the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, too, has unleashed himself. To rally the Democratic faithful at fund-raisers, he has repeatedly denigrated the man who not only preceded him in the Oval Office but, as Mr. Clinton tells it, left the United States in shambles in 1992.</p>
        <p>''The country was in the ditch,'' Mr. Clinton said in Boston on Friday. ''And the politics of Washington, D.C., was like watching, I don't know, 'Wayne's World' or something to most of us who lived out here in the world, the real world.''</p>
        <p>This is precisely the juncture in a presidential election when each man's heir is supposed to be coming into his own. But the two presidents are overshadowing the process by giving newly candid, newly bracing glimpses into how much they apparently dislike each other, which also frames how their would-be successors see each other and sell themselves.</p>
        <p>For example, the prime-time hour of the first night of the Republican convention here was largely about Mr. Clinton, even though no one uttered his name.</p>
        <p>When Laura Bush, the Texas governor's wife, talked about all the parents who tell her husband that they want their children to be able ''to respect the president of the United States,'' the ghost in that sentence was Mr. Clinton, and he was plenty visible to members of the audience, who cheered wildly.</p>
        <p>When General Powell said that Mr. Bush ''comes from a family with a generations-long tradition of public service,'' the obvious point of contrast was Mr. Clinton, not Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Today, the Texas governor went further and, like his father, took Mr. Clinton on directly, saying that the president's recent insults showed that he was ''so desperate to have his legacy intact by getting Al Gore elected, he'll say anything.'' The subject, yet again, was not a would-be president's agenda but a will-have-been president's self-conscious place in history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's aides expressed delight at the turn of events, saying that President Bush's ''Today'' show interview rooted out the bitterness beneath all the sweetness of the convention, disrupted the intricate choreography and cast the Texas governor as too feeble to fend for himself.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, the whole thing tells people a lot about George Jr.,'' said Mark Fabiani, a spokesman for the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers and supporters agree that the elder Bush is a window into the younger one, but they have a different take on what it shows: carefully nurtured values of honesty and integrity.</p>
        <p>And they seem to be betting that voters will share that vision: the convention tonight featured a video tribute to the former president, prominently showcasing his face and voice. Not so long ago, his eldest son's stump speeches had only the most oblique reference to him, a line about the Texas governor being the beneficiary of ''some pretty good training'' for the office he was seeking.</p>
        <p>One Republican strategist said that as soon as the Texas governor hooked up with Mr. Cheney, there could no longer be any pretense that President Bush was not a part of his political fortunes.</p>
        <p>A Republican official who sometimes advises the Bush campaign said that the Texas governor had reached a point in his campaign where he had proven his mettle and could now acknowledge and include both of his parents more openly without worrying about much of a downside. The upside, this official said, were polls this year that showed a sizable majority of voters with favorable opinions of the former president and the former first lady.</p>
        <p>But several people close to the former president said that his remarks about Mr. Clinton and the amount of attention they garnered  were not a political plot. It was all much more personal, Mr. Bush's friends said, and it betrayed a simmering ire that his son's big moment and his son's big party was being crashed by a man who, in the former president's view, had no manners.</p>
        <p>''It's not that Clinton beat him,''  said one of these friends, trying to explain President Bush's perspective. ''It's that Clinton has no respect for the presidency.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
