<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Republicans, a Night to Bolster Bush</title>
    <meta content="02CONV$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarzkopf, H Norman (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagel, Chuck (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleeza</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Republicans, a Night to Bolster Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain sheds rebellious image to laud Gov George W Bush, speech to Republican National Convention; holds Bush would be able to defend nation's interests abroad; speech anchors evening aimed at invoking symbols of military might and assuring national viewing audience that Bush can be trusted as commander in chief and steady hand in foreign policy despite his lack of experience; speakers include other military heroes: Bob Dole, Gen H Norman Schwarzkopf and Sen Chuck Hagel, and Condoleeza Rice, Bush's chief international affairs adviser, who as African-American also underscores his pledge to place minorities in key roles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain shed his rebellious image to play the admiring party stalwart at the Republican National Convention tonight, commending Gov. George W. Bush to independents and Democrats and -- addressing one of the governor's most pronounced vulnerabilities -- saying he would ably defend the nation's interests abroad.</p>
        <p>''I support him,'' said a subdued Mr. McCain, trying to erase tensions from a primary battle that had been so raw that Mr. McCain waited two months to reluctantly endorse Mr. Bush. ''I am grateful to him. And I am proud of him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain shed his rebellious image to play the admiring party stalwart at the Republican National Convention tonight, commending Gov. George W. Bush to independents and Democrats and -- addressing one of the governor's most pronounced vulnerabilities -- saying he would ably defend the nation's interests abroad.</p>
        <p>''I support him,'' said a subdued Mr. McCain, trying to erase tensions from a primary battle that had been so raw that Mr. McCain waited two months to reluctantly endorse Mr. Bush. ''I am grateful to him. And I am proud of him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's speech anchored an evening whose overarching objective was to assemble several faces, old and new, and invoke symbols of military might like the Persian Gulf War. The intention was to assure the national viewing audience that Mr. Bush could be trusted both as a commander in chief and someone who could provide a steady hand in foreign policy despite his lack of experience in the field.</p>
        <p>Thoughout the evening, a cavalcade of military heroes -- from Mr. McCain to Bob Dole to Gen. J. Norman Schwarzkopf to Senator Chuck Hagel -- offered testimonials to Mr. Bush, who did not serve in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>Joining the chorus in the other high-profile speech was Condoleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's chief international affairs adviser who, as an African-American, also underscores Mr. Bush's pledge to place minorities in consequential roles.</p>
        <p>''The George W. Bush that I know is a man of uncommonly good judgment,'' said Ms. Rice, a national security council official in President Bush's administration. ''He is focused and consistent. He believes that we Americans are at our best when we exercise power without fanfare and arrogance.''</p>
        <p>For all their praise of Mr. Bush's personal attributes, Mr. McCain and Ms. Rice said little about specific policies or countries.</p>
        <p>Despite the emphasis at this convention on molding a newly diverse and moderate Republican Party, the drama tonight was provided by stars of party's past, from former Presidents Gerald R. Ford and George Bush -- to an absent Ronald Reagan, represented here by his wife, Nancy.</p>
        <p>To the delight of the delegates, Barbara Bush at one point appeared unannounced on stage to introduce her son, who was linked via satellite.</p>
        <p>Besides trying to shore up Mr. Bush's record, speaker after speaker reminded the public of Republican presidents like Mr. Reagan and Mr. Bush, the governor's father, who were known for projecting respect for America abroad and for their emphasis on national security.</p>
        <p>General Schwarzkopf, commander of allied forces in the Persian Gulf war, appeared via satellite from a battleship, reminding the convention that ''10 years ago tomorrow, Iraq invaded Kuwait.''</p>
        <p>He asked: ''Wouldn't it be great for our armed forces, and for America, if we could have another commander in chief named George Bush?''</p>
        <p>To drive home the theme of military might, the convention ran a video tribute to World War II veterans and a musical medley of military service anthems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, the Republican nominee four years ago and World War II veteran, asked the audience to ''join me in saluting the greatest generation of veterans and every generation of our armed services.''</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Dole, who ran against Mr. Bush in the primaries and had a starring role at the convention in 1996 when she spoke reverently of her husband, said Mr. Bush would ''put an end to the smash-mouth politics of recent years and to the name-calling that tarnishes our trust.''</p>
        <p>Delegates rose in applause to a tableau representing every living Republican president: Mr. Ford and his wife, Betty, and Mrs. Reagan joined Mr. and Mrs. Bush in prime seats overlooking the convention.</p>
        <p>After a video tribute to Mr. Reagan, Mr. Bush leapt to his feet to lead another standing ovation; Mrs. Reagan and her step-daughter, Maureen, who both appeared emotionally struck by the ovation, held their arms around one another as the band played, ''Stand by Me.''</p>
        <p>Introduced by his mother, Barbara Bush, who drew an ovation of her own, Governor Bush appeared before the convention by a satellite hookup for the second night in a row.</p>
        <p>This time, the location was Gettysburg, Pa., where Abraham Lincoln delivered a famous speech and where general-turned-president Dwight D. Eisenhower once lived. Mr. Bush praised his foe from the primaries, saying of Mr. McCain,  ''His straight talk and strong convictions are admired across America.''</p>
        <p>Despite the familiar faces of past Republicans tonight, there was so concerted an outreach to Democrats from the stage that the convention played a videotape featuring the words of Franklin D. Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's popularity -- and eagerness to extend his appeal beyond his party -- afforded him the freedom to play to a broader audience outside the hall by giving a speaking slot, albeit not in prime time, to an openly gay congressman, Representative Jim Kolbe of Arizona. Mr. Kolbe spoke about international trade and made no mention of his sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>During his remarks, some members of the Texas delegation protested by taking off their cowboy hats and bowing their heads in prayer. Most delegates were respectful but offered only tepid applause.</p>
        <p>''We're not all the way there with our party,'' Mr. Kolbe, speaking of his party's embrace of homosexuals, said on ''Political Points,'' the webcast of The New York Times and ABC News. ''The Democratic Party isn't all the way there yet either in terms of its treatment of minorities and other groups.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it was the gauzy, smiling images of moderation that led to stirrings of resentment among some conservatives who voiced concerns that the convention did not truly reflect their views.</p>
        <p>At a crowded Christian Coalition rally at a downtown hotel this afternoon, delegates appeared thrilled to hear some of the conservative rhetoric missing from the convention hall.</p>
        <p>''I know this is a convention of sweetness and light,'' Pat Robertson, the coalition's founder, declared. ''Nobody wants to rock the boat.''</p>
        <p>Mike St. Clair, a delegate from Ankeny, Iowa, groused that the party was not drawing enough contrast with Democrats. ''There must be some contrast, otherwise it is hard for people to become passionate,'' he said. ''You have to be able to see the differences between the parties.''</p>
        <p>But this was clearly Mr. McCain's night. There were even ''McCain for President'' banners spotted in the sea of Bush placards.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign's decision to give a vanquished rival such a prominent role on the second night of the convention marked a striking departure from the last several Republican conventions. At the 1996 convention, the prized Tuesday-night slot was given to then-Representative Susan Molinari, who had been one of Mr. Dole's most steadfast backers.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. McCain recognized that there was no political upside to stirring up trouble for Mr. Bush and that he could score points by playing the loyal trooper. Strikingly, he was so determined to fall in line behind Mr. Bush that he did not raise his signature issue of campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain even played down his stunning upsets in the New Hampshire and Michigan primaries, calling himself ''a distant runner-up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, a prisoner of war in Vietnam whose primary campaign had raised questions about Mr. Bush's fitness to lead the military, said, ''Now it is my turn to serve.''</p>
        <p>But his comments spurred some of Mr. McCain's most ardent backers to grouse that he was being too adulatory, and abandoning his greatest attribute -- his maverick nature.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, who drew a potent turnout of independents and Democrats in the primaries, implored his supporters to rally behind Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''I say to all Americans, Republican, Democrat or independent,'' he asserted, ''if you believe America deserves leaders with a purpose more ennobling than expediency and opportunism, then vote for Governor Bush. If you believe patriotism is more than a soundbite and public service should be more than a photo-op, then vote for Governor Bush.''</p>
        <p>Former Senator Alan K. Simpson of Wyoming said Mr. McCain knew it was not in his interest to be a political menace at the convention. ''He has a great future with the party,'' Mr. Simpson said. ''You never want to be known as a poor loser.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Wright, a delegate from Salt Lake City, said, ''He might have ruffled some feathers tonight, but sometimes that is good. Sometimes the party needs that.''</p>
        <p>While the speakers touched on a panoply of foreign-policy issues, the matters left unaddressed were telling. For example, despite General Schwarzkopf's praise of President Bush's victorious leadership in the gulf war, American warplanes still bomb Iraq and President Saddam Hussein remains entrenched.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice said that Governor Bush would never let the United States be blackmailed by outlaw states, and urged construction of a national missile defense to safeguard against missile strikes, but did not dwell on the debate about the proposal.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice depicted Mr. Bush as a bilingual internationalist, meeting with leaders from Mexico, Russia and South Africa. But, in fact, many meetings were little more than handshakes and hellos.</p>
        <p>Yet the most memorable moments were the personal touches. Former President Bush, brimming with pride in one video, said his son's record ''can stand all the scrutiny in the world,'' and ''will show a man of honor, a man of integrity.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
