<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Warn of Inaction As AIDS Spreads in China</title>
    <meta content="02CHIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/02/world/02chin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EED81E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Warn of Inaction As AIDS Spreads in China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese medical experts are beginning to complain that government has done too little to study extent of AIDS infection or to prevent its spread; official inattention and lack of national public education program have allowed HIV to become rapidly growing problem that now affects some 600,000 Chinese; scientists charge conservatives have stymied their efforts to confront AIDS and have tried to camouflage nation's HIV problem; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During all the years that Yang Zhiyin was selling his blood, he had never heard of AIDS. All he knew was that he was desperately poor, and selling blood on the black market was what farmers did in his village when they needed cash. For much of a decade, Mr. Yang said, he rolled up his sleeve to the blood dealer's needle ''many many times.''</p>
        <p>One of those times, Mr. Yang, now 37, became infected with H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS. Because illegal blood rings often use unsterile collection methods, poor peasants like Mr. Yang are routinely exposed to blood-borne diseases, scientists say. And after Mr. Yang contracted the virus, he presumably spread it unwittingly to dozens of others like himself, who for the most part still do not know that they are infected -- or even that H.I.V. exists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During all the years that Yang Zhiyin was selling his blood, he had never heard of AIDS. All he knew was that he was desperately poor, and selling blood on the black market was what farmers did in his village when they needed cash. For much of a decade, Mr. Yang said, he rolled up his sleeve to the blood dealer's needle ''many many times.''</p>
        <p>One of those times, Mr. Yang, now 37, became infected with H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS. Because illegal blood rings often use unsterile collection methods, poor peasants like Mr. Yang are routinely exposed to blood-borne diseases, scientists say. And after Mr. Yang contracted the virus, he presumably spread it unwittingly to dozens of others like himself, who for the most part still do not know that they are infected -- or even that H.I.V. exists.</p>
        <p>With the AIDS virus skipping silently through China, a number of the country's leading medical experts have begun to loudly complain that the government has done too little to determine the extent of the problem and to prevent the spread of the disease. Official inattention and the lack of a national public education program about the disease have already allowed H.I.V. to transform from an fairly rare condition among intravenous drug users in 1990, to a rapidly growing problem that now affects an estimated 600,000 Chinese, the scientists say. And in another 10 years, they warn, China could have one of the world's largest populations of H.I.V. carriers, unless the government takes action.</p>
        <p>''The spread of AIDS is accelerating rapidly and we face the prospect of remaining inert against the threat,'' states an extraordinarily blunt report by a committee of eminent Chinese experts that was sent to China's leaders earlier this year. It adds: ''Owing to government indifference, AIDS prevention and control is gravely ineffective.''</p>
        <p>Although Chinese doctors have now started a number of research and education projects, there has been no nationally coordinated effort to determine the prevalence of H.I.V. so that the government has only a vague idea of how and where the disease is spreading, for example. The total budget for AIDS prevention last year was only a few million dollars -- far less than that of much smaller countries like Vietnam and Thailand. Local officials often resist efforts to test people in their jurisdiction for the virus, for fear high rates will reflect badly on them. In many cities, billboards promoting AIDS awareness or prevention through condoms have lasted only days before they were declared ''indecent'' and destroyed.</p>
        <p>''We've reached the point that if we don't wake up, it will be a national disaster,'' said Zeng Yi, a leading AIDS researcher who was on the committee.</p>
        <p>The battle over how China should handle AIDS generally pits government scientists concerned with a simmering epidemic against socially conservative propaganda, education and health officials, guardians of China's image and its moral values. The scientists protest that the conservatives have stymied their efforts to confront the disease, preventing frank discussions of sex and drug addiction, for example, and have even attempted to camouflage China's H.I.V. problem.</p>
        <p>''The central government doesn't seem to realize how serious this is,'' said Qiu Renzong, a bioethicist at the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, with clear exasperation. ''We have not yet had an effective risk reduction strategy, because some departments are very conservative. They think chastity is more important than condom use. They say that the only way to prevent H.I.V. transmission is to rely on China's traditional values!''</p>
        <p>Committee members like Professor Qiu say they intended their report to be a jarring wake-up call -- arguing for national AIDS education, condom use and needle exchanges for drugs addicts, for example. And some have been encouraged by the government's prompt initial response: appointing Deputy Prime Minister Li Lanqing to oversee the problem.</p>
        <p>''I think the government attitude is changing,'' said Dr. Zeng, hopefully.</p>
        <p>But others remain skeptical. ''Yes, there's been big progress, but compared to the speed at which H.I.V. is spreading it's not enough,'' said Wan Yanhai, a former government health worker, who said he was fired in the mid-1990's for speaking too frankly about H.I.V. ''Part of the reason there hasn't been a national survey is that they don't want to know.''</p>
        <p>Although there are now 17,000 people known to carry the AIDS virus in China, government officials say that the real figure is probably closer to 500,000 or 600,000. The number is still small compared with China's overall population, which exceeds 1.2 billion, but scientists say rates are extraordinarily high in some groups and in some locations. They estimate that the number of cases is now growing by 30 percent a year.</p>
        <p>Government officials say intravenous drug users probably account for about 70 percent of H.I.V. in the country. Dr. Zeng and many other experts believe that blood sellers like Mr. Yang may well be the second-largest group.</p>
        <p>But the first estimate may be skewed because it is based on the forced testing of drug addicts under arrest. And there is almost no hard information on blood sales, which have been banned since 1998. Prostitutes as well as gay men are also considered at high risk, but there are no reliable figures.</p>
        <p>Some surveys have found extremely high rates in localized populations: In the early 1990's more than 80 percent of drug addicts arrested near the Myanmar border were infected, Dr. Zeng said. More recently, a survey in Henan found rates as high as 16 percent in locales where illegal blood selling was common -- until local officials blocked further testing.</p>
        <p>But it is difficult to extrapolate from these pockets of high infection  to the larger population.</p>
        <p>''Because we haven't done the screening that needs to be done, we don't really know the size of the problem,'' said Dr. Zeng. ''That means that when the government confronts it, they think the problem's not too big.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Wan said, some of the most worrisome survey results have been kept secret. ''A lot of people still feel quite safe -- they think H.I.V. is a disease of foreigners,'' said Mr. Wan, who now runs a web site about H.I.V.</p>
        <p>The true picture will never be clear without very aggressive government intervention, experts said.</p>
        <p>Individuals from high-risk groups often do not realize they are in danger -- and have little incentive to be tested since treatment options for the disease in China are extremely limited.</p>
        <p>The medicines now widely given to patients in the United States to control the virus are too expensive and not licensed; traditional medicines have not yet proven effective.</p>
        <p>Also, although laws prohibit discrimination against people with H.I.V., harassment is the rule.</p>
        <p>''H.I.V. is like having leprosy in the 1930's,'' said Mr. Yang, the former blood seller who contracted the virus, and who said he would only speak if his home province was not identified. ''I have only told my immediate family.'' Mr. Yang only learned he was infected after a researcher wanting to test a new herbal medicine came to test blood sellers in his village.</p>
        <p>But perhaps the greatest obstacle is local officials who do not want to admit that prostitution, drug abuse or blood selling are occurring on their watch. They are particularly resistant to surveys of blood sellers, scientists say, since the practice was outlawed in 1998.</p>
        <p>Although there is a national network of blood banks that screen for H.I.V., blood shortages are common and illegal blood sales continue. Government scientists estimate that there are five million Chinese who regularly provide blood for pay.</p>
        <p>Doctors say H.I.V. rates in this group are probably very high because of the collection methods commonly used by the blood gangs, who buy the blood from farmers and then sell it to individual patients or small-town doctors.</p>
        <p>At illegal collection stations, blood is collected from a number of peasants with the same blood type at one time. The blood is then pooled, spun down to separate out the components needed for medical use, and the remainder is divided up and re-infused into the original donors. In this way, people like Mr. Yang are exposed to blood of 6 to 12 others every time they sell, experts say.</p>
        <p>The risk to hospitalized patients is probably not great, Dr. Zeng said, because hospitals generally screen blood products for the virus -- although in emergencies or in rural hospitals and clinics, there is evidence that the system can break down.</p>
        <p>Researchers and even government bureaus have initiated dozens of projects to educate citizens about H.I.V. But these are often privately funded and nationwide efforts have been hampered by lack of money and a strong puritanical streak.</p>
        <p>''When H.I.V. became a problem in the West, there were huge education campaigns,'' said Dr. Zeng, who has himself raised money for and organized a large traveling scientific exhibition on H.I.V. ''We talk about it openly one day a year -- on Dec. 1 -- International AIDS Day. That is not enough.''</p>
        <p>Last Dec. 1, for example, the State Family Planning Commission unveiled new television advertisements promoting the use of condoms to thwart H.I.V. By the next day they were ordered off the air by the State Administration for Industry and Commerce, which said they violated a law against advertising sex-related products.</p>
        <p>In June, a billboard advocating condom use in Wuhan was ordered removed just 22 hours after it was posted.</p>
        <p>''If you promote condoms among youth, it would lead to a great deal of sexual license and abandonment of sexual morality,'' said Zhu Qi, a government consultant who believes that the best answer to H.I.V. is chastity.</p>
        <p>It is an attitude that exasperates Professor Qiu. ''There is an old Chinese saying,'' he said. ''People don't shed tears until they see the coffin.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
