<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind the 'M' And the 'W,' A New Style</title>
    <meta content="02TOIL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000809T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bathrooms and Toilets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bathrooms and Toilets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDA113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind the 'M' And the 'W,' A New Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marin, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bathrooms have become as important to people who design restaurants in New York City as gleaming kitchens were in 1980's; Zagat Survey's New York City Nightlife 2000 guide includes listing of 'cool loos'; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO Stephen Lyle, fixing up the bathrooms at his new restaurant, Village, was less a chore than an archaeological dig. The chef and his aides carefully stripped and chipped away layers of plaster and drywall to unearth the ancient subway tile, dating from the 1920's or 30's. The phone-booth-size marble stalls were so small they had to be expanded in the women's room. A tiny window in the men's room, looking down from the building's second story onto Ninth Street, had been boarded up. They restored it.</p>
        <p>''When I was choosing the space, one of the things that sold me on it was these funky old bathrooms,'' said Mr. Lyle, who had been at Odeon for many years before opening Village this summer. It is no longer enough for bathrooms to be ''just functional.'' Like restaurateurs all over the city, Mr. Lyle believes that bathrooms ''are definitely a kind of definer.'' They are, he said, ''a statement about your personality, about who you are.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO Stephen Lyle, fixing up the bathrooms at his new restaurant, Village, was less a chore than an archaeological dig. The chef and his aides carefully stripped and chipped away layers of plaster and drywall to unearth the ancient subway tile, dating from the 1920's or 30's. The phone-booth-size marble stalls were so small they had to be expanded in the women's room. A tiny window in the men's room, looking down from the building's second story onto Ninth Street, had been boarded up. They restored it.</p>
        <p>''When I was choosing the space, one of the things that sold me on it was these funky old bathrooms,'' said Mr. Lyle, who had been at Odeon for many years before opening Village this summer. It is no longer enough for bathrooms to be ''just functional.'' Like restaurateurs all over the city, Mr. Lyle believes that bathrooms ''are definitely a kind of definer.'' They are, he said, ''a statement about your personality, about who you are.''</p>
        <p>Mark Stern, the manager at Village, offered a more basic assessment: ''The urinals are pretty incredible.''</p>
        <p>Polite dinner conversation now includes such observations. You go to a new place to eat, you talk about the food, the service, the decor and . . . the bathroom. The loo experience has become as important to the people who design restaurants in New York as gleaming open kitchens were in the 80's. No building material is too obscure, no plumbing detail below notice. Not terribly long ago, a conversation pissoir was still a novelty. You had Phillipe Starck's men's room waterfall in the Royalton. You had Bar 89 in SoHo, where the glass doors shift from transparent to opaque -- as long as the user remembers to turn the lock.</p>
        <p>Now, no new restaurateur dares to install cheap generic tile or unimpressively domestic fixtures. Porter's New York in Chelsea has shoe-polishing machines. At Fun, in Chinatown, you can see what's going on at the opposite sex's sink on a little video monitor. Communal sinks outside the men's and women's rooms are part of the scene at restaurants like Commune. Attendants are also back in action, directing diners to door No. 1, 2 or 3 at Thalia, Guastavino's and, more surprisingly, Vandam downtown -- or wearing black tie and offering mints and towels at Shelly's New York.</p>
        <p>It's gotten so that a good bathroom could be an incentive to return to a restaurant, a bad one a reason never to darken its stalls again. The Zagat Survey's ''New York City Nightlife 2000'' guide includes a listing of ''cool loos.'' Even a Lower East Side boite like Oliva has compact, design-conscious bathrooms: walls done in a blue wash, oval mirrors, original tile on the floor, lily in a vase filled with green grapes.</p>
        <p>''We did them in blue because of the seafood,'' said Eduardo Fontan, an owner. ''The idea was that the inside would contrast with the outside.'' The dining room is as spare as the bathroom is ornate.</p>
        <p>The food is Basque, but the woodwork on the bathroom doors has a Moroccan flavor. Mr. Fontan, who is from Madrid, used to own a furniture repair shop on Orchard Street, so the work was not difficult for him. Still, when was the last time you saw custom woodwork on a bathroom door?</p>
        <p>Roy Klein, the general manager of AZ in the Flatiron district, said, ''I'm a big bathroom guy, and I think ours are pretty cool.''  They were designed by Grant Koerner of Untitled Inc. in the building that once housed the club-restaurant Flowers. The big, pitched skylight over the center of the dining room is echoed by a smaller one in the bathroom. The sink is a transparent glass bowl with metal trim. And the glass mosaic tile on the floor seems to change color from every angle. The door is marked with a gender-progessive ''U.''</p>
        <p>New York bathrooms used to be characterized by their cramped confines and malodorous atmosphere. Larry Bogdanow, of Bogdanow Partners Architects, traces the expanded notion of bathroom space to the Americans With Disabilities Act. Passed a decade ago, it requires new restaurants to provide at least one bathroom large enough for a wheelchair's turning radius.</p>
        <p>''Restaurant bathrooms were really tight 10 years ago,'' Mr. Bogdanow said. ''I find that the extra space is also useful.'' In the women's room at the TriBeCa Grand Hotel, he put a lounge with a banquette. In both the men's and the women's rooms, the handicapped stall contains a changing table and a sink, making it almost a private bathroom.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most avant-garde toilettes around are at the Brasserie. Designed by Diller and Scofidio, a firm known for breathing only the most rarefied air of high architectural theory, the Brasserie bathrooms were as rigorously conceptualized as the rest of the supermodern space. The men's and women's rooms are divided by a wall made of Panelite, a translucent plastic. But they share a sink, an amber-hued, cast-resin trough that runs through the wall. On the mirror above the sink in the men's room it says, ''WASHISTOPURGEISTODENYIS-TOWASHIS.'' The women's side has a similar message.</p>
        <p>You might think that ''purge'' is not a desirable word to display above a sink in a New York bathroom. But Liz Diller, one of the partners of the firm, explained the thinking: ''It has to do with different aspects of cleaning oneself,'' she said. ''And the relationship between sin and dirt.''</p>
        <p>How much time did she and her colleagues spend worrying about the bathroom? ''A lot,'' Ms. Diller said. ''It's one of the most potentially interesting spaces in any kind of public space. There is all kinds of shame associated with bathrooms.''</p>
        <p>David Rockwell, never shy about calling attention to his restaurant designs, thinks of himself as a pioneer in the bathroom department. His most recent creation is New York Strip, a steakhouse opening next week where Asti used to be, at 13 East 12th Street. Previously, the room's major decor feature had been 8-by-10 glossies of opera singers. Many of them will survive, but the overall look has been revised to Euro bordello.</p>
        <p>In the conference room of his Union Square offices, Mr. Rockwell showed off the materials used in the bathroom: red glazed subway tile, red glass balls for the sconces,  shaded with red leopard-print fabric.</p>
        <p>There was also a black-and-white photograph of a naked woman, who did not resemble an opera singer. Mr. Rockwell said mildly naughty pictures like it would adorn the stalls in both men's and women's rooms. He promised that their subjects were authentic French and German women from the 30's and 40's.</p>
        <p>''You want to have one or two memorable things in the bathrooms,'' Mr. Rockwell said.</p>
        <p>The feeling is that diners notice these things during their rest stops. Laureen Barber designed Blue Hill, the small ground-level restaurant on Washington Place, for her brother-in-law, Dan Barber, the chef. She is a graphic designer, and this was her first restaurant. She was surprised to find that ''when people heard I was doing Blue Hill, all they wanted to talk about was the bathrooms.''</p>
        <p>In keeping with the overall design, the unisex bathroom is a haven of warm, dark tones, with one deep red wall and a greenish slate countertop, on top of which sit two low-wattage lamps and a few candles deployed to achieve maximum flattery.</p>
        <p>Practical concerns have been dealt with, too.</p>
        <p>''The No. 1 comment was that the wastebasket should be in close proximity to the door,'' Ms. Barber said. That was from the women. Men, she said, wanted a hook for their jackets.</p>
        <p>The wastebasket-by-the-door thing is a hygiene issue. Some diners evidently want to be able to turn the door handle with the towel, then do the germ-phobe's version of a slam dunk, tossing the prophylactic paper or cloth on the way out.</p>
        <p>Hygiene is also Shelly Fireman's reason for having attendants in his large, busy restaurants. At Shelly's New York, which replaced the Motown Cafe on 57th Street, men and women he calls bathroom valets solicitously offer towels, mints and combs.</p>
        <p>''I'm a believer in pathologically clean bathrooms,'' Mr. Fireman said. ''I don't know any other way.''</p>
        <p>What kind of response does he get to his omnipresent valets? ''It's a subliminal response,'' he said. ''Nobody finishes a meal and says: 'Wow! You've got a great bathroom!' ''</p>
        <p>Actually, they do now.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 9, 2000, Wednesday  An article last Wednesday about stylish restrooms in Manhattan restaurants misstated the name and scheduled opening date of a restaurant that is to be where Asti used to be, on East 12th Street. It is Strip House, not New York Strip. It opens on Sept. 6, not this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 9, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article last Wednesday about stylish restrooms in Manhattan restaurants misstated the name and scheduled opening date of a restaurant that is to be where Asti used to be, on East 12th Street. It is Strip House, not New York Strip. It opens on Sept. 6, not this week.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
