<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Travel; Hal Rosenbluth has paid out plenty in refunds for delayed flights, but he isn't complaining.</title>
    <meta content="Y02TRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/02/business/02TRAV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Refunds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rosenbluth International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbluth, Hal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D7113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Travel; Hal Rosenbluth has paid out plenty in refunds for delayed flights, but he isn't complaining.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Sharkey</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Business Travel column on Hal Rosenbluth of Rosenbluth International travel management company, who offered in May to pay cash refunds to customers whose air flights were delayed; unexpectedly large number of refunds he has had to pay have been more than balanced by 40 percent rise in ticket sales on company's Web site (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DELAYED four hours in Boston. Flight canceled abruptly in Atlanta. Stuck overnight in Dallas. Left Sunday morning, got here Monday. Still waiting for the sales team to roll in from Chicago.</p>
        <p>More than 2,000 corporate travel managers and travel industry suppliers milled around the trade show floor yesterday at the annual convention of the National Business Travel Association at the Los Angeles Convention Center. An impressive number of these hard-core travel professionals seemed to have tales of woe, like the rest of us, in this summer of the worst air traffic delays ever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DELAYED four hours in Boston. Flight canceled abruptly in Atlanta. Stuck overnight in Dallas. Left Sunday morning, got here Monday. Still waiting for the sales team to roll in from Chicago.</p>
        <p>More than 2,000 corporate travel managers and travel industry suppliers milled around the trade show floor yesterday at the annual convention of the National Business Travel Association at the Los Angeles Convention Center. An impressive number of these hard-core travel professionals seemed to have tales of woe, like the rest of us, in this summer of the worst air traffic delays ever.</p>
        <p>A good time, then, to check back in with Hal Rosenbluth, the iconoclastic boss of the worldwide Rosenbluth International travel management company who gave a case of the vapors to the cozy travel agency world in May with an audacious offer to pay cash refunds to customers whose flights were delayed. The offer, which is still in effect, was for those buying tickets on Rosenbluth's Biztravel.com Web site for flights on five major airlines. The basic terms: $100 for a flight arriving more than 30 minutes late and $200 for a flight more than an hour late; if a flight is more than two hours late, the full ticket price is refunded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenbluth said at the time that he had confidence that the airlines ''are doing their best to get their planes off on time.'' He said he did not think the offer, which generated tons of publicity, would break the bank. But that was before the air system screeched down into near- gridlock in June, with 50,000 delayed flights, the most ever.</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Rosenbluth, himself a frequent business traveler, might sound like a man singing the blues. ''I've been stuck; I've been grounded; I've been canceled; I've been overnighted against my will,'' he said. Just in the last two weeks, he  probably would have received about $5,000 back if he had taken advantage of his own company's flight-delay refunds, he added. Biztravel .com's total payout for its money-back offer as of last week: $298,832.33, according to Mr. Rosenbluth. About two- thirds of that total was for flights that were more than two hours late, or were canceled.</p>
        <p>''We put out more money than we thought we were going to put out,'' he said. ''I thought we were going to average somewhere around $10,000 to $15,000 a week. But in June and July, and especially in June with horrendous kinds of delays caused by weather, we were experiencing about $30,000 to $35,000 a week in payments.''</p>
        <p>So why is this man smiling? Volume, as the old joke goes. Thanks to the delays and the word of mouth about the refunds, ticket sales on the site are up 40 percent, Mr. Rosenbluth said. In the competitive and rapidly consolidating world of online travel booking, where establishing a brand name is crucial, the outlays have been worth it even when they went through the roof, he said.</p>
        <p>''I think we struck a nerve,'' said Mr. Rosenbluth, whose company announced on Monday that it had started Rosenbluth Everywhere, a new Web portal for corporate intranets that will enable corporate travel managers and travelers to link to a variety of custom online and wireless booking services, e-mail and corporate travel-management services.</p>
        <p>''Perversely, the delays have been great for us, though I'm hoping that as we get out of the summer and into the fall, the weather improves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The newly completed 17-mile-long Los Angeles subway has been ridiculed by mass-transit planners as a $4.5 billion pork barrel extravaganza. But it does have its virtues. The line runs from downtown Los Angeles to Hollywood, where it bores through the hills and emerges in the San Fernando Valley.</p>
        <p>Tourists are only beginning to find their way onto the subway, which is called the Metro Red Line. Here's a tip for business travelers to Los Angeles, many of whom do not stay in the more famous western precincts of town, but in the big new hotels clustered among the skyscrapers far away in the downtown part of the city: Try out the subway, which is fast, with clean, comfortable cars and beautifully designed -- if eerily noncrowded -- stations.</p>
        <p>It's especially useful for the increasing numbers of business travelers who are bringing families along on trips to popular tourist destinations like Los Angeles. According to industry statistics, 20 percent of business travelers take spouses or partners along, and the number of children going along on business trips tripled in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>From downtown, you can board the subway near the Convention Center, at Metro Center on Seventh Street, at Pershing Square, at the Civic Center and at Union Station. The ride to Hollywood takes about 20 minutes. It's a seedy but requisite stop, if only to wonder what Nathanael West would make of today's slack-jawed tourists wandering with their cameras over the faded sidewalk slabs of movie-star handprints and footprints in front of the decrepit old Chinese Theater.</p>
        <p>In June, the last -- and by far most expensive -- link of the line was completed under the Hollywood Hills and into the Valley. It's now just a 25-minute subway ride from downtown to Universal City, home of the popular Universal Studios theme park. By automobile, that same ride can take several hours on some days.</p>
        <p>And the price is right. A round-trip ticket sells for $2.70, and is good all day long, with unlimited stops.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
