<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living in the Lap of Bankruptcy, Financier Is Charged With Fraud</title>
    <meta content="02BREN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Jersey Securities Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brennan, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living in the Lap of Bankruptcy, Financier Is Charged With Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON with ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert; Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert E Brennan, whose has evaded federal and state securities investigators for decades, even after his First Jersey Securities was ruled fraud factory, is arrested and charged with fraud for allegedly cashing in $500,000 in gambling chips and keeping money less than month after declaring bankruptcy in 1995; has never before been charged with crime, even though he owes $200 million in fines and restitution to defrauded investors; denies charge; has continued luxurious lifestyle since his public disgrace (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back in the early 1980's when many Americans first started putting their money in the stock market, Robert E. Brennan was probably the most prominent pitchman drawing them in, inviting television viewers across the country to take a flier on hot, little-known stocks.</p>
        <p>Over the clatter of his helicopter he shouted, ''Come grow with us.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back in the early 1980's when many Americans first started putting their money in the stock market, Robert E. Brennan was probably the most prominent pitchman drawing them in, inviting television viewers across the country to take a flier on hot, little-known stocks.</p>
        <p>Over the clatter of his helicopter he shouted, ''Come grow with us.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, ''Us'' was First Jersey Securities, which a federal judge in New York later ruled was not a brokerage house, but a fraud factory; and a New Jersey judge called Mr. Brennan not a fabled financier, but ''a big crook.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday Mr. Brennan, 56, who nevertheless had managed to outwit federal and state securities investigators for decades, was arrested and charged with criminal fraud and, for the first time, could face a prison term.</p>
        <p>State and federal prosecutors say that less than a month after declaring bankruptcy in 1995, he cashed in $500,000 in gambling chips and kept the money rather than turning it over to a court-appointed trustee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan denied the allegations. Though he has lost or settled civil complaints and owes $200 million in fines and restitution to defrauded investors, he had never been charged with a crime until yesterday. Until recently, when penny stock fraud exploded, criminal prosecutors seldom brought securities fraud cases involving penny stocks.</p>
        <p>But the indictments were a signal moment in a tangled tale of financial intrigue that has played out over a quarter-century.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, Mr. Brennan became a power in New Jersey politics, a celebrated philanthropist and a racetrack magnate who at one point tried to buy the Meadowlands sports complex.</p>
        <p>He also developed a well-oiled machine for selling cheap stocks in often dubious companies in which he had an interest. The stocks were sold by hundreds of salesmen making cold calls and reading from sales scripts. And he taught other ambitious young men how to conduct the convoluted stock frauds that in recent years have cost Americans billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Even after First Jersey was shuttered, and Mr. Brennan publicly disgraced, he continued to maintain a gold-plated standard of living that involved traveling from his beachfront home in Florida to Monaco, Cannes, Paris, London, Istanbul, Thailand and Tahiti, usually on a private plane.</p>
        <p>Those trips, in fact, prompted both state and federal prosecutors to ask for bail of $1 million in each court. Mr. Brennan ''poses a serious risk of flight,'' said Henry E. Klingeman, an assistant United States attorney, citing Mr. Brennan's penchant for luxurious living, his French girlfriend, his trips by private jets and helicopters, and allegations that he has money hidden overseas. ''This defendant has the means to travel in ways that most defendants don't.''</p>
        <p>He was released on $250,000 bail on the state charges, and was given two days to raise $500,000 bail on the federal charges. In the meantime, he is under house arrest in Colts Neck, N.J.</p>
        <p>Speaking before Magistrate Stanley R. Chesler in Federal District Court in Newark, Mr. Brennan said he had only $15,000 to $20,000 in the bank and was restricted by other court orders to drawing down only $5,000 a month from that amount.</p>
        <p>His voice rising a bit in exasperation, he added, ''My lawyers are probably going to kill me for saying this, but this case might be a blessing that God sent down so that we can bring all these allegations that I have secret money all over the world and am living this extravagant lifestyle to an end.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan had not been expecting his arrest, said his lawyer, Michael Critchley. Law enforcement agents picked him up about 6:30 yesterday morning, while he was taking a shower at an apartment he maintains at Due Process, his onetime horse farm, which is now a private golf course in Colts Neck.</p>
        <p>From the very beginning, Mr. Brennan has always been a high roller in a world whose players generally stick to the shadows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan did not simply squirrel away the money he made; he used millions of it to buy racehorses,  to donate bulletproof vests to the state police, and to buy a plane and houses in Brielle, N.J., Saratoga Springs, N.Y., and Juno Beach, Fla. He became chairman of the Board of Regents of Seton Hall University; he still owes it millions of dollars in unfulfilled pledges.</p>
        <p>In 1974, he took over a New Jersey brokerage house with regulatory troubles and renamed it First Jersey Securities. Within five years, federal securities watchdogs had sued Mr. Brennan and his firm, alleging that they manipulated the shares of several obscure companies. But because the Securities and Exchange Commission does not have criminal powers, these were civil suits that did not carry serious penalties.</p>
        <p>The Brennan technique, as outlined in many civil suits in the intervening years, has since become familiar to thousands of Americans who have lost money speculating in the low-priced shares known as penny stocks. Indeed, the cold-calling salesmen pushing no-name stocks over the phone have even been depicted for the noninvesting public in the movie ''Boiler Room.''</p>
        <p>Basically, regulators and prosecutors contend, Mr. Brennan and his colleagues controlled all of the shares in a small company, shares that they pumped up through fake trades and false publicity. Brokers pushed customers to buy shares, but ignored orders to sell them, which might depress the price.</p>
        <p>Once the shares soared, the stock promoters and dealers would unload their shares on the unsuspecting public. Then, after they had cashed in, they would stop supporting the stock price; hapless investors were usually left holding worthless shares.</p>
        <p>In 1986, under regulatory pressure, Mr. Brennan announced he was selling First Jersey's brokerage operations and devoting himself to horse racing and philanthropy. In fact, state prosecutors say, he was busy controlling two other penny stock firms that used boiler-room tactics similar to those at First Jersey.</p>
        <p>In 1994, he went on trial in Federal District Court in Manhattan, facing civil charges of securities fraud brought by federal regulators. In that case, Judge Richard Owen found him guilty of conducting a ''massive and continuing fraud'' that hurt thousands of investors and netted Mr. Brennan millions in ill-gotten gains.</p>
        <p>Shortly thereafter, Mr. Brennan filed for bankruptcy protection, to keep from having to disgorge $75 million in profits and interest. The fight over his assets has dragged on for years; this spring, Mr. Brennan agreed to turn over the golf course to the bankruptcy trustee in return for more time to recover money that investigators believe he has hidden in trusts in places like Gibraltar and the island of Nevis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
