<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.O.C. Panel Clears Way For New Tests in Sydney</title>
    <meta content="02OLYM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Epo (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DF1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.O.C. Panel Clears Way For New Tests in Sydney</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Medical commission of International Olympic Committee approves use of combination of urine and blood tests to detect use of performance-enhancing drug EPO at 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The medical commission of the International Olympic Committee yesterday approved the use of a combination of urine and blood tests to detect the use of the performance-enhancing drug EPO at the 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>If the new test is endorsed as expected by the I.O.C.'s legal commission and executive board later this month, between 300 and 700 out-of-competition tests will be conducted randomly in Sydney from Sept. 2, when the Olympic Village opens, until the conclusion of the Games on Oct. 1, said Dr. Patrick Schamasch, the I.O.C.'s medical director. Out-of-competition tests, which are administered without notice, are considered the only reliable way to catch drug cheats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The medical commission of the International Olympic Committee yesterday approved the use of a combination of urine and blood tests to detect the use of the performance-enhancing drug EPO at the 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>If the new test is endorsed as expected by the I.O.C.'s legal commission and executive board later this month, between 300 and 700 out-of-competition tests will be conducted randomly in Sydney from Sept. 2, when the Olympic Village opens, until the conclusion of the Games on Oct. 1, said Dr. Patrick Schamasch, the I.O.C.'s medical director. Out-of-competition tests, which are administered without notice, are considered the only reliable way to catch drug cheats.</p>
        <p>Erythropoietin, known as EPO, is produced naturally by the kidneys and stimulates the production of red blood cells. A synthetic version can be a wonder drug for those who suffer from anemia and AIDS and those who are undergoing chemotherapy. In elite sport, however, EPO is believed to be used widely and illicitly to increase oxygen-carrying capacity in endurance sports such as cycling, running and swimming.</p>
        <p>EPO was at the center of the Tour de France drug scandal in 1998, which led to enormous pressure by international governments for the I.O.C. to develop a reliable method to detect the drug's use. For the Sydney Games, scientists intend to use an Australian-developed blood test in combination with a urine test developed by French researchers.</p>
        <p>Each test has its strengths and weaknesses. The blood test can detect the use of EPO over several weeks, but only indirectly. The urine test can detect direct use of EPO, but only for a period of three days.</p>
        <p>Many questions remain about an EPO test for Sydney, scientists and drug-testing experts said yesterday. Has the fast-tracked test undergone sufficient peer review? Can it withstand legal scrutiny? Will a significant number of so-called false positives ruin athletes' reputations unfairly? How much of a deterrent will the test actually create in Sydney, after athletes have already benefited from the training advantages provided by EPO?</p>
        <p>Even with the detectability of EPO, the use of performance-enhancing drugs is likely to be extensive at the Sydney Games. There will be no tests to detect substances like human-growth hormone, insulin-growth factor and products that work essentially as artificial blood. Drug use has become so sophisticated that athletes use topical steroid gels that flush from the system in hours. Some drug-testing experts also believe that the introduction of an EPO test will simply lead athletes to return to undetectable blood doping, in which blood is removed from a particular athlete and later reinserted to increase oxygen-carrying capacity.</p>
        <p>At the least, however, athletes who use EPO now face the possibility that they could be caught while at the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>''Today we achieved a major step,'' Schamasch said in a telephone conference call from I.O.C. headquarters in Lausanne, Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Asked about the drugs that remain undetectable, he said: ''It's a step you know. Paris wasn't built in one day. The final victory against doping needs to be done step by step. Many steps build a stairs.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gary I. Wadler, a professor of medicine at New York University and an expert on performance-enhancing drugs, said that although he believed the introduction of an EPO test was significant, he wished there had been more time to validate the test for athletes who live at various altitudes and with respect to sex and race.</p>
        <p>''Those are the issues that always surface when someone tests positive,'' Wadler said. ''The lawyers are going to feast on whether this has been validated sufficiently by an independent process.''</p>
        <p>Frank Shorter, the 1972 Olympic marathon champion, who will head an independent American drug-testing agency after the Sydney Games, said an EPO test was a ''huge step'' in the fight against drug cheats. But, he added, simply instituting the test in Sydney would create only a mild deterrent.</p>
        <p>If the I.O.C. is serious about treating the issue as a drug problem instead of a public-relations problem, Shorter said, it would begin using or threatening to use the EPO test immediately, saving urine and blood samples of athletes taken now and through the Sydney Games. Thus, cheating athletes would be worried that they might be caught now or later, and a real deterrent would be created for the Summer Games, he contended.</p>
        <p>''Here is an opportunity to shift the psychological advantage from cheaters to clean athletes,'' Shorter said. ''Let's not fall asleep now.''</p>
        <p>Charles Yesalis, a Penn State professor who is an authority on performance-enhancing drugs and a longtime critic of the I.O.C.'s drug-testing procedures, reacted skeptically. ''Nothing's changing here,'' he said. ''Somebody tell me why athletes won't go back to blood doping. These Games are going to be as drug laden as the rest.''</p>
        <p>Yesalis said he was concerned that what he called the ''short-circuiting'' of the scientific method to approve an EPO test might result in innocent athletes being accused unfairly. He said the test ''smacked of public relations.''</p>
        <p>''After four decades of pathetic behavior, the stench of hypocrisy is overwhelming,'' he said, noting that the I.O.C. had fallen years and millions of dollars behind in research for drug tests. ''If they expect me to get warm and fuzzy feelings, sorry, I'm burned out after four decades of disingenuous behavior.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
