<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faltering Steps Of a New Sitcom</title>
    <meta content="MB235736" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richards, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Michael Richards Show, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1D81E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faltering Steps Of a New Sitcom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC revamps and recasts The Michael Richards Show, sitcom that debuts in fall, after seeing first pilot episode; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Richards, who played  Kramer on ''Seinfeld,'' has not had an easy time producing his new sitcom. Called ''The Michael Richards Show,'' the comedy is about a bumbling private detective, played by Mr. Richards. It will make its debut on NBC this fall.</p>
        <p>NBC executives considered the show's pilot episode so lacking in hilarity that they refused to show it to critics who gathered last month in Pasadena, Calif., to learn more about the network's fall lineup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Richards, who played  Kramer on ''Seinfeld,'' has not had an easy time producing his new sitcom. Called ''The Michael Richards Show,'' the comedy is about a bumbling private detective, played by Mr. Richards. It will make its debut on NBC this fall.</p>
        <p>NBC executives considered the show's pilot episode so lacking in hilarity that they refused to show it to critics who gathered last month in Pasadena, Calif., to learn more about the network's fall lineup.</p>
        <p>With production scheduled to begin next week, the show has been retooled. The pilot was shot by a single camera, but new episodes will be filmed with four cameras on a traditional sitcom set and before a studio audience. Also, Mr. Richards will be joined by new cast members, an apparent ''Seinfeld''-like ensemble, including Tim Meadows of ''Saturday Night Live,'' William Devane of ''Knots Landing'' and Amy Farrington, who was most recently a guest star on ''E.R.''</p>
        <p>Several people close to the production have said that the script for the first episode also had some major problems and needed reworking.</p>
        <p>But Spike Feresten, one of the show's creators, said that despite having ''some problems with some jokes here or there,'' Mr. Richards was now quite happy with his first episode. Still, to ensure that everything goes smoothly, Mr. Richards has ''been in the room writing with us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If the project did not have Mr. Richards as its star, all of this retooling could be very worrisome for NBC, which, like the other networks, is struggling to develop a new hit comedy and has high hopes for the program. But executives there have repeatedly said that even the original, junked pilot scored high marks with test audiences, which are apparently still quite fond of Mr. Richards from his ''Seinfeld'' days.</p>
        <p>''People want to see him on television and they're excited that he's coming back,'' said Shirley Powell, an NBC spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Powell said that executives were optimistic about the show's future and that any changes in the scripts were a normal part of the process of producing a new TV show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feresten said that the first episode was to be shot on Aug. 18. After that, he said, the producers will show outlines for future episodes to network executives.</p>
        <p>''It's our hope they'll see the comedy in there,'' he said. ''But there are talented writers in that room, too.''</p>
        <p>There will be plenty of time to fix any problems that may arise. The show is not scheduled to make its debut until Oct. 24.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards was not available for comment. But when he was asked about the state of his new show last month by the critics in Pasadena, he said, ''There's no trouble here.''</p>
        <p>JIM RUTENBERG</p>
        <p>TV NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
