<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Word or Two for the Egg-Wise</title>
    <meta content="02WELL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING WELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Eating Well</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDE113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Word or Two for the Egg-Wise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros's Eating Well column on gains being made in preventing salmonella poisoning from eating raw eggs; says chances of an egg being infected have gone down from one in 10,000 in 1997 to one in 20,000 today; notes that a vaccine is now being used on some farms; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHENEVER the subject of raw eggs comes up, questions come flowing in. Although the government says no one should eat raw eggs, public health advice must be ''one size fits all,'' and the risk is not the same for everyone.</p>
        <p>The likelihood of getting salmonellosis from uncooked or lightly cooked eggs, whether in mayonnaise or mousse, is quite small for healthy adults. And it has grown even smaller in the last three years. In 1997, the chances of an egg being infected with salmonella were one in 10,000. Today the chance is one in 20,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHENEVER the subject of raw eggs comes up, questions come flowing in. Although the government says no one should eat raw eggs, public health advice must be ''one size fits all,'' and the risk is not the same for everyone.</p>
        <p>The likelihood of getting salmonellosis from uncooked or lightly cooked eggs, whether in mayonnaise or mousse, is quite small for healthy adults. And it has grown even smaller in the last three years. In 1997, the chances of an egg being infected with salmonella were one in 10,000. Today the chance is one in 20,000.</p>
        <p>But for certain groups, eating raw food like meat, fish or eggs is much riskier than it is for a healthy adult. About 300 people in the United States still die from salmonellosis every year. Raw or lightly cooked eggs (soft-boiled, for example) should not be eaten by children, the elderly, diabetics, pregnant women, those with weak immune systems or liver disease, or those taking medication to reduce stomach acid.</p>
        <p>In response to consumer pressure, the industry has assumed more responsibility for ensuring safety. It produced a consumer education campaign to raise awareness about safe food handling, and egg producers have adopted measures that did not exist just a few years ago.</p>
        <p>It wasn't until 1995 that the industry created a quality control program encouraging farms to watch for rodent and pest infestations and to wash and refrigerate eggs, controls most people assume have always been in place. Though the program is voluntary, 93 percent of large egg producers have adopted some version of it, according to the American Egg Board, a trade group.</p>
        <p>Salmonella is transferred from the chicken to the egg, so a vaccine is now being used on some farms. Food Animal Concerns Trust, a nonprofit organization financed by private foundations and individuals, which seeks to improve the safety of meat, poultry and eggs, is using the vaccine on 13 small farms in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The trust also endorses a technique called competitive exclusion, which introduces strains of beneficial bacteria in day-old and 2-day-old chicks, which prevents salmonella from taking hold. But the technique is relatively expensive, said Robert Wood, the executive director of the trust, and is used only for broilers and not for laying hens.</p>
        <p>Some supermarkets and specialty stores sell eggs pasteurized in the shell, which means they are heated just long enough to kill the germs without cooking the egg. Pasteurized eggs can be used in any recipe that calls for raw eggs, including mayonnaise and Caesar salad, though they must be cold in order to separate properly. Pasteurized egg whites have been available for a few years.</p>
        <p>Beyond these changes, Mr. Wood said the most promising innovation is the testing of flocks and their environments at critical points, along with the diversion of eggs to a pasteurization plant when salmonella is found. The Food and Drug Administration wants to make that system mandatory.</p>
        <p>Because the risk of salmonella poisoning rises with the age of the egg, the Agriculture Department said Monday that it plans to prohibit wholesalers from repackaging eggs that grocery stores return like remaindered books. The department plans to require a mandatory 30-day expiration date on all cartons. Currently, some cartons carry sell-by dates, and some carry Julian dates, which reveal when the eggs were packed, although in coded fashion: 001 means Jan. 1; 365 means Dec. 31.</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration has also proposed requiring safe handling instructions on cartons of eggs. They would be similar to the labels on meat and poultry but would include a statement saying eggs may contain harmful bacteria and warning that certain people are most at risk. The Egg Board favors a label without the warning.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, consumers should observe the following rules:</p>
        <p>Buy eggs only from refrigerated cases, and refrigerate them in their cartons, which helps keep them fresh.</p>
        <p>To avoid repackaged eggs, buy only those that carry the Agriculture Department shield.</p>
        <p>Look for Julian or sell-by dates on cartons, and buy the eggs with the latest dates.</p>
        <p>Use only clean, unbroken eggs. Discard dirty or broken ones.</p>
        <p>Do not leave eggs in any form at room temperature for more than two hours. For picnics, pack egg dishes with ice or commercial coolant in an insulated cooler or bag.</p>
        <p>Wash your hands, utensils and work surfaces to prevent cross-contamination.</p>
        <p>EATING WELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
