<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Korean Figures Show Conglomerates Still Deep in Debt</title>
    <meta content="Y02KOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/02/business/02KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Len, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED7113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Korean Figures Show Conglomerates Still Deep in Debt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL LEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Len, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Aug. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Official statistics show that debt levels of most of South Korea's conglomerates remain significantly higher than what government considers acceptable (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been nearly three years since the South Korean government ordered the nation's largest business conglomerates to reduce their staggering debts. But official statistics released today showed that the debt levels of most of the conglomerates remained significantly higher than what the government considers acceptable.</p>
        <p>For the first time, the major conglomerates reported their debt levels in consolidated financial statements, a widely accepted accounting system that brings together all the assets and liabilities of a parent company and its subsidiaries. Under an earlier accounting system, the true extent of a conglomerate's debt was hard to determine, obscured by the ability of subsidiaries to finance each other's loans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been nearly three years since the South Korean government ordered the nation's largest business conglomerates to reduce their staggering debts. But official statistics released today showed that the debt levels of most of the conglomerates remained significantly higher than what the government considers acceptable.</p>
        <p>For the first time, the major conglomerates reported their debt levels in consolidated financial statements, a widely accepted accounting system that brings together all the assets and liabilities of a parent company and its subsidiaries. Under an earlier accounting system, the true extent of a conglomerate's debt was hard to determine, obscured by the ability of subsidiaries to finance each other's loans.</p>
        <p>Except for Samsung, South Korea's second-largest business conglomerate, and Lotte, a hotel, food and beverage group, the nation's largest conglomerates failed to lower their debt-to-equity ratios below 2-to-1. That level, in which a company's long-term debts are twice the value of its stock, was set as a target by the government last year under new methods of evaluating the size of liabilities.</p>
        <p>Lowering the huge amounts of debt held by the conglomerates has been a focus of the Seoul government's financial and economic reform plans since the nation was forced to seek a $58 billion bailout package from the International Monetary Fund late in 1997. The debts of these conglomerates have been cited as a main cause of the financial crisis and the recession that followed.</p>
        <p>The average corporate debt-to-equity ratio stood at 2.25-to-1, according to the Financial Supervisory Commission, which has been overseeing the revamping of the conglomerates.</p>
        <p>Among the top four business groups, the debt-to-equity ratio of Hyundai was 2.3-to-1, LG2.7-to-1, SK 2.3--to-1 and Samsung 1.9-to-1.</p>
        <p>But the average debt-to-equity ratio rose to 3.5-to-1 when the highly leveraged financial units of the conglomerates were included, with Hyundai's rising to 3-to-1 and Samsung's to 4.4-to-1.</p>
        <p>Despite the statistics, government officials expressed optimism.</p>
        <p>''The debt levels were a lot lower than we had expected,'' said Lee Suk Jun, a manager at the commission's corporate accounting division. ''In fact, the debt ratios, excluding financial units, have actually gone down -- a sign we consider as a significant improvement.''</p>
        <p>Analysts were also optimistic that the new system of accounting for debts would lead to more effective ways to reduce them.</p>
        <p>''It's what we were expecting from fully consolidated balance sheet,'' said Paulo Rhee, the deputy chief of research at HSBC here. ''I'm positive that we're seeing more transparent numbers. Now we know more clearly what the problem areas are and the magnitude of the debt levels.''</p>
        <p>Others, however, said that financial support among the subsidiaries of a conglomerate remained a problem.</p>
        <p>Jang Ha Sung, a campaigner for minority shareholder rights and professor of business administration at Korea University, said the level of transactions between the same conglomerate's subsidiaries is ''a lot higher than I thought.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
