<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; New Century, Old Grudges</title>
    <meta content="02DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DB1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; New Century, Old Grudges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column sees presidential race between George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore finally emerging as battle for vindication between former Pres George Bush and Pres Clinton; holds Bush fights for symbolic second term Clinton denied him and Clinton for what he perceives as kind of third term he needs to enhance his legacy; sees feud fueled by class rage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>O.K. Now we're in business.</p>
        <p>After an icky evening of Republican kissy-face and blaxploitation (''Affirmative Action, the Musical''),  Poppy unleashed Chiang!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>O.K. Now we're in business.</p>
        <p>After an icky evening of Republican kissy-face and blaxploitation (''Affirmative Action, the Musical''),  Poppy unleashed Chiang!</p>
        <p>Unleashing Chiang, in the loopy Bush family patois used in golf and tennis, means giving the ball a good whack.</p>
        <p>After a week of President Clinton taunting W., saying that the Republican candidate's message was merely ''My Daddy was president,'' Daddy lost it.</p>
        <p>''And if he continues that, then I'm going to tell the nation what I think about him as a human being and a person,'' the former president threatened on NBC's ''Today.''</p>
        <p>Our summer of torpid politics suddenly came alive with the freaky spectacle of two presidents trash-talking. The race turns out to be what we thought it was all along: President Bush vs. President Clinton.</p>
        <p>George Senior is determined to prove once and for all that Bill Clinton is a tacky hick who defiled the presidency. Bill Clinton is determined to prove once and for all that George Senior is an irrelevant aristocrat who thinks the presidency is a family heirloom.</p>
        <p>Two intensely competitive chief executives, who had been trying not to meddle too much in the campaigns of their proteges, bolting off the reservation in a bid for vindication.</p>
        <p>George Senior is fighting for the second term he feels he was gypped out of by Bill Clinton. And Bill Clinton is fighting for the third term he needs to launder his legacy.</p>
        <p>W. and Al are alternately bystanders and stand-ins in the big rematch.</p>
        <p>It is as though the tape of the '92 election, on pause all these years, has started rolling again.</p>
        <p>The presidential hissy fit is driven by class rage. Edith Wharton would have savored this drama of manners.</p>
        <p>The Bushes have been privately steaming that Gore/Clinton have not abided by Marquess of Queensberry rules, allowing the Republicans to enjoy their nomination party without any Democrats throwing a punch.</p>
        <p>Bush Pere believes his manners toward his successor have been impeccable, and that he has been discreet out of loyalty to the office.</p>
        <p>''Who's been more gracious and charitable to Bill Clinton, even during Lewinsky?'' asked the former president's old friend Alan Simpson, the former Wyoming senator.</p>
        <p>So the Bushes felt the gentlemanly rules of order were broken over the last week when the Democrats put out an ad attacking Dick Cheney's conservative record and two more attacking W. on health care and the environment, and when Bill Clinton repeatedly mocked W. as a coddled daddy's boy at fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>''The country was in the ditch,'' Mr. Clinton said in Boston last Friday, talking about '92, comparing the Bush White House to a ditzy ''Wayne's World.''</p>
        <p>Nobody gave Mr. Clinton, who never knew his own father and who had to stand up to an abusive, alcoholic stepfather, a solid gold key to success. And he clearly thinks Al Gore, another regent raised to be president by a famous political father, is not up to the challenge of gutting the Bushes on the entitlement issue.</p>
        <p>It has to be galling to Mr. Clinton that Americans don't seem inclined to reward his vice president for the purring economy. And he is surely fed up with the Republicans acting as if his two terms were merely Bushus Interruptus.</p>
        <p>The remarkable thing is that this class war has caused everyone to reverse roles. In '92, W. was the vindictive one who lashed out when his father was criticized. Now dad has taken junior's role. And while it is usually vice presidents who serve as hatchet men, now Bill Clinton does that for his vice president.</p>
        <p>Even though Mr. Simpson says that the Bushes avoided publicly criticizing Mr. Clinton about Monica Lewinsky, that is in fact the subtext of W.'s campaign -- restoring ''honor and dignity'' to the White House. Mr. Clinton thinks a rejection of Mr. Gore would be a ratification of the Bushes' contention that he sullied the White House. The president can also see that it is hard for Al Gore to attack, because even people who agree with Mr. Gore find him insufferable on the attack. W. and Mr. Gore will probably keep campaigning, but we all know it's not about them anymore. Maybe it never was.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
