<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="2TRN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BOSTON RED SOX--Placed INF Jose Offerman on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 1B-DH Morgan Burkhart from Pawtucket of the International League.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Placed 3B Olmedo Saenz on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 2B Jose Ortiz from Sacramento of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Placed 2B Homer Bush on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BOSTON RED SOX--Placed INF Jose Offerman on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 1B-DH Morgan Burkhart from Pawtucket of the International League.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Placed 3B Olmedo Saenz on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 2B Jose Ortiz from Sacramento of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Placed 2B Homer Bush on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Optioned 1B Erubial Drazo to Tucson of the PCL. Recalled OF Jason Conti from Tucson.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  DALLAS MAVERICKS--Re-signed G Hubert Davis and F Gary Trent.  INDIANA PACERS--Re-signed F-C Sam Perkins to a one-year contract.  MIAMI HEAT--Acquired G Eddie Jones, F Anthony Mason, G Ricky Davis and G-F Dale Ellis from the Charlotte Hornets for F P.J. Brown, G Jamal Mashburn, F-C Otis Thorpe, G Tim James and G Rodney Buford. Re-signed G Anthony Carter to a one-year contract.  NEW YORK KNICKS--Re-signed F Kurt Thomas.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  DALLAS COWBOYS--Signed OL J.R. Conrad and OG Steve Scifres.  ST. LOUIS RAMS--Signed P Louie Aguiar to a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  BUFFALO SABRES--Re-signed D Jason Woolley to a one-year contract.  CALGARY FLAMES--Named Don Hay coach.  CAROLINA HURRICANES--Signed F Bates Battaglia, F Sandy McCarthy, D Steve Halko, C Byron Ritchie, C Greg Koehler and RW Shane Willis.  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Agreed to terms with F Krzysztof Oliwa on a two-year contract. Signed F Steve Heinze, F Geoff Sanderson and F Matt Davidson.  FLORIDA PANTHERS--Signed RW David Emma and D Michel Periard.  MONTREAL CANADIENS--Agreed to terms with F Brian Savage on a one-year contract.  OTTAWA SENATORS--Named Roger Neilson assistant coach. Agreed to terms with F Magnus Arvedson, D Chris Phillips, D Shane Hnidy, RW Ivan Ciernik and C John Emmons on one-year contracts.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Signed D Justin Hocking to a one-year contract.  TORONTO MAPLE LEAFS--Re-signed F Jonas Hoglund, F Yanic Perreault and F Alyn McCauley to one-year contracts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
