<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hampton a One-Man Highlight Reel as Mets Foil Reds</title>
    <meta content="02METS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E6D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hampton a One-Man Highlight Reel as Mets Foil Reds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Cincinnati Reds, 3-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>See Mike Hampton pitch. See Mike Hampton bat. See Mike Hampton field. See Mike Hampton sweat in the dugout before the Mets complete a 3-2 victory over the Cincinnati Reds.</p>
        <p>Just seeing Mike Hampton in a Mets uniform should be enough for Shea Stadium fans because he offered no objections to the trade that brought him to New York. Not that he had a choice when the deal was made with Houston last winter, but the good guys get credit no matter what the circumstances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>See Mike Hampton pitch. See Mike Hampton bat. See Mike Hampton field. See Mike Hampton sweat in the dugout before the Mets complete a 3-2 victory over the Cincinnati Reds.</p>
        <p>Just seeing Mike Hampton in a Mets uniform should be enough for Shea Stadium fans because he offered no objections to the trade that brought him to New York. Not that he had a choice when the deal was made with Houston last winter, but the good guys get credit no matter what the circumstances.</p>
        <p>Working on the mound last night, Hampton shut out the Reds for seven innings before slipping in the eighth and setting the stage for a parade of three relief pitchers. Armando Benitez secured the final three outs, but it was the third out that John Franco got in the eighth inning that was most critical.</p>
        <p>''I wish I was out there,'' said Hampton, who watched the last five outs from the dugout. ''It's not any mystery that I don't like being taken out of the game, but we have a good bullpen. You just root your teammates on and hope they get the job done.''</p>
        <p>Turk Wendell did not, giving up a run-scoring triple that left Dante Bichette 90 feet from tying the score, but Hampton nevertheless gained his 11th victory against 7 defeats and raised his record for the past two months to 9-3. Then there were those other contributions the left-hander made.</p>
        <p>Stepping to the plate in the second inning with Bubba Trammell at third base and Mike Bordick at first on successive singles with no out, Hampton lofted a sacrifice fly to right field, doubling the lead to 2-0. The run batted in was Hampton's sixth of the season. His R.B.I. ratio of one per 8.67 at-bats is better than those belonging to Kurt Abbott, Matt Franco, Lenny Harris (with the Mets) and Rey Ordonez.</p>
        <p>Hampton displayed the third phase of his triple-threat talent in the third inning. With two out, Chris Stynes rapped a ground ball back to the mound. The ball was too far to Hampton's left for him to snare it with his glove, so he quickly stuck out his left foot and knocked the ball down.</p>
        <p>In another sport, someone would have said, ''Kick save and a beauty.'' Having corralled the ball, Hampton coolly bent over, picked it up and threw to first for the third out.</p>
        <p>''It was just a reaction play,'' Hampton said. ''You see the ball hit up the middle, I'm trying to kick it or do something with it. I got it on the bottom of my shoe.''</p>
        <p>When Hampton signs with the Mets or another team as a free agent sometime after the season, his fielding and hitting will be taken into consideration, but he will get his $12 million or more a year primarily for his pitching. He did a little bit of that last night, too.</p>
        <p>Through seven innings, he allowed more than one base runner in an inning only once, and only once did he allow a runner to advance beyond first base. Both occurred in the fifth inning, which Hampton ended by inducing Stynes to ground out.</p>
        <p>The Reds, scrambling to catch the St. Louis Cardinals in the National League Central or the Mets in the wild-card race, finally scored in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>Stynes began the inning with a single, and Barry Larkin lashed a line drive to left that eluded Trammell and became a run-scoring double.</p>
        <p>Ken Griffey Jr. grounded out, and Manager Bobby Valentine called for Wendell to face Bichette, who promptly hit a high fly ball that collided with the right-field fence just as Derek Bell did. The ball won, and Bichette raced to third with a run-scoring triple.</p>
        <p>Now Valentine brought in Franco, who, with the infield in, induced Sean Casey to bounce to first for the second out. But then he walked Alex Ochoa.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to give him anything good to hit,'' Franco said. ''I wanted to nibble a little bit; maybe I nibbled too much. I thought maybe he would chase. On the other hand, I didn't want to walk him, which I did, and put the winning run on. It was a mistake on my part, but it worked out.''</p>
        <p>Benito Santiago was next, and he worked the count to 3-2. ''I was thinking if he comes inside here he has no chance because it's Johnny's bread and butter,'' Hampton said.</p>
        <p>Good thinking. ''I fed him most of the pitches away, away, away,'' Franco said, ''and kind of froze him up with a two-seam fastball. Guys who have been with me a lot know I like to freeze guys up inside.''</p>
        <p>Umpire Ed Rapuano called the pitch strike three, even though it appeared to be so inside that catcher Mike Piazza quickly moved his glove to show the ball in the strike zone.</p>
        <p>''In my opinion that was a strike,'' Franco protested, unable to stifle a laugh. ''It was right down the middle and he took it. Let me enjoy this, please.''</p>
        <p>All of the Mets, Hampton especially, enjoyed it.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DARRYL HAMILTON, who has been on the disabled list since April 7 with an ailing left foot and subsequent toe surgery, has played three games in his rehabilitation assignment with Class AAA Norfolk of the International League. He has had 14 plate appearances and wants to get between 30 and 40 before joining the Mets.</p>
        <p>Hamilton is hitting .308, which is important because General Manager STEVE PHILLIPS said that when Hamilton returns to the Mets, they want to see him ''hit the ground running, literally and figuratively.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
