<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>P.&amp; G. Reports Earnings in Line With Lowered Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y02PROC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DF1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>P.&amp; G. Reports Earnings in Line With Lowered Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble Co, troubled by rising costs, management turmoil and credibility problems on Wall Street, reports fourth-quarter results that are in line with lowered forecasts; company also advised that earnings growth in first half of its new fiscal year would be sluggish; reports fourth-quarter earnings of $516 million, compared with year-earlier $414 million; excluding an after-tax reorganization charge of $261 million, company earned $777 million, down 3 percent from year-earlier $799 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Procter &amp; Gamble Company, troubled by rising costs, management turmoil and credibility problems on Wall Street, reported fourth-quarter results yesterday that were in line with lowered forecasts. The company also advised that earnings growth in the first half of its new fiscal year would be sluggish.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended June 30, Procter said that it earned $516 million, or 36 cents a share, compared with $414 million, or 29 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Procter &amp; Gamble Company, troubled by rising costs, management turmoil and credibility problems on Wall Street, reported fourth-quarter results yesterday that were in line with lowered forecasts. The company also advised that earnings growth in the first half of its new fiscal year would be sluggish.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended June 30, Procter said that it earned $516 million, or 36 cents a share, compared with $414 million, or 29 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Excluding an after-tax reorganization charge of $261 million, the company earned $777 million, or 55 cents a share, down 3 percent from $799 million, or 58 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier, which excluded a charge of $385 million for the reorganization. Revenue for the most recent period rose 2.2 percent, to $9.66 billion from $9.45 billion.</p>
        <p>The results matched Wall Street estimates, which analysts lowered last month after the company said it would fall short of the 15 percent to 17 percent growth in earnings it had projected for the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Last month's profit warning was the third made by Procter since March. Its stock, which hit a 52-week high of $118.37 in January, has lost nearly 50 percent of its value since then. In a strong market for consumer stocks yesterday, shares of Procter rose $2.1875, to $59.25.</p>
        <p>Procter said that for all of its 2000 fiscal year, it had net income of $3.54 billion, or $2.47 a share, compared with $3.76 billion, or $2.59 a share, in the previous year. Revenue rose to $40 billion from $38 billion.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's earnings report was the first from Procter since Durk I. Jager abruptly resigned in June as chairman and chief executive. In the wake of his resignation, John E. Pepper returned to the company as chairman and Alan G. Lafley took over as president and chief executive. Mr. Jager, who held the top jobs for just 17 months, pushed the company on the path toward aggressive growth. But difficult business conditions, in addition to Procter's size and conservative, risk-averse culture, undermined his strategy.</p>
        <p>Looking forward, Procter said earnings growth in its first quarter would be ''about flat'' compared with earnings in the July-September period last year. Earnings growth should accelerate to the mid-single digits in the fall quarter and return to double-digit growth rates in the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>''P.&amp; G. is capable of delivering better profit results, and we will,'' Mr. Lafley said in a statement. ''Our plan is to focus on big, leadership brands, big markets and big customers; smarter, more effective and efficient commercialization and innovation; and better cost control and cash management.''</p>
        <p>If anything, Wall Street analysts said they were happy that the company had adopted a more realistic approach to its financial fortunes. But they said the company would be hard pressed to realize its projections for all of 2001.</p>
        <p>''Aggressive pricing, coupled with lower volume expectations for the first half translates into more conservative, achievable goals,'' said Andrew Shore, an analyst at Deutsche Bank Securities.</p>
        <p>During the company's conference call with analysts ''you seemed to almost hear a sigh of relief'' from Wall Street, Mr. Shore said.</p>
        <p>Heather Hay Murren, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, said she was encouraged that the company, which sells about 300 brands of food, beverage, beauty care and drug products, had lowered expectations for the first half of its new fiscal year. But she said Procter might be taking too rosy a view of how it will perform over the next six months.</p>
        <p>To meet full-year estimates ''suggests earnings growth in the second half of the year would be between 17 percent and 20 percent,'' she said. ''I don't think that is prudent.''</p>
        <p>Analysts agreed that it would take Procter some time to repair its damaged image on Wall Street. ''It will take two or three quarters of hitting their numbers to regain their credibility,'' said Sally J. Dessloch, an analyst at J. P. Morgan Securities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
