<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>32 Injured as City Bus Hits Traffic Agent and Crashes Into Midtown Building</title>
    <meta content="02BUS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>32 Injured as City Bus Hits Traffic Agent and Crashes Into Midtown Building</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City bus driver loses control on 34th Street, crosses two lanes of oncoming traffic and strikes an on-duty traffic enforcement agent before driving onto the sidewalk and smashing into a building; driver and 30 passengers are also injured (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A city bus driver lost control on 34th Street yesterday evening, crossed two lanes of oncoming traffic and struck an on-duty traffic enforcement agent before driving onto  the sidewalk and smashing into a building, the police said.</p>
        <p>Thirty passengers and the driver were also hurt, though none of the injuries were life-threatening, said Detective John Giammarino, a police spokesman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A city bus driver lost control on 34th Street yesterday evening, crossed two lanes of oncoming traffic and struck an on-duty traffic enforcement agent before driving onto  the sidewalk and smashing into a building, the police said.</p>
        <p>Thirty passengers and the driver were also hurt, though none of the injuries were life-threatening, said Detective John Giammarino, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>The blue-and-white M34 bus was headed east on 34th Street just east of Ninth Avenue about 7:20 p.m. when the driver apparently blacked out, an investigator said.</p>
        <p>The bus veered to the north side of the street and hit the traffic agent -- who was talking to the driver of a parked car -- and hit the parked car itself, Detective Giammarino said.</p>
        <p>The 19-ton bus, picking up speed, went up onto the sidewalk, crushed several saplings and a medium-sized tree, shattered a large concrete planter and cracked the facade of 333 West 34th, home to offices of Salomon Smith Barney and several other companies, witnesses and the police said.</p>
        <p>''Someone yelled, 'Where are you going?' and we just went over the tree and you could just see that you were going to crash,'' a passenger, Anne Roxone, told reporters.</p>
        <p>A witness, Jean Bolcy, 34, told The Associated Press that he saw the driver slumped over at the wheel as the bus headed for the building. ''He didn't even slow down,'' Mr. Bolcy said. ''If he hadn't hit that wall, he'd still be going.''</p>
        <p>Some of the passengers climbed out the windows of the bus.</p>
        <p>The 25-year-old driver, who had been driving for New York City Transit for 18 months, was in serious but stable condition at St. Vincents Hospital and Medical Center and was undergoing tests, the authorities said. He could not recall the moments leading up to the accident, an investigator said.</p>
        <p>The traffic agent, who suffered head and neck trauma, was in stable condition at Bellevue Hospital Center, said John Clark, a hospital spokesman.</p>
        <p>Twenty-eight of the passengers were taken to hospitals in Manhattan and one of them, who had upper body trauma, was admitted overnight at Bellevue, Mr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>None of the victims' names were released.</p>
        <p>333 West 34th, a nine-story building, received only cosmetic damage, said Paul Wien, a spokesman for the Buildings Department. The parked car, a 1999 Toyota Corolla, had its rear end badly damaged.</p>
        <p>All in all, said the city's director of  emergency management, Richard J. Sheirer, the accident could have been much worse.</p>
        <p>''This may be a true miracle on 34th Street, that you could have a city bus go up on the sidewalk at 7 o'clock on a warm summer night and have only one person get hit,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolcy's description of the driver slumped over at the wheel as the bus careered down the sidewalk was  reminiscent of accounts of another Midtown bus crash, in October 1997.</p>
        <p>In that accident, on Fifth Avenue, the driver suffered a seizure that pinned his foot to the accelerator.</p>
        <p>He lost control of his bus for seven blocks, killing a foot messenger, critically injuring a bicyclist and plowing into two cars before crashing into a building.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
