<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Injustice Of Incivility In Civic Duty</title>
    <meta content="02NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vera Institute of Justice</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citizens Jury Project</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Injustice Of Incivility In Civic Duty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman column expresses hope that deplorable conditions of jury duty in New York will be corrected now that all citizens are being called to serve; cites report from Citizens Jury Project, an offshoot of Vera Institute of Justice, on the dreary, filthy courthouses, rude judges and clerks and time wasted by lawyers arguing motions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT had been a long time since the last foray into the Criminal Courts Building in lower Manhattan, but a brief visit yesterday confirmed that it had lost none of its charm.</p>
        <p>As ever, the building, at 100 Centre Street, exuded all the joie de vivre of Stalinist architecture. The dank lobby had a stale smell, which is not surprising, given that the same air has circulated since the Impellitteri administration. The lighting made you wish you had remembered to bring infrared lenses. And some of the elevators seemed programmed to remain stationary until the autumnal equinox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT had been a long time since the last foray into the Criminal Courts Building in lower Manhattan, but a brief visit yesterday confirmed that it had lost none of its charm.</p>
        <p>As ever, the building, at 100 Centre Street, exuded all the joie de vivre of Stalinist architecture. The dank lobby had a stale smell, which is not surprising, given that the same air has circulated since the Impellitteri administration. The lighting made you wish you had remembered to bring infrared lenses. And some of the elevators seemed programmed to remain stationary until the autumnal equinox.</p>
        <p>It is hard to appreciate justice's full majesty in that kind of setting, a conclusion that many New Yorkers have reached now that jury duty is the great civic equalizer, forcing thousands to spend time in courthouses that they once safely avoided. One juror put it this way:</p>
        <p>''The disgraceful physical conditions just fuel the general malevolence of sitting around waiting for something to happen.''</p>
        <p>That remark was made to the Citizens Jury Project, an offshoot of the Vera Institute of Justice that monitored the courts in New York City for the last five years, specifically to see how jurors were faring. The jury project's conclusion, in a new report sent to the state's top judges, is that jurors are doing fine, all in all, but. . . .</p>
        <p>But too many judges and court clerks are unacceptably rude. But too much juror time is wasted while lawyers argue motions and fiddle around in ways that Sam Waterston never does on ''Law and Order.'' But it is unsettling to have your name and address made known to an accused murderer. But physical conditions are miserable in some courthouses, like 100 Centre Street.</p>
        <p>That last problem can be especially corrosive. ''When courts are a pigsty, you're just not going to get people in there cherishing the judicial system,'' said Julia Vitullo-Martin, a senior fellow at Vera who supervised the jury project. And now more New Yorkers than ever are coming face to face each day with the system's shortcomings.</p>
        <p>The last few years have brought a mini-revolution in the New York courts, with some two dozen occupations stripped of their automatic exemptions from jury duty. No longer may lawyers, doctors and police officers wriggle out of serving as jurors simply because of what they do for a living. The same goes for professions whose exemptions were, to be polite, odd. Why an embalmer or someone who fits artificial limbs should have been able to avoid a basic civic duty was always a mystery.</p>
        <p>Now, just about everyone is called, mayors included. At the same time, the amount of time that most jurors serve has shrunk. The results are dramatic. Here are the figures from the state's Office of Court Administration:</p>
        <p>From 1995 to 1999, the number of serving jurors in New York City grew by 30 percent, to 309,814 from 238,997. In Manhattan, top-heavy with lawyers and doctors, the increase was even more striking: 37 percent, to 100,562 from 73,553.</p>
        <p>This development would seem to have few downsides, if any. How can you argue against equal treatment? With military conscription long gone, jury duty may be the only shared civic experience that we have left, an issue of no small consequence in a city as socially fractured as this one is.</p>
        <p>DO we have anything else where citizens come together as a group?'' Ms. Vitullo-Martin said.</p>
        <p>''And reflect?'' she added.</p>
        <p>She is convinced (and personal experience here suggests she is right) that many New Yorkers who used to think that jury duty was only for those too witless to find a way out are now proud to be chosen. But if that is so, her jury project concluded after listening to 7,700 jurors, then extra measures are needed to make courthouse life more tolerable.</p>
        <p>Court administrators have to curb abuses by rude judges, the report says. Court clerks should be rewarded when they are cheerful and efficient. Restrictive rules, like those prohibiting jurors from taking notes, ought to be re-examined. ''Everybody now serves,'' Ms. Vitullo-Martin said. ''You cannot treat them like children.''</p>
        <p>And, the report says, something absolutely must be done to pep up dreary places like 100 Centre Street.</p>
        <p>One possibility that it suggests is having the state take back responsibility for courthouse maintenance, turned over years ago to the city. All too often, the report says, the city ''behaves like an absentee landlord,'' and that has led to ''the face of justice becoming shoddier by the day.''</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
