<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serial Rapist Gets 155 Years; Judge Suggests His Crimes Contributed to Diallo Shooting</title>
    <meta content="02RAPE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diallo, Amadou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carroll, Sean (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisch, Joseph (Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6DB1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serial Rapist Gets 155 Years; Judge Suggests His Crimes Contributed to Diallo Shooting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Joseph Fisch sentences Isaac Jones to 155 years to life in prison for sexually abusing or robbing 29 women over five years in Bronx, Manhattan and Westchester County; suggests that his crime spree might have contributed to fatal police shooting of Amadou Diallo since one of officers in that case said after the shooting that they had approached Diallo because he fit the general description of the rapist (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before sentencing a serial rapist to 155 years to life in prison, a Bronx judge suggested yesterday that the man's crime spree might have contributed to the fatal police shooting of Amadou Diallo. One of the officers in that case said after the shooting that they had approached Mr. Diallo because he fit the general description of the rapist.</p>
        <p>The man sentenced yesterday, Isaac Jones, 39, was a career criminal accused of raping, sexually abusing or robbing 29 women over five years in the Bronx, Manhattan and Westchester County, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before sentencing a serial rapist to 155 years to life in prison, a Bronx judge suggested yesterday that the man's crime spree might have contributed to the fatal police shooting of Amadou Diallo. One of the officers in that case said after the shooting that they had approached Mr. Diallo because he fit the general description of the rapist.</p>
        <p>The man sentenced yesterday, Isaac Jones, 39, was a career criminal accused of raping, sexually abusing or robbing 29 women over five years in the Bronx, Manhattan and Westchester County, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>In scathing remarks yesterday, the judge, Justice Joseph Fisch of State Supreme Court in the Bronx, said Mr. Jones had victimized many more people than those who were attacked. Mothers were fearful for their daughters, he said, and others confined themselves to their homes.</p>
        <p>Then Justice Fisch brought up Mr. Diallo. ''Would Amadou Diallo be alive today were it not for your activities here in the Bronx?''</p>
        <p>The death of Mr. Diallo resulted in murder indictments against the four officers who shot him, and the case eventually led to angry protests after the officers were acquitted in February.</p>
        <p>During the trial, one of the officers, Sean Carroll, said that when he saw Mr. Diallo standing in a vestibule on Wheeler Avenue in the Bronx, he thought Mr. Diallo looked like the serial rapist, or might have been a lookout for a robber. The officers approached Mr. Diallo and started shooting when he pulled out a wallet; the officers said at their trial that they took it to be a gun.</p>
        <p>Justice Fisch did not address those issues in his presentencing remarks. Asked about the judge's comment, Robert T. Johnson, the Bronx district attorney, whose office prosecuted the four officers, said he did not want to debate the matter.</p>
        <p>''I think there's a lot of speculation about what happened,'' Mr. Johnson said at a news conference yesterday. ''I don't want to retry the Diallo case, but we only have it on the say-so of the four defendants in that case, and even that was iffy, as to what they were doing and what their rationale was at that time.''</p>
        <p>The crimes for which Mr. Jones was sentenced yesterday include the rapes of two women and the robbery and sexual assaults of four others between Oct. 28, 1994, and Feb. 5, 1999, the day after Mr. Diallo's death. He also faces other trials in the rapes of 13 women and the robberies of 3 others in the Bronx, the rapes of 4 women in Manhattan and the rape of a woman in Mount Vernon in Westchester County. In his Bronx trial, he was acquitted of two other rapes.</p>
        <p>Seated next to his lawyer, his fingers fidgeting, his eyes downcast, Mr. Jones listened silently as Justice Fisch described the depravity of the crimes and the intense fear the defendant caused in much of the city.</p>
        <p>''Isaac Jones, you are a vicious, violent and brutal creature, without remorse, contrition or regret,'' the judge said. ''You blame everyone but yourself -- the police, the press, the district attorney -- and refuse to accept responsibility for your dastardly crimes. You have destroyed lives, uprooted homes and traumatized an entire community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones's sister, Laverne Jones, continued to insist that her brother was innocent, telling reporters after the sentencing that Justice Fisch did not know her brother. His lawyer, Kevin Canfield, also reaffirmed his position that the wrong man had been convicted, and said he would file an appeal.</p>
        <p>Justice Fisch, however, said Mr. Jones's guilt was not in doubt. He noted that DNA evidence linked Mr. Jones to the rapes for which he was convicted, and that Mr. Jones had given the police a detailed videotaped confession after New York police officers arrested him in April outside a Bronx pawn shop where his girlfriend had been trying to sell stolen jewelry.</p>
        <p>The judge belittled Mr. Jones's explanations for his crimes, saying his efforts to distinguish between ''stolen'' and ''hot'' property reminded him of George Washington Plunkitt, a Tammany Hall leader who drew a distinction between honest and dishonest graft.</p>
        <p>Justice Fisch even quoted Shakespeare in describing how the Isaac Jones who appeared before women in darkened alleys was not the same Isaac Jones his family knew. ''We are reminded in 'Hamlet,' '' the judge said, ''that 'the devil hath power to assume a pleasing shape.' ''</p>
        <p>Reading from a 15-page statement, the judge called Mr. Jones's crimes bestial and described him as a relentless stalker who took glee in humiliating women and inflicting pain.</p>
        <p>''You drove around in the early hours of the morning, in the stealth of darkness as cowards are wont to do, armed with a variety of weapons and disguises,'' the judge said. He noted that that one victim had been five months pregnant and that Mr. Jones had raped another woman because she had rejected his advances.</p>
        <p>In imposing a string of 25- and 5-year terms that added up to a minimum sentence of 155 years, Justice Fisch said, ''I hope and trust that I have removed from society a cruel, merciless and dangerous predator who has ruined many lives.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
