<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Candidate for Nothing, But Under 2 Microscopes</title>
    <meta content="02BERN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrett, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirtzman, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rudy! an Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">rudi giuliani: emperor of the city (book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDC113DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Candidate for Nothing, But Under 2 Microscopes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews two biographies: Wayne Barrett's Rudy! and Andrew Kirtzman's Rudy Giuliani: Emperor of the City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUDY!  An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani  By Wayne Barrett  Illustrated. 498 pages. Basic Books. $26.</p>
        <p>RUDY GIULIANI  Emperor of the City  By Andrew Kirtzman  Illustrated. 333 pages. William Morrow. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUDY!  An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani  By Wayne Barrett  Illustrated. 498 pages. Basic Books. $26.</p>
        <p>RUDY GIULIANI  Emperor of the City  By Andrew Kirtzman  Illustrated. 333 pages. William Morrow. $25.</p>
        <p>Here are two ambitious books on the same subject, and almost a single theme. The subject is Rudolph W. Giuliani, the most famous mayor in the world and a surprise noncandidate for Senate. And the theme is the depth of his flaws, despite the magnitude of his accomplishments as a mayor. The fact is that voters will not be using the information disclosed in these works to inform any electoral decisions in the very near future. Still, the books tell a great deal about recent local history and the role played in it by one of the more compelling and energetic protagonists in contemporary politics.</p>
        <p>The books are Wayne Barrett's ''Rudy! An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani,'' which is a major work of political biography, and Andrew Kirtzman's ''Rudy Giuliani: Emperor of the City,'' which is merely good.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman, who covers city politics for New York 1, focuses entirely on Mr. Giuliani's career as an elected official, with little about his background or even his earlier career as the United States attorney for the Southern District in Manhattan. If his book were the only one available about Mr. Giuliani, it would seem a competent, informed, fair-minded though generally critical account of Mr. Giuliani's life in city government.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barrett, a veteran reporter for The Village Voice, has written a book with broader shoulders and a deeper reach than Mr. Kirtzman's. It is also an indefatigable accumulation of facts and anecdotes about Mr. Giuliani guided by a muckraker's impulse to find an unsavory maximum about him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett unearths numerous details about Mr. Giuliani's family background that, he contends, the mayor has assiduously tried to keep secret, specifically that several of his close relatives, including his father, were criminals. He analyzes his record as United States attorney and finds a sizable gap between the record and the Great Prosecutor's reputation. He goes back to Mr. Giuliani's career as the youngest-ever associate attorney general in the Justice Department and finds that he played a major role in devising the Reagan Administration's contradictory policy of interdicting Haitian refugees while providing asylum for Cubans.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Barrett and Mr. Kirtzman aver early on that New York has become vastly better off in the years Mr. Giuliani has been mayor. ''It is hard to overstate the degree to which the culture of the city changed under his mayoralty,'' Mr. Kirtzman writes. By culture he means such matters as the extent of homelessness, the sense of lurking danger that New Yorkers used to live with on a daily basis, the neighborhood pornography stores that Mr. Giuliani closed down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett makes a similar overall judgment. ''There is little question but that New York City has become a better place to live on Rudy Giuliani's watch,'' he writes. ''It got dramatically safer and cleaner. The tax load dipped and the budget surplus soared.'' But one senses a pro forma quality to that remark, which is followed by nearly 500 pages portraying Mr. Giuliani as not just a zealot, but so driven by his zeal that he is unaware of his own corruptibility.</p>
        <p>''The arrogance that is like body odor to Rudy,'' he writes in his concluding chapter, ''repellent to others but undetectable to him, is rooted, strangely enough, in his concept of clean hands. He is never wrong, his swagger says, because he has spent his life uncovering and combating wrong, a knight besieged but undaunted by the compromised, confused and corrupt.''</p>
        <p>It isn't necessarily the case, contrary to an underlying assumption in both of these books, that a flawed man can't make an excellent mayor, but both authors do show direct connections between the flaws -- an unwillingness to share public credit chief among them -- and the city's problems. One important item in the bill of indictment in this sense was City Hall's effort to push the city's highly successful police commissioner, William Bratton, to resign, mainly because Mr. Bratton was getting too much credit in the press. Mr. Barrett contends that all the initiatives in the dramatic reduction in crime that occurred in New York came from within the police department. Still, he argues, Mr. Giuliani ''dumped Bratton when polls showed that 60 percent of New Yorkers credited him, while only 18 percent cited the mayor, for the two-year, 26.3 percent drop in felonies.''</p>
        <p>There is a relentlessness to Mr. Barrett's effort to discredit Mr. Giuliani that gives the impression of a journalistic vendetta, and yet there is much too much evidence in his book to ignore. (One minor mystery is that Mr. Barrett provides footnote references for only three of his 21 fact-packed chapters.) He details Mr. Giuliani's unfaithfulness to two wives -- his first marriage, to his second cousin Regina Peruggi, was annulled after 14 years. He mentions about every sighting on the record of Mr. Giuliani and his chief press aide, Cristyne Lategano, with whom he maintained an unseemly closeness. (Mr. Barrett, like other writers on this well-covered subject, provides no hard proof of just how intimate the two were.) He practically counts the failures of Mr. Giuliani to spend quality time with his children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett argues strenuously that Mr. Giuliani's record as United States attorney was actually not as good as his predecessor's in that job or as good as his rival's in the Eastern District in Brooklyn, although he does allow that Mr. Giuliani won his share of major cases, against organized crime and against corrupt Democratic politicians.</p>
        <p>''By the end of Rudy's term as U.S. Attorney, he had ushered in the end of an era: the demise of Democratic machine politics in New York City,'' he writes. Both Mr. Kirtzman and Mr. Barrett bring the Giuliani story up to date -- to his withdrawal from the Senate race after announcing almost simultaneously that he had prostate cancer and that he and his wife, Donna Hanover, were separating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman's book, while not as complete as Mr. Barrett's, is modestly more generous in some ways. He is willing, for example, to attribute to Mr. Giuliani sincerely held values and honest convictions even while assiduously chronicling his faults. ''Giuliani believed that his predecessors had gotten themselves and the city into trouble by blurring the distinction between right and wrong,'' he writes. ''His strategy was to stake out a principle, send a consistent message, and refuse to compromise.'' Still, Mr. Kirtzman's detailed account of Mr. Giuliani's pained relationship with Ramon Cortines, the former school's chancellor, is a study in manipulative unreasonableness.</p>
        <p>One has the sense that there is a degree of zeal in these books -- more in Mr. Barrett's than in Mr. Kirtzman's -- that mirrors the Giuliani zeal and that therefore leads the authors to miss a point. The steady listing of personal and political flaws makes one wonder how it is that, as both authors acknowledge, New York got so much cleaner, safer and more prosperous with Mr. Giuliani in charge. One reads these books with interest for their huge compilations of facts and details, and yet one reads feeling also that the answer to that question is missing in both.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
