<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chavez Says He Will Crush Political Foes In Venezuela</title>
    <meta content="Y02VEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/02/world/02VENE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Merida (Venezuela)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davila, William (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela/Merida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chavez Says He Will Crush Political Foes In Venezuela</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Aug. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venezuelan Pres Hugo Chavez says he will use troops to crush street protests and to oust William Davila, opposition party governor of Merida, who was leading in his re-election bid until 6,000 ballots cast for him were declared invalid and pro-Chavez candidate declared winner by small margin; Davila charges fraud; opposition candidates in five other states make similar charges (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Hugo Chavez said today that he would use troops to crush  street protests and to remove an opposition party governor who has accused the governing party of fraudulently altering the outcome of  elections last weekend.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be nothing more than a little spat, but we are obliged to guarantee order and prevent these groups from spoiling the beautiful process that we have concluded,'' Mr. Chavez said this afternoon, referring to the vote held across Venezuela on Sunday. ''If they lost, they lost,'' he added dismissively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Hugo Chavez said today that he would use troops to crush  street protests and to remove an opposition party governor who has accused the governing party of fraudulently altering the outcome of  elections last weekend.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be nothing more than a little spat, but we are obliged to guarantee order and prevent these groups from spoiling the beautiful process that we have concluded,'' Mr. Chavez said this afternoon, referring to the vote held across Venezuela on Sunday. ''If they lost, they lost,'' he added dismissively.</p>
        <p>Preliminary results from the national and local balloting, in which Mr. Chavez and 165 members of a new National Assembly were also elected, gave victory to the incumbent governor in the western state of Merida, William Davila, a leading opposition figure. But 6,000 ballots, most cast for Mr. Davila, were declared invalid for reasons that are still not clear, and the pro-Chavez candidate was declared the winner today, by a margin of less than 1,800 votes.</p>
        <p>''It is clear that there was a fraud, which the people of Merida reject,'' Mr. Davila said in remarks broadcast on national television today.</p>
        <p>Opposition candidates in five other states also made similar accusations about fraud in their races. Preliminary results had given Mr. Chavez's leftist Patriotic Pole coalition 12 of the 23 governorships at stake in the election in this oil-rich nation of 23 million people, but this afternoon Mr. Chavez said that his candidates had actually triumphed in 16 states and warned that he would not tolerate ''anarchy.''</p>
        <p>''We are consolidating our victory, and as in any battle, you have to fight for every inch of territory,'' he said. He minimized the protests as ''a mob with a few rocks and sticks'' and said that ''four or five canisters of tear gas ought to get them out of there,'' referring to the government offices where Mr. Davila has taken refuge.</p>
        <p>On Monday, two international observer groups, one led by former President Jimmy Carter and the other sent by the Organization of American States, had pronounced the balloting here clean and fair. Sustained opposition complaints of fraud in the tabulation of votes began in earnest only today, though, after the observer groups had begun to close down operations here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez, a former army colonel who led an unsuccesful coup attempt in 1992, announced the dispatch of troops this afternoon during a three-hour news conference at which he also discussed issues ranging from his government's foreign policy to his plans to reactivate the Venezuelan economy. His most significant comments, though, came in a response to a question about oil prices, which have recently soared to near-record highs.</p>
        <p>In recent years, Venezuela has been the leading supplier of the oil imported by the United States, and the country's energy minister, Ali Rodriguez Araque, was designated president of the Organization of Oil Exporting Countries, or OPEC, this spring. Mr. Chavez made it clear that he was delighted with the jump in oil prices and reiterated his position that he sees no reason to take any action to bring them down.</p>
        <p>''We are just defending our position,'' Mr. Chavez said. ''It's not that prices are high. They are fair and just.''</p>
        <p>Despite the oil bonanza, Venezuela's economy contracted by more than 7 percent last year, and now that the election is over, Mr. Chavez is under pressure to take steps to end that recession.</p>
        <p>He also reiterated his admiration for the Cuban and Chinese revolutions, saying those countries' economies ''have good things'' and have produced social benefits. But he then added that it is not his intention to ''try to import models from abroad,'' and said that his own revolutionary government welcomes foreign investment, so long as it is ''productive, not speculative.''</p>
        <p>Long a skeptic about American policies in the region, Mr. Chavez expressed concern about the $1.3 billion emergency aid package for neighboring Colombia that President Clinton approved last month. He said that while his government is ''willing to cooperate'' with Colombia and the United States, he hoped that the military aid would ''not be used to Vietnamize the Colombia conflict'' or contribute to an increase in the fighting there.</p>
        <p>''Let's hope this doesn't happen,'' he said. ''We are paying close attention.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chavez reserved his most critical comments for his domestic opposition, saying that some of his adversaries ''refuse to recognize Chavez as president'' and warning that he will not hesitate to use his expanded powers to bring them to heel. ''If they don't understand that or don't cooperate, we will apply the Constitution to them,'' he warned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
