<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>College Takes to Street to Drum Up Enrollment</title>
    <meta content="02RECR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Community Colleges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Enrollment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EEDC1E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>College Takes to Street to Drum Up Enrollment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City University of New York begins heavily marketing its six community colleges after the number of applicants in the late spring falls more than 10 percent below 1999; some CUNY professors suggest that students feel unwelcome because of new policies limiting remedial classes; CUNY administrators disagree, noting that those changes affect only senior colleges and attributing application decline to booming economy, which makes work more attractive than school; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Call it the big sell.</p>
        <p>The Borough of Manhattan Community College is plastering its name all over New York City -- in 350 buses, 1,000 subway cars and 24 movie theaters, to be exact -- to attract students, and is sending current students out on the streets to recruit. Ronald Spalter, the college's vice president for administration and planning, is even planning to send students to Jones Beach to collar prospects for this fall's class right on the sands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Call it the big sell.</p>
        <p>The Borough of Manhattan Community College is plastering its name all over New York City -- in 350 buses, 1,000 subway cars and 24 movie theaters, to be exact -- to attract students, and is sending current students out on the streets to recruit. Ronald Spalter, the college's vice president for administration and planning, is even planning to send students to Jones Beach to collar prospects for this fall's class right on the sands.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, on a sultry afternoon that threatened rain, three students positioned themselves between vendors hawking wireless telephones and health insurance at the bustling Fordham Plaza shopping center in the Bronx to sell the virtues of the college. They were looking for high school students, immigrants and other men and women from poor and working-class neighborhoods who may not have thought of college as a possibility.</p>
        <p>''Interested in college? B.M.C.C. is where you want to be,'' Theodore McNeil called as he trotted alongside likely-looking candidates.</p>
        <p>''If you can't afford the tuition there,'' he said, pointing to the nearby Fordham University campus, ''you can come to B.M.C.C.'' (B.M.C.C. tuition is $2,500 a year for state residents; Fordham's tuition is about $20,000.)</p>
        <p>The campaign is part of a wider push by the City University of New York to attract more students to its six community colleges after the number of applicants in the late spring fell more than 10 percent below the year before.</p>
        <p>Why the numbers slipped is unclear. Some CUNY professors suggest that students feel unwelcome because of the university's new policies limiting remedial classes. CUNY administrators disagree, saying that the changes affect the senior colleges, not the community colleges. They say the cause is the booming economy, which makes work more attractive than school.</p>
        <p>Whatever the cause, the university did not want to take a chance that enrollments would remain weak -- even though community college students often wait to enroll until classes begin and there could still be a last-minute surge. A decline in students means a decline in tuition revenues and could force the colleges to cut back.</p>
        <p>In June, Matthew Goldstein, CUNY's chancellor, leaned on the community colleges to mount recruiting campaigns, putting up about $250,000 to aid the effort. Last month, he took to the airwaves himself to promote CUNY, with 30- and 60-second radio spots advising listeners that ''It takes more than a high school diploma to get a good job,'' and inviting them to call 290-5678 for ''on-the-spot admission.''</p>
        <p>All of CUNY's community colleges now have their own recruiting and publicity programs. But none is as far-reaching as the one at B.M.C.C., which is probably less well known than the other CUNY community colleges, which draw most of their students from their own neighborhoods. B.M.C.C. draws only about a quarter of its students from Manhattan. Many of the rest come from the other boroughs and from Long Island and Westchester. Foreign students account for nearly 10 percent of its enrollment.</p>
        <p>Based in a sprawling modern building on Chambers Street near the Hudson River, the college has seen its enrollment slip to fewer than 15,000 from about 17,000 a few years ago.</p>
        <p>''We knew we had to correct the slide,'' said Antonio Perez, B.M.C.C.'s president.</p>
        <p>Another reason for the big publicity splash, he said, was that the college needs greater name recognition before it begins a multimillion-dollar fund-raising campaign.</p>
        <p>The publicity is costly. B.M.C.C. put the cost of the advertisements at more than $150,000. But Dr. Perez said an increase in students and a successful capital campaign would more than make up for the spending.</p>
        <p>At Fordham Plaza last week, Chanel Wray and Antoinette Daniels, members of B.M.C.C.'s women's basketball team (which took third place nationally among community colleges) laid out brochures for more than a dozen B.M.C.C. programs, including science, nursing, accounting and computer programming, as well as a pile of information on student aid.</p>
        <p>The students also mounted a large satellite dish with the college's name on it between their two tables.</p>
        <p>''It's a decoy, but it draws people's attention,'' said Ms. Wray, an 18-year-old liberal arts major at the college who is earning $8.46 an hour to recruit students.</p>
        <p>Business was brisk.</p>
        <p>Six young women decked out in multiple gold chains and earrings crowded around the college's table and chatted about the basketball team. After asking where the college was (on Chambers Street, near the Hudson River) and how they could get there (the 1, 2, 3, 9, A and C subway trains stop close by), two of them filled out short forms requesting more information.</p>
        <p>A gum-chewing woman with neon-pink toenails grabbed brochures on the college's nursing and early childhood programs.</p>
        <p>The driver of a shiny black Town Car limousine pulled over to the curb and leaned out the window to ask Mr. McNeil about the college. Mr. McNeil handed the driver a form, and he filled it out, passed it back and sped away.</p>
        <p>Several mothers stopped to fill out forms requesting more information for their children.</p>
        <p>''Parents don't take the time to invest in helping their children,'' commented Stephanie Fields, a tall woman with an assured manner. She said she just graduated from college herself and was now trying to find a place for her daughter, Arlene, who is a senior in high school.</p>
        <p>Some of the most serious candidates appeared to be immigrants hoping to move up to better jobs, a group that accounts for a sizable share of the students at all of CUNY's community colleges.</p>
        <p>Lanning Diaz, a medical school graduate from the Dominican Republic, looked carefully through the B.M.C.C. brochures, especially the ones about computer science. A tall man with a grizzled beard, he said that he had been thinking about returning to school to learn about computer applications in health care since his medical license is not valid here.</p>
        <p>He said he had already asked for his transcripts to be sent from the Dominican Republic to CUNY, but did not know which college he would attend. ''I barely know the names and locations of the colleges,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sunday Alao, a Bronx resident from Ghana, also looked slowly through the college brochures. He said that although he had studied college-level accounting and management in Ghana, he was working in a kitchen now and wanted to go back to school to enter nursing. What college he chooses, he said, depends on whether he can afford it and whether he can schedule classes around his job.</p>
        <p>Not everyone was interested.</p>
        <p>Sharon Brown, a chatty woman in a bright turban who described herself as an entrepreneur, stopped briefly. She said she did not have a college degree but did not want one, though she might consider a computer course.</p>
        <p>''Do they have Wealth Creation 101?'' she asked. ''That's what I'm interested in.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McNeil, who is 33 years old and has three children, was philosophic. ''With the Clinton administration and prosperity, a lot of people are focused on putting food on the table now,'' he said after several people passed by without stopping.</p>
        <p>''They don't want to think about what happens down the road. We're trying to get them to think about it.''</p>
        <p>B.M.C.C. officials are pleased with the response so far. As of mid-July, they say, the number of CUNY applicants requesting B.M.C.C. was nearly 2,800 -- more than 20 percent above last year.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McNeil said that whether the number of new students rose or fell, he was convinced that the recruiting effort was worthwhile.</p>
        <p>''On the off-chance it doesn't work,'' said Mr. McNeil, ''they can't say CUNY didn't reach out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
