<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charm Might Not Be Enough</title>
    <meta content="2BBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: MINOR LEAGUE NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pittsfield (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luttrell, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Berkshires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charm Might Not Be Enough</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM LUTTRELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Luttrell, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses uncertain future of minor league baseball in Pittsfield, Mass</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across the country, municipalities are building baseball stadiums, both for major and minor league teams, that attempt to recapture the charm and nostalgia of old-fashioned parks. Camden Yards in Baltimore and Riverfront Stadium in Newark are two examples. For a taste of authentic charm, baseball fans can look to Wahconah Park in Pittsfield, Mass.</p>
        <p>Wahconah Park, the home of the Pittsfield Mets of the Class A New York-Penn League, was built in 1919 in the mountains of Berkshire County. It features strange outfield dimensions and angles that have tested players like Lou Gehrig, George Scott, Rafael Palmeiro and Greg Maddux over the years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across the country, municipalities are building baseball stadiums, both for major and minor league teams, that attempt to recapture the charm and nostalgia of old-fashioned parks. Camden Yards in Baltimore and Riverfront Stadium in Newark are two examples. For a taste of authentic charm, baseball fans can look to Wahconah Park in Pittsfield, Mass.</p>
        <p>Wahconah Park, the home of the Pittsfield Mets of the Class A New York-Penn League, was built in 1919 in the mountains of Berkshire County. It features strange outfield dimensions and angles that have tested players like Lou Gehrig, George Scott, Rafael Palmeiro and Greg Maddux over the years.</p>
        <p>Plastic owls hang from the rafters to scare away pigeons. And of course, there's the sun. Wahconah Park was built long before night baseball, and the ballpark faces west, instead of east, as most stadiums do. When the sun sets beyond the center-field fence, it shines directly into the eyes of the batter, catcher and home plate umpire, requiring sun delays. Trees planted beyond the outfield fence have cut down on the frequency of the sun delays. In fact, the 1999 season was completed without one.</p>
        <p>Change, however, is coming to the Berkshires. The Mets hope to switch their New York-Penn League affiliation next season to the Queens Kings, currently playing at St. John's University, and then move that franchise to a new stadium in Coney Island. The Pittsfield club, operated by the National Pastime Corporation, will have to wait to find out what its new affiliation will be. Six of the league's player-development contracts with major league teams expire after this season.</p>
        <p>National Pastime is also moving its franchise to Troy, N.Y., and a new stadium beginning in 2002, potentially leaving Wahconah Park empty except for high school games.</p>
        <p>''The facility becomes paramount,'' Pittsfield General Manager Richard J. Murphy said. ''It is the most important aspect in the eyes of the major league franchises.''</p>
        <p>The grandstand has bench seating, the box seats have folding chairs, Murphy said, speaking of Wahconah Park. ''These are quaint things when you're only coming for a day, but for fans who want to be season-ticket holders, it's a problem. The refreshment stands are restrictive. We really can't handle more than 3,000 people. The restroom facilities are limited. And there are electrical and plumbing issues that are associated with old facilities. We've had banks of lights go out.</p>
        <p>''The city of Pittsfield needs to address the facility problem.''</p>
        <p>In 1996, the city agreed to do just that, exploring the possibility of building a new stadium for the Mets. But nothing was resolved. Murphy says the current City Council has renewed the push to build a stadium by 2002. If not, it seems the sun could set not only on Wahconah Park but on minor league baseball in the Berkshires.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL LEAGUE</p>
        <p>The Richmond Braves' manager, Randy Ingle, posted the 500th victory of his minor league career Saturday with a 9-5 triumph at Durham, N.C. Ingle, 42, has compiled a 500-520 record in a nine-year career that has included stops in Pulaski, Va., in the Rookie Appalachian League, Macon, Ga., Durham and Greenville, S.C., before coming to Richmond, Va., in 1999. His teams have had five winning seasons and have won two league championships. Ingle has twice been the Atlanta Braves' minor league manager of the year (1996 and 1997) and was also the Southern League manager of the year in 1997. But some of the shine has been taken off the milestone because Richmond is struggling with a 34-73 record.</p>
        <p>It looks like the Devil Rays were impressed by Paul Wilson's recent outings for the Norfolk Tides in Virginia. Wilson, who was traded by the Mets along with outfielder Jason Tyner for Bubba Trammell and Rick White, had a .069 earned run average in his last two starts for Norfolk. He had one victory and allowed one earned run and 10 hits while working 13 innings in those games. Over all, Wilson was 5-5 with a 4.23 E.R.A. at Norfolk. . . . Adrian Hernandez, El Duquecito, pitched a one-hit shutout last week against Scranton/Wilkes-Barre, Pa., striking out 11 in the 3-0 victory for Columbus, Ohio. Randall Simon hit a three-run homer for the Clippers' runs.</p>
        <p>PACIFIC COAST LEAGUE</p>
        <p>The Albuquerque Dukes, the Dodgers' top affiliate, just completed an eight-game road trip with six victories, including taking three of four from North Division-leading Salt Lake. The Dukes won 18 of 24 games during one July stretch and now have a 10-game lead in the Central Division. . . . John Roskos, one of the Las Vegas Stars' top hitters with 13 homers and 60 runs batted in and among the league leaders with a .346 average, suffered a broken nose when he was hit by a fastball Sunday. He will not return to the lineup for several days.</p>
        <p>JIM LUTTRELL</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: MINOR LEAGUE NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
