<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y29BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/world/29BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDD1F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: NO APPEAL OVER TWINS  The parents of 7-week-old twins joined at the pelvis have decided not to appeal a Court of Appeal decision giving doctors permission to separate the infants in an operation that will sacrifice the life of one to save the other. The couple, from the island of Gozo, near Malta, had argued that their Catholic faith compelled them to let nature take its course although it meant the probable death of both children. But their lawyer said that after two court decisions against them, ''they feel they have done the best they can for both daughters.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: UNITED AGAINST NEO-NAZIS  Leaders of the main political parties united in calls to combat right-wing extremism, which has led to a wave of neo-Nazi violence against foreigners. The Bundestag president, Wolfgang Thierse, left, said such attacks were an assault on a democratic society's values, and should not be regarded just as an east German problem. A government working group is considering the possibility of banning the neo-Nazi National Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: NO APPEAL OVER TWINS  The parents of 7-week-old twins joined at the pelvis have decided not to appeal a Court of Appeal decision giving doctors permission to separate the infants in an operation that will sacrifice the life of one to save the other. The couple, from the island of Gozo, near Malta, had argued that their Catholic faith compelled them to let nature take its course although it meant the probable death of both children. But their lawyer said that after two court decisions against them, ''they feel they have done the best they can for both daughters.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: UNITED AGAINST NEO-NAZIS  Leaders of the main political parties united in calls to combat right-wing extremism, which has led to a wave of neo-Nazi violence against foreigners. The Bundestag president, Wolfgang Thierse, left, said such attacks were an assault on a democratic society's values, and should not be regarded just as an east German problem. A government working group is considering the possibility of banning the neo-Nazi National Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: 5 KURDS SLAIN  Security forces reported killing five Kurdish rebels in fighting in the southeast part of the country, bringing the death toll among separatists to 10 in a week. Fighting between the Kurdistan Workers' Party and the military has eased since last year when Abdullah Ocalan, the jailed Kurdish leader, told his troops to put down their weapons. But the military has pressed on in smaller operations against Kurds in southeast Turkey and Iraq.</p>
        <p>Douglas Frantz (NYT)</p>
        <p>GREECE: 5 CHARGED IN FERRY SINKING  Charges of manslaughter have been brought against the captain and four crew members of a ferry that rammed a marked reef near the Aegean island of Paros on Tuesday, killing at least 66 people. The charges follow accounts by survivors that the ferry was on autopilot as the captain and senior crew members watched a soccer match on television.</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
        <p>ITALY: PEDOPHILIA ARRESTS  Eight people were arrested on charges of selling child pornography on the Internet, while the police said they are investigating 1,700 people suspected of buying sexually graphic and violent videos featuring children. The pedophilia scare turned into a media scandal after two channels of RAI, the state-controlled network, showed clips from the videos on the evening news. After a debate in Parliament on the issue, five RAI journalists said they would quit, including two editors in chief.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAQ: EMBARGO WEAKENED  With flights from Western Europe, the Middle East and Russia arriving almost daily in Baghdad, the Iraqi deputy prime minister, Tariq Aziz, said decade-old sanctions against Iraq were collapsing. ''The embargo has become odious and all people call for its removal,'' he said in Baghdad. Jordan, France and Russia have sent planes to Iraq, saying there never really was an air embargo, despite contrary assertions by Washington. Iceland and Yemen are also planning flights.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: DRUG CZAR'S JAILING UPHELD  A court upheld the 71-year prison sentence on Jesus Gutierrez Rebollo, a former head of the National Institute to Combat Drugs who was convicted on drug and weapons charges. Mr. Rebollo was arrested in 1997 after prosecutors found he had received gifts, payments and real estate from leaders of one of Mexico's most ruthless drug cartels. He also faces charges of abuse of authority.</p>
        <p>BOLIVIA: COCA PROTESTS  President Hugo Banzer canceled a trip to Japan in order to deal with rising protests by coca farmers, who are blocking roads across the country. The protests, which have already caused estimated losses of $100 million, are in support of demands that the military remove troops from the chatare, the country's principal area of coca cultivation.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>MOROCCO: WESTERN SAHARA TALKS  Morocco and the Polisario Front independence movement began direct peace talks in Berlin over the disputed territory of Western Sahara. The main sticking point is the carrying out of a long-delayed United Nations peace plan that calls for a referendum to decide whether the former Spanish colony should be incorporated into Morocco, which controls most of the territory, or become independent.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: MEAT BARRED  Responding to an outbreak of foot-and-mouth disease among livestock at two farms in the KwaZulu Natal Province, Botswana, Namibia, Singapore and Mauritius have banned imports of South African meat. Officials said they were destroying about 3,500 animals to stop the spread of the disease.</p>
        <p>Rachel L. Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: DISARMING TIMOR REBELS  Hundreds of Indonesian soldiers and policemen swept through nine militia strongholds in West Timor as part of a three-day operation to disarm the paramilitaries, officers said. The crackdown came after a government deadline for the militias to surrender their weapons passed on Wednesday. Indonesia is under intense pressure to disband the gangs after they killed three United Nations aid workers in Atambua on Sept. 6.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: STRIKES ON REBELS  Air force jets hit back at rebel-held positions as troops tried to recover from new rebel attacks that forced them to withdraw from some areas in the northern Jaffna Peninsula. A government statement said the jets struck Kilinochchi and Paranthan, rebel-controlled areas on the northern mainland, after troops withdrew their southernmost defenses at least half a mile.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
