<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Yugoslav Who Could Be Leader Sketches the Nation He Envisions</title>
    <meta content="Y29BEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/world/29BELG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DF163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Yugoslav Who Could Be Leader Sketches the Nation He Envisions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica says he wants to help shape Serbia into country with different sense of itself and its place in the world, less isolated and neurotic, a normal European nation with good dose of skepticism toward American foreign-policy goals; Kostunica, who claims election victory over Pres Slobodan Milosevic, says Serbia and Montenegro must work out new relationship, and work within United Nations Security Council resolution governing Kosovo to find modus vivendi that allows Serbs to return there with security, within democratic, unimperial state; he says Serbia must confront its own past, especially last decade of civil wars that Milosevic helped start; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Should Vojislav Kostunica take office as Yugoslavia's new president, he wants, he says, to help shape a country with a different sense of itself and its place in the world, less isolated and neurotic, a normal European nation with a good dose of skepticism toward American foreign-policy goals.</p>
        <p>In a series of conversations in recent weeks, before and after what he and his supporters insist was his victory in elections last Sunday, Mr. Kostunica has outlined a vision  broadly like this:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Should Vojislav Kostunica take office as Yugoslavia's new president, he wants, he says, to help shape a country with a different sense of itself and its place in the world, less isolated and neurotic, a normal European nation with a good dose of skepticism toward American foreign-policy goals.</p>
        <p>In a series of conversations in recent weeks, before and after what he and his supporters insist was his victory in elections last Sunday, Mr. Kostunica has outlined a vision  broadly like this:</p>
        <p>Yugoslavia needs to redefine itself, with its republics, Serbia and Montenegro, working out a new relationship if they can, and also needs to work within the United Nations Security Council resolution governing Kosovo to find a modus vivendi that allows Serbs to return there with security, within a democratic, unimperial state.</p>
        <p>Significantly, he said that Serbia needed to confront its own past, especially in the last decade of Yugoslavia's civil wars. Such a self-examination, he said, has been blocked so far  both by the incumbency of Slobodan Milosevic, who helped start those wars, and by the nature of the regime that Mr. Milosevic built: a Communist base infused by nationalism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica (pronounced kosh-TOON-eet-zah), a 56-year-old constitutional lawyer, said he would favor a form of state ''truth commission'' of independent historians and experts to examine the crimes and victims of all the parties to the Yugoslav wars.</p>
        <p>''There was a war in the former Yugoslavia, and we must try to face the results and consequences of this war one way or another,'' he said. ''We must look at everything. I would try to analyze all that -- what happened, how it happened, where do we stand, what we might have avoided, what was not possible to avoid, what are our victims, what are our crimes, what are others' crimes and victims.''</p>
        <p>Many who see themselves as victims of the Serbs -- Kosovo's Albanians, Bosnia's Muslims, and Croats in Croatia -- may bridle at such a broad examination, which those attacked often see as a way for Serbs to try to escape blame for their worst crimes. Indeed, Mr. Kostunica has been labeled a nationalist, albeit a moderate one, a description that he said makes him uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>''To me, nationalism is a natural state of mind, to be one who belongs to a nation,'' he said. Such national feeling -- which might be called patriotism elsewhere -- is not much different from that felt by the British or the French, he suggested.</p>
        <p>On the campaign trail, Mr. Kostunica traveled with a small retinue all over Serbia, using Serbian traditions to criticize the socialist regime of Mr. Milosevic, which he said had distorted the country's interests.</p>
        <p>His choice for a national anthem is the Serbian one from the 19th century, he often mentions God in his speeches, and he is proud of his family's bourgeois and anti-Communist traditions. This background fed his defense, in 1974, of a senior professor at Belgrade University who had criticized the Communist government, an action that led to Mr. Kostunica's firing. And in 1989, when Mr. Milosevic, then the relatively new leader of Serbia, offered to rehire those sacked, Mr. Kostunica refused.</p>
        <p>In a stop at his native village, Kostunici, he spoke extemporaneously of his family's house, now destroyed, and the values of the Serbia of 150 years ago, before the distortions of Communism. He contrasted the idea of ''a real Serbian house, built on real Serbian roots,'' to the borrowed architecture of Russia, China and Belarus, Mr. Milosevic's allies. His speech had a touch of mysticism, but it worked with the poor villagers and farmers who came to hear him.</p>
        <p>It had the ring of authenticity and humbleness, which were hallmarks of his campaign as ''a normal man,'' a Serbian patriot and the anti-Milosevic.</p>
        <p>The world is beginning to understand him better, Mr. Kostunika said.</p>
        <p>He has had much contact lately with the French foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, especially, given France's current presidency of the European Union. ''Vedrine has been open to understanding Serbian patriotism,'' Mr. Kostunica said.</p>
        <p>And in his criticism of the United States and its policies, there is more than a touch of the continental European view -- often articulated by the French -- that the ''hyperpower'' of the United States, with its enormous wealth and capacities, is often unconscious and unheeding of the dignity and interests of other nations. And Americans, he has said, often presume that what they define as good is good for everyone.</p>
        <p>''But being Serbian and European doesn't mean being anti-American,'' Mr. Kostunica said. ''I have no stereotypes and prejudices. What concerns me is state interests and policies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica, who translated the Federalist Papers into Serbo-Croatian in 1981, does see the Hague tribunal on war crimes in the former Yugoslavia as ''an instrument of American policy and not of international law.'' He criticizes the tribunal for refusing to examine possible war crimes by NATO leaders for the bombing of civilian targets here (as both Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch also believe). And he has said that he will not turn Mr. Milosevic, indicted last year for alleged war crimes in Kosovo, over to The Hague for trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica refuses to be explicit now on whether he would turn over Radovan Karadzic and Ratko Mladic, the two Bosnian Serb leaders indicted by the tribunal. They might be the price for what Mr. Kostunica wants: a re-entry into European institutions like the Council of Europe and the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, and the restoration of Yugoslavia as a respected member of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Kostunica, as in many who grew up in Tito's Yugoslavia, there seems to lurk some residue of that old country, which helped found the nonaligned movement and lived profitably between East and West.</p>
        <p>In his speech this week celebrating the victory he claims over Mr. Milosevic, Mr. Kostunica spoke of showing the world ''that we are worthy of the tremendous historic task, worthy of our ancestors, worthy of our history, that we have not been carried away by the rivers of the West or the East, that we shall let ourselves be carried by our own rivers, the Serbian and Montenegrin, that we stand responsible before the future generations.''</p>
        <p>He also speaks of the Serbian nation and of its historical tragedies, of the enormous number of Serbian refugees inside Serbia, of the need to help ''Serb brothers'' in the Bosnian Serb republic, but with the clear acknowledgment that they live in a different state, in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>And he says bluntly, ''Those who think that Serbia cannot exist as a nation without Kosovo are wrong.'' Kosovo, like Jerusalem, he said, ''is one of those problems without a solution, that must be managed,'' even if it goes against ''the American view that every problem can be solved.''</p>
        <p>A reporter for the magazine Vreme, Nenad Stefanovic, said Mr. Kostunica supported the Bosnian Serbs in the 1992-95 Bosnian war and -- like many Serbs -- backed their right to secede from a Bosnia governed by Muslims and Croats. However, Mr. Kostunica rejected the brutal expulsion and slaying of non-Serbs and never supported paramilitary troops.</p>
        <p>''He was a nationalist concerned for the fate of his nation, but never against other nations,'' Mr. Stefanovic said.</p>
        <p>A July 1998 photo of Mr. Kostunica awkwardly carrying a Kalashnikov, taken in Zubin Potok, in northern Kosovo, and published in the Belgrade daily Blic at the time, surfaced again during the election campaign. It was reprinted again this week by the Kosovo Albanian newspaper Koha Ditore. Mr. Kostunica said he went to the village, a stronghold of his party, where Serbs had formed a village watch committee to guard against attacks by the Kosovo Liberation Army, the Albanian rebel group that at the time was battling Serbian security forces. Someone handed him the gun, he said, and he was unaware of the photographer.</p>
        <p>Some of his allies now in the democratic opposition regarded Mr. Kostunica as a strange mixture of constitutional legalist, democrat and ''urban fascist'' for his fervent talk of Serbian national interests. Even now, the leader of his campaign, Zoran Djindjic of the Democratic Party, regards Mr. Kostunica's politics as traditionalist and even primitive, but without the murderous and malign nationalism manipulated by those, like Mr. Milosevic and Franjo Tudjman, the late Croatian leader,  who led Yugoslavia into disaster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica, Mr. Djindjic said, ''is a necessary bridge'' between the politics of the past and a more modern European future.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Kostunica is a strong advocate of the rule of law, of an independent judiciary, of a free press and university, and of constitutional agreements binding states.</p>
        <p>He said he hoped to lead Serbia and Yugoslavia into a new relationship with the world, a policy different from other former Communist states. Their first transitional leaders, he said, all former party apparatchiks, ''were ready to accommodate to everything asked for from abroad, especially from over the ocean, despite their own political beliefs.''</p>
        <p>Among those he criticizes for accommodation are Montenegro's president, Milo Djukanovic, the Bosnian Serb acting prime minister, Milorad Dodik, and Croatia's new president, Stjepan Mesic.</p>
        <p>But after NATO's bombing of Yugoslavia last year, he said, ''I've realized that my views can be a normal, authentic policy that suits most of the people in Serbia'' and not just the democratic opposition, from which he keeps a certain distance.</p>
        <p>''And suddenly I find this new policy of mine is respected abroad,'' he said this week, grinning -- ''by Europeans more, the Americans less, but even there with some understanding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
