<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can a Driven Baton Twirler Become Miss Congeniality?</title>
    <meta content="29BEAU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29BEAU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Driver, Minnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Field, Sally</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Beautiful (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5D71E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can a Driven Baton Twirler Become Miss Congeniality?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews Beautiful, directed by Sally Field; Minnie Driver stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Beauty may be only skin deep, but ugly is to the bone,'' the queen of the thunderously intoned wisecrack, Tallulah Bankhead, is reputed to have said on the subject of appearances. But if we are to believe ''Beautiful,'' a clumsy satire of the world of beauty pageants, most of those involved in that world are spiritually ugly to the bone.</p>
        <p>Take the movie's ruthless hard-boiled antiheroine, Mona Hibbard (Minnie Driver), a cutthroat competitor who exhibits not the tiniest stirrings of conscience or affection for any other human being until she has a sappy, unconvincing revelation near the end of the film.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Beauty may be only skin deep, but ugly is to the bone,'' the queen of the thunderously intoned wisecrack, Tallulah Bankhead, is reputed to have said on the subject of appearances. But if we are to believe ''Beautiful,'' a clumsy satire of the world of beauty pageants, most of those involved in that world are spiritually ugly to the bone.</p>
        <p>Take the movie's ruthless hard-boiled antiheroine, Mona Hibbard (Minnie Driver), a cutthroat competitor who exhibits not the tiniest stirrings of conscience or affection for any other human being until she has a sappy, unconvincing revelation near the end of the film.</p>
        <p>Typical of Mona's notorious pranks are the stunt she pulls on a contestant who has stolen her talent routine of twirling a flaming baton while singing ''A Bicycle Built for Two.'' Just before her rival goes onstage, Mona slips some glue on the baton. When the flaming instrument sticks to the hand of the panicked contestant, Mona just happens to be standing by with a fire extinguisher to save the day and further humiliate her, covering her in a thick blanket of foam.</p>
        <p>In another farcical moment Mona, who has recently been crowned Miss Illinois and is desperate for photo opportunities, rushes to the aid of a woman who has gone into labor in a supermarket. Instructing her young daughter Vanessa (Hallie Kate Eisenberg) to keep snapping pictures, she offers an impromptu serenade of ''The Wind Beneath My Wings'' before loading the poor woman onto a shopping cart and wheeling her to a  hospital while Vanessa follows dutifully snapping away.</p>
        <p>''Beautiful'' is at its most promising when it satirically scratches the eyes out of its subject, although these farcical bits are executed with a haranguing insistence that flattens much of their humor. Responsibility for the movie's relentless shrillness belongs both to Sally Field, who is making her insecure feature-film debut as a director, and to Ms. Driver, who is woefully miscast as Mona.</p>
        <p>Portraying a woman who grew up in a shack in Illinois with gross redneck caricatures for parents, Ms. Driver strives determinedly to carry off a role that at odd moments suggests a worst-nightmare parody of Kathie Lee Gifford. But the higher Mona rises on the pageant circuit, the more unbelievable her ascent becomes. For Ms. Driver, although striking looking, is simply too old for the role and utterly lacking in the sleek, airbrushed perkiness of the typical American beauty contestant. Her features are irregular, her smiles less than star bright, and the aura she exudes, even when plastering on a fake, toothy grin, can only be described as dark and heavy.</p>
        <p>The screenplay by Jon Bernstein rides on an implausible soap opera conceit more appropriate to a vintage Bette Davis weepie than to a contemporary satire. Early in her career Mona has a child who her saintly best friend, Ruby (Joey Lauren Adams), agrees to call her own. Mona, Ruby and Vanessa (who doesn't know the truth) live together until Ruby, who works as a nurse in an old-age home, is wrongfully accused of helping a patient commit suicide and thrown in jail.</p>
        <p>Suddenly Mona is forced to be a mother to the little girl who loathes her for very good reasons. She ends up taking the child with her to the finals of a Miss America-like competition in Southern California, where a vindictive, nosy television reporter (Leslie Stefanson) plans to expose her as a single mother and disqualify her from the pageant.</p>
        <p>''Beautiful'' wants to make a statement about sexism and beauty pageants with their phony humanitarianism, bogus talent shows and superficial values. But the movie is so nasty to its mostly female characters that it feels harshly misogynist. The sole angel among these screeching harpies is Ruby. And heaven knows why she puts up with Mona, who treats her like a doormat.</p>
        <p>Stylistically ''Beautiful'' teeters from a noisy sitcom (only one step removed from ''The Beverly Hillbillies'') to brickbat satire until it collapses in a pool of redemptive mush as Mona belatedly and unconvincingly discovers her maternal instinct.</p>
        <p>''Beautiful'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes profanity and off-color jokes.</p>
        <p>BEAUTIFUL  Directed by Sally Field; written by Jon Bernstein; director of photography, Robert Yeoman; edited by Debra Neil-Fischer; music by John Frizzell; production designer, Charles Breen; produced by John Bertolli and B. J. Rack; released by Destination Films. Running time: 112 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Minnie Driver (Mona), Joey Lauren Adams (Ruby), Leslie Stefanson (Joyce Parkins), Bridgette L. Wilson (Lorna Larkin), Kathleen Turner (Verna Chickle) and Hallie Kate Eisenberg (Vanessa).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
