<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore's Debate 'Advisers' Include Voices From the Campaign Trail</title>
    <meta content="29FOLK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/politics/29FOLK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FACES IN THE CROWD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sarasota (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Sarasota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DE163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore's Debate 'Advisers' Include Voices From the Campaign Trail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Gore has invited 13 'regular folks,' including 14-year-old high school freshman and 76-year-old retiree, to help him prepare for presidential debates; Gore aides say these people, all of whom Gore met in campaign appearances, will help brief him about concerns of real Americans; another purpose might be to provide fodder for newspaper and television stories in three days that Gore will be sequestered in Sarasota, Fla, for mock debates and strategy meetings; almost all of those Gore has invited come from important swing states where media is likely to compile reports about new Gore advisers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Vice President Al Gore travels to his debate preparation camp in Sarasota, Fla., on Saturday, he will be accompanied by many of the usual campaign suspects: his chairman, his media consultant and his message guru. But he will also bring along some unusual -- and unsuspecting -- advisers he picked up on the campaign trail, like Erin K. Conner, a 14-year-old freshman at Belleville West High School in Belleville, Ill., and Joyce E. Martin, a 76-year-old retiree from Clearwater, Fla.</p>
        <p>At considerable expense that some Gore aides do not even want to think about, Mr. Gore has invited 13 ''regular folks'' -- including Miss Conner's mother, who will chaperone her -- to help him prepare for one of the pivotal moments in the 2000 campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Vice President Al Gore travels to his debate preparation camp in Sarasota, Fla., on Saturday, he will be accompanied by many of the usual campaign suspects: his chairman, his media consultant and his message guru. But he will also bring along some unusual -- and unsuspecting -- advisers he picked up on the campaign trail, like Erin K. Conner, a 14-year-old freshman at Belleville West High School in Belleville, Ill., and Joyce E. Martin, a 76-year-old retiree from Clearwater, Fla.</p>
        <p>At considerable expense that some Gore aides do not even want to think about, Mr. Gore has invited 13 ''regular folks'' -- including Miss Conner's mother, who will chaperone her -- to help him prepare for one of the pivotal moments in the 2000 campaign.</p>
        <p>Gore aides say the purpose is for these people, all of whom Mr. Gore has met in campaign appearances, to help brief the vice president about the concerns of real Americans.</p>
        <p>But clearly, another purpose, or at least a consequence, is to provide fodder for newspaper and television stories in the three days that Mr. Gore will be sequestered for mock debates and strategy meetings.</p>
        <p>Not coincidentally, almost all of those Mr. Gore has invited come from important swing states where newspapers and television stations are likely to compile reports about the new Gore advisers. Three are from Michigan, two are from Illinois, and others are from Ohio, Pennsylvania, Florida, Georgia, New Mexico, Maine and Oregon. There are none from, say, Massachusetts, New York, Texas or Alabama -- states assumed to be squarely in either Mr. Gore's camp, or that of his Republican rival, Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>When the briefings and rehearsals end on Tuesday, Mr. Gore's guests are to accompany him to Boston for that night's nationally televised debate. Gore aides hope to secure tickets for the guests to sit in the debate hall, raising the prospect that Mr. Gore will allude to them during his thrust and parry with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Using audience members as props has become a regular feature of presidential debates and major speeches like the State of the Union in recent years, and Mr. Gore uses the tactic frequently. In his acceptance speech at the Democratic convention, for instance, he illustrated positions on prescription drug costs, education and a patient's bill of rights by pointing to several people who had been planted in the crowd.</p>
        <p>Expected to be among those in the debate entourage will be Winifred Skinner, a 79-year-old widow from Des Moines who has become an overnight national celebrity since an encounter with Mr. Gore on Wednesday at a forum on Medicare in Altoona, Iowa. Mrs. Skinner told Mr. Gore that she had to collect cans to make ends meet because her prescription drugs were so expensive. When Mr. Gore asked how much she raised that way, she charmed him by responding: ''You're not going to tell the government, are you?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Skinner has since been inundated by network TV reporters, making appearances this morning on NBC's ''Today'' and ABC's ''Good Morning America,'' among other shows. The Gore campaign offered to fly her to Sarasota and Boston, but she declined because she is afraid to fly. The campaign then offered to drive her to Boston. She hesitated because she did not want to leave behind her 6-year-old toy poodle, Bridget. You can bring the dog, the campaign said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Skinner said that once Bridget was accommodated -- ''she's the only family I've got'' -- she began to get excited. ''I've never been that far east,'' she said. ''And I was a debater in high school, so I love debates.'' She also said she planned to sell some cans she has accumulated for spending money on the trip. ''I'm no moocher,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The preparation sessions are to be held at the Mote Marine Laboratory, an 11-acre research and conference center where Mr. Gore also prepared for his 1996 vice-presidential debate. William M. Daley, Mr. Gore's campaign chairman and the former secretary of commerce, said today that the guests would help Mr. Gore stay focused on the debate's audience.</p>
        <p>''Candidates tend to stay fairly secluded when preparing for debates,'' he said. ''It is a rarefied atmosphere of policy briefings, debate rehearsals and briefing books. The presence of these special guests is an opportunity for us all to remember what's really important in this election.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's guests are demographically diverse. Short biographies distributed today by the Gore campaign note that Joseph Austin, a construction worker from Albuquerque, is Hispanic and Joseph Dulin, a principal from Ann Arbor, Mich., is black. Most of those invited were notified earlier this week.</p>
        <p>Several invitees, like Donald Jalbert of Lewiston, Me., and Claudia Amboyer of Shelby Township, Mich., are teachers Mr. Gore met while staying at their homes during his various campaign ''school days.'' Miss Conner caught his attention when she introduced him at an appearance at her school on Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Martin met Mr. Gore on Monday during a discussion about Medicare that preceded a speech in St. Petersburg. Her doctor had wanted to charge $450 for a recent office visit to examine an ailing wrist but accepted a $125 Medicare payment instead, she told Mr. Gore. ''If I didn't have Medicare I'd have been out of luck,'' she said today.</p>
        <p>Another guest will be an Atlanta firefighter, Matt Moseley, who is himself a bit of a celebrity since the day last year when he dangled from a helicopter to rescue a construction worker trapped by a raging fire. Mr. Gore called Mr. Moseley shortly after the rescue and then met him during a trip to Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moseley said he had been asking colleagues at his firehouse and other friends about the subjects they would like him to raise with Mr. Gore. His topics so far: prescription drug coverage, education, gun control, tax cuts and welfare reform.</p>
        <p>''It will be an honor to go,'' he said, ''and pretty reassuring that the person running to be leader of the free world would want to talk to what I would call real people in preparing for this debate.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps no one, though, was more stunned to be asked than Miss Conner, four years shy of voting age. ''I couldn't believe it,'' she said. ''But I think he knows that teenagers like myself are going to be the leaders of tomorrow and without our input we may not like the society that he forms.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FACES IN THE CROWD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
