<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the Goal Line Came To Replace the Color Line</title>
    <meta content="29TITA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29TITA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001006T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patton, Will</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Washington, Denzel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yakin, Boaz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howard, Gregory Allen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Remember the Titans (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D61E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the Goal Line Came To Replace the Color Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews Remember the Titans, movie written by Gregory Allen Howard and directed by Boaz Yakin; Denzel Washington and Will Patton star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's striking how many of the images that capture America's struggle to overcome its legacy of racism come from the world of sports. Think of Jesse Owens at the 1936 Olympics, Jackie Robinson stealing home, Arthur Ashe triumphing at Wimbledon, Tiger Woods winning his first major tournament.</p>
        <p>Whether you're black or white, these moments are likely to put a lump in your throat and inspire a justified swelling of civic pride. On the playing field, at least, our better selves can triumph over our baser instincts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's striking how many of the images that capture America's struggle to overcome its legacy of racism come from the world of sports. Think of Jesse Owens at the 1936 Olympics, Jackie Robinson stealing home, Arthur Ashe triumphing at Wimbledon, Tiger Woods winning his first major tournament.</p>
        <p>Whether you're black or white, these moments are likely to put a lump in your throat and inspire a justified swelling of civic pride. On the playing field, at least, our better selves can triumph over our baser instincts.</p>
        <p>''Remember the Titans,'' based upon a less well-known episode in the racial history of American sports -- the integration of a high school football team in Alexandria, Va., in 1971 -- does an awful lot of swelling.</p>
        <p>This is the kind of movie in which every big speech or heartfelt moment -- and aside from a handful of tense showdowns at the line of scrimmage, there's not much else to see -- is washed in on the flood tide of a thousand violins. (Trevor Rabin's score, poured over the action like ketchup, is mitigated a bit by the obligatory classic-rock song selection. It was nice to hear Leon Russell's version of ''A Hard Rain's a-Gonna Fall,'' but I think I've heard ''Spirit in the Sky'' enough for one lifetime.)</p>
        <p>''Remember the Titans'' is not a subtle picture: toward the end, a black player comes to visit his white teammate -- at first his bitter rival, now his bosom friend -- in the hospital. The nurse tries to shoo him away. ''Only kin is allowed,'' she says. ''Can't you see that's my brother?'' the bedridden warrior replies. All together now, ''He's got the whole world in his hands.''</p>
        <p>But football is not a subtle game, and if ''Remember the Titans'' is corny, it's unabashedly, even generously so. Directed by Boaz Yakin from a screenplay by Gregory Allen Howard, the film tells the true story of the T. C. Williams High School Titans in broad, accessible shorthand.</p>
        <p>Denzel Washington plays Herman Boone, who becomes the Titans' head coach by fiat of the Alexandria school board, which has also required the desegregation of Williams's team. Boone's predecessor, Bill Yoast (Will Patton), one winning season away from election to the Virginia Football Hall of Fame, swallows his pride, and brushes off the outrage of many of the town's prominent whites, to stay on as Boone's assistant.</p>
        <p>The relationship between the two men gradually mutates from hostile suspicion to grudging respect to loyalty and trust, an evolution mirrored by the players. The first, and strongest, part of the movie takes place at a preseason camp, where, under Boone's relentless drill-sergeant discipline (''This is not a democracy,'' he bellows. ''This is a dictatorship. I am the law.''), they meld into a cohesive fighting unit.</p>
        <p>Some of the scenes -- a locker-room dozens session, in which the players achieve solidarity by insulting one another's mothers -- feel a bit phony, but Mr. Yakin uses the physical intensity of the sport as a way of telegraphing the changing emotional texture of the team. Brutal tackles and errant punches have a way of turning into the hugs and handshakes of genuine camaraderie.</p>
        <p>''There's too much male bonding going on here,'' says Petey, the Titans' cocky running back (Donald Faison). Yes, indeed. Even by sports movie standards, there aren't a lot of women on the scene. Boone's wife (Nicole Ari Parker) barely speaks, and white women show up principally as opponents of the transracial bonding that comes relatively easily to the football players.</p>
        <p>Gary Bertier (Ryan Hurst), the white team captain whose initial resistance to playing alongside blacks does not survive camp, must contend with the stubborn bigotry of his mother and his girlfriend. On the first day back at school, the students are greeted by an angry white mob, including protesters carrying signs that say ''Mothers Against Busing.'' The strongest female presence is Yoast's perky, blond-ringleted daughter Sheryl (Hayden Penettier), whose passion for the sport is even more rabid than her dad's.</p>
        <p>''Remember the Titans'' was produced by Jerry Bruckheimer, whose recent pictures include action blockbusters like ''Armageddon,'' ''Bad Boys'' and ''The Rock,'' and it provides the emotional equivalent to those movies' visceral thrills. Mr. Yakin leaps from one big payoff to the next, and paints his characters in vivid, cartoonish colors. There's the fat white guy who's too goofy to be racist (Ethan Suplee); the beefy black guy who sings, jokes and dispenses inspiration (Earl C. Poitier); and the golden-haired hippie, a transplant from Southern California, with a throwing arm that's also pure gold (Kip Pardue).</p>
        <p>Happily, the younger members of the cast form a loose, funny, heartfelt ensemble; Mr. Hurst and Wood Harris, as his rival and comrade Julius Campbell, are especially fine. Mr. Washington and Mr. Patton are strong, complex enough presences to make up for the script's deficiencies.</p>
        <p>The football played by the Titans and their opponents is the old-fashioned, up-the-middle kind, yielding low final scores and bruised and muddy players. ''Remember the Titans'' is similarly solid; its satisfactions are time-tested, a little worn but nonetheless durable.</p>
        <p>The football sequences themselves are in the usual slamming, grunting Dolby, and if they don't quite shake your molars loose, the way Oliver Stone's ''Any Given Sunday'' did, you may put a hand to your chest from time to time to see if your ribs are still in place. If a heart beats inside those ribs, you'll also find a lump in your throat and an overwhelming urge to cheer.</p>
        <p>''Remember the Titans'' is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It includes some salty football-coach lingo and some rough gridiron action.</p>
        <p>REMEMBER THE TITANS  Directed by Boaz Yakin; written by Gregory Allen Howard; director of photography, Philippe Rousselot; edited by Michael Tronick; music by Trevor Rabin; production designer, Deborah Evans; produced by Jerry Bruckheimer and Chad Oman; released by Walt Disney Pictures/Jerry Bruckheimer Films. Running time: 113 minutes. This film is rated PG.</p>
        <p>WITH: Denzel Washington (Coach Boone), Will Patton (Coach Yoast), Wood Harris (Big Ju), Ryan Hurst (Gary Bertier), Donald Faison (Petey), Craig Kirkwood (Rev), Ethan Suplee (Lewis Lastik), Earl C. Poitier (Blue Stanton), Kip Pardue (Sunshine), Hayden Panettiere (Sheryl Yoast) and Nicole Ari Parker (Carol Boone).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW  Correction:  October 6, 2000, Friday  A film review in Weekend last Friday about ''Remember the Titans'' misattributed a line of dialogue spoken by a member of the Titans football team at a high school in Virginia. It is Cook (played by David Jefferson Jr.), not Petey (played by Donald Faison), who says, ''There's too much male bonding going on here.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 6, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A film review in Weekend last Friday about ''Remember the Titans'' misattributed a line of dialogue spoken by a member of the Titans football team at a high school in Virginia. It is Cook (played by David Jefferson Jr.), not Petey (played by Donald Faison), who says, ''There's too much male bonding going on here.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
