<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kazakhs' Motto: 'Fight to the End'</title>
    <meta content="29KAZA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kazakhstan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sattarkhanov, Bekzat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jumadilov, Bulat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibraimov, Yermakhan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dildabekov, Mukhtarkhan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D61E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kazakhs' Motto: 'Fight to the End'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kazakhstan boxers Bekzat Sattarkhanov, Bulat Jumadilov, Yermakhan Ibraimov and Mukhtarkhan Dildabekov have reached semifinals of Olympic tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the 1950's and 1960's, the Soviet Union sent settlers to the ''virgin lands'' of the Kazakh Soviet Socialist Republic, a landlocked area roughly four times the size of Texas just northwest of China. The newcomers, who were mostly Russians, brought with them the lessons of a centralized sports system, and in the sport of boxing, a specific technique.</p>
        <p>It was an upright, rigid style, and standoffish with an emphasis on shrewd ring maneuvers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the 1950's and 1960's, the Soviet Union sent settlers to the ''virgin lands'' of the Kazakh Soviet Socialist Republic, a landlocked area roughly four times the size of Texas just northwest of China. The newcomers, who were mostly Russians, brought with them the lessons of a centralized sports system, and in the sport of boxing, a specific technique.</p>
        <p>It was an upright, rigid style, and standoffish with an emphasis on shrewd ring maneuvers.</p>
        <p>But as Nurgali Safiullin, an Olympic boxing coach of Kazakhstan, a country formed after the breakup of the Soviet Union, said today: ''It's our thinking that battles should be won nose to nose. It's close combat. We don't like to rely on judges.</p>
        <p>''Kazakhstani people originated from a very warrior tribe, the Kipchaki. They've always been fighters. They know how to fight.''</p>
        <p>At the 2000 Sydney Games, Kazakhstan is proving its point. A nation of 14 million -- ''There used to be two million more, but a lot of Russians have gone back since the Soviet breakup,'' Safiullin said -- it has four fighters in the medal round of the boxing tournament.</p>
        <p>Or, in other terms, a country with a population approximately equal to that of Florida has as many fighters in the medal round as the United States. ''It's very exciting; our four fighters have already gotten telegrams from our president,'' Safiullin said. ''The telegram read, 'Fight to the end.' ''</p>
        <p>There is other motivation. Any Kazakh fighter winning a gold medal will get the equivalent of $100,000 from the government, Safiullin said. ''Our men will fight hard anyway,'' Safiullin said. ''It's the only way they know.''</p>
        <p>The fighters of Kazakhstan -- where 35 percent of the people live below the poverty level (about $40 a month) and the average life expectancy of males is 58 years -- fight with an uncompromising relentlessness that has made them crowd favorites at the Sydney boxing tournament.</p>
        <p>The Kazakhs fight in one direction, forward, and will walk through dozens of stiff punches to throw their own from close range. Of their four fighters competing in Friday's semifinals, the featherweight Bekzat Sattarkhanov is a student, the flyweight Bulat Jumadilov and the middleweight Yermakhan Ibraimov are police officers, and the superheavyweight Mukhtarkhan Dildabekov is in the military.</p>
        <p>While they are resolutely aggressive, the four are thinking fighters with good footwork. Their defense is solid since they hold their hands high, a technique learned under the Soviet system, Safiullin said. But they are hardly alike.</p>
        <p>Jumadilov, 27, said he liked to drive fast cars and considered Muhammad Ali his favorite athlete. In the ring, he has fast hands and scores points with punches in bunches.</p>
        <p>Asked about superstitions, Jumadilov, the flyweight world champion, answered, ''Before competitions, I don't like to talk to stupid people.''</p>
        <p>Ibraimov, 28, lists Mike Tyson as his favorite athlete because Tyson is ''a boxer who doesn't like to lose.'' Ibraimov fights as if he hates to lose, too. On Wednesday, he upset Cuba's Juan Hernandez, a reigning world champion. Ibraimov neutralized Hernandez's power and had the 31-year-old Hernandez, a three-time Olympian and silver medalist four years ago, suddenly looking very old.</p>
        <p>After his victory, Ibraimov joined the several dozen Kazakh rooters and officials in the grandstand. His countrymen took turns having their picture taken with him.</p>
        <p>''They are national heroes,'' Safiullin said through a translator. ''Our boxing program is the only national sports program that is totally supported by the government. Even during the breakup of the Soviet Union, because of our past successes the government didn't let it fall apart.''</p>
        <p>Kazakhstan has vast untapped fossil fuel resources as well as reserves of minerals and metals, but market reform has been slow and the process by which licenses are awarded to Western companies by the ruling elite is murky. Once the home of defense industries and test ranges, its radioactive and toxic chemical sites pose pollution problems. There are significant ethnic and religious differences because natives of the old Kazakh republic -- predominantly Muslim -- now outnumber the Russian immigrants when the opposite was true 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>In this context, the national boxing program flourishes, Safiullin said, with some challenges.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is ever perfect anywhere,'' he said. ''There are always some problems, but we get sponsors and things are going well.''</p>
        <p>In the boxing community, Kazakhstan's presence continues to grow with its boxing leaders serving as high-ranking members of the Amateur International Boxing Association, which governs Olympic boxing.</p>
        <p>Kazakhstan's success in Sydney has the American coach, Tom Mustin, trying to get the Kazakh fighters to come to the United States for a dual meet next year.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot to learn from them,'' Mustin said. ''They're extra strong; they know how to brawl and roughhouse. They must do neck exercises because punches don't seem to affect them.''</p>
        <p>Kazakhstan won a gold, a silver and two bronze medals at the 1996 Atlanta Games.</p>
        <p>''We want to do better this time,'' Safiullin said.</p>
        <p>Told that the United States coach wondered what exercises his team does to withstand the torrent of punches they customarily see, Safiullin laughed.</p>
        <p>''Tell him they go back centuries,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
