<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Great Dance'</title>
    <meta content="RV024416" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29GRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Damon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Craig</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Great Dance, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DC163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Great Dance'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews A Hunter's Story, documentary directed by Craig Foster and Damon Foster (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'A Hunter's Story'  Directed by Craig Foster and Damon Foster  Not rated; 90 minutes</p>
        <p>Under a blazing sun that goads the temperature to 120 degrees, the route lies across sand that sears the feet and through thorn bushes that rake the skin. The setting is the Kalahari Desert, which lies mostly in Botswana. Hour after hour, a man runs without stopping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'A Hunter's Story'  Directed by Craig Foster and Damon Foster  Not rated; 90 minutes</p>
        <p>Under a blazing sun that goads the temperature to 120 degrees, the route lies across sand that sears the feet and through thorn bushes that rake the skin. The setting is the Kalahari Desert, which lies mostly in Botswana. Hour after hour, a man runs without stopping.</p>
        <p>He runs not for a medal but for survival -- for himself, for his people. He has little water. After a year without rain, the first storm has only recently come.</p>
        <p>The runner is one of the !Xo San, a bush people whose relationship with this terrain, its animals and birds and insects, its shifting sands, its winds and the god they call Bihisabolo are elements of a 30,000-year history addressed with immense visual beauty, compassion and a sense of adventure in ''The Great Dance -- A Hunter's Story.'' (The exclamation point in !Xo San names represents a clicking sound.)</p>
        <p>The man running across the desert is one of the !Xo San hunters, a dying breed of men who can read the wind, the raindrops, the desert and its inhabitants as they seek food. And in the climactic scenes of this remarkable documentary directed by the brothers Craig and Damon Foster, the filmmakers follow a hunter named Karoha Langwane in a run to the death.</p>
        <p>By the time his race is concluded, the kudu he tracks stands exhausted, and Karoha slays it with his spears, winning food for himself and his people.</p>
        <p>Karoha and his fellow hunters, !Nqate Xqamxebe and the bow and arrow specialist Xlhoase Xlhokhne, are the focal figures of a film that reveals their remarkable skills as it displays the sere beauty of the landscape they inhabit at a time when civilization is encroaching and the survival of their immemorial way of life seems unlikely.</p>
        <p>These are men who can not only track using the most obscure of clues but also use those same clues to recreate the story of how some animal died or was killed before they came upon it.</p>
        <p>''That is what we do,'' one says of the hunting. ''That is who we are.'' And he adds: ''Tracking is like dancing. This is the great dance.''</p>
        <p>''The Great Dance'' opens today at the Cinema Village (22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village). With its scenes of hunting and slaying animals like porcupine or dining on carrion wrested from vultures, it is not a film for squeamish, well-fed people whose relationship with food is confined to freezers and shelves at the supermarket.</p>
        <p>After the film was completed, it notes without further explanation,  the individual hunting licenses of the !Xo people were revoked.</p>
        <p>In a very real way, ''The Great Dance'' constitutes an act of preservation and a requiem.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
