<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shifting Gears: 4 Cubans Battle to Finals</title>
    <meta content="29BOXI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savon, Felix</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rigondeaux, Guillermo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kendelan, Mario</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gutierrez, Jorge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2DF1F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shifting Gears: 4 Cubans Battle to Finals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuban boxers Felix Savon, Gulliermo Rigondeaux, Mario Kindelan and Jorge Gutierrez have reached finals of Olympic tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things did not start out well for the celebrated Cuban boxing team tonight when their light flyweight Maikro Romero lost a controversial decision to Brahim Asloum of France. It was the fifth consecutive defeat for a Cuban boxer in the Olympic tournament going back to Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Cuba's coach, Alcides Sagarra, who a month ago had suggested that his team would win 12 medals, waved his hands disdainfully at the judges when the Romero decision was announced, then stormed from the ring with a few angry shouts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Things did not start out well for the celebrated Cuban boxing team tonight when their light flyweight Maikro Romero lost a controversial decision to Brahim Asloum of France. It was the fifth consecutive defeat for a Cuban boxer in the Olympic tournament going back to Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Cuba's coach, Alcides Sagarra, who a month ago had suggested that his team would win 12 medals, waved his hands disdainfully at the judges when the Romero decision was announced, then stormed from the ring with a few angry shouts.</p>
        <p>But less than 30 minutes later, Sagarra was escorting his bantamweight Guillermo Rigondeaux into the same ring. Rigondeaux would dominate the American Clarence Vinson, winning easily on points, 18-6. It began a streak of four successive victories for the Cubans, the last another comfortable victory for the heavyweight Felix Savon.</p>
        <p>So the Cubans have four boxers, including the lightweight Mario Kindelan and the middleweight Jorge Gutierrez, fighting for gold medals Saturday. Diogenes Luna, a light welterweight, will try to make it five Cubans in the finals when he faces the American Ricardo Williams Jr. on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Vinson was never in tonight's fight, being beaten to the punch by Rigondeaux from early in the bout. Rigondeaux, who fights left-handed, is 4 inches taller than the 5-foot-2-inch Vinson and used his reach and footwork to ward off Vinson's advances and to score repeatedly.</p>
        <p>Tom Mustin, the United States coach, said Vinson has always had trouble against left-handed fighters. ''And this guy was strong and moved great side to side,'' Mustin said of Rigondeaux.</p>
        <p>Vinson will win a bronze medal because the losers of both semifinals are awarded bronze medals in boxing. Vinson fought with heart, as he kept trying to force the attack against Rigondeaux even though he trailed by several points. But Vinson could not routinely get close enough to his target, and Rigondeaux has a mighty left hand he knows how to use. Rigondeaux stopped Vinson for a count of 8 with one straight left hand to the face in the third round, and he knocked Vinson down a few moments later with another left.</p>
        <p>''I was a little flat today and he fought very well,'' said Vinson, who now plans to turn professional. ''He was a better fighter today. You win some; you lose some. I'll take the bitter with the sweet.''</p>
        <p>Savon advanced easily, though he didn't look sharp in his 14-8 victory on points against Germany's Sebastian Kober. Savon even briefly trailed during the fight's first round, but he rallied to build a cushy lead.</p>
        <p>Savon, 33, will be a favorite to win his third gold medal Saturday when he faces Sultanahmed Ibzagimov of Russia, who defeated Vladimir Tchantouria of Georgia. The Ibzagimov-Tchantouria bout had the Sydney crowd alternately booing and laughing, it was so comically slapstick. The two wrestled to the canvas at one point and spent four rounds wildly missing with clumsy punches.</p>
        <p>If he wins, Savon would become the second boxer to win three Olympic gold medals in one weight class, equaling his countryman Teofilo Stevenson's mark.</p>
        <p>Besides Williams, the Americans Jermain Taylor and Ricardo Juarez fight in Friday night semifinal bouts.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
