<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an Old Man's Reveries, The Past Lives On as Pain</title>
    <meta content="29FAIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29FAIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bergman, Ingmar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ullmann, Liv</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Faithless (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DF1F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an Old Man's Reveries, The Past Lives On as Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews Faithless, movie directed by Liv Ullmann from screenplay by Ingmar Bergman, and shown as part of New York Film Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here's an unsettling thought: The hardest lessons we learn in life (and maybe the only lessons we truly absorb) are those learned too late. It is precisely this sense of nagging regret and the compulsion to comb obsessively through decisions that can't be undone that haunts the characters in Liv Ullmann's morose and profound film, ''Faithless.'' For in looking back, there is usually a point at which past events lose their fluidity. That lingering question of what-if? evaporates, and the past becomes frozen, at once accessible and out of reach.</p>
        <p>Filmed by the actress and director (it's her fourth full-length feature) from a late screenplay by Ingmar Bergman, this attenuated two-and-a-half-hour reflection on marriage, adultery, parenthood and the casualties of sexual warfare unfolds like a brooding autobiographical epilogue to Mr. Bergman's much stormier 1974 masterpiece, ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' In its tone, style and message, ''Faithless'' is an old man's movie, paced at a measured hobble, its metaphysical gaze turned as much toward the sea and the sky as toward the houses on the shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here's an unsettling thought: The hardest lessons we learn in life (and maybe the only lessons we truly absorb) are those learned too late. It is precisely this sense of nagging regret and the compulsion to comb obsessively through decisions that can't be undone that haunts the characters in Liv Ullmann's morose and profound film, ''Faithless.'' For in looking back, there is usually a point at which past events lose their fluidity. That lingering question of what-if? evaporates, and the past becomes frozen, at once accessible and out of reach.</p>
        <p>Filmed by the actress and director (it's her fourth full-length feature) from a late screenplay by Ingmar Bergman, this attenuated two-and-a-half-hour reflection on marriage, adultery, parenthood and the casualties of sexual warfare unfolds like a brooding autobiographical epilogue to Mr. Bergman's much stormier 1974 masterpiece, ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' In its tone, style and message, ''Faithless'' is an old man's movie, paced at a measured hobble, its metaphysical gaze turned as much toward the sea and the sky as toward the houses on the shore.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ullmann, a colleague and collaborator of Mr. Bergman's for decades, has absorbed his sensibility and style so thoroughly that ''Faithless,'' which the New York Film Festival is showing this evening and on Monday at Alice Tully Hall, is more than just a reverent homage to the master. It feels almost like the product of artificial respiration, as if Ms. Ullmann (who starred in Mr. Bergman's ''Persona'' and ''Scenes From a Marriage'') and Mr. Bergman were breathing life into each other in long, sad exhalations.</p>
        <p>As in earlier Bergman films, the great Swedish actor Erland Josephson is a stand-in for the director. This time around, his character is a frail, aging film and theater director actually named Bergman who, while rattling around his office, conjures up the ghost of Marianne (Lena Endre), an actress he once loved who has since died and become his muse.</p>
        <p>When she appears, he coaxes her into delivering a blow-by-blow account of her love affair with her husband's best friend, David (Krister Henriksson), a director who turns out to be the old man's younger mid-40's self. As she tells the story, most of the events she recalls are remembered in extended flashbacks.</p>
        <p>There's nothing orderly or predictable about the drama in which Marianne is the prime mover and David, although the initiator of the affair, the follower. Her husband, Markus (Thomas Hanzon), a world-famous conductor, and their young daughter Isabelle (Michelle Gylemo) flit in and out as supporting players who are horribly damaged by the affair. As the story unfolds, you expect it to fade out, but it takes several surprising turns as hidden facts come to light.</p>
        <p>Unlike most tales of adultery, ''Faithless'' is an emotional mystery story that never solves (or even tries to solve) an essential puzzle. Why would a happily married woman jeopardize a successful marriage by having an affair with her husband's poorer, less attractive and admittedly unhappy best friend? For David, to put it bluntly, is no catch. As he warns at the outset of their affair, he is self-loathing, joyless and pathologically jealous. In one of the film's ugliest scenes, he coaxes Marianne into revealing the details of her past sexual adventures, then explodes with violent jealousy when she's finished.</p>
        <p>''Faithless'' offers few if any psychological or sexual clues to explain Marianne's faithlessness. She professes to have a great sex life with Markus, yet she still gives in to David's casual suggestion that they sleep together. Is it just curiosity? Altruism? When Marianne has an opportunity to end this rocky affair before the roof falls in, she chooses not to. The movie suggests that major life decisions that can have the most earthshaking, tragic consequences may ultimately come down to whims.</p>
        <p>The mystery is deepened by the film's extraordinary central performances. With his alarmed watery eyes gazing beseechingly into the void, Mr. Josephson's Bergman is an unforgettable portrait of the artist as an old man at once tormented by his past and unable to resist raking over its coals. If he has acquired a certain wisdom and humility late in life, they have arrived too late to do him any good, which only adds salt to his wounds.</p>
        <p>The only word to describe David, Mr. Bergman's self-portrait of his younger self, is unsparing. In every shot, Mr. Henriksson palpably registers David's inner suffering, as if beneath a surface joviality he were wincing through his life. Most complicated of all is Ms. Endre's Marianne, a woman who usually knows exactly what she's feeling but who has no understanding of the forces determining her behavior. She has the paradoxical quality of having a conscience but hardly any capacity for self-examination. In the end, you begin to wonder if this is Mr. Bergman's view of the opposite sex.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ullmann has filled the movie with references to earlier Bergman films, especially those in which she appeared. The mirror images of characters confronting one another echo ''Persona,'' while the couple's erupting domestic battles recall ''Scenes From a Marriage.''</p>
        <p>The very solemnity of ''Faithless'' reminds us that the institution of marriage isn't the awesome edifice it used to be, that our expectations of coupling ''till death do us part'' aren't as absolute and fearsome as they were in the 1950's and 60's when Mr. Bergman was at his creative peak. As excruciatingly painful as it is, sexual betrayal in marriage nowadays is less likely to be the life-or-death, kill-or-be-killed emotional battle that it is for these characters. The dam of all-powerful monogamy and the commitments it entails has been seriously breached.</p>
        <p>FAITHLESS  Directed by Liv Ullmann; written (in Swedish, with English subtitles) by Ingmar Bergman; director of photography, Jorgen Persson; edited by Sylvia Ingemarsson; art director, Goran Wassberg; produced by Kaj Larsen; released by Samuel Goldwyn Films/ Fireworks Pictures. Running time: 155 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown tonight at 6 and Monday at 8:30 p.m. at Alice Tully Hall as part of the 38th New York Film Festival.</p>
        <p>WITH: Therese Brunnander (Petra Holst), Juni Dahr (Margareta), Stina Ekblad (Eva), Lena Endre (Marianne), Bjorn Granath (Gustav), Michelle Gylemo (Isabelle), Thomas Hanzon (Markus), Krister Henriksson (David), Erland Josephson (Bergman), Johan Rabaeus (Johan), Marie Richardson (Anna Berg), Gertrud Stenung (Martha), Jan-Olof Strandberg (Axel) and Philip Zanden (Martin Goldman).</p>
        <p>FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
