<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Say State Takeover May Be Just What Nassau Needs</title>
    <meta content="29NASS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/nyregion/29NASS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DF163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Say State Takeover May Be Just What Nassau Needs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some politicians argue that Nassau County needs a state takeover of its finances; county officials, as they struggle to bring county back from edge of bankruptcy, are working under supervision of Nassau Interim Finance Authority, state-appointed oversight board that has power--if county fails--to seize control of Nassau's day-to-day operations; everyone involved in talks, including state board, is bent on preventing that (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a county with more than its share of fiscal nightmares, it is what politicians in both parties fear the most. Yet others say it is exactly what Nassau County needs: a state takeover of the county's finances.</p>
        <p>As they struggle to bring the county back from the edge of bankruptcy, county officials are working under the supervision of the Nassau Interim Finance Authority, a state-appointed oversight board that has the power -- if the county fails -- to seize control of Nassau's day-to-day operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a county with more than its share of fiscal nightmares, it is what politicians in both parties fear the most. Yet others say it is exactly what Nassau County needs: a state takeover of the county's finances.</p>
        <p>As they struggle to bring the county back from the edge of bankruptcy, county officials are working under the supervision of the Nassau Interim Finance Authority, a state-appointed oversight board that has the power -- if the county fails -- to seize control of Nassau's day-to-day operations.</p>
        <p>Everyone involved in the talks, including the state board, is bent on preventing that. A takeover would strip local officials of their authority to spend and borrow money. The state board could unilaterally cut spending, withhold state aid and freeze the wages of county employees -- without having to answer to voters.</p>
        <p>''This is bad for everybody,'' said Lisanne G. Altmann, a Democrat and the chairwoman of the County Legislature's budget committee. ''We lose. The constituents lose. I mean, there is almost no reason to come to work.''</p>
        <p>But there would be some winners -- at the very least, the bankers, bondholders and others in the financial community who earn a living off the county and would benefit from the strict budgetary discipline a control board would impose.</p>
        <p>And many say the biggest beneficiaries would be the people of Nassau County, because a takeover would accomplish what politicians have long been unable or unwilling to do themselves: cut spending and raise revenues enough to balance the budget and erase a $143 million deficit next year.</p>
        <p>''The control board is less politically reluctant to implement the kinds of things that need to be put in place,'' said Steven J. Murphy, managing director of state and local government ratings at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy speaks from experience. An analyst of Nassau County's finances, he studied the fiscal collapses of Troy and Utica, N.Y., and Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>In the annals of municipal financial mayhem, Nassau will go down with those cities, as well as with New York City in the 1970's, as examples of how runaway labor costs and lavish services became too expensive, Mr. Murphy said. A sure way to stop the slide, say many of those who endured financial takeovers in other places, is to surrender fully to outside control.</p>
        <p>''It was helpful to have the control board there,'' said Mark P. Pattison, the Democratic mayor of Troy, who steered that upstate city through its recent fiscal storm and won a second term. ''In the past, keeping the municipal unions happy and not raising taxes was the recipe for getting re-elected. I was going to hold down raises. The board reinforced my stance.''</p>
        <p>In otherwise wealthy Nassau County, however, local officials staunchly oppose a state takeover -- even though by doing so,  they are setting themselves an unappetizing task: untangling a fiscal routine in which taxpayers have supported a highly paid police force, pristine parks and numerous patronage jobs that helped push the county into financial crisis.</p>
        <p>It did not help, budget analysts say, that Thomas S. Gulotta, the three-term Republican county executive, resisted raising property taxes for the general fund. Last November, angry voters took revenge at the polls for what many called gross mismanagement. They elected the first Democratic-controlled County Legislature since 1917, routing the county's nationally renowned Republican political machine.</p>
        <p>Now, less than a year later, this county so used to iron rule faces a different kind of control.</p>
        <p>Under the state law that created it in June, the oversight board would still have to consult with local officials if it moved to control Nassau's finances. But it would have sweeping powers.</p>
        <p>The seven-member board would be able to approve or reject any outside contracts or obligations, essentially hiring as it saw fit. It would control all borrowing, for long-term projects like a road or bridge and short-term needs like filling a payroll gap to keep the government running or financing retroactive pay raises for county police officers.</p>
        <p>The board would be able to withhold or dispense $105 million in transitional state aid that has been promised to the county by Gov. George E. Pataki if it gets its fiscal house in order and cuts costs. And most significantly, the board would have the power to freeze or suspend future pay raises granted to county union workers through a collective bargaining agreement or an arbitrator's award.</p>
        <p>The law also spells out various ways the county could trigger a state takeover -- chiefly, by not convincing the board that its budgets for the next four years are sound. On Monday, the state board will comment publicly on a four-year proposal by Mr. Gulotta; the Legislature must approve a plan by Oct. 30, though the board would like one sooner. The board could then send that plan back to the county for modification, then would approve or reject it.</p>
        <p>Most county officials say they do not expect a takeover, but they are preparing themselves for the possibility.</p>
        <p>''When I think, 'What if,' it is extremely disturbing,'' said Judith A. Jacobs, a Democrat and the presiding officer of the County Legislature.</p>
        <p>All three leaders in the bitterly divided county government -- Ms. Jacobs, Mr. Gulotta and Peter J. Schmitt, the Republican minority leader -- have vowed to keep a control board from wresting power.</p>
        <p>''There is no winner if there is a control board,'' Mr. Schmitt said.</p>
        <p>Some said the biggest losers would  be those most reliant on government aid.</p>
        <p>''Bus service and programs for the handicapped and people with drinking problems and programs for keeping kids out of trouble -- they could take a meat cleaver and cut them all out,'' said Neal M. Lewis, the executive director of the Long Island Neighborhood Network, a civic group.</p>
        <p>In Orange County, Calif., local officials maintained fiscal control after that wealthy county lost more than $2 billion in a risky investment scheme and declared bankruptcy in December 1994. William J. Popejoy, the former chief executive of the county who was appointed to help solve the crisis, said the arrangement allowed county residents to have a hand in their own destiny.</p>
        <p>Still, others insist that a state takeover may be the only solution in Nassau. And as the county's problems mount, officials, political strategists and others involved in county government have privately admitted that a control board could at least provide the kind of political cover necessary to make some very tough decisions.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that the service-demanding public would be losers at all,'' said Raymond D. Horton, a Columbia University Business School professor, who was the executive director of the temporary commission on city finances during New York City's fiscal mess.</p>
        <p>''Basically, it looks like the political system is weighed down by a lot of inertia, whether it is run by the Republicans or the Democrats,'' Mr. Horton said, ''and something has got to jolt them out of their dream-walk. A control board could do that.''</p>
        <p>One almost certain loser in a state takeover would be the county police department. In Troy, Mayor Pattison said, police officers received no raise in the first year of control by a state board headed by H. Carl McCall, the state comptroller.</p>
        <p>Nassau police spending, which makes up 23 percent of the total county budget, has risen more than 60 percent in the last decade. Salaries and fringe benefits for members of the department -- who earn $114,000 a year on average -- make up almost 90 percent of the more than $500 million police budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta has negotiated new contract proposals with two police unions that would raise pay 22 percent for officers and detectives over the next five years, but they are expected to be rejected by the Legislature. In those agreements, the unions made $35 million in concessions, but reserved the right to withdraw them if the state board takes control.</p>
        <p>Gary DelaRaba, the president of the 2,100-member Police Benevolent Association, said he was hopeful that there would be no takeover. But if it does happen, he said, officers would not strike.</p>
        <p>Ms. Altmann, the chairwoman of the Legislature's budget committee,  said she was saddened by the prospect of a takeover. She said it bothered her that the county never raised taxes incrementally over the years  to stave off so drastic a remedy.</p>
        <p>''It reminds me of 'The Wizard of Oz,' '' Ms Altmann said. ''At the end, Dorothy figures she could have clicked those red slippers and gone home. We have all been wearing the red slippers. We could have clicked our heels three times and we would have straightened this mess out a long time ago.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
