<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clash Over Religion and Rules Sidelines Soccer Players, but Keeps the Lawyers Busy</title>
    <meta content="29SOCC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/nyregion/29SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rosh Ha-Shanah</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rosh Hashana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rosh Hashana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DF163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clash Over Religion and Rules Sidelines Soccer Players, but Keeps the Lawyers Busy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>AVON, Conn., Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Conflict involving 10-year-old soccer players arises in Connecticut after parents of seven of Avon Soccer Club's starting players would not allow them to play Saturday, Sept 30, during Rosh Hashana, Jewish New Year; Avon club was scheduled to play Fairfield United in Connecticut state soccer tournament; controversy reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 10-year-old boys of the Avon Soccer Club will not be playing the lads of Fairfield United in the Connecticut state soccer tournament this Saturday. Whether this is due to religious intolerance, as Avon's coach believes, or the inability of some suburban parents to follow the rules, as the Fairfield coach thinks, is for the lawyers to decide.</p>
        <p>The conflict between the two teams arose this week after it became known that the parents of 7 of the Avon squad's 11 starting players would not allow them to play Saturday, during Rosh Hashana, the Jewish New Year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 10-year-old boys of the Avon Soccer Club will not be playing the lads of Fairfield United in the Connecticut state soccer tournament this Saturday. Whether this is due to religious intolerance, as Avon's coach believes, or the inability of some suburban parents to follow the rules, as the Fairfield coach thinks, is for the lawyers to decide.</p>
        <p>The conflict between the two teams arose this week after it became known that the parents of 7 of the Avon squad's 11 starting players would not allow them to play Saturday, during Rosh Hashana, the Jewish New Year.</p>
        <p>But Fairfield's coach, Donald F. Houston, a Bridgeport labor lawyer, refused to let his team play Avon's before Saturday, saying that an earlier date would not be fair. And league rules do not allow the game to be played later. If Avon's players do not show up Saturday, Fairfield will automatically win and advance in the tournament.</p>
        <p>''For me to reschedule the game before Saturday would mean that I couldn't have all my players,'' Mr. Houston said today, citing injuries to two of his starters, including his son. ''I didn't see why I had to disadvantage my team to play his team.''</p>
        <p>Avon's coach, Len Goldberg, accused Mr. Houston of ''hiding behind the rules'' and imposing his will on both teams' players. ''This is a case where someone wants to win a game at all costs, no matter what,'' Mr. Goldberg said bitterly.</p>
        <p>Since both teams won the tournament's first-round games last Saturday, Mr. Houston and Mr. Goldberg have acknowledged having two unpleasant phone conversations with each other, including one Tuesday evening that was mediated by an official with the Connecticut Junior Soccer Association, to no avail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houston said he learned of the scheduling problem only after he called Mr. Goldberg on Sunday. Even without its 7 Jewish players, he added, Avon would still have 10 players, enough to field a team, albeit one without substitutes. He refused to call the disagreement a religious matter. ''I see it as a soccer scheduling issue only.''</p>
        <p>Some soccer association officials agreed, saying Jewish holidays are one of many types of obstacles to building a coherent game schedule for thousands of young players.</p>
        <p>''There's tons of conflicts, not just religious holidays. Boy Scout outings, school outings, all kinds of things,'' said Richard Nelson, an association representative in the southwest district, which includes Fairfield. ''It's certainly not a religious issue.''</p>
        <p>Last spring, he noted, a team had to play even though some of its players were absent because of a school outing.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Goldberg pointed out that coaches of other teams with Jewish players agreed this week to play games ahead of schedule. Two teams, from Farmington and Simsbury, both of which have several Jewish boys on their rosters, will also forfeit this Saturday's games, Mr. Goldberg said.</p>
        <p>This being western Connecticut, there are plenty of lawyers already involved, including at least one Avon soccer mom and the majority leader of the State Senate, George C. Jepsen.</p>
        <p>Ted Rozsa, another soccer association official, said the coaches were partly to blame for the conflict. ''Obviously the chemistry between these two people is not working well,'' Mr. Rozsa said. ''As a consequence of this, there won't even be a game.''</p>
        <p>The soccer imbroglio caught the attention of Mr. Jepsen, the second-highest-ranking Democrat in the Senate, who learned of it Wednesday night through Rachel Rubin, a lawyer with the State Ethics Commission. Her son Andrew, 10, plays for Avon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jepsen said, ''I think the non-Jewish kids on the Avon team who chose not to play without their teammates are showing a lot more character than the Fairfield coach.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Goldberg told his players' parents of the impasse, they unanimously agreed to boycott Saturday's game rather than give in to Mr. Houston.</p>
        <p>''I just think it's sad that because of the High Holidays, the other coach isn't willing to discuss changing the date of the game,'' Ms. Rubin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Houston said he did not intend to drag his players' parents into the disagreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
