<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="29MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/nyregion/29MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DC163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DEAD FETUS FOUND AT N.Y.U.  A late-term fetus was found dead Wednesday in the closet of a New York University dormitory room, the police said. The authorities said the mother, a student, had apparently had a miscarriage, wrapped the remains in a blanket and kept them in her room for about three weeks. The mother reported the miscarriage to a university official, the authorities said. A spokesman for the city medical examiner said more tests were planned to determine whether the fetus was alive. The mother was not charged, although the police said the investigation remained open.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DEAD FETUS FOUND AT N.Y.U.  A late-term fetus was found dead Wednesday in the closet of a New York University dormitory room, the police said. The authorities said the mother, a student, had apparently had a miscarriage, wrapped the remains in a blanket and kept them in her room for about three weeks. The mother reported the miscarriage to a university official, the authorities said. A spokesman for the city medical examiner said more tests were planned to determine whether the fetus was alive. The mother was not charged, although the police said the investigation remained open.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: LENNON KILLER UP FOR PAROLE  The chairman of the State Senate Corrections Committee yesterday urged that parole be denied next week to the killer of John Lennon.  The chairman, Senator Michael F. Nozzolio,  said the slaying of Lennon in 1980 by Mark David Chapman, above,  was ''one of the most senseless acts of violence in New York State history.'' Mr. Chapman, 45, is serving a 20-year-to-life sentence at Attica state prison for the killing.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: JACKSON CRITICIZES POLICE  he Rev. Jesse Jackson criticized the Police Department yesterday for lowering admission standards for some of the Police Academy's recruits. Appearing at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice, Mr. Jackson said the ''bar of justice must remain high -- academically, morally and emotionally.'' He added, ''One does not have to dumb down recruits to make better police.'' On Wednesday, the Police Department removed a requirement that recruits have 60 college credits for any applicant with at least two years as a city traffic or school security agent, saying the change would expand the number of minority applicants.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CON ED ORDERED TO PAY IN SUIT  A Manhattan jury yesterday ordered Consolidated Edison to pay $1.9 million to a former schoolteacher who suffered brain damage after he received a severe electrical shock while using a public telephone. The former teacher, Philip Vanaria, 48, said he also sustained crippling physical injuries from the shock while using a telephone in 1997 in Greenwich Village. Mr. Vanaria's lawyer, Barton Slavin, said Con Ed was negligent in the way it installed a water pump in a high- voltage vault under the sidewalk where the pay phone stood. A Con Ed spokesman, Joseph Petta, said defects in the vault where Mr. Vanaria had been injured were corrected immediately, but the utility admitted that its negligence had caused Mr. Vanaria's injuries.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: EX-KOCH AIDE ACQUITTED  A former New York City health official and top mayoral aide to Edward I. Koch was acquitted yesterday of charges that he had detonated stink bombs on two Trans World Airlines flights. The former official, Victor E. Botnick, was on trial in Federal District Court in Brooklyn on charges of setting off the stink bombs in August 1998 while flying to and from Paris. The government had alleged that Mr. Botnick became angry after the airline inadvertently canceled his family's reservations on a flight to Israel to celebrate his son's bar mitzvah in December 1997.</p>
        <p>Alan Feuer (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BUS ACCIDENT KILLS PEDESTRIAN  A Greyhound bus struck and killed a pedestrian on West 30th Street last night, the police said. The bus was eastbound on West 30th Street between 10th and 11th Avenues at 7:20 p.m. when it hit the man, who was in his 40's, said Officer Gary Cillo, a police spokesman. The man was carrying no identification and his name was still not known late last night, the police said. He was declared dead at the scene. The driver of the bus did not receive a summons for the accident, Officer Cillo said.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>OLD WESTBURY: NEW HEAD OF COLLEGE  Edward Guiliano, 50, has been inaugurated as the new president of New York Institute of Technology in Old Westbury. He is the school's former provost and vice president for academic affairs, and has been at the institute for more than 25 years. He succeeds Matthew Schure, who became president of the Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine.</p>
        <p>Tina Kelley (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: POLICE CHIEF FINALISTS  The city has announced five finalists, including two Texas police chiefs, to fill Hartford's position of chief of police, which has been open for a year and a half. They are John E. Gavrilis, of the criminal investigation bureau of the Baltimore Police Department; Melbourne E. Gorris, the police chief in Port Arthur, Tex.; Arthur J. Kelly III, the police chief in New Bedford, Mass.; Thomas R. Maltese, the director of police and public safety in North Brunswick, N.J.; and Bruce Preston Marquis, the police chief in the Houston Independent School District. The city manager, Saundra Kee Borges, is expected to interview each man and make a job offer before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Paul Zielbauer (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>RIVERSIDE: FREE BRIDGE AVAILABLE  New Jersey Transit cannot give a bridge away, at least not yet. The 150-foot Roncocas Creek Bridge, which has linked Riverside and Delanco since 1905, is to be removed when a new bridge is built for a light rail line, said Charles Ingoglia, a spokesman for the agency. Federal guidelines require that the steel bridge, which is considered historic, be donated to an organization that will preserve it, but so far no group has volunteered.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR  Today</p>
        <p>TOXIC CLEANUP BEGINS  The New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection begins the second phase of the cleanup of the Ellis Site in Evesham Township, near Camden. The site was identified in 1983 as a repository of PCB's, lead and other potentially toxic substances. Soil has been removed and a system to pump up and filter contaminated ground water will be installed.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>RENT PROTEST PLANNED  The Metropolitan Council on Housing, a New York tenants' rights group, plans a sleep-in protest at 6 p.m. at City Hall to protest rent increases for rent-stabilized housing that take effect today and to call for reform of the Rent Guidelines Board.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
