<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everything's New but the Mountains and the Sea</title>
    <meta content="29VANC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE ROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vancouver (British Columbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/British Columbia/Vancouver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/British Columbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D91E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everything's New but the Mountains and the Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple Jr On the Road article on Vancouver; explores delights of clean leafy city with tang of the sea, glorious setting, temperate climate, very little crime, and cosmopolitan pleasures of food and art; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conspire to arrive by ship. Like Naples, like New York and Cape Town, Vancouver looks its best from the water, its shiny glass towers rising like Xanadu against a backdrop of indigo peaks whose foothills dip their toes in the harbor.</p>
        <p>Jan Morris, who has seen a city or two in her day, wrote that Vancouver's setting, at the southwest corner of Canada, ''is better than San Francisco's, because of the greenness, better than Sydney's, because of the mountains all around, rivaled perhaps only by Rio and Hong Kong.'' More than 40,000 newcomers take up residence each year, and the Vancouver metropolitan area now boasts a population of more than two million, third largest in Canada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Conspire to arrive by ship. Like Naples, like New York and Cape Town, Vancouver looks its best from the water, its shiny glass towers rising like Xanadu against a backdrop of indigo peaks whose foothills dip their toes in the harbor.</p>
        <p>Jan Morris, who has seen a city or two in her day, wrote that Vancouver's setting, at the southwest corner of Canada, ''is better than San Francisco's, because of the greenness, better than Sydney's, because of the mountains all around, rivaled perhaps only by Rio and Hong Kong.'' More than 40,000 newcomers take up residence each year, and the Vancouver metropolitan area now boasts a population of more than two million, third largest in Canada.</p>
        <p>Clean and leafy, blessed with a temperate climate marred only by rainy winters, a model of municipal etiquette, Vancouver seems to have it all. It is relatively crime-free; Vicky Gabereau, the host of a nationally televised talk show originating here, said proudly, ''There's no place in town I wouldn't walk, day or night, unless I was wearing a big diamond ring or planning to take my shirt off.''</p>
        <p>Geographically Vancouver may be isolated, but it is nevertheless as cosmopolitan a city as any boulevardier could hope for. A friend of mine who lives in Seattle, three hours south of here, remarked that this city ''has a sexy beat, a kind of skirt-swinging glamour'' that she finds missing from her hometown.</p>
        <p>''Everyone wants to live here,'' said Mike Harcourt, a former mayor and provincial premier, and he may be right. The local papers carried an article recently disclosing that Lloyd Axworthy, Canada's foreign minister, planned to quit politics to run a think tank at the University of British Columbia.</p>
        <p>John Nichol, a onetime senator in Ottawa, said he missed ''the tang of the sea in my nostrils, the sense that everything beyond is Asia'' when he left Vancouver. The city's other special quality, he added, is its newness. ''Everyone in Vancouver is just out of the bush, or almost,'' he said. ''There was nothing here, nothing at all to speak of, just 80 or 90 years ago.''</p>
        <p>If Canada as a whole lives a calmer life than the United States -- Kim Campbell, a former prime minister, once famously described her countrymen as ''decaffeinated Americans'' -- people in Vancouver are even more laid-back. In summer the workweek tends to start about noon on Mondays and end about noon on Fridays. Canadians who live elsewhere call this region Lotusland.</p>
        <p>That implies, of course, a degree of disengagement from the serious business of life, and it is true that Vancouver is full of distractions: sailing in the sheltered waters that stretch from here to Vancouver Island, skiing in Whistler, just 75 miles up the Sea-to-Sky Highway, or simply gazing at the magnificent panoramas outside one's office or apartment window. No point in fighting all that, so in summer performing-arts groups move outdoors, offering Shakespeare in a waterside park and Mozart in the Coast Mountains.</p>
        <p>''Even loyalty to our professional teams can be fleeting,'' a rabid local sports fan said, and that may be one big reason the local heroes don't fare better. In Vancouver participating in sports trumps watching them.</p>
        <p>The Vancouver Canucks have never won hockey's Stanley Cup, Canada's big prize. But the Canucks have one distinction: they sell not only hamburgers and hot dogs at their games but sushi, too. Waves of immigrants from Japan, India, Vietnam and especially Hong Kong have given the city an Asian flavor.</p>
        <p>It has three Chinese-language daily papers and a Chinese-language radio station. It eats dim sum -- excellent dim sum -- the way New York eats corned beef. Exotic fruits like mangosteen, longan and rambutan, rare or unavailable in the United States, are sold by every greengrocer in town. By some estimates almost a third of the city's population has its roots in Asia, and more than half the city's schoolchildren speak English as a second language.</p>
        <p>An Urban Forest</p>
        <p>Downtown Vancouver is situated on a thumb-shaped peninsula, with water on three sides -- Burrard Inlet, which forms the harbor; English Bay; and False Creek, which is neither false nor a creek. (It's another inlet.) At the peninsula's tip is one of the city's most remarkable features, Stanley Park, a 1,000-acre reserve, much of it dense, natural forest, only a 15-minute walk from the heart of downtown. Vancouver folk defend it as fiercely as New Yorkers defend Central Park, resisting any incursion into their ''wilderness.''</p>
        <p>Astonishingly, the park is only slightly younger than Vancouver itself. As they began rebuilding after a disastrous fire in 1886, the city fathers persuaded Ottawa to give them the land, once a military reservation, for an urban oasis.</p>
        <p>If you want to see how the city lives, join the crowds who visit the park on weekends. Amid bronze-leaved Japanese maples and ancient cedars whose corded trunks reach straight and tall to the sky, Mr. and Mrs. Vancouver and their kids throng Stanley Park on foot, in horse-drawn carriages, on bicycles, on in-line skates.</p>
        <p>Waiting there for them are rugby fields, a cricket pitch, tennis courts, three beaches, a pool, a lake, a lagoon, a restaurant, a fish-and-chips stand, a pitch-and-putt golf course, angling piers, yacht basins, a rowing club, a lawn-bowling club, an aquarium with 8,000 marine creatures, a zoo, cormorants and seals posing on the rocks at low tide, and not a scrap of litter. You'll find plenty of that in the tacky Gastown area downtown, along with T-shirt shops and mediocre restaurants, if you're misguided enough to go there.</p>
        <p>Don't. Stay instead in Stanley Park, and drink in the matchless panoramas of sea and sky surrounding you. I'll bet you find it hard not to gush. My wife, Betsey, noticed the motto on the license plate of a parked car. ''Beautiful British Columbia,'' it said. ''They don't lie,'' Betsey said.</p>
        <p>Tranquil Loveliness</p>
        <p>After Stanley Park head to Chinatown. Actually, Vancouver's Chinese population has grown so much that it now fills four Chinatowns; you want to visit the original one, which stretches along Pender Street. One building there bears the date 1889. But Nathan Fong, a writer and food stylist who walked through the crowded street markets with us -- pointing out unfamiliar items like whole lotus roots, and one or two that even he did not recognize, like a globular fruit called santol -- said that things had changed drastically.</p>
        <p>''When I used to walk here with my parents and grandparents about 25 years ago,'' he said, ''we always saw people we knew. But not anymore.''</p>
        <p>The neighborhood beauty spot is Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Classical Garden and the adjacent park, which reproduce exactly the tranquil loveliness of the famous gardens of Suzhou in China. Rugged objects (weirdly weathered limestone rocks) are contrasted with gentler ones (waterlilies). Contorted miniature pines line pebble walkways. Thousands of crates of building materials were shipped from China to ensure authenticity, and no nails, screws or power equipment were used.</p>
        <p>Near Main and Pender, the Times Square of Chinatown, there are dozens of restaurants. Small shops like Dollar Meat that sell uncooked as well as barbecued ducks and lamb reminded me of similar places in Causeway Bay, Hong Kong, except that these are spotlessly clean: no flies, no dogs. Other stores sell dried fish like pomfret, dried mushrooms and other wrinkly things.</p>
        <p>Quails filled the window of one poultry dealer. A single farmer in the Fraser Valley south of Vancouver, Mr. Fong told us, raises 25,000 quails a week, mostly for Chinese gourmands in the Vancouver area.</p>
        <p>The great surge in Chinese immigration was caused by political uncertainty in Hong Kong in the 1980's and early 90's. Some wealthy Chinese hedged their bets, staying on in Hong Kong and building two or three houses in Vancouver as investments (and possible future refuges). But the successful hand-over of the former British colony to Beijing calmed a lot of nerves and kept many Chinese at home. Vancouver people no longer talk quite so much about Hong Kouver.</p>
        <p>Vancouver is named for Capt. George Vancouver of the British Navy, who explored Burrard Inlet in 1792. But it was the coming of the Canadian Pacific Railway, which decided in 1884 to make this its transcontinental terminus, that ensured the city's future. Shipping is a major business here; looking across to Asia, Vancouver is Canada's principal port. Timber from the heavily wooded hinterland has been a major business from the earliest days.</p>
        <p>New lines of work have developed in recent decades. Tourism is one, stimulated by Vancouver's beauty, the quality of its food (especially in the Asian restaurants, which may be unmatched in North America) and its convenience as a jumping-off place for Alaskan tours. Environmental research, software and other technologically based companies also generate thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>Creativity at Work</p>
        <p>On Granville Island in the center of the city you can see the creativity of Vancouver at work. A group of shabby warehouses and derelict factories has been converted into studios for glass blowers, potters, weavers, quilters and the like; only the best, chosen by a jury, are granted space. A rope factory nearby has been transformed into a public market selling everything from classic French stocks to Korean sweet-potato noodles to dolmas to fish, fish, fish and more fish. The island has quickly become one of the city's favorite places.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more surprisingly, Vancouver has become a film capital. Hollywood producers and homegrown auteurs as well have made movies a billion-dollar-a-year business in Vancouver, and the long white trailers of the crews are a familiar sight on local streets. Robert Altman was one of the first directors to discover the low costs, high skills and photogenic land- and cityscapes hereabouts; he made ''McCabe and Mrs. Miller'' here in 1970, and dozens of other films have followed. Recently much of ''The X-Files'' was filmed here.</p>
        <p>Not all of the traffic as been one-way; the actors Michael J. Fox and Jason Priestley, to name just two, are local boys who migrated south.</p>
        <p>Hipsters' Hangout</p>
        <p>''In Canada when you don't fit in where you grew up, you come to Vancouver,'' said Tom Rowe, one of the partners in the film-producing Sextant Entertainment Group. ''There is tolerance and freedom here, which has an impact in the film business and other things.''</p>
        <p>Like writing. Douglas Coupland, a local novelist, coined the expression ''Generation X'' in his 1991 novel of that name, and William Gibson, who lives here, too, gave the word ''cyberspace'' to the language in his 1982 short story ''Burning Chrome.'' W. P. Kinsella wrote a novel, ''Shoeless Joe,'' about that game they play across the border; it became the film ''Field of Dreams.''</p>
        <p>And like the counterculture. Vancouver was full of hippies 40 years ago, and there are still quite a few around. You see more sandals here, summer and winter, than you do in most cities. Sophie's Cosmic Cafe in Kitsilano is a reminder that that now-gentrified area was once the hipsters' hangout. There is also weed, known here as ''B. C. Bud.''  Marijuana-growing and marijuana-smoking are widespread. Last May hundreds of people gathered for a ''smoke-in'' on the steps of the Vancouver Art Gallery. The police ignored them, and support is growing for legalization among politicians and newspaper columnists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harcourt, the former mayor, has been wrestling since he was a long-haired storefront lawyer in the 1960's with what he called ''our major challenge: how to handle the inevitable growth without losing the city's soul.''</p>
        <p>Having helped to block the building of a proposed waterfront freeway, as well as the bulldozing of old, characterful neighborhoods, Mr. Harcourt became an apostle of rapid transit, green zones and wilderness reserves to limit the paving-over of farmland. One consequence has been increasing urban density, typified by a forest of steel-and-glass skyscraper apartment blocks along False Creek in central Vancouver.</p>
        <p>But congestion, especially traffic congestion, remains a problem, and now officials here and across the border are working on a comprehensive growth-control strategy for the basin stretching hundreds of miles from here to Olympia, Wash.</p>
        <p>Arthur C. Erickson is Vancouver's big architectural kahuna, one of a triad of Canadian stars, along with Israeli-born Moishe Safdie (designer of Vancouver's elliptical, technologically advanced, hugely popular new library, which draws 8,000 visitors a day), and Frank O. Gehry, whose worldwide practice is based in California. An apostle of Le Corbusier, Mr. Erickson designed the Canadian Embassy on Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, near the Capitol.</p>
        <p>For his hometown Mr. Erickson, 76, has produced a Sikh temple, several office buildings, most of Simon Fraser University in nearby Burnaby and Robson Square, the focal point of downtown Vancouver. There he reworked an old courthouse, now the Vancouver Art Gallery, which augments its small collection of modern Canadian art with traveling shows, and created a three-block-long mall. Ferragamo, Vuitton, Dunhill and other chic-eries cluster around it.</p>
        <p>Justice for All</p>
        <p>At the far end of the mall, Mr. Erickson placed the Law Courts, one of his key works. Conceived as the antithesis of traditional court buildings, which are often dark and forbidding, it is dominated by a vast, airy, welcoming atrium, which is covered by a sloping glass-and-tubular-steel roof and heavily planted with vines and shrubs. Justice, it says, is available to all.</p>
        <p>The other must-see Erickson building is off to the west. (It is on the West Side of town, not to be confused with the West End or with West Vancouver.) At the University of British Columbia he adapted the post-and-beam construction methods of the aboriginal Indians for a Museum of Anthropology that displays a comprehensive collection of their evocative art, some of which bears an uncanny resemblance to that of the Marquesas Islands in the Pacific.</p>
        <p>The collection includes baskets, textiles, jewelry and wooden sculptures of ravens, otters and bears. Its high point, however, is the largest grouping anywhere of totem poles, those magical, towering objects carved for thousands of years by the coastal tribes. They stand in a Great Hall, formed by a series of enormous reinforced concrete trusses and sheathed in glass on one side.</p>
        <p>Not far away is the Van Dusen Botanical Garden: 55 acres with 7,500 unusually clearly labeled plants from around the world that thrive in Vancouver's relentlessly benign climate. The magisterial conifers, grouped by genus, are particularly notable; among them are sequoias and cedars, firs and pines and spruces of the types that clothe the nearby mountains.</p>
        <p>Beachhead for the Arts</p>
        <p>The performing arts have established a solid beachhead in Vancouver. Less than five years old, Ballet British Columbia has flourished under the leadership of John Alleyne. The Vancouver Opera suffered a big setback in 1988 when poor attendance at some of its arcane offerings, like works by Leos Janacek, caused the Briton Brian McMaster to quit as general director. But it recovered, and it will offer four productions this season, including Stravinsky's ''Rake's Progress.''</p>
        <p>Founded in 1919, the Vancouver Symphony was dealt an even harder blow in 1988; out of money, it was forced to suspend operations. But  Romanian-born Sergiu Comissiona rebuilt it in a nine-year stint as music director. He will be replaced this fall by Bramwell Tovey, a young Englishman who is identified with choral works and new music.</p>
        <p>Bill Millerd's Arts Club Theater Company, based on Granville Island, will stage eight Canadian and foreign plays this fall, including Yazmina Reza's ''Art'' and Martin McDonagh's ''Cripple of Inishmaan.'' To the irritation of some chauvinists, the Vancouver Playhouse does fewer Canadian plays; next door, the Queen Elizabeth Theater is host to touring musicals and rock concerts.</p>
        <p>But perhaps the most successful of Vancouver's theatrical efforts is Bard on the Beach, an annual festival in a red-and-white tent in Vanier Park that stages Shakespeare against the ever-stirring backdrop of water and mountains. It began in 1990 with one play and a budget of $25,000. This summer, with a $1.2 million budget, the festival staged 146 performances of three plays, including a rousing ''Henry IV, Part 1,'' with Duncan Campbell, a star for years at Stratford, Ontario, as Falstaff; and his son, Torquil, as Prince Hal.</p>
        <p>''We've touched a nerve, I guess,'' said Christopher Gaze, an Anglo-Canadian actor who founded the company and still leads it. ''We played to 96 percent capacity last year. We're affordable, accessible and out of doors, which is what this city wants. We struggled a little, but then the support came -- whumpf! -- like a forest fire.''</p>
        <p>Wonders by Rail and Boat</p>
        <p>Given good weather, the call of the wild can be irresistible in Vancouver, even for sedentary souls like Betsey and me, and you don't have to rent an ocean kayak or a mountain bike to explore the city's glorious surroundings.</p>
        <p>One easy way to do it is by taking a steam train, the Royal Hudson, which puffs up the coast to the logging town of Squamish most mornings in summer, snaking past waterfalls and mammoth Douglas firs, clinging at times to cliffs 100 feet above the sea. The return trip, made by boat, is no less spectacular.</p>
        <p>A scenic 90-minute ferry ride across the Strait of Georgia, winding through the rocky, conifer-shrouded Gulf Islands, will deposit you (and your rental car, which is well-nigh indispensable) on 350-mile-long Vancouver Island, which shields the city from the Pacific. Victoria, the trim little provincial capital, is the best place to head for first.</p>
        <p>Not so very long ago, I'm told, Victoria was pure, provincial Victoriana. Morley Safer, the Canadian-born CBS correspondent, remembers arriving one afternoon in the 1960's at the vine-covered old Empress Hotel and discovering a the dansant in progress, with music by Billy Tinkle and his Orchestra.</p>
        <p>Modern Victoria is much less sedate. Betsey and I spent a Sunday morning in one of the many hotels that circle its landlocked harbor, reading the newspapers, eating breakfast and watching the tiny local ferries scuttle back and forth like cockleshells, dwarfed by the big Seattle boat. Seaplanes came and went, kayaks slid silently past, and handsome yawls heeled in the wind. Best of all, it happened to be the day of the annual Chinese dragon boat races, with 20 oars flailing away on each canoe and a drum booming a steady cadence.</p>
        <p>Brilliant summer flowers filled every pot, every hanging basket and every bed around the harbor, all as carefully tended as a dowager's coiffure. But the truly amazing displays are at Butchart Gardens, a half-hour north. There, in and around an old limestone quarry, we encountered millions of roses, billions of dahlias, trillions of tuberous begonias, some as big as a softball, and zillions of Japanese and Chinese tourists. I exaggerate, but not much. Every spring the gardens import 135,000 flower bulbs from the Netherlands, and every summer evening bushes and blossoms are lighted by thousands of lights linked by 11 miles of hidden wiring. It is a show worth crossing a continent to see.</p>
        <p>ON THE ROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
