<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- Fighting Marketing Pirates; Sponsors Guard Their Investments at Olympics</title>
    <meta content="Y29ADC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/business/29ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D71F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- Fighting Marketing Pirates; Sponsors Guard Their Investments at Olympics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sydney, Australia, is going farther than any previous host city of Olympic Games to protect its official sponsors from competitors who want to steal a little of the spotlight from them; is keeping so-called ambush marketers far from Olympic arenas and sites; nonsponsor companies remain visible, but Sydney has little of flea-market ambience that made Atlanta games a byword for crass commercialism; ambush marketing is such touchy subject because costs of Olympic sponsorship are so high; International Olympic Committee's 11 worldwide sponsors put up $550 million for four years leading up to Sydney Games, while local sponsors paid additional $315 million; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has become an urban legend at these Olympic Games. Security guards are supposedly confiscating bottles of Pepsi-Cola from visitors at the gates of the Olympic Park. Pepsi, The Sydney Morning Herald wrote, is on the forbidden list -- along with guns, knives and explosives.</p>
        <p>Not true, says the Sydney Olympic Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has become an urban legend at these Olympic Games. Security guards are supposedly confiscating bottles of Pepsi-Cola from visitors at the gates of the Olympic Park. Pepsi, The Sydney Morning Herald wrote, is on the forbidden list -- along with guns, knives and explosives.</p>
        <p>Not true, says the Sydney Olympic Committee.</p>
        <p>''We've given no instructions for Pepsi to be confiscated,'' Bob Bowden, a spokesman, said. ''People are allowed to bring food and drink into the park. We haven't specified what kind of drink.''</p>
        <p>Despite the denials, Mr. Bowden said the Olympic Committee had been unable to snuff out the rumor. That may reflect the consensus, both here and abroad, that Sydney has gone farther than any previous host city to protect its official sponsors from being ambushed by rivals.</p>
        <p>Pepsico's archrival, of course, is Coca-Cola, which paid an estimated $55 million to be a worldwide sponsor of the Olympics. The company is blanketing Sydney's Olympic Park with red-and-white umbrellas, lawn chairs and other reminders of its ubiquitous soda.</p>
        <p>Unlike the 1996 Games held in Coke's hometown of Atlanta, Sydney has kept so-called ambush marketers far from Olympic arenas and sites. Although nonsponsor companies are visible here, Sydney has little of the flea-market ambience that made the Atlanta Games a byword for crass commercialism.</p>
        <p>''They've really done a great job,'' said Gary Pluchino, vice president of Carlson Marketing Group, which works for the Olympic sponsors I.B.M., Samsung Electronics and Eastman Kodak. ''It's enormously helpful for these companies, which are using the Games as a platform around the world.''</p>
        <p>Ambush marketing is such a touchy subject because the costs of an Olympic sponsorship are so high. The International Olympic Committee's 11 worldwide sponsors plunked down $550 million for the four years leading up to the Sydney Games, while local sponsors paid an additional $315 million.</p>
        <p>Nothing better captures the difference between Atlanta and Sydney than the role played by Nike. In 1996, Nike, the athletic shoe and apparel maker, was the most aggressive ambush marketer of the Games -- leasing a parking garage near Centennial Park to promote its athletes and peddle its products.</p>
        <p>Today, Nike is inside the tent, as an Australian sponsor of the Games. That status has allowed it to plaster its trademark swoosh all over Sydney without worrying about protests from other sponsors.</p>
        <p>Among its showier gestures, Nike has wrapped a skyscraper in perforated film painted with expansive images of three Australian athletes who endorse Nike shoes: Cathy Freeman, the sprinter; Lleyton Hewitt, the tennis player; and Lauren Jackson, a star player on the women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>''People expected this to be a huge shift for us, like 'you were the black sheep of the family, and now you're the white sheep,' '' said Martha Ivester, the Olympics marketing director of Nike. ''But the reality is, we're doing the same marketing. People always expect us to be in-your-face.''</p>
        <p>For all the talk, Nike seems to have mellowed. Four years ago, it thumbed its nose at the whole concept of sponsorship. ''We don't sell dreams. We sell shoes,'' declared an eight-page advertising insert in Sports Illustrated. A television commercial said: ''You don't win silver. You lose gold.''</p>
        <p>This time around, the tone is softer: Nike's commercials talk about drawing on one's inner strength to win. The Australian campaign has Olympic athletes promising to put their lives in order after the Games.</p>
        <p>Like other people at Nike, Ms. Ivester seems almost nostalgic for the insurgent days of Atlanta, when Nike spurned a sponsorship and still won more attention for its marketing than the officially sanctioned companies. Although Ms. Ivester is excited about Nike's new status, she said that the company -- because of its close identification with sports and its superstar endorsers -- did not need the sponsorship as much as nonsports companies.</p>
        <p>''The whole point of being an event sponsor is to get visibility for your brand,'' Ms. Ivester said. ''The moment Marion Jones steps on the track wearing our shoes, we get all the visibility you could want.''</p>
        <p>Nike only signed its deal with the Australian Olympic Committee last December after its competitor, Reebok, pulled out following a dispute over the scope of the agreement. By picking up the $5 million contract just nine months before the Games, Nike was able to dictate its terms.</p>
        <p>Nike agreed to design and produce uniforms for the Australian athletes, but not the 47,000 volunteers who work at the Olympic Park. The company obtained waivers of an International Olympic Committee rule that prohibits the use of Olympic athletes in ads during the two weeks of the Games. As part of its agreement, Nike has also been allowed to build mobile playgrounds around Sydney that feature Nike products.</p>
        <p>In Atlanta, the company's promotional efforts were centered on Nike Park, a flashy complex near Centennial Park that drew crowds and the envy of less inventive sponsors.</p>
        <p>Marketing coups like that are all but impossible here because most of the sporting events are concentrated in the tightly controlled Olympic Park at Homebush Bay. Not only is the park free of ambush advertising, the organizers have bought up most of the billboards on the surrounding roads.</p>
        <p>''It certainly helps to have a new facility that is not surrounded by buildings on which you can hang big fluorescent signs,'' Mr. Bowden of the organizing committee said. ''You've basically got to hijack the airspace above the park if you want to get a marketing message out there.''</p>
        <p>And as Mr. Bowden points out, skywriting over Homebush is prohibited by the Olympic Arrangements Act, a government law that covers everything from security and parking to airspace. The act permits the authorities to remove unauthorized ads in the vicinity of the park that are deemed to be ambush marketing.</p>
        <p>While it says it has not yanked bottles of Pepsi, the Sydney organizing committee has let little else slip by. A catering service in the park was ordered to change the appearance of its bacon-and-egg roll because it looked suspiciously like an Egg McMuffin (McDonald's is a worldwide sponsor).</p>
        <p>''We're not out to ban legitimate marketing,'' Mr. Bowden said. ''But we want to protect the investment of our main sponsors.''</p>
        <p>Even in Sydney, the Olympic committee cannot eradicate every incidence of ambush marketing. Among sportswear manufacturers, the Italian company Fila has taken up the mantle of Nike. In 1998, it signed a lease on a replica of the legendary schooner Bounty, which was tyrannized by Captain Bligh.</p>
        <p>Now, the Bounty -- its fluttering foresail emblazoned with the Fila name -- is tied up at a wharf in Sydney's harbor. The company uses the ship to wine and dine clients. But its biggest value is as a floating advertisement; it sits just across a bay from the iconic Sydney Opera House.</p>
        <p>Alessandro de Pestel, Fila's vice president of communication, said the company spent $2 million on its Sydney marketing campaign. That compares with $10 million for a full-fledged Australian sponsorship. ''Everybody has learned from Nike,'' said Mr. de Pestel, as he relaxed with a double espresso on the aft deck.</p>
        <p>For its part, Nike has gone easy on Fila, Adidas, and other nonsponsors that are practicing ambush marketing here. Adidas, for example, has widely trumpeted its association with Ian Thorpe, the 17-year-old Australian swimmer who won three gold medals. That may be because Nike is likely to revert to its outsider status in future Olympics.</p>
        <p>''People in the U.S. probably wouldn't know who Ian Thorpe is if Adidas hadn't done so much advertising with him,'' Ms. Ivester said. ''Does that make us mad? Kind of yes, kind of no.''</p>
        <p>There are no mixed feelings between Australia's two airlines, Qantas Airways and Ansett Australia, owned by Air New Zealand. They are engaged in the most rancorous battle between a sponsor and an ambusher. Ansett is the official airline of the Games; Qantas, the longtime carrier of the Australian Olympic team, is out in the cold.</p>
        <p>Television viewers could be forgiven for thinking it was the other way around. By signing an estimated $8 million deal with Australia's Seven network, the local broadcaster of the Games, Qantas has been able to place its commercials around the hottest events involving Australian athletes.</p>
        <p>Making matters worse for Ansett is the Qantas theme song, ''I Still Call Australia Home,'' which has become the unofficial anthem of the Games. While Ansett has managed to keep the song out of formal Olympic ceremonies, one of Australia's gymnasts chose it for her floor routine.</p>
        <p>''We have been disappointed with a lot of the ambush activity undertaken by our competitor,'' said Jane Corbett-Jones, a spokeswoman for Ansett. ''But we're satisfied that our sponsorship has met the objectives we originally set out.''</p>
        <p>And the Qantas theme song?</p>
        <p>''It's fair to say that it evokes a lot of sentiment among Australians,'' Ms. Corbett-Jones said. ''One way or another, the song is going to be played, and there's not a lot we can do it about it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
