<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="29TRANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DA143DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>MLB--Announced that Pittsburgh 1B Kevin Young was suspended for two games and fined $2,000 by the commissioner's office for making contact with an umpire Sept. 21 at Milwaukee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>MLB--Announced that Pittsburgh 1B Kevin Young was suspended for two games and fined $2,000 by the commissioner's office for making contact with an umpire Sept. 21 at Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>National League  MONTREAL EXPOS--Acquired OF Terrmel Sledge from the Seattle Mariners, completing the trade that sent C Chris Widger to the Mariners.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS--Signed G Chris Mullin.  HOUSTON ROCKETS--Traded G Bryce Drew to Chicago for a conditional future first-round draft pick or two future second-round draft picks.  MIAMI HEAT--Signed G Rick Brunson and G-F Jamal Robinson.  ORLANDO MAGIC--Signed G Troy Rolle.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>XFL  NEW YORK-NEW JERSEY HITMEN--Named Rusty Tillman coach.  SAN FRANCISCO DEMONS--Named Jim Skipper coach.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  NHL--Announced the suspension of Tampa Bay Lightning LW Gordie Dwyer for 23 games for an altercation with on-ice officials during a pre-season game on Sept. 19 against the Washington Capitals.  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Recalled G Scott Fankhouser, D Brett Clark, F J.P. Vigier and F Herbert Vasiljevs from Orlando of the IHL.  CALGARY FLAMES--Assigned F Daniel Tkaczuk, D Mike Martin, LW Jason Botterill, and LW Miiko Elomo to Saint John of the AHL.  NEW YORK RANGERS--Assigned G Johan Holmqvist to Hartford of the AHL and D David Wilkie to Houston of the IHL. Called up G Jason LaBarbara from Hartford.  SAN JOSE SHARKS--Assigned d Mikael Samuelsson to Kentucky of the AHL.  WASHINGTON CAPITALS--Signed D Jakub Cutta to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>International Hockey League  CHICAGO WOLVES--Released C Adam Calder, C Brad Englehart, C Todd Robinson, C Cam Severson, RW David Jesiolowski, RW Trent Walford, LW Robert Starke, LW Curtis Wilgosh, D Benoit Cotnoir, D Andy Fermoyle, D Sean Molina, D Mike Perna, D Philippe Roy, G Kendall Sidoruk and D Benoit Thibert.  KANSAS CITY BLADES--Announced the Vancouver Canucks have assigned D Bryan Allen, D Zenith Komarniski and RW Jarrko Ruutu to the team.  ok.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>NCAA--Declared Temple freshman basketball F Carlton Aaron eligible for the 2000-01 season.  SOUTHERN CONFERENCE--Suspended Chattanooga WR Cos DeMatteo for one game for a confrontation with Georgia Southern CB Lavar Rainey and reprimanded Rainey for provoking DeMatteo during a game on Sept. 23.  BUTLER--Named Mike Marshall men's assistant basketball coach.  JACKSONVILLE--Accepted an invitation to join the Pioneer Football League in the fall of 2001.  MERRIMACK--Named Matt Read men's lacrosse coach.  NORTHEASTERN--Named Lisa Fisher and Shon Hardy women's assistant basketball coaches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
