<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Firestone Uneasy Over Threatened Changes</title>
    <meta content="Y29TIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/business/29TIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaizaki, Yoichiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D81F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Firestone Uneasy Over Threatened Changes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone Inc, which is struggling to cope with the recall of 6.5 million Firestone tires, is facing growing uncertainty about who will running company; Yoichiro Kaizaki, president of Firestone's parent, Bridgestone Corp of Japan, created uncertainty two weeks ago by declaring that management reshuffle is likely at its American subsidiary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., which is struggling to cope with the recall of 6.5 million Firestone tires, can chalk up one more problem: growing uncertainty about who will be running the company in the days ahead.</p>
        <p>Yoichiro Kaizaki, the president of Firestone's parent, the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, created the uncertainty two weeks ago by declaring that a management reshuffle was likely at its American subsidiary, which is based in Nashville. But there has been no announcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., which is struggling to cope with the recall of 6.5 million Firestone tires, can chalk up one more problem: growing uncertainty about who will be running the company in the days ahead.</p>
        <p>Yoichiro Kaizaki, the president of Firestone's parent, the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, created the uncertainty two weeks ago by declaring that a management reshuffle was likely at its American subsidiary, which is based in Nashville. But there has been no announcement.</p>
        <p>There was a flurry of reports in the Japanese media today that Masatoshi Ono, Firestone's chairman and a protege of Mr. Kaizaki, would be demoted. Bridgestone, based in Tokyo, denied the reports while repeating that management changes might be coming. Mr. Kaizaki ''may be considering a kind of management reshuffle, but nothing has been decided,'' Ken Kitawaki, Bridgestone's manager of public relations, said in a telephone call from Nashville, which he is visiting this week.</p>
        <p>Crisis management experts say that promising a shake-up without taking immediate action is a bad idea because it tends to undercut the authority and morale of the people who might be losing their jobs. ''It puts everyone on tenterhooks, because they don't know what their role is going to be in the future,'' said C. B. Bhattacharya, an associate professor at Boston University who specializes in how corporations manage their reputations during crises.</p>
        <p>Firestone is already struggling to preserve its brand in the face of Congressional hearings and investigations by federal regulators and the attorneys general of 39 states. Complaints to regulators have linked the tires to 101 deaths and more than 400 injuries. Almost all of the deaths and injuries have occurred in Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>The confusion at Firestone came as the tire maker and the Ford Motor Company also quarreled publicly over the role that Firestone would play in supplying tires to the next generation of Ford Explorers, beginning with the 2002 Explorer, which is scheduled to go on sale in January. Firestone said in a statement today that it ''is slated to be the sole supplier on the 2002 Ford Explorer when it launches in 2001,'' and that other tire makers would become involved later.</p>
        <p>But Della DiPietro, a Ford spokeswoman, denied this, saying that Ford had been working with Michelin as well as Firestone since 1997 to supply tires for the next Explorer, and that Michelin tires would be available from the beginning. Lynn Mann, a spokeswoman for Michelin, said ''We're happy to stand behind Ford's announcement.''</p>
        <p>Firestone said in a statement tonight that Michelin would be providing some tires.</p>
        <p>Ford has also said it is talking to Goodyear about tires for the 2002 Explorer.</p>
        <p>In a potentially ominous development for Ford, Blueovalnews.com, a Web site devoted to news about Ford, plans to announce on Friday that it will share information with regulators about patterns of defects in Fords. Blueovalnews is popular with technicians at Ford dealerships, and Robert Lane, the site's founder, said that the site would allow technicians and the public to fill out forms online about vehicle problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lane said that Blueovalnews had been asked unofficially by officials at the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration to begin collecting the data. Tim Hurd, a spokesman for the safety regulation agency, said that the agency had not officially asked the Internet site to provide information but added that one or more investigators might have asked it to do so.</p>
        <p>Michael Vaughn, a Ford spokesman, said that the site's efforts were unnecessary because Ford already gathers information from its dealers and works closely with regulators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
