<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saul Fletcher</title>
    <meta content="RV003308" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fletcher, Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EFDD163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saul Fletcher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews Saul Fletcher's photographs at Anton Kern Gallery; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anton Kern Gallery</p>
        <p>558 Broadway, near Prince Street</p>
        <p>SoHo</p>
        <p>Through Oct. 14</p>
        <p>Imagine a cross between the early 20th-century Pictorial photography of Edward Steichen and early 90's abject art and you are close to the evocative, slightly macabre, sometimes overly precious images of Saul Fletcher, an English photographer who is having his second solo show in New York. Almost all of the images, small C-prints and occasionally Polaroids, are shot, using available light, against the same pockmarked plaster wall. They appear to be the work of a shut-in working in a nearly empty attic with the occasional cooperation of family members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anton Kern Gallery</p>
        <p>558 Broadway, near Prince Street</p>
        <p>SoHo</p>
        <p>Through Oct. 14</p>
        <p>Imagine a cross between the early 20th-century Pictorial photography of Edward Steichen and early 90's abject art and you are close to the evocative, slightly macabre, sometimes overly precious images of Saul Fletcher, an English photographer who is having his second solo show in New York. Almost all of the images, small C-prints and occasionally Polaroids, are shot, using available light, against the same pockmarked plaster wall. They appear to be the work of a shut-in working in a nearly empty attic with the occasional cooperation of family members.</p>
        <p>Many of Mr. Fletcher's photographs depict impromptu still lifes, installation-art-like arrangements of fragile materials or odd little performance-like scenes involving one or two people and some props. Sometimes all we see is the crazed silhouette of a dried wreath spreading out like veins, some faint lines drawn in pencil across the uneven plaster, a perplexing row of six little nooses, or an expans of crisscrossing lines of black thread that form a surprisingly dense grid. These images have a striking intensity of mood: a Miss Haversham-like beauty mixed with intimations of sinister rituals and obsessions.</p>
        <p>Other images pay homage to the history of painting. The gray-on-gray image of a skull, the nearly black-on-black shot of a vase of dark leaves, the softly lighted arrangement of a dead rabbit and two dead blue birds -- all evoke Chardin. The works involving figures are more expressionistic, the analogies tending toward Bosch and Bruegel. In one, the artist's father wears a dark suit and hunches petulantly on a folding chair. A piece of wood extends out of one pant leg in a long jagged horizontal, an artificial limb that looks dangerous to all concerned. In another, the artist wears a dark suit and bowler, carries a staff and is seen from the side bending forward slightly, while his young son, also darkly dressed and carrying a staff, seems to grow out of his back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fletcher's images have the distinction of not looking like a lot of photographs these days. They are not large, brightly colored or populated by adolescents, nor do they refer to portraiture, fashion or film. They risk nostalgia and obscureness, but they refreshingly invoke photography as a solitary art, a vehicle for a personal poetry and a conduit of light's infinite wonders, while adding a mildly deranged little twist to the lengthening history of set-up photography.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
