<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Danish Voters Say No to Euro; A Blow to Unity</title>
    <meta content="29EURO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/business/29EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eurocurrency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Denmark</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rasmussen, Poul Nyrup (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DF163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Danish Voters Say No to Euro; A Blow to Unity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Denmark votes not to join Europe's common currency, the euro, undermining already fragile monetary experiment and turning its back on rapid European political integration championed by France and Germany; final results show 53.1 percent of electorate voting 'No' to euro and 46.9 percent in favor; result is severe blow to Social Democratic prime minister, Poul Nyrup Rasmussen, who warned that Danes should accept euro or face isolation; rejection seen as ominous warning to European leaders that they may have raced ahead of their electorates in adopting euro, pressing for intensified political cooperation needed to support currency and talking of European federalism; 11 states of 15-member European Union introduced euro last year without holding popular vote (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denmark voted today not to join Europe's common currency, the euro, undermining an already fragile monetary experiment, and turning its back on the rapid European political integration championed by France and Germany.</p>
        <p>In the first popular test for the euro, introduced last year without such democratic consultation in 11  states of the 15-member European Union, Danes voted to preserve the krone rather than join Europe's ambitious experiment with a shared currency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denmark voted today not to join Europe's common currency, the euro, undermining an already fragile monetary experiment, and turning its back on the rapid European political integration championed by France and Germany.</p>
        <p>In the first popular test for the euro, introduced last year without such democratic consultation in 11  states of the 15-member European Union, Danes voted to preserve the krone rather than join Europe's ambitious experiment with a shared currency.</p>
        <p>Final results showed 53.1 percent of the electorate voting ''No'' to the euro and 46.9 percent in favor. The result was a severe blow to the Social Democratic prime minister, Poul Nyrup Rasmussen, who campaigned vigorously with a message that Danes should accept the euro or face isolation.</p>
        <p>The rejection appeared to contain an ominous warning to European leaders that they may have raced ahead of their electorates in adopting the euro, pressing for the intensified political cooperation needed to support the currency and talking of European federalism. The phrase ''democratic deficit'' is now heard often in discussion of Europe.</p>
        <p>''I am generally pro-European but I voted 'No' to register my protest at the lack of democratic openness in the way a united Europe is being built,'' said Ebbe Kloevedal Reich, a writer, as he stood in the misty rain in Copenhagen today. ''It is simply not a democratic process at the moment.''</p>
        <p>The vote was in line with a broad political trend in Europe toward the rediscovery of national identity and away from supra-national Europeanism, at least in its current form. Pia Kjaersgaard, a nationalist Danish leader similar to Jorg Haider in Austria, has been a leader of the campaign against the euro. She will now be strengthened.</p>
        <p>For much of the day the euro traded in a narrow range around 88 cents, but after the vote it dropped to about 87.5 cents in New York trading. Euros are not yet in general circulation, but individual currencies like francs and marks are locked to the new currency.</p>
        <p>Today's relative stability of the euro reflected several factors: a rejection had already been factored in by many traders, recent European Central Bank intervention has demonstrated that monetary authorities will not let the currency slip much below this level and the Danish economy is small.</p>
        <p>But just 21 months ago, at its introduction, the euro bought $1.17, and the Danish rejection suggested that the currency's chronic weakness is not about to end.</p>
        <p>Confronting such weakness may require the support of something as big as a government for Europe, but  the Danes have shown Europeans do not want that for now. A tension seems certain to persist between a common currency and the absence of common fiscal and other policies to support it.</p>
        <p>The likelihood that Britain and Sweden will adopt the euro has receded as a result of the vote. These are the other two European Union states outside the euro after Greece's adoption of the currency earlier this year. In the case of Britain, one of the Union's largest economies, this absence is unsettling to European monetary authorities.</p>
        <p>''With a 'No' from the Danes, there would certainly be a loss of confidence in the euro,'' Klaus-Dieter Kuehbacher, a member of the governing council of the German Bundesbank, said today before the final results were announced. He suggested further Central Bank intervention was possible.</p>
        <p>A further sharp fall in the euro appears unlikely in part because its problems have begun to hurt the earnings of American corporations in Europe. Sales in euros now translate into fewer dollars. The Federal Reserve Board has joined in supporting the euro and a consensus appears to exist, for the moment, that the currency is near its tolerable floor.</p>
        <p>The euro was always a political project, adopted in haste soon after German unification a decade ago as a means to tie a united Germany forever to its European neighbors and advance the vision of a United States of Europe, dear to the former German chancellor, Helmut Kohl.</p>
        <p>It is this vision, imposed over their heads, that is now being questioned by many of the 375 million citizens of the European Union who are concerned about the loss of national identity and national authority.</p>
        <p>One of the questioners today was Louisa Jacobsen, a lawyer who said she had favored European integration. But recent developments -- particularly the imposition by 14 European Union governments of sanctions on Austria for including Mr. Haider's rightist Freedom Party in a governing coalition -- enraged her.</p>
        <p>''What happened in Austria was a scandal, and that it why I voted 'No,' '' she said, troubled, like many Danes, by the idea that ''Europe'' could punish a small country for its democratic choice. ''We need a break, a pause, in a process of integration that is going much too fast.''</p>
        <p>The Austrian sanctions were lifted earlier this month, but not before damage had been done to the pro-euro campaign in Denmark, a nation of 5.3 million people. This small nation has long been divided over European integration, and swing voters like Ms. Jacobsen were always likely to have the final say.</p>
        <p>In the end, a combination of the rightist nationalism of Ms. Kjaersgaard and a wide range of anxieties over the future of Denmark's welfare state and the nature of democracy in a united Europe clearly came together to produce the rejection. This odd coalition outweighed the solidly pro-euro sentiments of Denmark's business community.</p>
        <p>The governing Social Democrats, by far the largest party with 35 percent of the vote, were unable to deliver their voters to the pro-euro cause because of widespread concern among them that pressure for lower taxes from European monetary authorities would eventually make Denmark's comprehensive welfare state unaffordable.</p>
        <p>Tax cuts and deregulation are favored by the European Central Bank  to spur European growth to a point where it can begin to compete with the vigorous American economy, making the euro more attractive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
