<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Devotion To Japanese Art Is Requited</title>
    <meta content="29ANTI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29ANTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scholten Japanese Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholten, Rene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charle, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9103AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Devotion To Japanese Art Is Requited</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Suzanne Charle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charle, Suzanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scholten Japanese Art, Rene Scholten's new gallery in Manhattan, offers show on art of Edo period in Japan; woodblock print (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rene Scholten came to love Japanese art through a circuitous route. On a trip to Japan while working as a software consultant, Mr. Scholten, who is Dutch, purchased an inexpensive woodblock print. Then he saw a fine 1929 print by Torii Kotondo of a beautiful woman applying powder. Completely seduced, he bought it.</p>
        <p>When an art dealer friend said he wanted to quit, Mr. Scholten took over his shop in The Hague. Business expanded, and so did the gallery; Mr. Scholten left his high-tech life and became a partner in Hotei Publishing, expanding its list of books on Japanese art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rene Scholten came to love Japanese art through a circuitous route. On a trip to Japan while working as a software consultant, Mr. Scholten, who is Dutch, purchased an inexpensive woodblock print. Then he saw a fine 1929 print by Torii Kotondo of a beautiful woman applying powder. Completely seduced, he bought it.</p>
        <p>When an art dealer friend said he wanted to quit, Mr. Scholten took over his shop in The Hague. Business expanded, and so did the gallery; Mr. Scholten left his high-tech life and became a partner in Hotei Publishing, expanding its list of books on Japanese art.</p>
        <p>His most recent venture is Scholten Japanese Art in Manhattan, which he opened two weeks ago with the help of two respected experts, Katherine Martin and Rosemary Bandini. Its first show focuses on the art of the Edo period in Japan (1603 to 1867). Intricate netsuke, the fanciful toggles that delighted the Japanese gentry for whom they were carved, are suspended in illuminated plastic cubes, as are shimmering lacquer boxes, better suited to holding admiration and wonder than more substantial stuff. On the walls are prints by some of the great masters: Suzuki Harunobu, Katsukawa Shuncho, Kitagawa Utamaro and Utagawa Hiroshige. Mr. Scholten spent $10 million to convert three floors of the town house at 63 East 66th Street, and it shows.</p>
        <p>Woodblock prints known as ukiyo-e have been the portal into Japanese art for many Westerners, including Monet, whose collection can be seen at his home-museum in Giverny, and van Gogh, who copied two of Hiroshige's prints, most famously ''Ohashi Bridge.'' The fragile colored prints were also favorites of Frank Lloyd Wright; an exhibition of his collection and his architecture in Japan will be at the Japan Society in March. The allure has not faded. A recent woodblock show at the Asian Art Museum in San Francisco drew more than 80,000 visitors. ''They have an immense following,'' said its director, Emily Sano.</p>
        <p>''Not everyone can collect Monet, but they can collect prints,'' said Ms. Martin, the Scholten gallery's managing director. ''Here are artists at a turning point. They are creating totally new abstract images, taking proportion and perspective and color and playing with them.''</p>
        <p>The prints lead the viewer into the floating world ukiyo, a Buddhist concept for the sad and transitory nature of the material world. Edo artists transformed the idea into the transitory world of pleasure, a demimonde of geisha and parties, actors and theater.</p>
        <p>The high-flying Edo era was a boom period. Like present-day New York, Edo (now Tokyo) was the center of commerce and trade. Merchants flush with money from a new economy sought to spend it on pleasure and more pleasure. Ukiyo-e put the spotlight on this self-indulgent, glamorous world, immortalizing the day's most sought-after courtesans, the season's most popular Kabuki actors. ''The beauties were Edo's supermodels, the actors its rock stars,'' Ms. Martin said. ''The prints were the Edo period's color TV.''</p>
        <p>The prints were major productions. Publishers hired artists who drew images that were then carved into wood blocks (sometimes a dozen or more for one print) by a master engraver. The blocks were given to a printer who worked under the publisher and the artist.</p>
        <p>Although publicly scorned by the higher caste samurai, the burgeoning merchant class collected the prints as passionately as later generations would collect posters and baseball cards. Some artists became almost as famous as their subjects. Utamaro, who worked at the end of the 18th century, was the Richard Avedon of Edo. Known for his innovative close-ups of the beauties of the day, he at once idealized them and captured, through simple elegant lines, their emotions and personalities. (His ''Mirror of Courtesans of the Green Houses'' is for sale at Scholten for $25,000.)</p>
        <p>''There were thousands of images and varying levels of prints, ranging from cheap ephemera to mica-ground prints for the wealthy,'' said Sebastian Izzard, a dealer who has just opened a new space at 42 East 76th Street, Manhattan. Many were lost to fire or ruined by water. In the Meiji period, when the Japanese turned their eyes to the West, some were actually used for packing.''We have no real idea of how many have survived,'' said Mr. Izzard, who worked at Christie's for 17 years. ''What we do know is that there are many 'sleeping prints' stored away. Whenever a fine 'unique' print is sold for a high price at auction, another surfaces.''</p>
        <p>One of Scholten's aims is to make the gallery a focus for Japanese art: a library on the third floor will be open to students, scholars and collectors, and Ms. Martin plans a series of lectures next year. (Information and appointments: 212-585-0474.) ''We want to develop collectors,'' Mr. Scholten said. ''And you can only really do that through a gallery.''</p>
        <p>George Mann, a collector from Chicago, agreed: ''It's one thing to see a print on a wall at a museum, and quite another to hold it and examine it. An even larger barrier is psychological. You can't own a museum print. A print in a gallery is much more seductive.''</p>
        <p>The novice has much to learn. A print of the famed Ohashi bridge by Hiroshige can sell for anywhere from several hundred dollars to tens of thousands. In a recent auction at Christie's an early impression went for $52,875; at Scholten, another fine impression costs $75,000. At issue is the quality and condition of the print. Often an early edition will command the highest price: the artist was there supervising the  printer, making sure the proper colors were used. In later editions, when the artist was off creating new images, a printer might take shortcuts, using less expensive pigments.</p>
        <p>But the first impression does not always command the highest price. Sometimes a coterie of patrons commissioned a deluxe edition printed on special paper with special pigments. Or the publisher or artist decided to edit the print to make it more salable or attractive. The first prints of Hiroshige's ''Ohashi,'' for example, are sometimes known as ''Two Boats''; in later editions two boats in the background were etched out to make the print more aesthetically appealing. Popular works could be printed and reprinted until the block became so worn that the impressions were virtually unreadable. The title of Hiroshige's series ''100 Views of Edo'' was actually changed to ''100 Views of Tokyo.'' ''The name of the city changed in 1868, 10 years after the print was made,'' Mr. Izzard said. ''The condition of the blocks had to be pretty rough.''</p>
        <p>The prints are as ephemeral as their subjects, soon fading in direct light. Improperly stored, they become food for worms and insects. Today most serious collectors keep prints in acid-free paper in boxes, taking them out to look at or to hang on a wall, for only a brief time, behind protective glass.</p>
        <p>Prices for ukiyo-e are driven by fashion, just as they were in the Edo period. Although a popular image in excellent condition would be out of reach for most (an actor print by Sharaku just sold at Christie's for $280,000), there are still many prints in fine condition available for as little as $3,000 or $4,000. ''You might not be able to afford a fine print of 'Ohashi,' '' Ms. Martin said. ''But there are excellent prints from the same series that you could buy for $3,000. The market, today as in the past, is driven by changing tastes.''</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
