<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharon Touches a Nerve, and Jerusalem Explodes</title>
    <meta content="Y29ISR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/international/29ARAFAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temple Mount (Jerusalem)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ramallah (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DA1F3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharon Touches a Nerve, and Jerusalem Explodes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sharon Touches a Nerve, and Jerusalem Explodes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenberg, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ariel Sharon, right-wing Israeli opposition leader, leads group of Israeli legislators onto bitterly contested Temple Mount to assert Jewish claims there, setting off stone-throwing clash that leaves several Palestinians and more than two dozen policemen injured; Sharon entourage is tightly guarded by Israeli security cordon; violence spreads to streets of East Jerusalem and to West Bank town of Ramallah; Yasir Arafat, Palestinian leader, condemns Sharon's tour as 'dangerous action' against Muslim holy sites; Sharon claims he brought message of peace; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tightly guarded by an Israeli security cordon, Ariel Sharon, the right-wing Israeli opposition leader, led a group of Israeli legislators onto the bitterly contested Temple Mount today to assert Jewish claims there, setting off a stone-throwing clash that left several Palestinians and more than two dozen policemen injured.</p>
        <p>The violence spread later to the streets of East Jerusalem and to the West Bank town of Ramallah, where six Palestinians were reportedly hurt as Israeli soldiers fired rubber-coated bullets and protesters hurled rocks and firebombs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tightly guarded by an Israeli security cordon, Ariel Sharon, the right-wing Israeli opposition leader, led a group of Israeli legislators onto the bitterly contested Temple Mount today to assert Jewish claims there, setting off a stone-throwing clash that left several Palestinians and more than two dozen policemen injured.</p>
        <p>The violence spread later to the streets of East Jerusalem and to the West Bank town of Ramallah, where six Palestinians were reportedly hurt as Israeli soldiers fired rubber-coated bullets and protesters hurled rocks and firebombs.</p>
        <p>''I brought a message of peace,'' Mr. Sharon said after a one-hour tour that Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, condemned as a ''dangerous action'' against Muslim holy sites.</p>
        <p>The complex, known to Muslims as Haram al Sharif, or the Noble Sanctuary, contains Al Aksa Mosque and the Dome of the Rock, sacred shrines of Islam. It is revered by Jews as the site of the First and Second Temples as well as the place where Abraham was prepared to sacrifice his son, Isaac. A dispute about sovereignty over the area, in Jerusalem's walled Old City, has created an impasse in the Israeli-Palestinian peace talks.</p>
        <p>''I believe that Jews and Arabs can live together,'' Mr. Sharon declared as stones and rubber-coated bullets flew at the holy site. ''It was no provocation whatsoever,'' he said of his visit. ''It's our right. Arabs have the right to visit everywhere in the Land of Israel, and Jews have the right to visit every place in the Land of Israel.'' Injured Palestinians and police officers were carried off on stretchers minutes after the visit ended.</p>
        <p>Ordinary Israelis can visit the Temple Mount like any other tourists, although most Orthodox rabbis have forbidden entry because of the area's special sanctity under Jewish law.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sharon, who has a provocative reputation among Palestinians, is no ordinary Israeli. Among other things, he owns a home in a Muslim neighborhood of the Old City. The house, which flies an Israeli flag, has occasionally been a focus of confrontation between Palestinians and police officers guarding it.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Sharon used his visit to criticize what he called concessions on Jerusalem by Prime Minister Ehud Barak, the tour seemed no less an attempt to upstage Benjamin Netanyahu, the former prime minister who could challenge Mr. Sharon in coming primaries for the leadership of the Likud Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu returned to Israel today from the United States after Israel's attorney general announced on Wednesday that there was insufficent evidence to prosecute him on corruption charges, clearing the way for a possible political comeback. But Mr. Sharon asserted today that he would remain party leader, and that he had asked Mr. Netanyahu to join him in efforts to topple Mr. Barak.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon's tour was meant to assert Israeli sovereignty over the Temple Mount, but the vast security operation organized for the visit suggested that he had anything but free access to the compound, which is effectively run by Islamic officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon entered as a police helicopter clattered overheard and a thousand armed policemen were positioned in and around the Temple Mount, including antiterror squads and ranks of riot officers carrying clubs, helmets and plastic shields. Throughout the tour, Mr. Sharon was ringed tightly by agents of the Shin Bet security service.</p>
        <p>Faisal Husseini, the top Palestinian official in Jerusalem, said that the extraordinary police deployment belied Israeli claims of sovereignty over the Temple Mount, which was captured along with the rest of East Jerusalem in the 1967 Arab-Israeli war. ''Israel has no sovereignty here,'' Mr. Husseini said. ''They have military might, they have the power of occupation, but not sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon went into the compound through a gate used by tourists above the Western Wall, a remnant of a wall that surrounded the ancient temple plaza. His head was barely visible in the crush of security men and police officers around him. Inside, police officers kept Palestinians behind barriers as Mr. Sharon and his entourage walked around, pausing to listen to explanations by an Israeli archaeologist.</p>
        <p>Scuffles broke out when a few hundred Palestinian youths shouting ''God is great!'' and ''With soul and blood we will redeem you, Al Aksa!'' surged against police lines in an attempt to reach Mr. Sharon. Palestinian officials and Israeli Arab lawmakers who were with the crowd said that they were pushed and beaten.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Sharon left, dozens of youths hurled stones, chairs and metal objects at the police, who responded with rubber-coated bullets and riot sticks. At least four Palestinians were later reported to have been treated for injuries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon was trailed by Israeli Arab legislators who shouted ''Murderer, get out!'' and ''Al Aksa is Palestinian!'' Palestinians remember Mr. Sharon as the architect of Israel's 1982 invasion of Lebanon, during which Christian militiamen allied with Israel massacred hundreds of Palestinians at the Sabra and Shatila refugee centers in Beirut.</p>
        <p>''This is a man of blood,'' said Ahmad Tibi, one of the Israeli Arab lawmakers. ''His history says that he is not interested in peace.''</p>
        <p>The clashes at the Temple Mount spilled outside the Old City walls to Salah a-Din Street, the main shopping thouroughfare of East Jerusalem, where youths hurled stones at police and Israeli vehicles, lightly injuring a bus passenger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon's visit was ''a direct attempt to derail the peace process and an attempt to inflame the whole region,'' Mr. Husseini said.</p>
        <p>Peace efforts were further shadowed by an overnight bombing in the Gaza Strip that killed an Israeli soldier and wounded another. Two roadside charges were detonated near an army-escorted convoy of cars heading for the Israeli settlement of Netzarim.</p>
        <p>Despite the unrest and injuries in Jerusalem, Mr. Sharon said, his visit had been worthwhile.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry about the casualties, and I wish the wounded a speedy recovery, but a Jew in Israel has the right to visit the Temple Mount,'' he said. ''The Temple Mount is still in our hands.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
