<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Was He a Fastidious Romantic Or an Impassioned Classicist?</title>
    <meta content="29MEND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29MEND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Boychoir</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masur, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED71E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Was He a Fastidious Romantic Or an Impassioned Classicist?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews New York Philharmonic program of Mendelssohn, conducted by Kurt Masur with American Boychoir; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mendelssohn, the present subject of celebration at the New York Philharmonic, has not played the posterity game with any great success. History often prefers engines of change. Some people may not like Schoenberg's music, but they will never forget the name. Everyone likes Beethoven and Mozart, but their names, like Schoenberg's, are writ particularly large by virtue of movements they represent. We keep track of the past by dividing it into eras, and all three of these men are prominent hinges joining one period to the next.</p>
        <p>Mendelssohn falls between the cracks of historical chronology. He is either a Romantic composer disciplined by Classical reticence or a Classical composer with Romantic tendencies. To add to the confusion, he may be both. Mendelssohn's early death at 38 came half a century after Mozart's, but what could be more Mozartean in its civility and symmetry than the four choral pieces sung by the American Boychoir at Avery Fisher Hall on Wednesday night?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mendelssohn, the present subject of celebration at the New York Philharmonic, has not played the posterity game with any great success. History often prefers engines of change. Some people may not like Schoenberg's music, but they will never forget the name. Everyone likes Beethoven and Mozart, but their names, like Schoenberg's, are writ particularly large by virtue of movements they represent. We keep track of the past by dividing it into eras, and all three of these men are prominent hinges joining one period to the next.</p>
        <p>Mendelssohn falls between the cracks of historical chronology. He is either a Romantic composer disciplined by Classical reticence or a Classical composer with Romantic tendencies. To add to the confusion, he may be both. Mendelssohn's early death at 38 came half a century after Mozart's, but what could be more Mozartean in its civility and symmetry than the four choral pieces sung by the American Boychoir at Avery Fisher Hall on Wednesday night?</p>
        <p>After intermission, the Philharmonic under Kurt Masur gave the complete Incidental Music to ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' an astonishing teenage work as charming for its disciplined contours as for its descriptive sound effects.</p>
        <p>Two of the vocal items -- ''Denn Er Hat Seinen Engeln Befohlen'' and ''Lift Thine Eyes to the Mountains'' -- derive from the 1846 oratorio ''Elijah,'' written 11 years after the rhapsodic ''Carnaval'' of Schumann (a Mendelssohn admirer) and 16 after Berlioz's flamboyant ''Symphonie Fantastique.'' Compare Mendelssohn's chaste, buoyant love of melody and form with Wagner's ''Tannhauser'' and ''Lohengrin,'' both finished at about the same time. The ''Laudate pueri'' and ''Surrexit pastor bonus'' reflect the ideals of 18th-century counterpoint that their composer commanded so impressively.</p>
        <p>Having these four pieces sung by boys outlines the aura of innocence around so much of Mendelssohn's music. The harmony is anything but anachronism. Deep sophistication in the name of simplicity, youth and confidence sums up this music. Also the ability to incorporate bursting emotion within tightly measured melodic arcs. Conducted by James Litton and accompanied on the piano by Scott Dettra, the American Boychoir sang this difficult music with an unforced expressivity and clean command.</p>
        <p>The ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' music stands in the middle of the Philharmonic's minifestival of Mendelssohn; the oratorio ''St. Paul'' will be done four times beginning next Thursday. The piece also reflects Mr. Masur's love of big mixed-media pieces from the past. Here, John De Lancie delivered the minimally smart-alecky and mostly effective spoken text. Danielle De Niese's charm and enthusiasm took our minds off a soprano technique that is not quite finished. The mezzo-soprano Margaret Lattimore did well in her brief contributions. Philip Myers played the extensive horn solos with a big rich tone and unusual sureness.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic provided the kind of delicacy and fineness that Mr. Masur associates with this music. It was a satisfying evening and will be repeated tonight and next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
