<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West Nile Victim Recalled As a Hale and Hearty Man</title>
    <meta content="29VICT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/nyregion/29VICT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Opalka, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DF163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West Nile Victim Recalled As a Hale and Hearty Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>LITTLE FALLS, N.J., Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Anthony Opalka of Little Falls, NJ, 82-year-old man who died of complications from West Nile virus two weeks ago; he projected an image of vigorous good health (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before he died of complications from West Nile virus two weeks ago -- becoming the first fatality of the outbreak in the United States this year -- Anthony Opalka projected an image of vigorous good health.</p>
        <p>At age 82, Mr. Opalka, a retired welder, walked his little dog, Bingo, through the neighborhood most days -- first in the early morning and then two or three more times. On some of his walks, he would visit friends at the State Police laboratory near his home. Other times, he would go to Passaic Valley High School and its wooded campus, about a mile from the little Cape Cod he shared with his son and daughter-in-law and their teenage daughter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before he died of complications from West Nile virus two weeks ago -- becoming the first fatality of the outbreak in the United States this year -- Anthony Opalka projected an image of vigorous good health.</p>
        <p>At age 82, Mr. Opalka, a retired welder, walked his little dog, Bingo, through the neighborhood most days -- first in the early morning and then two or three more times. On some of his walks, he would visit friends at the State Police laboratory near his home. Other times, he would go to Passaic Valley High School and its wooded campus, about a mile from the little Cape Cod he shared with his son and daughter-in-law and their teenage daughter.</p>
        <p>''He was so active you just didn't expect his death,'' said one neighbor, Shirley Close. ''I never thought of him as sick. To live to be 82 and then get bit by a mosquito and die -- it's quite shocking.''</p>
        <p>Before Gov. Christine Todd Whitman and state health officials announced Mr. Opalka's death on Wednesday, some in this town of 12,000 21 miles west of Manhattan were already jittery about mosquitoes and the West Nile virus. On Tuesday, officials at Passaic Valley High, a regional school that draws teenagers from Little Falls, Totowa and West Paterson, canceled the marching band's regular practices at dusk because of worries about mosquitoes from a nearby creek.</p>
        <p>Workers from the Passaic County Mosquito Commission visited the campus this week but decided not to spray pesticide because they did not consider it a mosquito breeding ground, the township administrator, William Wilk, said today.</p>
        <p>Since the state's announcement, scores of worried residents have called Town Hall for information. In response, town officials have scheduled a meeting for all residents on Saturday morning. State health and environmental officials have been invited to answer residents' questions, Mr. Wilk said.</p>
        <p>Several dead crows have been found around town this summer, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilk said two of the dead crows found here tested positive for the West Nile virus. But, he said, they were not recovered from Mr. Opalka's neighborhood. Still, he said, the county mosquito control commission considered parts of the neighborhood to be mosquito breeding grounds this summer, and sprayed woods and curbside drainage basins on two streets near Mr. Opalka's home.</p>
        <p>State officials said yesterday they believed that Mr. Opalka was probably bitten sometime in August. On Sept. 3, he began to experience nausea and vomiting. Three days later, he was hospitalized, they said. He suffered respiratory failure on Sept. 9 and died five days later.</p>
        <p>Mr. Opalka's death has stunned his neighborhood, essentially because many residents there say they considered him more active than most 82-year-olds.</p>
        <p>He did not hesitate to climb a ladder and paint his house, and he helped delivery men unload electrical equipment and supplies at a contractor's shop across from his home.  When floodwaters began filling some streets in his neighborhood during Tropical Storm Floyd last September, Mr. Opalka was out in the dark with his son, Michael, warning residents about the danger and helping some of them move items from flooded basements to first floors.</p>
        <p>He was also remembered today for acts of kindness and generosity. Routinely in his retirement, neighbors said, Mr. Opalka would drive neighborhood children to school if they missed the bus. And eight years ago, he regularly visited an ailing 4-year-old girl who came to New Jersey from Poland for complex heart surgery. The child and her mother, who spoke no English, stayed at Marian and Jim Ceston's home, a block from Mr. Opalka's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Opalka, who was raised in Poland, often visited the girl's family while they stayed near his house m and chatted with them in their native tongue.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to make them feel welcome,'' Ms. Cestone said. ''It's really too bad this had to happen.  We're going to miss him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
