<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DRUG OFFERS MORE PRIVACY, AND COULD RESHAPE DEBATE</title>
    <meta content="29ABOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/science/29ABOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. APPROVES ABORTION PILL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ru-486 (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mifepristone (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolata, Gina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henney, Jane E (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFDD163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DRUG OFFERS MORE PRIVACY, AND COULD RESHAPE DEBATE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kolata, Gina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Food and Drug Administration approves marketing of abortion-inducing pill mifepristone, or RU-486, first alternative to surgical abortion approved in United States; pill, a prescription drug, will be available to doctors in four weeks, and will allow them to offer abortions outside of specialty clinics; it will allow women to have abortions in privacy of their homes up to seven weeks after their last menstrual period; most women who seek abortions do so later in their pregnancies, but drug has taken on immense symbolic importance for both supporters and opponents of abortion rights; approval of drug brings out sharp contrasts in views on abortion of Vice Pres Al Gore, who supports FDA move, and Gov George W Bush, who says FDA is wrong; Dr Jane E Henney, FDA commissioner, says decision was based on persuasive data showing that drug is safe and effective; says politics played no role in decision; chart; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration announced yesterday that it had approved the marketing of an abortion-inducing pill, the first alternative to surgical abortion approved in the United States.</p>
        <p>The pill, a prescription drug, will be available to doctors in about four weeks, its distributor said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration announced yesterday that it had approved the marketing of an abortion-inducing pill, the first alternative to surgical abortion approved in the United States.</p>
        <p>The pill, a prescription drug, will be available to doctors in about four weeks, its distributor said.</p>
        <p>The drug, mifepristone, or RU-486,  will allow doctors like family practitioners and obstetricians to offer abortions outside of specialty clinics, and it will allow women to have abortions in the privacy of their homes up to seven weeks after their last menstrual period.</p>
        <p>Although most women who seek abortions do not do so until later in their pregnancies, the drug has taken on immense symbolic importance for both supporters and opponents of abortion rights. Many supporters of abortion rights have said its approval will transform the struggle over legal abortion, making the procedure more accessible and more private, and stall efforts by opponents of abortion to identify women who are having the procedure and doctors who are providing it.</p>
        <p>Approval of the drug immediately brought out the sharp contrasts in the views on abortion of Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Mr. Gore said he was pleased with the decision, and Mr. Bush said it was wrong.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jane E. Henney, the F.D.A. commissioner, said in an interview,  ''Politics had no role in this decision.'' It was based, Dr. Henney said, on persuasive data showing that the drug is safe and effective.</p>
        <p>The drug will be distributed under the name Mifeprex by Danco Laboratories of New York City, a company formed specifically to find someone to make the drug and then to market it. While Danco is marketing the drug, the company has refused to disclose the manufacturer.</p>
        <p>Advocates of abortion rights said they were elated by the health agency's action.</p>
        <p>''Never have I seen anything like this,'' said Gloria Feldt, the president of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, which participated in clinical trials of the drug. ''Never has there been a drug approval that has been through such an arduous political process.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Feldt called the drug ''the most significant technological advance in women's reproductive health care since the birth control pill.''</p>
        <p>It was a setback for those who oppose abortions, and some of them saw it as a contradiction in Clinton administration policy.</p>
        <p>''I think it should give people pause,'' said Dr. Richard Land, the  president of the Southern Baptist Convention's ethics and religious liberty commission.</p>
        <p>''I wonder how they square this with making abortions safe, legal and rare,'' Dr. Land said, citing an oft-repeated Clinton administration goal. ''It will make them more plentiful and less safe.''</p>
        <p>In its announcement, the health agency set relatively few restrictions on doctors' freedom to prescribe the drug, beyond requiring that the doctors be able to determine the length of time that a woman has been pregnant and that they make sure that women who receive mifepristone have ready access to surgical abortions, should they need them.</p>
        <p>A woman will be given written instructions on the pill's use and its side effects, which can include bleeding and cramping, headaches, vomiting or diarrhea, and her doctor must sign a statement saying they have read the instructions and will comply with them exactly. The woman must also agree to have a surgical abortion if the pills do not succeed.</p>
        <p>A woman first takes mifepristone, which blocks the action of progesterone, a hormone required to maintain a pregnancy, and 36 to 48 hours later  takes a second drug, misoprostol, which makes the uterus contract, expelling the fetal tissue. In clinical trials, the drug combination failed to result in complete abortion in about 5 percent of cases.</p>
        <p>The F.D.A. also required that the Population Council, a nonprofit group that holds the United States patent to mifepristone, keep track of how many women suffer serious side effects and the number of cases in which the pill fails to induce abortion. The council will also audit doctors to see whether they and the women taking the drug are signing the patient agreement.</p>
        <p>Although advocates of abortion rights have been pushing for approval of mifepristone for years, it is not clear how many American women will choose it.</p>
        <p>The drug can be used only until seven weeks after a woman's last menstrual period, and just one-third of abortions performed in the United States occur at that stage, according to the Alan Guttmacher Institute, a nonprofit group that researches reproductive health.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, side effects like excessive bleeding are extremely rare in first-trimester surgical abortions, and abortions are legal even into the third trimester of pregnancy in some states. Some doctors said they anticipated many women seeking an abortion would prefer the surgical approach, since the procedure usually is over in a day.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that mifepristone is highly effective and there are good results most of the time,'' said Dr. Warren Hern, director of the Boulder Abortion Clinic in Colorado. But, Dr. Hern said, citing side effects like incomplete abortions, ''people have a way of denying these problems with the drug and saying it's a magic bullet. It's not.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Feldt of Planned Parenthood  said women in clinical trials said they liked mifepristone abortions because they felt more natural than surgical ones.</p>
        <p>''They feel more in charge, more in control of their personal health,'' Ms. Feldt said.</p>
        <p>But Olivia Gans, who is the director of American Victims of Abortion at the National Right to Life Committee, said she worried that women might not understand what they were getting into when they took the drug.</p>
        <p>''We are just seeking another way to deliberately end a life,'' she said. ''How honest are we going to be with the American public about what's at stake with this drug?''</p>
        <p>Heather O'Neill, a Danco spokeswoman, said that the company had not yet set a price for the drug but that she expected insurance companies and government programs that now pay for surgical abortions to pay for mifepristone also.</p>
        <p>But doctors who want to use mifepristone may find that insurance questions and F.D.A. restrictions are just part of their requirements. In some states, abortion laws might restrict the drug's use. For example, many states require abortion providers to register and report every abortion. Some have detailed requirements for the design of offices and clinics. Some states require that fetal remains be examined by a doctor and in North Dakota, the remains must be cremated, incinerated, or buried, the law says.</p>
        <p>As a result, some doctors who could administer the drug may choose not to do so. Spokesmen at health agencies in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut said yesterday that it was not clear if their states had laws that might restrict access to the pill or require guidelines for doctors who prescribed it.</p>
        <p>Janet Benshoof, the president of the Center for Reproductive Law and Policy, a legal advocacy organization that has represented abortion clinics, said, ''Any doctor who regularly does abortions in most states has been subjected to extra scrutiny from law enforcement -- they don't fool around with this.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Benshoof said that in many states the laws written for surgical abortions also applied to pill-induced abortions.</p>
        <p>''Despite mifepristone's great potential to improve medical services for women, anti-abortion state legislatures have already erected a labyrinth of laws restricting all abortion,'' Ms. Benshoof said.</p>
        <p>Mifepristone was first synthesized 20 years ago, in France, and came on the market in Europe more than a decade ago. But from the beginning its introduction into the United States was entangled in abortion politics.</p>
        <p>In 1990, Dr. Land said, he went to Europe with a group of opponents of abortion, like the National Right to Life Committee and the Knights of Columbus, to tell executives at Roussel-Uclaf SA, the drug's maker, and its parent company, Hoechst AG, that they would face boycotts and protests if they attempted to sell the drug in the United States. (Hoechst merged with Rhone-Poulenc last December into a merged company called Aventis.)</p>
        <p>''We told Hoechst that it would be unfortunate if they were to market the drug in the U.S. since they had an unfortunate history when it came to death-dealing materials,'' Dr. Land said.</p>
        <p>The company was part of a conglomerate that had a major interest in the chemical used in German gas chambers in World War II. ''We knew and we wanted them to know that we knew,'' Dr. Land said.</p>
        <p>Soon afterward, Roussel-Uclaf said it would not seek approval to market mifepristone here; without a new drug application, the F.D.A. could not fully assess the drug.</p>
        <p>When he first came into office, in 1993, President Clinton asked federal regulators to assess whether the drug was safe and if it should be sold in this country. Dr. David A. Kessler, who was commissioner of the F.D.A. from October 1990 until March 1997, prevailed upon Roussel-Uclaf to donate its patent to the Population Council, which wanted to sponsor clinical trials in the United States and find a company to produce and market the drug. In May of 1994, Roussel-Uclaf donated its patent.</p>
        <p>''We really did think that we should have a chance to evaluate the drug,'' Dr. Kessler said. ''We didn't think that politics should get in the way of that.''</p>
        <p>Four years ago, the Population Council presented its data on the drug's safety and efficacy to an advisory committee of the health agency, which recommended the drug be approved for marketing in this country. But the Population Council still had no one willing to manufacture the drug. As a result, the agency could not issue final approval.</p>
        <p>''You can't approve a drug unless the drug exists, unless you can inspect the plant,'' Dr. Kessler said.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, some doctors have been using methotrexate, a drug used to treat cancer patients, to induce abortions. This use is legal, but its use is not widespread because methotrexate was not extensively tested and is not approved as an abortion drug.</p>
        <p>The decision to announce the approval of mifepristone, Dr. Henney, the F.D.A. commissioner, said, reflects the agency's own six-month interval to rule on applications to market a drug. Danco submitted crucial information six months ago, she added.</p>
        <p>''I would go back again to saying that politics did not play a role in this,'' Dr. Henney said. ''The people who know me and the people who know this agency know that we make our decisions based on the scientific evidence that we have before us. These are scientific decisions.''</p>
        <p>U.S. APPROVES ABORTION PILL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
