<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Number of Insured Americans Is Up for First Time Since '87</title>
    <meta content="Y29INS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/national/29INSU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Census Bureau</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDE163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Number of Insured Americans Is Up for First Time Since '87</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Census Bureau reports that number of Americans without health insurance declined in 1999 to 42.6 million, reduction of 1.7 million from 1998, after rising relentlessly for 11 years; proportion of people without insurance also declined for first time since 1987, to 15.5 percent in 1999, from 16.3 percent in 1998; economists say robust economy and expansion of government programs contributed to decline; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After rising relentlessly for 11 years, the number of Americans without health insurance declined last year, to 42.6 million, a reduction of 1.7 million from 1998, the Census Bureau reported today.</p>
        <p>The proportion of people without insurance also declined for the first time since 1987 -- to 15.5 percent in 1999, from 16.3 percent in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After rising relentlessly for 11 years, the number of Americans without health insurance declined last year, to 42.6 million, a reduction of 1.7 million from 1998, the Census Bureau reported today.</p>
        <p>The proportion of people without insurance also declined for the first time since 1987 -- to 15.5 percent in 1999, from 16.3 percent in 1998.</p>
        <p>The robust economy and an expansion of government programs contributed to the decline, economists and health policy experts said.</p>
        <p>With the unemployment rate at 4.1 percent, a 30-year low, many employers have found that they must offer health insurance to attract and retain workers. In addition, low-income people are receiving coverage from government programs created or expanded in recent years.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Mills, a statistician at the Census Bureau, said, ''The driving force behind this improvement was an increase in the likelihood of people having employment-based health insurance.''</p>
        <p>The number of people with health insurance through their employers rose last year by 3.4 million, to 172 million. This change accounted for 85 percent of the increase in the number of people with health insurance.</p>
        <p>Recent studies have found rapid increases in the cost of employer-paid health coverage, which could make it difficult to sustain the growth in the number of people covered by the plans.</p>
        <p>For children, as for the population as a whole, coverage increased last year. The number of uninsured children declined to 10 million last year, from 11.1 million in 1998. The proportion of children without coverage declined as well, to 13.9 percent from 15.4 percent.</p>
        <p>The plight of the uninsured has emerged again as a political issue, in Congress and in many of this year's election campaigns, including the presidential race.</p>
        <p>President Clinton welcomed the new data, saying: ''I am extremely pleased with today's announcement. I believe it validates our health care and economic policies.''</p>
        <p>The number of uninsured is still nearly three million higher than when Mr. Clinton took office in 1993.</p>
        <p>Since Congress rejected his proposal for universal health insurance in 1994, Mr. Clinton has been advocating smaller steps to expand coverage. The White House, Congress and governors of both parties have been working to increase coverage for children, in particular, and today's data offered some evidence that the efforts were beginning to pay off.</p>
        <p>The Census Bureau said that government programs, including Medicaid and the new Children's Health Insurance Program, had helped increase coverage among poor children and youngsters with family incomes just above the poverty level ($13,290 for a family of three).</p>
        <p>But overall, the bureau said, in the last year, there was no change in the proportion of the population (24 percent) covered by government health insurance programs.</p>
        <p>The number of people without insurance rose by an average of more than a million a year from 1987 to 1998. The trend puzzled and frustrated health care experts because it persisted in a strong economy with low unemployment.</p>
        <p>For several years, the number of Americans with employer-sponsored health insurance has been creeping up. But the changes received little notice because they coincided with the erosion of other types of coverage. For example, millions of low-income people, including former welfare recipients, were losing Medicaid. That erosion stopped last year. The number of people covered by Medicaid held steady around 28 million, the Census Bureau said.</p>
        <p>Genevieve M. Kenney, an economist at the Urban Institute here, said, ''The percentage of poor children without coverage has dropped back to where it was in 1996,'' the year Congress passed a landmark law limiting access to welfare.</p>
        <p>Paul Fronstin, an economist at the Employee Benefit Research Institute, a nonpartisan study center, said he was not surprised by the data.</p>
        <p>''Small firms are more likely to offer health benefits today than two years ago,'' Mr. Fronstin said. ''They need to do so to recruit and retain workers. At the same time, the strong economy puts them in a position where they can offer health benefits even though health costs are increasing.''</p>
        <p>In recent months, many employers have seen their health insurance premiums rise by 10 percent to 30 percent, mainly because of increased spending on prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>Ronald F. Pollack, executive director of Families USA, a consumer group, said: ''The new Census Bureau numbers are welcome news, but no cause for celebration. It's like a morning drizzle after a prolonged drought.''</p>
        <p>In its report, the Census Bureau made these points:</p>
        <p>*More than one-fifth of all poor children, and nearly one-third of all poor people, are still uninsured. Nearly half of poor people who worked full time last year were uninsured.</p>
        <p>*Households making less than $50,000 accounted for almost all of the increase in insurance coverage. Among those with incomes of $50,000 or more, there was no change in the proportion having coverage.</p>
        <p>*Hispanics people were more likely to be uninsured than any other major racial or ethnic group. About 33 percent of Hispanic people, 21.2 percent of blacks, 20.8 percent of Asian-Americans and 11 percent of non-Hispanic whites were uninsured last year.</p>
        <p>The Census Bureau found a notable increase in insurance coverage among poor children 12 to 17 years old. The proportion of such children without insurance declined to 25.7 percent last year, from 30.4 percent in 1998.</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, an early proponent of the Children's Health Insurance Program, said he was pleased to see that it had contributed to the increase in coverage, adding that Congress should take the next step and let parents enroll with their children.</p>
        <p>To compare states, the Census Bureau suggested using three-year averages of data from 1997 to 1999. By this measure, the proportion of people without health insurance ranged from a high of 24.1 percent in Texas to a low of 8.8 percent in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Arizona, New Mexico, California and Louisiana also had high proportions of people without insurance. The comparable figures were low for Rhode Island, Hawaii and Iowa.</p>
        <p>The proportion of people without health insurance was slightly above the national average in New York, where 17.1 percent were uninsured. The figures were below the national average in Connecticut (11.5 percent) and New Jersey (15.4 percent).</p>
        <p>Among people 18 to 64 years old, the Census Bureau said, workers were more likely than nonworkers to have health insurance. But, it said, the reverse was true among poor people. About 53 percent of poor workers were insured in 1999, compared with 59 percent of poor people who were not working. People who have low-wage jobs often cannot obtain or afford insurance from their employers.</p>
        <p>People from 18 to 24 years old were less likely than any other age groups to have health insurance coverage in 1999, the bureau said. Twenty-nine percent of these young adults were uninsured.</p>
        <p>One-third of the foreign-born population lacked health insurance, the Census Bureau found. But, it said, the probability that immigrants will be insured increases with the length of their residence in the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
