<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Priest of a Boundless Era</title>
    <meta content="29RUSK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/arts/29RUSK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan Library</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruskin, John (1819-1900)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glueck, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D91E3AF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Priest of a Boundless Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Glueck reviews Morgan Library exhibit of art and writings by John Ruskin; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much has been made of John Ruskin (1819-1900) this year, and not without a reason. It is the centenary of the death of this artist, art and architectural critic extraordinaire, social reformer, polymath lecturer, first official professor of art in England (at Oxford University) and an admirer of little girls whose mismarriage to a full-grown woman ended in disaster.</p>
        <p>So far in 2000, there has been a big Ruskin show at the Tate Britain in London, another at the Yale Center for British Art and a third at the Grolier Club in New York, as well as the publication of ''John Ruskin: The Later Years,'' the second and last volume of a biography by Tim Hilton (Yale University Press). ''The Countess,'' a play by Gregory Murphy about Ruskin's unconsummated marriage, is currently running at the Lamb's Theater in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Much has been made of John Ruskin (1819-1900) this year, and not without a reason. It is the centenary of the death of this artist, art and architectural critic extraordinaire, social reformer, polymath lecturer, first official professor of art in England (at Oxford University) and an admirer of little girls whose mismarriage to a full-grown woman ended in disaster.</p>
        <p>So far in 2000, there has been a big Ruskin show at the Tate Britain in London, another at the Yale Center for British Art and a third at the Grolier Club in New York, as well as the publication of ''John Ruskin: The Later Years,'' the second and last volume of a biography by Tim Hilton (Yale University Press). ''The Countess,'' a play by Gregory Murphy about Ruskin's unconsummated marriage, is currently running at the Lamb's Theater in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Now the Morgan Library has mounted its own show of Ruskiniana, ''Ruskin's Italy, Ruskin's England,'' a biographical assemblage of 133 objects: letters, manuscripts, photographs, drawings, paintings -- including several self-portraits -- and artifacts. They were mined entirely from the Morgan's own Ruskin collection, proclaimed by the library to be one of the world's most comprehensive.</p>
        <p>The Morgan is very good at this kind of thing, creating a sort of 3-D biographical sketch from its own material. In 1998 the library presented a fine one on Charles Lutwidge Dodgson, who as Lewis Carroll wrote ''Alice in Wonderland.'' While ''Ruskin's Italy, Ruskin's England'' can't exactly be described as an art show, it has a number of paintings and drawings by Ruskin himself as well as by the British artists J. M. W. Turner, John Constable and the Pre-Raphaelites  John Everett Millais, William Holman Hunt, Edward Burne-Jones, Dante Gabriel Rossetti and others in the Ruskin pantheon.</p>
        <p>Behind Ruskin's illustrious and influential career lay a troubled life. He was the only child of wealthy and zealously religious parents who refused to let go of him. (When he enrolled at Oxford, his mother took up residence near the university.) His disastrous marriage left him a lonely bachelor; like Dodgson (1832-1898) he was subject to fits of unrequited love for little girls. And he was beset by bouts of mental illness, possibly inherited from his paternal grandfather, who late in life slit his own throat. In the end, this brilliant and privileged personage died in the care of relatives and in his last decade rarely speaking.</p>
        <p>But it is Ruskin's genius that this show celebrates: the enormous energies as a writer, critic, artist, educator and reformist that made him a giant of the Victorian age whose published works ran to 39 volumes. He set new standards for criticism, looking to art for morality, spirituality and a reflection of nature's truth. His early interest in the work of Turner inspired the eloquent if sometimes longwinded meditations on art and architecture that began with his first book, the five-volume ''Modern Painters'' (1843-1860).</p>
        <p>The meditations continued in ''The Seven Lamps of Architecture'' (1849), a paean to medieval architecture as the true expression of national values, which established Ruskin as a leader in the Gothic Revival movement. And in ''The Stones of Venice'' (1851-53) he extolled Venetian Gothic architecture as reflecting national and domestic integrity, as opposed to the ''corrupt'' Venetian Renaissance that succeeded it.</p>
        <p>On view here in bound form and holograph manuscript pages, the books established him as the most influential art critic and theorist of the age; one who saw the function of art as a universal language, declared that the whole rationale of the artist was to be a ''seeing and feeling creature,'' and held the advanced belief that true art, though arrived at through nature, need not rely on representation.</p>
        <p>The exhibition, organized more or less chronologically by Robert Parks, curator of literary and historical manuscripts at the Morgan, starts with Ruskin's family and childhood. Early on he showed signs of his polymath talents: he collected minerals, a lifelong pursuit; wrote poetry; and at the age of 10 composed a book of ''Amusing Characters for Children,'' for which he did little poems and drew color illustrations copied from George Cruikshank's drawings for ''Grimms' Fairy Tales.'' Also on view are 18 sermons he wrote between ages 13 and 15 on the first five books of the Bible, hand-bound into five thin booklets. And there is a holograph manuscript of his essay, written at 17, on the effects of literature on moral character, in which he championed the works of Sir Walter Scott and Lord Byron, two of his literary heroes.</p>
        <p>Among the show's highlights are a number of Ruskin's detailed drawings and quick sketches for ''The Seven Lamps of Architecture.'' He never regarded his drawings as art but as useful notes. Still, his precise and elegant draftsmanship is nothing short of beautiful, exemplified in a meticulously shaded rendering of the stone balls surrounded by flowing leaves that adorn part of the central gate of St. Mark's in Venice. ''It looks as if its leaves had been sensitive, and had risen and shut themselves into a bud at some sudden touch, and would presently fall back again into their wild flow,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>At the time he was preparing ''The Stones of Venice,'' climbing all over ancient buildings to sketch and take photographs and measurements, Ruskin's marriage (in 1848) to Euphemia Gray, the daughter of a business acquaintance of his father, was falling apart. Holograph letters from ''Effie'' to her parents detail the main causes: too much interference from Ruskin's parents, his absorption in his work and his sexual indifference, not to say disdain. In 1854 the marriage was annulled, and the next year she wed Millais, until then a close Ruskin friend. (In his unfinished autobiography, ''Praeterita,''  Ruskin has nothing whatever to say about his marriage.)</p>
        <p>Ruskin's interest in Turner goes back to his youth, when he started collecting the work of the older artist. In ''Modern Painters'' he defended Turner against widespread ridicule in the press for the turbulently expressionist later works that are today regarded as masterpieces. He praised him as ''a great inventive landscape painter'' able ''to give the far higher and deeper truth of mental vision, rather than that of the physical facts.'' Two watercolors by Turner shown here were, in fact, commissioned by Ruskin: the grand, stormy ''Pass at Faido, St. Gotthard'' (1843) and the far more tranquil ''Lucerne From the Lake'' (1845).</p>
        <p>That Ruskin could be wide of the mark is evident in his famous rejection of Whistler's ''Nocturne in Black and Gold: The Falling Rocket,'' offered at the Grosvenor Gallery in 1877 for 200 guineas. ''I have seen, and heard, much of Cockney impudence before now,'' Ruskin wrote, ''but never expected to hear a coxcomb ask 200 guineas for flinging a pot of paint in the public's face.''</p>
        <p>Whistler sued, winning only a farthing in damages, and was bankrupted by the court costs. But posterity has declared in his favor. Shown here are a copy of Whistler's 1878 book, ''Whistler v. Ruskin: Art and Art Critics,'' and a holograph letter of 1878 from Burne-Jones to Ruskin about the former's court appearance in the case. Testifying for Ruskin, this Pre-Raphaelite Romantic allowed Whistler's work to be art, but declared it unfinished and poorly composed.</p>
        <p>The show touches on many other aspects of Ruskin's life and career, among them his mentoring of Kate Greenaway, the children's book illustrator and one of the few female artists he publicly praised; his work as a teacher at the London Working Men's College and at Oxford; his zeal as a social reformer and environmentalist as he pushed for a minimum wage, pensions and nationalized education; and his pathetic infatuation with a 10-year-old girl named Rose La Touche, whom he met when he was 39 and tried to reach by spiritualism after her early death.</p>
        <p>The end of Ruskin's life is sadly sketched out in notes made by him during periods of mental collapse. ''Worst horror I ever knew,'' is the terse comment in one of them. His working career ended in 1889, and there is a terrible photograph of him, vacant of expression and much diminished physically, as he slumps on a bench next to the robust female cousin who took care of him.</p>
        <p>Still, he left behind much to commemorate.</p>
        <p>''Ruskin's Italy, Ruskin's England'' is at the Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-0610, through Jan. 7.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
