<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Try Hard Not to Remember The Lowlights of September</title>
    <meta content="29CURR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/29/sports/29CURR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DD163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Try Hard Not to Remember The Lowlights of September</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Curry, in On Baseball column, notes that New York Mets have clinched wild-card playoff berth despite 12-14 record in Sept (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The custodian started cleaning and replacing the Champagne-soaked ceiling boards in the Mets' clubhouse before the last player had finished showering on Wednesday night. The giddy and relieved Mets had treated the clubhouse like a frat house after clinching a wild-card playoff berth, so the tidying was necessary.</p>
        <p>Climb a ladder, remove the board, scrub it down and return it. The mundane routine could serve as a metaphor for how the Mets hope their play evolves once September drifts into October. The Mets desperately hope a season that crumbled into a three-week debacle can suddenly revert to something pristine during the postseason. That is a hefty hope.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The custodian started cleaning and replacing the Champagne-soaked ceiling boards in the Mets' clubhouse before the last player had finished showering on Wednesday night. The giddy and relieved Mets had treated the clubhouse like a frat house after clinching a wild-card playoff berth, so the tidying was necessary.</p>
        <p>Climb a ladder, remove the board, scrub it down and return it. The mundane routine could serve as a metaphor for how the Mets hope their play evolves once September drifts into October. The Mets desperately hope a season that crumbled into a three-week debacle can suddenly revert to something pristine during the postseason. That is a hefty hope.</p>
        <p>Where are the Mets of August? Where are the Mets who had a most valuable player in Mike Piazza, a reliable bullpen, solid starting pitching and crisper defense? That team looked like it was durable enough to go to the World Series. But the current Mets, slipping, stumbling and then finally standing, are not as formidable. While the Mets played well enough to extend their season and looked slick while pelting Greg Maddux and the Braves, 8-2, last night, it is difficult to suddenly ignore almost a month of ragged play.</p>
        <p>''In August, we were probably the hottest team in baseball,'' reliever John Franco said. ''Then we took a month off. Maybe it's a good sign.''</p>
        <p>That refrain was echoed throughout the clubhouse. It is a new season. The last month did not destroy us. On and on, the Mets claimed that another brutal September did not matter. They had survived. The more they uttered it, the more they tried to believe it. Maybe they believe it, but not everyone else does and not everyone else should. The Mets have to prove themselves again.</p>
        <p>''We could sit here and say that we didn't play well and we didn't do this or do that,'' outfielder Darryl Hamilton said. ''But we're in the playoffs. Whether you're the wild card or the division champs, nobody's won any playoff games yet.''</p>
        <p>As the Mets kept repeating that they think they can, they think they can, Manager Bobby Valentine and General Manager Steve Phillips deflected questions about the postseason rotation and roster. Valentine, Phillips, the Met coaches and other executives will meet over lunch today to discuss their starting pitchers and their 25-man postseason roster.</p>
        <p>Before the Mets' officials take three bites, they should choose Al Leiter as the starter for the opener of the division series over Mike Hampton, and they should decide to keep 10 pitchers instead of 11 because Bubba Trammell and Matt Franco have more value than the struggling Pat Mahomes.</p>
        <p>Regardless of whether the opener is in San Francisco or in St. Louis, the Mets will benefit from starting Leiter, at 16-8 with a 3.20 earned run average, because he has been steadier than Hampton, who is 14-10 with a 3.22 E.R.A. The Giants are 17-20 and the Cardinals 17-22 against lefty starters.</p>
        <p>Leiter has pitched in more postseason games than Hampton has, he is better on the road (7-5, 3.70 E.R.A.) and he would be a better choice to pitch a Game 5. Rick Reed should start Game 2 because Hampton is superior at Shea Stadium, where he is 10-4 with a 2.13 E.R.A. The third game of a three-of-five-game series is a swing game. Teams are trying to avoid a sweep, complete a sweep or snap a 1-1 tie, and the Mets would feel much cozier with Hampton lurking there.</p>
        <p>''I don't care what we do,'' Leiter said. ''I just want to get them out.''</p>
        <p>Valentine offered evidence that Leiter would pitch the opener. Even though Hampton will start tonight and be on schedule to pitch in Game 1, Valentine has refused to commit to keeping him on schedule. Meanwhile, Valentine said Leiter would not make his next start on Sunday, which means the Mets are most likely saving him for the opener. Leiter has the flu, but Valentine said he would not start even if he were healthy. Leiter would have eight days between Tuesday's start and Game 1, but Valentine said, ''He's good with rest.''</p>
        <p>After carrying 11 pitchers during the 1999 postseason, the Mets should trim that to 10 and keep 15 reserves. If the Mets use the left-hander Glendon Rusch as their fourth starter, they can switch Bobby Jones to the bullpen, and he will assume Mahomes's role.</p>
        <p>''We used 11 last year and 11 all season,'' Phillips said. ''To me, that's open for discussion.''</p>
        <p>After pitching splendidly last season, Mahomes has been a disappointment this year, allowing 30 earned runs in the last 26 and a third innings. If the Mets do not include Mahomes, they can take eight regulars and seven reserves: Hamilton, Todd Pratt, Kurt Abbott, Lenny Harris, Timo Perez, Trammell and Matt Franco. Joe McEwing will surely be the victim of Perez's emergence, but the Mets can live without Mahomes and McEwing. They need Perez for speed, which he displayed while walking twice to ignite two rallies against Maddux last night. No Met can give them what Perez gives them.</p>
        <p>The Mets want everyone to believe in them. When Leiter was asked if the Mets could recover from a 12-14 September and soar through October, he feigned a look of concern and said, ''I don't think we can do it.'' Then Leiter laughed and adjusted his answer, but the Mets have to make sure his joking words are not prophetic.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
