<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Father and Son Livin' la Dolce Vita</title>
    <meta content="26WOME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenaway, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fellini, Federico</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Eight and One-Half Women (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDD123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Father and Son Livin' la Dolce Vita</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie 8 1/2 Women, Peter Greenaway's homage to Fellini classic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when a movie aspires to the intricate structure and weight of a knotty modernist poem, how good can it be when watching it gives you the queasy feeling that you are taking a math exam? That question could be applied to almost every work by the British filmmaker Peter Greenaway, whose movies, to a greater or lesser extent, feel like hybrids of art school essays and brain-tickling puzzles.</p>
        <p>Granted, Mr. Greenaway, at his best, can be a brilliant theoretician and collagist. But there is often something forbiddingly inhuman about his cinematic chess matches, which make Stanley Kubrick's most elaborate cinematic games look like child's play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even when a movie aspires to the intricate structure and weight of a knotty modernist poem, how good can it be when watching it gives you the queasy feeling that you are taking a math exam? That question could be applied to almost every work by the British filmmaker Peter Greenaway, whose movies, to a greater or lesser extent, feel like hybrids of art school essays and brain-tickling puzzles.</p>
        <p>Granted, Mr. Greenaway, at his best, can be a brilliant theoretician and collagist. But there is often something forbiddingly inhuman about his cinematic chess matches, which make Stanley Kubrick's most elaborate cinematic games look like child's play.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenaway's newest film, ''8 1/2 Women,'' is, among other things, a homage to Federico Fellini's 1963 masterpiece ''8 1/2,'' fragments of which are shown early in the movie. Just as Marcello Mastroianni served as the director's alter ego in that film, here the main character, Philip Emmenthal (John Standing), a middle-aged widower, is apparently a stand-in for Mr. Greenaway. In charting the erotic adventures of Philip and his son, Storey (Matthew Delamere), who establish a private bordello on their Geneva estate, the movie is Mr. Greenaway's personal take on a theme that obsessed Fellini: the erotic mystery and power of women. Although ''8 1/2 Women'' throws in a group of nuns late in the game, its allusions to Fellini's Catholicism seem halfheartedly dutiful.</p>
        <p>At one point, Philip wonders out loud if Fellini slept with the actresses who appeared in his movies or if he had Mastroianni do this for him. When he asks his son how many filmmakers make movies to satisfy their sexual fantasies, Storey replies that most probably do. And so we are treated to Mr. Greenaway's fantasies, which are pretty standard, although adorned with the stereotypical British kinks (a fascination with undergarments and the posterior).</p>
        <p>But as ''8 1/2 Women'' quickly reveals, the two directors are really poles apart in their attitudes toward sex. Even though the film flaunts full frontal nudity (both male and female) and plenty of frank sexual talk, it is so visually and emotionally chilly that its effect is often anti-erotic.</p>
        <p>When studying human flesh, Mr. Greenaway and his production designers have a way of making even well-shaped naked bodies look unappetizing. Plenty of beautiful women traipse through the movie, but their skin appears chalky and porous. The actual sex, none of it very explicit, is charged with neither passion nor even much lust. The couplings have the feel of laboratory experiments during which desire is analyzed to death.</p>
        <p>Fellini's women, especially the giant prostitutes he contemplated with the awe of a little boy peering up at a mountain, may have been threatening, but his Mediterranean slopes were steamy and lushly foliated. Mr. Greenaway's women are as enigmatic and as threatening as Fellini's, but most are photographed to appear as chilly as corpses. This is odd in a film where shots frequently allude reverently to famous nude paintings. As a seminar on the changing image of women in art, the movie is a turn-off.</p>
        <p>Several of those who join the bordello are Japanese, imported from Kyoto, where they exposed themselves to blackmail by their addiction to gambling in pachinko parlors. These Asian archetypes range from  a dragon lady to a Madame Butterfly-like refugee from the Kabuki theater who can respond to Philip only if he adopts the disguise and manners of a Kabuki female impersonator. The gambling theme is illustrated to tedious redundancy with images of tumbling coins that along with the earthquakes that periodically rumble through the movie are meant to symbolize love as an earthshaking game of chance, a natural event that's inevitable and can't be precisely predicted.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Greenaway's imagination, as in Fellini's, women end up calling the shots. Having arrived at the bordello, the women establish the rules. Then, one by one, they end up leaving the estate.</p>
        <p>The most vivid and powerful female character, Palmira (Polly Walker), is a free-spirited but demanding sensualist who gives herself to Philip and ultimately kills him with her inexhaustible libido. For the role of Beryl, a woman who loves horses and pigs, Amanda Plummer sports a bizarre S-and-M getup reminiscent of her bondage gear in ''Butterfly Kiss.'' Natacha Amal is Giaconda, an avaricious baby-making machine who drives a hard bargain and sells her newborns for $25,000 apiece.</p>
        <p>With its stiffly staged, symbol-laden visual tableaus, ''8 1/2 Women'' unfolds like an art history textbook. What it reveals is finally less than meets the eye. Its message is quite simple and all too familiar: when it comes to sex, all men are little boys.</p>
        <p>8 1/2 WOMEN</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Peter Greenaway; director of photography, Sacha Vierny; edited by Elmer Leupen; production designer, Wilbert Van Dorp; produced by Kees Kasander; released by Lions Gate Films. Running time: 120 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: John Standing (Philip Emmenthal), Matthew Delamere (Storey Emmenthal), Polly Walker (Palmira), Amanda Plummer (Beryl), Toni Collette (Griselda), Kirina Mano (Mio), Vivian Wu (Kito) and Natacha Amal (Giaconda).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
