<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling the Obscenity Case at the Start of It All</title>
    <meta content="26TVWK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Contemporary Arts Center (Cincinnati)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Woody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mapplethorpe, Robert (1946-89)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrie, Dennis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dirty Pictures (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Picking Up the Pieces (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DC123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling the Obscenity Case at the Start of It All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Caryn James</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James TV Weekend reviews of Showtime movie Dirty Pictures, based on turmoil over Robert Mapplethorpe's photographs; photo of James Woods as museum director Dennis Barrie; Woody Allen movie Picking Up the Pieces on Cinemax also reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a decade of the culture wars -- of politicians nibbling away at the National Endowment for the Arts, of Congress and artists dueling about what is fit for America to see -- there was a chilling inexorableness to the most recent skirmish, when the mayor of New York tried to cut off financing for the Brooklyn Museum of Art over a religious portrait made with elephant dung. The issue of public art exhibitions has been so co-opted by politics, where else could things have led?</p>
        <p>''Dirty Pictures'' revisits a case that helped set off this continuing battle: in 1990 the Contemporary Arts Center in Cincinnati, and its director, Dennis Barrie, were charged with obscenity after showing Robert Mapplethorpe's photographs, with images of sadomasochism, homosexuality and naked children. It may be a sign of how accustomed we have become to such conflicts that this earnest, pedestrian film is completely unable to recapture what a galvanizing event that was for both sides. It would have taken a work with far more energy and dramatic flair to convey the shock of that cultural moment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a decade of the culture wars -- of politicians nibbling away at the National Endowment for the Arts, of Congress and artists dueling about what is fit for America to see -- there was a chilling inexorableness to the most recent skirmish, when the mayor of New York tried to cut off financing for the Brooklyn Museum of Art over a religious portrait made with elephant dung. The issue of public art exhibitions has been so co-opted by politics, where else could things have led?</p>
        <p>''Dirty Pictures'' revisits a case that helped set off this continuing battle: in 1990 the Contemporary Arts Center in Cincinnati, and its director, Dennis Barrie, were charged with obscenity after showing Robert Mapplethorpe's photographs, with images of sadomasochism, homosexuality and naked children. It may be a sign of how accustomed we have become to such conflicts that this earnest, pedestrian film is completely unable to recapture what a galvanizing event that was for both sides. It would have taken a work with far more energy and dramatic flair to convey the shock of that cultural moment.</p>
        <p>The film moves in several directions. It is partly a predictable domestic soap opera. In a restrained performance, James Woods plays Mr. Barrie as a man who never set out to be a crusader but who feels morally compelled to defend the First Amendment when he has to. (Though the film depicts both sides of the argument, it is straightforward in its sympathy for Mr. Barrie, this script's hero.) Soon his wife (Diana Scarwid) is socially ostracized, and their two young sons are bullied at school. It is only a matter of time before the patient wife is tossing vases around the living room.</p>
        <p>But the film is also partly a courtroom drama; it is partly about politics, as a conservative sheriff (Craig T. Nelson) goes after the museum, and it is partly about the largest issue of all. As the forewoman asks the other jurors about Mapplethorpe's work, ''Is it obscene or is it art?'' The film intends to show the convergence of all these elements but instead dissipates the impact of each.</p>
        <p>The title ''Dirty Pictures'' suggests a film that wants to have it both ways, to be a serious work that titillates and seduces its audience into paying attention. But it is cautious even in its use of the Mapplethorpe photography. The images flash by quickly in several sequences: some are of flowers, some are portraits of celebrities (Susan Sarandon, Susan Sontag, Andy Warhol), some are the images that set off the conflict. The film doesn't dwell on the graphic details; even if you have seen the photographs, they go by so fast they can be difficult to identify.</p>
        <p>Frank Pierson, the director, also directed Mr. Woods in the much better ''Citizen Cohn.'' Even his attempts at arty touches seem tame here: there are stylized images of the jury room, as if the actors were on a bare stage; talking heads offer comments, including William F. Buckley Jr. on the conservative side and Representative Barney Frank on the liberal side, but they are familiar platitudes. ''If you can't defend what is unpalatable to you personally, then you don't actually believe in free speech,'' Salman Rushdie says.</p>
        <p>As an artist, Mapplethorpe was taken more seriously than most of those whose work has set off cultural shockwaves. That makes ''Dirty Pictures'' even more of a lost opportunity.</p>
        <p>PICKING UP THE PIECES  Cinemax, tonight at 8</p>
        <p>There are some movies whose existence is so baffling that ''The X-Files'' could spend several episodes trying to sort out the conspiracy theories behind their creation. The mystery behind the witless black comedy ''Picking Up the Pieces'' is not why this film has gone straight to cable, but why so many people who should have known better were sucked into it.</p>
        <p>Woody Allen plays a New York butcher called Tex who has fled to Texas, where he lives in a trailer with his dog, his 10-gallon hat and his wife. She is a faithless former Mafia moll named Candy, played by Sharon Stone with a baby-doll voice. The film looks as if it took two days to shoot and cost two cents to make, though it was directed by Alfonso Arau (''Like Water for Chocolate'') and shot by Vittorio Storaro (one of the great cinematographers, whose films include ''Reds'').</p>
        <p>At the start, Tex chops up Candy and scatters her body in the desert. Soon her severed hand, with its shimmery blue nail polish, turns up in the New Mexico town of El Nino and begins to perform miracles. These are not clever miracles, but the kind in which a flat-chested woman grows breasts before our eyes and a dwarf grows a gigantic penis (all discreetly clothed on screen). In no time the magic hand makes El Nino a tourist mecca, to the delight of the corrupt mayor (Cheech Marin).</p>
        <p>These cliches might seem to offer plenty of possibilities for irreverent satire, but it would take a miraculous severed hand to save this script (credited to Bill Wilson, described by Cinemax simply as ''a first-time screenwriter''). The humor is always lazy. We see a man in bed with a beautiful prostitute, and he soon puts on his priest's collar. (We've never seen that one before.) Played by David Schwimmer with a slightly less hangdog expression than on ''Friends,'' the priest is, of course, in love with the golden-hearted prostitute.</p>
        <p>Eventually, a mean Texas sheriff (a toothpick-chewing Kiefer Sutherland) goes after Tex. The church sends in investigators, including a bishop (Elliot Gould) and a nun (Fran Drescher, whose unchanging grimace makes hers the worst of the film's many humorless performances).</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen has the only funny moments, including a scene in the confessional. Tex sounds suspiciously like a Woody Allen character, as if he had doctored his own lines. Maybe if he had rewritten and directed the entire film, it might have been something.</p>
        <p>Did they all make a pact with the devil? Did someone drug their drinks at a Hollywood party and make them sign contracts while hallucinating? Whatever they thought going in, all the actors look uneasy on screen, as if they were on a plane plummeting from the sky and were putting on brave faces while they crash.</p>
        <p>DIRTY PICTURES  Showtime, tomorrow night at 9</p>
        <p>Directed by Frank Pierson; written by Ilene Chaiken; Michael Manheim, producer; Hiro Narita, director of photography; music by Mark Snow.</p>
        <p>WITH: James Woods (Dennis Barrie), Craig T. Nelson (Leis), Diana Scarwid (Dianne), Leon Pownall (Prouty), David Huband (Sirkin), Judah Katz (Mizibov), R. D. Reid (Albanese) and Matt North (Lobb).</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
