<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jubilant Hezbollah Chief Leaves His Next Move Open</title>
    <meta content="Y26HEZB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Golan Heights</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shebaa Farms</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nasrallah, Hassan (Sheik)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D9123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jubilant Hezbollah Chief Leaves His Next Move Open</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, leader of Hezbollah, refuses to say what direction his country and his movement will take, now that Israel's 18-year occupation of southern Lebanon has ended; he says Hezbollah will not consider withdrawal complete until all Lebanese prisoners are released from Israeli jails and small plot of land called Shebaa Farms near Golan Heights is vacated by Israel; Israeli officials say Shebaa Farms does not figure into withdrawal plans; Nasrallah will not say if his militia would lend arms to fight on behalf of Syria to drive Israel out of Golan Heights or assist Palestinian extremists who may try to use southern Lebanon as launching pad for attacks on Israel; Nasrallah has made no secret of his antipathy toward Israel and United States, but he has tacitly accepted peace negotiations that both Lebanon and its overlord, Syria, have entered into with Israel over past eight years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Israel abruptly gone from southern Lebanon, the militant Islamic group Hezbollah stands at a crossroads. The man who straddles it, with the authority to determine what direction his country and his movement take, is a chubby-cheeked 39-year-old Shiite Muslim cleric named Hassan Nasrallah.</p>
        <p>In Beirut today, as a national holiday was declared to celebrate the Israeli retreat and as Hezbollah solidified its hold on liberated villages in the south, the normally reticent Sheik Nasrallah made grandiose pronouncements as if he were commander in chief of a victorious army after a long campaign -- as many in the Arab world believe he is. He proclaimed that his fighters had won the only Arab victory in the 50-year conflict with Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Israel abruptly gone from southern Lebanon, the militant Islamic group Hezbollah stands at a crossroads. The man who straddles it, with the authority to determine what direction his country and his movement take, is a chubby-cheeked 39-year-old Shiite Muslim cleric named Hassan Nasrallah.</p>
        <p>In Beirut today, as a national holiday was declared to celebrate the Israeli retreat and as Hezbollah solidified its hold on liberated villages in the south, the normally reticent Sheik Nasrallah made grandiose pronouncements as if he were commander in chief of a victorious army after a long campaign -- as many in the Arab world believe he is. He proclaimed that his fighters had won the only Arab victory in the 50-year conflict with Israel.</p>
        <p>He also received a stream of visitors bearing congratulations -- among them the foreign minister of Iran, Kamal Kharazi -- at his beat-up Beirut headquarters, and he fielded questions about his intentions now that Hezbollah's 18-year resistance to Israeli occupation has paid off.</p>
        <p>But Sheik Nasrallah, who has made an art form out of ambiguity to keep both Israel and his rival Lebanese political factions in suspense, still refused to give anything away.</p>
        <p>He repeated what he had said earlier this week -- that Hezbollah does not consider the withdrawal complete and will not until all Lebanese prisoners are released from Israeli jails and a small plot of land called Shebaa Farms near the Golan Heights is vacated by Israel.</p>
        <p>In Israel, officials have said that a portion of that land was never part of Lebanon and so does not figure into any withdrawal plans.</p>
        <p>Sheik Nasrallah said the retreat by Israeli soldiers and many of their allies in the South Lebanon Army  was ''an important step.'' But he would not say whether Hezbollah would give up its military operations if its further conditions were met.</p>
        <p>''We always said that we weren't going to answer that question until a complete withdrawal takes place,,'' he told journalists tonight. ''I know what should be done, but I won't tell you because it's a tactical ploy.''</p>
        <p>Nor would Sheik Nasrallah say whether his militia would lend its arms to a fight on behalf of Syria to drive Israel out of the Golan Heights or assist Palestinian extremists who may try to use southern Lebanon as a launching pad for attacks on Israel.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah -- ''Party of God,'' in Arabic -- has heroic stature in Lebanon and beyond, and Sheik Nasrallah, who has concentrated substantial religious and political authority in his own hands, has both options and constraints in deciding which way to take it.</p>
        <p>He has been the general secretary of the organization since 1992, when his predecessor, Abbas Musawi, was assassinated by Israel forces. Under Sheik Nasrallah's stewardship, Hezbollah has tried to recast itself as a national resistance movement, fielding candidates in parliamentary elections and inviting Sunni Muslims and Christians to join its ranks.</p>
        <p>Trained exclusively in Islamic law and modern weaponry, Sheik Nasrallah has made no secret of his antipathy toward Israel and the United States. Israel, he has said, is a ''cancerous'' interloper in the region. His eldest son, Muhammad Hadi, then 18, was killed in a fight with Israeli soldiers in the security zone in 1997.</p>
        <p>But in his intermittent interviews during the past eight years, he has also tacitly accepted the peace negotiations that both Lebanon and its overlord, Syria, have entered into with Israel. If a peace accord is signed, Sheik Nasrallah has said, Hezbollah will resist as a political party by opposing any normalization of relations with Israel.</p>
        <p>A founding member of Hezbollah, he served as a commander in the Bekaa region during the 1980's, when the militia effectively ran the area, enforcing a strictly puritanical Islamic social code. Now Sheik Nasrallah presides over a many-tentacled organization that not only runs a militia of an estimated 5,000 fighters but manages schools, hospitals, a television station, two radio stations, construction crews, an Internet site and a political party with nine seats in the Lebanese Parliament.</p>
        <p>The organization is tightly structured but still has its layers of diverse elements. Many of its veterans fought with radical Palestinian factions in the civil war and later moved under the Iranian umbrella after the Palestinians were ejected from Beirut. Still others came from Amal, the first national movement representing the traditionally marginalized Shiites. Others are clerics with loyalties to different factions of Shiite theologians in Iraq and Iran.</p>
        <p>Born in 1960, the son of a grocer from the Bekaa, Sheik Nasrallah attended theological schools in two of the famous centers of Shiite Muslim learning -- Karbala, in Iraq, and Qum, in Iran -- before returning to Lebanon in 1982. That year, Israel invaded Lebanon in an effort to control guerrilla attacks on its northern towns. Also that year, Iran, flush with the fervor of its 1979 Islamic revolution, dispatched some 1,000 of its elite Revolutionary Guards to the Bekaa to train Lebanese Muslims in warfare and, according to Western intelligence officials, terrorism.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah, the fruit of their training mission, operated in relative secrecy for two years, first proclaiming itself and its holy war against Israel and the United States in 1984.  But the State Department has accused Hezbollah of being involved or at least suspected of involvement in the 1983 bombings of the United States Embassy in Beirut, which killed 63 people, and the Marine barracks in Beirut, which killed 241. The group later expanded its operations to kidnapping Americans and Europeans in Lebanon.</p>
        <p>Sheik Nasrallah has denied that the group participated in the bombings, but was quoted last month in an Arabic magazine as saying he wished that it had, because ''that would have been a great honor.''</p>
        <p>Israeli analysts see Sheik Nasrallah as the political, rather than military, mastermind of Hezbollah, adept at navigating between the often rival ambitions of the group's main patrons, Iran and Syria, and just as nimble at adjusting to shifts in their policies.</p>
        <p>''He knows how to integrate the pragmatic and the ideological,'' said Shimon Shapira, a military adviser to Benjamin Netanyahu, the former Israeli prime minister, and the author of a book on Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>That attribute was on display in his statements today. Sheik Nasrallah said the time is not yet right for Hezbollah to demand a bigger share of political power in Lebanon or even to try to capitalize on its current  popularity to win a bigger bloc of seats in parliamentary elections in August. ''It's important after a victory to maintain internal unity,'' he said. ''So we would rather keep the same number of seats.</p>
        <p>''The Hezbollah can be modest politically, as well as in every other way,'' he added with a smile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
