<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Can't Understand Why Ordonez Can't Hit</title>
    <meta content="26METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ordonez, Rey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DC133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Can't Understand Why Ordonez Can't Hit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commenting on hitting problem of New York Mets shortstop Rey Ordonez, who is batting .187; his inability to be functional batter is confounding team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With two outs, the bases loaded and the Mets trailing the San Diego Padres by two runs on Wednesday, Manager Bobby Valentine sent Matt Franco to bat for Rey Ordonez. It was not a surprising move -- Ordonez has been removed for a pinch-hitter nine times this season -- but it came in the sixth inning, the earliest Ordonez has been hit for this season.</p>
        <p>The Mets' shortstop, who had been preparing to hit, returned to the dugout, dropped his bat and equipment on the ground and walked out of the Qualcomm Stadium dugout. If he had a problem with the move, he did not say so after the game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With two outs, the bases loaded and the Mets trailing the San Diego Padres by two runs on Wednesday, Manager Bobby Valentine sent Matt Franco to bat for Rey Ordonez. It was not a surprising move -- Ordonez has been removed for a pinch-hitter nine times this season -- but it came in the sixth inning, the earliest Ordonez has been hit for this season.</p>
        <p>The Mets' shortstop, who had been preparing to hit, returned to the dugout, dropped his bat and equipment on the ground and walked out of the Qualcomm Stadium dugout. If he had a problem with the move, he did not say so after the game.</p>
        <p>''I want to bat in that situation, but I'm not a good hitter right now,'' Ordonez said.</p>
        <p>Ordonez is batting .187, and his inability to be a functional hitter is confounding the Mets, who begin a three-game series with the St. Louis Cardinals at Busch Stadium on Friday. They believe he has the ability to hit, but he has not shown it for any extended period this season.</p>
        <p>One scout who saw the Mets-Padres series, in which Ordonez went 0 for 9, said he was stunned by Ordonez's inability to hit a breaking ball; even a foul ball seemed like an accomplishment, the scout said. Batting in front of the pitcher, of course, Ordonez sees his share of breaking balls. He has been unable to lay off them, walking only twice this month.</p>
        <p>''He knows to lay off, but it's easier said than done,'' said Tom Robson, the Mets' hitting coach. ''It's all recognition. It's not chasing breaking balls; it's recognizing that they are breaking balls. He's not trying to hit that down-and-away slider.''</p>
        <p>There have been times when Ordonez has looked good, when he has seemed like a capable hitter. Last Saturday, he was finishing his swing high, and had singles to left and right field. But when Ordonez gets too excited at the plate, Robson said, he regresses. Valentine sees the same thing.</p>
        <p>''He knows exactly what he has to do, and he continues to try to bring it into the game,'' said Valentine, who does not expect to regularly pinch-hit for Ordonez in the middle of games, despite Wednesday's decision.</p>
        <p>''Tom and he talk two times a game or so,'' Valentine said. ''He knows. He goes up with the idea to do it, but sometimes he reverts to his old habits.''</p>
        <p>Valentine clashed with Ordonez early this season in Philadelphia, after the second of two consecutive games in which Ordonez was removed for a pinch-hitter. When Ordonez refused to meet Valentine in his office, Valentine reportedly berated him in front of the team, criticizing his attitude.</p>
        <p>Ordonez said the incident is ''no big deal'' now, and Valentine also played it down. It may be only a coincidence, but the day after the confrontation, Ordonez had three hits.</p>
        <p>The Mets must find out how to motivate Ordonez, because his confidence is important to his hitting. He has been hitting the ball a bit harder lately, Robson said, but he needs some bloops to fall in to raise his average and, thus, his confidence.</p>
        <p>''You fail 7 out of 10 times and you're pretty good, so you're always going to deal with failure,'' Robson said. ''You've got to. That's not easy to do sometimes, especially when you don't get three hits out of every 10 at-bats; you get two out of 10.''</p>
        <p>Ordonez said he recognizes this, and that he does not let one bad day lead to more. ''Every day's a different day,'' he said. ''You go 0 for 4 one day, you go to the park and it's a different day.''</p>
        <p>The Mets need him to hit. A full half of their hitters -- Kurt Abbott, Franco, Mark Johnson, Joe McEwing, Jon Nunnally, Ordonez and Jay Payton -- are batting below .215, which explains why so many potential rallies are snuffed when the 7-8-9-1 hitters come up. But Ordonez is the only everyday player among the struggling.</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez of Seattle will be an alluring free-agent shortstop this winter, but the Mets may be bound to Ordonez, or at least to paying for his four-year, $19 million contract. Such a rich contract for a poor offensive player could be difficult to move in an era in which offense dominates.</p>
        <p>The Mets gave Ordonez the deal to avoid arbitration and to ensure that, if they wish, they can keep together an outstanding defensive infield for several years. Ordonez's defense has not been as automatic as it was last year, when he won his third consecutive Gold Glove, but Valentine said he has no worries about Ordonez defensively.</p>
        <p>While Ordonez got the contract for more than his defense, he was also being rewarded for showing improvement offensively. Ordonez batted .258 last season and drove in 60 runs, both career bests.</p>
        <p>Ordonez said he is trying to concentrate on hitting up the middle and the opposite way. But nothing has worked so far, at least not for more than a few days, and last season's adequate offensive performance is only a memory.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes every year is not the same,'' Ordonez said. ''I want to hit, but I can't. Keep working hard -- that's all I can do.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
