<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Invisible All Night, Smits at Last Saves Pacers</title>
    <meta content="26PACE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smits, Rik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDA133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Invisible All Night, Smits at Last Saves Pacers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rik Smits, Indiana Pacers center, sparked Indiana's 88-84 win over New York Knickerbockers in second game of Eastern Conference finals with dramatic play, following injury to Knicks center Patrick Ewing early in first quarter; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Rik Smits, a giant frozen in ice for three quarters, dropped in a layup and converted a free throw for a 3-point play with eight minutes remaining in Game 2 of the Eastern Conference finals tonight, the Pacers trailed by 3 points. As he emerged, he suddenly brought his team back to life as well.</p>
        <p>Indiana's 7-foot-4-inch center, playing without the 7-foot shadow of Patrick Ewing beside him, found himself in uncharted territory -- the fourth quarter -- usually the time when he retires to the bench burdened with aching feet and fouls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Rik Smits, a giant frozen in ice for three quarters, dropped in a layup and converted a free throw for a 3-point play with eight minutes remaining in Game 2 of the Eastern Conference finals tonight, the Pacers trailed by 3 points. As he emerged, he suddenly brought his team back to life as well.</p>
        <p>Indiana's 7-foot-4-inch center, playing without the 7-foot shadow of Patrick Ewing beside him, found himself in uncharted territory -- the fourth quarter -- usually the time when he retires to the bench burdened with aching feet and fouls.</p>
        <p>But there he was in the final nine minutes of the game, revitalized, making 3-point plays, collecting loose balls and dunking with authority, in dramatic contrast to his dismal 1-for-7 beginning.</p>
        <p>''I felt good in the fourth quarter, so I said, 'Forget about it,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Smits played with five fouls for the final 6 minutes 27 seconds, but he nonetheless showed a carefree, sacrificial mentality, scoring 10 of his 12 points in the fourth quarter to spark Indiana to an 88-84 victory in a crucial Game 2.</p>
        <p>''The reason why we won the ball game was because of Rik,'' the Pacers' Reggie Miller said. ''That 3-point play at the end was huge.''</p>
        <p>Smits did not have the game of Jalen Rose, who was reliably hot from start to finish, playing all 48 minutes. Nor did Smits have the 16 rebounds of Dale Davis. It was Davis's rebound off his own miss at the foul line in the final 5.8 seconds, and Rose's resounding dunk, that preserved the victory.</p>
        <p>But it was Smits's two 3-point plays leading up to the dramatic finish that made it all possible. On his first 3-point play, Allan Houston was assessed his fifth foul. On the second 3-point play, Smits beat out Houston and Latrell Sprewell for a loose ball, then finished the play with a resounding dunk and converted the foul shot to tie the game at 80-80 with 3:01 left.</p>
        <p>''I saw a loose ball and then an open path to the basket. I ended up getting a good look at the basket,'' Smits said. He got the looks in the first half, but could not complete the plays.</p>
        <p>''Rik was frustrated in the first half,'' Coach Larry Bird said. ''He looked like he was off-balance all night, but he did make some good plays for us down the stretch.''</p>
        <p>Smits's teammates were much more effusive. ''I've said all along that Rik is the key to this series,'' Mark Jackson said. ''He's going to get those open looks and he can knock them down.''</p>
        <p>In the beginning, Smits found the basket closed for business, though, missing his first six shots in awkward fashion. Austin Croshere, who led the Pacers with 22 points in Game 1, missed his first seven shots, too, and the problem seemed symbolic of a Pacers team struggling to take advantage when the Knicks lost Ewing early in the first quarter to a foot injury.</p>
        <p>Indiana was its own enemy. ''A lot of guys shot so well in Game 1 that we were taking our shots for granted tonight,'' Smits said. ''I might have rushed my shots. You think, 'I don't have it going tonight, maybe I should pass.' When you think about it too much, that's what happens.''</p>
        <p>By the time he re-entered the game in the the fourth quarter, with the Pacers trailing, 69-65, Smits was no longer thinking about his struggles, only about winning. ''I personally hadn't done anything all game,'' he said. ''I did not care if I picked up more fouls, I had to do something out there. At that point, there's nothing to lose.''</p>
        <p>At this point, the Knicks are the team with everything to lose, heading back to New York with a 2-0 deficit and Ewing's status once again in question.</p>
        <p>''Not knowing if Patrick is going to play a lot, Rik has to put a lot of pressure on Kurt Thomas, Chris Dudley and Marcus Camby, because we feel they have no answer for him,'' Miller said.</p>
        <p>''When he gets it going like that and can command the double team, that will make shots a lot easier on the perimeter for me and Jalen. He is the one player, as well as Mark, when they get on the low post, who can demand the double team.''</p>
        <p>And, as Smits has scored 28 points in the first two games of the series, he has proven he can demand the ball with results.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
