<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Jets Loaded With Passers, Lucas Becomes the Odd Man Out</title>
    <meta content="26JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Chad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucas, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D9123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Jets Loaded With Passers, Lucas Becomes the Odd Man Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ray Lucas, quarterback who in large part helped salvage Jets' 1999 football season, is being squeezed out as heir apparent to Vinny Testaverde by new quarterback-in-waiting Chad Pennington but seems unruffled (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ray Lucas approached his locker on the opening day of the Jets' minicamp and saw a cluster of reporters engulfing Vinny Testaverde. As Lucas squeezed by, he joked about how little space he has when reporters are around, situated as he is between Testaverde and the team's new quarterback-in-waiting, Chad Pennington.</p>
        <p>The geography of locker assignments has become weirdly symbolic for the Jets this spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ray Lucas approached his locker on the opening day of the Jets' minicamp and saw a cluster of reporters engulfing Vinny Testaverde. As Lucas squeezed by, he joked about how little space he has when reporters are around, situated as he is between Testaverde and the team's new quarterback-in-waiting, Chad Pennington.</p>
        <p>The geography of locker assignments has become weirdly symbolic for the Jets this spring.</p>
        <p>Lucas, whose 85.1 quarterback rating last season ranked him seventh in the National Football League and third in the American Conference, is wedged between the star quarterback of the present and the player whom Coach Al Groh anointed as the quarterback of the future moments after his selection in the first round of the draft.</p>
        <p>The player who, in large part, helped salvage the Jets' 1999 season, going 6-2 in eight starts after Testaverde was hurt on opening day and Rick Mirer proved to be ineffective, is now, it seems, being squeezed out as the Jets' heir apparent.</p>
        <p>But Lucas is as unruffled today as he was when he played last season. He seems, in fact, to relish the abundance of quarterbacks as the Jets opened their four-day minicamp on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''What team has three good quarterbacks?'' Lucas said. ''Not many. What am I going to cry about? Surprised? Yeah. That's how the business is. You've got to prove it every year. I can't rest on what I did last year. I only played nine games. It doesn't make me the savior of New York. It's not a slap; it's business. There is no gratitude in the N.F.L.''</p>
        <p>Last season, Lucas completed 161 of 272 passes for 1,678 yards and 14 touchdowns, and he had undoubtedly hoped to cash in with a long-term contract. But the Jets are unlikely to commit themselves to Lucas now.</p>
        <p>As an exclusive rights player, he will probably have to settle for the one-year tender worth $385,000 that the Jets offered. Next year, Lucas will be a restricted free agent.</p>
        <p>Groh said he had not talked to Lucas about his contract, because he does not see any signs that Lucas is upset. He also said that Lucas seems more self-assured in practices because he has had game experience.</p>
        <p>Asked how Lucas should feel about the selection of Pennington, Groh said, ''He ought to look at it as it's our job to surround ourselves with the best players we can.''</p>
        <p>Lucas declined to discuss the specifics of his contract situation.</p>
        <p>''The money is nice,'' he said. ''If I work hard, it will be there some day. I'll catch up to it eventually. The best thing is my players believe in me. To this day, they know if I get on the field we have a chance to win. That's the only thing that matters to me.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Nose tackle JASON FERGUSON, who was a restricted free agent, signed a one-year deal this week. His hopes for a long-term contract were dashed by the Jets' salary cap constraints, he said. ''They won't pay Keyshawn or Mo, you know they're not going to pay me,'' Ferguson said with a laugh, referring to the tense contract negotiations that led to KEYSHAWN JOHNSON's trade and MO LEWIS's one-year contract. . . . The rookie defensive lineman SHAUN ELLIS and offensive tackle RYAN YOUNG got into a scuffle during practice that quickly escalated into a scrum involving at least a dozen players. ''I told him very quietly that that's what you've got to do in this league; you've got to stand up for yourself,'' Coach AL GROH said of Ellis. ''I'll put up with it one time. The next time it will indicate to me he's a hothead.'' . .  The Jets will have to cut veterans to make room under the salary cap to sign their four first-round draft picks, but Groh dampened speculation that linebacker ROMAN PHIFER, or anyone else, would be cut June 1. The Jets may instead wait until they are ready to sign the picks to make the cuts.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
