<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frazar Handles Wind and Rolls to a Three-Shot Lead</title>
    <meta content="26GOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memorial Tournament (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perry, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scherrer, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frazar, Harrison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4D6123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frazar Handles Wind and Rolls to a Three-Shot Lead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, Ohio, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harrison Frazar holds three-stroke lead at end of first round of Memorial Tournament in Dublin, Ohio, with six-under-par 66; Ken Perry and Tom Scherrer are tied for second place (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day when only three players broke 70, Harrison Frazar broke away from the field.</p>
        <p>To call the first round of the Memorial Tournament a test would be an understatement. Not only did tricky winds gust to 20 miles an hour today, but the Muirfield Village Golf Club course has also been toughened for this year's event under the watchful eyes of the designer and the host, Jack Nicklaus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day when only three players broke 70, Harrison Frazar broke away from the field.</p>
        <p>To call the first round of the Memorial Tournament a test would be an understatement. Not only did tricky winds gust to 20 miles an hour today, but the Muirfield Village Golf Club course has also been toughened for this year's event under the watchful eyes of the designer and the host, Jack Nicklaus.</p>
        <p>But Frazar grew up in Abilene, Tex., where golfers learn to deal with wind as soon as they learn to grip a club. Today, Frazar had an extremely firm grip on his game as he shot an impressive six-under-par 66 to take a three-stroke lead.</p>
        <p>Kenny Perry and Tom Scherrer were tied for second place at 69, while four players were tied at 70: Justin Leonard, Greg Norman, Gabriel Hjertstedt and Greg Kraft.</p>
        <p>How solid was Frazar? He is the first PGA Tour player this year to lead by three strokes after the first round. Today, he was the only player who did not make a bogey. And though the par-5 holes have been made more difficult this year at Muirfield, Frazar birdied all four of them.</p>
        <p>After two third-place finishes this year in Greensboro, N.C., and New Orleans, Frazar, at age 28, believes his first tour victory could be forthcoming, perhaps even this weekend.</p>
        <p>''I grew up in Texas, which just makes you more comfortable when the wind blows,'' said Frazar, who is 35th on this year's money list with $524,085.</p>
        <p>''You're used to hearing the wind whistle through your hat, so the panic mode doesn't come in as much. I don't get to the golf course and hope that it blows 20 miles an hour. But if it does, I feel like I've got a pretty good shot.''</p>
        <p>Frazar's work was far from done. Tiger Woods, the world's No. 1 player and the defending champion, was five strokes behind Frazar after shooting an opening-round 71.</p>
        <p>The most popular player at this course remained Nicklaus, who was honored Wednesday during an emotional ceremony, and who provided some excitement today. Nicklaus struggled for most of his round, but he birdied three of the final four holes to finish with a very respectable 75.</p>
        <p>Leave it to Nicklaus, at age 60, to finish strong. After making an 11-foot putt for birdie at No. 15, he hit his approach shot at No. 17 to six feet, then made the birdie putt. Then, after missing the green on his approach shot at No. 18, Nicklaus ended the day by chipping in for a birdie from 20 feet, as the gallery roared.</p>
        <p>''From where I was, it was a lot of fun to finish that way,'' Nicklaus said. ''I struggled something awful with my putter, but I finally made one at No. 15, and that opened up the floodgates.''</p>
        <p>It was also a good day for Nicklaus's son, Gary, who shot 72, despite making bogeys on No. 16 and No. 18.</p>
        <p>''Knowing what this golf tournament means to my father and to my mother, I've wanted to play in this for a long time,'' said Gary Nicklaus, a rookie on tour, who lost to Phil Mickelson in a playoff last month at the BellSouth Classic. ''It's very special for me to be here.''</p>
        <p>But Frazar will begin Friday as the man to catch. He and Leonard were college roommates at the University of Texas, and while Leonard joined the tour right after college and became a star, Frazar took a different path. He sold real estate for a year, uncertain if he wanted to make golf his career. Eventually, his love for the game brought him back, and being on the tour has reunited him with Leonard, who remains a close friend.</p>
        <p>Leonard has been mired in the worst slump of his career, without a top 10 finish all year. So while Frazar was pleased with his own performance, he was also pleased to see Leonard shoot 70.</p>
        <p>''If anyone is going to rebound and be better for it, it's Justin,'' Frazar said. ''He could bounce back and win three of the next four tournaments.''</p>
        <p>But Frazar hoped that Sunday would be his turn to win, although no first-round leader has gone on to win the Memorial.</p>
        <p>''I've been playing really well the past couple of months,'' he said. ''I guess you could say I felt it coming.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
