<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton, in Rochester, Takes On Queries on Motive</title>
    <meta content="26HILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0D8123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton, in Rochester, Takes On Queries on Motive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton uses town hall forum in Rochester, NY, in part to answer what she acknowledges are continuing concerns about her ambitions and motives in running for Senate seat to represent state in which she never lived until five months ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton used a town hall forum in Rochester yesterday in part to answer what she acknowledged were continuing concerns about her ambitions and motives in running for a Senate seat representing a state where she had never lived until five months ago.</p>
        <p>Would she serve a full six-year term?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton used a town hall forum in Rochester yesterday in part to answer what she acknowledged were continuing concerns about her ambitions and motives in running for a Senate seat representing a state where she had never lived until five months ago.</p>
        <p>Would she serve a full six-year term?</p>
        <p>''I am committed,'' Mrs. Clinton said, ''because I think it would take a good six years to be able to accomplish issues that I care about. Doing what I would like to see us do to get the pieces in place for a good economic strategy, you can't do that in a year or two or three.''</p>
        <p>Will she live in New York even if she loses?</p>
        <p>''Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>When told by a participant that ''many of your potential colleagues in the U.S. Senate knew you as a polarizing personality; that scares me,'' Mrs. Clinton rattled off a list of issues on which she has worked with the Republican leadership. And she drew titters with an end point, ''After what I've been through for the last seven years nothing they can say can possibly hurt my feelings.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton has addressed some of those concerns before, particularly on her residency and ambitions, but they have been freshly raised by her new opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, a Long Island Republican who announced his candidacy on Saturday after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani dropped out.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton took questions for about an hour and a half from 85 people participating by e-mail, by fax and in a studio for a ''Voice of the Voter'' program sponsored by WXXI Public Broadcasting, WOKR-TV and the Rochester Democrat &amp; Chronicle. The program was broadcast live on radio and the Internet and was to be shown last night on television in an upstate region where the two candidates are vying for critical votes.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton appeared on the program after a Manhattan news conference to accept the endorsement of the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League. Mr. Lazio scoffed at the endorsement, saying he too is ''pro-choice.'' But he has drawn criticism from abortion rights advocates for opposing public financing for abortions and a late-term procedure critics call ''partial birth abortion,'' a stance he says is more in line with ''mainstream New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>Many questions, however, focused as much on style as on substance. Mrs. Clinton appeared poised in response to questions about her personality and ambitions, issues Republicans cite as faults. She sounded surprised only when she was asked ''if you were to die tonight do you know if you would spend eternity in heaven or hell, and if you don't know would you allow me to tell you how you could know?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton seemed to wrestle with a response. She started by saying ''I greatly respect the question'' and ended with ''I also do not believe that we should be, in public, putting people in a position of responding to questions that are really focused on ones of personal faith.''</p>
        <p>In between she said, ''I hope that I will be someone who will live a life that is worthy of my strong Methodism and my Christian faith and my commitment to doing the very best I can to keep the example of our Lord and savior. But I cannot tell you where I will be. I can only hope and pray that I will find favor in God's eyes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio only came up once directly, when a questioner inquired about the linking by her supporters of Mr. Lazio to former House Speaker Newt Gingrich. Mr. Lazio supported much of Mr. Gingrich's so-called Contract With America, the 1994 agenda of conservative policies that Republicans used to regain control of the House.</p>
        <p>''I cannot speak for all my supporters because certainly the facts are that he was closely allied'' with Mr. Gingrich during those years, she said. ''I think New Yorkers need to know that.''</p>
        <p>And, responding to a question on whether she would favor local issues as Alfonse D'Amato initially did or national ones, like Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Mrs. Clinton stayed in the middle. ''I would hope to do both,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
