<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Proud Met Unveils a Prize</title>
    <meta content="26INSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ps 1 Center for Contemporary Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Acquavella Galleries</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carracci, Ludovico (1555-1619)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koons, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Findlay, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D6153DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Proud Met Unveils a Prize</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; Metropolitan Museum hangs newly-restored Ludovico Carracci painting The Lamentation, bought in January at Christies for $5.2 million; photo; soaring prices for work by Jeff Koons and Guggenheim's plans for retrospective noted; merger of PS 1 gallery and Museum of Modern Art complete merger; Michael Findlay, retiring from Christie's, will direct Acquavella Galleries (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After four months of conservation and restoration, the Metropolitan Museum of Art has hung a recent acquisition: ''The Lamentation'' by the Italian Baroque painter Ludovico Carracci.</p>
        <p>The museum bought the painting for $5.2 million at Christie's in January. The price was huge, considering that the estimate had been $300,000 to $500,000. But at auction all it takes is two serious bidders, and in this case the Met's competition was the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After four months of conservation and restoration, the Metropolitan Museum of Art has hung a recent acquisition: ''The Lamentation'' by the Italian Baroque painter Ludovico Carracci.</p>
        <p>The museum bought the painting for $5.2 million at Christie's in January. The price was huge, considering that the estimate had been $300,000 to $500,000. But at auction all it takes is two serious bidders, and in this case the Met's competition was the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.</p>
        <p>Painted around 1582, ''The Lamentation'' is a sprawling image of Jesus that stretches the full width of the canvas, which measures 37 1/2 by 68 inches. Not only are works by Carracci rare, but the painting itself is also considered exceptional.</p>
        <p>''It marks the beginning of the Baroque,'' said Andrea Bayer, assistant curator of European paintings at the Met. ''The naturalist treatment of the body of Christ is incredible and was painted from a live studio model.''</p>
        <p>The painting had been in a South American collection, with no artist's attribution. But when it arrived at Christie's, Anthony Crichton-Stuart, head of the old master paintings department, noticed that ''there were two old labels on the back marked Palazzo Tanari in Bologna,'' he said. ''Alessandro Tanari, who died in 1639, was an important collector of contemporary Bolognese painting.'' Mr. Crichton-Stuart said the painting was stylistically similar to others by Carracci, most notably in the angular faces, the exaggerated perspective and the coloration.</p>
        <p>The Met already has four paintings by Annibale Carracci, the artist's far better-known cousin. This is its first painting by Ludovico. The museum is organizing ''The Beginning of Baroque: Carracci at the Metropolitan,'' which is to open on July 7 and will include paintings, drawings and prints.</p>
        <p>Koons Redux</p>
        <p>Jeff Koons, the 1980's art star who drifts on and off the art world's radar screen, is making yet another comeback. Prices for his work have been soaring: one collector paid $1.8 million at Christie's in November for a porcelain sculpture of a seminude blond woman hugging a Pink Panther. Last week another paid $1.7 million there for a sculpture of a woman sitting in a bubble bath clutching her breasts.</p>
        <p>Another Koons creation, a 43-foot-tall terrier puppy made of live flowers, is being installed at the site in Rockefeller Center where the Christmas tree stands every year. And yesterday ''Split-Rocker,'' a 40-foot-tall topiary -- half pony, half dino -- with 75,000 live flowers in the shape of a giant child's rocking toy was unveiled in the Benoit XII Cloister in the Papal Palace in Avignon, France.</p>
        <p>''For a while everybody wanted to know what happened to Jeff,'' said Lisa Dennison, deputy director and chief curator of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, who has been closely involved with Mr. Koons's work. For years the museum has been planning a major Koons retrospective. It was unofficially scheduled for this month, then officially announced for next May. Now, Ms. Dennison said, the Guggenheim hopes to hold the exhibition in the fall of 2003 or the winter of 2004.</p>
        <p>Some of the delays have been due to the high costs of fabrication and technical difficulties in making the works that are part of ''Celebration,'' a series of large-scale sculptures and paintings. Because of their size and the materials -- stainless steel and plastics that are hard to manufacture -- they require special use of foundries, a cost that has nearly bankrupted some dealers who hoped to produce the pieces.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koons wanted to finish the ''Celebration'' series before the retrospective, Ms. Dennison said. He also wanted to have a body of new work that could be shown for the first time at the Guggenheim.</p>
        <p>Several months ago Mr. Koons returned to the Sonnabend Gallery, which has handled him on and off since 1986. In November the gallery showed some of his ''Easyfun'' series, a dozen large tinted mirrors based on generic cartoon animals, including a sheep, a donkey, a bear, a kangaroo and a cow. Now Sonnabend is working with galleries in Europe to present a series of ''Easyfun'' shows that also include paintings and one sculpture. The shows are to be in London, Berlin, Paris and Milan. Larry Gagosian is also planning a show of Mr. Koons's work in his Los Angeles space in March.</p>
        <p>Opening on Oct. 26 at the Deutsche Guggenheim Berlin will be a show of several new paintings commissioned for that space. ''The work will probably travel to Bilbao,'' Ms. Dennison said. ''Then it will enter the collection of the Guggenheim Museum and Deutsche Bank.''</p>
        <p>'We're Cooking'</p>
        <p>Although it has been 15 months since P.S. 1 and the Museum of Modern Art announced their intention to merge, the deal was approved by the New York State Board of Regents only a month ago, and the two institutions met just last week to approve a new board. It has 27 members: 18 nominated by P.S. 1 and approved by the Modern, and 9 nominated by the Modern and approved by P.S. 1. ''The deal is done,'' said Glenn D. Lowry, director of the Modern. ''We're open for business and we're cooking.''</p>
        <p>Retire? Hardly</p>
        <p>Michael Findlay has taken early retirement after 16 years at Christie's. But that doesn't mean he plans to stop working. William Acquavella announced this week that Mr. Findlay, whose most recent job at Christie's was international director of fine arts, would become the director of the Acquavella Galleries on East 79th Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The new post will entail buying and selling art, Mr. Acquavella said, as well as helping with the administration of the gallery. ''I'm ready to concentrate on a smaller number of paintings and a smaller number of collectors,'' Mr. Findlay said.</p>
        <p>Much of his work at Christie's involved working with dealers and collectors in Southeast Asia. ''He was our ambassador there,'' said Edward Dolman, Christie's chief executive worldwide. Replacing him in Asia will be Toshihiko Hatanaka, who works for Christie's in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
