<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nights Of Jazz, Sweet And Hot</title>
    <meta content="26JAZZ$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000529T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vision Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jvc Jazz Festival</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DB123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nights Of Jazz, Sweet And Hot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff preview of three upcoming jazz events in New York City: list of scheduled performances in Vision Festival, Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival and JVC Jazz Festival; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IVEY-DIVEY, as Lester Young would have said.  June is almost upon us, and as usual, jazz clubs, independent concert producers and the big jazz festivals -- there are now three -- are wrangling for the attention of New Yorkers. This means an astonishing bounty for anyone interested in jazz (with Latin music, gospel and soul as connected satellite genres, in the tradition of the big festivals). There's no choice but to see it as one big unofficial citywide festival, the best and most complete in the world.</p>
        <p>The Vision Festival, now in its fifth year, has been an unexpected success, marshaling various strands of jazz bohemianism into an 11-day series with the air of a community effort much more than of a business venture. The Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival, presided over by Michael Dorf, was once a midget slinging pebbles from the cultural margins, but it has become the great enveloper, taking up much of the burden of presenting jazz from all subgenres and ingeniously marketing it on the Internet and its Knitting Factory record label. This year's edition features more outdoor events, many of them gigantic bills and some of them free. (This is a positive development: it will help New Yorkers return to the notion of festivals as something fun that spills all over a public space, rather than self-contained, wallet-chewing affairs.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IVEY-DIVEY, as Lester Young would have said.  June is almost upon us, and as usual, jazz clubs, independent concert producers and the big jazz festivals -- there are now three -- are wrangling for the attention of New Yorkers. This means an astonishing bounty for anyone interested in jazz (with Latin music, gospel and soul as connected satellite genres, in the tradition of the big festivals). There's no choice but to see it as one big unofficial citywide festival, the best and most complete in the world.</p>
        <p>The Vision Festival, now in its fifth year, has been an unexpected success, marshaling various strands of jazz bohemianism into an 11-day series with the air of a community effort much more than of a business venture. The Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival, presided over by Michael Dorf, was once a midget slinging pebbles from the cultural margins, but it has become the great enveloper, taking up much of the burden of presenting jazz from all subgenres and ingeniously marketing it on the Internet and its Knitting Factory record label. This year's edition features more outdoor events, many of them gigantic bills and some of them free. (This is a positive development: it will help New Yorkers return to the notion of festivals as something fun that spills all over a public space, rather than self-contained, wallet-chewing affairs.)</p>
        <p>The JVC Jazz Festival, led by George Wein, has refined its formula of the concert as major event to the point that more and more of its bookings are closely modeled on successful shows from earlier years; on the other hand, as an interesting turn, its Symphony Space series is full of artists who were yesterday's downtown rebels.</p>
        <p>To curb your frustration over the too-much blues, here's a list of recommendations for the end of May and the month of June in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>TONIGHT:  Vision Festival, New Age Cabaret. The fifth annual Vision Festival, which brings together much that lies on the wilder shores of jazz and improvised music, continues through the weekend. Tonight's program features the Michele Rosewoman quintet, a strong mainstream jazz project led by a New York musician who has long been ahead of the curve with jazz's new rhythmic developments.</p>
        <p>There's a trio with the alto saxophonist Rob Brown, the drummer Hamid Drake and the violinist Mat Maneri, three of the most talented musicians playing in the avant-garde. Kidd Jordan, New Orleans saxophonist, is to share a quartet with the drummer Alvin Fielder, who hasn't been heard much since the 80's. Also on the bill: the adventurous clarinetist Perry Robinson, in a quartet, and one of the festival favorites, the quintessential, tear-the-walls-down  ensemble called Other Dimensions in Music.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON QUINTET,  Village Vanguard. Some of the best musicians make instruments seem small in their hands. The trombonist Wycliffe Gordon is one of those; in almost every Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra concert, it is guaranteed that he will play something -- maybe only a detail, not always a full-fledged improvisation -- with such extraordinary deftness that he wins over the audience completely. On one level, his band is as straight as it gets: it's Ellington- and Basie-inspired, suitable for all ages. But Mr. Gordon's manipulations of sound in his careful improvisations (he is armed with several kinds of mutes) are as exciting as it gets.</p>
        <p>Monday</p>
        <p>GUILLERMO KLEIN AND LOS GUACHOS,  Jazz Standard. Mr. Klein, from Argentina, has a broad view of what can be accomplished by a big band; traces of Hermeto Pascoal, Steve Reich and Kenny Wheeler filter through his music, and he achieves a choral effect in his broad saxophone section. It's brilliant, colorful stuff, whispered about hotly among musicians; after years of sporadic gigs, this regular Monday  night engagement at the Jazz Standard may prove to be an important booking for one of the decade's most promising young artists.</p>
        <p>Tuesday</p>
        <p>ERIC REED'S NEW YORK SEVEN,  Village Vanguard. After years of playing in a trio, it was great to see the young pianist Eric Reed busy himself with some larger-scale arrangements last year. And the band, more so than is represented on his records, is actually a band: a fearsome one with a particularly swinging rhythm section, boasting the bassist Barak Mori and the young wonder drummer Rodney Green.</p>
        <p>Wednesday</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO HIP-BOP TRIO,  Iridium. Mr. Martino is one of jazz's finest guitarists, with a limpid sound and a subtle mode of expression. But he still likes to play in the earthy, funky context he began with the 1960's in Philadelphia. His new trio includes Larry Goldings, an organist, and a drummer, Idris Muhammad, one of the funkiest players alive.</p>
        <p>Thursday</p>
        <p>ORNETTE COLEMAN,  Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival, the Lawn, Battery Park. This compressed display of Mr. Coleman's abilities has three parts: ''Freedom Symbol,'' a composition for a 20-piece classical chamber ensemble with a cadenza for each performer, which dates to 1989; it was performed at Alice Tully Hall several years ago, but because of the nature of Mr. Coleman's art, it's quite different each time. Then there's a performance by Global Expression Project, which puts Mr. Coleman, the bassist Charnett Moffett and the drummer Denardo Coleman in the context of three Indian percussionists; and finally the Ornette Coleman Trio, with Charlie Haden and Billy Higgins. These three -- usually with a fourth member, but no matter -- have produced some of the most important music in the second half of the 20th century. As they have proved in recent years, they're still capable of making time stop.</p>
        <p>Next Friday</p>
        <p>CHARLIE HADEN'S QUARTET WEST WITH STRING ORCHESTRA,  the Angel Orensanz Foundation. The foundation, a beautiful, crumbling synagogue on the Lower East Side, will be the co-star of this concert. Never having heard a full orchestra fill its great space, I can only imagine that Mr. Haden's romance-drenched love letters to the 1940's and 50's might find their sweet spot there.</p>
        <p>June 3</p>
        <p>URI CAINE'S GOLDBERG VARIATIONS,  Jazz Standard. Mr. Caine's ''Golderg Variations'' album, to be released in June on Winter &amp; Winter, is the latest installment in this pianist's continuing series of rather ingenious takes on classical music. Here he takes several dozen of Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations and reinterprets them with the help of singers, a swinging clarinet, a D.J.  and others. The performed version is  not your everyday club gig; it ends a week at the club for Mr. Caine, preceded by his jazz trio and his radical Gustav Mahler project.</p>
        <p>June 4</p>
        <p>MAX ROACH AND CECIL TAYLOR,  Bell Atlantic Festival, Columbia University Steps. At Town Hall in 1989, the last time Mr. Roach and Mr. Taylor played together in the United States, their duet was one of the best shows I had ever seen: it was full of each musician's usual patterns yet  they found a common ground. Opening this concert is the rough-and-ready David S. Ware Quartet, which has mellowed a little, judging from its new record, ''Surrendered'' (Columbia/Sony); a duet by the drummer Joey Baron and the bassist Ron Carter; and Bob Stewart leading the  LaGuardia High School Jazz Band, a surprisingly mighty ensemble of teenagers.</p>
        <p>June 5</p>
        <p>ROSWELL RUDD AND BROAD STROKES,  Bell Atlantic Festival, Knitting Factory. The rehabilitation of the trombonist Roswell Rudd's career in the last few years has resulted in some unforgettable local performances: with the reunited New York Art Quartet last summer  and with Sonic Youth at the Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity in Brooklyn Heights last winter, a show so good that even after many minutes of Mr. Rudd's yawped declamations over the rock band's ringing drones, you still wanted more. Here it is: Mr. Rudd's new 12-piece band Broad Strokes (can it really have three vocalists, as advertised?) will be joined by three-quarters of Sonic Youth.</p>
        <p>June 6</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY QUINTET,  Bell Atlantic Festival, Knitting Factory. This is a band that keeps getting better; if you want to hear the future of jazz as art, look here. Mr. Osby, the saxophonist, plays thin, pinpointed lines over a fluctuating rhythm section, the band improvises its form onstage and the leader's connection with the pianist Jason Moran has become one of the great partnerships in the recent history of the music. If you've experienced Mr. Osby on record as a little dry, see what happens when the band loosens up onstage.</p>
        <p>June 7</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE,  Bell Atlantic Festival, Knitting Factory. The saxophonist is focused and voluminous; the four different bands he is showing in one night aren't so much different personalities as different mouthpieces for his brand of sprawling, contracting and expanding, odd-meter music. Paraphrase and Big Satan are familiar trios, but the next two groups, Quicksand and Composure, promise a slightly different palette, with the involvement of the pianist Craig Taborn; it's hard to remember the last time Mr. Berne played alongside any kind of keyboards.</p>
        <p>June 8</p>
        <p>MATTHEW SHIPP STRING TRIO,  Knitting Factory. JAMES CARTER,  Blue Note. The boundary between composition and improvisation is never blurrier than with Mr. Shipp, the pianist, and his trio of piano, bass and violin; I had heard the band's dark, slow, sweeping, abstract and volatile music quite a bit on record and was still taken aback to hear it replicate long album tracks pretty much as I remembered them. Then, head over to the Blue Note to hear the outgoing, excitable saxophonist. From a different end of the entertainment spectrum, Mr. Carter will be playing selections from a rocking new record, ''Layin' In the Cut'' (Atlantic), which treats the avant-funk of the early 80's -- the James Blood Ulmer/Jamaaladeen Tacuma school -- as sacred texts. It's exhilarating music and a good interpretive idea.</p>
        <p>June 9</p>
        <p>''AS LONG AS YOU'RE LIVING YOURS'': THE MUSIC OF KEITH JARRETT,  Jazz Standard. This gig, timed to an RCA record release of the same name, isn't a bad idea because Mr. Jarrett's impressionistic written music gets short shrift in deference to his stature as a soloist. The band looks tempting, including the saxophonists George Garzone and Jimmy Greene and the drummer Billy Kilson, one of the sparks of Dave Holland's great new band.</p>
        <p>June 10</p>
        <p>ROY HAYNES TRIO,  Birdland. It sounds like a cliche, but at 75, Mr. Haynes isn't slowing down: he's still the razor-sharp dresser, master rhythm-displacer and loud snare-drum hitter he was in the bebop days. He's so naturally modern it hurts, and his new record, ''The Roy Haynes Trio'' (Verve/Universal),  with Danilo Perez and John Patitucci, is a challenge to rhythm sections everywhere.</p>
        <p>June 11</p>
        <p>LOS LOBOS, LOS VAN VAN, BARBARITO TORRES, DAVID SANCHEZ SEXTET, BOBBY SANABRIA Y ASCENSION,  Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival, Austin J. Tobin Plaza, World Trade Center. Maybe it's only marginally jazz, but what a wild bill, predicated only on improvisation, the Spanish language and musical excellence. The Cal-Mex band Los Lobos seems to have been around forever, and it may still be the best rock band in America. The Cuban group Los Van Van could take the title of best dance band in the world. Barbarito Torres's old, elegant style on the lutelike laud is known to all followers of the Buena Vista phenomenon. David Sanchez, from Puerto Rico, is a superior jazz player, whether he's using the rhythms and forms of his island or not. The percussionist Bobby Sanabria draws on some of the best of the jazz and Latin players in New York for his octet.</p>
        <p>June 14</p>
        <p>JVC TRIBUTE TO CHARLIE BYRD AND GEORGE VAN EPS,  JVC Jazz Festival, Kaye Playhouse. Plenty of festival tributes are about love, respect and  homage but tributes to guitar players inspire more than that. JVC festival's annual guitar-a-thon concerts, produced by Charles Carlini, tend toward flat-out obsession. The long parade of guitarists who come out to play a few numbers can seem a little daunting on paper, but these concerts build up a rhythm of their own  and the bated breath of guitar-players in the audience gives these events a peculiar urgency. On the bill: the rhythmically muscular Ron Affif, the quiet-as-a-mouse Gene Bertoncini and the fluid utility players Howard Alden and Frank Vignola as well as Bucky Pizzarelli, Mark Whitfield and others.</p>
        <p>June 16</p>
        <p>JOAO GILBERTO,  JVC Jazz Festival, Carnegie Hall. Early this year, Mr. Gilberto, the bossa nova originator, put out a new record, ''Joao Voz e Violao''; he has been both reviled for it (by those who wish he would record some new songs) and praised for it. You can't help liking the voice deepened with age and the Swiss-watch sense of rhythm negotiated between his guitar and his singing, with no orchestrations to get in the way. But the album, to be released in the United States in June, is close to what he delivered two years ago at a similar Carnegie Hall concert, which was extraordinary. Most of us would settle for a replica. If you haven't seen him before, go.</p>
        <p>June 17</p>
        <p>PETER BROTZMANN TENTET,  Hammerstein Ballroom. In the last decade, Mr. Brotzmann, the German saxophonist, has become something of a father figure for American free-jazz musicians, especially in Chicago, where the jazz bohemians are studious and organized and win MacArthur prizes.</p>
        <p>His Tentet, filled with the cream of the Chicago out-jazz scene, leans toward written arrangements -- a good thing for Mr. Brotzmann, whose bellowing tone could rip a hole in the wall and who has more musicality than he often lets on. (At the Ballroom, he is opening for Sonic Youth.)</p>
        <p>June 18</p>
        <p>JOHN LURIE AND THE LOUNGE LIZARDS,  JVC Jazz Festival, Symphony Space. It's the 20th-anniversary concert for a band that nobody, initially, could have predicted would last. The band has come so far from the jokey, awkward ''fake jazz'' it started out with that you need to revise your opinion, if you heard it then and haven't paid attention since. In the new Lounge Lizards, African and Asian music sits comfortably with good old American humor and pathos, and sometimes the band will play something so richly Ellingtonian that even Wynton Marsalis would approve.</p>
        <p>June 20</p>
        <p>RUBEN BLADES,  JVC Jazz Festival, Carnegie Hall. One of the great singers and lyricists in popular music, Mr. Blades since the early 70's has combined political acuity with a strong, communicative musical enthusiasm; he doesn't condescend to his audiences by overmoralizing when he sings about political issues. His latest record, ''Tiempos'' (Sony Discos), recorded with a new young band called Editus, combines all kinds of music from South America into a coherent whole.</p>
        <p>Opening is Orquesta Aragon, the Cuban charanga band whose dynastic history dates to the late 1930's.</p>
        <p>June 21</p>
        <p>ELVIN JONES AND CECIL TAYLOR,  Blue Note. Mr. Jones, the drummer,  and Mr. Taylor, the pianist, played a duet at the Blue Note last winter, and its subtleties were striking: Mr. Jones used mallets for almost the entire set I caught. It's nice to see this relationship worked out in the more casual atmosphere of a jazz club rather than the one-time-only big-ticket hoopla of the festivals, and their second time around will be worth another visit.</p>
        <p>June 22</p>
        <p>''FROM SPIRITUALS TO SWING,''  JVC Jazz Festival, Carnegie Hall. This concert honors the famous 1938 and 1939 Carnegie Hall concerts produced by John Hammond (the recorded version has just been reissued on Vanguard) that brought together Count Basie's big-band swing, boogie-woogie and stride piano from Meade Lux Lewis and James P. Johnson, and the sanctified harmonies of the Golden Gate Quartet. In the even more eclectic year 2000 version, the participants include the present version of the Basie orchestra; the singers Dianne Reeves and Angelique Kidjo; the New Orleans patriarch Allen Toussaint; and Harlem's ecstatic, trombone-heavy shout band, the McCollough Sons of Thunder.</p>
        <p>June 23</p>
        <p>CASSANDRA WILSON AND CESARIA EVORA,  JVC Jazz Festival, Carnegie Hall. Here's a double bill that makes sense. Putting Ms. Wilson's recent music up against true-blue jazz singers has always created an imbalance and causes headaches as listeners wonder if her artful, chanteusy, folk-Americana is jazz or not. Ms. Evora, the charismatic morna singer from  Cape Verde, strikes much closer to the cloudy-day emotional territory that Ms. Wilson aims for.</p>
        <p>June 24</p>
        <p>ARETHA FRANKLIN,  JVC Jazz Festival, Avery Fisher Hall. Ms. Franklin is still a house-wrecker, and a performer so imposing that her mood is easily transmitted to her audience. If she's happy or frustrated, it becomes part of the performance and you're taken up in it -- which is what performances ought to do anyway.</p>
        <p>June 25</p>
        <p>BRIAN BLADE FELLOWSHIP,  Village Vanguard. Mr. Blade, a former sideman for Joshua Redman and one of the greatest drummers to have come along in the last decade of American music, writes music for an expanded small group that doesn't sound like anything in jazz. It's sentimental, sometimes slightly hymnlike music, arranged for a steel guitar and two saxophones; it's a bit cinematic, but for a very private, interior sort of movie.</p>
        <p>June 27</p>
        <p>MILTON NASCIMENTO,  Beacon Theater. As generations of new listeners keep discovering treasure-trove records like ''Clube da Esquina'' (Blue Note/Capitol) Mr. Nascimento's small but committed American audience has grown beyond the jazz world that first accepted him in the 70's. Back from a period of illness, he still has the voice, with that almost religious quality of purity and its rich emotional currents.</p>
        <p>June 29</p>
        <p>HAPPY APPLE,  Tonic. This trio from Minneapolis plays jazz as if it doesn't have any hangups about what anybody's going to call it.  Among its quirks are an electric bassist who has not been particularly influenced by Jaco Pastorious, and a general subtext of indie-rock subversion.</p>
        <p>Following the Beat</p>
        <p>The Vision Festival, which began last Friday, runs through Monday. All shows are at New Age Cabaret, 23 St. Marks Place, East Village; www.visionfestival.org. Tickets are $20 an evening. The Bell Atlantic Jazz Festival runs from Thursday to June 11 at more than a dozen venues. Prices generally range from $20 to $70, with food and drink minimums in some cases. There are a few shows with tickets ranging from $2 to $8, and many outdoor events are free. Information and tickets: (212) 343-8805. The 28th annual JVC Jazz Festival opens on June 12 and runs through June 24, with shows at nine venues in Manhattan and one in Englewood, N.J. Tickets range from $20 to $75, except for one event featuring Bobby Watson and Horizon at the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, for which tickets are $9 and $12. Information and tickets: (212) 501-1390 or on line at www.festivalproductions.net. Here are day-by-day listings for performances recommended in Ben Ratliff's critic's notebook article.</p>
        <p>TONIGHT: Vision Festival, featuring Michele Rosewoman Quintessence, 7 p.m.; Rob Brown Trio, 8; Kidd Jordan-Alvin Fielder Quartet, 9; David Budbill and William Parker, 10; Perry Robinson Quartet, 11; Other Dimensions in Music (Roy Campbell, Daniel Carter, William Parker, Rashid Bakr and Matthew Shipp), midnight. Tickets: $20.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW: Wycliffe Gordon Quintet, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m. and 1 a.m. Cover charge: $20 plus $10 drink minimum. (212) 255-4037.</p>
        <p>MONDAY: Guillermo Klein and Los Guachos, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, 8 and 10 p.m. Cover charge: $15  with a $10 food and drink minimum. (212) 576-2232.</p>
        <p>TUESDAY: Eric Reed's New York Seven. Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m. Cover charge: $15 plus $10 drink minimum. (212) 255-4037.</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY: Pat Martino Hip-Bop Trio. Iridium, 44 West 63rd Street, Manhattan,  8:45 and 10:45 p.m. Cover charge: $25 plus $10 drink minimum. (212) 582-2121.</p>
        <p>THURSDAY: Ornette Coleman (Trio, Global Expression Project and Freedom Symbol),  the Lawn, Battery Park, 6:30 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $65 (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>NEXT FRIDAY: Charlie Haden's Quartet West with String Orchestra. Angel Orensanz Foundation, 172 Norfolk Street, Lower East Side, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 in advance, $25 on day of show (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 3: Uri Caine's Goldberg Variations. Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, 8 and 10:30 p.m. and midnight. Cover charge: $25 plus $10 minimum (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 4: Max Roach and Cecil Taylor, with David S. Ware Quartet, Ron Carter and Joey Baron, and the La Guardia High School Jazz Band, Columbia University Steps, Broadway and 116th Street, Morningside Heights, 6 p.m. Free. (Bell Atlantic Festival.)</p>
        <p>JUNE 5: Roswell Rudd and Broad Strokes, with guest appearance by members of Sonic Youth, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 in advance, $30 on day of show (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 6: Greg Osby Quintet. Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, 10 p.m. Tickets: $25 in advance, $30 on day of show (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 7: Tim Berne (with Paraphrase at 7 p.m., Big Satan at 8 p.m., Quicksand at 10  p.m. and Composure at 11 p.m.), Knitting Factory, Old Office, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa. Tickets: $25 advance, $30 on day of show (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 8: Matthew Shipp String Trio, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, 10 p.m. Tickets: $25 in advance, $30 on day of show (Bell Atlantic Festival); James Carter, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, 9 and 11:30 p.m. Cover charge: $27.50 at tables, $15 at bar, plus $5 minimum. (212) 475-8592.</p>
        <p>JUNE 9: ''As Long As You're Living Yours: The Music of Keith Jarrett,'' Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, 8 and 10:30 p.m. and midnight. Cover charge: $25 plus $10 minimum (Bell Atlantic Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 10: Roy Haynes Trio, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Manhattan, 9 and 11 p.m. Cover charge: $30 plus $10 minimum. (212) 581-3080.</p>
        <p>JUNE 11: Los Lobos, Los Van Van, Barbarito Torres, the David Sanchez Sextet and Bobby Sanabria y Ascension, World Trade Center, Austin J. Tobin Plaza, Lower Manhattan, 1 p.m. Free. (Bell Atlantic Festival.)</p>
        <p>JUNE 14: Tribute to Charlie Byrd and George Van Eps, Kaye Playhouse, Hunter College, East 68th Street between Lexington and Park Avenues, 8 p.m. Tickets: $35 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 16: Joao Gilberto, Carnegie Hall, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $60 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 17: Peter Brotzmann Chicago Tentet (opening for Sonic Youth), Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20. (212) 307-7171.</p>
        <p>JUNE 18: John Lurie and the Lounge Lizards, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, 8 P.M. Tickets: $31 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 20: Ruben Blades and Editus, and Orquestra Aragon, Carnegie Hall, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $55 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 21: Elvin Jones and Cecil Taylor, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, 9 and 11:30 p.m. Cover charge: $35 at tables or $20 at the bar, plus $5 drink minimum. (212) 475-8592.</p>
        <p>JUNE 22: ''From Spirituals to Swing,'' a celebration of the legendary 1938 and 1939 Carnegie Hall concerts, with the Count Basie Orchestra, Dianne Reeves, Don Byron Sextet, Allen Toussaint and the SRC All-City Gospel Chorale, Carnegie Hall, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $55 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 23: Cassandra Wilson and Cesaria Evora, Carnegie Hall, 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $65 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 24: Aretha Franklin and Stanley Turrentine Quintet. Avery Fisher Hall, 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $75 (JVC Festival).</p>
        <p>JUNE 25: Brian Blade Fellowship, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, Gre West Village, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m. Cover charge: $15 plus $10 drink minimum. (212) 255-4037.</p>
        <p>JUNE 27: Milton Nascimento. Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, 8 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $50. (212) 496-7070.</p>
        <p>JUNE 29: Happy Apple. Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, midnight. Cover charge: $5. (212) 358-7501.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK  Correction:  May 29, 2000, Monday  A Critic's Notebook article in Weekend on Friday about jazz festivals in Manhattan included an outdated reference to a performance by John Lurie and the Lounge Lizards. Their concert on June 18 has been canceled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 29, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>A Critic's Notebook article in Weekend on Friday about jazz festivals in Manhattan included an outdated reference to a performance by John Lurie and the Lounge Lizards. Their concert on June 18 has been canceled.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
