<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Rejects Federal Salmonella Tests in Texas Meat Plants</title>
    <meta content="Y26MEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dallas (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Agriculture Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Beef Processors Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickman, Dan (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fish, A Joe (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salmonella (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0D7123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Rejects Federal Salmonella Tests in Texas Meat Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal District Court Judge A Joe Fish of Dallas strikes down Agriculture Dept's inspection standards for meat-processing plants, saying they do not fairly measure sanitary conditions; Judge Fish had earlier ruled that department could not shut down Supreme Beef Processing plant in Dallas after it failed three salmonella tests; Agriculture Sec Dan Glickman says he will appeal ruling; consumer groups say if ruling is upheld, it would force department to return to poke-and-sniff system in effect for last 100 years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge in Texas struck down the Agriculture Department's inspection standards for meat-processing plants yesterday, saying they did not fairly measure sanitary conditions.</p>
        <p>The standards, and the laboratory tests used to enforce them, were the foundation of the four-year-old government effort to limit meat and poultry contamination by salmonella.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge in Texas struck down the Agriculture Department's inspection standards for meat-processing plants yesterday, saying they did not fairly measure sanitary conditions.</p>
        <p>The standards, and the laboratory tests used to enforce them, were the foundation of the four-year-old government effort to limit meat and poultry contamination by salmonella.</p>
        <p>The judge, A. Joe Fish of Federal District Court in Dallas, said the tests measured the quality of the meat brought into a plant, but not necessarily the conditions of the plant itself.</p>
        <p>Judge Fish ruled that federal law did not give the government the authority to close a meat-processing plant based on the bacterial tests.</p>
        <p>Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said the Department of Agriculture would take ''whatever legal steps are necessary'' to overturn the ruling.</p>
        <p>The ruling applies only to plants in the northern district of Texas that process ground beef. But beef from those plants is shipped all over the country.</p>
        <p>The department plans to continue to enforce the standards in processing plants and slaughterhouses elsewhere in the country and will continue to test for salmonella in slaughterhouses in the northern district of Texas.</p>
        <p>If the ruling is upheld, consumer groups say, it could force the Agriculture Department to return to the poke-and-sniff system, in which inspectors smelled for contamination, that had been in effect since the beginning of the century.</p>
        <p>''This decision leaves the shell but cuts out the heart of U.S.D.A.'s efforts to prevent food poisoning,'' said Caroline Smith DeWaal, food safety director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest, a consumer advocacy group.</p>
        <p>But Steven F. Spiritas, president and chief executive of Supreme Beef Processing, which brought the lawsuit, said the company was pleased with the ruling.</p>
        <p>''This decision,'' Mr. Spiritas said, ''confirms what we have said from the very beginning, that U.S.D.A.'s use of the salmonella test to determine the sanitary condition of the processor plant is flawed and outside the scope of U.S.D.A.'s authority.''</p>
        <p>In December, Judge Fish ruled that the department could not shut down Supreme Beef's plant in Dallas. The government had removed its inspectors, which are legally required for a plant to operate. The closing of the plant, which had failed three salmonella tests, was the first under the new regulations.</p>
        <p>Just a few weeks later, the plant was forced to recall 180,000 pounds of ground beef because one sample of the beef tested positive for the deadly bacteria E. coli O157:H7.</p>
        <p>In his decision Judge Fish said, ''Because the U.S.D.A. performance standards and salmonella tests do not necessarily evaluate the conditions of a meat processor's establishment, they cannot serve as a basis for finding a plant's meat adulterated.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Indeed, a plant could, in theory, be completely sanitized from top to bottom but if the meat in it tests positive for salmonella, the U.S.D.A. could withdraw its inspectors, effectively closing a plant that is sanitary.''</p>
        <p>Ninety percent of the nation's large beef-processing plants and 84 percent of the small ones have systems that keep salmonella-tainted beef out of their plants, and they are in compliance with the Agriculture Department's salmonella standards. Two other plants have failed inspections three times, but have agreed to make changes to come into compliance.</p>
        <p>Since the department's regulations requiring salmonella testing went into effect, studies show salmonella contamination of ground beef products has dropped by as much as 50 percent. And according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, food poisoning dropped in 1999 for the first time in many years. The disease control agency said the new inspection system deserved part of the credit for this improvement.</p>
        <p>Salmonella can be deadly for young children, the elderly and those with weakened immune systems. Last year about 600 deaths and 1.4 million illnesses were attributed to salmonellosis.</p>
        <p>Carol Tucker Foreman of the Consumer Federation of America called on the Agriculture Department to stop buying ground beef for federal programs, especially those serving children, like the school lunch program. Last December the department canceled its contract with Supreme Beef for hamburgers for the school lunch program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
