<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japan Moves to Correct a Deliberate Omission of Data</title>
    <meta content="Y26JAP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D7123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japan Moves to Correct a Deliberate Omission of Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic Planning Agency says it will correct its deliberate omission of data made in recent report on Japan's economic growth; says corrected data will be reflected in economic growth figures released June 10; denies it omitted data for Oct-Dec period to make report appear stronger that it really was; also says that when data is included, gross domestic product in that quarter will show 1.6 percent decline from year before, rather than drop of 1.43 percent indicated in the original report (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government said today that it would correct its deliberate omission of data made in a report on economic growth released a few weeks ago. The corrected data will be reflected in economic growth figures released June 10.</p>
        <p>The Economic Planning Agency, which computes the gross domestic product figures, denied that it had omitted the data for the October-to- December period in order to make the report appear stronger than it really was. But the agency did say today that when the data is included, the gross domestic product in that quarter shows a 1.6 percent decline from the year before, rather than a drop of 1.43 percent, which was the figure the agency had originally reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The government said today that it would correct its deliberate omission of data made in a report on economic growth released a few weeks ago. The corrected data will be reflected in economic growth figures released June 10.</p>
        <p>The Economic Planning Agency, which computes the gross domestic product figures, denied that it had omitted the data for the October-to- December period in order to make the report appear stronger than it really was. But the agency did say today that when the data is included, the gross domestic product in that quarter shows a 1.6 percent decline from the year before, rather than a drop of 1.43 percent, which was the figure the agency had originally reported.</p>
        <p>A sharper decline in gross domestic product for the period would probably make it more difficult for the government to achieve its target of 0.6 percent economic growth in the fiscal year that ended March 31, at a time when the ruling party is facing an election.</p>
        <p>Omission of the data has focused attention on how the Japanese government compiles and calculates data about the economy. That data is scrutinized by economists and financial markets for insights into whether the economy is emerging from a prolonged slump.</p>
        <p>The Economic Planning Agency called a special news conference today after an article on the omission that appeared in The New York Times and on its Web site on Wednesday. Before that article, the omission had not been questioned, although agency officials said today that the agency's vice minister, Takashi Nakanomyo, had mentioned a problem with the data on capital spending at a news conference held after the preliminary economic figures for the October-December quarter were released on March 13.</p>
        <p>Akira Sadahiro, head of the agency's Economic Research Institute, reiterated today the agency's position that the omission of the data was not done for political reasons. ''Our handling of the data was rational,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Masaaki Maruyama, head of the national expenditures division of the agency, has said he decided to omit information that showed capital spending by financial institutions had fallen far more sharply than the agency had estimated in calculating the gross domestic product figure released in March.</p>
        <p>In its initial compilation of the gross domestic product, the agency had estimated that investment by banks, securities houses and insurance companies had declined 3 percent in the October-December quarter. Based on that estimate as well as many other components, the agency said in March that gross domestic product had fallen 1.4 percent.</p>
        <p>Typically, the agency replaces that estimate with data collected in a survey that it conducts.</p>
        <p>But the revision announced on May 11 did not include the survey data, which showed that capital spending by financial institutions fell 37.3 percent, far more than what the agency had expected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maruyama said the agency had initially decided not to use the survey data because there was no easy way to explain the discrepancy between it and the estimate used in the original calculation.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
