<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</title>
    <meta content="26VIDB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Man on the Moon (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Snow Falling on Cedars (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Movie (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Miss Julie (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DE123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of films now released on video: Man on the Moon, Snow Falling on Cedars, American Movie and Miss Julie; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Man on the Moon</p>
        <p>Jim Carrey (left) delivers an electrifying homage to the comedian Andy Kaufman, but Milos Forman's film fails to answer the question of who Kaufman was or how he got that way. All the material is here: the uncanny impersonations, the wrestling matches with women, the bombastic tirades of Kaufman's trash-talking alter ego, the lounge singer Tony Clifton. But this remains a surprisingly straightforward show-business rise-and-fall story. As entertaining as that can be, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, it ''limits the film's ability to give Kaufman three dimensions.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Man on the Moon</p>
        <p>Jim Carrey (left) delivers an electrifying homage to the comedian Andy Kaufman, but Milos Forman's film fails to answer the question of who Kaufman was or how he got that way. All the material is here: the uncanny impersonations, the wrestling matches with women, the bombastic tirades of Kaufman's trash-talking alter ego, the lounge singer Tony Clifton. But this remains a surprisingly straightforward show-business rise-and-fall story. As entertaining as that can be, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, it ''limits the film's ability to give Kaufman three dimensions.''</p>
        <p>1999. Universal. $107.37; DVD, $29.99. 118 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: May 30.</p>
        <p>Snow Falling on Cedars</p>
        <p>Scott Hicks's stunningly beautiful film, based on David Guterson's novel, makes the mistake of retaining the book's intricate flashbacks, which proves disruptive. In 1950 a young Japanese-American (Rick Yune) stands trial for murder on the fictitious San Piedro Island north of Puget Sound. That attracts the interest of a journalist (Ethan Hawke), who years earlier had an affair with the defandant's wife (Youki Kudoh) and relates to the internment of Japanese-Americans during World War II.</p>
        <p>But the darting back and forth doesn't serve an adaptation that is ''admirably high-minded and visually gorgeous but fatally anesthetized by its own grandiosity'' (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. Universal. $107.37; DVD, $29.99. 126 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: May 30.</p>
        <p>American Movie</p>
        <p>''The American Dream stays with me each and every day,'' says Mark Borchardt, the funny, garrulous subject of his own documentary. For him, one of the those big, sterile houses he craves will be just reward for the no-budget ''Blair Witch Project'' knock-off he is making with the assistance of his Uncle Bill and anyone else he can enlist. Along the way we discover Mr. Borchardt, his own best character, in a film that by its end ''has blossomed into much more than a portrait of one fiendishly determined filmmaker'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1999. Columbia Tri-Star. $99.36; DVD, $27.95. 107 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Miss Julie</p>
        <p>In Mike Figgis's adaptation of Strindberg's drama, a wealthy count's imperious, neurotic daughter (Saffron Burrows) spars sexually with her virile, opportunistic footman, Jean (Peter Mullan). These days the pairing might have at least led to some hot sex, but here it is cause for a repressed, emotionally sadomasochistic ritual of humiliation. Nor does haste help. ''The dialogue may be crisply idiomatic, but there's finally nothing realistic about the speed with which the characters hurtle through their mood swings and power plays'' (Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. MGM. $49.95; DVD, $24.98. 103 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: May 30.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>WHITNEY: THE GREATEST HITS. A Whitney Houston DVD roundup includes all her music videos; commentary by the singer and an interview with Clive Davis, the former president of Arista Records; her premiere television appearance on ''The Merv Griffin Show'' in 1985; her television acting debut on ''Gimme a Break''; various concert performances; views from behind the scenes at the making of albums and videos; and 21 Houston favorites, from ''You Give Good Love'' to ''I Learned From the Best.'' 2000. BMG. $24.98; also available on VHS, $19.99.</p>
        <p>DEVIL'S ISLAND. With its trailer trash Icelandic style, Fridrik Thor Fridriksson's film carves a vividly realized slice of life out of the bleak landscape of Camp Thule near Reykjavik, an American military base where, as Garrison Keillor might put it, the men are drunks, the women unhappy and the children dysfunctional. Nevertheless, they're a lively lot who number a witch who curses God, a mother of three who escapes by marrying an American pilot and her two grown sons, a boozy brawler and a shy, quiet potential hero. The cast, Lawrence Van Gelder wrote in The New York Times, ''delivers performances so convincing and un-self-conscious that 'Devil's Island' at times seems to be a documentary.'' 1999. Winstar. $89.98; DVD, $29.98. 103 minutes.</p>
        <p>GINEVRA'S STORY. Before the ''Mona Lisa,'' Leonardo da Vinci painted ''Ginevra de' Benci,'' his first known portrait. Meryl Streep narrates an exploration of Leonardo's original mysterious lady by the National Gallery of Art in Washington. 2000. Home Vision. $29.95. 57 minutes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
