<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sympathy for Japan's Leader Ebbs in a String of Gaffes</title>
    <meta content="Y26JAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mori, Yoshiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obuchi, Keizo (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D9123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sympathy for Japan's Leader Ebbs in a String of Gaffes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's new prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, has made series of gaffes and provocative statements that have caused steep delcine in government's public support in recent opinion polls; death of Prime Min Keizo Obuchi on May 14 was expected to give his Liberal Democratic Party strong sympathy vote in parliamentary elections June 25; now Mori's fellow party members are playing down their connections to him; faux pas that prompted strongest reaction was remark Mori made last week, which many felt alarmingly echoed Japan's militaristic past; he called Japan a 'divine nation' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When leaders of Japan's governing party met secretly seven weeks ago to choose a successor to Prime Minister Keizo Obuchi, who was felled by a stroke, the idea was not only to ensure a quick transition but also to perpetuate the party's long hold on power.</p>
        <p>But to the growing consternation of party members, through a series of gaffes and provocative statements the new prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, has presided instead over a steep decline in the government's public support, recent opinion polls indicate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When leaders of Japan's governing party met secretly seven weeks ago to choose a successor to Prime Minister Keizo Obuchi, who was felled by a stroke, the idea was not only to ensure a quick transition but also to perpetuate the party's long hold on power.</p>
        <p>But to the growing consternation of party members, through a series of gaffes and provocative statements the new prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, has presided instead over a steep decline in the government's public support, recent opinion polls indicate.</p>
        <p>The death of Mr. Obuchi on May 14 was once expected to give his Liberal Democratic Party a strong sympathy vote in the parliamentary elections scheduled for June 25. But now party members are expecting a fight for their political lives.</p>
        <p>And most tellingly, in a system in which campaign money and prestige traditionally flow from on high, the party's candidates are playing down their connections to their embattled new leader.</p>
        <p>Some members of Mr. Mori's party have urged that the election be postponed, but party leaders have resisted the idea. Hoping to quell the dissension, Mr. Mori has announced plans for a news conference on Friday to explain his recent remarks.</p>
        <p>The faux pas that has prompted the strongest reaction was a remark Mr. Mori made last week to a Shinto religious group of lawmakers that many felt alarmingly echoed Japan's militaristic past.</p>
        <p>''Japan is a divine nation with the emperor at its core, and we want the people to recognize this,'' Mr. Mori said.</p>
        <p>The prime minister tried to quiet the tempest by saying he supported Japan's democratic, pacifist Constitution and was merely urging more spiritual values for Japan's youth. But his failure to retract the comment seemed to make things worse.</p>
        <p>By the end of the week, support for Mr. Mori's cabinet had dropped to about 20 percent in newspaper polls, about half of what it was after he took office.</p>
        <p>There have been other problems for Mr. Mori, including persistent but unconfirmed press reports that he was arrested while frequenting prostitutes as a college student, and that the prime minister had improperly secured membership in an expensive private golfing club.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mori's chief cabinet secretary, Mikio Aoki, a schoolmate of the prime minister at Waseda University, denied that Mr. Mori had been arrested, saying he would have remembered the incident if it had been true. But Mr. Aoki, who served in the same post under Mr. Obuchi, has been under fire himself over his shifting explanations of the circumstances of Mr. Obuchi's hospitalization and the secretly arranged succession.</p>
        <p>And on Wednesday, Mr. Mori was forced to acknowledge press reports that he spoke at a wedding in 1995 that was attended by members of a major Japanese crime syndicate. The prime minister said he had not checked who would be present before accepting the invitation to speak.</p>
        <p>For the most part, Mr. Mori has responded to the trouble, somewhat awkwardly, by keeping out of view, or at least as quiet as possible.</p>
        <p>For two weeks now, the prime minister has canceled his weekly appearance at question time, the regular debate in Parliament with the opposition. And at a public appearance last weekend, Mr. Mori joked, ''I will simply read what has been written for me,'' as he pulled out a sheath of prepared remarks.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Mori, Kazuhiko Koshikawa, denied that the prime minister was ducking question time, saying his failure to attend was ''because of the rude way that the opposition parties treated the prime minister during a meeting between the leader of the L.D.P. and leaders of the opposition.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, the opposition has had a field day.</p>
        <p>''He's like a child refusing to attend school,'' said Tsutomu Hata, secretary general of the Democratic Party. ''The prime minister should not run away from his job.''</p>
        <p>But from the perspective of some Liberal Democratic Party candidates facing a tough campaign, what would be even worse would be to have the prime minister speaking freely again.</p>
        <p>''The more he talks, the more our votes fly out the window,'' one of the party's candidates complained to Tokyo Shimbun. In a headline on Wednesday, The Daily Yomiuri, another conservative newspaper that is traditionally supportive of the Liberal Democratic Party, said bluntly that ''one more gaffe could prove one too many'' for Mr. Mori.</p>
        <p>With anxieties over the elections running high, few governing party politicians were willing to speak about Mr. Mori this week, either in criticism or in his defense.</p>
        <p>But one legislator, Yoshihide Suga, said the new prime minister's ''divine country'' comment had given the opposition ''real momentum'' going into the elections and sown fear in the hearts of governing party members.</p>
        <p>''L.D.P. people have begun taking down posters with Mori on them,'' Mr. Suga said. ''At this rate, soon you won't find any posters with Mori's picture on them in urban areas.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
