<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reform Party Is Embroiled Over Buchanan Domination and Its Impact on Platform</title>
    <meta content="Y26REF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Patrick J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perot, Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DB133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reform Party Is Embroiled Over Buchanan Domination and Its Impact on Platform</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>TUCSON, Ariz., May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>There is growing likelihood that Patrick J Buchanan will secure Reform Party's presidential nomination, and $12.5 million in federal campaign money that goes along with it; some Reform leaders are so worried that Buchanan and his delegates will take over party and force it to adopt conservative platform on abortion and other issues that they are collecting signatures to draft party's founder, Ross Perot, for third consecutive campaign; another group within party is quietly trying to have Green Party candidate, Ralph Nader, run for Reform nomination; still others want party to forgo nominating presidential candidate this year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time Reform Party leaders met, three months ago in Nashville, tensions rose to such an extreme that two women wrestled over control of a microphone, and the police were summoned to prevent the rowdiness from growing worse.</p>
        <p>Now party leaders are fighting over much more than a microphone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time Reform Party leaders met, three months ago in Nashville, tensions rose to such an extreme that two women wrestled over control of a microphone, and the police were summoned to prevent the rowdiness from growing worse.</p>
        <p>Now party leaders are fighting over much more than a microphone.</p>
        <p>The growing likelihood that Patrick J. Buchanan, the conservative television commentator and former Republican, will secure the Reform Party's presidential nomination and the $12.5 million in federal campaign money that goes along with it has created another element of conflict within the loosely organized and often chaotic party.</p>
        <p>Some Reform leaders are so worried that Mr. Buchanan and his delegates will take over the party and force it to adopt a conservative platform on abortion and other issues that they are collecting signatures to draft the party's founder, Ross Perot, for a third consecutive campaign.</p>
        <p>Another group opposed to Mr. Buchanan, led by the party's national secretary, is quietly negotiating to have the Green Party candidate, Ralph Nader, run for the Reform nomination.</p>
        <p>Still other party members are urging the leadership to endorse no presidential candidate this year, rather than Mr. Buchanan, and to turn efforts to building the party from the ground up by fielding candidates in state, city and local races. Moreover, Reform leaders in at least two states, Colorado and Georgia, have condemned Mr. Buchanan for some of his views and tactics and have demanded that he resign from the party.</p>
        <p>Georgia's rebuke came after an effort by Buchanan supporters to create a parallel Reform Party that would emphasize the candidate's strongly conservative views. Anne Merkl, the Georgia Reform Party chairwoman, said the Buchanan campaign had made similar attempts in seven other states.</p>
        <p>''By doing that,'' Ms. Merkl said, ''the Reform Party will be destroyed as we once knew it.''</p>
        <p>While it seems doubtful that the dissidents can prevent Mr. Buchanan's nomination, the discord could complicate the nominating process, making it less likely that the party's convention in Long Beach, Calif., in August will end on a note of unity.</p>
        <p>''We're unconventional, to say the least,'' said Gerald R. Moan, a Tucson businessman and former Long Islander who became party chairman just three weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moan replaced Pat Choate, Mr. Perot's 1996 running mate and a close friend of Mr. Buchanan. Mr. Choate had won the job at the chaotic party meeting in Nashville but resigned because of an illness in his family.</p>
        <p>For such a swirl of activity against him, Mr. Buchanan does not seem especially concerned.</p>
        <p>''He'd prefer that things not be this way,'' said Bay Buchanan, his sister and chief strategist as campaign manager. ''But we're staying focused on what we're doing, trying to stay out of the fray. It's really no different than any other party. People are very unhappy when they don't get their candidate in the race.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan's ascendancy in the Reform Party has largely come through the graces of Mr. Perot, who has always encouraged disaffected Republicans and Democrats to join the cause. In recent years, few Republicans grew as disaffected as Mr. Buchanan, and by last year, as Mr. Perot withdrew from public view, he made it clear that Mr. Buchanan would be welcome in the party. But the two have not talked in two years, Ms. Buchanan said, although Russell  J. Verney, a former party chairman who remains close to Mr. Perot, said it had been closer to five years.</p>
        <p>In either case, for Mr. Buchanan, who spent years clashing with the Republican Party leadership, it was the opening he needed, both for an unobstructed path to the presidential general election and for the mantle as leader of a political party. And by  winning 5 percent of the vote Mr. Buchanan would ensure the party federal campaign money for 2004.</p>
        <p>After Gov. Jesse Ventura of Minnesota resigned from the party in February and Donald J. Trump, the New York real estate developer, dropped out of the Reform presidential race -- each angrily citing Mr. Buchanan's influence -- a vacuum was left in party leadership.</p>
        <p>Trying to fill it, Mr. Buchanan has wooed delegates, placed supporters in Reform state leadership positions and offered his America-first, socially conservative views as a credible  alternative to the major party candidates, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>To win the Reform nomination, a candidate needs a majority of the votes of members who have either requested a ballot from the party,  registered as a party member in a state where the party is recognized or signed a petition supporting a party candidate in a state that has not recognized the party. Ballots can be cast in person, by mail, phone or by the Internet from July 4 to the start of the convention. But if two-thirds of the convention delegates disagree with the popular choice, they can vote to overturn the selection and pick another candidate.</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Buchanan appears unstoppable. With no viable challengers, he is well on his way to securing the delegate support he needs to assure the Reform Party nomination, and, as the rules permit, to allow him as the nominee to rewrite the party platform to include his positions on social issues -- a possibility, Ms. Buchanan said.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Buchanan has gathered enough signatures to get the Reform Party on the ballot in at least five states beyond the 20 that will automatically recognize the party based on Mr. Perot's showing in the 1996 presidential election. The Buchanan campaign expects to collect enough signatures to get the party or the candidate on the ballot in all 50 states by the final state filing deadline, Sept. 5 in Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>So much momentum by a single campaign might appear to unite a party starved for respect and credibility. But as Mr. Buchanan forges ahead, so do his opponents.</p>
        <p>''Plenty of the old-timers are still here, and they are very concerned about Pat Buchanan,'' said Ira Goodman, the New Jersey start party  chairman who is leading the effort to draft Mr. Perot. ''Our goal is to go into the primary with an alternative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Goodman insisted that support among party members for Mr. Perot is widespread. But drawing him back into a potentially loud and contentious primary fight would seem a rather daunting challenge for now. Mr. Perot has withdrawn from the political arena.</p>
        <p>''He has not even asked to speak at the convention,'' said Mr. Moan, the party chairman, who takes that to mean Mr. Perot will not attend. ''If he comes, he'll speak. But if he doesn't come, that could be interpreted as a rebuke to Buchanan.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Verney said he did not know what Mr. Perot would do, an assertion that appears to leave open the possibility Mr. Perot might indeed be a candidate.</p>
        <p>''I can't rule it out,'' Mr. Verney said, which was the same response he offered six months ago. Only now, time is a factor; to qualify as a presidential candidate under the party's rules, Mr. Perot would have to notify the leadership by July 1 that he intends to run.</p>
        <p>''He's not launched a full-fledged campaign to be the next president,'' Mr. Verney said of Mr. Perot, who has not granted an interview in some time. ''But he hasn't ruled it out. If the members feel he would be the best person to represent the principles, ideals and goals, well, it has to happen by July 1.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Verney, who often represents Mr. Perot's views, was equally unsure whether Mr. Buchanan's ultimate goal was to run for president or rebuild the Reform Party.</p>
        <p>''It's a strange strategy,'' Mr. Verney said of Mr. Buchanan's recent aggressiveness. ''I don't understand throwing sharp elbows at would-be friends. It makes you wonder whether his goal is to be elected president on Nov. 7 or own a party on Nov. 8.''</p>
        <p>''We're doing both,'' Ms. Buchanan said. ''Pat wants to be president and he wants to build the party.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Goodman has been collecting signatures of support for Mr. Perot, Jim Mangia, the Reform Party's national secretary, has been talking to Green Party leaders about Mr. Nader's interest in running as the Reform candidate. Despite Mr. Nader's leftward leanings, his politics are not so different from the Reform platform on issues like campaign finance reform and permanent trading status for China.</p>
        <p>But only 36 states allow a candidate to run with the support of more than one party.</p>
        <p>Donna Donovan, the party press secretary, said some members, ''as a last-ditch option,'' believe the party should sit out the presidential campaign this year and build for the future instead.</p>
        <p>While that is highly unlikely, Ms. Buchanan's view was that party members should not worry.</p>
        <p>''We're at the embryonic stage as a party,'' she said. ''Pat is bringing in new blood and a new image to the party, I'm sure, and we want to have a strong third party. So if it gets a conservative tint this time, someone else wins four years later, and then it'll have a different tint.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
