<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surveying Greece</title>
    <meta content="26EATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Astoria (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greece</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED7173DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surveying Greece</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out reviews of Greek restaurants in Manhattan and Astoria, Queens; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Greek food, with its simple ingredients, relatively simple preparations and emphasis on seafood, is the perfect choice for warm weather. Here are a dozen restaurants that explore the spectrum of Greek cooking. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Artos</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 838-0007</p>
        <p>307 East 53rd Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>A colorful bread oven is the centerpiece of Artos, which was designed by Adam Tihany. When the restaurant opened in 1995, it was dedicated to Greek village foods, but nowadays the menu reflects what some have termed nouvelle grecque, traditional Greek foods lightened and gussied up with modern techniques. So dishes like old-fashioned baby lamb chops and pan-seared chicken coexist with sauteed shrimp ''with spicy fish veloute sauce and aromatic saffron,'' and references to stir-fried vegetables, shiitake mushrooms and sun-dried tomatoes. Why not?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Greek food, with its simple ingredients, relatively simple preparations and emphasis on seafood, is the perfect choice for warm weather. Here are a dozen restaurants that explore the spectrum of Greek cooking. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Artos</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 838-0007</p>
        <p>307 East 53rd Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>A colorful bread oven is the centerpiece of Artos, which was designed by Adam Tihany. When the restaurant opened in 1995, it was dedicated to Greek village foods, but nowadays the menu reflects what some have termed nouvelle grecque, traditional Greek foods lightened and gussied up with modern techniques. So dishes like old-fashioned baby lamb chops and pan-seared chicken coexist with sauteed shrimp ''with spicy fish veloute sauce and aromatic saffron,'' and references to stir-fried vegetables, shiitake mushrooms and sun-dried tomatoes. Why not?</p>
        <p>2. Avra</p>
        <p>* [1 star]</p>
        <p>(212) 759-8550</p>
        <p>141 East 48th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>In stark terms, a meal at Avra is a blind date with a fish. The customer picks out a whole fish, priced by the pound, from a lineup of glistening beauties arrayed on a bed of ice. Then the restaurant grills it. The restaurant, with its stark white walls, beamed ceiling and wood floor, suggests a well-heeled taverna, and the menu plays it straight for the most part. Seafood is the thing: about 14 kinds, all grilled in olive oil and served with a drizzle of olive oil and lemon. The varieties include Arctic char, red porgy, black sea bass and Maine lobster, as well as Mediterranean fish like loup de mer, blue-spotted sea bream and pandora, described on the menu as ''the Greek pride.'' The appetizers tend to be Greek standards like taramosalata, spinach pie, grilled sardines with lemon juice, and grilled octopus with onions and red wine vinegar, but the entrees, for those who want something more complex than plain grilled fish, show a mild sense of adventure. There's kakavia, or Greek bouillabaisse, and grilled halibut served over spinach and rice with a touch of fennel and dill. Nonfish entrees include grilled chicken with green beans, and lamb chops with lemon potatoes and okra.</p>
        <p>3. Christos Hasapo-Taverna</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(718) 726-5195</p>
        <p>41-08 23rd Avenue</p>
        <p>Astoria, Queens</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Christos Hasapo-Taverna was intended to recreate a Greek market that combines a butcher shop, or hasapo (pronounced HAHS-ah-poh), with a restaurant. At Christos the emphasis on beef, great American slabs of it, is a departure from the Greek practice. You can see for yourself: steaks and chops, displayed in a big glass case, are available for purchase. The best cuts are the robust shell steak, the richly flavored T-bone and the tender veal chop, as well as the more traditional Greek cuts like lamb chops and a variety of organ meats. This warm, handsome restaurant also has an appealing dessert tray.</p>
        <p>4. Estiatorio Milos</p>
        <p>** [2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 245-7400</p>
        <p>125 West 55th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The centerpiece here is a display of the most gorgeous fish imaginable, from the shiny sardines to the gleaming Arctic char to the regal loup de mer, all shimmering on a bed of ice. Then there are the lobsters in their tank and the myriad oysters. The choices can be overwhelming, but the execution is mostly simple and satisfying: whole fish grilled over charcoal. Among the highlights are fabulous tiny squid, flavorful grilled sardines, charred octopus, grilled shrimp and just about any of the whole fish. But beware of costs: the price on the menu for the whole fish is per pound, and since the fish are almost always more than a pound, the bill can be a shock. The restaurant's wine list is beautifully chosen, and for dessert, why not select something simple and traditional: thick homemade yogurt with thyme honey?</p>
        <p>5. Gus's Place</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 645-8511</p>
        <p>149 Waverly Place, near Christopher Street</p>
        <p>Greenwich Village</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>It's easy to imagine Gus's Place on a Greek island, cooled by gentle breezes from the sea. Tiny fried fish are hard to stop eating, while traditional Greek spreads like melitzanes salata (pureed eggplant and onion), taramosalata (fish roe puree) and tzatziki (a blend of yogurt, garlic, cucumbers and dill) are fine renditions. You can make a meal of appetizers like chickpea fritters and tender sauteed squid. Main courses include herb-crusted grilled tuna and stuffed salmon wrapped in phyllo pastry.</p>
        <p>6. Meltemi</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 355-4040</p>
        <p>905 First Avenue, at 51st Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The rollicking Meltemi is one of the better moderately priced Greek seafood restaurants around. Waiters bustle about in all directions, exuding enthusiasm and offering recommendations as they point to the glistening fish in the glass display case. Octopus is grilled over charcoal until the edges are crusty and is served in its red wine marinade. Jumbo shrimp, butterflied and grilled, are delectably sweet and delicate, while porgy and red snapper are terrific grilled whole. Dessert is a selection of pastries that go well with the free glasses of sweet muscat.</p>
        <p>7. Metsovo</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 873-2300</p>
        <p>65 West 70th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Instead of seafood, this restaurant, named after a town in northwestern Greece, specializes in hearty stews, roasts and savory pies from the hills that form a spine through the region. The food is not the only departure. With worn brick walls, a rustic wood floor, a cozy fireplace and dozens of candles creating a dim, romantic glow, Metsovo's gently transporting dining room is a far cry from the usual bright blue-and-white artifact-bedecked Greek restaurant. The house specialties form the heart of the menu and are the best choices, especially the Epirus mountain pies, offered with different fillings each day. A crisp, double-crusted serving may be stuffed with dandelion and Swiss chard; octopus with tomatoes, potatoes and rice; or eggplant, roasted tomato and green pepper with bechamel sauce. Tender chunks of baby lamb roasted and served on a glossy round loaf of bread that absorbs the juices; and baby goat served with papardelle and a light dill cream sauce topped with smoked metsovone cheese, are also good. Dessert selections change frequently. Hope for the luscious fig compote served with vanilla ice cream, or the wonderfully thick and fresh yogurt drizzled with honey as clean as a mountain meadow.</p>
        <p>8. Molyvos</p>
        <p>*** [3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 582-7500</p>
        <p>871 Seventh Avenue,</p>
        <p>near 55th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Here Greek food is presented by people who passionately want you to love it. They cover the table with captivating mezedes, little tastes like tiny mint-laced triangles of spinach wrapped in layers of pastry so thin they crunch as you bite into them, then instantly melt away. Tzatziki, the dip made of cucumbers and garlic, has a base of sheep's milk yogurt that gives it a truly Greek tang. Tyro keftedes, small pungent balls of fried cheese, one bite each, are perfect between sips of ouzo. (There are 10 to choose from.) The hardest part about eating at Molyvos is pacing yourself, especially when confronted with dishes like the savory and delicious lamb shank, the wonderful stewed rabbit and the simple and satisfying grilled fish. The room is as relaxed and airy as a Greek taverna, and the service is careful and kind.</p>
        <p>9. Periyali</p>
        <p>*** [3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 463-7890</p>
        <p>35 West 20th Street</p>
        <p>Flatiron district</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Many otherwise squeamish New Yorkers were introduced to octopus at Periyali, where this signature dish is marinated in red wine, olive oil and oregano, then charcoal-broiled to a crusty, delicious tenderness. But beyond octopus, this handsome restaurant offers dishes like calamari with garlic sauce, grilled calf's liver with caramelized onions, charcoal-grilled lamb chops redolent of fresh rosemary, and grilled shrimp simply dressed with olive oil, lemon and herbs. Desserts are equally good.</p>
        <p>10. Rafina</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 327-0950</p>
        <p>1481 York Avenue,</p>
        <p>near 78th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ Visa and Mastercard</p>
        <p>At this elemental Greek restaurant, you know exactly what you'll get: simple ingredients, simply prepared. Charcoal-grilled octopus is crunchy outside, tender within, while grilled whole fish like porgy, red snapper and striped bass are enhanced by their simple marinade of olive oil, lemon juice, oregano and garlic, and they arrive moist and delicious. An assortment of Greek dessert pastries are complementary with dinner. Rafina also has a pretty garden in the back.</p>
        <p>11. Syros</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(718) 278-1877</p>
        <p>32-11 Broadway</p>
        <p>Astoria,</p>
        <p>Queens</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Syros is named after the Greek island on which the owner, Theodore Menis, grew up. The dining room is attractive enough, in a conventional kind of way. It has the usual open kitchen and display cases of fish and meat. With a glass ceiling, the main dining room in the rear is warm and bright on sunny days and glows with candlelight at night. The room is the typical blue and white, decorated with fishing artifacts and murals of island scenes. Greek dips like melitzanes salata, taramosalata and tzatziki are particularly good. Syros's grilled fish is superb: perfectly cooked, moist and delicious, like an unexpectedly large porgy, tender and full of the fragile flavor that is so easily lost, beautifully seasoned with no more than salt, oregano, lemon juice and olive oil. Grilled shrimp, big and butterflied, are similarly cooked just enough to release their delicate shrimpy flavor. Main courses come with sides like lemon roasted potatoes (a standard that is especially good here), rice and dandelion greens, which are oily and not so good. Syros offers much to like, including its friendly, helpful waiters and a reasonably priced list of mostly Greek wines.</p>
        <p>12. Uncle Nick's</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 245-7992</p>
        <p>747 Ninth Avenue,</p>
        <p>near 51st Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Once a little hole in the wall in Clinton, Uncle Nick's has expanded into a handsome Greek seafood taverna. Appetizers are terrific, among them sauteed Greek sausage and saganaki, in which a sheep's-milk cheese is set aflame and served in a lemon-butter sauce. The fish is always impeccably fresh, but too often it is overcooked and arrives dry. Make clear to the staff how you want it cooked. A nice little wine list offers some inexpensive and delicious Greek choices.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>EATING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
