<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regulatory Snags Cited as Gene Technology Deal Ends</title>
    <meta content="Y26BIOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pe Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fors, Lance</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DF133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regulatory Snags Cited as Gene Technology Deal Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>PE Corp, in race with the government to sequence the human genome, drops plans to acquire Third Wave Technologies Inc, small company, Madison, Wis, with promising DNA analysis technology, at least in part because of antitrust concerns at Justice Department; Lance Fors, chief executive of Third Wave, says antitrust review of acquisition seemed to be taking longer than expected, with no assurance of approval; Justice Department makes no comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The PE Corporation, which is racing the government to sequence the human genome, has dropped plans to acquire a small company with promising DNA analysis technology, at least in part because of antitrust concerns at the Justice Department, executives said.</p>
        <p>PE Biosystems, the unit of PE that dominates the market for machines used to sequence genes, had said in January that it would buy Third Wave Technologies Inc., for about $330 million in stock. But late yesterday the two companies said they had agreed to terminate the acquisition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The PE Corporation, which is racing the government to sequence the human genome, has dropped plans to acquire a small company with promising DNA analysis technology, at least in part because of antitrust concerns at the Justice Department, executives said.</p>
        <p>PE Biosystems, the unit of PE that dominates the market for machines used to sequence genes, had said in January that it would buy Third Wave Technologies Inc., for about $330 million in stock. But late yesterday the two companies said they had agreed to terminate the acquisition.</p>
        <p>Third Wave, which is privately held and based in Madison, Wis., is developing technology for identifying variations in genes among individuals. Such variations, which can determine whether a person has blue or brown eyes or is susceptible to a certain disease, are expected to be the key in the future to so-called personalized medicine -- drugs tailored to each patient's genetic makeup. So a race is on to find and analyze these differences, which are known as single nucleotide polymorphisms, or S.N.P.'s.</p>
        <p>Celera Genomics, another subsidiary of PE that is competing with a government-backed project to obtain the sequence of all the letters in the human genetic code, has said that it plans to move into personalized medicine. The acquisition of Third Wave Technologies was expected to help in that task.</p>
        <p>Lance Fors, chief executive of Third Wave, said the antitrust review of the acquisition seemed to be taking longer than expected, with no assurance of approval. With the market for S.N.P.-finding equipment poised to boom, the company needed to be free to act. ''We are in the regulatory approval limbo and it makes it very hard to execute business plans,'' he said. ''It was a protracted review. The market opportunities could have passed us by.''</p>
        <p>Michael W. Hunkapiller, president of PE Biosystems, said the company had received ''no formal notification from the Justice Department that they had concerns.'' But he also said  the companies decided they needed to move more quickly.</p>
        <p>A Justice Department spokeswoman did not return a call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Third Wave and PE Biosystems said they would still collaborate. ''We still have access to the technology,'' Dr. Hunkapiller said. He said he was not aware of any broader investigation of PE. And two people who were questioned by the Justice Department, who insisted on anonymity, said the concern appeared confined to this deal.</p>
        <p>According to people in the industry, there appeared to be concern that PE Biosystems might not make the Third Wave technology widely available. There is also some concern that PE would have a strong position in the two types of technology used in studying gene variations.</p>
        <p>PE is already a leading supplier of chemicals and equipment for the polymerase chain reaction, or P.C.R., a widely used technique for replicating DNA so there is enough to be analyzed. Virtually all the systems used to detect gene variations rely on P.C.R. But Third Wave's technology does not, making it an alternative and one that is possibly cheaper and less time-consuming.</p>
        <p>Still, there were other factors, including the nearly 40 percent decline in PE Biosystems share price since the deal was announced.</p>
        <p>Arthur Holden, chairman and chief executive of the SNP Consortium, which was created by 10 large drug companies to search for the gene variations, said he was surprised by antitrust concern because many companies are offering technology to find S.N.P.'s. He said the drug companies would have welcomed the Third Wave deal because it would have provided more financial resources for the small company to perfect its technology.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
