<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sad Lot of a Rare Slave, Told in the Swing of Brazil</title>
    <meta content="26JOYC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dance Brazil</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED6153DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sad Lot of a Rare Slave, Told in the Swing of Brazil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Dance Brazil; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dance Brazil has come a long way since its founding in 1977. Inspired by the vision of Jelon Vieira, the company's choreographer and artistic director, and the performer Loremil Machado, the troupe played a crucial role in introducing traditional Afro-Brazilian dance to American dance audiences. The emphasis was on Capoeira, the exciting Brazilian martial arts form in which men battle with their feet, dancing upended on their hands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vieira has bravely -- and mostly successfully -- taken a next step. One may miss the do-or-die attack of earlier Capoeiristas. But the two world premieres presented on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater are an honest and interesting attempt to use the material to create more ambitious dance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dance Brazil has come a long way since its founding in 1977. Inspired by the vision of Jelon Vieira, the company's choreographer and artistic director, and the performer Loremil Machado, the troupe played a crucial role in introducing traditional Afro-Brazilian dance to American dance audiences. The emphasis was on Capoeira, the exciting Brazilian martial arts form in which men battle with their feet, dancing upended on their hands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vieira has bravely -- and mostly successfully -- taken a next step. One may miss the do-or-die attack of earlier Capoeiristas. But the two world premieres presented on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater are an honest and interesting attempt to use the material to create more ambitious dance.</p>
        <p>''Black Anastacia,'' choreographed by Carlos Dos Santos Jr. to music by Cyro Baptista and Peter Scherer, tells the story of a slave named Anastacia who was brought to Brazil in the 17th century. A tribal queen and Yoruba high priestess in Africa, Anastacia spoke out in Brazil against conversion to Roman Catholicism. She was muzzled with an iron mask, which forced her to communicate through gesture and her eyes.  She died from injuries inflicted by the mask, but her example enabled Africans brought to Brazil to worship in their own religion, in part by drawing parallels between Catholic and Yoruba religious icons and practices.</p>
        <p>The story is a little hard to follow but patience pays. The dance begins and ends with the dying, still beautiful old Anastacia (Sueli Ramos) in her iron mask. Her story is told in flashbacks centering around the vibrant, courageous young Anastacia (Agatha Oliveira). There are scenes of village life, the abduction of villagers to be sold into slavery and the miserable life of the slaves, who move like the living dead. Mr. Dos Santos tellingly uses Ms. Ramos to double as Yemanji, the goddess of the sea, with Alex Brito portraying both the Catholic priest and the captain of the guards who is both drawn to, and antagonistic toward, the young Anastacia.</p>
        <p>''Ginga'' is a joyous closing dance, a largely successful attempt by Mr. Vieira and Edileusa Dos Santos to evoke the modern-day Brazilian spirit with all its ''ginga'' or the swing of its everyday life. A full-company pageant set to vivid music by Tote Gira, performed live, ''Ginga'' incorporates Capoeira in slow-motion, impressively controlled solos and duets and in rushing, chasing group scenes performed by five Capoeiristas, one of them a big, bold woman. Their nicknames suggest they are the Brazilian equivalent of New York's popular hip-hoppers.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
