<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking Cold War Mold</title>
    <meta content="26MISS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shultz, George P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking Cold War Mold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush's proposal to consider unilateral reductions in American nuclear arsenal may foretell end of traditional theories of arms control (News Analysis); Bush is giving new voice to idea of large cuts in offensive weapons, coupled with construction of missile defenses; one of Bush's advisers is George P Shultz, who as secretary of state in Reagan administration was skeptic about Reagan's vision of space-based umbrella to shield US from nuclear warheads; Shultz says his thinking has evolved on such defenses because of rapid advance of technology (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush's proposal this week to consider unilateral reductions in the American nuclear arsenal was a break with decades of strategic doctrine, a break that may foretell the end of traditional theories of arms control.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Bush's vision, still lacking in many details, the threat of global annihilation -- or ''mutual assured destruction'' -- would no longer govern relations between the United States and other powers. The size of the American nuclear arsenal would no longer depend on the number of warheads that Russia possesses, nor be set in lengthy and painstaking arms control negotiations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush's proposal this week to consider unilateral reductions in the American nuclear arsenal was a break with decades of strategic doctrine, a break that may foretell the end of traditional theories of arms control.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Bush's vision, still lacking in many details, the threat of global annihilation -- or ''mutual assured destruction'' -- would no longer govern relations between the United States and other powers. The size of the American nuclear arsenal would no longer depend on the number of warheads that Russia possesses, nor be set in lengthy and painstaking arms control negotiations.</p>
        <p>And the defensive shield against nuclear weapons that he proposes to build -- significantly larger than that envisioned by the Clinton administration -- would be shared with American allies and, perhaps one day, with Russia or even China.</p>
        <p>Many of these ideas have been percolating among a bipartisan body of experts in the arms control community for years.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it was President Ronald Reagan who trumpeted the idea of slashing offensive nuclear weapons and relying instead on a defensive shield that would render nuclear missiles obsolete. And at Reykjavik, Iceland, in 1986, Mr. Reagan also agreed with Mikhail Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, on the principle of eliminating all their nuclear weapons, before he was pulled back by his advisers.</p>
        <p>Years later, arms control is suddenly back at center stage in a presidential campaign that was expected to focus on domestic policy. And some of those same advisers who pushed Mr. Reagan away from his radical views on arms control are now advising Governor Bush, the presumptive Republican nominee, as he gives new voice to the idea of large cuts in offensive weapons, coupled with construction of missile defenses, and places it squarely on the current political agenda.</p>
        <p>President Clinton will push his own arms control agenda in Moscow in 10 days when he meets with President Vladimir Putin to discuss cuts in long-range warheads. For new cuts, the administration wants Moscow to accept changes in a 1972 treaty to allow the fielding of a limited missile defense system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his advisers argue that it is long past time for a radical reassessment of nuclear armaments. The idea of holding populations hostage to annihilation is worse than immoral, they say; it is irrelevant. They complain that President Clinton has wasted much of the decade since the end of the cold war by clinging to the orthodoxy of using the specter of ''mutual assured destruction'' to deter any nuclear power from contemplating a first strike.</p>
        <p>''It's way past time for some fresh thinking about the structure of military capability in light of the kind of world we now live in,'' said George P. Shultz, secretary of state in the Reagan administration and one of Mr. Bush's foreign policy advisers. ''That really hasn't been done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shultz, who was well known as a skeptic about Mr. Reagan's vision of a space-based umbrella to shield the United States from nuclear warheads, said his thinking has evolved on such defenses because of the rapid advance of technology. He said Mr. Bush knows that current technology cannot produce an impermeable nuclear shield any time soon. But, he added, ''it's not too much to say there is a reasonable prospect to interpose a thin layer of defense.''</p>
        <p>Barry Blechman, a nuclear analyst at the Henry L. Stimson Center in Washington, called this sort of talk ''a breakthrough in Republican thinking.''</p>
        <p>''Bush is talking about going down to numbers that are lower than the military is currently willing to go,'' Mr. Blechman said.</p>
        <p>What's more, Mr. Bush is discussing the possibility of making such reductions unilaterally, rather than through years of negotiations with Russia or China over accuracy, throw-weights, basing modes, build-downs and other esoterica.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he envisions a sweeping review of strategic needs by the Pentagon that will help establish the optimal size of the nuclear force. He will then challenge Russia to match American reductions in weaponry. His chief foreign policy adviser, Condoleezza Rice, calls these ''reciprocal unilateral measures'' and describes them as a simpler and less time-consuming way to do arms control than the interminable talks that have dominated arms control efforts with Moscow.</p>
        <p>As another Bush adviser put it: ''The governor said he was going to figure out what we need, reduce to that level, and encourage the Russians to do the same. We're not going to build stuff we don't need just because Russians have stuff they don't need.''</p>
        <p>But that was precisely the calculation that governed the arms race in the second half of the 20th century: each superpower kept building up its stockpile to match the other's, far beyond the needs of deterrence or any possible military requirement.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore had hoped that such questions would not become central to the presidential campaign this year. He and other administration officials felt they had neutralized much of the Republican fervor for a robust missile shield by moving toward a decision this year on a limited system of land-based national missile defense.</p>
        <p>But Governor Bush portrayed the administration's approach as timid. He proposed a broader missile shield to appeal to conservatives and deeper weapons cuts than the administration has been willing to entertain.</p>
        <p>Since the days of the missile gap, four things have changed the nuclear equation in fundamental ways: The Soviet Union fell apart. Advances in technology have held out the promise of missile defenses that may be at least partly effective. Years of arms control agreements have reduced the numbers of nuclear weapons by thousands with no apparent impact on the relative security of the United States and Russia. And a handful of smaller nations, among them North Korea and Iraq, have made strides toward developing nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his advisers argued this week that United States policy has not kept pace with any of these developments.</p>
        <p>''While deterrence remains the first line of defense against nuclear attack, the standoff of the cold war was born of a different time,'' Mr. Bush said in a speech Tuesday at the National Press Club. ''Yet almost a decade after the end of the cold war, our nuclear policy still resides in that already distant past.''</p>
        <p>He proposed measures that would alter that policy, including building a defensive system that would cover all 50 states and could be extended to protect allies in Europe, the Middle East and Asia. In addition to holding out the possibility of large unilateral arms cuts, he said most American nuclear weapons should be removed from hair-trigger alert status.</p>
        <p>He also offered reassurance to Moscow and Beijing that the American system, though it would almost surely entail violating the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972, was not aimed at neutralizing their arsenals of long-range weapons.</p>
        <p>That is an argument that has so far been rejected by those two countries, especially by China, whose relatively small nuclear force could be rendered irrelevant by even the limited antimissile system favored by Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Both countries argue that the old system of deterrence that Mr. Bush derides as outdated is still the most reliable method of keeping the nuclear peace. Chinese officials have said they might have to accelerate their own nuclear program if the Americans build an antimissile shield.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore quickly issued a statement rejecting Mr. Bush's ideas as risky and irresponsible. He said Mr. Bush wanted to resurrect the discredited Star Wars program of the Reagan era and flaunt American military superiority over Russia, China and every other nation. And he chastised Governor Bush for opposing the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which was defeated in the Senate last fall on a largely party-line vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's response drew a rebuke from Mr. Bush's advisers.</p>
        <p>Brent Scowcroft, the national security adviser to President George Bush and a retired Air Force general, said construction of missile defenses should not be seen as a threat to the nuclear forces of Russia and China nor as an incentive for them to beef up their arsenals.</p>
        <p>Moscow has sufficient political and financial reasons to continue to draw down its nuclear stockpile, he said, while Beijing is likely to  continue its nuclear buildup regardless of what the United States does because it faces growing threats in its own region.</p>
        <p>''This goes back to the cooperative concept,'' he said. ''We tell both of them, 'North Korea is a problem for us; it's a problem for you, too. How can you help us, by changing the threat or helping us deal with it?' ''</p>
        <p>In a statement today, Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr., the senior Democrat on the Foreign Relations Committee, praised Mr. Bush's ideas -- up to a point. He applauded his intention to undertake a thorough review of America's nuclear posture and endorsed his plan to take weapons off high-alert status. He agreed that the size of the nuclear arsenal could safely be reduced.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Biden also said that Mr. Bush held an unrealistic view of the feasibility and cost of missile defenses and that a radical revision of decades of deterrence unnerve allies and adversaries alike.</p>
        <p>The senator urged Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore to remove the question from the political debate and to allow the next president to study the matter outside of the electoral arena.</p>
        <p>''The longest-lasting foreign policy debate is not likely to be settled any time soon,'' Mr. Biden said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
