<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eritrea Gives Up Vital Town to Ethiopia; Peace Hopes Rise</title>
    <meta content="Y26ETH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eritrea-International Relations-Ethiopia</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Eritrea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zalembessa (Eritrea)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Organization of African Unity</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Eritrea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Eritrea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EED9123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eritrea Gives Up Vital Town to Ethiopia; Peace Hopes Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eritrean troops abruptly pull back from Zalembessa, strategic town still in dispute with Ethiopia, in what may be decisive step toward end of war that has claimed thousands of lives and crippled two of Africa's most promising nations; Ethiopia has claimed Zalembessa as part of its territory and now says it has 'destroyed' Eritrean army; Eritrea says it withdrew to comply with plea from Organization of African Unity; says Ethiopia must now pull back from huge swath of Eritrean land it captured in last two weeks; major questions remain about whether either side is ready for peace; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eritrean troops abruptly pulled back today from a strategic town still in dispute with Ethiopia, in what may be a decisive step toward the end of a war that has claimed thousands of lives and crippled two of Africa's most promising nations.</p>
        <p>As ever in the two-year-old war, the sides could not agree what happened today. Ethiopia said Eritrean troops fled after a punishing, two-day assault on positions around the town of Zalembessa, which Ethiopia claims as part of its territory. Ethiopia said it had all but won the war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eritrean troops abruptly pulled back today from a strategic town still in dispute with Ethiopia, in what may be a decisive step toward the end of a war that has claimed thousands of lives and crippled two of Africa's most promising nations.</p>
        <p>As ever in the two-year-old war, the sides could not agree what happened today. Ethiopia said Eritrean troops fled after a punishing, two-day assault on positions around the town of Zalembessa, which Ethiopia claims as part of its territory. Ethiopia said it had all but won the war.</p>
        <p>''It was simple,'' said Selome Taddesse, an Ethiopian spokeswoman. The Eritrean army, she said, ''was smashed, kicked, destroyed, devastated, humiliated and sent packing and running.''</p>
        <p>But Eritrea, which has suffered major defeats since Ethiopia opened an offensive on May 12, said it had withdrawn to comply with a plea on Wednesday from the Organization of African Unity to end the war. Eritrea sought the moral high ground, saying that the war was not worth so many lives and that the burden was now on Ethiopia to pull back from the huge swath of Eritrean land it captured in the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they will pull out,'' said Yemane Ghebremeskel, a spokesman for Eritrea's president, Isaias Afwerki. ''I don't think they are interested in peace.''</p>
        <p>Major questions, in fact, remain about whether either side is ready for peace. There was still fighting today along the central front, though with none of the intensity of the recent battles. But with Zalembessa, which Eritrea captured in June 1998, back in Ethiopia's hands, Eritrea has lost a major strategic position, perhaps so important that the war may now find its way to an end.</p>
        <p>That was, at any rate, the way Ethiopians took the news today in the capital, Addis Ababa. Thousands of people thronged the streets, beeping car horns and cheering for what they called a major victory. In Asmara, Eritrea's capital, the streets were quiet.</p>
        <p>But relief groups said they would continue to work in western Eritrea, where hundreds of thousands of people were reported uprooted in the last week of fighting. Today, the United Nations World Food Program trucked out 79 tons of high-energy biscuits to feed nearly 40,000 Eritreans displaced in the west.</p>
        <p>The deliveries will continue, officials said, until the fighting is over and perhaps beyond, depending on whether people are able to get back home and plant crops. ''At the moment, it's unclear, it's unpredictable, it's fluid,'' said Lindsey Davies, a World Food Program spokeswoman in Asmara.</p>
        <p>The war began in May 1998, between two nations on the Horn of Africa that were once the closest of friends. Eritrea, for decades the northernmost province of Ethiopia, became independent in 1993 with Ethiopia's blessing in a swell of good feeling after fighters from north and south overthrew the military dictatorship of Megistu Haile Mariam.</p>
        <p>Both countries' economies were growing quickly. Both leaders, Mr. Afwerki of Eritrea and Meles Zenawi of Ethiopia, were hailed by Western nations as being among a new breed of progressive leaders in Africa.</p>
        <p>But they never marked their 620-mile border, and after months of skirmishes, Eritrea moved troops into the Badme region, claiming it according to colonial boundaries. Ethiopia said it was invaded.</p>
        <p>Since then, the war has been fought in fierce bursts, with both nations, among the poorest in the world, spending what United States officials said was $1 billion on weapons. Moreover, in a war of modern weaponry between two large and well-trained armies, the casualties have been stunningly high: Low estimates run from 20,000 dead, but the toll is perhaps triple that, from the fighting before May. The Organization of African Unity said this week that thousands more had died since.</p>
        <p>On May 12, Ethiopia opened an offensive, saying the cost of the war was too high, especially because about eight million of its people are facing severe food shortages.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia has gained ground with a speed that surprised many military experts, particularly because the Eritreans were fighting the kind of defensive war that they excelled at in their 30-year guerrilla war against Mr. Mengistu and Emperor Haile Selassie.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia has said publicly that its only goal was to regain the land that Eritrea occupied two years ago. But in private, Ethiopian officials made no secret of their desire to destroy Eritrea's military and, if possible, bring down Mr. Afwerki's government.</p>
        <p>Whether Ethiopia feels it has inflicted enough damage, many experts said, may determine whether the war will end soon.</p>
        <p>''The humiliation of Eritrea has long been an important part of the Ethiopian plan,'' said a Western military analyst in Ethiopia, who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Another possible block to peace is the essential scrappiness of Eritrea, a country of only 3.5 million people compared with Ethiopia's 60 million. For 30 years, the Eritreans held off the armies of Mr. Mengistu and Haile Selassie.</p>
        <p>Today, Eritrea continued to cast this war in a similar light, saying Mr. Zenawi's government also wants to conquer Eritrea.</p>
        <p>''They will continue the war,'' Mr. Ghebremeskel, the Eritrean spokesman, said. ''The international community will know that their agenda is something else.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taddesse denied that Ethiopia had any designs on land beyond the border, saying it would withdraw from the land it has taken in the west as soon as Eritrea pulled its troops from the roughly 20 areas it claims as its own. So far, she said, she saw no evidence of their withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I can assure you 100 percent,'' she said, ''the minute we regain our territory, we will stop.''</p>
        <p>For the last several months, Ethiopia and Eritrea had accepted all but the fine print of a peace deal brokered by the Organization of African Unity. A major sticking point was that Eritrea wanted a cease-fire before settling those final details; Ethiopia wanted the cease-fire afterward.</p>
        <p>Today, after nearly two weeks of fighting, Eritrea said the cease-fire could come later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
