<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sticky Road to a Killer App</title>
    <meta content="26YERG$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yergin, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D9123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sticky Road to a Killer App</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daniel Yergin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yergin, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Daniel Yergin offers advice on how to talk the talk when doing business on Internet</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years ago content was going to be king on the Internet. Last year it was all about selling to consumers. This year, especially as the Internet retail stocks plunge, it's e-business -- company-to-company commerce. If you want to keep up with something moving this fast, you need to know how to talk the talk of the new world.</p>
        <p>First, do not speak of markets or sectors. Say ''space,'' as in, ''They're in some of my space'' or ''We want to dominate that space.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years ago content was going to be king on the Internet. Last year it was all about selling to consumers. This year, especially as the Internet retail stocks plunge, it's e-business -- company-to-company commerce. If you want to keep up with something moving this fast, you need to know how to talk the talk of the new world.</p>
        <p>First, do not speak of markets or sectors. Say ''space,'' as in, ''They're in some of my space'' or ''We want to dominate that space.''</p>
        <p>But don't think of space as a vacuum. It is filled with verticals. These are something like industry sectors. What you must do with a vertical is  ''drill down'' into it until you hit paydirt, famously called a killer app  -- a lucrative niche to mine.</p>
        <p>The phrases B2C, as in business to consumer, and B2B, for business to business, must roll off the tongue as easily as ''good morning'' and ''good night.'' B2B drives down costs by disintermediating -- cutting out middle steps and companies from the business chain. It's great unless you are the one being disintermediated. For future positioning, it would be wise, as well, to begin practicing D2D, as in device-to-device, and m-commerce, for mobile commerce.</p>
        <p>''Business model'' should be mentioned a lot, mainly because no one really knows which Internet business models will work. And because another big question, reflected in the Nasdaq's troubles, is how one can actually make money from the Internet, it's good to mention ''revenue models'' frequently.</p>
        <p>Even if your models are shaky, you know what you want to attract:  eyeballs. And what you want from those eyeballs is stickiness -- that is, repeat business, people coming back to your site again and again. That means what you are really seeking are ''sticky eyeballs.''</p>
        <p>You already know, of course, about the new economy and the old economy. But be sure to use the terms in the preferable way -- not as nouns, but as modifiers, as in new-economy valuation or old-economy thinking. Space is new economy. Market is old economy. Got it?</p>
        <p>Legacy, with all its warm old associations of something gratefully inherited, like money or values, has turned decidedly negative. Now legacy is your existing business, with all its commitments and incentives and organization, holding you back and preventing you from moving in Internet time. The past is no longer prologue; it's a drag.</p>
        <p>As for the future, the basic rule to remember, one whose codification has been attributed to a number of people, is a sobering one. ''If you don't cannibalize your business, someone else will.'' Sticky eyeballs and all.</p>
        <p>Daniel Yergin, chairman of Cambridge Energy Research Associates in Cambridge, Mass., is co-author of ''The Commanding Heights.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Yergin, chairman of Cambridge Energy Research Associates in Cambridge, Mass., is co-author of ''The Commanding Heights.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
