<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDD133DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Eritrea Leaves Vital Town, Raising Hopes for Peace  Eritrean troops pulled back from a strategic town, Zalembessa, in what might be a decisive step toward ending fighting that has claimed thousands of lives in two years. Ethiopia said Eritrean troops fled after fighting around the town, which Ethiopia claims. Eritrea said it had withdrawn to comply with a plea from the Organization of African Unity to end the war, adding that the war was not worth its cost in human life. It also called on Ethiopia to pull back from the huge swath of Eritrean land captured in the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Venezuela Election Postponed  The Supreme Court ordered the postponement of the election scheduled for Sunday, saying that the ''reliability and transparency'' of the electoral process could not be guaranteed. No new date was set for the balloting. The National Electoral Council had conceded at a judicial hearing that it could not ensure an accurate, timely and fair vote count.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Eritrea Leaves Vital Town, Raising Hopes for Peace  Eritrean troops pulled back from a strategic town, Zalembessa, in what might be a decisive step toward ending fighting that has claimed thousands of lives in two years. Ethiopia said Eritrean troops fled after fighting around the town, which Ethiopia claims. Eritrea said it had withdrawn to comply with a plea from the Organization of African Unity to end the war, adding that the war was not worth its cost in human life. It also called on Ethiopia to pull back from the huge swath of Eritrean land captured in the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Venezuela Election Postponed  The Supreme Court ordered the postponement of the election scheduled for Sunday, saying that the ''reliability and transparency'' of the electoral process could not be guaranteed. No new date was set for the balloting. The National Electoral Council had conceded at a judicial hearing that it could not ensure an accurate, timely and fair vote count.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Peru Election to Proceed  The government of President Alberto K. Fujimori said a runoff presidential election would be held on Sunday despite nationwide protests and calls from Washington and other allies that it be postponed to ensure a legitimate ballot count. Violent protests followed the announcement.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Israeli Overture to Lebanon  Prime Minister Ehud Barak went to a northern border town and issued an appeal to the Lebanese president, Emile Lahud, to begin peace talks. Mr. Barak's remarks were made in an address the Israeli Parliament at its first plenary session outside Jerusalem, a demonstration of support for communities on the northern frontier following Israel's troop withdrawal from southern Lebanon.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Lebanese celebrated a new holiday, National Resistance Day, with a jubilant rally at the now empty Khiam prison, which is notorious in Lebanon for the reported torture of guerrilla fighters by Israel's allies in the South Lebanon Army militia. Low-level tensions surfaced at the Israeli-Lebanese border, as the exuberance mixed with the palpable hostility toward Israel.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Iran Hard-Liner Resigns  Former President Hashemi Rafsanjani resigned from the new Parliament, the state radio announced, depriving hard-liners of a leading figure in the power struggle between conservatives and reformists.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Serbian Opposition in Disarray  The leaders of the democratic opposition are divided about how to respond to the seizure of the main opposition television station by the government of President Slobodan Milosevic, undercutting their credibility and damaging the image of unity they are trying to project.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>Erich Mielke  A former head of the dreaded East German security agency known as the Stasi, he was 92.</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-17</p>
        <p>U.S. May Rank Vehicles By Tendency to Roll Over  The Transportation Department said it wanted to publish a ranking of cars, vans, pickups and sport utility vehicles that it said correlated with their tendency to turn over. Rollovers kill nearly 10,000 people a year, and the the department has been trying since 1973 to find a way to reduce those deaths. Officials said they hoped rankings would encourage manufacturers to make their vehicles lower and wider. But some safety advocates favored the establishment  of performance standards.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>C.I.A. Disciplines Officials  The C.I.A. said it had reprimanded six current or former officials for their roles in the initial investigation into evidence that John Deutch, the agency's former director, had mishandled classified information.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Pentagon Official Reprimanded  Defense Secretary William S. Cohen reprimanded his spokesman, Kenneth H. Bacon, and another senior Pentagon official for giving information to a journalist in 1998 from the personnel file of Linda R. Tripp.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Prosecutor in Secrets Case  George A. Stamboulidis, a federal prosecutor on Long Island, was named to lead the case against Wen Ho Lee, a scientist accused of illegally downloading nuclear secrets.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Meat Inspection Rules Voided  A federal judge in Texas struck down the Agriculture Department's inspection standards for meat-processing plants, saying they did not fairly measure sanitary conditions. The standards, and the laboratory tests used to enforce them, were the foundation of a four-year-old government effort to limit meat and poultry contamination by salmonella.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>'Epidemic of Oral Disease'  Oral diseases, from tooth decay to mouth cancer, threaten the health of poor people, members of minorities, children and the elderly, a surgeon general's report said.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Pataki Vetoes Measure On Fire Risk of Cigarettes  Governor Pataki vetoed a bill that would have made New York the first state to require that cigarettes meet fire-safety standards. He said the bill might have encouraged bootlegging, and he urged lawmakers to send him an amended version.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Queens Restaurant Killings  Two men bound, gagged and shot seven workers at a Wendy's in Flushing late Wednesday. Five died. The police expressed confidence that they would soon make arrests.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Graham Dance Cancellations  The Martha Graham Dance Company pulled out of two major festivals and suspended operations because of financial problems.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Giuliani to Return Donations  Mayor Giuliani's disbanded Senate campaign will begin returning nearly $2.8 million to contributors and will enclose with the checks a letter suggesting that the money be given to Representative Rick A. Lazio.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A Costly Pursuit in New Jersey  Jon S. Corzine has already spent nearly $25 million seeking the Democratic Senate nomination, more than three times as much as anyone ever spent on a Senate primary and within striking distance of the most ever spent on an entire Senate election.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Drugs Through the Internet  The police and officials at the Peddie School in Hightstown, N.J., said the four students taken unconscious to a hospital on Tuesday had overdosed on a legal cough syrup narcotic, dextromethorpan, or DXM, that they bought online. The 17-year-olds were released the next day. Experts say DXM is gaining popularity among teenagers.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Knicks Fall to 0-2 vs. Pacers  Indiana beat the Knicks, 88-84, in Game 2 of the Eastern finals.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18, 20</p>
        <p>Phone-Cable Merger Approved  The Justice Department approved AT&amp;T's acquisition of MediaOne, giving it control over more than a third of the nation's cable network for television, high-speed Internet access and online phone service.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Doctors Sue 3 Big Insurers  The California Medical Association accused WellPoint Health Networks; the HealthNet unit of Foundation Health Systems; and PacifiCare Health Systems of violating federal racketeering laws by coercing doctors and interfering with physician-patient relationships for financial reasons.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Shaking Up Merrill Lynch  E. Stanley O'Neal, head of the firm's brokerage business, was said to have picked a fellow nonbroker, James Gorman, as No. 2 executive, moved other executives out of top jobs and promoted several others.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; E31-44</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Nuclear swords and shields; judicial reforms in Albany; a threat to meat inspection.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E41  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
