<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Star Rebuked By Equity</title>
    <meta content="26BROA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON STAGE AND OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Actors Equity Association</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shubert Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Theater Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lane, Nathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Rosie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">lithgow, john</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ride Down Mount Morgan, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sweet Smell of Success, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">sweet smell of success, the (play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Manhattan Theater Club</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Shubert Organization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Actors Equity Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Nathan Lane</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DC123DF935A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Star Rebuked By Equity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; Actors Equity panel rebukes Patrick Stewart for curtain speech attacking Shubert Organization for not promoting play Ride Down Mount Morgan; Nathan Lane to help Rosie O'Donnell host Tony Awards; Kevin Spacey provides funds to keep play Cobb from closing; John Lithgow to star in workshop of musical version of The Sweet Smell of Success; photo; Manhattan Theater Club announces 2000-2001 schedule featuring work of young playwrights (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a mild rebuke, a disciplinary panel of Actors Equity has ruled that Patrick Stewart, the star of Arthur Miller's ''Ride Down Mount Morgan,'' will have to make a formal -- but not public -- apology to the Shubert Organization for a curtain speech he made attacking the play's producers.</p>
        <p>The speech, in which Mr. Stewart accused the Shuberts of failing to promote ''Mount Morgan,'' prompted the Shuberts to file disciplinary charges against Mr. Stewart accusing him of unprofessional behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a mild rebuke, a disciplinary panel of Actors Equity has ruled that Patrick Stewart, the star of Arthur Miller's ''Ride Down Mount Morgan,'' will have to make a formal -- but not public -- apology to the Shubert Organization for a curtain speech he made attacking the play's producers.</p>
        <p>The speech, in which Mr. Stewart accused the Shuberts of failing to promote ''Mount Morgan,'' prompted the Shuberts to file disciplinary charges against Mr. Stewart accusing him of unprofessional behavior.</p>
        <p>After hearing several hours of testimony on May 11, the panel, composed of five union members, made its decision.</p>
        <p>A 10-day appeal period ended yesterday, and several people familiar with the decision said Mr. Stewart would not appeal it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart, who has won critical praise for his role as a defiant bigamist in ''Mount Morgan,'' made the speech at the matinee and evening performances of ''Mount Morgan'' on April 29. He said he felt ''frustrated and helpless'' because of what he considered the producers' lack of support for the play.</p>
        <p>The Shuberts countered by saying that more than $1 million had been spent on promoting the play, which received good reviews.</p>
        <p>Under Equity rules, an actor found to be behaving in an unprofessional manner can be fined or, in extremely rare cases, expelled from the union.</p>
        <p>Tony Lineup</p>
        <p>The Tony Awards announced the schedule yesterday for the June 4 telecast, and the entertainment lineup was no surprise: seven musical numbers (from three revivals and four new musicals), and a big opening number from the host Rosie O'Donnell.</p>
        <p>As for the plays, Keith Sherman, a spokesman for the awards, said the plays would be part of ''a videotaped package'' devoted to both new work and revivals. Last year's approach -- a medley of lines from a half-dozen plays -- was widely viewed as a failure.</p>
        <p>One small surprise yesterday: Nathan Lane will help Ms. O'Donnell with the hosting duties. His official title? Special guest star.</p>
        <p>''They had toyed with saying 'The Tony Awards, hosted by Rosie O'Donnell, valet parking by Nathan Lane,' '' he said. ''But they thought this was better.''</p>
        <p>Kevin Spacey Steps Up</p>
        <p>As far as pinch hitters go, there are not many people you'd rather have in your dugout than Kevin Spacey.</p>
        <p>Just ask the current cast and crew of ''Cobb,'' the 1989 drama by Lee Blessing about the irascible baseball legend Ty Cobb who starred for the Detroit Tigers in the early years of the century. The show, which received good reviews but has had only decent audiences, was to have closed its run at Theater 3 on West 43rd Street last Sunday.</p>
        <p>But then Mr. Spacey entered the game. Last Thursday night, Mr. Spacey, a recent Oscar winner for ''American Beauty,'' saw ''Cobb'' during a sweep through New York between films. The draw, he said, was Matthew Mabe, who plays the title role and was an understudy last year in ''The Iceman Cometh,'' in which Mr. Spacey starred.</p>
        <p>''I figured I should go to support Matthew,'' said Mr. Spacey. ''Plus, I never knew anything about Cobb.''</p>
        <p>What he found so impressed him that when he heard about the imminent closing, he pulled out the theatrical equivalent of a Louisville Slugger: his checkbook.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Spacey nor officials at the Melting Pot Theater Company, the producers, are saying how much money Mr. Spacey gave, but it was enough to extend the run at least two weeks. Mr. Spacey has been phoning ''anybody who'll take my call'' to get producers to see the show.</p>
        <p>''It's the kind of theater I like to encourage,'' Mr. Spacey said. ''I don't mind kicking up a little dust to get people to pay attention to something like this.''</p>
        <p>'Sweet Smell'</p>
        <p>In the canon of loathsome megalomaniacs, they don't get much better than J. J. Hunsecker.</p>
        <p>Portrayed by Burt Lancaster in the 1957 classic, ''Sweet Smell of Success,'' Hunsecker is a powerful Broadway columnist whose career of dishing gossip and innuendo has hardened him into a dark, ruthless cipher.</p>
        <p>In short, Hunsecker is a character most actors would love to play. And now, with a workshop of the musical version of ''Sweet Smell'' in the offing, John Lithgow has landed the role. Brian d'Arcy James will play Sidney Falco, the scurrilous press agent portrayed by Tony Curtis in the movie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lithgow is probably best known now from the television show  ''Third Rock From the Sun.'' But he won a Tony in 1973 for ''The Changing Room'' and was nominated two other times.</p>
        <p>The six-week workshop, which begins on June 26, will conclude with two sets of performances for potential producers at the beginning of August. It is not, unfortunately, open to the public, but the production itself is aiming for a Broadway debut in the spring of 2001.</p>
        <p>Young Playwrights</p>
        <p>A youth movement (of sorts) has taken hold at Manhattan Theater Club.</p>
        <p>The theater, which scored a critical hit this week with ''Proof,'' by the 30-year-old playwright David Auburn, has announced a 2000-2001 schedule packed with all manner of talented 30-somethings.</p>
        <p>Heading the list is David Lindsay-Abaire, also 30, whose newest play, ''Wonder of the World,'' opens the season on Stage One. The show, about a woman who leaves her husband in search of adventure, had its world premiere at the Woolly Mammoth Theater in Washington this week. On Stage Two, the playwright Melanie Marnich, 37, will stage her play ''Blur.''</p>
        <p>Another new voice, Rebecca Gilman, 35, will also be produced on Stage One with her ''Boy Gets Girl,'' a drama about a woman who is stalked by a stranger.</p>
        <p>In the sole nod to seniority, the latest from Alan Ayckbourn, 61, his ''Comic Potential,'' fills out the schedule on Stage One.</p>
        <p>ON STAGE AND OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
