<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A China Unicom Offering Raises Almost $5 Billion</title>
    <meta content="Y17TEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">China Unicom Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DA1631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A China Unicom Offering Raises Almost $5 Billion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China Unicom Ltd, China's second largest phone carrier, raises $4.92 billion amid bouyant demand in largest initial public stock offering in Asia outside Japan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Capitalizing on the recent popularity of telecommunications stocks and the enduring appeal of the world's most populous country, China Unicom Ltd. raised $4.92 billion today in the largest initial public offering in Asia outside Japan.</p>
        <p>The company, China's second-largest telephone carrier, priced its shares at 15.58 Hong Kong dollars each, or about $2. That is near the top of the range set by the company earlier this week. Unicom had already raised the range by 10 percent to account for the buoyant demand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Capitalizing on the recent popularity of telecommunications stocks and the enduring appeal of the world's most populous country, China Unicom Ltd. raised $4.92 billion today in the largest initial public offering in Asia outside Japan.</p>
        <p>The company, China's second-largest telephone carrier, priced its shares at 15.58 Hong Kong dollars each, or about $2. That is near the top of the range set by the company earlier this week. Unicom had already raised the range by 10 percent to account for the buoyant demand.</p>
        <p>Executives close to Unicom said the institutional part of the offer, which accounts for most of the 2.46 billion shares, was subscribed more than five times over. Unicom priced its American depository shares at $19.99 a share. The shares will begin trading in New York next Wednesday and in Hong Kong the next day.</p>
        <p>''Unicom is going to be very successful,'' said Seton Lor, a fund manager at Manulife Financial, an investment firm here. ''Telecom stocks are very much in vogue these days. The stock is also priced at a lower multiple than China Telecom, because it has businesses other than cellular.''</p>
        <p>China Telecom, the nation's largest telephone carrier, held the record for the largest previous offering, raising $4.2 billion in late 1997. Unicom, which was started by the Chinese government in 1994 to create competition for Telecom, has languished in the shadow of its powerful rival.</p>
        <p>It has less than one-third the mobile-phone subscribers: 4.15 million versus 15.6 million. It has had a revolving door of senior managers. It has zigzagged confusingly on cellular technology. It has been forced to unravel partnerships with foreign investors. And it derives 63 percent of its revenue from paging -- a service many experts regard as the horse and buggy of the Internet age.</p>
        <p>Yet for all that, China Unicom now has its own page in the annals of China's corporate reform. Even people who faulted the company agree that it has bright prospects.</p>
        <p>''Unicom has an enormous opportunity in front of it,'' said Hani Abuali, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette in Hong Kong. ''China is going to be the world's largest cellular market.''</p>
        <p>The number of cellular subscribers in China jumped from 13.7 million in 1997 to 43.2 million at the end of last year. That still represents a penetration rate of only 3.4 percent. China Unicom's executives note that the company's franchises, which extend up and down the country's economically prosperous coast, cover 67 percent of the total cellular subscribers in China.</p>
        <p>Statistics like that have made China Telecom a shooting star on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. Since May 24, its shares have risen more than 30 percent. That performance goaded Unicom's executives to raise the price range of their offering. Analysts say the timing was impeccable.</p>
        <p>''From my discussions with fund managers, people are looking for alternative ways to invest in China,'' Mr. Abuali said. ''This is a good alternative investment.''</p>
        <p>Unicom's success is also a good omen for other large Chinese state-owned companies, which the government hopes to begin privatizing in the coming months. These include the China National Offshore Oil Corporation and Sinopec, an oil and petrochemical giant.</p>
        <p>China Unicom's offering is managed by Morgan Stanley Dean Witter and the China International Capital Corporation, a Beijing-based investment bank partly owned by Morgan Stanley.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
