<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Africa's Swelling Refugee Crisis</title>
    <meta content="17SAT1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5D71631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Africa's Swelling Refugee Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on plight of Africa's outcast multitudes; calls for international help but also points out that improving lives of refugees also requires new attitudes within Africa and end to wars</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The recent fighting between Ethiopia and Eritrea and the war in Sierra Leone are adding to Africa's outcast multitudes. Refugees and the internally displaced -- those who flee their homes without crossing borders -- are among the saddest byproducts of the continent's wars. Africa has more than 3 million refugees and some 15 million internally displaced, a much higher number than 10 years ago. These outcasts are straining the resources of their host communities and the good will of donors, and yet there is no end to the stream of people fleeing for their lives.</p>
        <p>The average refugee from Kosovo received more than $1 a day from the international community. In Africa, the average refugee gets 11 cents. The internally displaced, who are only now starting to receive assistance from the outside world, most often get nothing. In many refugee camps, the only nourishment provided by the World Food Program and the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees is flour and oil. Powdered milk is sometimes available, and nutritional biscuits are given to malnourished children. Because donor nations are giving less, the refugee agency has had to cut back on health care and education, which only goes through age 10 or 12. Some refugees from Somalia and Sudan have lived in these conditions for 20 years, unable to return until their homelands are at peace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The recent fighting between Ethiopia and Eritrea and the war in Sierra Leone are adding to Africa's outcast multitudes. Refugees and the internally displaced -- those who flee their homes without crossing borders -- are among the saddest byproducts of the continent's wars. Africa has more than 3 million refugees and some 15 million internally displaced, a much higher number than 10 years ago. These outcasts are straining the resources of their host communities and the good will of donors, and yet there is no end to the stream of people fleeing for their lives.</p>
        <p>The average refugee from Kosovo received more than $1 a day from the international community. In Africa, the average refugee gets 11 cents. The internally displaced, who are only now starting to receive assistance from the outside world, most often get nothing. In many refugee camps, the only nourishment provided by the World Food Program and the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees is flour and oil. Powdered milk is sometimes available, and nutritional biscuits are given to malnourished children. Because donor nations are giving less, the refugee agency has had to cut back on health care and education, which only goes through age 10 or 12. Some refugees from Somalia and Sudan have lived in these conditions for 20 years, unable to return until their homelands are at peace.</p>
        <p>Yet some of these refugees are not much worse off than their hosts. Guinea, a very poor country, now has more refugees per capita than any other nation. Some countries, such as Sudan, produce refugees in one region and shelter them in another.  Host nations get some reimbursement from the U.N. and sometimes get food aid, but they must provide land and some social services and keep order in the camps. African countries, historically generous to refugees -- especially when they were fleeing colonial oppression -- are now balking at the burden. Many politicians are finding it profitable to restrict refugees' rights and blame them, rightly or wrongly, for problems like crime.</p>
        <p>The exodus from the Rwandan genocide in 1994 illustrated a new, debilitating obstacle to protecting refugees. Perpetrators of the genocide fled to the camps across the border, turning them into internationally funded military bases. Rwanda was an extreme example, but many camps -- which host countries tend to build on the border to emphasize their temporary nature -- become recruiting zones or rest stops for combatants. It is common for camps to be controlled by one side in the conflict. Some camps of refugees from Sudan in Ethiopia, for example, are essentially run by the Sudan People's Liberation Army, and relief workers must carefully negotiate their access.</p>
        <p>The U.N.'s refugee relief agency is weakly managed and needs more oversight -- in part because member nations use it as a patronage pit -- and its dependence on host countries to provide services is another breeding ground for corruption.  But the agency is struggling with a difficult and dangerous mission: 24 members of its staff, and 23 workers for the World Food Program, have been killed since 1992. The reluctance of donors has also crippled the agency, which finds it easier to raise money for emergency appeals than to alleviate the chronic miseries of most African refugees.</p>
        <p>Although current refugee aid is meager, its most important shortcoming is that it does not go to the vast majority who have not crossed a border. The internally displaced should get aid when countries request it, or when a state has collapsed to the point where no one can give permission.</p>
        <p>Improving the lives of refugees also requires new attitudes within Africa. Host governments should not build camps close to borders. Countries such as Tanzania, Kenya and South Africa have joined many European nations and the United States in passing or considering laws that would turn away refugees or restrict their rights. These laws are pernicious everywhere. But what refugees need most is what all Africans need most -- an end to the wars that have diverted the continent's resources and created so much suffering.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
