<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Both Parties Offer Snapshots of Their Expected Nominees</title>
    <meta content="Y17ADB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFDB1631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Both Parties Offer Snapshots of Their Expected Nominees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts and reviews of ads promoting candidacies of Al Gore and George W Bush; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Republican and Democratic National Committees are on the air this weekend with issue advertisements on behalf of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore. The spots are running in 17 states, including crucial ones like Illinois, Michigan, Ohio and Pennsylvania.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Republican and Democratic National Committees are on the air this weekend with issue advertisements on behalf of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore. The spots are running in 17 states, including crucial ones like Illinois, Michigan, Ohio and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The Republican Spot</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Cold Harbor Films</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- In the opening scenes, greeting-card images of America -- an orange sunrise, a windmill on a wheat field -- melt into one another. Cut to a quick succession of shots of Mr. Bush mixing with voters and then to a series of portraits of average citizens.</p>
        <p>SCRIPT -- Announcer: ''With our nation at peace and more prosperous than ever, now is the time to find real solutions to America's problems. George Bush knows that to keep our commitment to seniors we must strengthen and improve Social Security now, or the retirement of the baby boom generation will push it near bankruptcy. He's proposing a bipartisan plan to strengthen and improve Social Security. The Bush plan guarantees everyone at or near retirement every dollar of their benefits. No cuts in Social Security. You paid into it, it's your money and it will be there for you. And the Bush plan gives younger workers a choice to invest a small part of their Social Security in sound investments they control for higher returns. Learn more about George Bush's voluntary plan for personal Social Security retirement accounts. The Bush blueprint: Better for seniors today, better for all of us tomorrow.</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- With aging baby boomers inching ever closer to eligibility for retirement benefits, shoring up Social Security has become a signature issue of the presidential campaign. The party's 60-second commercial highlights Mr. Bush's plans for a partial privatization of the system, allowing workers to invest part of their payroll taxes as they see fit. Vice President Al Gore has been a fierce critic of the idea, arguing that the less financially savvy could fall prey to foolhardy investment schemes.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- A direct appeal to Mr. Bush's own generation. While polls show that older people are wary of privatization plans for their retirement money, younger voters are more amenable to the idea. The spot is also an emblem of the Bush marketing style: no scare tactics, just lots of postcard panoramas and loving snaps of the candidate wading into crowds. As such, it is indistinguishable from Mr. Bush's own commercials.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Spot</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Victory 2000</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- In 30 seconds, with a musical underscoring but no voice-over, a Gore family album, including black-and-white pictures of Mr. Gore as a boy with his father, Senator Albert Gore Sr., and shots of the candidate with his wife, Tipper, and their children. Cut to a graphic that says, ''The Gore plan: promote responsible fatherhood,'' and shots of other fathers and children.</p>
        <p>SCRIPT -- (graphics only) Don't ever doubt the impact that fathers have on children. Children with strong fathers learn trust. That they're wanted, they have value. Boys learn from their fathers how to be fathers. I know I did -- Al Gore.</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- Yes, that is Mr. Gore's family.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- The commercial, pegged to Father's Day, is serenely composed, and more of a traditional biographical spot than an issue advertisement. The reference to Mr. Gore's plan to encourage fathers to live up to their obligations comes from a proposal he recently outlined that would provide financial bonuses to states that did the most to crack down on deadbeat fathers. But that is almost subtext in this spot, which is essentially a testimonial to a candidate's family values.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
