<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Safety, Texas A&amp;M Suspends Bonfire Rituals</title>
    <meta content="Y17BONF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas A&amp;m University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowen, Ray (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DB1631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Safety, Texas A&amp;M Suspends Bonfire Rituals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Texas A&amp;M president Ray Bowen suspends football bonfire ritual for two years, in response to accident last November that killed 12 people; photo; university will use time to plan scaled-down, tightly supervised event (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In response to the worst accident in the history of Texas A&amp;M University, the president of the university today suspended its traditional football bonfire ritual for two years to allow time to plan a scaled-down, tightly supervised event that will better ensure student safety.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the university's president, Dr. Ray Bowen, reverberated across Texas and punctuated a seven-month period of criticism and Texas A&amp;M soul-searching after a four-tier stack of logs nearly 60 feet tall collapsed Nov. 18, killing 11 students and a former student and injuring 27 others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In response to the worst accident in the history of Texas A&amp;M University, the president of the university today suspended its traditional football bonfire ritual for two years to allow time to plan a scaled-down, tightly supervised event that will better ensure student safety.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the university's president, Dr. Ray Bowen, reverberated across Texas and punctuated a seven-month period of criticism and Texas A&amp;M soul-searching after a four-tier stack of logs nearly 60 feet tall collapsed Nov. 18, killing 11 students and a former student and injuring 27 others.</p>
        <p>''That tragedy was a wake-up call for everyone here and everyone in the country,'' said Dr. Bowen in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>University officials said the bonfire could resume in the fall of 2002, provided that students met conditions established by Dr. Bowen. He said that when classes resumed in late summer, he would convene a committee of administrators, faculty members and students to begin reorganizing the event.</p>
        <p>Canceling the next two bonfires will allow appropriate time to plan, Dr. Bowen said. He predicted that a smaller, safer bonfire tower would be built, with increased oversight.</p>
        <p>''We are quite optimistic we can create a safe structure,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The bonfire, a tradition that began in 1909 at Texas A&amp;M on the eve of its football game against its archrival, the University of Texas, annually draws thousands of people to the A&amp;M campus, about 90 miles northwest of here in College Station.</p>
        <p>Student crews working with little supervision stacked and bound thousands of logs felled from nearby forests into a tower shaped like a wedding cake. The final week of construction, known as Push, required round-the-clock efforts as students raced to finish in time to set the stack afire at a pep rally before the game against the University of Texas.</p>
        <p>In May, a five-member independent commission appointed by Texas A&amp;M issued a report saying that design flaws in the log tower were largely to blame for the collapse. The report also said students building the tower were inadequately trained, and criticized university officials for failing to provide adequate supervision.</p>
        <p>Reaction to today's announcement was quiet on the A&amp;M campus. The academic year ended several weeks ago and most students had left the campus. Only about a dozen students and faculty members attended Dr. Bowen's news conference.</p>
        <p>''I think it's good they're making this decision, though I don't know about the two-year period of holding off,'' said Justin Lightsey, 19, a sophomore from nearby Bryan. ''I think it's good they're making it safer. My parents, though, told me not to participate.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Braus, whose son Dominic remains in physical therapy after suffering extensive injuries to his arm in the collapse, said she was pleased with the new safeguards.</p>
        <p>Ms. Braus also said that she did not blame the university for her son's injury and that she was elated that one of A&amp;M's oldest traditions would eventually continue.</p>
        <p>''You can't stop Christmas trees, you can't stop Easter eggs,'' Ms. Braus said. ''These traditions have to continue.''</p>
        <p>The pressure to continue the bonfire tradition has been enormous. More than 8,000 students have signed a petition supporting its continuance.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month the Texas A&amp;M faculty senate recommended that Dr. Bowen suspend the tradition for at least one year. And on Wednesday, the Texas Board of Professional Engineers voted to conduct an inquiry to determine whether state engineering laws were violated.</p>
        <p>Lt. Gov. Rick Perry, an alumnus of the university, endorsed the new policy. ''He supports the administration,'' said Eric Bearse, a spokesman for the lieutenant governor. ''The most important thing is to ensure the safety of the students, and they have put together a process that puts safety first and foremost.''</p>
        <p>Officials said the restructured bonfires would differ greatly from those of recent years, when students spent up to three months cutting down thousands of trees and then building the tower of logs. In the future, the event will last only two weeks. The trees will be donated from companies; the students will not cut them down. Also, Dr. Bowen said, the reduced size of the tower will lessen the environmental damage, a point criticized even before the accident.</p>
        <p>In addition, construction will end by midnight, and university officials will provide continual supervision. A fence will surround the site and a video camera will record construction. The hierarchy of the student organization, which had been run by upperclassmen known as Red Pots and Brown Pots, will be reorganized.</p>
        <p>And the unstable wedding cake shape will be abandoned in favor of a teepee shape used in the 1950's and 60's. Professional engineers will draft the design and establish the construction protocol.</p>
        <p>Officials said that the bonfire structure would be assessed and certified every year and that failure to meet the specifications would result in penalties.</p>
        <p>''If they don't comply, if the rules are broken, there will be no bonfire the following year,'' said Cindy Lawson, the school's executive director for community relations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
