<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Expected on Dismissals In White House Travel Office</title>
    <meta content="17TRAV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White House Travel Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Robert W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5D71631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Expected on Dismissals In White House Travel Office</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Independent counsel Robert W Ray is expected to file final report on Hillary Clinton's role in firing of seven employees of White House travel office (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The independent counsel who has been investigating the Clintons on several fronts is expected to file his final report next week with a special judicial panel on what role Hillary Rodham Clinton played in the firing of seven longtime employees in the White House travel office.</p>
        <p>The report will not be made public, but lawyers familiar with the investigation say it is highly unlikely to include a recommendation that anyone be prosecuted. The independent counsel, Robert W. Ray, who replaced Kenneth W. Starr last October, may announce that conclusion publicly when he files the report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The independent counsel who has been investigating the Clintons on several fronts is expected to file his final report next week with a special judicial panel on what role Hillary Rodham Clinton played in the firing of seven longtime employees in the White House travel office.</p>
        <p>The report will not be made public, but lawyers familiar with the investigation say it is highly unlikely to include a recommendation that anyone be prosecuted. The independent counsel, Robert W. Ray, who replaced Kenneth W. Starr last October, may announce that conclusion publicly when he files the report.</p>
        <p>The report itself, which will not be available to the public for at least three months, will deal with whether Mrs. Clinton was a moving force behind the decision to fire the seven in 1993 and whether she or other White House aides tried to conceal whatever role she played.</p>
        <p>Under the independent counsel law governing Mr. Ray's operations, Mrs. Clinton's lawyers will be given an opportunity to review any reference to her in the report. She is entitled to include any dissenting comments in the next 90 days.</p>
        <p>After that period, the three-member judicial panel is allowed to make the report public, meaning its disclosure could come in the final stages of Mrs. Clinton's Senate campaign.</p>
        <p>The report will deal with two starkly contradictory accounts of Mrs. Clinton's role in the dismissal of the travel office employees just a few months after she and her husband moved into the White House.</p>
        <p>The workers who helped plan arrangements for news organizations as they accompanied the president on his travels found themselves suddenly barred from the White House grounds on May 19, 1993.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton has regularly depicted herself as largely uninvolved in the dismissals. Her lawyer told the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, that she had no idea how the firings were initiated.</p>
        <p>In March 1996, a House committee began an investigation and she offered a more detailed response, insisting that she was only interested in being kept informed about what was happening in the travel office.</p>
        <p>She also told investigators that she was busy at the time helping her daughter get adjusted in a new school, tending father who had suffered a stroke and trying to plan a national health care system.</p>
        <p>The independent counsel began investigating the matter at the request of Attorney General Janet Reno after a memorandum was found in which a senior White House official said Mrs. Clinton had instigated the firings and created a climate of anxiety in the White House about doing it quickly.</p>
        <p>The official, David Watkins, said in his memorandum to Thomas F. McLarty III, then the White House chief of staff, that ''we both knew there would be hell to pay'' if ''we failed to take swift and decisive action in conformity with the first lady's wishes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
