<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Workers Cut As Hospitals Tighten Belts</title>
    <meta content="17HOSP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beth Israel Medical Center (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4D61631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Workers Cut As Hospitals Tighten Belts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City hospitals, reeling from federal spending cuts and struggling to adapt to an era in which doctors' offices have replaced them as centers for many procedures, are desperetely cutting their budgets; some centers, notably Beth Israel Medical Center and St Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital, are laying off workers and scaling back medical departments; others, like city's public hospitals, are farming out functions like security (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City hospitals, reeling from federal spending cuts and struggling to adapt to an era in which doctors' offices have replaced them as centers for many procedures, are desperately cutting their budgets.</p>
        <p>Some centers, notably Beth Israel Medical Center and St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital, are laying off workers and scaling back medical departments. Others, like the city's public hospitals, are farming out functions like security. And executives at nearly every hospital, even those serving affluent communities, are turning a sharp eye to budgets, looking for things to trim or eliminate as they clamor for relief from Washington.</p>
        <p>''Who else am I going to lay off around here?'' said Frederick D. Alley, the chief executive of Brooklyn Hospital Center. ''I have been at it for four years.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City hospitals, reeling from federal spending cuts and struggling to adapt to an era in which doctors' offices have replaced them as centers for many procedures, are desperately cutting their budgets.</p>
        <p>Some centers, notably Beth Israel Medical Center and St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital, are laying off workers and scaling back medical departments. Others, like the city's public hospitals, are farming out functions like security. And executives at nearly every hospital, even those serving affluent communities, are turning a sharp eye to budgets, looking for things to trim or eliminate as they clamor for relief from Washington.</p>
        <p>''Who else am I going to lay off around here?'' said Frederick D. Alley, the chief executive of Brooklyn Hospital Center. ''I have been at it for four years.''</p>
        <p>The hospitals under the most financial pressure are those that serve a large number of uninsured patients, who drain the coffers of state programs, and patients enrolled in Medicare, the government insurance program for the elderly and disabled, which has significantly trimmed reimbursements to hospitals in recent years.</p>
        <p>This week, executives at Continuum Health Partners, the parent of Beth Israel, St. Luke's-Roosevelt and Long Island College Hospital, said that they would eliminate 800 to 900 jobs in July, most from their executive ranks. About 200 would be union health care positions, said Peter A. Kelly, the system's chief operating officer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly and his staff are further evaluating each of its centers' programs with an eye toward cutting. ''I would rather eliminate a program, as opposed to making across-the-board reductions that would strip away more staff,'' Mr. Kelly said in an interview, adding that he has not ruled out future layoffs. Departments under particular scrutiny, he said, were pediatrics and obstetrics. Both departments tend to run a deficit in most hospitals. .</p>
        <p>Other hospitals are making similar moves.</p>
        <p>The New York Health and Hospitals Corporation, which runs the public hospitals, plans to cut the number of its workers this year, said a spokeswoman, Dr. Jane Zimmerman. In December, the corporation offered early retirement, and 800 people took it.</p>
        <p>''We anticipate in the next fiscal year, we will reduce the work force by 1,000 people,'' she said, of the period beginning July 1. Most of that, she said, is expected to come through attrition.</p>
        <p>The system has a hiring freeze and has taken out 1,000 beds, which, because of obscure components of federal law, they hope will result in more government money. It will also hire outside companies to be in charge of hospital security in hopes of saving $10 million a year.</p>
        <p>But even the wealthier centers are crying penury. New York Presbyterian Hospital will probably make labor cuts soon, said its president, Dr. Herbert Pardes.</p>
        <p>At Mount Sinai Medical Center, $100 million in cuts were needed to break even by the end of the year, and the hospital is not there yet, said its chief executive, Dr. John W. Rowe.</p>
        <p>''We have fired consultants and reduced the work force by 400 positions,'' he said, 100 of them layoffs. None of the eliminated jobs involved patient care, he added.</p>
        <p>''We are considering the next round of budget reductions to be implemented over the summer, and it is quite possible the further work force reductions will be needed to close our gap,'' Dr. Rowe said. ''We are giving a robust review of each clinical program as we evaluate opportunities for reductions.''</p>
        <p>The hospitals that are the most cash-strapped are clearly those that serve the growing ranks of New York's uninsured. Brookdale Hospital and Medical Center, for example, which serves a huge swath of poor neighborhoods in Brooklyn, has been negotiating with Albany leaders for support, said the hospital's chief executive, Dr. Alvin I. Kahn. The help is ''very crucial,'' Dr. Kahn said. ''Our whole future rides on them.''</p>
        <p>In addition, the hospital has eliminated its ophthalmology residency program, though not the department. New York Methodist Hospital in Brooklyn recently shuttered its home health care agency to stem losses approaching $5 million.</p>
        <p>Most hospitals trace their troubles to the Balanced Budget Act passed by Congress in 1997. Under the act, Medicare reimbursements were reduced, as were special funds for hospitals serving poor populations. New York area hospitals, many of which are affiliated with medical education programs, were especially hurt by the act's reductions to centers that train doctors.</p>
        <p>By 2002, when all the cuts are fully phased in, hospitals in New York State will have lost $5 billion in federal revenue, studies show. New York and seven other states were spared further Medicare cuts though a recent move by the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>Couple that with the thousands of people who have dropped out of the Medicaid program under welfare reform, and the bottom line for many centers is red.</p>
        <p>But outside of reimbursement cuts, hospitals have also had a hard time adjusting to the movement of much of health care into doctors' offices and outpatient centers. Many procedures, like chemotherapy for cancer patients or simple surgeries, are done in these settings now, and centers that serve long-term care patients, such as nursing homes, have moved into other areas of care once reserved for hospitals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly of Continuum said he believed his centers needed to focus more on outpatient care. ''I think we have to accelerate our look,'' he said. ''Let's face it, we have a health care system that for far more years than any of us has been around has focused on inpatient care. Everybody is learning how to shift that focus and deal with it without losing quality of care.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
