<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boston U. Founds a Company To Sift Landmark Heart Data</title>
    <meta content="Y17HEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Framingham Heart Study</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Framingham Genomic Medicine (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolata, Gina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lenfant, Claude (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DA1631F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boston U. Founds a Company To Sift Landmark Heart Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kolata, Gina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boston University establishes company to analyze valuable medical data from Framingham Heart Study, which is administered by university under federal contract; data will continue to be public and freely available to reseachers, but new company, Framingham Genomic Medicine, with $21 million from venture capitalists, will assemble information in ways useful for specific research; Dr Claude Lenfant of National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute supports use of 52 years of stored data, which includes DNA information (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what some call a taste of the future of genetic medicine, Boston University has created a company to analye a valuable cache of medical data from a federally financed study that has lasted 52 years. The university expects that companies will want to use the data to facilitate the search for new drugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what some call a taste of the future of genetic medicine, Boston University has created a company to analye a valuable cache of medical data from a federally financed study that has lasted 52 years. The university expects that companies will want to use the data to facilitate the search for new drugs.</p>
        <p>The study, the Framingham Heart Study, is administered by theuniversity under contract with the ational Heart, Lung and Blood Institute. Begunin 1948, it has followed thousands of residents of the twon of Framingham, Mass., gathering medical data about them and, more recently, storing DNA.</p>
        <p>The data have always been public, and will continue to be freely available to researchers who request them, the university explained. And the study's participants, who are anonymous, will remain so.</p>
        <p>But the new company, Framingham Genomic Medicine, supported by $21 million from venture capitalists, will assemble the study's data in ways useful to companies or scientists. For example, researchers seeking clues to genes and environments that protect against heart disease will be able to sift through participants' medical histories and genetic data to home in on the information they want.</p>
        <p>Boston University expects to own about 20 percent of the company's stock, said David Lampe, a university spokesman. In addition to that 20 percent, Mr. Lampe said, the university will donate some stock to a trust that will be administered for the benefit of participants in the Framingham study, a way of compensating people who have cooperated in the effort for so many years without any payment.</p>
        <p>The details of the arrangement are still being worked out, with crucial features, like an ethics adviser to represent the research participants themselves, still under discussion. But the company and the university are confident that the remaining questions can be resolved. And others said the agreement was a natural consequence of medicine's increasing thirst for data that can link medical and genetic information.</p>
        <p>''This is the beginning of a new era,'' said Dr. Arthur Holden, chairman and chief executive of the SNP Consortium, a collaboration of 14 companies, mostly drug makers, that are creating a publicly available map of the human genome, concentrating on individual places on DNA where people differ. ''The demand for genetic databases is beginning to increase, and many of the leading university centers are beginning to think about how they can commercialize their samples and data sets.''</p>
        <p>The new initiative by Boston University could be a boon to medical science, said Dr. Claude Lenfant, director of the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute. There is no study like the one in Framingham, with more than 12,000 participants who have faithfully come in over the years for regular medical exams and have willingly provided all the information that investigators request. The problem has been taking that vast and complex set of data and extracting information from it.</p>
        <p>''We have 50 years of data that are sitting in a basement,'' Dr. Lenfant said. ''If somebody wants to do this, more power to them. I think it's terrific to have the data used. I'm all for it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lenfant emphasied that the heart institute would insist that the Framingham data continue to be freely available apart from the new company, that the confidentially of the study participants be maintained and that the Boston University investigators who administer the Framingham study have no financial ties to the new company. Dr. Fred Ledley, chief executive officer of Framingham Genomic Medicine, said he had already taken care of Dr. Lenfant's concerns.</p>
        <p>The company's work will be data analysis, a task that will require an investment of $20 million to $40 million, Dr. Ledley said.</p>
        <p>The Framingham study began before computers were invented, and its records have been kept in 160 different databases. Laboratory tests, graphs and images must be put into computers and analyzed. ''We have half a million X-rays and EKG's,'' Dr. Ledley said.</p>
        <p>Then there is the genetic information. Since the 1980's, the study participants have given permission for genetic studies, providing blood samples that have allowed researchers to extract the DNA and store it. Dr. Ledley said he expected to look at 50,000 different genetic landmarks on the participants' DNA.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the company, seeking to protect the participants, is proposing the creation of an ethics panel to advise them, Dr. Ledley said. The company has asked Dr. Arthur Caplan, bioethicist at the University of Pennsylvania, to head it.</p>
        <p>''We didn't sign anything; we're not on board yet,'' Dr. Caplan said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
