<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mystified as Ever, Knoblauch Goes Back to Work</title>
    <meta content="17KNOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DD1731F934A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mystified as Ever, Knoblauch Goes Back to Work</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees second baseman Chuck Knoblauch returns to team following dismal fielding performance against Chicago White Sox in which he committed three errors; he took several days off but says he still feels uncomfortable and acknowledges that he will seek some kind of treatment to address persistent problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch said the first thing he did after leaving Yankee Stadium on Thursday night was call his mother. He intimated that he had received some undisclosed treatment for his chronic throwing difficulties after the 1999 season and he claimed that he was not thinking about retiring from baseball.</p>
        <p>The second baseman who does not always throw straight was back at the Stadium, back in the Yankee lineup and back trying to cope with the unexplainable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch said the first thing he did after leaving Yankee Stadium on Thursday night was call his mother. He intimated that he had received some undisclosed treatment for his chronic throwing difficulties after the 1999 season and he claimed that he was not thinking about retiring from baseball.</p>
        <p>The second baseman who does not always throw straight was back at the Stadium, back in the Yankee lineup and back trying to cope with the unexplainable.</p>
        <p>A little anxious and a little tentative, Knoblauch talked about feeling as if he has scant control over the simple act of throwing a ball from second base to first base. It is something Knoblauch has done regularly since he was in Little League, but he has made unreliable throws for about two years, a problem that exploded when he committed three errors in a 12-3 loss to the Chicago White Sox on Thursday night. He wound up departing before the game was over.</p>
        <p>''I was wondering if I was in Central Park,'' Knoblauch said, ''not Yankee Stadium.''</p>
        <p>But Knoblauch, who publicly acknowledged for the first time that he would seek some type of treatment for his problem, knew he was definitely in Yankee Stadium last night. The fans gave him a standing ovation before he singled in the first inning, gave him a partial standing ovation when he caught a pop-up and they draped supportive banners over the railings, like one that said, ''We love you Knobby and our team needs you.''</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, there were no grounders hit to Knoblauch in the eight innings that he played in a 3-1 loss to the White Sox, so he did not need to make any throws.</p>
        <p>In the ninth, Clay Bellinger replaced Knoblauch, who injured his left ankle on a slide, and handled one grounder flawlessly, causing some apparently inattentive fans to howl because they thought it was Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>It was one game, one step, but Knoblauch still felt something was missing. He said he still felt as uncomfortable as he had Thursday.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is different,'' said Knoblauch, who had two of the six Yankee hits in the game but was disappointed that he did not have a chance to make a throw. ''Nothing has changed. It's not gone away.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, after his three wild throws, Knoblauch was part of a haunting scene, standing alone as three other infielders gathered on the mound for a pitching change by Manager Joe Torre. ''I think he only proved that he was human,'' the manager said afterward.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch ended some of the suspense about his future yesterday by showing up for work with his teammate Jason Grimsley at 2:30 p.m. About 50 fans cheered Knoblauch when he sauntered from the parking lot into the Stadium and they scolded a television camera operator who was filming the second baseman. Knoblauch seemed oblivious to the attention.</p>
        <p>After a security guard escorted Knoblauch to the clubhouse, the Yankees kept the doors closed to reporters for an extra 20 minutes so that Knoblauch could meet with Torre. Torre asked Knoblauch what he wanted to do and told him, ''You're my second baseman.''</p>
        <p>Once Knoblauch had spoken to Torre, he invited reporters to his locker. Knoblauch said he had received so many calls from teammates that he called it a ''suicide watch,'' but he emphasized that he would not have ''done anything crazy'' because of his errant throws.</p>
        <p>''I woke up today and felt all right,'' Knoblauch said. ''I looked outside and the sun was shining.''</p>
        <p>As recently as last October, Alan Hendricks, Knoblauch's agent, said that he did not want to talk about Knoblauch's problems and he did not want his client to discuss them either. But Knoblauch acknowledged that he would now seek treatment, although he refused to specify what kind. He previously mentioned a sports psychologist or a hypnotist as options, and he hinted that he had tried to combat the problem before spring training.</p>
        <p>''You've got to remember you guys don't know exactly what I did last winter,'' he said. ''I know there's speculation that I didn't do anything.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Brian Cashman said Knoblauch's potential treatment would not be divulged. When Cashman was asked if it behooved the Yankees, who have millions of dollars invested in Knoblauch, to nudge him to seek treatment, he said,  ''I think it's a good idea that we support him as best as we can.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch was self-deprecating, loose and private. He would not say why he asked to speak to Torre after making his third error on Thursday, even though the answer was obvious. Torre said Knoblauch, his eyes filled with frustration, had told him: ''I don't know what to do. I'm tired of hurting the team.''</p>
        <p>That is when Torre and Knoblauch agreed that he should return to his apartment and avoid reporters.</p>
        <p>''You're stuck for anything to say,'' Torre said. ''You just want to hug him.''</p>
        <p>Strangely, Knoblauch said the wild throw that he made in Chicago on May 24 was actually worse than Thursday's three bad throws because he threw the ball harder this time. Knoblauch spoke about retirement three weeks ago and about reaching a ''breaking point,'' but he did not consider quitting yesterday. He made 26 errors last year, 14 on throws, and has 12 this year, 8 on throws.</p>
        <p>''You have the desire,'' Knoblauch said about wanting to play. ''This is what you do.''</p>
        <p>Still, three hours before last night's game, Knoblauch was not sure if playing was the best thing for him. Knoblauch, who bypassed infield practice, sifted through words like ''scared'' and ''apprehensive'' to vainly try to express how he feels. He insisted his personal life was ''great'' and refused to blame a complicated divorce or his father's Alzheimer's disease for his woes.</p>
        <p>''You don't fix something like this,'' Torre said. ''This is something you have to endure more than you fix.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch, who had deep bags under his eyes and who had not shaved in a few days, was standing near Roger Clemens's locker after completing interviews. He was relaxed as he talked about how so many people had called and how his mother, Linda, wished she could fly from Texas to New York and hug him.</p>
        <p>Then Knoblauch glanced into Clemens's locker and pointed to a miniature stone football on the shelf. Knoblauch told a reporter that Clemens had given him one of the footballs with a saying from Vince Lombardi inscribed across it: ''The harder you work, the harder it is to surrender.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
