<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Levi's new campaign, hopeful hand-wringing.</title>
    <meta content="Y27ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jeans (Apparel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Levi Strauss &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tbwa/chiat/day</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DE1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Levi's new campaign, hopeful hand-wringing.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Levi Strauss &amp; Co is beginning crucial advertising campaign to attract consumers 18 to 24, while not alienating older customers; multimillion-dollar campaign was developed by TBWA/Chiat/Day; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT seems appropriate that an ambitious new campaign for Levi's jeans carries the theme ''Make them your own'' because the ads are most likely a make-or-break effort for the maker of the campaign, if not also for the maker of the jeans.</p>
        <p>The multimillion-dollar campaign, which begins this week, is the most recent in a series of multimedia blitzes for the jeans maker, Levi Strauss &amp; Company, by the San Francisco office of TBWA/Chiat/ Day, the agency that was rocked last week by the loss of its large Taco Bell creative assignment. The initial efforts can be seen in a 52-page supplement to the August issue of Vogue magazine and on the Web site www.levi.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT seems appropriate that an ambitious new campaign for Levi's jeans carries the theme ''Make them your own'' because the ads are most likely a make-or-break effort for the maker of the campaign, if not also for the maker of the jeans.</p>
        <p>The multimillion-dollar campaign, which begins this week, is the most recent in a series of multimedia blitzes for the jeans maker, Levi Strauss &amp; Company, by the San Francisco office of TBWA/Chiat/ Day, the agency that was rocked last week by the loss of its large Taco Bell creative assignment. The initial efforts can be seen in a 52-page supplement to the August issue of Vogue magazine and on the Web site www.levi.com.</p>
        <p>The previous campaigns for Levi's jeans from TBWA/Chiat/Day have generally been dismissed as lacking in appeal to consumers 18 to 24, the core audience being courted so desperately by Levi Strauss to return as customers. The weakness of the campaigns to date -- does anyone remember ''Opt. For the original,'' ''Calvin wore them'' or ''Our models can beat up your models''? -- has been exacerbated by the failure of Levi Strauss to produce apparel in styles popular with younger shoppers. For example, so-called hard jeans languished unsold on store shelves.</p>
        <p>The result has been a serious slump in Levi Strauss sales, down 6.4 percent in the quarter ended on May 28 compared with the period a year earlier. In 1999, sales tumbled to $5.1 billion, down 28.2 percent from a peak of $7.1 billion as recently as 1996.</p>
        <p>''We hope the caliber of the work will be a heck of a lot higher than where it has been,'' said Chuck McBride, executive creative director at TWBA/Chiat/Day San Francisco, part of the TBWA Worldwide unit of the Omnicom Group. He was interviewed on Tuesday by telephone from London, where he was working on additional commercials for the campaign.</p>
        <p>According to executives close to the relationship between Levi Strauss and the agency, TBWA/ Chiat/Day San Francisco was on the verge of being dismissed until Mr. McBride, using the agency's own money, produced on his own a batch of commercials to demonstrate how the ''Make them your own'' theme would work.</p>
        <p>Mr. McBride demurred at a suggestion that his unconventional tactic had saved the account for TBWA/ Chiat/Day. He offered two words with a laugh, ''The beginning.''</p>
        <p>''What this brand needed was to hold still and do some great work that would be consistent over time, so kids could sit down and say: 'Oh, so that's what it means to wear Levi's jeans,' '' Mr. McBride said, ''which I don't think a lot of young people necessarily know.''</p>
        <p>''This proposition has really lit a fire under the organization,'' he added, referring to the new theme.</p>
        <p>That assessment was echoed by Sean Dee, brand marketing director for Levi's at Levi Strauss in San Francisco, who joined Mr. McBride for the interview.</p>
        <p>''We've now got our chance to leverage the brand over time,'' Mr. Dee said. ''It's not about the company, but the people who wear the pants.''</p>
        <p>''And it's not about everybody being the same,'' he added, taking a veiled dig at recent campaigns carrying the theme ''Everybody in . . .'' from a major competitor, Gap Inc.</p>
        <p>''Kids want to be associated with brands that let them be themselves,'' Mr. Dee said, ''so they can say 'I can embrace them and make them my own.' ''</p>
        <p>''The biggest difference is that we actually can now back up any brand claims with the right products,'' he added. ''If you don't hit that, it's just advertising.''</p>
        <p>The initial television commercial in the campaign, titled ''Dressing Room,'' was shot on videotape, for a more realistic look, by Spike Jonze, the hot young director of music videos and movies. The spot resembles a voyeur's dream come to life: Attractive young male and female models try on Levi's in front of a dressing room mirror.</p>
        <p>''Our big challenge is to have things resonate with young people but not alienate the 25-plus crowd,'' the traditional buyers of Levi's jeans, Mr. Dee said. Tests showed that ''the work we've done with Spike is unbelievably appealing to older consumers,'' he added, as well as their younger counterparts. At least two other commercials are planned, one for Levi's corduroys and the other for Levi's 569 jeans.</p>
        <p>Mr. McBride's unusual save-the-account initiative also included the production of offbeat commercials for a new product, known as Levi's Engineered Jeans. The four spots manipulate still photographs to produce an effect similar to strobe lights, borrowing a technique used in performances by the Icelandic musicians known as GusGus.</p>
        <p>Can the venerable Levi's brand be reinvigorated by the campaign? Mr. Dee was sanguine.</p>
        <p>''It's not an easy job,'' he said, ''but, yes, we think we can do this.''</p>
        <p>''No, kids don't like Levi's,'' he added. ''They were more like 'Levi's are pretty cool but haven't done much for me lately.' This is a great opportunity for us.''</p>
        <p>If not, he and Mr. McBride might join the Taco Bell Chihuahua in wearing signs that proclaim ''Will Work for Food.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
