<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Personal Tailor For Denimed Masses</title>
    <meta content="27SHOP$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jeans (Apparel)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interactive Custom Clothes Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D71E3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Personal Tailor For Denimed Masses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Online Shopper column on her happy experience buying a pair of jeans through Interactive Custom Clothes Co, whose Web site allows shopper to have jeans cut to his or her exact measurements and to specify details like button color, fabric weight and number of pockets; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I PANICKED one day recently because I could not find my lucky jeans.</p>
        <p>As I pawed through a pile of 10 other ill-fitting pairs -- the ones with the button fly that is so hard to button, the ones that shrank in the wash, the ones with the puckered waistband, the ones that sag after a couple of hours of wear -- I realized that the last time I felt so desperate was after I discovered that my engagement ring had fallen out of my pocket while I was gardening.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I PANICKED one day recently because I could not find my lucky jeans.</p>
        <p>As I pawed through a pile of 10 other ill-fitting pairs -- the ones with the button fly that is so hard to button, the ones that shrank in the wash, the ones with the puckered waistband, the ones that sag after a couple of hours of wear -- I realized that the last time I felt so desperate was after I discovered that my engagement ring had fallen out of my pocket while I was gardening.</p>
        <p>I hunted for two hours with a flashlight before I found the ring in a patch of ivy. But finding a pair of jeans that fits right is a slightly more difficult undertaking. So when I heard about the Interactive Custom Clothes Company, or IC3D, an online retailer that offers customers the opportunity to build a pair of jeans perfectly sized to fit their measurements for less than $100, I immediately went to the IC3D site to investigate.</p>
        <p>The home page welcomed me with the greeting: ''It's your universe, wear whatever you want totally custom.'' This statement conjured up a wondrous world that off-the-rack shoppers like me have rarely glimpsed: a place where sleeves don't hang down over hands, waistbands do not slide hipward and sleeveless shirts do not gape open under the arms.</p>
        <p>The possibility of owning such a wardrobe has become increasingly rare since the advent of the mass manufacture of clothing. Because that trend became firmly entrenched after World War I, when all those factories that had been producing soldiers' uniforms turned in peacetime to the fabrication of civilian wear, I never thought I could do much to fight it. Instead, I just counted myself fortunate not to have been alive to wear the formless, waistless fashions of the 1920's.</p>
        <p>But a return to tailor-made clothing makes sense in an era when manufacturers of items as diverse as computers and automobiles are building customized products to satisfy customers' idiosyncratic desires for big hard drives and metallic paint finishes. ''Apparel in particular is really ripe for mass customization because everybody's body is unique and we have been sacrificing when we buy off the rack,'' said Joseph Pine, the author of ''Mass Customization: The New Frontier in Business Competition'' (Harvard Business School Press, 1992).</p>
        <p>As a result, a growing number of online retailers -- Moda1to1.com, E-madeinitaly.com, Americanfit.com -- are selling tailor-made clothing for prices that range from $100 for a dress to $780 for a men's suit. Shoppers can point and click to choose fabric, color and cut, then type in their measurements.</p>
        <p>Beyond merely creating jeans that are the right size, IC3D offers customers the option of specifying every detail -- from button color to fabric weight to the number of pockets to how wide the ankle opening should be (the company's software can generate a pattern accurate to one-tenth of an inch). This level of specification does not come cheap: jeans cost from $70 to $95 (including shipping) depending on the choice of fabric.</p>
        <p>Although this excited me at first, I soon realized that it was going to be no faster than trying on 20 pairs of ill-fitting jeans under the pitiless glare of fitting room lights. In fact, when I clicked on my fabric choice, denim, 30 options appeared -- and I didn't know what most of them were.</p>
        <p>Oh, I could pick between stonewashed or ''raw,'' all right, but did I want fabric that was ''ring-spun, left hand twirl,'' or did I want ''a right-hand twirl?''</p>
        <p>It felt kind of like the way they built ''The Six Million Dollar Man'' on television in the 1970's after the opening credits intoned: ''We have the technology. We have the capability to make the world's first bionic man.'' Only in this case, the thread color would be crucial to the outcome. What if I made a mistake?</p>
        <p>That is the biggest risk, of course,  when shoppers try to design their own clothes. ''Be careful, or else you might not like what you get,'' said Robert Leeds, a lecturer in the marketing department at the University of Southern Florida who worked for years in the apparel industry. ''The fabric might feel scratchy. Maybe you won't like the buttons. And don't forget there are fashions in everything. Even in black socks, the number of ribs changes from season to season. Are these jeans going to be fashionable?''</p>
        <p>Skittish, I phoned Peter del Rio, the founder of Ic3d.com, who reassured me. ''We are guaranteeing that they will fit right, and if they don't, we will determine why and fix them,'' he said, adding that in the four years the company has been selling online, 95 percent of customers are ''totally happy.''</p>
        <p>About half of the company's first-time customers avoid the headache-provoking choices by opting for the site's Copy Cat feature, he said, which prompts you to mail in your favorite pair of jeans. The company creates a copy for you, then mails them back. Or he suggested using the Denim Wizard feature to get started. After asking five ''lifestyle'' questions like ''Are you more concerned about fabric quality or low price?'' and ''What kind of climate are you going to wear your jeans in?'' the wizard recommends a denim for you.</p>
        <p>That's why I went with ''Riviera,'' described as a ''soft perfect denim with no unique characteristics.'' Then I went back to my closet, where I determined that most of my jeans were sewn with orange thread and had copper buttons and five pockets. So I chose those features, as well. Then I measured myself in 11 places, including some (like ''front rise'') that I had never heard of before. Mr. del Rio said not to worry too much; within an inch of accuracy, the measurements should produce a pair of well-fitting jeans, he said.</p>
        <p>The total came to $85. When the jeans arrived, less than a week after I placed the order, I followed the company's instructions and washed and dried them before trying them on. The fit was perfect. They are in fact the best-fitting jeans I've ever had. I have a new lucky pair.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
