<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yielding to Pressure, Japan Delays Sale of Nippon Credit</title>
    <meta content="Y27JAP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nippon Credit Bank Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Softbank Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E5DD1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yielding to Pressure, Japan Delays Sale of Nippon Credit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japanese regulators postpone by one month sale of nationalized Nippon Credit Bank to group of investors led by Softbank Corp; some of Japan's most powerful politicians are applying pressure on Financial Reconstruction Commission to renegotiate contract, objecting to provision that would alllow new owners of bank to transfer back to government any loans that lose more than 20 percent of their value for three years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japanese regulators today postponed by one month the sale of the nationalized Nippon Credit Bank to a group of investors led by the Softbank Corporation, one of the world's largest Internet investment companies.</p>
        <p>The delay came after some of Japan's most powerful politicians applied intense pressure to the Financial Reconstruction Commission, the agency responsible for overseeing the rehabilitation and overhaul of Japan's debt-ridden financial system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japanese regulators today postponed by one month the sale of the nationalized Nippon Credit Bank to a group of investors led by the Softbank Corporation, one of the world's largest Internet investment companies.</p>
        <p>The delay came after some of Japan's most powerful politicians applied intense pressure to the Financial Reconstruction Commission, the agency responsible for overseeing the rehabilitation and overhaul of Japan's debt-ridden financial system.</p>
        <p>Hiromu Nonaka, the secretary general of the ruling Liberal Democratic Party and perhaps the most influential political figure in Japan, is leading the push to force the agency to renegotiate the contract to sell Nippon Credit, one of two large banks the government nationalized at the height of Japan's financial crisis two years ago.</p>
        <p>The politicians object to a provision in the contract that would allow the new owners of the bank to transfer back to the government any loans that lose more than 20 percent of their value for three years. That provision was also part of the contract governing the sale of the Long-Term Credit Bank, now known as Shinsei Bank, to a group of investors led by Ripplewood Holdings L.L.C., a Wall Street investment company. That deal kicked off a debate here about how public money is used. Shinsei used the provision to shift to the government 200 billion yen, or more than $1.8 billion at current exchange rates, of loans it made to the Sogo Company, a failing department store operator. That forced the government to make a choice between spending public money to rescue Sogo or giving up on the company, which has 9,900 employees.</p>
        <p>Since Shinsei and Nippon Credit are both creditors of a number of visibly struggling companies, like the convenience store operator Daiei Inc. and the building contractors Hazama Corporation and Kumagai Gumi, the government will probably face the same tough choice repeatedly -- unless politicians can somehow ban the granting of guarantees against further deterioration in loan values. Already, the government is squirming to avoid making a decision on whether to waive debts owed to the two banks by Hazama, which is particularly troublesome because construction companies are among the Liberal Democrats' biggest political supporters.</p>
        <p>''This special clause was a complete mistake,'' said Yoshimi Watanabe, a member of Parliament who sits on the finance committee in the lower house.</p>
        <p>Kimitaka Kuze, the chairman of the Financial Reconstruction Commission, said today that the agency would not change the terms of the sale to Softbank and its partners, including the Orix Corporation and the Tokio Marine and Fire Insurance Company.</p>
        <p>He said the commission merely wanted to explain its reasons for including the provision to the public. Bankers from Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, which managed the sale of Long-Term Credit Bank, and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, which is handling the sale of Nippon Credit for the government, have said repeatedly that without such guarantees, there would be no sales.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuze acknowledged that the delay in the sale, which was to have been completed next Tuesday, came at the request of politicians, raising further questions about the independence of Japan's financial watchdog. ''It is true that I talked to Shizuka Kamei the day before yesterday,'' Mr. Kuze said, referring to the ruling party's policy chief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kamei has joined Mr. Nonaka in pushing to change the laws governing financial reform and the sale of bankrupt financial institutions. In a television talk show on Sunday, Mr. Nonaka questioned the way the commission has been guaranteeing buyers of failed banks against further deterioration in loans. ''It's a big problem in the Financial Reconstruction Law that measures for coping with subsequent losses were not stipulated,'' he said, adding that the ruling party would seek to put such clearly defined measures into law during the special session of Parliament that will begin on Friday.</p>
        <p>Whether any change in the law could be applied retroactively to the sale of Nippon Credit remains to be seen. The Softbank group agreed to a delay in the sale in hopes that some of the controversy would die down, a representative from one investor said today.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Orix, however, made it clear that the investors would not accept changes to the agreement. ''That provision is a very important part of the contract,'' he said. ''It's difficult to say what would happen if the government tries to remove that from the agreement, but if that were to happen, there is a strong possibility that we would pull out.'' The commission's five-member policy board met today and agreed that it must honor the original agreement.</p>
        <p>But politicians have already demonstrated a surprising ability to force the commission to change course, despite the implications for its independence. Two weeks ago, political pressure pushed the commission to abandon overnight its decision to participate in a plan with other banks to forgive some of the $17 billion of debt owed by the Sogo Company after Mr. Nonaka and others complained about the use of public money for such a purpose.</p>
        <p>That about-face pushed Sogo into bankruptcy, setting off waves of concern about the stability of the Japanese financial system and the fragility of the economic recovery. Now politicians are seeking ways to protect themselves from a series of similar debacles, which could occur any time, given the precarious finances of many of Japan's retail, construction and real estate companies.</p>
        <p>''This argument of Mr. Nonaka's is one that has a lot of popular support,'' Mr. Watanabe said. ''I think the Financial Reconstruction Commission is in a lot of trouble."</p>
        <p>He said he had no concerns about how such a last-minute change to terms of a deal that were finalized on June 30 might affect the government's credibility. ''Already the credibility of and confidence in the Japanese government have been lost,'' he said.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
