<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Final Approval on Swiss Holocaust Claims</title>
    <meta content="Y27HOL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Korman, Edward R (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DE1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Final Approval on Swiss Holocaust Claims</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Edward R Korman gives final approval to $1.25 billion accord to settle suit by Holocaust survivors against Swiss banks that allegedly hoarded assets deposited in World War II (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge gave final approval yesterday to a $1.25 billion accord to settle claims of Holocaust survivors who had sued a group of Swiss banks that they said had hoarded assets deposited in World War II.</p>
        <p>The ruling by Judge Edward R. Korman in Federal District Court in Brooklyn takes hundreds of thousands of survivors and their family members one step closer to collecting the money from the banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge gave final approval yesterday to a $1.25 billion accord to settle claims of Holocaust survivors who had sued a group of Swiss banks that they said had hoarded assets deposited in World War II.</p>
        <p>The ruling by Judge Edward R. Korman in Federal District Court in Brooklyn takes hundreds of thousands of survivors and their family members one step closer to collecting the money from the banks.</p>
        <p>The ruling requires that a draft of a distribution plan be worked out in 30 days. The money could begin to be distributed to the plaintiffs and their heirs by Dec. 31.</p>
        <p>In the prologue to his ruling, Judge Korman used the words of Ernest Lobet, a Holocaust survivor who testified in a hearing related to the case, to summarize the balance that he thought the agreement struck between an idealized version of equity and real-life concerns.</p>
        <p>''I do not say it is fair,'' the judge quoted Mr. Lobet as having said, ''because fairness is a relative term. No amount of money can possibly be fair under those circumstances. But I'm quite sure it is the very best that could be done by the groups that negotiated for the settlement.''</p>
        <p>The case began about three years ago, when a series of class-action suits were filed in Brooklyn by Jews who had deposited money in Swiss banks as the Nazis took power in Germany.</p>
        <p>The suits said Swiss institutions, including the two largest Swiss banks, UBS and Credit Suisse, had blocked the survivors' efforts to reclaim money that was directly deposited in the banks or that the Nazis had looted and stored in the banks.</p>
        <p>A preliminary agreement was reached in August 1998. Since then, Judge Korman worked with the survivors and banks' lawyers to hammer out the details.</p>
        <p>The ruling was greeted by both sides as fair and expedient.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a wise and thoughtful opinion that crosses a very important threshold,'' the survivors' chief lawyer, Burton Neuborne, said. ''Until this settlement was approved, we were locked. This unlocks the process, and we can start giving the money out.''</p>
        <p>Roger M. Witten, a lawyer in Washington who represents the banks, said: ''We are very pleased that the judge put his stamp of approval on the fundamental fairness of the settlement. It is an important step in getting the money distributed to members of the class.''</p>
        <p>The Swiss government also welcomed the decision, saying it ''provides for complete legal and material resolution of World War II-related issues for the Swiss economy as well as Swiss public entities,'' Reuters reported.</p>
        <p>But a handful of potential sticking points remains. One possible pitfall concerns several private Swiss banks and banks run by the cantonal, or state, governments, that have been reluctant to publish the names of hundreds of accountholders or allow their records to be placed in a database of all Swiss accounts opened during the war. In his order, Judge Korman said if those banks refused to open their records, they would not be protected against future lawsuits.</p>
        <p>He seized on the intransigence of those banks to make a larger point about the historical reluctance of the Swiss banking system to relax its secrecy laws in connection with accounts from the Holocaust era. He said in his order that there was no evidence that the Swiss had destroyed any records of the victims' accounts, but added that if the Swiss authorities had been more forthcoming decades ago, recent disputes might have been avoided.</p>
        <p>''A historic opportunity was lost,'' he wrote, quoting Paul A. Volcker, a former chairman of the Federal Reserve who led an independent panel that investigated the problem.</p>
        <p>In December, the panel issued a report that said 54,000 Swiss accounts had probable or possible links to Holocaust victims. As of May, 550,000 people had returned questionnaires in an effort to be included in the class-action settlement.</p>
        <p>The court now turns to the task of distributing the money. A special master appointed by Judge Korman, Judah Gribetz, is generally expected to file a draft distribution plan with the court by Sept. 1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
