<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Big Accounting Firms Assail S.E.C.'s Proposed Restrictions</title>
    <meta content="Y27AUDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kpmg Llc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andersen, Arthur, &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deloitte &amp; Touche</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levitt, Arthur Jr (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DC1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Big Accounting Firms Assail S.E.C.'s Proposed Restrictions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>KPMG, Arthur Andersen and Deloitte &amp; Touche strongly criticize proposal by Securities and Exchange Commission to restrict types of consulting work that firms can provide for companies whose financial statements they audit; argue that there are no proven cases in which an audit has been compromised because an auditing firm had other relationships with a company; accounting firms are already barred from providing many consulting services to auditing clients, and SEC is proposing two extensions of those prohibitions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representatives of three major accounting firms strongly criticized a proposal today to restrict the types of consulting work that the firms can provide for the companies whose financial statements they audit.</p>
        <p>At a hearing here by the Securities and Exchange Commission, its first public hearing on an accounting issue in more than 20 years, representatives of KPMG, Arthur Andersen and Deloitte &amp; Touche argued that there were no proven cases in which an audit had been compromised because the auditing firm had other relationships with the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representatives of three major accounting firms strongly criticized a proposal today to restrict the types of consulting work that the firms can provide for the companies whose financial statements they audit.</p>
        <p>At a hearing here by the Securities and Exchange Commission, its first public hearing on an accounting issue in more than 20 years, representatives of KPMG, Arthur Andersen and Deloitte &amp; Touche argued that there were no proven cases in which an audit had been compromised because the auditing firm had other relationships with the company.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the S.E.C., Arthur Levitt, said he hoped a decision could be reached that would satisfy everyone involved. But he also said he was convinced that action was needed in part because of a perception that auditor independence had been limited by such relationships. ''We cannot dismiss perception as being a terribly important issue for the industry,'' Mr. Levitt said.</p>
        <p>While accounting firms are already barred from providing many consulting services to auditing clients, the S.E.C. is proposing two extensions of those prohibitions.</p>
        <p>One would forbid internal audits of companies -- those normally performed by company employees for the use of management -- when the same accounting firm is to conduct the outside audit, an independent examination in which the responsibility is to investors.</p>
        <p>Proponents argue that external auditors would be reluctant to criticize their colleagues' work. And the comptroller of the currency, John D. Hawke Jr., said bank regulators were worried about the practice and that 7 of the nation's 50 biggest banks had retained their outside auditors for such work.</p>
        <p>The other area that would be barred is information services consulting -- which has grown as consultants, many from auditing firms, design and install large management information services. If such systems provide incorrect information, critics say, the auditors whose firms designed the systems may be less vigilant in reviewing the reports.</p>
        <p>The two accounting firms that have indicated greater willingness to accept such rules, PricewaterhouseCoopers and Ernst &amp; Young, did not testify today. Both are divesting themselves of their consulting practices, and KPMG is in the process of doing the same.</p>
        <p>The proposed rules drew some support today. John Biggs, chairman of TIAA-CREF, the huge pension fund manager, called for ''adoption of one unalterable rule: independent public audit firms should not be the auditors of any company for which they simultaneously provide other services; it's that simple.''</p>
        <p>Auditors would not be prohibited from offering the disputed services to people other than their own auditing clients. But the auditing firms that oppose the proposed rules said they would be forced to sell their consultancy arms because they could not compete, for clients or for staff members, with consulting firms that could serve any company.</p>
        <p>Robert R. Garland, national managing partner of Deloitte &amp; Touche's auditing service, said: ''Given what is at stake, and the fact that there is no demonstrated problem, it would be irresponsible to take on the considerable risks surrounding the proposed rule. There is no evidence that broad scope of services has an adverse effect on audit quality. My own personal experience has caused me to conclude just the opposite.''</p>
        <p>J. Terry Strange, global managing partner for auditing at KPMG, said ''nonaudit services enhance audit effectiveness.'' And he maintained that the S.E.C. action was rushed, with only a 75-day comment period.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levitt clearly wants to complete action before a new president can replace him as chairman, and opponents want to delay a decision in the hope that a new chairman will reverse course.</p>
        <p>While firms opposed to the rules repeated that there was no evidence any audits had been compromised, some proponents insisted that such evidence would be rare as no auditor was likely to write a memo saying he had approved a bad audit because he feared losing revenue for his firm.</p>
        <p>Douglas R. Carmichael, an accounting professor at Baruch College, who served as research director for an investigation into the issue by a commission headed by Manuel Cohen, a former S.E.C. chairman, said there had been such cases. He cited a 1978 audit of the Westec Corporation, which the Cohen panel concluded had been compromised because of consulting services. And he said a 1998 civil suit that raised suspicion of such conflicts had been settled by the accounting firm involved,  with the evidence sealed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
