<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using an Opponent's Bid To Beat the Odds on a Slam</title>
    <meta content="27CARD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DB1E3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using an Opponent's Bid To Beat the Odds on a Slam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on use of opponent's bid to beat odds on slam; diagramed deal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many contracts at the bridge table are not as good as they appear. In the diagramed deal, the North-South hands are a good bet for six no-trump. That will succeed if the spades divide evenly or if the heart finesse wins, giving the contract a 68 percent chance.</p>
        <p>But if West has opened two hearts the heart finesse is virtually certain to lose and the prospect of a favorable spade split diminishes. The chances are now, it would seem, down to about 20 percent. But a clever declarer can improve that considerably by using the information gained from the opening bid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many contracts at the bridge table are not as good as they appear. In the diagramed deal, the North-South hands are a good bet for six no-trump. That will succeed if the spades divide evenly or if the heart finesse wins, giving the contract a 68 percent chance.</p>
        <p>But if West has opened two hearts the heart finesse is virtually certain to lose and the prospect of a favorable spade split diminishes. The chances are now, it would seem, down to about 20 percent. But a clever declarer can improve that considerably by using the information gained from the opening bid.</p>
        <p>Sitting South in a recent rubber bridge game was Florine Atkins Garber, whose husband, Keith Garber, is one of the managers of the newly expanded FrankLin Club (340 Dogwood Avenue in Franklin Square on Long Island).</p>
        <p>She and her partner started cautiously but nevertheless arrived in six no-trump. North's natural jump to five no-trump was overenthusiastic, but four no-trump would have had the same result since South had maximum values for her two-spade bid.</p>
        <p>West led the diamond queen against six no-trump, and South could count 11 sure tricks. The heart finesse was sure to fail, so the main chance appeared to be an even spade split. South immediately saw a second possibility, and prepared for it by taking the diamond king followed by the ace.</p>
        <p>She then tested spades, and was not alarmed when West discarded hearts on the second and third rounds. This improved the chance that her back-up plan would succeed. She ran four club winners and reached this ending:</p>
        <p>[Diagram]</p>
        <p>South cashed dummy's last club, throwing the spade eight. If West had bared the heart king South would have known what to do. Instead, sensing doom, West gave up the diamond jack.</p>
        <p>South was confident that West had begun with six hearts and thus four diamonds. She led the diamond two, endplaying West, and scored two heart tricks at the finish to make her slam.</p>
        <p>Was six no-trump the only makeable slam? Not quite. It is hard to imagine a contract of six clubs being reached from the South side, but that could also have succeeded. If East is able to lead a heart, all slams fail.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
