<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Festival of Animation, Animatedly</title>
    <meta content="27VIDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Onimusha (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3D61E3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Festival of Animation, Animatedly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Annual computer animation festival is held in New Orleans; Onimusha, opening movie for video game to be used in Sony Play Station 2, wins top award;' photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An army of samurai come roaring on horseback down a medieval hillside in a driving rain, kicking up mud and water. Several of them dismount, swords and spears spinning, and break into a brutal ballet of combat and impalings. One of them takes an arrow through the throat, an image lifted directly from Akira Kurosawa's ''Throne of Blood'' and given a fresh twist in this bleak, computer-generated landscape.</p>
        <p>''Onimusha,'' the opening movie for a video game to be used in the soon-to-be-released Sony Play Station 2, won best-of-show honors at the computer animation festival at this year's Siggraph convention in the humid funk of a Louisiana July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An army of samurai come roaring on horseback down a medieval hillside in a driving rain, kicking up mud and water. Several of them dismount, swords and spears spinning, and break into a brutal ballet of combat and impalings. One of them takes an arrow through the throat, an image lifted directly from Akira Kurosawa's ''Throne of Blood'' and given a fresh twist in this bleak, computer-generated landscape.</p>
        <p>''Onimusha,'' the opening movie for a video game to be used in the soon-to-be-released Sony Play Station 2, won best-of-show honors at the computer animation festival at this year's Siggraph convention in the humid funk of a Louisiana July.</p>
        <p>Each year, Siggraph brings together the leading artists, companies, researchers, animators and visionaries from the worlds of computer animation, virtual reality and interactive technology -- and each year, one of the highlights is a computer animation festival featuring the best of the submissions that come in from all over the world.</p>
        <p>More than 650 entries were received this year; 135 were chosen to be part of the festival. They were shown in four screening rooms at the New Orleans convention center, just upstairs from the vast cacophonous trade show floor where companies like Adobe, Nvidia, NewTek, SGI and Discreet were showing off their latest high-tech gizmos.</p>
        <p>A few blocks away, at the ornate, refurbished Saenger Theater, a two-hour ''Electronic Festival'' of the year's short-film highlights was shown each night.</p>
        <p>The event is seen in the world of computer graphics as a kind of annual assessment of the state of the art in computer-generated special effects and computer animation -- both of which are increasingly important in Hollywood, in video games and on the World Wide Web.</p>
        <p>It was at such festivals over the last two decades that many breakthroughs in computer animation were first given a public viewing, as artists in the highly competitive field showed off for one another with the geek equivalent of a cocky swagger.</p>
        <p>''The significant trend this year was the advance of game animation with a more cinematic feel,'' said Joe Takai, an animator for Industrial Light and Magic who served as chairman of this year's festival committee. ''Game developers are paying more attention to story development and styles in the way that feature films have done for years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Takai said the committee was particularly impressed with the number of foreign entries -- about 48 percent of those submitted -- as well as the unusual number of high-quality entries from students, an indication of how a new generation of cheaper animation software is allowing even beginners to produce pieces good enough to compete with the the offerings of the biggest animation companies.</p>
        <p>''Stationen,'' from a German animator named Christian Sawade-Meyer, was just such a piece, and it won the festival's jury award, its second prize. In the short film, a man drags a box filled with withering plants across an apocalyptic wasteland, occasionally pausing to try to plant some in the arid soil only to watch them wither and die. Eventually, he discovers a glistening spring, but it is too late: the plants are dead.</p>
        <p>The top award to ''Onimusha'' also highlights the high number of festival selections from the video gaming world. These have been made possible by advances in photo-real animation, in motion-capture techniques (which allow actors whose bodies are covered with computer sensors to act out complex movements that can later be transferred to animated characters) and by a new generation of video game consoles like Sony's Play Station 2 and Microsoft's X-Machine, on which the games will eventually be played.</p>
        <p>Hollywood was here, too, of course. Industrial Light and Magic had a short film about the computer-generated water effects it created for ''The Perfect Storm.'' Digital Domain showed the credit sequence from ''The Fight Club,'' which begins inside a person's head and follows a thought as it rushes through his brain and out his eyeball. Sony Pictures' Digital Human Project showed some bits of the intricate computer-generated skeleton and muscle work that made possible its  forthcoming invisible-man thriller, ''The Hollow Man.''</p>
        <p>Academic researchers, at the heart of Siggraph from the beginning, contributed pieces that highlighted advances in the use of virtual light and three-dimensional graphics. In ''The Light of Mies van der Rohe,'' Henrik Wann Jensen of Stanford University showed the interplay of natural light over an entire day as it splashes across a computer-generated architectural model. In ''The Last Drawing of Canaletto,'' Cameron McNall of the University of California at Los Angeles brings to three-dimensional life a final sketch by the artist and takes the audience on a virtual ride through the painting, seeing the figures from various angles inside the frame.</p>
        <p>Young and relatively inexperienced animators also made an impressive showing. In the film that probably got the festival's biggest laughs, Robert Rioux did a version of a light-saber duel between Darth Vader and Luke Skywalker from ''Star Wars'' in which they are made of Lego blocks and in which Vader ends up berating his son for being a slacker and needing a haircut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
