<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Biography as Intense as Its Subject</title>
    <meta content="27MASL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liberace (Wladziu Valentino Liberace) (1919-87)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pyron, Darden Asbury</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Liberace: An American Boy (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D81E3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Biography as Intense as Its Subject</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews Liberace: An American Boy by Darden Asbury Pyron; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIBERACE  An American Boy  By Darden Asbury Pyron  Illustrated. 494 pages. The University of Chicago Press. $27.50.</p>
        <p>In a discussion of the import of ''I'll Be Seeing You'' as Liberace's signature song, the star's inexhaustible biographer, Darden Asbury Pyron, manages to invoke Dante's Beatrice, ancient Jewish elders, the Greek goddess Artemis and ''The Sound and the Fury.'' All this is by way of contemplating the meaning of ''seeing,'' and it blessedly is not accompanied by any great claims for Liberace's theoretical wisdom on the point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIBERACE  An American Boy  By Darden Asbury Pyron  Illustrated. 494 pages. The University of Chicago Press. $27.50.</p>
        <p>In a discussion of the import of ''I'll Be Seeing You'' as Liberace's signature song, the star's inexhaustible biographer, Darden Asbury Pyron, manages to invoke Dante's Beatrice, ancient Jewish elders, the Greek goddess Artemis and ''The Sound and the Fury.'' All this is by way of contemplating the meaning of ''seeing,'' and it blessedly is not accompanied by any great claims for Liberace's theoretical wisdom on the point.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pyron, who previously trained his hyperanalytical eye on Margaret Mitchell (in the well-received ''Southern Daughter'') and ''Gone With the Wind,'' is daffily intent on making a scholarly study of the performer famed for introducing rhinestone-studded hot pants to Las Vegas. And at the very least, he winds up making his own biographical impulse understood. There may be no urgent need to plumb ''the inner vision adumbrated in the lyrics of 'I'll Be Seeing You,' '' but Mr. Pyron makes a reasonable connection between Liberace's carefully created persona as ''Mr. Showmanship'' and the cultural climate in which he sustained his gaudy, big-hearted brand of celebrity for 50 years. It was a career fittingly immortalized in ''Bartlett's Familiar Quotations,'' which cites Liberace for coining the phrase ''laughed all the way to the bank.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Pyron's stupefyingly serious ''Liberace'' carries too much baggage (including 54 pages of chatty footnotes on top of a dense 427-page text) to resemble ordinary show-business hagiography, it does reveal that Walter Liberace first wowed listeners as a 3-year-old playing ''Yes, We Have No Bananas'' on the family upright piano in his Wisconsin home. ''The first manifestation of his genius is legendary,'' notes Mr. Pyron, who claims to have approached Liberace without any great affection but obviously warmed to his subject, just as readers may.</p>
        <p>As a boy who loved to entertain, to make silk flowers and to carve animals out of soap, one who spoke ''in a voice you don't often hear at football games,'' little Wally shaped his nascent stage personality to blunt classmates' enmity, escape a domineering father and brighten the workaday gloom of the Depression. Mr. Pyron, who lards his thoughts about Liberace with as many larger references as possible, especially when Greek mythology is an option, notes the entertainer's lack of satisfaction with his early success by saying: ''When asked what labor wanted, Samuel Gompers supposedly cried 'More!' It was an American idiom. Liberace spoke it with his soul.''</p>
        <p>So he created a piano act featuring candelabra inspired by a movie about Chopin, classical-sounding renditions of popular music, piano lessons for audience members, frequent references to his mother (he solicited tuna recipes for her benefit) and outrageous visual trappings that became legendary in their own right. And the essence of his performance, even in the years when it marked him as ''a cultural Antichrist,'' was its delight in being square. ''There's a whole, big, wonderful country between L.A. and N.Y.C.,'' he proclaimed with typical gusto. ''It's full of lots of smart people with opinions and tastes of their own. You have to be prepared to please that whole country. You have to be prepared to entertain everyone. If you have something for everybody, they'll have something for you . . . their love and appreciation.''</p>
        <p>But Liberace's homosexuality was not liable to please everyone. And public awareness of it could have done great damage to a career based on his appeal to women as ''the greatest lover since Valentino,'' in the words of one delusional Chicago newspaper, or at least as a friendly figure who approached consumerism with religious fervor. ''The main thing about Mr. Liberace,'' one fan told a reporter, ''is that he is through and through a Continental. When he kisses your hand, you know he isn't going to chew off your arm.'' He needed to sustain that aura, as well as the gaudy caricature of wealth and high culture that appealed so successfully to middle-class America, as a professional matter of life or death.</p>
        <p>Though Liberace was so glittery a star in the early 1950's that the book includes a picture of Elvis Presley gazing up at him delightedly as part of a Las Vegas audience, his career hit an ugly patch in the latter part of that decade. Innuendoes from publications like Hollywood Confidential (''Why Liberace's Theme Song Should Be 'Mad About the Boy' '') nearly did him in. And it was an extraordinary sign of the times that he chose to sue an English newspaper for hinting at his homosexuality, replying, ''No, sir, never in my life'' when asked in court, ''Have you ever indulged in homosexual practices?'' Mr. Pyron is at his best in explaining why, for a man with an incongruously conservative, even retrograde vision of Americana, a lie like that was a curious, backhanded way of telling some larger truth.</p>
        <p>''As he grew more artificial, he became more genuine,'' Quentin Crisp commented about Liberace. And this biography, in refracting the life of ''the showman'' (a virtual pronoun as Mr. Pyron uses it) through such watershed American events as World War II, the birth of television, the creation of Las Vegas style, the Stonewall uprising and the scourge of AIDS (which killed Liberace in 1987, though he refused to acknowledge the disease), makes that point in a larger sense.</p>
        <p>By the end, so imprisoned by vanity that he nearly refused a face-lift if it meant removing his wig, Liberace had become a true American bellwether, a man whose life was fraught with signs of his times even if his memoirs, contrary to Mr. Pyron's claim, do not warrant comparison to Benjamin Franklin's. He had achieved a strange and enduring feat of self-creation. And ''finally,'' in the words of one person quoted here, ''it was impossible to make fun of Liberace because he was having too much fun making fun of himself.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
