<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shares Fall on Worries That Earnings Will Begin to Fade</title>
    <meta content="Y27STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DD1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shares Fall on Worries That Earnings Will Begin to Fade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones industrial average drops 183.49 points, or 1.7 percent, to 10,516.48; Nasdaq composite index falls 41.85 points, or 1 percent, to 3,987.72, while Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index drops 22.05 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,452.42; US bond prices and yields are little changed; yield on Treasury's 10-year note slips to 6.02 percent, from 6.03 percent, as price rises 2/32, to 103 15/32; yield on 30-year bond is unchanged at 5.81 percent; graphs; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks tumbled yesterday after several companies warned that their profits would be lower than expected in the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>Xerox said that its third-quarter profits would come in below forecasts and that second-quarter profits were half what they were a year ago. Shares of Xerox dropped 3 3/16, to 15.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks tumbled yesterday after several companies warned that their profits would be lower than expected in the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>Xerox said that its third-quarter profits would come in below forecasts and that second-quarter profits were half what they were a year ago. Shares of Xerox dropped 3 3/16, to 15.</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler, despite an 18 percent jump in second-quarter profits, said that new-product costs and stiffer competition in North America would push earnings for the rest of the year below expectations. But its stock rose 1 5/16, to 53 9/16.</p>
        <p>After the market closed, Amazon.com reported that its second-quarter loss had more than doubled, compared with last year, and that its revenue had fallen a little short of market expectations. Shares of Amazon tumbled in-after hours trading, falling below 33, before recovering a bit to $33 11/16. Earlier in the day an analyst from Lehman Brothers lowered her rating on the stock. On Tuesday, the stock dropped after the announcement that Amazon's president and chief operating officer had resigned to become chief executive of VerticalNet Inc., a Web site manager.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 183.49 points, or 1.7 percent, to 10,516.48. The Dow was led lower by sharp declines in Hewlett-Packard and J. P. Morgan. The Nasdaq composite index fell 41.85 points, or 1 percent, to 3,987.72, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 22.05 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,452.42. The Nasdaq was pulled lower by declines in Nextel Communications, Altera, Intel and Microsoft. The S.&amp; P. was pulled lower by General Electric and AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>In the bond market, prices and yields were little changed. The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note slipped to 6.02 percent, from 6.03 percent Tuesday, as the price, which moves in the opposite direction, rose 2/32, to 103 15/32. The yield on the 30-year bond was unchanged at 5.81 percent.</p>
        <p>Stock prices have been locked in a trading range since April and it is hard to tell how they will break out of it as long as the possibility looms that the Federal Reserve will continue to raise interest rates to slow economic growth and keep inflation in check.</p>
        <p>The overall earnings outlook for the second quarter is still positive, with reports coming in better than expected, according to both I.B.E.S. International and First Call/Thomson Financial, which collect analysts' earnings estimates on the companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 index. But that is not helping investors at the moment.</p>
        <p>It may be that two negative messages are coming through to investors at the same time. One is the possible rise in rates when Fed policy makers meet Aug. 22. Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, made that clear Tuesday when he told Congress that the August decision would depend on whether economic data for July confirmed that the economy was slowing.</p>
        <p>The other is that the growth rate of earnings will slow in the second half of the year, especially if the Fed is successful in taming economic growth. While a small slowdown in earnings has been in the forecasts collected by First Call and I.B.E.S., investors may not have focused on it yet.</p>
        <p>The report earlier this week that demand for personal computers was weaker than expected in the second quarter has also weighed down the technology sector.</p>
        <p>Results of yesterday's Treasury auction of 2-year notes:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>High Price: 99.937  High Yield: 6.284%  Low Yield: 6.210%  Median Yield: 6.265%  Accepted at low price: 58%  Total applied for: $31,358,358  Accepted: $15,037,258  Noncompetitive: $1,553,345  Interest set at: 6.25%</p>
        <p>The 2-year notes mature July 31, 2002.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
