<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Unearth Artifacts A Step Ahead of Firefighters</title>
    <meta content="Y27FIR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mesa Verde National Park (Colo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colorado</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sink, Mindy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EEDB1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Unearth Artifacts A Step Ahead of Firefighters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MINDY SINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sink, Mindy</byline>
      <dateline>CORTEZ, Colo., July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Archaeologists are scrambling ahead of wildfire in Mesa Verde National Park, Colo, to identify previously undiscovered Indian sites, often working just ahead of crews building fire lines; fear both flames and firefighters may destroy artifacts; usually have time only to mark sites on map or in field; sometimes help dig fire breaks; park is only national park devoted solely to protecting cultural remains; fire, which has burned about third of park, is about 40 percent contained; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even the darkest clouds have a silver lining, and Mesa Verde National Park officials are clinging to such optimism as firefighters struggle to contain a wildfire that has burned 23,000 acres in and near the park.</p>
        <p>''We are going to be redefining what Mesa Verde means,'' the park's public affairs officer, Will Morris, said. ''We will have to reconsider the way we approach natural and cultural resources. There may be a silver lining in archaeological finds to this really dark cloud.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even the darkest clouds have a silver lining, and Mesa Verde National Park officials are clinging to such optimism as firefighters struggle to contain a wildfire that has burned 23,000 acres in and near the park.</p>
        <p>''We are going to be redefining what Mesa Verde means,'' the park's public affairs officer, Will Morris, said. ''We will have to reconsider the way we approach natural and cultural resources. There may be a silver lining in archaeological finds to this really dark cloud.''</p>
        <p>As the fire has raced through the park, archaeologists have scrambled ahead of it, working to identify previously undiscovered Indian sites. By today, at least a dozen new ones had been found.</p>
        <p>Often, the archaeologists are working just ahead of crews building fire lines, trying to prevent a false step or stray swing of a pickax from crushing a bit of antiquity. The scientists fear that both the flames and the firefighters may destroy artifacts before the fire is tamed. Usually, they have had time only to mark the sites on a map or in the field. Sometimes, they help dig fire breaks.</p>
        <p>''This is not the time to be doing any kind of extensive study,'' Linda Towle, Mesa Verde's chief archaeologist, was quoted by The Associated Press as saying.</p>
        <p>Archaeologists said they will try to return and study the sites, hoping they uncover more insight into the lives of early inhabitants.</p>
        <p>Mesa Verde is best known for being home to the largest preserved Anasazi cliff dwellings in the country, and is the only national park devoted solely to protecting cultural remains. The area was settled by ancestors of the Apache, Navajo, Hopi and Pueblo tribes. The cliff dwellings were built about 900 years ago then abandoned a hundred years later.</p>
        <p>The wildfire, which has burned about a third of the park, is about 40 percent contained.</p>
        <p>Rain and winds the night before helped extinguish some hot spots, but also made some areas flare up.</p>
        <p>The size of the fire, the value of the park and its proximity to the communities around it have made it a priority, said Justin Dombrowski, information officer with the Rocky Mountain Incident Command Team, which is overseeing the operation.  Wildfires have consumed more than 100,000 acres west of the Rocky Mountains this year, and the season is shaping up to be one of the worst in five years. Crews, equipment and other resources were stretched so thin that fire managers will organize and train military crews to help.</p>
        <p>As of Wednesday, the cost of fighting the large fires burning in the West was $26.3 million, according to  the National Interagency Fire Center in Boise, Idaho.</p>
        <p>In Colorado, the 52,000-acre park is surrounded by private land, Bureau of Land Management areas and the Ute Mountain Ute Reservation.</p>
        <p>The fire is believed to have started on Thursday after a lightning strike on private land.</p>
        <p>As they work, archaeologists at Mesa Verde are aware that they have been through this at least once before. After a 5,000-acre fire in 1996, archaeologists discovered 400 previously unknown archaeological sites to add to 4,000 known sites.</p>
        <p>Those sites provide more insight into the lives of the early inhabitants.</p>
        <p>''We learned they were controlling water more than we thought, and that they were here for a lot longer time than we thought,'' said Julie Bell, an archaeologist at the park.</p>
        <p>They also have discovered that the area might have been more populated than previously thought. For example, Battleship Rock, a significant petroglyph was largely burned in 1996. But with the surrounding brush and trees gone, archaeologists found evidence of a larger community around the rock.</p>
        <p>''Mesa Verde is famous for its cliff dwellings -- Cliff Palace, Balcony House -- and that's only one small part of it,'' Ms. Bell said. ''Those were built in the last 100 years of 800 years of occupation.''</p>
        <p>Four more cliff dwellings were found after the 1996 fires, but they were small storage units, not as impressive as the large apartment structures. Archaeologists also found earlier homes -- pithouses that were built in holes -- remnants of stonewalls, including one wall that was about four feet tall, and ancient trash piles.</p>
        <p>''It's a double-edged sword,'' Ms. Bell said of the post-fire discoveries. ''The fire will uncover a lot of more sites, but the aftereffects of the fire are going to threaten all of the sites because if we don't have the vegetation to stop the water, runoff erosion is going to be a huge problem.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bell was one of 18 archaeologists who worked ahead of fire crews this week, trying to avoid potentially important sites as they dug fire lines.</p>
        <p>As thunderstorms were rolling in Wednesday afternoon, again providing a chance for lower temperatures and more humidity, talk turned to when the park might reopen.</p>
        <p>''The next process and goal is to open the park,'' said Larry Wiese, the park superintendent.</p>
        <p>And although it appeared by late Wednesday that the park's crown jewel cliff dwellings would not be touched by the fire, experts said the resources were invaluable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
