<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gold Mover Pinch-Hits at Saratoga Opener</title>
    <meta content="27RACI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Schuylerville Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gold Mover Pinch-Hits at Saratoga Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gold Mover wins Schuylerville Stakes at Saratoga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Up until Tuesday afternoon, Mark Hennig was going to scratch Gold Mover from the Schuylerville Stakes. His filly had already won all three of her races, including a gritty upset of colts at Churchill Downs, and he wondered if running a 2-year-old after just 18 days of rest was the right thing to do. Besides, he had another undefeated filly, With Ability, ready to go.</p>
        <p>But his plans changed today when With Ability came down with a cough on Tuesday. She was scratched, and Gold Mover was led to the gate, turned loose in a field of five and romped home a winner in the very first stakes race of the 132nd Saratoga meet. A meet that, despite gray skies and intermittent sprinkles, got off to a record-breaking start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Up until Tuesday afternoon, Mark Hennig was going to scratch Gold Mover from the Schuylerville Stakes. His filly had already won all three of her races, including a gritty upset of colts at Churchill Downs, and he wondered if running a 2-year-old after just 18 days of rest was the right thing to do. Besides, he had another undefeated filly, With Ability, ready to go.</p>
        <p>But his plans changed today when With Ability came down with a cough on Tuesday. She was scratched, and Gold Mover was led to the gate, turned loose in a field of five and romped home a winner in the very first stakes race of the 132nd Saratoga meet. A meet that, despite gray skies and intermittent sprinkles, got off to a record-breaking start.</p>
        <p>''I really didn't want to run those two against each other and With Ability was a little fresher, but then she coughed and looked a little flat so we changed up,'' said Hennig, who, with the victory in the Grade II  $108,200 race, now has four stakes victories in the 2-year-old filly division this year. ''It's nice to know that if one of them gets sick, there is another who can come in and be a great backup.''</p>
        <p>Hennig's original plan was to run With Ability in the Schuylerville, Gold Mover in Monmouth Park's Sorority on Aug. 12 and his stakes-winning filly Raging Fever in the Adirondack at six and a half furlongs here on Aug. 14. Now it looks as if With Ability will go to Monmouth, on the Jersey Shore.</p>
        <p>The Schuylerville was roughly run by everyone but Gold Mover, the daughter of Gold Fever. She broke first from the No. 1 post while behind her, Seeking It All and Miss Doolittle pinballed off each other. Her rider, Craig Perrett, found himself alone on the lead as he crested the turn in the six-furlong sprint. But Robbie Davis, aboard Miss Doolittle, settled his filly after the rough start and then zoomed her up the rail to get eyeball to eyeball with Gold Mover.</p>
        <p>''I was kind of surprised when Robbie made that inside move,'' Perrett said. ''I thought it was a bit premature. But I had so much horse and I took the race right at him. We put her away quickly and discouraged that other filly.''</p>
        <p>With Miss Doolittle dispatched, Gold Mover withstood a late charge from Aaron Gryder and Seeking It All, a New York-bred filly who was sent off at long odds and came within a neck of the upset. ''She was running the best of any of them,'' said Gryder. ''She was reaching out to win at the end.''</p>
        <p>Gold Mover won by a neck in 1:111/5 , paid $3.20 for $2 to win and earned $64,920 for her owner, Edward P. Evans.</p>
        <p>Besides a glimpse of Hennig's accomplished stable of young fillies, the crowd of 27,810 -- a record for a July opening day -- got a first look at the more than $8 million in renovations to the grand old track, as well as a pretty good indication that those who came into the meet hot will remain so.</p>
        <p>Jerry Bailey, who won the Belmont spring riding title with 66 victories and an astounding 38.6 percent winning percentage, rode two more winners yesterday. He was also named to replace Jorge Chavez on the multiple stakes winner Behrens in next week's Whitney by the trainer James Bond.</p>
        <p>And the trainer Joe Orseno, whose charges for the Frank Stronach stable include the potential champions Golden Missile, Red Bullet and Perfect Sting, unveiled another budding star with 2-year-old Macho Uno. The son of Holy Bull demolished six other 2-year-olds in his debut, which was some consolation after Orseno said he was not running Red Bullet in the $1 million Haskell Invitational next week at Monmouth because of a viral infection that has plagued the Preakness winner.</p>
        <p>With 34 stakes remaining with purses totaling more than $8.6 million, the New York Racing Association is intent on bettering the records it set last year. In 1999, on-track attendance rose 3.7 percent to 920,218 for a daily average of 25,562, and the on-track handle increased by 5.4 percent to $111,969,548. The on-track handle of $3,061,913 yesterday was down slightly from last year's opening day.</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>The second of six highly anticipated 2-year-old stakes heads Thursday's card -- the Sanford Stakes, a Grade II $100,000 race for colts. It offers what the trainer D. WAYNE LUKAS believes may be a Triple Crown horse: Yonaguska, who is 2 for 2.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
