<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief of Spain's Big Phone Company Quits</title>
    <meta content="Y27TEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telefonica Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Kpn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Altadis</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Villalonga, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alierta, Cesar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4D71F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief of Spain's Big Phone Company Quits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Benjamin</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Juan Villalonga resigns as chairman of Telefonica, Spain's telecommunications company, humiliated by abandonment of $58 billion merger with Royal KPN of Netherlands in face of opposition from Spanish government; Villalonga's clashes with government supporters on Telefonica board suggest that as much as revitalized Spanish economy has become more open and entrepreneurial in last decade, there are limits to antagonizing country's clubby elite; Cesar Alierta, chairman of Spanish tobacco company Altadis, is named to scucceed Villalonga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juan Villalonga, the chairman of Spain's vast telecommunications company, Telefonica, resigned today, leaving a once-stodgy Spanish monopoly that he had turned into a giant with fast-growing holdings in Latin America and the Internet.</p>
        <p>Speculation had spread that Mr. Villalonga, 47, would resign after today's board meeting in the wake of an abandoned $58 billion merger with the Dutch phone company Royal KPN. The failure of the deal in May, because of Spanish government opposition, humiliated Mr. Villalonga, people close to the company said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Juan Villalonga, the chairman of Spain's vast telecommunications company, Telefonica, resigned today, leaving a once-stodgy Spanish monopoly that he had turned into a giant with fast-growing holdings in Latin America and the Internet.</p>
        <p>Speculation had spread that Mr. Villalonga, 47, would resign after today's board meeting in the wake of an abandoned $58 billion merger with the Dutch phone company Royal KPN. The failure of the deal in May, because of Spanish government opposition, humiliated Mr. Villalonga, people close to the company said today.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Villalonga's clashes with government supporters on the Telefonica board suggest that as much as the revitalized Spanish economy had become more open and entrepreneurial in the last decade, there are limits to antagonizing the country's clubby elite.</p>
        <p>Cesar Alierta, 55, chairman of the Spanish tobacco company Altadis, was named to succeed Mr. Villalonga. ''The appropriate time has come for a change in the company's leadership,'' Telefonica said in a statement. What compensation Mr. Villalonga will receive was not disclosed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alierta, who has an M.B.A. from Columbia University, is no stranger to privatization and cross-border deals -- he led his company's $2.4 billion merger with Seita of France. Still, he will be following a remarkable act on the European business scene. Mr. Villalonga took the helm of Telefonica in 1996, when the company was still state-owned. Under the direction of a new center-right government, it was privatized a year later and Mr. Villalonga quickly moved to transform Telefonica into a stellar performer, outpacing other newly privatized European phone companies.</p>
        <p>Telefonica made some $21 billion in acquisitions, gaining a huge share of the Brazilian market, as well as chunks in Argentina and Peru. Under Mr. Villalonga's leadership, the company became the largest supplier of telecommunications services in the Spanish-  and Portuguese-speaking world. Telefonica says it reaches a potential market exceeding 550 million customers in 24 nations through affiliates in Europe, the United States, Latin America and Africa. Sales in 1999 approached $21 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga also spun off cellular phone and multimedia businesses, as well as the Internet arm, Terra Networks. The spinoffs -- taking advantage of the market's voracious appetite for such businesses -- and Mr. Villalonga's aggressive, flashy style won over investors. Shares of Telefonica have risen sharply since Mr. Villalonga took over, though dropping amid the management uncertainty in recent months. Today, the company's American depository receipts rose $1.875, to $67.3125.</p>
        <p>The change of leadership seemed largely a relief to investors and analysts, who said Telefonica was likely to maintain its course. ''Over the medium term, there might be some volatility in Telefonica shares,'' said Glen Spencer Chapman, an analyst with Ibersecurities here. ''But it's a good company and cheap compared to other telecoms in Europe. It would appear that Telefonica will go ahead with the deals it has on the horizon.''</p>
        <p>Another analyst, Nahum Sanchez de la Madrid, of Benito Monjardin, said Mr. Villalonga's resignation ''eliminates the uncertainty which has sapped confidence in the company over the past several months.''</p>
        <p>Telefonica's $12 billion planned acquisition of Lycos, the American Internet portal, will not be affected by the change, executives said today. Robert J. Davis, Lycos's chief executive, said Mr. Villalonga's resignation removed a cloud over the merger. ''It now becomes clear to our shareholders that the deal will get done,'' he said, noting that the merger agreement did not give Telefonica or Terra the right to back out. Lycos shares gained 10 percent today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga's departure came after signs that the close political ties that had put him at Telefonica's helm were starting to unravel. He was a high school classmate of the prime minister, Jose Maria Aznar, and after years with the consultants McKinsey &amp; Company and with Credit Suisse First Boston and Bankers Trust, he was put in charge of privatizing Telefonica by Mr. Aznar's new government. With official support, he challenged ingrained Spanish business practices.</p>
        <p>But his rough-and-tumble deal-making ways in time exacted political costs. In March's general election, the opposition Socialists made much of the millions of dollars of stock options Telefonica had awarded Mr. Villalonga and other top executives. They accused Mr. Aznar's government of rewarding cronies while ignoring the poor.</p>
        <p>And last month, the newspaper El Mundo reported that Spain's stock market authority had reopened an investigation into accusations that Mr. Villalonga purchased company options as Telefonica was negotiating an alliance with WorldCom. The accusations first circulated two years ago, but regulators said then that they had found nothing illegal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga has denied the insider-trading charges, saying he had bought the options on 264,244 shares two months before the alliance was announced.</p>
        <p>He has also became fodder for Spanish gossip columns after he separated from his wife last year and began dating a former Mexican beauty queen who lives in Miami. His jet set lifestyle did not find favor among ordinary Spaniards.</p>
        <p>More important, Spanish nationalism derailed Telefonica's biggest cross-border deal. In May, the government and two banks represented on Telefonica's board, Banco Bilbao Vizcaya Argentaria and La Caixa, helped scotch the KPN merger. While Mr. Villalonga had sought a deal so as to create a pan-European network of fixed-line, data and wireless services, Madrid officials opposed the linkup, arguing that the Dutch government would be the biggest shareholder in the new company. The government threatened to use its golden share in Telefonica to torpedo the deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villalonga ''was maybe too independent for BBVA and La Caixa,'' Mr. Chapman of Ibersecurities said. ''Sometimes, Mr. Villalonga was perceived as too aggressive.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
