<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schilling To Arizona, As the Mets Just Shrug</title>
    <meta content="27CURT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daal, Omar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schilling, Curt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Travis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daal, Omar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Padilla, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Figueroa, Nelson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D61F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schilling To Arizona, As the Mets Just Shrug</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arizona Diamondbacks acquire pitcher Curt Shilling from Philadelphia Phillies for Travis Lee, Omar Daal, Nelson Figueroa and Vicente Padilla; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Arizona Diamondbacks didn't need a No. 1 starter, but they secured one anyway yesterday. Randy Johnson, meet Curt Schilling.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks, giving Philadelphia four players, won the Schilling chase over several other teams, including the Mets, who were on his trade-acceptable list. Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, said the Phillies wanted ''major league-ready talent,'' particularly for first base and the closer's role, and the Mets could not satisfactorily meet their requirement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Arizona Diamondbacks didn't need a No. 1 starter, but they secured one anyway yesterday. Randy Johnson, meet Curt Schilling.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks, giving Philadelphia four players, won the Schilling chase over several other teams, including the Mets, who were on his trade-acceptable list. Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, said the Phillies wanted ''major league-ready talent,'' particularly for first base and the closer's role, and the Mets could not satisfactorily meet their requirement.</p>
        <p>''I made numerous proposals to them, but didn't get any back in return,'' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks presented the Phillies with Travis Lee, a first baseman-outfielder, who was recently demoted to the minor leagues; Omar Daal, a starting pitcher, who has tumbled from a 16-9 record last year to 2-10 this season; Vicente Padilla, a promising young Nicaraguan right-hander with closer potential; and Nelson Figueroa, a right-handed pitcher from Brooklyn, whom Arizona obtained from the Mets two years ago.</p>
        <p>Schilling was the second starting pitcher the Phillies traded in two weeks. They previously sent Andy Ashby, their No. 2 starter, to the Atlanta Braves. Schilling will join Johnson in posing a formidable challenge to any team facing them in the same series -- a postseason series, for example. No other team has a 1-2 tandem that throws as hard and strikes out as many batters.</p>
        <p>''He's No. 1 on most teams,'' Jerry Colangelo, the Arizona managing partner, said by telephone from Phoenix, where Schilling grew up. ''We believe pitching is where it is. To throw Randy and Schilling out in any series we feel is significant.''</p>
        <p>Schilling, 33 and right-handed, was so eager to join Arizona that he acceded to Colangelo's request and waived his right, as a player traded in the middle of a multiyear contract, to demand a trade after the season. He has next season, at $6.5 million, left on his contract. No extension was discussed before the trade was completed, Colangelo said.</p>
        <p>''I told them we're trading for a guy we want,'' Colangelo added. ''We want to know we have him for sure for two years and at an appropriate time we'll sit down and talk. He's excited. He wanted to come here.''</p>
        <p>Although statistically the Diamondbacks have the second-best pitching staff in the National League, they have had problems. Daal has not been the hard-throwing successful pitcher he was in 1999, and Todd Stottlemyre has been plagued by injuries.</p>
        <p>He has been out for a month with a slight tear in his right elbow and is not expected back until September at the earliest.</p>
        <p>Schilling has had his own ailments. He began this season nearly a month late after rehabilitating from a December shoulder operation. He was also slow in working his way into his successful style of pitching.</p>
        <p>In his first eight starts, Schilling had a 1-4 record and a 6.34 earned run average. In his last eight, since June 16, he has compiled a 5-2 record and a 2.00 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Because of his belated start, Schilling's name does not appear among the National League leaders in the strikeout category, which Johnson leads overwhelmingly with 228. However, the new teammates have a strikeout achievement in common.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Schilling became the fifth pitcher in major league history to attain the 300-strikeout plateau in two successive seasons, finishing with an even 300 after having had 319 the year before.</p>
        <p>Johnson became No. 6 last season, adding 364 strikeouts to the 329 he had in 1998.</p>
        <p>Few teams in history have had pitchers who can dominate hitters as Johnson and Schilling have with strikeouts.</p>
        <p>''Koufax and Drysdale come to mind,'' Joe Garagiola Jr., the Arizona general manager said, but added, ''I'll take these two guys.''</p>
        <p>As for any 1-2 pitching punch, the Braves have Greg Maddux and Tom Glavine, and the Yankees have an assortment of starters who, when pitching effectively, can present a formidable 1-2. Phillips said he would take the Mets' Al Leiter and Mike Hampton, but added: ''Arizona is a better team right now. Schilling is a great pickup. In their division they'll be tough; in a playoff, they've got a strong rotation.''</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks have been in first place in the N.L. West for all but five days of this season, but a recent skid -- 9 losses in 15 games -- has made them vulnerable, and the San Francisco Giants have taken advantage, standing one game back at the start of play last night.</p>
        <p>The Phillies have debated internally for a couple of years whether they should trade Schilling for a hefty package of players.</p>
        <p>They decided to do it now, more than halfway through a very disappointing season.</p>
        <p>''We feel that we have improved our ball club, improved the future of our ball club,'' General Manager Ed Wade said at a news conference in Philadelphia. ''I wish we could have done it without losing Curt Schilling, but obviously we couldn't.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
