<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Beach, in Los Angeles's Shadow, Strives for a Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="Y27LONG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Beach (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Long Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DB1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Beach, in Los Angeles's Shadow, Strives for a Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <dateline>LONG BEACH, Calif., July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Beach, Calif, muscular port city of 450,000, struggles for recognition in shadow of neighboring Los Angeles as it prepares to host Reform Party convention; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To hear municipal officials here tell it, there is no more enduring, supportive relationship in a region known more for affairs and heartbreaks than the bond between this industrious, muscular port and that livable but, let's be honest, tough if not troubled city just north, Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Scratch that happy surface, however, and Long Beach will concede somewhat more complex feelings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To hear municipal officials here tell it, there is no more enduring, supportive relationship in a region known more for affairs and heartbreaks than the bond between this industrious, muscular port and that livable but, let's be honest, tough if not troubled city just north, Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Scratch that happy surface, however, and Long Beach will concede somewhat more complex feelings.</p>
        <p>Henry Taboada, its city manager, summarized the prevailing view when he recalled going to Washington with Los Angeles officials last year to seek financing for a major rail link to the cities' adjacent, sometimes bitterly competitive ports.</p>
        <p>As they entered a Congressional hearing room, the huge Los Angeles delegation took literally every seat at the table, Mr. Taboada said, forcing him to almost physically remove one of the aides so there would be a seat for the only other person in the Long Beach delegation, the mayor, Beverly O'Neill.</p>
        <p>''It was that or get no seat at the table,'' Mr. Taboada said.</p>
        <p>By any measure, Long Beach is a substantial city. With roughly 450,000 residents, it is larger than St. Louis, Atlanta, Pittsburgh or Minneapolis. It has one of the largest container ports in the world, a huge Boeing manufacturing center and a university. It has more than five miles of beaches. And, perhaps most important, it has clawed its way back from a series of economic calamities, including more than 50,000 aerospace job cuts and military base closings that made the last recession all the more fierce here.</p>
        <p>But Long Beach also has a complex, a product of its sense of always resting uncomfortably in the shadow of the flashier, more prosperous and, truth be told, infinitely more effervescent neighbor to the north.</p>
        <p>It is a struggle Long Beach officials know they cannot win, and so they put the best face on things, no more evident than now. Los Angeles will be thrust into the spotlight as  host to the Democratic National Convention from Aug. 14 to Aug. 17. And Long Beach? From Aug. 9 to Aug. 13, it will play host to the Reform Party convention, a role that some city officials admit reinforces their poor-stepchild image, at least in the eyes of the media, but does put their town  on the map.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some officials make a virtue of the city's second-tier status. Los Angeles is preparing nervously not just for tens of thousands of delegates, politicians and journalists but also for well-organized and aggressive demonstrators. The embattled Los Angeles police have already been criticized for a crowd-control plan yet to be put in effect.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Dale L. Brown, deputy police chief in Long Beach, said his city was anticipating exactly zero demonstrators at what is expected to be a sedate Reform Party gathering.</p>
        <p>''You're right, there are times we feel we don't get the recognition we deserve,'' Mr. Brown said. ''But sometimes it's nice to be in the shadows.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taboada added: ''We won't get the attention Los Angeles will. On the other hand, there are only three presidential conventions, and we have one of them.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Neill, the mayor, said that in her view, the problem was a matter of perception and nothing more.</p>
        <p>''What we want,'' she said, ''is to help people realize that when you say Los Angeles County, you don't just mean Los Angeles. I don't grumble about it, maybe because I've gotten used to dealing with this my whole life. But we're not an appendage, and we just want people to see that.''</p>
        <p>Then she did an uncanny impression of Ross Perot, who led the Reform Party when it held its last convention here four years ago and who, she said, offered this compliment: ''Your city is very nice.''</p>
        <p>Long Beach is no stranger to ups, downs and identity crises. It was founded in 1882 as Willmore City, named for an English developer who put up about a dozen houses and then failed. A few dozen more buildings were thrown up, and the settlement was reborn in 1888 as Long Beach. Today it covers about 50 square miles that comprise one of the most heavily industrialized areas in the region. On the drive south from Los Angeles on the freeway, the first sign that one has arrived is a huge oil refinery; indeed, the city still produces substantial amounts of oil.</p>
        <p>During World War II, Long Beach became home to a Navy base, a naval shipyard and a big Navy hospital. These, along with big airplane factories, became the mainstay of the economy.</p>
        <p>But Long Beach was hit with a triple whammy during the 1990's:  the recession, base closings and military procurement cutbacks sent the unemployment rate soaring to 9.2 percent in 1993. An ugly racial incident, in which the police were filmed putting the head of a black suspect, himself a former police officer, through a plate glass window, almost led the city to dissolve its police force and bring in the county sheriff's department to keep the peace.</p>
        <p>''We did not have just a death knell,'' Mr. Taboada said. ''It was one death knell after another.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Neill became mayor in the bleak days of 1994 and has worked not just to revive the city but to transform it. In addition to technology, she has pushed tourism along the waterfront, where the most notable symbol is the Queen Mary, docked there and used as an entertainment center.</p>
        <p>The success has been mixed, but unquestionably the city is back on its feet; today the unemployment rate is 5 percent, compared with 4 percent nationally. ''We've been celebrating everything,'' Ms. O'Neill said. ''We celebrated the first store opening. We celebrated the beginning of new construction. We celebrated anything that said hope.''</p>
        <p>The former Navy hospital has been transformed into a gigantic mall, although it does not have a major department store. (Indeed, there is none anywhere in Long Beach.) The city obtained government financing to build the Aquarium of the Pacific, a big tourist attraction on the refurbished waterfront, but it lost about $7.5 million from late 1998 through this March.</p>
        <p>Yet the investment continues. Several acres of unsightly blacktop just behind city hall are to be torn up soon for apartment complexes, the first such residential construction in the area since 1992.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Neill and other officials say their concern now is not so much to ensure that the Reform delegates see the transformation as to get the media to take note of the successes as Long Beach's own, not Los Angeles's.</p>
        <p>''Long Beach in the middle of the Mojave Desert would be a great media story,'' Mr. Taboada said. ''But because we're on the underbelly of Los Angeles, when we get attention it's negative -- or it has been. We feel like we can't get our message out, but maybe this will help.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
