<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Samaranch Says I.O.C. 'Has a New Philosophy'</title>
    <meta content="27JUAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2002)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Salt Lake City (Utah)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Samaranch, Juan Antonio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah/Salt Lake City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4D71F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Samaranch Says I.O.C. 'Has a New Philosophy'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Juan Antonio Samaranch, president of International Olympic Committee, in interview, discusses wide range of topics including upcoming Sydney Olympics and continued investigation into possible bribery and fraud in Salt Lake City's bid to host 2002 Winter Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With only 50 days remaining before the opening ceremonies of the Summer Olympic Games in Sydney, Australia, Juan Antonio Samaranch, the president of the International Olympic Committee, was interviewed yesterday by Christopher Clarey of The New York Times. The interview took place in Samaranch's office overlooking Lake Geneva at the I.O.C.'s headquarters in Lausanne, Switzerland, and it covered a wide range of topics, from preparations for the Summer Games to the continuing investigation into possible bribery and fraud in Salt Lake City's bid to be host of the 2002 Winter Olympics.</p>
        <p>Q. How important do you think Sydney is for the future of the Olympics and how important is the success of Sydney after the problems of the last couple of years?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With only 50 days remaining before the opening ceremonies of the Summer Olympic Games in Sydney, Australia, Juan Antonio Samaranch, the president of the International Olympic Committee, was interviewed yesterday by Christopher Clarey of The New York Times. The interview took place in Samaranch's office overlooking Lake Geneva at the I.O.C.'s headquarters in Lausanne, Switzerland, and it covered a wide range of topics, from preparations for the Summer Games to the continuing investigation into possible bribery and fraud in Salt Lake City's bid to be host of the 2002 Winter Olympics.</p>
        <p>Q. How important do you think Sydney is for the future of the Olympics and how important is the success of Sydney after the problems of the last couple of years?</p>
        <p>A. I would not like to link what happened in Salt Lake City with Sydney. Because what happened in Salt Lake City, the I.O.C. really was affected. It affected some of our members, the organization, myself and so on. But I can assure you the Olympic Games was not affected and I can tell you for example that now we are waiting for the candidates for 2008. That decision will be made next year. We have 10 candidates, 10 very strong candidates, and that means that the prestige of the Games are not affected.</p>
        <p>Speaking with regards to Sydney, we want to have a great Games. If it's possible, the best one. We don't know. The day before yesterday I was in Athens. I had a lovely tea with the president of the organizing committee of the Sydney Games, Michael Knight. And he's very happy, and if he is very happy, I am very happy.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the positive aspects of Sydney from your point of view at this stage, and what are the aspects that concern you?</p>
        <p>A. The positive aspects is that they work very well. They work on time. All the sports facilities were ready one year before. We could have pre-Olympic events to test these events at all the Olympic sites and Australia is a country which is crazy about sport. They expect great results from their team, around 60 medals. This is fantastic for a country of 19 million people and the bad thing for me regarding the Games is that they are in the spring [in the Southern Hemisphere]. Spring is not very warm. It could be cold. We could have rain, and that is, for me, the main problem.</p>
        <p>Q. Has there been progress on the idea of having South Korea and North Korea marching together in the opening and closing ceremonies in Sydney?</p>
        <p>A. I wrote to the two presidents to have the possibility of a joint team with the same uniform maybe and they discussed it during the visit of the president of South Korea to North Korea, and we got the official answer from South Korea:. they agree. But as of today we have not had an answer from North Korea.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you expect you will have one soon?</p>
        <p>A. We need it soon. In two weeks it will be too late. Not to parade together but to parade together in the same uniform, it will be too late in two weeks. Because the I.O.C. offered to present the same uniform for both teams. It was a present of the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>Q. What will the I.O.C. do in Sydney to attempt to project a more open, accessible approach, to combat the image it has as a closed, pampered club?</p>
        <p>A. The most important thing is that the I.O.C. has a new philosophy and that inside the I.O.C. we must have many members coming from international federations, many members coming from national Olympic committees. And also we have a fourth partner now, a very important partner, those are the athletes.</p>
        <p>At this moment, we have 113 members and 30 of these members, they took part in the Olympic Games and 16 of these 30 members, they won medals in the Games. And that means that more than 25 percent are athletes or ex-athletes. In Sydney, during the Olympic Games, we will elect eight new members of the I.O.C. coming from active athletes. They will be elected by 10,000 athletes in the Olympic Village. And one of these eight will even sit on the executive board of the I.O.C., which means the government of the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>Q. How will the I.O.C. project itself in Sydney? Will you still be in the finest hotels and driving around in chauffeured cars?</p>
        <p>A. We will be in a hotel, a normal hotel. I will have my bedroom and a living room to meet with the people from the delegations who want to see me. That is what I need.</p>
        <p>Q. And for transportation?</p>
        <p>A. We will have a van to have some people with me, and we'll see. Listen, I need a car, don't I? But it will be a van.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have any research that shows the effect of your reforms on public opinion of the I.O.C.?</p>
        <p>A. I think the situation is much more quiet. This very big scandal that you mentioned was a very big scandal in the United States and some other countries but I can assure you that this was not the case in all the countries.</p>
        <p>Q. There are very likely to be Aboriginal protests of some form in Sydney. Are you concerned there will be any negative impact on the Games?</p>
        <p>A. I don't think so. Because all the Aboriginal people are Australians. Maybe they will demonstrate on the occasion of the Games because they have a very important showcase, but also I think they are very much interested in the success of the Games. I will arrive in Sydney on the third or fourth of September. If I can meet with them again, I am ready.</p>
        <p>Q. Michael Johnson and Maurice Greene are not going to be running in the 200 meters in Sydney, because of what happened in the American Olympic trials. Would the I.O.C. ever consider giving a wild-card berth to defending champions as the International Amateur Athletic Federation has done with track and field world championships, or do you believe the system is fine the way it is now?</p>
        <p>A. The wild cards are not the responsibility of the International Olympic Committee. It must be a request coming from the I.A.A.F. If the I.A.A.F. makes this request, I think the International Olympic Committee is ready to study this request in a positive way.</p>
        <p>Q. Does the I.O.C. want to ensure the best athletes are at the Games in their best events?</p>
        <p>A. It is an American problem, 100 percent. If Greene and Johnson are not there, then two other Americans will be there, and as you know, in your country, you have a lot.</p>
        <p>Q. Tom Welch and Dave Johnson have been at the center of the Salt Lake City scandal and now they have been indicted. Is that a sign of Salt Lake City's failings or the I.O.C.'s failings? And how do you view their indictments on a personal level?</p>
        <p>A. I was not surprised, because all the people said that Welch and Johnson would be indicted, but personally I can say that with them I had a very good relationship. They were very friendly and very cooperative always with me and the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>Q. But is it primarily a failure on the Salt Lake City end or I.O.C. end?</p>
        <p>A. What I have a right to say is that it was a mistake by some members of the I.O.C. and also, it was a mistake on the other side.</p>
        <p>Q. You have been to Athens recently. How is the situation evolving there since you expressed your concerns publicly about the organization there?</p>
        <p>A. Much, much better. The day before yesterday I was with the prime minister, Costas Simitis, and I also had a short talk with the president of the country, and the appointment of the new president of the organizing committee is Madame Gianna Angelopoulos and I think it was the best decision. She was a great victor when she brought the Games to Athens for 2004. Now she is there and she is running the team she had during the bid and we are confident now that things are going in the right way.</p>
        <p>Q. You have been quoted as saying you wish you had stepped down as president after the Barcelona Games. Is that true and if so, why?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, it is true. Because after the great success of Barcelona in my city, I was at that moment 71 or 72. It was the right moment maybe to leave. But on this occasion, I allowed myself to ask for re-election for four more years, because in the four years to come there would be the centennial of the I.O.C. and a big congress in Paris and to be the president of the I.O.C. was a great honor on the occasion of the centennial. But after, there came the last election in 1997, and maybe yes, that was a mistake. Maybe.</p>
        <p>Q. Six of the seven I.O.C. presidents have been Europeans and there has been one American, Avery Brundage. Do you think it is desirable to have a greater geographical representation in the future?</p>
        <p>A. Maybe yes, but Europe is very important in the Olympic movement. Speaking of the Summer Games, maybe 60 percent of the medals and 60 to 65 percent of the participants are from Europe and for the Winter Games, maybe 85 percent of the medals and participants are coming from Europe.</p>
        <p>Q. What sort of qualities do you think your successor will need to succeed in the role of president in the years ahead?</p>
        <p>A. I think it serves no purpose to give advice or to recommend certain types of qualities for the next president. After you're gone, you're gone. But maybe one important thing is that the next president must be a full-time president, like me, and living in Lausanne, because if not, you are giving all the powers to the I.O.C. staff. And the staff of the I.O.C. and also in all the other organizations must be responding to the decisions of the elected people.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think that unlike you, he or she should draw a salary?</p>
        <p>A. Why not? If he does not have the economical means to not be paid, he must be paid, like many international federation presidents and international organization presidents are paid.</p>
        <p>Q. Some people believe that the 2008 Games will be the last in which the Internet does not play a major role in viewing and the last before the sports program evolves. Do you agree and how do you envision the I.O.C. negotiating this transition?</p>
        <p>A. Maybe the next president can change many things in the program. Maybe. I couldn't, because to accept new sports is very easy, but to get rid of sports is quite impossible. But maybe the next president can succeed where I did not. As for the Internet, we don't know. That is something which is a mystery for us about the future of television and the Internet and for this reason in November we are organizing a big congress to have some light shed on what the future of the Internet and television will be. What we have to guard against is not to pit the Internet against television. I'm speaking for today. I don't know what can happen one or two years from now. At this moment, I believe we have to put the Internet and television together.</p>
        <p>Q. There has been an increasing number of prominent athletes switching nationalities. Eunice Barber, the heptathlon world champion who was born in Sierra Leone, became a French citizen shortly before winning. Lyudmila Engquist became a Swedish citizen shortly before winning a gold medal in the hurdles in Atlanta. Does it concern you that as nationality becomes a commodity, it might dilute the impact of the Games?</p>
        <p>A. In the I.O.C. we have a rule and the rule is that if you are to change nationality, there must be an agreement between the two Olympic committees and if there is no agreement, you must wait three years. If a boy is marrying a German girl and gets German nationality, normally he can compete for that new country. I think in your country, you have a good example with your professional leagues. They are full of foreign people. We have our rule that's all, and we are respecting this rule.</p>
        <p>Q. You said last year that ''I used to be happy to open the door of my office. Now, I am happy if I close it behind me.'' How do you feel now?</p>
        <p>A. I said this because last year was not an easy year for me, to be the leader, to try to get through these reforms, because the members of the I.O.C., when they were elected, they had a lot of powers and prerogatives and to convince them it was time to change and to give up many prerogatives, like the visits to the bidding cities for the Olympic Games and so on, was not easy.</p>
        <p>So that means at that moment, it was not easy. Now, it's a pleasure again, but I'm also thinking that this pleasure will not last very long.</p>
        <p>Q. You're referring to the end of your term next year?</p>
        <p>A. In 11 months, I will be an ex-president.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
