<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; The Truth, As Always, Is Stranger. ...</title>
    <meta content="27MATT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Bently Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Tiffany F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5DF163DF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; The Truth, As Always, Is Stranger. ...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column discusses case of Bently Louis Grant, mentally disturbed homeless man who was arrested on attempted murder charges for attacking Tiffany Goldberg with brick on street in midtown Manhattan; Grant has been ordered released after evidence shows that he did not commit crime (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE case of Bently Louis Grant could be a segment on ''Law and Order.'' Probably will be some day, it's such a natural. New York is horrified by a high-profile crime, there's pressure to solve it, an arrest, charges, and then. . . .</p>
        <p>Mr. Grant, 35, is the mentally disturbed homeless man who was arrested after an intensive 10-day search and charged with hitting a young woman on the head with a chunk of concrete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE case of Bently Louis Grant could be a segment on ''Law and Order.'' Probably will be some day, it's such a natural. New York is horrified by a high-profile crime, there's pressure to solve it, an arrest, charges, and then. . . .</p>
        <p>Mr. Grant, 35, is the mentally disturbed homeless man who was arrested after an intensive 10-day search and charged with hitting a young woman on the head with a chunk of concrete.</p>
        <p>After hours of questioning, he signed a confession. Two witnesses chose him from lineups. Investigators also have a police sketch that looks so much like Mr. Grant you'd think he had posed for it. He was charged with attempted murder, assault and possession of a weapon, and faced up to 25 years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>But on Tuesday, six days after his arrest, Mr. Grant was ordered released. What triggered his release was that truth-teller of our era -- the videotape. And the instincts of a resourceful prosecutor.</p>
        <p>It happened like this:</p>
        <p>Mr. Grant was originally stopped on July 13 by police officers canvassing homeless people in Murray Hill for the man who attacked Tiffany F. Goldberg. They questioned him, took his photo, and released him because they didn't have enough evidence to hold him.</p>
        <p>But after a witness identified him from a photo lineup, he was picked up in Park Slope on July 19.</p>
        <p>Police investigators questioned Mr. Grant in the 13th Precinct station house from around 8 p.m. through the night. His Miranda rights were read to him, the authorities said, but he must have waived them because he did not have a lawyer.</p>
        <p>He confessed at 6:50 Thursday morning. Then Amy Schwartz, an assistant district attorney, began to ask her own questions. She did not like what she heard.</p>
        <p>Her boss, Robert M. Morgenthau, the Manhattan district attorney, said: ''His story did not hang together. After talking to him for some time, she felt he was not at the scene of the crime.''</p>
        <p>According to investigators, Mr. Grant said in his confession that he was in the Virgin Megastore on 14th Street between Broadway and Fourth Avenue before Ms. Goldberg was attacked on 29th Street between Lexington Avenue and Park Avenue South. But then he recanted, saying he was in the store at the time of the assault.</p>
        <p>That store, said Mr. Morgenthau, has 31 video cameras trained on shoppers. Investigators got the tapes, monitored 15 hours of them starting on Friday, and finally saw Mr. Grant captured on video Monday afternoon, validating his alibi. In addition, the videos showed him wearing a white shirt. Witnesses had said the attacker was wearing a yellow one.</p>
        <p>''From the beginning, when you've got a homeless guy who says 'I did it,' that sets off bells,'' Mr. Morgenthau said. ''I immediately said, 'I hope we've got the right guy.' People do not like to hear this, but I'd say about a third of homeless people have severe mental problems. That's why they are homeless.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schwartz concluded that the wrong man was in custody and asked a judge to release him. Mr. Grant, who has no criminal record, is being held at Elmhurst Hospital Center for psychological evaluation, at his family's request. The district attorney's office has six months from the day of arrest to determine whether to prosecute or dismiss the charges.</p>
        <p>YESTERDAY investigators were still focusing on Mr. Grant as the principal suspect, but by last night they were agreeing that the case against him was weak.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morgenthau, who determines whom to prosecute in Manhattan, said, ''The way it looks to us now, this alibi is 98 percent sure, 99 percent.''</p>
        <p>He thinks he does have the right man in a similar case -- the assault last fall of Nicole Barrett by a man wielding a paving stone. Paris Drake, a street vendor, was charged in January with attempted murder. ''If we made a mistake, we are going to correct it,'' Mr. Morgenthau said, ''but it looks like a good case.''</p>
        <p>Then again, so did the case against Mr. Grant. Until the videotapes turned up. How do these things happen?</p>
        <p>''When you get these highly publicized cases, there is tremendous pressure,'' Mr. Morgenthau said. ''The police had every reason to arrest this guy. They had eyewitnesses. They got a confession. They did their job. Then we did our job, continued to investigate, found he was the wrong guy.''</p>
        <p>Even without the videotape, he said, he is quite sure Ms. Schwartz would have picked up inconsistencies in Mr. Grant's story.</p>
        <p>It would be nice to think so. Maybe that's how ''Law and Order'' will write the script.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
