<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JDS Uniphase Fourth-Quarter Profits Exceed Estimates</title>
    <meta content="Y27UNI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000728T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jds Uniphase Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDC1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JDS Uniphase Fourth-Quarter Profits Exceed Estimates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>JDS Uniphase Corp reports fourth-quarter earnings that exceed analysts' estimates; posts net loss of $419 million compared with loss of $194.2 million a year ago; says profit was $114 million and sales grew 173 percent, to $524 million from $192 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The JDS Uniphase Corporation, a fast-growing maker of components for fiber optic networks, reported fourth-quarter earnings today that exceeded analysts' estimates when excluding charges for the company's wave of acquisitions.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended June 30, JDS, based in San Jose, Calif., and Nepean, Ontario, posted a net loss of $419 million, or 54 cents a share, compared with a loss of $194.3 million, or 60 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The JDS Uniphase Corporation, a fast-growing maker of components for fiber optic networks, reported fourth-quarter earnings today that exceeded analysts' estimates when excluding charges for the company's wave of acquisitions.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended June 30, JDS, based in San Jose, Calif., and Nepean, Ontario, posted a net loss of $419 million, or 54 cents a share, compared with a loss of $194.3 million, or 60 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Excluding merger-related charges and other special items, JDS Uniphase reported profit of $114 million, or 14 cents a share. In the period a year earlier, the combined profit of JDS Fitel and the Uniphase Corporation -- which merged in June 1999 -- was $41 million, or 6 cents a share. Sales grew 173 percent, to $524 million from $192 million.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected the company to earn 12 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Although JDS Uniphase reported its results after the markets closed, investors anticipated a strong quarter and drove the company's shares up $5.75, to $135.9375, in Nasdaq trading.</p>
        <p>JDS Uniphase traded more shares in a single day than any other United States stock -- just more than 200 million -- as money managers added it to their holdings before it became part of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index. The stock was added to the S.&amp; P. 500 after exchanges closed.</p>
        <p>In a conference call, executives of JDS Uniphase predicted that revenue growth would accelerate and increased their estimates of quarter-to-quarter growth to the high teens from 15 percent, not including the effects of acquisitions. Revenue in the most recent quarter grew 33 percent from the previous quarter, or 25 percent excluding acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Although JDS Uniphase's explosive revenue growth was expected, ''it shows you how powerful this industry is,'' said Jim Kedersha, an analyst with SG Cowen. The company also benefits from a market where demand exceeds supply and the barriers to adding supply are high, he said.</p>
        <p>JDS Uniphase's rapid growth and aggressive acquisition strategy had already given it a high profile, but the spotlight has shown more brightly on the company since reports that the Nortel Networks Corporation might sell its optical components division to Corning Inc. for about $100 billion. Nortel and Lucent Technologies, which has said it will spin off a similar components business, are large customers of JDS Uniphase as well as competitors.</p>
        <p>The future of the components businesses of Nortel and Lucent adds an element of uncertainty, Mr. Kedersha said. ''I think people are going to be concerned about how will the competitive environment change if these two big captive suppliers get spun out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Joseph Strauss, the president and chief executive of JDS Uniphase, said the market was sufficiently dynamic to support many suppliers. ''I think there is enough to eat for a long time,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''The Internet is just getting going. We need many, many suppliers to meet this opportunity.''</p>
        <p>JDS Uniphase's results included those of Epitaxx Inc., Sifam Ltd., Optical Coating Laboratory Inc., Cronos Integrated Microsystems Inc. and Fujian Casix Laser Inc., which were acquired between Nov. 15, 1999, and May 8. Results for the quarter do not include those of E-Tek Dynamics Inc., which was acquired on June 30.</p>
        <p>Reporting separately, E-Tek had sales of $123 million for the quarter that ended June 30 and pro forma net income of $23 million, or 32 cents a share. Pro forma sales combining JDS Uniphase and E-Tek were $641 million, the company said. Pro forma net income was $137 million, or 14 cents a share.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY  Correction:  July 28, 2000, Friday  An article in Business Day yesterday about the quarterly financial performance of the JDS Uniphase Corporation misspelled the name of its chief executive. He is Jozef Straus, not Joseph Strauss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 28, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about the quarterly financial performance of the JDS Uniphase Corporation misspelled the name of its chief executive. He is Jozef Straus, not Joseph Strauss.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
