<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hero's Welcome for Arafat, From Those Who Showed Up</title>
    <meta content="Y27GAZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IMPASSE AT CAMP DAVID: THE PALESTINIANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ramallah (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DB1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hero's Welcome for Arafat, From Those Who Showed Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>GAZA, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinians give Yasir Arafat hero's welcome for holding fast at Camp David to demands for sovereignty over all of East Jerusalem, Gaza; frenzied welcome seems carefully orchestrated by Arafat's Fatah movement; Ramallah rally in support of Arafat attracts only 200 people; many Palestians seem deeply disllusioned with him for failing to improve living conditions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Yasir Arafat returned to this hardscrabble territory, he was given a hero's welcome today for holding fast at Camp David to Palestinian demands that Israel surrender sovereignty over all of East Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat was hoisted onto supporters' shoulders and hailed by thousands waving flags and banners and carrying his portrait. It was a rare moment of adulation for Mr. Arafat, whose popularity has been eroded by the hardships and corruption that have been hallmarks of life under the rule of his Palestinian Authority in the Gaza Strip and the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Yasir Arafat returned to this hardscrabble territory, he was given a hero's welcome today for holding fast at Camp David to Palestinian demands that Israel surrender sovereignty over all of East Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat was hoisted onto supporters' shoulders and hailed by thousands waving flags and banners and carrying his portrait. It was a rare moment of adulation for Mr. Arafat, whose popularity has been eroded by the hardships and corruption that have been hallmarks of life under the rule of his Palestinian Authority in the Gaza Strip and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>At Gaza airport and again outside his headquarters in Gaza City, the 70-year-old Palestinian leader responded, despite evident fatigue, by clambering atop the roof of his armored Mercedes limousine and raising his fingers in a victory salute.</p>
        <p>One of many banners outside El Montada, the handsome stone building overlooking the Mediterranean in Gaza City where Mr. Arafat has his headquarters, put the matter squarely. ''We welcome you home with honor,'' it said. ''We hail your heroic stand in not surrendering a single centimeter of Palestinian land, and in not giving up Jerusalem. You are a great leader of the Palestinian people.''</p>
        <p>As frenzied as it was, the welcome appeared to involve only a tiny fraction of the one million Palestinians living in Gaza. It also appeared to have been carefully orchestrated by the Fatah movement, Mr. Arafat's faction of the Palestine Liberation Organization.</p>
        <p>A similar story unfolded on the West Bank, where a rally in support of Mr. Arafat in the town of Ramallah attracted only 200 people. One reason for the small crowd was that Mr. Arafat's plane landed at the height of the working day. But many Palestinians appear deeply disillusioned with their leader for failing to deliver better living conditions in the six years since the Palestinian Authority assumed responsibility for most of Gaza from Israel.</p>
        <p>But from the voices among the 5,000 people at the airport, and amid the tumult of a similarly-sized gathering at the Gaza headquarters, it seemed that Mr. Arafat had done the only thing he could in holding out for all of the Old City of Jerusalem, which contains ancient sites sacred to Arabs, Jews and Christians.</p>
        <p>Teenage boys, Muslim clerics, middle-aged shopkeepers, policewomen, small children scampering cheerfully through police security lines of comic-opera efficiency, all were of a single accord.</p>
        <p>''We should never give up any part of Jerusalem -- never,'' said Eyad Daoud, a 17-year-old high school student.</p>
        <p>A 50-year-old official working in Mr. Arafat's religious affairs ministry, Abdul Fattah, stood back serenely from the hubbub in the city, a model of clerical propriety in a gold-trimmed robe and a loose white hood. ''All Arabs, and all Muslims, need Jerusalem, and acknowledge it as the Palestinians' rightful capital,'' he said. ''If the world wants peace, East Jerusalem must return to the Palestinians. There is no other way.''</p>
        <p>On its face, the welcome appeared to endorse Mr. Arafat's rejection of the compromise urged by President Clinton, involving limited Israeli concessions to Palestinian autonomy in the eastern parts of the city as part of an overall peace settlement. It would also have allowed the return to Israel of a few thousand of the more than three million Palestinian refugees dispersed around the region.</p>
        <p>But things on this sun-scorched day were not necessarily quite as appearances suggested.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Mr. Arafat emphasized during a brief stop at Alexandria for talks with the Egyptian president, Hosni Mubarak, and again in remarks at Gaza airport, that he was still hopeful of resuming negotiations with Israel before the Sept. 13 deadline he has set for unilaterally declaring a Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>The date, a possible trigger for renewed violence between Israelis and Palestinians, is the anniversary of the signing of the Oslo accords in 1993 on the White House lawn.</p>
        <p>Considering the unlikelihood of Mr. Barak or any other Israeli leader coming forward within the next seven weeks with sweeping concessions on Jerusalem, Mr. Arafat's eagerness for negotiations suggested that he, at least, has not ruled out a compromise.</p>
        <p>One possibility would be the one raised at Camp David, under which the thorny issue of Jerusalem's status would be deferred while other issues, including the West Bank and Palestinian statehood, are settled.</p>
        <p>For the moment, though, Mr. Arafat is sticking to the position he took at the peace talks: there can be no final peace, nor even an interim settlement, without Israel conceding sovereignty over East Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>''Jerusalem is not only for the Palestinians, it is for the Arab nation, for Muslims everywhere, for Christians,'' he told reporters at the airport. He added, ''Jerusalem is the capital of the Palestinian state, like it or not. Whoever does not like it, let him go and drink from the sea.''</p>
        <p>Part of Israel's calculation in negotiating with Mr. Arafat has been that Palestinians might be willing to trade their historic links with Jerusalem for a quick transition to full statehood, international aid and more relaxed ties with Israel. American officials have said President Clinton dangled the prospect of generous Western aid in the closing hours of the Camp David meeting, only for the Palestinian leader to remain immovable on Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Despite the hubbub today, there may be a sizable proportion of Palestinians who are not willing to wait another generation or more for the benefits of peace, even if a compromise on Jerusalem is part of the price.</p>
        <p>One long-term Gaza resident said that, at age 35, he could wait no longer for the benefits of a final settlement.</p>
        <p>''All this posturing brings us nothing, or less than nothing,'' he said. ''What do we have to show for six years of Palestinian autonomy here? No jobs, terrible shortages of electricity and water, bad schools, bad hospitals, bad everything -- worse even than when the Israelis were here. And now we say, 'Jerusalem or nothing.' It's a dream.''</p>
        <p>If there was one point of agreement among the Palestinians, it was that the events in Camp David should not be the signal for renewed violence, and especially not of a ''second intifada,'' or uprising, like the one that caused widespread mayhem in the late 1980's and early 1990's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat implied as much by speaking of the hope of resuming negotiations, and one of his chief lieutenants, Nabeel Shath, who accompanied the Palestinian leader to Camp David, made it explicit. ''There will be no violence from the Palestinians, not unless Israel makes violence, or the settlers turn to it,'' he told reporters.</p>
        <p>Some young Palestinians have spoken menacingly of a resumption of attacks by Hamas, the radical Islamic group that engaged in a terror campaign in the mid-1990's. But Palestinian analysts say Mr. Arafat's Fatah group has largely emasculated Hamas by arresting or exiling many of its leading figures. In any case, Israeli military officials have said that they have alerted army and police units to be especially vigilant in the coming days.</p>
        <p>In the circumstances, Mr. Arafat and his associates in the Palestinian leadership seem set on making the best of what, after years of working toward unchallenged Palestinian statehood, has unarguably been a setback. Mr. Shath, the senior Arafat aide who participated in the Camp David talks, said that despite the appearance of failure, the Palestinians had left Camp David convinced that they had achieved a major breakthrough simply by getting the Israelis and the Americans to concentrate on Jerusalem as the main obstacle to peace.</p>
        <p>''We are not disappointed,'' he said. ''The talks were very useful, very important, because all the issues that have been taboo all these years -- above all, Jerusalem -- are now on the table.''</p>
        <p>IMPASSE AT CAMP DAVID: THE PALESTINIANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
