<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 'Tough' Plane, Almost All the Time</title>
    <meta content="Y27PIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONCORDE CRASH: THE COCKPIT VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concorde Airplane</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3DA1F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 'Tough' Plane, Almost All the Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pilots who have flown Concorde, commenting on Air France crash, say plane is tough and robust, but impossible to control should it lose side-by-side pair of engines at low speed just after takeoff; insist Concorde's design would not have contributed to disaster (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the aftermath of the crash of an Air France Concorde near Paris, some of the pilots who have flown them pondered a paradox today. The supersonic airliner, according to one, is tough and robust, with ''tremendous reserve capacity'' to power its way out of trouble. But, according to another, if the plane lost a side-by-side pair of its four engines at low speed just after takeoff, it would be ''impossible to control.''</p>
        <p>Investigators in France reported today that the pilot of Concorde Flight AF4590 had noted a problem in an engine that had been repaired earlier in the day. But that, a former pilot said, would not fully explain the contrail of flame that witnesses saw just after the airplane lifted off from Charles de Gaulle airport on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the aftermath of the crash of an Air France Concorde near Paris, some of the pilots who have flown them pondered a paradox today. The supersonic airliner, according to one, is tough and robust, with ''tremendous reserve capacity'' to power its way out of trouble. But, according to another, if the plane lost a side-by-side pair of its four engines at low speed just after takeoff, it would be ''impossible to control.''</p>
        <p>Investigators in France reported today that the pilot of Concorde Flight AF4590 had noted a problem in an engine that had been repaired earlier in the day. But that, a former pilot said, would not fully explain the contrail of flame that witnesses saw just after the airplane lifted off from Charles de Gaulle airport on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''That great long plume of flame implies some sort of catastrophic failure, when the engine breaks up and blows apart,'' said John Hutchinson, a former Concorde pilot. And failure on that scale, aviation experts said, could well have damaged the plane's control systems, or even another nearby engine housed in the Concorde's wings close to the fuel tanks.</p>
        <p>''Failure of both engines at low speed just after takeoff is impossible to control,'' said another former pilot, Germain Chambort, in a television interview here.</p>
        <p>Investigators have yet to establish the extent of the engine failure that caused the flame. But pilots from the elite corps of Concorde aviators, flying airplanes whose value is calculated far more in corporate prestige than dollars-and-cents return on investment, insisted that the Concorde's design -- with its engines much closer together than on most subsonic planes -- would not have contributed to the disaster.</p>
        <p>''I have complete confidence in that part of the design,'' said Mike Bannister, the chief Concorde pilot for British Airways. Brian Trubshaw, the former Concorde test pilot who flew the plane on its maiden flight over Britain in 1969, told reporters at the Farnborough Air Show that ''she is in her essence a safe plane.'' He was at the show to promote his autobiography, ''Concorde: The Inside Story.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Hutchinson, the former pilot, said he regarded the Concorde as ''a very safe airplane that has got at least 10 years and maybe 15 years of life'' left in it.</p>
        <p>Few of the former pilots and aviation experts who spoke to reporters today ventured an opinion on how the Concorde might have behaved in its final moments. But Malcolm English, editor of Air International, said the drill would have been to avoid a stall -- when an airplane loses the airspeed it needs to fly -- and seek a safe landing. If, however, an intense fire burned through the controls, even the most rudimentary anti-stall maneuvers would be impossible. ''If that's what happened, then it looks like they lost flight control,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under those circumstances, an airplane would pitch and stall.</p>
        <p>One pilot reportedly suggested that if the experience of a Concorde simulator was anything to go by, a simple engine failure would be easier to control on a Concorde than on some subsonic planes. Compared with those, ''keeping Concorde on centerline is a piece of cake,'' Capt. John Wiley, a USAirways pilot, was quoted as telling a Farnborough Air Show news bulletin published by Aviation Week. With a double engine failure programmed into the simulator, he said, the plane veered to one side while rolling to the other. But regaining control, he added, was ''not even a bad dream, much less a nightmare.''</p>
        <p>''But how difficult is Concorde to fly?'' Mr. Wiley ruminated. ''One simulator session may not be the best measure for this answer, but let's just say it takes a lot of commitment to fly Concorde.''</p>
        <p>THE CONCORDE CRASH: THE COCKPIT VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
