<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Calls for Defeat of G.O.P. 'Old Guard'</title>
    <meta content="Y27GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rainbow/push Coalition</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0D91F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Calls for Defeat of G.O.P. 'Old Guard'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, warning against apathy within Democratic ranks, urges members of Rev Jesse Jackson's Rainbow/PUSH Coalition to set aside doubts about him and work to defeat Republican 'old guard' ticket of Gov George W Bush and Dick Cheney; Chicago speech caps several days of campaigning in which he sought to reach out to party's core liberal wing; his aides say they are counting on Jackson to energize black voters by raising questions about Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warning against apathy within the Democratic ranks, Vice President Al Gore today urged members of the Rev. Jesse Jackson's organization, the Rainbow/PUSH Coalition, to set aside doubts about him and work to defeat the Republican ''old guard'' embodied in the ticket of Gov. George W. Bush and Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>Speaking before a mostly black audience of more than 100 people in a hotel ballroom here, Mr. Gore said  the dismaying imperfections of politicians had turned off many people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warning against apathy within the Democratic ranks, Vice President Al Gore today urged members of the Rev. Jesse Jackson's organization, the Rainbow/PUSH Coalition, to set aside doubts about him and work to defeat the Republican ''old guard'' embodied in the ticket of Gov. George W. Bush and Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>Speaking before a mostly black audience of more than 100 people in a hotel ballroom here, Mr. Gore said  the dismaying imperfections of politicians had turned off many people.</p>
        <p>But he implored his listeners to avoid cynicism, cautioning that their indifference could help elect Mr. Bush and thus allow the Republicans to undermine civil rights, workers' rights, the economy, the environment and health care programs.</p>
        <p>''There can be absolutely no doubt that voters will go to the polls choosing between two very different visions for our future,'' Mr. Gore said. ''It is the choice between the old guard that gave us deficits, division and social injustices, and a new vision for prosperity and progress, investment, inclusion and growth to lift up all of our people.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Do not look at the imperfections and use that as an excuse for closing your heart and turning away. You have to overcome the cynicism, overcome the reluctance, overcome the doubt.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did not explain what he meant by ''imperfections.''</p>
        <p>His speech capped several days of campaigning in which he has sought to reach out to the party's core liberal wing, which includes environmentalists, unions and black and Hispanic voters. Many polls have shown relatively little enthusiasm among those constituencies for Mr. Gore. And as if to hammer home that point, his audience today applauded only occasionally.</p>
        <p>His advisers say they are counting on Mr. Jackson -- who closed his remarks today with a chant of ''More with Gore'' -- to energize black voters by raising questions about Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>In introducing Mr. Gore today, Mr. Jackson -- once a bitter rival who has become his close ally -- asserted that the Clinton administration's policies had improved the lives of black families. But he also warned that ''prosperity fatigue'' might be creating apathy among black voters. And then he opened a slashing attack on Mr. Cheney, a former five-term congressman from Wyoming and secretary of defense under President George Bush, the governor's father.</p>
        <p>''Dick Cheney voted against Head Start,'' Mr. Jackson said. ''He voted against equal rights for women. He voted against sanctions against South Africa, not once but six times. He voted against freeing Nelson Mandela from jail.''</p>
        <p>Saying Mr. Cheney's record rivaled that of Senator Jesse Helms, the Republican conservative from North Carolina, Mr. Jackson added, ''Beneath the veneer lies an individual of extreme views.''</p>
        <p>''We all know that image is a big part of high-tech politics,'' he said. ''How somebody looks on TV can hide flaws. Dick Cheney has an image that is palatable. But Jesus warned us to beware wolves in sheep's clothing.''</p>
        <p>Implicit in Mr. Jackson's remarks was the concern, shared by many Democrats, that the Republicans are winning the public relations battle, successfully wooing centrist independent and swing voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore acknowledged that concern, saying, ''I do give our opponents some credit'' for their tactics.</p>
        <p>''They have concocted a strategy of phrases and photo opportunities to convey the impression of inclusion and moderation,'' he said. ''But you and I know this is not about show business. It is about the lives and livelihoods of hard-working families. You know from a hard history and long struggle that talk is cheap. Deeds are what counts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also raised questions about Mr. Bush's commitment to civil rights, recalling that the governor had supported South Carolina's right to fly the Confederate battle flag over its state house.</p>
        <p>''He took a look up there at the flag pole,'' the vice president said of Mr. Bush. ''He saw the American flag; he saw the dome. But he did not see a symbol of injustice and oppression. Something was wrong with his vision.''</p>
        <p>In his remarks today, Mr. Gore avoided the raspy, high-energy Southern-preacher speaking style he sometimes assumes when addressing black audiences. Instead, he spoke in a calm, almost easy-going voice as he delved into his confessional themes.</p>
        <p>''I ask you to turn away from any who say that politics is not worth your hearts,'' he said. ''Many hearts have been broken. Many have been disillusioned, disappointed; many have turned away. And some of the best and most effective men and women in America now keep politics at an arm's length.''</p>
        <p>''I will not let you down,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
