<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jets' Thomas and Young, Side by Side On the Field and Off</title>
    <meta content="27JETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Young, Ryan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5D71F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jets' Thomas and Young, Side by Side On the Field and Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Play of offensive linemen Randy Thomas and Ryan Young at New York Jets training camp described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Randy Thomas and Ryan Young are sauntering into the Hofstra cafeteria for another lunch together, another day side by side, preparing for a season in which they will spend much of their football time -- and off time -- together. Thomas and Young are the sturdy duo who emerged on the right side of the offensive line last year, the two rookies who, first Thomas, then Young, won starting spots next to each other, just as they live much of their day.</p>
        <p>Thomas seems to spend an inordinate amount of time at the serving station, piling plate upon plate on his tray, a testament to the legendary eating habits that appear to be the only thing that comes between the two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Randy Thomas and Ryan Young are sauntering into the Hofstra cafeteria for another lunch together, another day side by side, preparing for a season in which they will spend much of their football time -- and off time -- together. Thomas and Young are the sturdy duo who emerged on the right side of the offensive line last year, the two rookies who, first Thomas, then Young, won starting spots next to each other, just as they live much of their day.</p>
        <p>Thomas seems to spend an inordinate amount of time at the serving station, piling plate upon plate on his tray, a testament to the legendary eating habits that appear to be the only thing that comes between the two.</p>
        <p>''I try not to venture to buffets with Randy,'' Young said.</p>
        <p>If Thomas's gargantuan appetite provokes shock even in his teammates -- there was the time the manager of a nearby Chinese restaurant gave him a dirty look when he consumed 16 lobster tails at the all-you-can-eat $17 buffet -- then the continuation of his fine rookie performance at right guard has been no surprise.</p>
        <p>He was a second-round draft choice last season and was the highest guard chosen. He quickly won the starting job in a training camp in which Bill Parcells said finding offensive guards was a priority. Thomas was the first rookie guard to open the season as a Jets starter since Randy Rasmussen in 1967.</p>
        <p>''Randy was playing the right guard spot and Bryan Cox was playing the left inside linebacker on a drill,'' Coach Al Groh recalls of the training camp in which Thomas emerged. ''He came off and hit Bryan a couple of times and Bryan yelled at Bill, 'Bill, you don't have to look any further, you found your guard right here.' ''</p>
        <p>The right side of the offensive line is extremely young. Thomas and Young, who took over at right tackle in the ninth game last season when Jason Fabini suffered a knee injury, are 24 years old. The third-year players Fabini (25 years old) and Kerry Jenkins (26) are at left tackle and left guard. The elder statesman, center Kevin Mawae, 29, is starting his seventh season. Young and Thomas have been together since they joined the Jets, when they were placed as roommates. Now they spend their down time together, too, Thomas with his fiancee and Young with his wife, trying not to talk about football.</p>
        <p>''We learn from each other off the field,'' Young said. ''We learn how the other person thinks. We have a great friendship and a great working relationship.''</p>
        <p>Thomas said: ''I'm comfortable with him beside me.''</p>
        <p>So are the Jets. Today, Groh said Thomas and Young ''get it.'' Earlier in training camp, Groh said Thomas had the talent and ambition to separate himself from other guards in the league, and Cox said Thomas was one of the players he was most impressed with in camp.</p>
        <p>''Randy, obviously, is a great player and is going to get even better,'' Mawae said. ''Having Randy next to Ryan is going to make Ryan even better. Those two feed off each other. To have them in the game and see how they react is something neat.''</p>
        <p>Thomas, though, has been unable to influence Young in at least one area. Young watches what he eats, saying what slides off Thomas would stick to him. Thomas, who said that in his life he has probably eaten a mile of fried chicken, doesn't understand why everyone talks about his eating habits.</p>
        <p>''The reason guys get upset is because I don't get fat,'' said Thomas, who maintains 301 pounds on his 6-foot-4-inch frame. ''I have a nice digestive system.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>BILL PARCELLS, who does not submit to interviews with reporters who cover the Jets, was in the building while a tape of an appearance on ESPN played Wednesday. In the interview, Parcells repeated that he has coached his last game. As for the trade of KEYSHAWN JOHNSON, Parcells contended that renegotiating Johnson's contract would have meant the Jets would have not been able to sign at least five or six players. Parcells said that rather than having one player, Johnson, signed for five years, the Jets were able to sign four players -- their four first-round draft picks -- for five years. Parcells neglected to mention that the Jets wouldn't have had four first-round picks to sign if Johnson had stayed, because two of those picks came over from Tampa Bay in the trade. When asked about Johnson's remarks that had Parcells still been the coach he would still be a Jet, Parcells skirted the question, saying the Jets made an organizational decision and that it was his job to present the organization with options. ''If we weren't able to get two No. 1 draft choices, I don't think it would have been a consideration,'' Parcells said. ''When that option came up, in addition to the draft choices we got with BILL BELICHICK, we thought maybe we could revamp our defense, fill a big need at tight end, and then if the quarterback draft pick turns out to be the guy who quarterbacks your team for 10 to 12 years, then I think at the end of the day you have to feel that the trade was worth it.'' . . . Defensive tackle RICHARD SEALS left the practice clutching his upper left arm and did not return.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
