<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Judge Allows Spraying to Continue</title>
    <meta content="27NILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Roosevelt Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baer, Harold Jr (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1D81F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Judge Allows Spraying to Continue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Harold L Baer Jr clears way for New York City to continue spraying pesticides to control spread of West Nile virus, but steady rain forces city to postpone for day its plans to spray much of Manhattan and Roosevelt Island (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge yesterday cleared the way for New York City to continue spraying pesticides to control the spread of West Nile virus, but steady rain forced the city to postpone for a day its plans to spray much of Manhattan and Roosevelt Island.</p>
        <p>A coalition of environmental groups had sought an emergency order to halt the spraying of Anvil, a pesticide that had already been used in Central Park, across Staten Island and in parts of Queens and Brooklyn, in areas where the virus was found in birds and mosquitoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge yesterday cleared the way for New York City to continue spraying pesticides to control the spread of West Nile virus, but steady rain forced the city to postpone for a day its plans to spray much of Manhattan and Roosevelt Island.</p>
        <p>A coalition of environmental groups had sought an emergency order to halt the spraying of Anvil, a pesticide that had already been used in Central Park, across Staten Island and in parts of Queens and Brooklyn, in areas where the virus was found in birds and mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>But after two hours of testimony by witnesses for the city and the environmentalists, Judge Harold Baer Jr. of United States District Court in Manhattan ruled that the environmental groups had not presented enough evidence to require a temporary restraining order to stop the spraying.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists, represented by the Pace Environmental Litigation Clinic at the Pace University School of Law in White Plains, filed a lawsuit last week, contending that the spraying campaign violated environmental laws.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani harshly criticized the environmentalists yesterday, saying their effort to stop the spraying was a ''mindless attempt to frighten people.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''They are so far over on the other side in their zealous advocacy that they are missing the importance of human life.''</p>
        <p>The mosquito-borne virus killed 7 people in the New York region last year and made 55 others seriously ill. No human cases have been reported this year, but the virus has been found in 11 mosquito samples in the region, including three pools in New York City, and one in Connecticut. The virus has also been found in more than 50 birds in New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups argued in court yesterday that the city was not using the pesticide properly and that the minimal risk of humans' contracting the virus did not justify spraying throughout the city.</p>
        <p>''In reality, people are very confused,'' said Mitchel Cohen, a leader of the No Spray Coalition, one of the plaintiffs in the lawsuit. ''On the one hand, they are worried about spraying, but there's an orchestrated hysteria around the West Nile virus, as if it's a health emergency. Where's the health emergency around the flu?''</p>
        <p>Also yesterday, West Nile virus was discovered in Boston, the first time the disease was found outside the New York metropolitan region since it surfaced last year. The 1999 outbreak, which began in northern Queens, was the first appearance of West Nile in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts health officials said the virus caused the death of a crow found in a park in Jamaica Plain, a neighborhood in southwest Boston. Dr. Ralph J. Timperi, director of the State Laboratory Institute at the Massachusetts Department of Health, said it was unclear whether the bird had come from another state or was infected in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Officials have been testing sick birds for several months, and after finding the virus in the crow, they said they would begin spraying larvicide in the area to kill mosquito eggs and would intensify their surveillance and monitor hospitals to check for reports of symptoms of the virus.</p>
        <p>Most often, infection with West Nile virus in people leads to a mild illness that feels like influenza. But the virus can also cause encephalitis, a deadly swelling of the brain, with symptoms including severe headache, high fever, stiff neck, confusion, loss of consciousness and muscle weakness. Those most at risk are the elderly, those with weak immune systems, and children under 5.</p>
        <p>New York City health officials said yesterday that, weather permitting, they would conduct ground spraying in Manhattan and Roosevelt Island from midnight tonight to 5 a.m. tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The rain forced Suffolk County, where the West Nile virus was confirmed late Tuesday in three mosquito samples, to cancel spraying planned for last night in Ocean Park, Summer Club and Davis Park. The spraying was rescheduled for later today and was expanded to include three areas in and around Babylon, where the virus was detected in mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Spraying was also scheduled in Westchester and Rockland Counties for the next few days.</p>
        <p>Nassau County, where the virus has been found in birds but not in mosquitoes, has held off on spraying.  Officials there said that while they had stepped up their surveillance  along the border of the two counties, they did not think spraying was necessary because they had not found infected mosquitoes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
