<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buchanan's Opponents Steel For Tough Convention Fight</title>
    <meta content="Y07REF$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Patrick J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagelin, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perot, H Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D7133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buchanan's Opponents Steel For Tough Convention Fight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Months of bickering and conflict are expected to reach climax at upcoming national convention of Reform Party in Long Beach, Calif, to nominate presidential candidate; four-day meeting promises sharp skirmishes as delegates choose between Patrick K Buchanan and John Hagelin for party's nomination and $12.6 million in federal campaign funds that goes with it; party has moved into such contentious terrain that founder Ross Perot has made no plans to attend; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Months of bickering and conflict are expected to reach a climax of sorts this week, when the Reform Party gathers to nominate a presidential candidate at its national convention in Long Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>Unlike the tame and carefully planned Republican convention that anointed Gov. George W. Bush of Texas on Thursday, the four-day meeting of Reform Party members promises some sharp skirmishes as the delegates choose between Patrick J. Buchanan and John Hagelin for the party's nomination and the $12.6 million in federal campaign funds that goes with it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Months of bickering and conflict are expected to reach a climax of sorts this week, when the Reform Party gathers to nominate a presidential candidate at its national convention in Long Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>Unlike the tame and carefully planned Republican convention that anointed Gov. George W. Bush of Texas on Thursday, the four-day meeting of Reform Party members promises some sharp skirmishes as the delegates choose between Patrick J. Buchanan and John Hagelin for the party's nomination and the $12.6 million in federal campaign funds that goes with it.</p>
        <p>The party has moved into such contentious terrain that Ross Perot, the party founder and two-time presidential candidate, has had virtually nothing to do with it since the 1996 election. So far as anyone can tell, he has made no plans to attend the convention.</p>
        <p>''This is a war over the direction of the Reform Party,'' said Russell J. Verney, the party's former chairman and a leading force against Mr. Buchanan.</p>
        <p>Leaders on both sides of a dispute over Mr. Buchanan's candidacy agree that what happens in Long Beach will go a long way toward defining the Reform Party's future: determining whether it will be a party that focuses on governmental reform, as envisioned by Mr. Perot, or, if Mr. Buchanan wins the nomination, on the conservative positions he has championed for years, like opposition to abortion, affirmative action, illegal immigration and homosexuality. That Mr. Buchanan has made those issues the hallmark of his presidential campaign represents the party's major source of conflict.</p>
        <p>While the party under Mr. Perot was always silent on those issues, Mr. Buchanan has brought them to the fore, as he did again on Sunday in a round of morning talk shows, offering further evidence to his opponents that he intends to transform the Reform Party into a haven for social conservatives and disaffected right-wing Republicans.</p>
        <p>Criticizing the Republican Party for excluding conservatives at its nominating convention last week, Mr. Buchanan said on the CBS News program ''Face the Nation'': ''There wasn't a single voice up there for the unborn. There was nobody that got up and spoke about right to life.''</p>
        <p>Referring to Gen. Colin L. Powell, the former chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and a major speaker at the Republican convention, Mr. Buchanan said on the ABC News program ''This Week'': ''Affirmative action, quotas, racial preferences are wrong. They're unjust discrimination against white folks because of the color of their skin or where their ancestors came from, and I don't care if General Powell gets up and says they're right. For heaven's sakes, why did not a single Republican get up and say, 'That is wrong?' ''</p>
        <p>After a lifetime as a Republican, Mr. Buchanan joined the Reform Party last year and set off to re-energize it by recruiting voters and party organizers. His plan worked. But the stronger his forces became, the more he worried longtime party members, especially Perot supporters, who feared their founding principles would be ignored. Indeed, on several programs yesterday, Mr. Buchanan accused his opponents of trying to destroy the party by blocking his efforts and ''simply mixing the Kool-Aid for the party,'' as he said on CBS.</p>
        <p>The feuding factions will not even wait until the official start of the convention, on Thursday, to open fire.</p>
        <p>Instead, it all starts Tuesday morning, when the party's national committee -- 3 people from every state and the District of Columbia, plus the 11 members of the executive committee -- meets to consider challenges over who has the right to serve on the committee.</p>
        <p>The Buchanan campaign, which called for the meeting, has challenged as many as 30 people, the seating of whom would have a huge bearing on who wins the nomination. By party rules, most issues need a two-thirds majority on the national committee, although the Buchanan forces contend they need just a simple majority to settle a dispute over who is chairman of the convention credentials committee.</p>
        <p>That is important because if the Buchanan forces prevail, their ally, Frank Reid, the Ohio state chairman, would oversee the convention credential process and play a persuasive role in settling more than 40 convention delegate challenges, the resolution of which affects the seating of hundreds of delegates.</p>
        <p>And here is why that is so important: By party rules, a candidate can ask that the primary vote, which began last month and concludes this week, be set aside so that the delegates, by a two-thirds vote, can choose the party nominee.</p>
        <p>By controlling the delegates, Mr. Buchanan would not have to worry about the possibility that Mr. Hagelin, a quantum physicist who has run for president twice before on the Natural Law Party ticket but has uncertain support within the Reform Party, might win the popular vote.</p>
        <p>The national committee is also scheduled to resolve another pivotal issue: whether a recent vote by the executive committee to disqualify Mr. Buchanan from the primary should stand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagelin has accused the Buchanan campaign of corrupting the primary process by submitting the names of ineligible voters to be sent ballots. A panel was appointed to review the charge, and it asked both campaigns to provide material that proved the legitimacy of the names they submitted.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Buchanan's campaign refused, the panel recommended that he be disqualified, a decision the executive committee affirmed.</p>
        <p>But Buchanan forces asserted that the executive committee vote was improper, sending the dispute before the national committee.</p>
        <p>For all the tension and conflict, Mr. Buchanan seems not to be affected in the least. He has boldly predicted he will win the nomination. On ''Fox News Sunday,'' he said, ''I think you will see at Long Beach the fact that this is a Buchanan party, a conservative party, reform party and populist party, and you will be surprised at the unanimity.''</p>
        <p>One who certainly would be surprised by unanimity is Mr. Hagelin. He said last week that if Mr. Buchanan won the nomination by any spurious means, he would sue him.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
