<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As magazines enter their heftiest season, stunts help reach the overwhelmed reader.</title>
    <meta content="07ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Glamour (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">In Style (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DB133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As magazines enter their heftiest season, stunts help reach the overwhelmed reader.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In Style magazine's September issue will include a detachable mini-magazine bound inside the back cover; Glamour will publish its first stand-alone issue, a 100-page special issue expanding its popular Dos and Don'ts feature; both innovations are attempts to break through the magazine advertising clutter that comes each September; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REVERSE-BOUND pullout and a stand-alone sound like stunts that gymnasts will attempt next month as they compete for medals at the Summer Games. Well, those stunts are planned for September, but look for them from magazine publishers in America rather than Olympic athletes in Australia.</p>
        <p>Each September, many magazines publish what are their largest issues, fattened by advertisements for new car models and clothes as well as promotions pegged to the coming school year and football season. The more ad pages that appear, the more advertisers strive to be heard above the din. The result: an increase in nontraditional print ads that fold out, up or down; come with Post-It Notes or perforations; and require special devices like 3-D glasses or bar code scanners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REVERSE-BOUND pullout and a stand-alone sound like stunts that gymnasts will attempt next month as they compete for medals at the Summer Games. Well, those stunts are planned for September, but look for them from magazine publishers in America rather than Olympic athletes in Australia.</p>
        <p>Each September, many magazines publish what are their largest issues, fattened by advertisements for new car models and clothes as well as promotions pegged to the coming school year and football season. The more ad pages that appear, the more advertisers strive to be heard above the din. The result: an increase in nontraditional print ads that fold out, up or down; come with Post-It Notes or perforations; and require special devices like 3-D glasses or bar code scanners.</p>
        <p>''Clutter begets clutter,'' said Charlie Rutman, executive vice president and managing director at Carat USA in New York, a media agency owned by the Aegis Group.</p>
        <p>''For the people who want to win the game, there are two ways to do it,'' Mr. Rutman asserted. ''Either spend more, and create even more clutter, or try and be innovative, unusual, impactful, which gets you beyond the clutter.''</p>
        <p>Two large magazines based in New York -- In Style, part of the Time Inc. unit of Time Warner, and Glamour, part of the Conde Nast Publications unit of Advance Publications -- are taking new steps to help advertisers catch the attention of readers.</p>
        <p>In Style will include in its September issue, due out on Aug. 25, a mini-magazine dubbed a reverse-bound pullout because it will be bound inside the back cover and can be detached to be read separately. The pullout will be composed of 18 editorial pages and 18 ad pages; the September issue is to run 704 pages, including about 435 ad pages.</p>
        <p>The Jones New York clothing line will solely sponsor the pullout, titled the In Style Going Out Guide.</p>
        <p>And Glamour will publish on Aug. 15 its first stand-alone issue, which will be sponsored by three advertisers: Revlon, the Sara Lee Corporation and the Zale Corporation.</p>
        <p>The 100-page special issue, expanding a popular monthly Glamour feature known as ''Dos and Don'ts,'' will be sold separately from the regular September issue, at a cover price of $3.50.</p>
        <p>The inspiration for the pullout was ''word from our readers, and advertisers, that people are tearing pages of the magazine out and shopping from them,'' said Louis Cona, publisher of In Style.</p>
        <p>''When I was on an airplane in the spring flying back from Milan, I saw a pullout in Wallpaper,'' he added, referring to a youthful home and life style magazine published in Britain by the Time Life Entertainment Group unit of Time Warner, which devoted its reverse-bound mini-magazine to remodeling bathrooms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cona said he believed that such a supplement ''had never been done in the U.S. before, but there is a big demand for being unique, for standing out.''</p>
        <p>At Revlon, Cheryl Vitali, executive vice president for Revlon global marketing in New York, said: ''We evaluate many, many opportunities and pass on a lot of them. We were intrigued by this one because it's a smart idea and we hope we'll get to benefit from that. We like the content; it has value, versus something that's a throwaway.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, both Glamour and In Style placed their projects under the supervision of the editorial departments rather than the advertising departments. That means the contents are composed of articles, not so-called ''advertorial'' copy.</p>
        <p>''We haven't been big on advertorials; we've probably done just two or three,'' Mr. Cona said, adding: ''I think they confuse the reader. Advertisers should take advantage of the power of the editorial.''</p>
        <p>That was the motivation for Jones New York to participate, said Benny Lin, senior vice president and creative director at the parent, the Jones Apparel Group in New York.</p>
        <p>While Jones is ''always open to new ideas to set us apart and raise our brand awareness, we're very selective,'' Mr. Lin said. ''The magazines we partner with need to have good integrity.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Cona told Mr. Rutman at Carat USA about the supplement, Mr. Rutman recommended it to Mr. Lin, who approved it. The sponsorship cost an estimated $1 million.</p>
        <p>The three advertisers for the Glamour ''Dos and Don'ts'' issue are paying a sum estimated at just more than $1 million for their sponsorships. Besides their ad pages, they will also sponsor a consumer sweepstakes, a fund-raiser for Goodwill Industries and a clothing drive, ''Donate Your Don'ts,'' at offices of ad agencies, Conde Nast, Revlon and Sara Lee.</p>
        <p>Conde Nast will print 600,000 copies of the special Glamour, compared with a circulation of 2.1 million for a regular September issue. In Style is printing about 2.3 million copies of its September issue into which the pullout will be reverse-bound. Jones New York will distribute additional copies of the pullout to retailers to give to shoppers.</p>
        <p>In Style is already planning a second reverse-bound pullout, Mr. Cona said, to appear in the fall; a retailer will be the likely sponsor, he added.</p>
        <p>Deborah Fine, publisher of Glamour, said she anticipated bringing out two standalone ''Dos and Don'ts'' issues in 2001, increasing that to four a year ''eventually.''</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
