<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving Online Audiences News They Want</title>
    <meta content="07TUBE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FeedRoom (Web Site)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yahoo Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zatso.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jagfn.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFDC133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving Online Audiences News They Want</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Web sites offer users television-style news reports in digestible bits that can be pieced together into personalized newscasts; are based on assumptions that consumers want information and entertainment on demand and that high-speed Internet connections, offered by broadband services, can finally give it to them; Yahoo, Zatso.com and Jagfn.com offer services, but the most ambitious is FeedRoom, which Jonathan Klein is setting up with $35 million in venture capital; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is how Jonathan Klein, a former high-level executive at CBS, sees the future of news:</p>
        <p>Viewers will click on video reports they want to see, when they want to see them. Computerized news services will learn users' viewing habits and offer them news bits tailored to their tastes. Advertisers will aim at  viewers based on their supposed news preferences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is how Jonathan Klein, a former high-level executive at CBS, sees the future of news:</p>
        <p>Viewers will click on video reports they want to see, when they want to see them. Computerized news services will learn users' viewing habits and offer them news bits tailored to their tastes. Advertisers will aim at  viewers based on their supposed news preferences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein is so sure that his vision of the future is accurate that he is staking $35 million in venture capital on a new Web site, FeedRoom, which is to make its public debut later this month.</p>
        <p>FeedRoom is one of a handful of new Web sites offering users television-style news reports on the Internet, in digestible bits that can be put together into personalized newscasts. Yahoo has a similar offering, as does Zatso.com, a new company from San Francisco. Another site, called Jagfn.com, posts video reports about financial news.</p>
        <p>These services are based on the new-media assumptions that consumers want information and entertainment on demand and that high-speed Internet connections, offered by broadband services, can finally give it to them.</p>
        <p>''If you want to watch good news, you'll watch good news; if you like to watch crime news, you'll watch crime news,'' said Mr. Klein, who was executive vice president of CBS News from 1995 to 1998. ''It's putting the clicker in the viewer's hand and saying, 'You decide.' ''</p>
        <p>Sometime in the not too distant future, Mr. Klein predicts, this new style of newscast will replace the traditional news fare of the major networks and local TV stations.</p>
        <p>Whether that prediction is an accurate one and whether it would be a step forward or back for journalism are matters of heavy debate in the television news industry, which is struggling to hang on to viewers amid increased competition.</p>
        <p>And even if Mr. Klein is right,  analysts say, it is not clear that sites like his would be well received by people not yet accustomed to watching anything resembling TV on computers that, for the most part, have poor pictures and make for uncomfortable viewing.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Mr. Klein's news service is among the most ambitious attempts yet to recreate a television news experience on the Internet. Though the concept has been around for a while, it has been slow to take off because of inadequacies in Internet technology.</p>
        <p>And the more established news providers have been hesitant. They are waiting to see which business models will survive and how viewing habits will develop, once more people have broadband, or high-speed, Internet connections.</p>
        <p>FeedRoom, which will require users to have broadband connections, is meant to be user friendly, with a central video window occupying one-quarter of the computer screen (currently, video windows occupy only about one-sixteenth). The main window is flanked by smaller ones advertising the available reports. A separate box offers viewers links to different types of reports under categories like health, entertainment, finance and sports.</p>
        <p>The reports will be provided by local stations around the country that have struck deals to provide  video to FeedRoom, which in return will share advertising revenue and design the stations' individual Web pages. Last week, Mr. Klein announced two such agreements with the NBC television station group and Tribune Broadcasting.</p>
        <p>What stops these major media companies from doing it themselves?</p>
        <p>''We still have a very large, successful broadcast business that we have to continue to run and grow,'' said Jay Ireland, president of the NBC station group. ''These guys had a combination that proved very valuable, and it gets us out there quicker.''</p>
        <p>With the NBC and Tribune deals in place, FeedRoom now has ties to 32 TV stations that reach 45 percent of the country's television markets. Mr. Klein said he hoped to complete similar deals with other big television networks by the end of the year. Although no major advertiser is signed yet, he said he had enough financing -- from investors like Warburg Pincus, Ridgewood Capital and Intel -- to operate for two years without ad revenue.</p>
        <p>But FeedRoom is designed with advertisers well in mind, and Mr. Klein said he expected to close some deals soon. The site is equipped with software that can identify users and, based on what segments they tend to select, aim specific banner ads at them. The system is also programmed to give on-screen prominence to the types of segments an  individual viewer tends to choose.</p>
        <p>The automatic winnowing is worrisome to many journalists and media experts, who fear that the proliferation of personalized news would enable viewers to filter out information that is important but may not be sizzling entertainment.</p>
        <p>''The business model might do a very good job of supporting narrow content for things like sports or business or health,'' said John V. Pavlik, executive director of Columbia University's Center for New Media. ''But I'm not so confident that the business model will support public affairs journalism. Who, exactly, is going to be the sponsor for that type of news?''</p>
        <p>Some network news executives said last week that they shared that concern, especially in light of the low TV ratings for last week's Republican convention.</p>
        <p>''It has potentially enormous implications for not only how we do our business, but also for our democracy,'' said Andrew Heyward, president of CBS News.</p>
        <p>But while ''it has implications for the citizenry that might be disturbing, that doesn't mean you can stop it,'' he added. ''This is where the technology is heading.''</p>
        <p>For now, big-network news executives like Mr. Heyward seem satisfied to sit back and monitor expensive experiments like Mr. Klein's.  ''The FeedRoom is one of what are going to be numerous experiments in the early days of broadband,'' Mr. Heyward said. ''No one knows which is going to prevail.''</p>
        <p>Analysts have little research on which to base forecasts because of the embryonic state of broadband Internet access -- whose 31 million users so far are mostly office workers and college students, according FeedRoom's research.</p>
        <p>But that does not stop analysts from debating whether computer users are ready for personalized, TV-style, online newscasts.</p>
        <p>''It's really hard to do broadband video right now,'' said David Card, a media analyst with Jupiter Communications. ''Point one: There aren't a lot of people who have broadband. Point two: Even in broadband, it's not a beautiful experience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein acknowledged the challenges. ''It's an enormous risk,'' he said. ''But the rewards are enormous if this thing works.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
