<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judah Got Last Punch and Last Word</title>
    <meta content="Y07FIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Judah, Zab</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Millett, Terronn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DA133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judah Got Last Punch and Last Word</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <dateline>UNCASVILLE, Conn., Aug. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zab Judah scores 4th-round technical knockout over Terronn Millett to retain International Boxing Federation junior-welterweight title; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After his impressive victory on Saturday night, Zab Judah still wanted the last word.</p>
        <p>At the postfight news conference, Judah had two questions for his beaten opponent, Terronn Millett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After his impressive victory on Saturday night, Zab Judah still wanted the last word.</p>
        <p>At the postfight news conference, Judah had two questions for his beaten opponent, Terronn Millett.</p>
        <p>''Do I have speed?'' Judah said.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' Millett replied.</p>
        <p>''Can I punch?'' Judah said.</p>
        <p>''Yes, you can crack too,'' Millett answered.</p>
        <p>Millett found out about Judah's power and speed the hard way at the Mohegan Sun Casino. Knocking down Millett twice in the second round and once in the fourth, Judah, a Brooklyn native, won by a technical knockout at 2 minutes 47 seconds of the fourth round to keep the International Boxing Federation's junior-welterweight championship. At age 22 and undefeated (24 victories and 18 knockouts), Judah gave further evidence that he is one of boxing's rising young stars.</p>
        <p>Millett (22-2-1) is a 32-year-old former champion, a veteran fighter who hoped to teach Judah a lesson. Instead, Judah dominated the fight with his hand speed, movement and confidence. Judah remained unbeaten, and his confidence remained untouched.</p>
        <p>''I don't want credit above and beyond other fighters, but I want my due,'' Judah said. ''I trained hard for this fight. I was ready.''</p>
        <p>Judah took control in the second round, knocking down Millett with a hard left to the chin. Millett got off the canvas, but he was clearly hurt. Judah continued on the offensive and after taking a series of blows, Millett went down again.</p>
        <p>Millett survived the round, as well as Round 3, but the fight ended in the fourth round. Setting up Millett beautifully and scoring with combinations, Judah connected with a left hand that sent Millett stumbling and then onto the canvas near the ropes. Millett rose at the count of four, but Referee Michael Ortega looked into Millett's eyes and saw a fighter in trouble. Ortega waved his arms ending the bout, and Judah began celebrating.</p>
        <p>It was not a victory without incident, however. Millett knocked down Judah in the first round, catching him off guard with a sharp and powerful left hand to the body. Judah looked more embarrassed than hurt, but he was also knocked down in February when he won the title from Jan Bergman. Questions may be raised about Judah's defensive ability, but Judah insisted he was knocked down only because he was intent on being the aggressor.</p>
        <p>''A lot of fighters run, but I'm not afraid to put it on the line,'' Judah said. ''He caught me with a hook out of nowhere. I didn't see it.''</p>
        <p>But that was the last problem Judah had on Saturday night. And with Millett vanquished, Judah will turn his attention to bigger and better fights. Judah seems headed toward a showdown with Kostya Tszyu to determine who is the best in their 140-pound division. But do not look for a fight between Judah and Tszyu until at least next year. ''I think Zab will take one or two more fights first,'' said Shelly Finkel, Judah's co-manager. ''We're going to build up to that fight, because if Zab beats Tszyu, there's not really any place else for Zab to go in that division.''</p>
        <p>But Judah's career seems headed for stardom. He rarely takes more than a few weeks off, and he is improving as he gains more experience. With three victories already this year, Judah has been both busy and successful. And for a change he talked about taking a break.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to the Bahamas,'' Judah said. ''I need a vacation.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
