<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bits of History Are Stolen From San Antonio Missions</title>
    <meta content="Y07STA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mission San Juan Capistrano (San Antonio)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Calvin, James (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capistrano, Giovanni de</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D8133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bits of History Are Stolen From San Antonio Missions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thieves break into 300-year-old Mission San Juan Capistrano in San Antonio, Tex, and take three hand-carved 18th-century statues from altar, including one dating to 1731 that depicts mission's namesake, Giovanni de Capistrano; pastor, Rev James Calvin, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Someone is stealing pieces of this city's past, and whatever the motives, the thefts have stunned local church officials, stumped the police and saddened heritage-conscious people.</p>
        <p>Between midnight and dawn on Tuesday, thieves broke into the 300-year-old Mission San Juan Capistrano near here and stole three hand-carved 18th-century statues from the church's altar, including one dating to 1731 that depicts the mission's namesake, Giovanni de Capistrano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Someone is stealing pieces of this city's past, and whatever the motives, the thefts have stunned local church officials, stumped the police and saddened heritage-conscious people.</p>
        <p>Between midnight and dawn on Tuesday, thieves broke into the 300-year-old Mission San Juan Capistrano near here and stole three hand-carved 18th-century statues from the church's altar, including one dating to 1731 that depicts the mission's namesake, Giovanni de Capistrano.</p>
        <p>''This is somebody who knew exactly what they were doing,'' said the Rev. James Galvin, the mission's pastor. ''They studied the church's routines, they brought their own equipment to enter the building and hoist out the statues. This was not a casual thing, but very well planned.''</p>
        <p>It was the fourth theft from one of San Antonio's five Spanish missions since June, when a two-foot-tall statue of the Virgin Mary disappeared from the nation's oldest church, Mission Conception. Later that month, an antique thurible, an incense-burning device, was taken from the same church. Four paintings on wood of Our Lady of Guadalupe were chiseled from their frames at San Juan Capistrano last month.</p>
        <p>''We've obviously got a pattern here,'' said Msgr. Larry Stuebben, the vicar general of the Roman Catholic archdiocese. ''Someone is targeting the missions, and the entire city feels as if we've been punched in the stomach.</p>
        <p>''There are people living around those missions whose families have lived there for 250 years,'' he said. ''The symbolic presence of those churches and those artifacts in their midst is a very important thing. Generations have grown up among these things, and when they are taken, it seems as if nothing is sacred.''</p>
        <p>Even in a city like this, where legends seem to inhabit every street corner, the Spanish missions have always held a special status.</p>
        <p>In equal parts forts, churches and social centers in the early 1700's, they rest today like a string of faded Old World pearls on a 23-mile Mission Trail that meanders along the banks of the San Antonio River into downtown, ending at the most famous mission of all, San Antonio de Valero, better known as the Alamo.</p>
        <p>''The missions are also national parks,'' Monsignor Stuebben said. ''It would be as if someone chipped the nose off one of the presidents on Mount Rushmore. They are seen as part of the heritage and life of the whole community, not just the Catholic community, and that just adds another awful element to the whole tragic thing.''</p>
        <p>Officials of the National Park Service said that although they operate information booths at the missions during the day, the properties are owned by the Catholic Church, which is responsible for security at the sites.</p>
        <p>But Monsignor Stuebben said: ''Just keeping the buildings up is an enormous expense. We can't afford to provide around-the-clock security.''</p>
        <p>Until now, church officials had kept silent about the robberies, fearing that more attention would encourage copycat thefts. But after Tuesday's loss, Monsignor Stuebben said it was decided to go public to prevent the sale of the artifacts in the international art market, although he would not speculate on their monetary value.</p>
        <p>''These are not sculpted by Michelangelo or anyone famous, and they are not intrinsically valuable as art,'' he said. ''Their value is in their history and their importance to the people of the missions. What is 300 years of tradition and culture worth?''</p>
        <p>Gregoria Gaitan, 72, who says her family members have been parishioners at Mission San Juan Capistrano for centuries, believes money may not have been the object of the thefts.</p>
        <p>''It has to go deeper than that,'' she said. ''This is someone who was out to hurt the church. This is a poor church, not a rich one. The statues are much more valuable to the people as history than anything that someone could buy.''</p>
        <p>Ernest Gaigenmillar, a member of the church for more than 50 years, agreed. ''It's sickening. These statues aren't worth much money; it's just a way of striking out at the people in the church,'' he said, although he could offer no explanation for why someone would do so.</p>
        <p>''Who can figure the mind of someone who would steal from a church?'' Mr. Gaigenmillar said.</p>
        <p>Sandy Gutierrez, a spokeswoman for the San Antonio Police Department, said the police were investigating but had no suspects.</p>
        <p>Most church members and officials seem resigned to their loss, and shaken by what the thefts say about contemporary society.</p>
        <p>''It makes me sad that people do these things,'' Father Galvin said. ''The statues belong to the people. They are history itself. Someone is taking lovely art out of people's lives, art that everyone should be able to enjoy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
