<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Where Fans Flock And Dollars Fly</title>
    <meta content="07CHAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DF103CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Where Fans Flock And Dollars Fly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass Sports of The Times article on George Steinbrenner's dismay at high attendance at Yankee Stadium that thwarts his bid for new stadium and at prospect of sharing New York Yankees revenues with small-market baseball teams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRAPPED in the Bronx, or thoughts from the deepest, darkest recesses of George Steinbrenner's mind:</p>
        <p>I just can't believe what's happening. What's wrong with these people? I tried for years to warn them of the dangers of coming to Yankee Stadium, and for years they heeded my warnings. Remember 1996? I did some of my best work that year. We won the World Series, but we had only two and a quarter million fans come to the old ball yard in the Bronx. It was no coincidence that it was during that year that my friend the mayor released a report recommending the construction of a new park on the West Side of Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRAPPED in the Bronx, or thoughts from the deepest, darkest recesses of George Steinbrenner's mind:</p>
        <p>I just can't believe what's happening. What's wrong with these people? I tried for years to warn them of the dangers of coming to Yankee Stadium, and for years they heeded my warnings. Remember 1996? I did some of my best work that year. We won the World Series, but we had only two and a quarter million fans come to the old ball yard in the Bronx. It was no coincidence that it was during that year that my friend the mayor released a report recommending the construction of a new park on the West Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>I have only myself to blame. I dragged my feet and didn't let Rudy know what I wanted to do. I kept saying I'd announce my decision after the season. I just never said what season. I never said I'd take Manhattan, forget the Bronx and Staten Island, too. If I had, maybe I wouldn't be in this quandary. Look at what has happened.</p>
        <p>Another crowd of 50,000-plus showed up at the Stadium yesterday for the game with Seattle that we played so badly I should have offered them tickets for another game. That makes 11 crowds of 50,000 or more in the first 53 home dates, four more than last year for the same number of dates. (I don't keep these things in my head; I just tell my P.R. people to get me the information and they jump.)</p>
        <p>For the first time in Yankees history, not just my history but the Yankees' entire history, we are averaging 41,000 fans a game. If we just maintain that average -- and I'm afraid we're going to exceed it as we get closer to another championship -- we'll finish with a total attendance of 3.32 million. Last year we reached three million for the first time, and we would break that record.</p>
        <p>So how on earth am I supposed to convince anyone that we need a new park? Why would the city and the state be willing to spend a billion dollars or more on a new park when we're doing better than ever at the old one? Not just better than ever, really, better than anyone would have ever expected.</p>
        <p>We got too good for our own good. We are a prisoner of our own success. In the mid-70's we went to the World Series three years in a row and won two in a row, and in those three seasons we had a total of 6.44 million fans. We'll have more than that just for this season and last.</p>
        <p>We have become too attractive. The fans find us too irresistible. We're like a human magnet that is pulling people into the Bronx despite the dangers. At this point, we probably couldn't even justify renovating Yankee Stadium for three-quarters of a billion. That's what the 1996 study said it would cost. Today it would probably cost closer to a billion. Rudy's a lame duck. He probably couldn't even push that plan through.</p>
        <p>My luxury boxes, will I ever get my luxury boxes? Baltimore, Cleveland, Seattle and Detroit have luxury boxes. Colorado, San Francisco, Houston and Arizona have luxury boxes. For heaven's sake, Pittsburgh and Milwaukee are going to have luxury boxes. And George Steinbrenner isn't going to get luxury boxes. I get the Grand Concourse that hasn't been grand for 50 years.</p>
        <p>But now that I'm thinking about this, maybe I should forget about it. Who needs a new park with luxury boxes if those other, incompetent owners are going to take my money? Yeah, remember that blue-ribbon report? Those guys want to take half of my local revenue and give it away. They want to play Robin Hood and rob me of my hard-earned money and give it to the poor.</p>
        <p>I can just see my good friend Bud wearing green tights and riding from place to place dropping off bags of my money. One for the Expos and one for the Twins and one for this team that never wins.</p>
        <p>This year they're going to take about $25 million from me and spread it around to those so-called small-market clubs. Right. When did the Angels and the Phillies become small-market clubs? Next thing you know, they'll be giving some of it to the Mets, too.</p>
        <p>Who needs to generate more revenue just to give it away? If I want to give money to charity, I can send a check to the Little Sisters of the Poor. It'll cost me a lot less.</p>
        <p>That report said we already have the most local revenue --  $650 million for the past five years, it said. With our local television money going up in a new deal, way up -- I have to be careful and not talk out loud about it because we've been sued over it -- our total local revenue will go up. So we will already be giving away more of my money. Why should I sweat out construction of a new park or renovation of the one we have just so those greedy guys can get their hands deeper into my pockets?</p>
        <p>I have no intention of operating the George Steinbrenner Foundation for Wayward Baseball Teams. I gotta call Rudy in the morning and tell him I've made my decision. No more procrastinating, no more fence-sitting. Rudy, we're not going anywhere. But you better reserve your seats for the rest of the season. They're flocking to the Stadium. What a wonderful place to see a ballgame.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
