<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cultural Barriers Hinder Education of Asian-Americans About AIDS</title>
    <meta content="07AIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0D6133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cultural Barriers Hinder Education of Asian-Americans About AIDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Community groups are working to educate Asian-Americans, particularly recent immigrants, about prevention of treatment of HIV and AIDS; task is particularly hard because of wide range of languages involved and cultural beliefs that discourage talk about sex and death, let alone sexually-transmitted diseases; lack of knowledge about HIV is of particular concern in New York, which has highest number of Asian-Americans with AIDS of any metropolitan area in nation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The diversity of cultures and languages among Asian-Americans may cause headaches for schoolteachers and census takers, but rarely does it affect matters of life and death.</p>
        <p>One glaring exception is in the prevention and treatment of H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The diversity of cultures and languages among Asian-Americans may cause headaches for schoolteachers and census takers, but rarely does it affect matters of life and death.</p>
        <p>One glaring exception is in the prevention and treatment of H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
        <p>The efforts needed to educate Asian-Americans, especially recent immigrants, about the disease are greater than for any other ethnic group, say scholars and outreach workers. That is because of the variety of languages spoken and because of cultural beliefs that discourage discussion about sex and death, let alone about sexually transmitted diseases.</p>
        <p>''It seems that they are years and years behind in terms of how the illness is treated and the social perceptions of the illness,'' said Dr. Ezer Kang, a clinical psychologist at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center who is studying H.I.V.-positive Asian-Americans. ''There's a lack of acceptance and lack of awareness of H.I.V. in the general community.''</p>
        <p>Public health agencies have not been very effective in directly tackling these problems, and the task has been left to community groups, said Dr. Kang and other experts. For example, two groups were passing out fliers and condoms at a Chinatown street fair yesterday.</p>
        <p>The lack of knowledge about H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, among many recent Asian immigrants is a problem nationwide, but is of particular concern in New York, which has the highest number of Asian-Americans with AIDS of any metropolitan region in the country, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. At the end of 1997, the latest year for which information is available, they accounted for 306 out of 39,625 people with AIDS in New York. (Outreach workers say that number is an undercount because many Asian-Americans with AIDS never report it.)</p>
        <p>Recent studies also show that as an ethnic group, Asian-Americans have the highest rate of late intervention, meaning that patients are already infected with an AIDS-related disease by the time they get a diagnosis. The latest study, released in February by the New York City Department of Health, shows that of a sample of 118 people made up mostly of Asian-Americans and a few Native Americans with AIDS in 1997 and 1998, 44 percent were cases of late intervention. That is in contrast to 28 percent for blacks, 24 percent for Hispanics and 21 percent for whites.</p>
        <p>The main reasons for that, experts say, are a dearth of materials about the disease in Asian languages, an unfamiliarity on the part of public health agencies with Asian cultures, and cultural beliefs that may hinder an understanding of H.I.V.</p>
        <p>Kevin Huang, 31, of Brooklyn, ran into that problem with his father. ''When I told him I had AIDS, and I told him I was gay at the same time, he said, 'Well, what is that?' '' Mr. Huang said. ''I was very angry. We still really don't talk about it much.''</p>
        <p>To some extent, federal and local governments have recognized the need for outreach, and have given funds to most of the half-dozen or so community groups in the city that provide services to Asian-Americans. Those groups in turn have found a need to employ an array of strategies that can be as simple as handing out multilingual fliers at street fairs or as offbeat as giving away condoms stuffed in red ''lucky money'' envelopes popular with Chinese-Americans.</p>
        <p>A top priority is to make outreach efforts specific to language and culture. To that end, the Asian and Pacific Islander Coalition on H.I.V./ AIDS, known as Apicha, has 75 peer educators fluent in a dozen languages, from Bengali to Tagalog to various Chinese dialects. The group plans to buy multilingual subway advertisements this fall using grant money from the city.</p>
        <p>Other outreach groups have made educational videotapes that show Chinese- and Korean-Americans in dramatized situations dealing with H.I.V. The actors speak in Asian languages, and the situations are set in immigrant neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>But the experts say that merely presenting materials in different languages isn't enough. Each culture has a different attitude toward sex and H.I.V. that has to be addressed individually.</p>
        <p>Thai immigrants, for example, are more receptive to learning about H.I.V. because the high rate of infection in Thailand has led to relatively open discussion, said Prescott Chow, a program director at the Asian and Pacific Islander American Health Forum, based in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>But Catholic Filipino-Americans often shy away from discussing safe sex practices because of church teachings on birth control and on abortion, said Therese Rodriguez, executive director of Apicha.</p>
        <p>One evening last November, Ms. Rodriguez lectured on AIDS to 30 or so Filipino-American leaders gathered in the Filipino consulate in Midtown Manhattan. She said she was stunned by some of their questions: Can you get H.I.V. by kissing infected people? Or sleeping next to them? Or breathing the same air?</p>
        <p>''This is H.I.V. 101, and it's not getting out there,'' Ms. Rodriguez said.</p>
        <p>Many East Asian immigrants come from societies that avoid open talk about AIDS or sex. For years, the Chinese government refused to acknowledge that AIDS existed in China. In Japan, the news media covered the epidemic ''like witch hunting,'' and high school sex education still revolves around ''flowers and pollen metaphors,'' said Yoshiharu Muto, a journalist based in New York who has written about AIDS for a Tokyo newspaper and who heads the Japanese AIDS Workshop Series.</p>
        <p>The workshop is a volunteer group that was founded in 1993 to educate the flood of Japanese expatriates -- most of them businessmen and students -- that arrived in the metropolitan area in the 1980's, Mr. Muto said.</p>
        <p>The group held a monthly lecture series that was advertised through fliers and Japanese-language newspapers. Up to three dozen people showed up each time, mostly students, social workers and housewives. But Mr. Muto said he was disappointed that only a handful of businessmen attended the lectures.</p>
        <p>Apicha has taken a different strategy to reach South Asians. The group has found that private meetings work better than public lectures with them, said Faraz Ahmed, a Pakistani-American outreach worker.</p>
        <p>Educators talk about H.I.V. at house parties, and Mr. Ahmed rides around in taxis to teach drivers. Those cabbies who take customers to sex establishments can pass on the information, he said.</p>
        <p>Outreach to Chinese immigrants often takes place in dense neighborhoods like Chinatown or Sunset Park, where H.I.V.-positive people often hide their condition because they fear being ostracized, Dr. Kang said.</p>
        <p>Apicha set up two tables yesterday at a Chinatown street fair. One woman was furiously stuffing condoms into red ''lucky money'' envelopes, while a man was handing out fliers to passers-by. A few teenagers took the pamphlets, but most of the older people walked away.</p>
        <p>''It's what we expected,'' said Nadia Islam, an outreach worker. ''I told all our volunteers that they might have a tough time, but you have to be persistent.''</p>
        <p>The Chinese-American Planning Council has begun a program to educate prostitutes in Chinatown. Many came from China or Southeast Asian countries with no intention of becoming prostitutes, but now work out of massage parlors or apartments to pay debts, said ManChui Leung, an outreach director at the planning council. The peer educators often talk to the women one on one in their homes or where they work and accompany them to be tested for H.I.V.</p>
        <p>''It's been a very successful program for us, but tough, because a lot of people are undocumented,'' Ms. Leung said. ''It's tough dealing with the police, and with a lot of the businesses shutting down and opening up.''</p>
        <p>Reaching out to church congregations can be just as difficult. Religious beliefs -- from Islam to Catholicism -- often play a large role in the silence surrounding sex. In Korean- and Chinese-American communities, Christian churches would be ideal places for H.I.V. and AIDS outreach because they often draw recent immigrants, but ministers rarely allow sex education in their houses of worship, Ms. Leung said.</p>
        <p>Seongho Kim at Korean Community Services said many ministers had rejected his offer to set up H.I.V. lectures. In January, the youth director of a church in Flushing agreed, but the minister balked.</p>
        <p>One workshop did give Mr. Kim a glimmer of hope, though. Last year, the Korean Youth Center in Flushing invited him and his colleagues to talk to more than a dozen youth ministers, most in their 20's. They met several times during the year.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Kim and many health educators, their greatest hope is that a new generation -- liberated from the cultural beliefs that their more traditional parents hold -- can accept and pass on these lessons about sex, life and death.</p>
        <p>''I want them to grow healthy both mentally and physically,'' Mr. Kim said. ''At the same time, I want them to keep their own culture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
