<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Daley's Hand, Gore Aides See a Glass Half Full</title>
    <meta content="07GORE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CAMPAIGN CHAIRMAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, William M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2DE103CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Daley's Hand, Gore Aides See a Glass Half Full</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>NASHVILLE, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former commerce secretary William M Daley has significantly revived once flagging morale of Democratic campaign six weeks after taking charge of Vice Pres Al Gore's presidential drive; has curtailed infighting and imposed badly needed discipline on campaign's strategy and message; has freed Gore to focus on essential decisions rather than on power struggles back home, and has reassured Democratic partisans that campaign is back on track; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six weeks after taking charge of Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign, William M. Daley has not yet figured out where everybody works in the sprawling and frenetic Gore headquarters here.</p>
        <p>''Um, where's Mark's office?'' he sheepishly asked a young aide one night this week, scrunching his bushy eyebrows as he wandered right past the door to the lair of the deputy campaign manager Mark Fabiani.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six weeks after taking charge of Vice President Al Gore's presidential campaign, William M. Daley has not yet figured out where everybody works in the sprawling and frenetic Gore headquarters here.</p>
        <p>''Um, where's Mark's office?'' he sheepishly asked a young aide one night this week, scrunching his bushy eyebrows as he wandered right past the door to the lair of the deputy campaign manager Mark Fabiani.</p>
        <p>And yet, in his short time here, the former commerce secretary seems to have significantly revived the once flagging morale of the Democratic campaign, both in Nashville and beyond.</p>
        <p>After a spring when the campaign was accused of squandering any momentum created by Mr. Gore's victories in the Democratic primaries, Mr. Daley has moved to curtail the infighting that had sapped the campaign's energy and to impose badly needed discipline on its strategy and message. He has freed Mr. Gore to focus on essential decisions rather than on the power struggles back home, and he has reassured Democratic partisans that the campaign is back on track.</p>
        <p>Top Gore supporters, including Congressional leaders and officials with major constituent groups, say that they have noticed a distinct change since Mr. Daley replaced the ailing Tony Coelho and that they have been soothed by Mr. Daley's straightforward presence.</p>
        <p>''He came and spoke to our caucus last week, and the turnaround in attitude that he brought was very noticeable,'' said Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the minority leader. ''He exuded a confidence about the organization that my colleagues needed and wanted to hear.''</p>
        <p>John J. Sweeney, the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., had initially complained that he had not been consulted about Mr. Gore's appointment of Mr. Daley, who earned the enmity of labor by leading the administration's lobbying for the North American Free Trade Agreement and the normalization of trade relations with China. But after Mr. Daley spent two days this week meeting with labor leaders in Chicago, Mr. Sweeney had nothing but kind words.</p>
        <p>''I think things are moving in the right direction,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''Daley has been working extremely hard on a number of fronts. And certainly I can say he's been meeting with us regularly and making sure that working-family issues are at the center of the campaign.''</p>
        <p>The latest change in the campaign's leadership, its second in barely a year, could have been deeply destabilizing. But as Mr. Gore moves into two critical weeks in which he will select a running mate and accept his party's nomination in Los Angeles, his aides and leading supporters say they feel more optimism than at any point since the vice president swept the primaries.</p>
        <p>''Morale is shockingly high here for a campaign that's 10 points behind,'' one top Gore aide said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's campaign, by almost any standard, had a lousy spring. After the primaries, the campaign drifted for weeks with little sign of a general-election strategy. Mr. Gore allowed Gov. George W. Bush of Texas to cruise unchallenged back to the center after he was forced to the right in the Republican primaries.</p>
        <p>The campaign also manufactured its own crisis when the vice president broke with the White House to maintain that Elian Gonzalez should be given permanent residence status, a move seen as such a craven appeal for Cuban-American votes that it reinforced Mr. Bush's contention that the vice president would say anything for political advantage.</p>
        <p>The campaign experimented constantly with its message and its tone, first attacking Mr. Bush stridently, then backing away. That, too, only seemed to buttress the Republican criticism of Mr. Gore, whose various public transformations inspired Mr. Bush to declare in his acceptance speech at the Republican convention that he was ''not running in borrowed clothes.'' By late spring, Mr. Gore had unwittingly made himself an underdog, consistently trailing in the polls despite his association with the prosperity of the Clinton era.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley, a 51-year-old Chicago native, was not looking for work when Mr. Gore woke him from a deep slumber at 12:15 a.m. on June 15 to tell him that Mr. Coelho, who had led the campaign for a year, was resigning for health reasons. He said he felt he had the best job in government and was content to ride out the Clinton administration in his spacious office in Washington, and on the golf course on weekends.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore, who had spoken to Mr. Daley about leading the campaign a year before, was insistent that he needed his considerable political skills. ''I was out of it, I mean dead sound asleep,'' Mr. Daley said of the phone call. ''I said, 'Well, why don't we get together tomorrow and have a cup of coffee?' And he said, 'Why don't you get up and make a cup of coffee?' '' Forty-five minutes later the deal was sealed, and Mr. Daley immediately began to shed his duties at Commerce. He started full time on July 17, commuting between Washington and Nashville.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley, who is known for his straight talk, acknowledged in an interview this week that the Gore campaign was troubled at the time. ''It's not a secret that there was a period there of internal debate on the thrust of the campaign,'' he said, ''a concern that we had lost some ground from the primaries, that Bush was running a good noncampaign campaign, that his base came home quicker and that we were still working on our base.''</p>
        <p>In addition, the direction of the campaign had become a struggle among distinct power bases: the paid staff, led by Mr. Coelho and Donna Brazile, the campaign manager, who themselves had occasional disputes; Washington consultants like Carter Eskew, Tad Devine, Robert Shrum, Bill Knapp and the pollster Harrison Hickman, some of whom have moved to Nashville; Gore family members, including Mr. Gore's wife, Tipper, his daughter Karenna Gore Schiff and his brother-in-law, Frank Hunger; staff members in the office of the vice president in Washington; and old Gore hands like Peter Knight, Roy Neel, Tom Downey and Jack Quinn, all of whom are now Washington lobbyists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coelho, who resigned after suffering epileptic seizures and intestinal problems, receives mixed reviews from Mr. Gore's aides. He is  almost revered, for having guided Mr. Gore successfully through his primary fight with Bill Bradley and for obsessively pursuing goals like winning the endorsement of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. He and Ms. Brazile made difficult but needed cuts in staff and budget and oversaw last fall's move of the campaign from Washington to Nashville (the headquarters are now in an office park conveniently on Mainstream Drive).</p>
        <p>But despite his long tenure as a congressman from California, Mr. Coelho was never able to become the public face of the campaign, largely because his role as leader of the United States exhibit at a 1998 world exposition in Portugal was the subject of a State Department investigation into suspicions of financial irregularities. And by insisting on tight control of all aspects of the campaign, including access to the candidate, he bred resentment and alienation among many advisers with long relationships with Mr. Gore. For instance, Mr. Quinn, a former Gore chief of staff, said he and other former aides had felt ''underutilized'' during Mr. Coelho's tenure.</p>
        <p>The internal tensions were papered over while Gore aides made common cause of defeating Mr. Bradley. But they re-emerged after the primaries, and all too often the candidate himself was called upon to mediate, Mr. Daley said.</p>
        <p>''I think there was a lot of squirreling around here about the battles, the personality disputes, and I think that sucked him into it a lot,'' Mr. Daley said. ''I think he was having a lot of people call him, you know, nyah, nyah, and you hear this about this one, this about that one, this one's not doing this, nothing's being done, yadda, yadda, yadda. And they were all going around each other to him, and that's not the way it should be. The candidate cannot be made to be put in that position, and I think he was being put in that position by just about everybody here.''</p>
        <p>That has changed, Mr. Daley asserts. ''He's performing much better, because I think he's not burdened by worrying about the campaign as much,'' he said. ''He's doing his thing. He's not the campaign manager. He's not the chief issues person. He's the candidate, and I think he's made that transfer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley's arrival coincided with the unveiling of the campaign's latest message, a double-barreled populist appeal that casts Mr. Gore as the candidate most likely to continue the country's prosperity and Mr. Bush as the captive of powerful interests. Mr. Daley has insisted that the campaign stick with those themes for the last month and has encouraged the kind of dexterity that led Mr. Gore to rip up his schedule one day in July and go to Texas to blame Mr. Bush for that state's fiscal problems.</p>
        <p>''It used to be we couldn't stay on message for a week,'' one senior Gore aide said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fabiani, the campaign's communications director, said Mr. Daley had brought ''an overall direction to the campaign so we can stay on course no matter what happens, rather than being buffeted by events and things beyond our control.'' Mr. Eskew, a top strategist, said Mr. Daley had ''brought some stability and confidence, and those are important in showing the external world that there's a mission and a plan.''</p>
        <p>As a longtime Democratic operative, as well as the son of Chicago's former mayor and the brother of its current one, Mr. Daley has the advantages of vast connections in party politics and an intimate knowledge of the Midwestern states that are expected to be this fall's battlegrounds.</p>
        <p>He has presented the campaign's case in regular television appearances, has become a crucial adviser on convention planning and the vice presidential selection; he is overseeing the expansion of the campaign's paid staff to 300 people from 75.</p>
        <p>He also brought Ronald A. Klain, a former Gore chief of staff, and Monica Dixon, a former deputy chief of staff, to Nashville to invigorate the campaign's rapid response operation (known as ''the kitchen''), a mainstay of the 1992 and 1996 Clinton campaigns. And he has renewed contact with Gore allies who felt shut out, prompting Mr. Quinn to observe that ''he's the sort of guy who leaves no resource unused.''</p>
        <p>In a close election, such things can matter, several Gore aides said.</p>
        <p>''These campaigns are all about the candidates,'' Mr. Quinn said, ''but campaign leadership really does keep people rowing not only in the right direction but rowing together.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CAMPAIGN CHAIRMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
