<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernandez's Tortured Body Language Needs No Translation</title>
    <meta content="07YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5DF103CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernandez's Tortured Body Language Needs No Translation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seattle Mariners defeat New York Yankees, 11-1; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez has a familiar pose whenever a game starts to crumble around him. He slouches his body, pins his right hand on his waist like someone who is impatiently waiting in line for a driver's license and peers out to where another damaging hit has just landed. ''How did that happen?'' El Duque seems to be saying to himself.</p>
        <p>Hernandez struck the pose often on an overcast day at Yankee Stadium yesterday, a day that did not last too long for the sluggish pitcher or for the Yankees. El Duque had not started a game in 24 days, he had difficulty throwing strikes and he wondered why the Seattle Mariners were pummeling the strikes he did throw in coasting to an 11-1 victory. ''How did this happen?'' El Duque surely said to himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez has a familiar pose whenever a game starts to crumble around him. He slouches his body, pins his right hand on his waist like someone who is impatiently waiting in line for a driver's license and peers out to where another damaging hit has just landed. ''How did that happen?'' El Duque seems to be saying to himself.</p>
        <p>Hernandez struck the pose often on an overcast day at Yankee Stadium yesterday, a day that did not last too long for the sluggish pitcher or for the Yankees. El Duque had not started a game in 24 days, he had difficulty throwing strikes and he wondered why the Seattle Mariners were pummeling the strikes he did throw in coasting to an 11-1 victory. ''How did this happen?'' El Duque surely said to himself.</p>
        <p>It happened because the Mariners were patient. They made a rusty Hernandez work deep into counts, and then they treated a pitcher who was considered one of the best in American League in April like an impostor. Hernandez trudged back to the dugout after the fourth inning as if he were walking over land mines, knowing that his long-anticipated return to the rotation ended in an 85-pitch debacle.</p>
        <p>''I think he was very frustrated because, like he does most of the time and like we do, when he goes out there, we expect him to shut down the opposition,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''He wasn't able to do that today.''</p>
        <p>Hernandez was on the disabled list with a sprained right elbow and back spasms, but he did not blame the five earned runs on eight hits and three walks on any physical discomfort. Hernandez had a strong fastball and a decent slider. He simply did not locate his pitches precisely and the Mariners waited, pounced and then rode Paul Abbott's eight excellent innings to the rout.</p>
        <p>''He was trying to battle,'' catcher Jorge Posada said about Hernandez. ''You could see that he was in a battle. He was frustrated with himself. They were laying off some tough pitches, and I think he got frustrated a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Although Torre and Posada both called Hernandez frustrated and although El Duque's body language revealed exasperation, he bristled when he was asked about being frustrated after matching his second-shortest outing of the season. ''I couldn't win and we didn't win,'' Hernandez said through Leo Astacio, his interpreter. ''Frustration is for the weak, and I don't consider myself weak.''</p>
        <p>It was a lost weekend for Hernandez, who returned from rehabilitating in Tampa, Fla., on Friday and immediately created a controversy by asserting that one of the Yankees' coaches supposedly said he was not ''as hurt as much as I thought.'' Torre was upset with Hernandez's charge, which the pitcher tried to minimize by apologizing to the coaches on Saturday.</p>
        <p>''I feel bad for making them feel bad,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, Torre admitted that Hernandez's words would probably not evaporate. Hernandez said it to reporters and, regardless of his retraction, everyone knows what he said after returning from working under Billy Connors, a Yankees vice president and pitching instructor.</p>
        <p>''I think there will always be that little thing out there, that element of question,'' Torre said. ''Sometimes we magnify things. As far as I'm concerned, he has had so much support from everyone here.''</p>
        <p>While Hernandez and Allen Watson were drilled, Abbott used a fastball and a changeup to disarm the Yanks and win for the second time in seven starts. The Yankees began three innings with runners on first and second, but Abbott induced double plays each time. After Bernie Williams homered in the fourth, the Yankees loaded the bases and stranded all three runners. Abbott did not give up a hit in eight at-bats with runners in scoring position.</p>
        <p>''We ran into a buzz saw,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>From the outset, Hernandez never looked comfortable. He wore a blue, long-sleeve shirt on a 76-degree day and jogged out to the mound seconds before the national anthem began. After Hernandez went ahead, 0-2, on Stan Javier, he threw three straight balls before Javier singled to right field for his first of five hits. One out later, Alex Rodriguez looped a single to center.</p>
        <p>Hernandez had a 1-1 count on Edgar Martinez when he threw a fastball up and in to give Martinez a different look or maybe to get him to foul off the pitch. But Martinez's quick, compact swing enabled him to hammer a pitch that was near his eyes over the left-field fence, giving the Mariners a 3-0 bulge and giving him a major-league-best 103 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>''He seems like he can hit a ball over his head,'' Posada said. ''He's that good.''</p>
        <p>When the pitching coach, Mel Stottlemyre, visited the mound after Martinez's homer, Hernandez looked perturbed. Hernandez walked two batters in the third, but he escaped unscathed from a bases-loaded situation. He could not escape more danger in the fourth when four of the first five batters slapped hits and the Mariners surged to a 5-0 lead, leaving Hernandez looking frustrated and wondering what had happened.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing is, I feel good,'' Hernandez said. ''My elbow is fine. My back is fine. All the rest will solve itself.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>BERNIE WILLIAMS's 24th homer gave him 100 runs batted in, the fourth time he has reached that plateau in his career. Williams reached 100 in the Yankees' 106th game, the fastest to that mark since Joe DiMaggio got to 100 in 105 games in 1948. DiMaggio finished that season with 155. . . . ALLEN WATSON pitched for the first time since being activated on Friday and gave up three earned runs in two innings. He was booed. ''I guess all fans are like that when you're losing,'' Watson said. ''Yeah, they were a little harsh.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
