<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Reorients to Political Role and 'Tough Fight'</title>
    <meta content="07CHEN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DE103CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Reorients to Political Role and 'Tough Fight'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>NORMAL, Ill., Aug. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Republican Vice Presidential candidate Dick Cheney, who repeats promise of tough fight to 'restore honor, integrity and decency to the Oval Office,' and who acknowledges that Republicans bear some responsibility for partisan bickering and backbiting in Washington; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In stump speeches that echoed his combative address to the Republican National Convention, Dick Cheney today repeated his promise of a ''tough fight'' to ''restore honor, integrity and decency to the Oval Office.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate, acknowledged in an interview that House Republicans bore some responsibility for the ''partisan bickering and backbiting'' in Washington that he criticizes in his speeches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In stump speeches that echoed his combative address to the Republican National Convention, Dick Cheney today repeated his promise of a ''tough fight'' to ''restore honor, integrity and decency to the Oval Office.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate, acknowledged in an interview that House Republicans bore some responsibility for the ''partisan bickering and backbiting'' in Washington that he criticizes in his speeches.</p>
        <p>''I can't deny it has been a two-way street,'' Mr. Cheney said, on the third and final day of a rail trip across the Midwest with Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. ''The process by which we Republicans took control in '94 left some scar tissue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, the second-ranking House Republican until he became defense secretary in 1989 under President George Bush, also denied waging a specific offensive against President Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've attacked President Clinton at this stage,'' he said. ''We've made it clear what we want to bring to the White House. If it implies any criticism of the Clinton administration, that's their problem, not ours.''</p>
        <p>But in his sharply worded convention speech, Mr. Cheney said, ''We are all a little weary of the Clinton-Gore routine'' and promised ''a stiff dose of truth'' to counter the ''lectures and legalisms and carefully worded denials'' of the Clinton White House. ''For all of their sentimental talk about children,'' Mr. Cheney said in a typical passage, ''Clinton and Gore have done nothing to help children oppressed by bureaucracy, monopoly and mediocrity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said today that the style of Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois was more in line with Mr. Bush's ''compassionate conservatism'' than the scorched earth tactics of the former speaker, Newt Gingrich, a friend of Mr. Cheney's.  ''Denny Hastert is probably more suited to the kind of thing we're talking about now than Newt,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich, of course, is a name that most Republicans are running away from these days. There is little mention of the hard-edged politics of confrontation that predated Mr. Bush. And Mr. Cheney fits that mold of the conservative pragmatist who brings the campaign depth in foreign affairs and the business world.</p>
        <p>In his speeches, Mr. Bush describes Mr. Cheney, 59, as ''humble,'' ''strong,'' ''steady'' and someone who has brought ''nobility to public service.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the rail tour, Mr. Cheney has stuck to his role as the solid, substantive but colorless understudy, the intellectual ballast who would never upstage the top of the ticket. And that is just how Mr. Bush wants it, his aides say.</p>
        <p>''Part of what's involved is to get reoriented back into the political world,'' said Mr. Cheney, who until two weeks ago was chairman of the Halliburton Company, the giant oil services company. ''All of this has happened so fast.''</p>
        <p>The pace is about to get even faster.</p>
        <p>Breaking tradition with the role of previous vice presidents, who typically were dispatched to shore up their voter base, Mr. Cheney said he would spend most of the campaign in states that will be decisive in the fall elections.</p>
        <p>''Because Republicans are so united, we have the freedom to send him to swing states,'' said Karen P. Hughes, communications director for the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush will campaign in California and the Pacific Northwest later this week with his former rival, Senator John McCain of Arizona, Mr. Cheney will visit Missouri, Michigan, Ohio, Kentucky and Illinois.</p>
        <p>To cover as much ground as possible in the next three months, the two candidates will separate, with Mr. Cheney saying that he plans to campaign four or five days a week, depending on the states.</p>
        <p>''So we'll try from time to time to get together, for joint appearances, but most of the time we'll have separate schedules,'' Mr. Cheney said in an interview today aboard the train rolling through Illinois cornfields.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Cheney campaigns alone, he said, he will hammer home the same issues -- education, Social Security reform, tax cuts and rebuilding the military -- that are staples of Mr. Bush's stump speech.</p>
        <p>But the emotional undercurrent of Mr. Cheney's message is a call to Republicans to evict what they call a scandal-tainted Democratic administration.</p>
        <p>''It will be a tough fight, but it's absolutely essential for us to do whatever has to be done in order to restore honor, integrity and decency to the Oval Office,'' he said today at a rally in Joliet, Ill.</p>
        <p>The two candidates' body language at rallies on this four-state trip suggests that Mr. Bush is comfortable with Mr. Cheney, but not close in the way between Bill Clinton and Al Gore were on their first post-convention bus tour in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney, for example, usually just shake hands after the introductions. Today, for the first time, each threw an arm around the other's waist, and they waved together to a cheering crowd in Joliet, Ill.</p>
        <p>The two candidates are opposites in other ways. ''Mr. Cheney has a wry sense of humor,'' Ms. Hughes said. ''The governor's is more rambunctious.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney did have a rare moment of playfulness as the train pulled into Akron, Ohio, the other day. When he spotted some photographers on the platform, he threw his arms up in a Nixonesque victory pose, grinning until his wife, Lynne, nudged him to quit clowning around.</p>
        <p>Of course, it always takes time to mesh two candidates. At times, Mr. Cheney seems more appended than integrated into the well-oiled Bush campaign. The 13-page schedule for the campaign's whistle-stop tour repeatedly describes when ''the governor'' arrived or departed. But Mr. Cheney was mentioned only once -- when he and his wife are scheduled to get off the campaign plane in Dallas, one stop before Mr. Bush flies on to Austin.</p>
        <p>Despite his hamming for cameras, Mr. Cheney still doesn't seem completely at ease on the podium.</p>
        <p>He introduces Mr. Bush usually in two minutes or less. Mr. Cheney delivers two lines from his convention speech -- ''It is time for them to go,'' and ''Help is on the way'' -- in a matter-of-fact monotone.</p>
        <p>When the more dynamic Mr. Bush speaks, Mr. Cheney tends to fidget on stage, folding his arms, then jamming his hands in his suit pants, then clasping his hands behind his back.</p>
        <p>None of this bothered Republicans who turned out to see their candidates.</p>
        <p>''Cheney just seems very sincere,'' said Teri Almy, 55, who works in the Iona County Clerk's office and came to the rally in East Lansing, Mich.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Cheney insisted that he is running for ideals developed over three decades of public service. When Mr. Bush asked him to run, Mr. Cheney said he had no good reasons other than personal considerations.</p>
        <p>''People say, look at what he gave up: a great C.E.O.'s job, making millions of dollars a year, he had his own private airplane; now he's out here running for public office, what the hell's wrong with him,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>But he said the crowds on the trail have already vindicated his decision.</p>
        <p>''Mostly what people say is, thank you, we really appreciate you're willing to take this on,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''That counts for a hell of a lot.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
