<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain Fights Tide of Anti-Pedophile Attacks</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5D9133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain Fights Tide of Anti-Pedophile Attacks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British government says it will urgently press for stricter laws on child molesting but resists widespread calls for public identification of released violators, who have been associated with current vigilante attacks nationwide (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain said today that it would urgently press for stricter laws on child molesting but resisted widespread calls for public identification of released violators that have been associated with current vigilante attacks across the country.</p>
        <p>Home Office Minister Paul Boateng pledged that the government would strengthen laws protecting children from sexual abuse, but he said, ''The decisions about whether or not people are told names and addresses are not matters for newspapers, they are not matters for ministers, they are matters for police and the probation service.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Britain said today that it would urgently press for stricter laws on child molesting but resisted widespread calls for public identification of released violators that have been associated with current vigilante attacks across the country.</p>
        <p>Home Office Minister Paul Boateng pledged that the government would strengthen laws protecting children from sexual abuse, but he said, ''The decisions about whether or not people are told names and addresses are not matters for newspapers, they are not matters for ministers, they are matters for police and the probation service.''</p>
        <p>His newspaper reference was to Britain's top-selling tabloid, The Sunday News of the World, which under the headline ''Name and Shame'' has been running photographs and whereabouts of men convicted of molesting children who have been released from prison. Although the paper had promised to name 100,000, it ended the practice today after publishing only 82.</p>
        <p>Lynch-mob attacks and firebombings have occurred in 11 communities in England and Scotland since the campaign began two weeks ago, the majority of them at homes of people wrongly identified as suspected pedophiles or who look like people pictured in the newspaper or have similar names. A rioting crowd of 150 -- many carrying signs with the emotive News of the World headline -- overturned vehicles, smashed windows and threw stones and rocks at the police on Thursday and Friday nights in Plymouth in Southern England.</p>
        <p>The newspaper, which is owned by the press magnate Rupert Murdoch, has been condemned by police officials and human rights groups arguing that its campaign has actually further endangered children by driving sex offenders underground. ''The government's concern has to be the protection and welfare of children and the maintenance of public order,'' Mr. Boateng said. ''The News of the World approach to this issue in naming and shaming threatened both.''</p>
        <p>But the newspaper said it was abandoning its effort only because it had started an ''unstoppable force'' for a law for public identification of known offenders. It said 300,000 people had already signed a petition for a law that would let parents see registers of convicted pedophiles in their area, and it printed forms for its 4.1 million readers to sign and send to the government, with the promise of a receiving a ''badge of pride'' to wear.</p>
        <p>Modeled after the so-called Megan's Law in the United States, the British version is being promoted as Sarah's Law, in memory of Sarah Payne, 8, who was abducted last month near her grandparents' home and later found dead and naked off a country path after a search that aroused front-page sympathy throughout Britain.</p>
        <p>The girl's mother, Sara Payne, 31, made affecting televised daily appeals for her daughter's return during the two weeks that hundreds of  police officers combed fields in Surrey, and she was pictured on today's News of the World front page endorsing the campaign and helping count signed petitions.</p>
        <p>Megan's Law, a New Jersey statute that all 49 other American states have used as the model for similar laws, was created in 1994 in response to the brutal rape and murder of Megan Kanka, 7, of Hamilton Township, by a twice-convicted sex offender who was living across the street unbeknown to her parents. Under the law, all sex offenders must register with the police, and community organizations involved with children are alerted to the presence of those who are considered potentially repeat offenders. The law counsels a number of preventive steps and explicitly rules out verbal and physical vigilantism.</p>
        <p>Michael Howard, known as a strict law-and-order official when he served as Britain's Home Secretary in the last Conservative government, warned on Saturday that proposals for public surveillance would lead to vigilantism ''that no civilized society could tolerate'' and could increase risks to children by discouraging released sex offenders from registering with the police at the high level they do now. He said the level in Britain was 97 percent -- the highest compliance of any country in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boateng did not detail what steps he was contemplating to redeem his pledge to tighten up procedures, but the government is known to be looking at proposals for longer sentencing, including life terms with no possibility of parole.</p>
        <p>The editor of The News of the World, Rebekah Wade, said, ''As a result of our naming and shaming campaign, I believe the introduction of Sarah's Law is now inevitable.'' She cited that as the reason the newspaper had ended the campaign and added, ''Our job now is to force the government to act -- and we'll name and shame every politician who stands in our way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
