<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Un-Brooklyn Crime; Army Officer Charged in Killings in Land Fraud</title>
    <meta content="17CAPT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lau, John (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barone, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barone, Liane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DA1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Un-Brooklyn Crime; Army Officer Charged in Killings in Land Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Capt John Lau of United States Army, officer with South European Task Force stationed in Italy in 1996, is charged with murdering Alexander and Liane Barone and dumping their bodies into Newtown Creek, located between Brooklyn and Queens in New York City; Lau is currently serving ten year sentence for defrauding Barones in Florida land deal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Capt. John Lau of the United States Army, an officer with the South European Task Force stationed in Italy, left behind his wife, three young children and the busy affairs of his foreign posting to make a brisk two-day trip home to New York four years ago.</p>
        <p>Among his reasons for the trip, Captain Lau later told investigators, were that he hoped to discuss a transfer with a general, deliver an anniversary gift to some friends and pick up Chinese foods not available in Vicenza, where he was stationed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Capt. John Lau of the United States Army, an officer with the South European Task Force stationed in Italy, left behind his wife, three young children and the busy affairs of his foreign posting to make a brisk two-day trip home to New York four years ago.</p>
        <p>Among his reasons for the trip, Captain Lau later told investigators, were that he hoped to discuss a transfer with a general, deliver an anniversary gift to some friends and pick up Chinese foods not available in Vicenza, where he was stationed.</p>
        <p>But, investigators say, the most pressing matter that put Captain Lau on Delta Flight 73 to New York on May 22, 1996, was murder.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say that during his 50-hour visit, Captain Lau met with a young couple he had defrauded in a land deal, beat them to death and dumped their bodies into Newtown Creek, a brackish body of water that divides Brooklyn and Queens. Then, say investigators for the Brooklyn district attorney's office, he drove to the airport the next day, boarded a flight to Italy and resumed his work for the task force that responds to military emergencies in Europe.</p>
        <p>Last month, Captain Lau, whose discharge from the Army is pending, returned to New York, this time to face charges in the murder of the couple, Alexander Barone, 32, and his wife, Liane, 29. He is being held without bail.</p>
        <p>In Brooklyn, where many killings stem from drug dealing and domestic disputes, investigators said that murders that arise from white-collar crime are uncommon. A suspect who is a decorated Army officer accused of committing the crime during a short furlough from foreign soil is unheard of.</p>
        <p>''The combination of the defendant and his background, and the crime and the motive underlying it, makes it more unusual than most,'' said Barry M. Schreiber, chief of the district attorney office's homicide bureau.</p>
        <p>Captain Lau, 37, whose family lives in Brooklyn, has denied any murder role. His lawyers have said that after an exhaustive four-year inquiry, investigators have yet to uncover any eyewitnesses or physical evidence, like fingerprints, that link Captain Lau to the crime.</p>
        <p>His lawyer, Gary Villanueva, said the defense would have no comment.</p>
        <p>The water-swollen bodies of the Barones were discovered in the creek at 9 a.m. on May 24, 1996. Initially, the police thought they were robbery victims. Their wallets were missing, as was any identification. Their skulls had been fractured with a blunt instrument.</p>
        <p>The bodies were not identified for four days. But within a week, investigators sought to interview Captain Lau, the last person known to have seen the couple alive. Robbery had become an unlikely motive, investigators said. Someone had found the victims' wallets and had mailed them to their address, with credit cards undisturbed.</p>
        <p>Local investigators and the Army's Criminal Investigation Division began to pursue a new theory: that Captain Lau had killed the Barones to cover up his role in a Florida real estate deal in which the Barones and others had been cheated.</p>
        <p>The deal dated from 1987, when Captain Lau was in the Reserves and was making his living as an independent real estate agent. He had offered to help Mr. Barone, a friend from their days in the Reserve Officers Training Corps at Polytechnic University in Brooklyn, buy a lot in a development known as Deep Creek, near Port Charlotte, Fla. To help finance the deal, according to court records, Captain Lau told Mr. Barone he would lend him $13,000.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Captain Lau never bought the land for the Barones, nor did he lay out any money on their behalf. He just pretended to. And several months later, when he arranged for the Barones to resell the property to a family in Queens, that too was a fictional transaction, papered over with bogus documents that concealed that neither family had ever seen a deed.</p>
        <p>But the Queens family, the Leongs, dutifully sent the Barones a check for $224 every month as outlined in their installment plan. And every month, to pay down their debt, the Barones sent a $200 check of their own to Captain Lau, even after he went on active duty in 1992 and later was posted to Italy.</p>
        <p>For nine years, the monthly payments continued. But in 1996, when the Leongs tried to pay off their balance and secure the deed, they discovered during a title search that the Barones had never owned the property. They complained to the Barones, who in turn called Captain Lau in Italy. He promised, investigators say, to come to New York in a few days to clear things up.</p>
        <p>Captain Lau arrived at Kennedy Airport at 3:30 p.m. on May 22. The following night he met the Barones for dinner and, he said, to drop off some papers related to the sale. While they were upset at their real estate problem, the couple were happy. Two days earlier, Mr. Barone had graduated from the University of Pennsylvania with a master's degree in architecture.</p>
        <p>Captain Lau told investigators that instead of going to dinner, they went to his mother's house for a short time, and then the couple asked him to accompany them to Shea Stadium to meet a friend in the parking lot. The friend, whom the captain called Gene, was preparing to visit Italy and wanted advice from someone who lived there, Captain Lau recounted, and so they waited for him outside the stadium in parked cars.  But when Gene did not show up after several hours, Captain Lau said, at 1 a.m. he left to go back to his mother's house in Queens.</p>
        <p>Captain Lau, who had no previous  criminal record or history of violence, has said someone else must have attacked the Barones after he left. ''Murder is outside of my scope of realm,'' he said at a 1999 hearing.</p>
        <p>The police version is different. Gene does not exist, they say, and was invented to explain the missing hours when the murders occurred. They say that during those hours Captain Lau, possibly acting with someone else, killed the couple, put their bodies into their red 1984 Trans Am and drove the car to the Metropolitan Avenue bridge over Newtown Creek, where he dumped the bodies.</p>
        <p>The car was found in Manhattan three weeks later, stained with blood.  A 15-inch-long metal ratchet was found inside that investigators say may have been used in the murders. They say the killings were premeditated, because the person who drove the car after the crime appears to have been wearing gloves, an analysis of the steering wheel showed.</p>
        <p>In charging Captain Lau, the office of Charles J. Hynes, the Brooklyn district attorney, has cited injuries the captain had when he was interviewed 12 days after the killings. They included a large scratch across his back and a scab on his left shoulder that investigators say are evidence he had been in a struggle. But the captain said he had simply scratched his back in the shower and been hit by falling plaster while making home repairs.</p>
        <p>Much of the evidence consists of what prosecutors have characterized as multiple inconsistencies in Captain Lau's statements. He initially denied that there was fraud in the land deal, for example.</p>
        <p>And in a conversation Captain Lau recounted for investigators, he said he and Mrs. Barone had discussed the Trans Am while waiting for Gene outside Shea Stadium. The captain recalled complimenting Mrs. Barone on the car's mint condition, and she had said of her husband, ''He doesn't ever let me drive this car.'' Investigators said Mrs. Barone would never have said such a thing,  because she had no driver's license and did not drive.</p>
        <p>Last year, Captain Lau was charged in federal court in Brooklyn in connection with the land fraud, and during that case, Paul Schoeman, an assistant United States attorney, put forward some of the murder evidence. The captain ultimately pleaded guilty to mail fraud, but steadfastly denied any role in the murder of the Barones.</p>
        <p>As part of the captain's defense at a sentencing hearing, his lawyer, Steven Brounstein, said any inconsistencies were an insufficient foundation on which to build a murder case. Mr. Brounstein said the lead investigator in the case, Bob Burton of the Brooklyn district attorney's office, had sent out nearly 400 subpoenas for evidence, but still there were no fingerprints, fiber evidence or eyewitnesses to tie his client to the crime.</p>
        <p>He said Captain Lau, at 5 feet 4 inches, was too small to have killed both Barones at the same time. And he said Captain Lau had been caught cutting corners in land deals before, but when that happened, he had merely paid what he owed. The $20,000 in this case, he said, was not enough to motivate a murder.</p>
        <p>But Judge Reena Raggi, who presided in the federal case, said she did not believe Captain Lau's account and sentenced him to 10 years in prison, far above the 16 months suggested under sentencing guidelines.</p>
        <p>In explaining her sentence, she said in court that she had been persuaded that the captain had probably committed the murders, even if the sum involved was small.</p>
        <p>''He had more to lose than money,'' Judge Raggi concluded. ''He had his career.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
