<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Challenging The Kingdom Of Greenwich</title>
    <meta content="17TOWN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leydon, Brenden P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DD1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Challenging The Kingdom Of Greenwich</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>GREENWICH, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Purdy Our Towns column on work of lawyer Brenden P Leydon in successful suit against Greenwich, Conn, town ordinance that restricted town's beaches and parks to Greenwich residents only (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT might not come as a surprise to residents of Greenwich that Brenden P. Leydon was in his Stamford law office yesterday morning preparing to do battle in another lawsuit some might consider trifling. He was going to trial in a personal injury case on behalf of an elderly man who suffered two broken fingers in a family dust-up.</p>
        <p>''I think most lawyers would just not waste their time taking it to a full jury,'' said Mr. Leydon, 32. ''But I like to fight for what I think is right.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT might not come as a surprise to residents of Greenwich that Brenden P. Leydon was in his Stamford law office yesterday morning preparing to do battle in another lawsuit some might consider trifling. He was going to trial in a personal injury case on behalf of an elderly man who suffered two broken fingers in a family dust-up.</p>
        <p>''I think most lawyers would just not waste their time taking it to a full jury,'' said Mr. Leydon, 32. ''But I like to fight for what I think is right.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon is known here as that Stamford lawyer who made a big deal about the ''residents only'' beach at Greenwich Point Park. Viewed as a nuisance when he filed his lawsuit in 1995, Mr. Leydon became the sand in Greenwich's Top-Siders, rubbing this way and that until the State Appellate Court ruled last week that Greenwich cannot keep outsiders off its beach.</p>
        <p>The court might as well have outlawed films in Cannes. Greenwich's character is reflected in both the park's serene beauty and in the sign at the entrance declaring ''Greenwich Residents and Guests Only.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon was neither when he and a friend tried to jog through the park in 1994. A guard caught them at the gate. ''They came out and said 'Halt!' '' he said. ''At that point I thought it was a ridiculous law, but I assumed if they were doing it, they could do it.''</p>
        <p>A constitutional law class he was taking at Rutgers University Law School made him think otherwise. Earning law school credit as he sued, Mr. Leydon filed what was apparently the first challenge to Greenwich's beach policy. In 1998, a trial court judge agreed with town attorneys that a 1919 law gave Greenwich the right to establish parks and beaches exclusively for its residents. But the Appellate Court said public parks and beaches were for everyone, a ruling likely to open ''resident only'' facilities in other Connecticut towns if it is not reversed by the State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon is not as intent on swimming as he is on making a point. ''I just find it offensive as an American to walk through a park and be stopped and asked for your ID,'' he said.</p>
        <p>People in Greenwich find it offensive that they have to open up their treasured park, with its wooded paths, broad beach and views of Manhattan. They say they don't fear outsiders, just the effect of more people on an already crowded park.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to say you're exclusive,'' said Nina Cocchi, who was playing with her grandchild on the beach. ''But on the other hand you pay taxes and there are some amenities that go along with the taxes.'' Rather than suing to swim, she suggested that Mr. Leydon ''make friends with someone in Greenwich and come as a guest.''</p>
        <p>Ralph G. Elliot, a lawyer representing Greenwich, said the town bought the park ''with our own money and maintained it with our own money'' for more than 50 years with the understanding that it could be restricted to Greenwich's 60,000 residents.</p>
        <p>IT'S part of the local culture. If you're lost and ask for directions to the public beach, you're likely to get the subtle message that if you need to be told where the beach is, you probably can't get in.</p>
        <p>''There really isn't a public beach in Greenwich,'' a guard at the Mead Point gated community says before giving directions. A few miles later, a woman in a corporate parking lot answers a plea for help with a question: ''Do you have a beach pass?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon never had a pass, which Greenwich residents have to pay for. He grew up in Stamford (where anyone can go on the beach but parking is by permit only), went to Tufts University, was in the National Guard and then returned to Stamford as a substitute teacher and wrestling and soccer coach before going to law school.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon is savoring his victory. But he hasn't yet squeezed into his Speedo, lathered up with sunscreen and headed to the Greenwich beach. He's been busy with the case of the broken fingers, among others. Besides, at Greenwich Point Park, the restrictions are still in force while the State Supreme Court decides whether to review the case.</p>
        <p>On Monday, a gatehouse guard, Jim Reilly, was diligently checking passes when two women went through on in-line skates, both pushing children in jogging strollers. Mr. Reilly waved them in, sighing under his breath. ''They're supposed to be one behind the other, in tandem, not abreast,'' he said, perturbed. But at least they had their passes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
