<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artichokes: Out of the Pot, Onto the Fire</title>
    <meta content="17ARTI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Artichokes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raichlen, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DE1E3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artichokes: Out of the Pot, Onto the Fire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN RAICHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raichlen, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven Raichlen describes pleasures of grilled artichokes; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I FIRST tasted a grilled artichoke at a rough-and-tumble chophouse in Barcelona called La Tomaquera. I loved the crackling crisp leaves, the hauntingly smoky flavor. And I really loved the surprise of having hot off the grill a vegetable I usually eat boiled.</p>
        <p>Firm, dense, low-moisture vegetables are not the usual candidates for grilling. Artichokes in particular seem as if they would turn leathery and tough. But every rule has its exception.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I FIRST tasted a grilled artichoke at a rough-and-tumble chophouse in Barcelona called La Tomaquera. I loved the crackling crisp leaves, the hauntingly smoky flavor. And I really loved the surprise of having hot off the grill a vegetable I usually eat boiled.</p>
        <p>Firm, dense, low-moisture vegetables are not the usual candidates for grilling. Artichokes in particular seem as if they would turn leathery and tough. But every rule has its exception.</p>
        <p>Few cooking methods do more to bring out a vegetable's natural sweetness. The high, dry heat caramelizes the plant sugars. The charring imparts a pleasantly bitter flavor to counterpoint the sweetness. Add the scent of wood smoke and you transport most vegetables from the realm of the merely delectable to the kingdom of the sublime.</p>
        <p>The trick with grilling artichokes is to add moisture. Not anything as dull as water, but butter or oil, flavored with loads of garlic and parsley. Steady basting infuses the whole artichoke with unforgettable flavor and juiciness.</p>
        <p>At La Tomaquera, a tiny restaurant dominated by a charcoal grill in the open kitchen, butter is the lubricant of choice. Lots of garlic, parsley and hot red pepper flakes add intense flavor. The artichokes are grilled until they start to turn tender, then the leaves are opened up like a flower and more butter is added. By the end, the leaves are crisp and golden brown.</p>
        <p>Artichokes are also grilled in Sardinia, with garlic-scented olive oil. The procedure was taught to me by Katherine Deumling, who spent a year on a Thomas J. Watson Foundation fellowship studying how culinary traditions are passed down from generation to generation in Italy.</p>
        <p>In this method, the clump of fibrous thistles in the center of the artichoke, called the choke, is removed before grilling. Oil mixed with raw garlic and parsley is placed in the cavity to perfume the artichoke from the inside out. The ingredients are similar to those in Barcelona, but the dish has a completely different taste.</p>
        <p>Selecting artichokes for grilling may run counter to your intuition: the best candidates are large but not jumbo, and are older, with leaves that have started to spread open. This allows the butter or oil -- and the heat -- to penetrate deep inside, giving the leaves their signature crispness. Avoid hard, tightly closed artichokes, which are difficult to grill.</p>
        <p>The other ingredient needed here is patience. It takes long, slow grilling to achieve the proper crispness in the artichokes. I use a medium fire, but you may need to reduce the heat to medium-low to keep them from burning.</p>
        <p>BARCELONA-STYLE GRILLED ARTICHOKES  Adapted from La Tomaquera  Time: About 1 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>8 artichokes</p>
        <p>1/2 lemon  2 1/2 sticks (1 1/4 cups) unsalted butter  5 cloves garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1/3 cup minced flat-leaf parsley</p>
        <p>1/2 to 1 teaspoon hot red pepper flakes  Coarse sea salt and coarsely ground black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat grill to medium. Cut stems off artichokes, so they stand upright, and rub bottoms with cut lemon to prevent discoloring. Trim spines off leaves with scissors. Gently pry leaves apart to open each artichoke, almost like a flower.</p>
        <p>2. Melt butter in a saucepan. Add garlic, parsley and pepper flakes, and cook over medium heat until garlic loses its raw taste, 1 to 2 minutes. Using a pastry brush, brush artichokes all over with butter, dabbing between leaves. Season generously with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>3. Place artichokes on grill, stem end down. Grill until bottoms are deep golden brown, 30 minutes, turning with tongs to cook evenly. Baste often with butter, and season again with salt and pepper. Reduce heat if artichokes start to burn.</p>
        <p>4. Transfer artichokes to a platter. Starting in center, working with tongs or fingers, pry open and spread leaves to open each artichoke completely like a flower in full bloom. Baste with more butter and season again. Invert artichokes and cook until deep golden brown, 30 to 45 minutes more. Leaves should be crisp and should pull out easily; the heart should be tender.  (To test, insert a slender skewer into heart; it should go in easily.)</p>
        <p>5. Invert artichokes again (bottoms toward coals again), and drizzle with any remaining butter. Season again. Cook a few more minutes to crisp bottoms. Serve at once, providing napkins and finger bowls.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>SARDINIAN-STYLE GRILLED ARTICHOKES  Adapted from Katherine Deumling  Time: About 1 hour 45 minutes</p>
        <p>8 artichokes  1 lemon, halved  1 cup extra virgin olive oil  Coarse sea salt and fresh pepper  4 cloves garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1/2 cup chopped parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat grill to medium. Cut top third off each artichoke, and rub with lemon to prevent discoloring. Cut spines off leaves with scissors, and rub with lemon. Trim ends of stems, leaving as much of stem intact as possible.</p>
        <p>2. Using a grapefruit spoon or melon baller, scrape out the purplish inside leaves and fibrous part of each artichoke, creating a cavity. Squeeze lemon into each cavity. Generously brush artichokes inside and out with oil, and season with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>3. Place artichokes on grill, stem side up, and grill until cut side is nicely browned, about 30 minutes. Invert artichokes, brush well inside and out with more oil, and place 1 teaspoon or so chopped garlic and 1 tablespoon parsley in each cavity. Season again. Cover grill, and continue grilling  artichokes, basting with oil, until very tender, about 30 minutes. Serve at once, providing finger bowls and napkins.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
