<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Sues Newark, Claiming Bias on Police Beards</title>
    <meta content="17BEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhodes, Kevin (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerr, Anthony (Police Officer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0DB1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Sues Newark, Claiming Bias on Police Beards</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States Justice Department files religious discrimination suit against Newark, NJ, seeking damages for two Muslim police officers who were threatened with dismissal because they failed to shave their beards under policy that has since been struck down in Federal court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Justice Department filed a religious discrimination suit against Newark today, seeking damages for two Muslim police officers who were threatened with dismissal because they failed to shave their beards under a policy that has since been struck down in federal court.</p>
        <p>The suit stems from a complaint by the two officers, Kevin Rhodes and Anthony Kerr, filed with the federal Equal Opportunity Employment Commission protesting a police department ban on beards, said Bill Lann Lee, the Justice Department's acting assistant attorney general for civil rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Justice Department filed a religious discrimination suit against Newark today, seeking damages for two Muslim police officers who were threatened with dismissal because they failed to shave their beards under a policy that has since been struck down in federal court.</p>
        <p>The suit stems from a complaint by the two officers, Kevin Rhodes and Anthony Kerr, filed with the federal Equal Opportunity Employment Commission protesting a police department ban on beards, said Bill Lann Lee, the Justice Department's acting assistant attorney general for civil rights.</p>
        <p>The ban provided for medical exemptions, but not religious ones, and therefore, the officers said, discriminated against their Islamic faith, which requires them to wear beards.</p>
        <p>The suit seeks compensatory damages for pain and suffering, lost overtime and any other harm the two officers, as well as any other officers in similar circumstances, may have suffered as a result of the ban.</p>
        <p>The suit also calls on the police department, which is the state's largest, to take permanent steps to eliminate religious discrimination.</p>
        <p>''Employers have a duty to accommodate reasonably the religious observances, practices and beliefs,'' Mr. Lee said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The Newark policy was struck down in March 1999 by the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit in a suit filed by two other officers, Faruq Abdul-Aziz and Shakoor Mustafa. The United States Supreme Court refused to hear Newark's appeal of the decision.</p>
        <p>While the ban was found to be unconstitutional, the earlier suit did not seek damages, said Kara Peterman, a Justice Department spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Michelle Hollar-Gregory, the Newark corporation counsel, said she had not seen today's suit and would not  comment. But Ms. Hollar-Gregory said the department was abiding by last year's appeals court ruling while a new grooming policy was created.</p>
        <p>In a separate development today, the New York State Park Police agreed to pay $25,700 to a Muslim state park police officer who said he had been suspended for wearing a beard. As part of the settlement of the federal civil rights suit filed by the officer, Muhammad Ali, the park police also agreed to let officers seek exemptions to wear beards on religious grounds, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>In another related case, on March 24, Judge Faith R. Hochberg in Newark temporarily blocked a similar ban by the State Department of Corrections after 33 Sunni Muslim corrections officers filed a lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Robert R. Cannan, who represents the corrections officers, said the signal sent by the Justice Department's suit against Newark could aid in his settlement negotiations with the Corrections Department.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
