<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="17TRANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D61F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Announced INF Jerry Hairston of Rochester of the International League has been placed on the 7-day disabled list.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Optioned RHP Roy Halladay to Syracuse of the International League. Recalled RHP Peter Munro from Syracuse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Announced INF Jerry Hairston of Rochester of the International League has been placed on the 7-day disabled list.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Optioned RHP Roy Halladay to Syracuse of the International League. Recalled RHP Peter Munro from Syracuse.</p>
        <p>National League  CINCINNATI REDS--Activated SS Barry Larkin from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned INF Gookie Dawkins to Chattanooga of the Southern League.  PITTSBURGH PIRATES--Called up OF Emil Brown and RHP Josias Manzanillo from Nashville of the PCL. Designated RHP Jose Parra for assignment.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Activated RHP Mark Thompson from the 15-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of LHP Jose Rodriguez from Memphis of the PCL. Optioned RHP Justin Brunette and 1B Larry Sutton to Memphis. Transferred RHP Dave Wainhouse from the 15-day to the 60-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  CHARLOTTE STING--Waived G Erica Jackson.  WASHINGTON MYSTICS--Announced the resignation of Wes Unseld, general manager. Promoted Melissa McFerrin from assistant coach to general manager.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS--Signed OT Travis Claridge and OT Michael Thompson. Waived G Adam Hernandez.  DENVER BRONCOS--Signed WR Leroy Fields.  GREEN BAY PACKERS--Signed P Tom Hutton.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Agreed to terms with OL Brad Meester, LB T.J. Slaughter and OL Joe Chustz.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Signed TE Hayward Clay.  NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS--Withdrew a qualifying offer to RB-KR Derrick Cullors, making him a free agent.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Signed F Jeremy Reich and D Dan Watson.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  MLS--Suspended New York-New Jersey MF Lothar Matthaeus for one game for an accumulation of yellow-card points.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BLOOMFIELD--Named Jack Sullivan men's basketball coach.  DETROIT-MERCY--Announced the retirement of Bob Miller, baseball coach.  LYCOMING--Named Scott Kennell men's soccer coach.  MEMPHIS--Fired Jeff Hopkins, baseball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
