<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Hillary Clinton's Remarks at Nominating Convention</title>
    <meta content="17HTEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D81F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Hillary Clinton's Remarks at Nominating Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Hillary Rodham Clinton's remarks to New York State Democratic Convention in Albany (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Hillary Rodham Clinton's remarks to the New York State Democratic Convention last night in Albany:</p>
        <p>Tonight I'm deeply honored and humbled to accept the nomination of the New York Democratic Party for the United States Senate. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Hillary Rodham Clinton's remarks to the New York State Democratic Convention last night in Albany:</p>
        <p>Tonight I'm deeply honored and humbled to accept the nomination of the New York Democratic Party for the United States Senate. . . .</p>
        <p>And I pledge to you that I will work my heart out every day in this campaign to become your next senator. And I will work every day in the Senate to keep faith with you, with the values and the ideals of the Democratic Party of New York.</p>
        <p>Because make no mistake about it: This election is not about me or about any Republican opponent. It's about the people of New York, and the mission that we are pledged to. What is that mission? I think it is to strengthen our families and to protect our children, to improve our schools and to extend health care to every New Yorker. To free our families and our communities from the terror of gun violence. Strengthen Social Security and modernize Medicare. Ensure America's continued leadership in the world.</p>
        <p>It was, after all, New York Democrats who led the way in building the great American middle class. In giving rise to the labor union, to civil rights, to women's rights, to gay rights.</p>
        <p>We can continue leading this by building on the progress of the last seven years. Twenty-one million new jobs, balanced budgets, lowered crime, stronger schools, better child care, a cleaner environment, a safer and more inclusive American community. And our thanks must go to Vice President Al Gore and President Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>New York has made tremendous strides in the last seven years. But there are still too many forgotten New Yorkers. Millions of children without the families, health care or education they need to prepare them for the future. Millions of mothers and fathers working full time but still stressed with too little money or too little time. An upstate economy that isn't generating enough jobs to keep our young people here.</p>
        <p>We have some of the greatest institutions of higher learning in the nation. Yet too many of our students still can't afford a college education.</p>
        <p>We have some of the best public schools around. Yet far too many of our students are crammed into overcrowded, dilapidated school buildings more suited to the 19th century than the 21st.</p>
        <p>We have the finest hospitals in the world. Yet more than half a million children in New York do not have health insurance, and two million older New Yorkers cannot afford their prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>We have the most beautiful scenery -- from the Finger Lakes to the Adirondacks to Long Island's beaches. Yet we face environmental challenges to our air, our water and our health.</p>
        <p>I know we can do better and New York should not settle for less.</p>
        <p>We owe it to ourselves and to our children.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
