<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Senate Rival Uncertain, Party Nominates Mrs. Clinton</title>
    <meta content="17HILL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFD71F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Senate Rival Uncertain, Party Nominates Mrs. Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton accepts nomination of New York State Democratic Party for United States senator; Clinton, plunging into race shrouded in confusion with speech that reflected her uncertain political reality, still does not known whether Rudolph Giuliani will be her Republican opponent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton tonight accepted the nomination of the New York State Democratic Party for United States senator, plunging into a race shrouded in confusion with a speech that reflected her uncertain political reality: she still did not know if her opponent this fall would be Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The result was a political transposition. The Democratic convention was based here in the state capital, but the attention of the 11,500 Democrats who assembled in the Pepsi Arena, among them the president of the United States, was firmly focused on New York's City Hall. Right through this evening, Democrats were still trading rumors that Mr. Giuliani was about to seize Mrs. Clinton's spotlight by finally announcing whether his diagnosis of prostate cancer and the public unraveling of his marriage would lead to his leaving the race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton tonight accepted the nomination of the New York State Democratic Party for United States senator, plunging into a race shrouded in confusion with a speech that reflected her uncertain political reality: she still did not know if her opponent this fall would be Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The result was a political transposition. The Democratic convention was based here in the state capital, but the attention of the 11,500 Democrats who assembled in the Pepsi Arena, among them the president of the United States, was firmly focused on New York's City Hall. Right through this evening, Democrats were still trading rumors that Mr. Giuliani was about to seize Mrs. Clinton's spotlight by finally announcing whether his diagnosis of prostate cancer and the public unraveling of his marriage would lead to his leaving the race.</p>
        <p>In this extraordinarily unsettled atmosphere, Mrs. Clinton -- indeed, all the Democrats who spoke during the nearly five-hour session -- offered none of the kind of sharp partisan attacks on Mr. Giuliani that would be customary at this kind of political gathering. Mrs. Clinton's acceptance speech presented her election as a contest between political philosophies, an attack not on any candidate but on Republican policies that the first lady's aides said would stand whether her opponent ended up being Mr. Giuliani or another Republican.</p>
        <p>''Make no mistake about it: this election is not about me or about any Republican opponent,'' Mrs Clinton said. ''It's about the people of New York, and the mission that we are pledged to. What is that mission? I think it is to strengthen our families and to protect our children, to improve our schools and to extend health care to every New Yorker. To free our families and our communities from the terror of gun violence.''</p>
        <p>She went on to describe the mission as ''to strengthen our families, to protect our children, improve our schools and to extend health care to every New Yorker.''</p>
        <p>The sole official task at hand for this gathering of 352 delegates, joined in the bleachers by an audience of thousands, Democratic office-holders, advocates and lobbyists, was to nominate Mrs. Clinton. They did that with a single shout of ''Aye!'' at 9:13 tonight, and then Judith Hope, the chairwoman of the state Democratic Party, went to the microphone and announced: ''Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the next senator of the United States, Hillary Clinton, and the president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>The enthusiastic and confident tone of the session suggested how far Mrs. Clinton had come since she began traveling the state last summer, a reflection both of what Democrats tonight described as the evolution of Mrs. Clinton's political skills and of the recent difficulties that have confronted Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>She was the unanimous choice of delegates here tonight. No other Democrat even managed to gather the 15 signatures needed to have his or her name entered into nomination.</p>
        <p>''We have a united Democratic Party,'' Mrs. Clinton told a crush of reporters and state legislators who turned out to see her at a prenomination reception sponsored by the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, a Manhattan Democrat. ''We're going to work in this campaign; we're going to be victorious in November.''</p>
        <p>If the events here were largely predictable, the Democratic Party took pains to take note of what transpired here in Albany tonight: a first lady was chosen for the first time to run for public office. The words ''History in the Making'' were affixed to the front of the lectern, and this city buzzed as the news spread that President Clinton would accompany his wife to the event.</p>
        <p>Even on what should have been the most orderly of days, there were touches of disorder throughout the evening, in keeping with the history of both the Democratic Party of New York and the nation's first family. With jockeying among elected officials for a high-profile spot at this unusually high-profile convention, the party was unable to produce a copy of its program until just 45 minutes before the convention was gaveled to order, and the convention was running behind schedule within the hour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's decision to attend was a last-minute change of course, the outcome of a debate in Mrs. Clinton's camp over whether his appearance would overshadow the first lady on her day, or whether it would seem odd for a candidate's spouse not to be by her side at this event.</p>
        <p>The first lady and her aides were tinkering with her speech until the last moment, just as her husband frequently does with his.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's campaign, which has pushed ahead full throttle even in the midst of uncertainty about the candidate himself, had a response to Mrs. Clinton's speech out more than two hours before she was scheduled to speak.</p>
        <p>''No matter how hard Mrs. Clinton tries to reinvent herself,'' said Juleanna Glover Weiss, a spokeswoman for Mr. Giuliani's campaign, ''there is still only one candidate in this race with the record of success and follow-through that has improved the lives of New York families.''</p>
        <p>It was, in some senses, a tricky political day for Mrs. Clinton's campaign, as it sought to balance competing forces -- taking advantage of what should be a stellar moment in the campaign, without seeming to be overly harsh toward Mr. Giuliani at a time of personal difficulty for the mayor.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton did not mention Mr. Giuliani's name in a speech that went on for 39 minutes. Her speech was, in fact, notably unadventurous, as she endorsed a number of Democratic positions on issues that her aides hope will be key in the campaign. Among them were gun control, increasing the minimum wage, providing affordable health care to all, and opposing broad-based Republican tax cuts in Congress.</p>
        <p>In some ways, in terms of the length of her remarks as well as the laundry-list presentation, her speech was reminiscent of the State of the Union addresses that were given for eight years by the man who sat silently behind her on the stage tonight.</p>
        <p>President Clinton smiled and clapped throughout the evening, particularly when his wife firmly attached herself to his record and offered an effusive tribute to her husband.</p>
        <p>''I am delighted that the president is here this evening,'' Mrs. Clinton said, making no mention of the debate among her and her aides as to whether he should attend.</p>
        <p>''And I am so grateful for his support,'' she continued as the hall fell silent. ''I would not be standing here tonight were it not for Bill and were it not for all he has done for me, and I could not be prouder as an American and as a New Yorker to have a president who has meant so much to our country. We are a better country than we were in 1992.''</p>
        <p>The audience rose in an ovation to the president.</p>
        <p>Although Mrs. Clinton seemed to be taking pains tonight not to be too partisan, Senator Charles E. Schumer, the Democrat elected in 1998, offered in his nomination speech for Mrs. Clinton a hint of the line of attack that he has counseled her to use in the fall.</p>
        <p>''With Hillary's victory,'' Mr. Schumer said, ''we're going to tell Trent Lott that he's no longer running the United States Senate. We're going to tell Trent Lott that his dream of a Supreme Court that overturns Roe v. Wade and an N.R.A. that writes all gun legislation is dead, buried, gone with Hillary Rodham Clinton's victory.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
