<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks and Heat Face the Twilight Zone</title>
    <meta content="17KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D71F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks and Heat Face the Twilight Zone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for fifth game of National Basketball Assn Eastern Conference semifinal playoff series between New York Knickerbockers and Miami Heat; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is hard to condense all the pugnacious behavior, league-mandated suspensions, venomous talk and late-game drama that are the Knicks versus the Miami Heat into one neat package. But if it were necessary to capsulize this annual scrum, it would be done this way: Game 5.</p>
        <p>Twice the final contest and once the scene of a fight that injected hatred into this competitive postseason get-together, Game 5's have defined this series. Always pivotal, they decide which team staggers away bruised but victorious, regardless of the length of the series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is hard to condense all the pugnacious behavior, league-mandated suspensions, venomous talk and late-game drama that are the Knicks versus the Miami Heat into one neat package. But if it were necessary to capsulize this annual scrum, it would be done this way: Game 5.</p>
        <p>Twice the final contest and once the scene of a fight that injected hatred into this competitive postseason get-together, Game 5's have defined this series. Always pivotal, they decide which team staggers away bruised but victorious, regardless of the length of the series.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Charlie Ward and Miami's P. J. Brown scuffled beneath the basket, starting a melee that resulted in the series-turning suspensions of those two players plus Patrick Ewing, Allan Houston, Larry Johnson and John Starks over Game 6 and Game 7.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Miami coughed up its No. 2 seeding without Alonzo Mourning, who had been suspended for his no-holds-barred, no-punches-landed altercation with Johnson three days before.</p>
        <p>A year later, Allan Houston took his final step into stardom with a soft 10-foot jumper that kissed the rim and the backboard before falling through the net to end the Heat's season with 0.8 seconds left.</p>
        <p>And this year, tonight's Game 5 at American Airlines Arena will give the winner room to exhale for the first time in this series; a 3-2 lead will be tough to overcome in a rivalry in which neither team has won consecutive games in the last nine postseason meetings.</p>
        <p>''I think this is the pivotal game,'' Latrell Sprewell said today. ''I think this game is going to obviously put the winner in a situation where they can close the series out, and that's what we're looking for as a team. I'm sure they're looking for the same thing. We understand that, and they do too. This is the game that's probably going to decide this series.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks, who must break the win-one, lose-one streak to claim the series, are playing down the history, saying it will be of no value tonight. But a quick skim of the past would perhaps embolden them; for Game 5, though always set in Miami, has been magical for the Knicks the past two seasons.</p>
        <p>Though it was frustrating three years back when the Knicks, up three games to one, lost Game 5 and, largely because of the suspensions, the next two contests, odd occurrences have let them advance in the years since.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Buck Williams brushed the dust off his 38-year-old body and registered 12 points and 14 rebounds to complement Houston's 30-point effort. After totaling only seven minutes in the previous four games, Williams, who retired before the next season, logged 30 minutes that afternoon.</p>
        <p>And last year's Game 5, which has become known for Houston's coach-saving, franchise-revitalizing buzzer-beater, was perhaps even more remarkable because of the way a hobbled Ewing outplayed Mourning. Playing with a sore Achilles' tendon, Ewing posted a game-high 22 points and 11 rebounds, while Mourning managed 21 points and 5 rebounds.</p>
        <p>The victory, which sparked the Knicks toward the National Basketball Association finals and most likely saved Coach Jeff Van Gundy's job, made the Knicks only the second No. 8-seeded team to take a playoff series from a No. 1-seeded team.</p>
        <p>''I wish that history could help us,'' Van Gundy said after today's practice. ''Tomorrow, it's just one game, and what happened last year or two years ago or even last game, for that matter, means very little.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks are more concerned with solving their current problems than basking in their favorable history. After being outrebounded in each of the first four games, they are intent on finding a way to crash the backboards better. Van Gundy is hoping that Marcus Camby, who has recorded just 10 points and 9 rebounds over the last two games, will assert himself on the glass.</p>
        <p>''His rebounds have gone down each game, and we need him to figure out how he can get on the boards consistently, because if he gets on the boards he's going to have scoring opportunities and he can have a real big impact on the game,'' Van Gundy said. ''Second shots will lead to more points, and he could also get to the free-throw line. For us to win two more games, he's going to have to be a very, very good rebounder for us.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks also need Sprewell to break out of his Miami malaise. In the two road games against the Heat, Sprewell has averaged 11 points and 3 assists on 24 percent shooting. Appearing more comfortable in the two games at Madison Square Garden, he has averaged 19.5 points and 4.5 assists while shooting 41.4 percent from the floor.</p>
        <p>''I'm not worried about myself,'' he said. ''That's not my goal to go down there and make sure I get 25 to 30 points. My goal is to go down there and play hard and make the right plays.''</p>
        <p>While most of the Knicks brushed off the relevance of the previous Game 5's, Ward said the events of the past remained alive in the Knicks' psyche. He said they all remember 1997, when several Knicks, including Ewing, were suspended for leaving the bench while Ward and Brown were tangled up.</p>
        <p>''When you compete very hard, things happen,'' Ward said. ''But we've learned. This is a new year. It's 2000. We've learned after three years of what has happened in the past. If anything happens, no one's leaving their bench, and the guys on the court will take care of whatever.''</p>
        <p>As always, whoever takes care of business best in Game 5 will take hold of this tug-of-war series.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
