<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell Calls Fine On Knight Too Soft</title>
    <meta content="17BOOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DB1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell Calls Fine On Knight Too Soft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses reaction of New York Knickerbockers to fine and suspension of Indiana basketball coach Bob Knight (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were no cameras in the Oakland Convention Center when Latrell Sprewell's frustration boiled over and he lunged at P. J. Carlesimo in December 1997, only stunned teammates who moved in to pry his hands from the coach's throat. But by the time he stalked out of the arena, Sprewell found himself fighting for his National Basketball Association life, soon to be suspended and later traded from the Golden State Warriors as a pariah.</p>
        <p>So, Sprewell wondered aloud today, why the same fate did not befall Indiana Coach Bobby Knight, since Knight's transgression, perhaps not as vicious, was being shown across the nation with a list of other incidents that had marred the coach's career. On Monday, Knight received a reprimand, a three-game suspension and a $30,000 fine, along with a warning. Sprewell ended up missing 68 games and losing $6.4 million in salary during his suspension.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were no cameras in the Oakland Convention Center when Latrell Sprewell's frustration boiled over and he lunged at P. J. Carlesimo in December 1997, only stunned teammates who moved in to pry his hands from the coach's throat. But by the time he stalked out of the arena, Sprewell found himself fighting for his National Basketball Association life, soon to be suspended and later traded from the Golden State Warriors as a pariah.</p>
        <p>So, Sprewell wondered aloud today, why the same fate did not befall Indiana Coach Bobby Knight, since Knight's transgression, perhaps not as vicious, was being shown across the nation with a list of other incidents that had marred the coach's career. On Monday, Knight received a reprimand, a three-game suspension and a $30,000 fine, along with a warning. Sprewell ended up missing 68 games and losing $6.4 million in salary during his suspension.</p>
        <p>''It's just sad to me, knowing what I went through,'' Sprewell said after the Knicks' practice at Purchase College in preparation for Wednesday night's Game 5 of the Eastern Conference semifinals. ''It was like I was the worst person in the world with my incident, and then to turn around and have it be just the opposite in the collegiate level, it's sad. What can you say. It's a double standard, but life isn't fair.</p>
        <p>''They probably should have dealt with that a little harder, a little stricter.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell sees a double standard not only in the punishment but also in the sentiment that surrounds their cases. Whether the double standard is one based on race or because he is a player and Knight is a coach, Sprewell is unsure.</p>
        <p>''Certain people are going to see it that way,'' Sprewell, who is black, said of the race issue. Carlesimo and Knight are white. ''Others are going to see it as maybe he was just being a coach. We all have our difference of opinion on things like that. I think it is a double standard, but it's not like that happened in the N.B.A., so you can't really compare. Even though it's similar, they were handled differently. I think the coach, there are times where you can be more vocal and you can be on a guy because you're coaching and you try to motivate players. You can get away with being more abusive verbally.''</p>
        <p>But verbal rantings were not the reason for the suspension. Knight's verbal tirades have been well documented for years, with no punishment doled out. And Sprewell, who has said that his attack on Carlesimo came when he could no longer absorb the words of his coach, was asked when enough is enough.</p>
        <p>''That's the fine line,'' he said. ''I kind of stepped over that line. It's one of those things that, as a player, you've got to deal with in the right way.''</p>
        <p>Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy, while noting that he had never seen the videotape of Knight's grabbing Neil Reed around the throat and that he had never physically handled a player, felt that the conditions placed on Knight to retain his job would make coaching impossibile.</p>
        <p>''I think they are going to take away a lot of his ability to coach,'' Van Gundy said. ''He's going to have to worry about his tone of voice. You can't be nice all the time and have a chance to win.</p>
        <p>''The first time a kid gets upset over playing time now he can say, 'The guy yelled at me.' I think it speaks volumes how much support he has from his players. You can really tell a lot by how much player support he received, and his former players, it says a lot about him and how he's handled the players.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy was asked if he had ever been physical with a player, and the 5-foot-7-inch former point guard said: ''I've never tried to physically intimidate anybody. I don't think that would work too well.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy Sees Physical Game</p>
        <p>While the Knicks and the Heat have been criticized for their physical style of basketball with the Knicks becoming the first team to top 90 points when they won, 91-83, on Sunday, Van Gundy expects to see more of the same. And more important, that is just fine with him.</p>
        <p>''I think it depends on what you like from basketball,'' Van Gundy said. ''If you like defense and hard play and hustle, you'd really like this series. If you want to see Sprewell in the open floor on breakaways and the other team parting the Red Sea instead of taking the foul, you ain't seeing that.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
