<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GIULIANI ENDORSES INTERIM EXECUTIVE FOR SCHOOLS CHIEF</title>
    <meta content="17LEVY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DA1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GIULIANI ENDORSES INTERIM EXECUTIVE FOR SCHOOLS CHIEF</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani backs appointment of Harold O Levy as New York City schools chancellor; cites issues on which they disagree but will continue to negotiate; Levy welcomes Giuliani's change of heart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reversing course after four months of vociferous opposition, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that he would now support the appointment of Harold O. Levy as chancellor of the New York City school system, making Mr. Levy the likely overwhelming choice of the city's Board of Education when it meets today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, a corporate executive with no significant experience in running schools until he became interim chancellor in January, thus completed a remarkable courtship of a lukewarm board and a hostile mayor, an effort solidified by a number of well-received initiatives to enlarge summer school, make superintendents more accountable and shrink the board's bureaucracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reversing course after four months of vociferous opposition, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that he would now support the appointment of Harold O. Levy as chancellor of the New York City school system, making Mr. Levy the likely overwhelming choice of the city's Board of Education when it meets today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, a corporate executive with no significant experience in running schools until he became interim chancellor in January, thus completed a remarkable courtship of a lukewarm board and a hostile mayor, an effort solidified by a number of well-received initiatives to enlarge summer school, make superintendents more accountable and shrink the board's bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>The mayor vehemently opposed Mr. Levy's candidacy for the interim position in January, threatening to go to court to block the appointment and opposing the grant of a waiver by the state education commissioner for Mr. Levy, who does not have the education credentials required by state law for a school administrator. In fact, it is extremely unusual for school systems to select administrators who are not educators.</p>
        <p>But since Mr. Levy was approved as interim chancellor on a 4-to-3 vote by the board, he has won over the board with his hands-on style of management, warning superintendents that he would hold them accountable for school performance while promoting a more intellectual climate in the school system's leadership.</p>
        <p>Since his appointment as interim chancellor after the departure of Rudy Crew, Mr. Levy has strongly resisted the notion that he was there only to keep the chancellor's seat warm, working diligently to court board members, borough politicians, teachers and school administrators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani offered his endorsement as he spoke to reporters outside City Hall yesterday, a day that he was scheduled to visit his doctors, who are advising him on treatments for his recently discovered prostate cancer. The mayor said he told Mr. Levy in a meeting on Monday ''that I would support him so his appointment would be unanimous.''</p>
        <p>''There are areas of reform where we don't see eye to eye,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''And those are the areas that we agreed to continue to talk about.'' Among them, he said, are his belief that both the Board of Education and the community school boards should be eliminated, replaced by a chancellor reporting directly to the mayor.</p>
        <p>He also indicated that he wanted to experiment with school vouchers, an area in which Mr. Levy has declined to offer a position. It was the vouchers issue that drove a wedge between Mr. Giuliani and Dr. Crew, who had previously had a warm relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani did not discuss a third potential area of disagreement: merit pay for teachers who raise their students' scores.</p>
        <p>Despite those potential obstacles, he said he decided to support Mr. Levy because he thought that the interim chancellor had ''done a good job'' with the day-to-day management of the school system.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, Mr. Levy said, ''I am grateful for the mayor's support, and I look forward to working with him to move this system to a higher level of performance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he would continue to push for changes in education, including the use of vouchers in one or two of New York City's 32 community school districts, allowing parents of children in failing schools to send their children to private schools at public expense.</p>
        <p>''I still believe,'' he said, ''there should be more aggressive use of charter schools and that that is moving much too slowly as another form of competition.'' The Board of Education has begun converting several of its schools to charter schools, freeing them from direct control by the local school districts. But it has resisted some broader efforts to establish in the city new charter schools, which are privately managed but which receive their financing from the public school system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said that in several areas, he had supported Mr. Levy's efforts as interim chancellor, including adding air-conditioners for what is likely to be the city's largest summer school program ever.</p>
        <p>Just two weeks ago, the mayor's two appointees to the Board of Education sharply criticized Mr. Levy over his summer school plans.</p>
        <p>It was after the board's May 3 meeting, at which Mr. Levy outlined his summer school plans, that Irving S. Hamer Jr., the board's Manhattan representative, said he wanted to be considered as a candidate for chancellor. One day later, Dr. Hamer withdrew his bid after fellow board members said he had missed the deadline to apply. One week after that, the last of 5 other finalists for the job, chosen from more than 80 applicants from around the nation, also withdrew from consideration.</p>
        <p>In large part, Mr. Levy, 47, who is on leave as an international compliance executive at Citigroup, won over the board and the mayor with his get-tough approach. From his first day on the job, he focused on issues both large and small, posting a notice in the lobby of the board's aging headquarters in Brooklyn warning that jobs were in danger if the building was not cleaned up.</p>
        <p>In the following weeks, Mr. Levy suspended an entire community school board in Queens, notified superintendents that they would be evaluated at the end of the school year on a host of new performance criteria, and asked school principals by e-mail for their ideas about how to improve the school system.</p>
        <p>He also took steps to promote a more thought-provoking atmosphere in the school system, championing a weekly lunchtime arts performance by schoolchildren at the board's headquarters, offering copies of favorite poems to board members and sponsoring a group violin lesson for superintendents with Isaac Stern.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levy only began to dip his toe into issues of teaching and learning, and those are the issues that would be likely to affect the long-term success of his tenure as chancellor. Earlier this month, he said he believed that the schools should do away with their recently adopted practice of adjusting student scores on standardized tests to emphasize relative performance -- a practice known as norming -- rather than simply counting how many answers a student got right or wrong.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Levy said he thought that the Board of Education should begin training teachers itself rather than relying entirely on schools of education to do so.</p>
        <p>Signaling his own interest in influencing the debate on those issues, Mr. Giuliani said he intended to ''re-establish the practice I had followed of a regular meeting with the chancellor and his staff,'' including the deputy chancellor for instruction, ''so there could be as much mutuality of purpose as possible in order to make sure that the school system works as effectively as possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
