<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rockies Rookie, at 31, Sinks the Mets</title>
    <meta content="17METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Colorado Rockies</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD71F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rockies Rookie, at 31, Sinks the Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Colorado Rockies defeat New York Mets, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Bubba Carpenter was announced as a pinch-hitter in the 11th inning last night, the mere mention of his name caused some fans at Shea Stadium to giggle. Bubba? What kind of name is Bubba? Who is Bubba? They yelled to Bubba, they chanted his name and they teased the rookie.</p>
        <p>Well, the fans teased Carpenter for one pitch, because Bubba hammered Turk Wendell's second pitch over the right-field fence to propel the Rockies to a 4-3 victory over the Mets in 11 draining innings at Shea Stadium. It was Carpenter's first major league homer, it came at an opportune time for Colorado and it came at an even more opportune time for a player who had spent nine depressing years in the minor leagues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Bubba Carpenter was announced as a pinch-hitter in the 11th inning last night, the mere mention of his name caused some fans at Shea Stadium to giggle. Bubba? What kind of name is Bubba? Who is Bubba? They yelled to Bubba, they chanted his name and they teased the rookie.</p>
        <p>Well, the fans teased Carpenter for one pitch, because Bubba hammered Turk Wendell's second pitch over the right-field fence to propel the Rockies to a 4-3 victory over the Mets in 11 draining innings at Shea Stadium. It was Carpenter's first major league homer, it came at an opportune time for Colorado and it came at an even more opportune time for a player who had spent nine depressing years in the minor leagues.</p>
        <p>''I didn't hear any of what they said, but it doesn't surprise me,'' he said. ''I don't think there are too many Bubbas running around the streets of New York City.''</p>
        <p>If fans were asked if they thought Mike Piazza or Carpenter would get the game-winning hit last night, 99 percent would have guessed Piazza. Piazza is a perennial All-Star and a future Hall of Famer while Carpenter is a career minor leaguer. But Piazza had a chance to end the game in the 10th inning when the Mets had runners on first and second and he smacked a hard grounder off Julian Tavarez to squander that opportunity.</p>
        <p>That handed a first-in-a-lifetime chance to the 31-year-old Carpenter, who had spent his entire career in the Yankees' organization before signing with the Rockies this season. Carpenter smacked Wendell's 1-0 fastball toward the Mets' bullpen and sprinted around the bases as if he were trying to score a touchdown. Spending the last five full years at Class AAA Columbus will do that.</p>
        <p>Finally, after 922 minor league games and 3,035 minor league at-bats, the affable guy named Bubba had homered in the majors. Carpenter called Shea one of the most beautiful ballparks he had ever seen, which would be true since he had only seen two, and he could not stop smiling as he discussed last night's homer.</p>
        <p>''It was such a high feeling,'' said Carpenter, who was even a replacement player with the Yankees in 1995. ''You're not thinking about anything you're so high. As soon as I hit, I just said, 'Get out of the yard, please.' It's actually easy to hit in that situation because of the adrenaline. If you can't hit in that situation, you're dead. You need to be six feet under.''</p>
        <p>It is only May so the Mets (20-20) are not six feet under, but they lost for the 13th time in 19 games and wasted a solid performance by Rick Reed. Reed allowed two earned runs and struck out 10 in seven innings, but his throwing error also led to Colorado's third run.</p>
        <p>The Mets rallied from a 3-1 deficit against Masato Yoshii on Piazza's run-scoring groundout in the fourth and Todd Zeile's homer in the seventh. But there were numerous opportunities that the Mets fumbled while going 0 for 6 with men in scoring position against their former teammate. Yoshii pitched seven innings and gave up three earned runs.</p>
        <p>''We misfired a little,'' Mets Manager Bobby Valentine said. ''We had chances, and they always seemed to be with two outs.''</p>
        <p>After Robin Ventura's homer tied the score, 1-1, in the second, Jeffrey Hammonds had a one-out single in the fourth. Reed focused too much on the runner, and his throw to first slithered under Zeile's glove for a two-base error. With the infield in, Reed wound up talking to himself after Darren Bragg hit a 200-foot blooper into center. Bragg stole second and scored on Brent Mayne's single to left, giving Colorado a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>The Mets tied the score in the seventh, but Piazza could not end the game in the 10th and Carpenter could an inning later.</p>
        <p>The outfielder, who was recalled from Class AAA Colorado Springs when Larry Walker, the 1997 most valuable player, went on the disabled list, had a chance. He held the ball after the game, not sure if he would send it to his father, Bill, or keep it. It had been a long wait for Bubba.</p>
        <p>''I'm playing ball,'' Carpenter said, describing his perseverance. ''It's a game. It's fun. I still love coming to the ballpark every day. If I had to play another nine years to get to the big leagues, I'd do it.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DARRYL HAMILTON, who had surgery eight days ago to shave down both bone spurs and a joint in his left big toe, was in a much happier mood than he had been before the 45-minute procedure. ''It was good to have that done,'' he said. ''It gave me a little peace of mind to know I'm going to be O.K. That was something I didn't know a couple of weeks ago. I thought if I had surgery, I might be out the whole season.'' The 35-year-old center fielder hopes to start running in two weeks and rejoin the Mets in five weeks. . . . Even though the Braves enjoy a seven-game bulge over the Mets, FRED WILPON said his team should not gaze at the wild-card standing. ''I think we have to try to overtake the Braves,'' he said. . . . After not starting for four straight games because of an inflamed right shoulder, shortstop REY ORDONEZ returned and made several strong throws. . . . BOBBY J. JONES, who has disabled with a strained right calf muscle, will return to the rotation and start tomorrow.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
