<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Flyers' Neilson Recovers, He Watches and Waits</title>
    <meta content="17HOCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neilson, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7D81F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Flyers' Neilson Recovers, He Watches and Waits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Hockey column on Roger Neilson, who began season as head coach of Philadelphia Flyers, recovering from treatment for bone marrow cancer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On national television Monday night, HBO televised a long feature about Roger Neilson, who began the season as head coach of the Philadelphia Flyers. It documented his life-and-death fight against bone marrow cancer, a struggle he seems to be winning.</p>
        <p>Neilson was watching television when the show was broadcast, but he didn't tune in to that particular channel. He was at the Flyers' training headquarters, viewing the live feed of the Dallas-Colorado game in the Western Conference finals. The Flyers, who tied the Eastern finals, 1-1, by beating the Devils, 4-3, last night, might have to play the Stars or the Avalanche in the Stanley Cup finals. And Neilson has his priorities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On national television Monday night, HBO televised a long feature about Roger Neilson, who began the season as head coach of the Philadelphia Flyers. It documented his life-and-death fight against bone marrow cancer, a struggle he seems to be winning.</p>
        <p>Neilson was watching television when the show was broadcast, but he didn't tune in to that particular channel. He was at the Flyers' training headquarters, viewing the live feed of the Dallas-Colorado game in the Western Conference finals. The Flyers, who tied the Eastern finals, 1-1, by beating the Devils, 4-3, last night, might have to play the Stars or the Avalanche in the Stanley Cup finals. And Neilson has his priorities.</p>
        <p>''I still haven't watched it,'' he said last night of the HBO show when he arrived for work before Game 2 at First Union Center. ''Somebody made me a tape. I'll get to it.''</p>
        <p>All things considered, Neilson looks pretty good. He wears a baseball cap to cover the hair loss, although a few wispy strands poke out the back of his hat. Always a fitness buff, Neilson looks trim and fit, having lost 10 pounds during the treatment and only putting back 2 so far.</p>
        <p>''I'm exercising and eating well,'' Neilson said. ''I didn't eat for a month. You're on the I.V. Everything's going well. I go six to nine miles a day on my bike. I walk or run three miles a day. I'm going to be in better shape than I was. I enjoy riding my bike a lot more now than I did before.</p>
        <p>''With a thing like this, you realize how great it is to be healthy again. You can see how important your health is. No matter how everything else is going, you've got to have your health. It's nice to have it back.''</p>
        <p>Neilson underwent chemotherapy and a stem-cell transplant, but won't know for sure if the cancer is in remission until his bone marrow is tested in a month or so. But he said his blood counts are good and that his protein level is good. His sister died of the same disease two years ago. When asked if his religious faith and determination helped him in his ordeal, Neilson replied: ''Both. It certainly helps to have a strong religious faith.''</p>
        <p>Neilson's illness and recovery has been one of the sobering stories in sports in recent months. And his return to the Flyers has not been without its difficult adjustments. No longer the head coach of the team, Neilson is called ''Special Assistant to the Head Coach.'' The top job has gone to Craig Ramsay, one of Neilson's assistants and close friends.</p>
        <p>Throughout Neilson's recovery, he and his doctor said his goal was to return to the bench for the second round of the playoffs. The team is now in the third round. Neilson tried to return two weeks ago but was rebuffed by the Flyers, who cited concern for his health. But other factors were present.</p>
        <p>One was the success of the team, which improved under Ramsay. Another was the status of Eric Lindros, who was stripped of his captain's rank after accusing the team medical staff of failing to diagnose a concussion. Neilson and Lindros are close. Lindros is still out of action. In an interview with a Toronto radio station recently, Neilson said that the Flyers probably didn't want their coach to be a cancer patient who was close to Lindros.</p>
        <p>When word of this reached Philadelphia, Neilson said at first that he was just joking, although anyone who heard the interview doubted that. Later, Neilson apologized. During the same interview, he also said that he was disappointed that the Flyers had withdrawn what he thought was a generous contract extension. For the last two rounds, in addition to looking at videotapes and other games on television, Neilson has sat in the coach's box high above the rink, taking notes of Flyers games and passing on his observations to the coaching staff.</p>
        <p>In recent days, there were some reports of a rift between Neilson and Ramsay, something Neilson again denied with emphasis last night.</p>
        <p>''Absolutely,'' he said, when asked if the reports were wrong. ''Craig and I have been together for years. I don't know where that came from. We've been close through it all. We're just helping him all we can.''</p>
        <p>It is a habit of Neilson's to use the words ''we'' and ''you'' instead of ''I'' whenever he can.</p>
        <p>When asked if he planned to return to the bench for the final round, should the Flyers qualify, Neilson said: ''No. Craig's handling it for the rest. It was decided he'd do it for the rest of this year.'' What about Neilson's future with the team? ''That will be discussed after the season is over,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He didn't sound optimistic about that. When the HBO interviewer asked Neilson whether he thought he might not come back as head coach of the Flyers, Neilson said, ''Certainly that's the impression we're getting here in the last few days.''</p>
        <p>When asked about possibly coaching another team, Neilson offered a slight smile and said, in his dry way: ''I don't know how many teams are looking for a 65-year-old coach with cancer. But you never know.''</p>
        <p>ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
