<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lovable Sore Thumb In Bedford Hills' Eye</title>
    <meta content="17COMB$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bedford (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Combes, Abbott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEED61738F934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lovable Sore Thumb In Bedford Hills' Eye</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBOTT COMBES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Combes, Abbott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abbott Combes article on his decrepit 1982 Chrysler LeBaron convertible, which he uses as station car to commute from home to railroad station in affluent Bedford Hills suburb of New York City; says vehicle is probably eyesore to residents who regard expensive, late-model transports as symbols of prosperity and status (Special section, Cars); photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE commuter parking lots at the Bedford Hills train station are lease-to-lease with cars right out of the promised land -- you know, the ones that can climb mountains, ford streams, ferry soccer leagues, shake traffic, repel mud and after all that drop off a couple of beautiful people at the Plaza.</p>
        <p>The makes and models are showroom perfect for a New York suburb that doesn't mind wearing its affluence pretty much everywhere it can: Audi, Acura, BMW, Caravan, Expedition, Grand Cherokee, Infiniti, Jaguar, Land Rover, Lexus, Mercedes, Outback, Pathfinder, Saab, Suburban, Volvo. . . . And then there is that 1982 Chrysler LeBaron convertible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE commuter parking lots at the Bedford Hills train station are lease-to-lease with cars right out of the promised land -- you know, the ones that can climb mountains, ford streams, ferry soccer leagues, shake traffic, repel mud and after all that drop off a couple of beautiful people at the Plaza.</p>
        <p>The makes and models are showroom perfect for a New York suburb that doesn't mind wearing its affluence pretty much everywhere it can: Audi, Acura, BMW, Caravan, Expedition, Grand Cherokee, Infiniti, Jaguar, Land Rover, Lexus, Mercedes, Outback, Pathfinder, Saab, Suburban, Volvo. . . . And then there is that 1982 Chrysler LeBaron convertible.</p>
        <p>Know my station car, know me. If you are what you drive, I am a machine who has gone a certain number of miles and seen better days but keeps on making it up the hills and around the corners, somewhat the worse for wear but able to catch an eye or two, dented but not bowed, still bound for glory even if bound by duct tape.</p>
        <p>A few particulars, though not too many, because the past isn't always an ideal prologue. Moby, as my daughter christened the LeBaron four years ago when it became mine (she knows a great white whale when she drives one), was purchased from a friend's son for $100 cash and the assumption of a $360.97 garage bill. It has a 2.2-liter engine, an automatic transmission and four cylinders. The odometer, which rolls when it feels like it but hasn't felt like it lately, says 111,746. (Maybe it's the number's third time around, making it the real charm.)</p>
        <p>The top goes up and down, with help (arms). It keeps out rain and snow, also with help (duct tape, strategically and stylishly placed). The power windows work. The original rear window does not. The once-clear vinyl became so opaque that the blurs were blurry, and the canvas trim securing its zipper rotted so badly that there was no cloth left to restitch, much less hold the safety pins reinforcing the thread. A piece of heavy plastic, ingeniously attached with Velcro, has taken the guesswork -- and some of the fun -- out of reverse and thus far has resisted most of the elements.</p>
        <p>The heater, defroster and (unnecessary) air-conditioner operate just fine; their fan does not. The back-seat floor is, to put it delicately, brittle. There is a broken-off key in the driver's-side door.</p>
        <p>As to the essentials, engine and chassis, the car starts and it goes, and as long as it does I don't go out of my way to lift the hood or crawl under the body. It creaks; I creak. When we do, we find Mario Chiacchia at Haines Road Servicecenter or Dave Zasso and his son-in-law, Rob Cantisani, at Meineke, and they make things right.</p>
        <p>The third essential, the radio-tape deck, is groovy enough for a middle-aged guy who won't grow up.</p>
        <p>Moby, ersatz mean machine that it is, is also something of a fop and does not go quietly into the parking lot, literally or figuratively. When in doubt, accentuate the negative. For example, when the trim on the doors, a hideous vinyl-and-chrome concoction, began to fall off, I replaced it with a wood crown molding stained mahogany. Having long railed against vanity plates, I got them myself (AKA KIT -- you figure it out) and encased one of them in a bejeweled license frame so tacky that the manager of the auto-parts store didn't want to sell it to me.</p>
        <p>The back bumper is prime promotional space, of course, and I've tried to add to Moby's, and my own, mystique. There is a 1978 Red Sox sticker (one disappointing year is as good as the next) and one for the Washington Redskins. The Ivy League is represented by my daughters' schools, and one of my own, Dartmouth and Princeton, which is another reason I couldn't drive a fancier car even if I wanted to. A Grateful Dead sticker tells everyone that ''my other car is a tour bus.''</p>
        <p>My favorite, though, which I have to duplicate periodically, broadcasts how The Washington Star (where I worked) has hijacked ''Doonesbury'' from The Washington Post. (The Star, alas, was hijacked right out of existence shortly thereafter, 18-plus years ago, and ''Doonesbury'' hurried right back to The Post.) Rounding out the mobile bulletin board are the Beastie Boys, the Bahamas National Trust and the 1995 women's America Cup team, a trio that definitely wasn't made for one another but get along famously here.</p>
        <p>INSIDE, not quite as public but hanging from the mirror for all to see, are a disco ball and a religious medal. (The medal is supposed to be St. Christopher, but may in fact be St. Francis, left over from a blessing-of-the-pets church service. Whoever -- what's good for the traveling goose must be good for this gander.) Completing the interior design are Pearl Jam and Mountain Dew stickers, which came with the car; a remnant of red carpet around the gearshift; and a doormat welcoming the Publisher's Clearing House check bearer, which no one wanted at home because he never came.</p>
        <p>That's Moby: what you see is what you get, or maybe less, shoddily presentable yet decrepit enough to quell any passing fancy of restoration. (A new top, installed, would cost $700, which would lead to bodywork, which wouldn't make sense without a new motor, which would. . . .) Unlike most of his neighbors occupying the other 157 parking spots in Lot 4 at the Bedford Hills station, Moby cannot climb mountains, ford streams, etc. What Moby can do, and do faithfully, is get me to the train and home again five days a week, and on the weekends  through my appointed rounds. Hitting on three of four speakers, he can also help me reacquaint other joy riders with the great rock 'n' roll and folk artists of ages past, the likes of Bill Haley, Carl Perkins, Buddy Holly, the Kingston Trio, Clyde McPhatter,  Darlene Love, Freddy Cannon, Cat Stevens, John Fogerty, John Mellencamp (with and without Cougar), Meat Loaf. . . . So many tunes, so little driving time.</p>
        <p>I am by no means the first to note the demise of the station car, but even in an area like upper Westchester County, showcase as it is to the rich and richer (and some others), it continues to mystify. My fellow travelers, many of them friends, insist that their late-model transports are not meant to bespeak prosperity, status, but merely to ensure reliability: why should they put up with question marks when they can afford exclamation points? (Even the relatively pedestrian cars, the Fords and the Chevys, the Hondas and the Toyotas, all seem to be as shiny as a dealer's brochure.) These commuters have outgrown the rattletrap station cars of myth, they say, and then they inevitably add their own tearful remembrances of clunkers past. Right. It certainly is a sign of modern maturity to leave a $40,000 machine, which can climb mountains, ford streams, etc., in a parking lot where its only job is not to get stolen.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, almost no one is crass enough to offer a truly discouraging word in Moby's presence. In my town, surface politesse rules. Behind all the eyebrows that Moby raises, however, I wouldn't be surprised to discover disdain. Where I see resourcefulness, economy and individuality, others probably see shallowness, stinginess and erosion of community values. They also see, we would both agree, someone who doesn't have more money than he knows what to do with.</p>
        <p>There may also be some regional differences working here. (Remember the Red Sox sticker?) In Massachusetts, when I grew up there, new cars were never a distinguishing characteristic of the aristocracy. Old money tended to be cheap, so that it didn't give away any to the new money. Frugality was what counted, and the more miles you got for your buck, the better. New York, on the other hand, has always been a lay-rubber, flash-your-wad kind of place. It's the difference between believing that getting there is what counts and believing that how you get there is what counts.</p>
        <p>Well, as far as this transplanted New Englander is concerned, Moby gets me there, and he gets me there in style. Our journeys together have not always been bumpless. There have been collisions between my optimism and his obstinance; he always wins, and I always pay: axles, cylinders, starter, radiator, gas tank, muffler, rotors, brake shoes, brake drums, coils, battery, tires, ignition switch, rear-view-mirror glue. . . . And I must confess, having just finished with a calculator and receipts, that Moby's welfare has helped the local economy more than I might have wished (as some naysayers warned from Day 1). Total investment, from purchase to crown molding and all geriatrics in between: $6,106.93. Not exactly a bargain, but what price enlightenment? Amortizing it over four years, that's only $4.23 a day. As a Zen master would say, be happy with your paradoxes.</p>
        <p>And so I am. My station in life may well leave something to be desired, but my station car does not.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
