<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forget Microchips: Simple Things Make Driving Safer</title>
    <meta content="17WALD$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D81738F934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forget Microchips: Simple Things Make Driving Safer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Array of low-tech highway innovations that are making roads safer for drivers; among them are better designed concrete medians and rumble strips to alert drowsy or inattentive motorists; photo (Special section, Cars) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMEDAY, cars might come equipped with automatic pilots that let them safely follow one another bumper to bumper at 60 miles an hour. They might have transmitters that send a signal to the police whenever there is an accident, giving location and severity of impact. Highways might have sensors that instantaneously measure traffic speed and spot areas of congestion simply by tracing patterns of cellular-phone use.</p>
        <p>But while ''smart car'' and ''smart highway'' innovations like these have been demonstrated to be feasible, it may be years, or decades, before they are operating and saving lives. What about now?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMEDAY, cars might come equipped with automatic pilots that let them safely follow one another bumper to bumper at 60 miles an hour. They might have transmitters that send a signal to the police whenever there is an accident, giving location and severity of impact. Highways might have sensors that instantaneously measure traffic speed and spot areas of congestion simply by tracing patterns of cellular-phone use.</p>
        <p>But while ''smart car'' and ''smart highway'' innovations like these have been demonstrated to be feasible, it may be years, or decades, before they are operating and saving lives. What about now?</p>
        <p>The answer, engineers say, may lie in an array of safety innovations that are no less smart, only less glamorous. Concrete and steel are getting smart, too, or at least being used in smarter ways.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about simple physics here, as opposed to microchips,'' said David J. Hensing, the deputy executive director of the American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials.</p>
        <p>Consider the humble concrete barrier. Known to the public as the Jersey barrier, it is more and more common in medians, as grass strips between roadways are paved to make extra lanes. (To engineers, Jersey barrier is not a generic term; it denotes a newer version of the General Motors barrier, named for the car company, which tested barrier models in the 1950's.)</p>
        <p>The problem is that a badly designed barrier can help flip over a car, sharply increasing the chance of death or serious injury. In 1998, the first event in 239 fatal crashes was hitting a concrete traffic barrier, according to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, and in an additional, uncounted number, one or more vehicles eventually hit a barrier.</p>
        <p>Standard barriers are 32 inches high, but like two mountains with peaks of the same altitude, they have different profiles. The G.M. barrier begins at ground level, with a 2-inch vertical face; then it slopes at 55 degrees for 13 inches, and rises to full height at a slope of about 80 degrees.</p>
        <p>That design was well thought out, but for reasons that no longer seem sensible, engineers say. ''Part of the basis for that barrier was that it was somewhat forgiving on minor impacts,'' said Dean C. Alberson, an associate research engineer at the Texas Transportation Institute, part of Texas A&amp;M University. ''If there was a grazing-type blow, maybe you could keep from tearing up a lot of sheet metal. The tire interaction with the lower section would partially redirect you back onto the road.''</p>
        <p>But 13 inches of fairly shallow slope gives the front tire something to climb, making the car tilt. As cars got smaller and the distance between the front bumper and the wheel grew shorter, the wheel contacted the shallow slope sooner, with more weight on it. And as time passed, cars -- and new species, like sport utility vehicles and vans -- were more likely to be front-wheel or four-wheel drive, making a front wheel even more likely to scale the face of the barrier.</p>
        <p>So states moved to the Jersey barrier, which begins with a 3-inch vertical face, then 10 inches (not 13) at 55 degrees, then a nearly vertical climb.</p>
        <p>Then the states began experiments with test vehicles. No one thought that these were realistic, because the vehicles were driverless and rigged for steering and constant acceleration; in a real accident, drivers use brakes and the steering wheel. But they showed better performance from an even steeper barrier, with a 3-inch vertical face and then a 55-degree slope that rose only 7 inches, not 10 or 13. Many states are moving to this ''F shape'' barrier as they build or renovate roads. Texas has gone one better, developing a barrier with a constant slope of 79 degrees and no break at all. It performs well in crashes, and, maintenance departments are discovering, its geometry does not change as roads are repaved and the asphalt level rises.</p>
        <p>Some constant-slope barriers are 42 inches high, which allows multiple layers of asphalt to be added over the years without affecting safety, and provides more protection for heavy vehicles.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the optimum shape for the barrier depends on the speed of the impact.</p>
        <p>What is best for any given spot? ''You never know until after the fact,'' said Richard D. Powers, a highway engineer for the Federal Highway Administration, part of the Department of Transportation, which sets standards for roads built or renovated with federal money. A barrier that lets a car list can be good at dissipating the energy of the crash with minimal harm to the occupants, Mr. Powers said. But if it leads to a car's flipping over because the speed at impact was too high, then in hindsight it was not the best kind of barrier to hit.</p>
        <p>The reason for the uncertainty is that no one knows what the average impact is. ''We certainly don't have good information on impact speeds or angles,'' Mr. Powers continued. ''The only time we have fairly good information is when somebody is killed.'' He noted that the data system was developed by a different agency, the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, which he said was more concerned with vehicles than with highways, and added, ''The information on the roadside environment leaves a lot to be desired.''</p>
        <p>The ends of guardrails have also been redesigned. When highway builders first started putting them up, there were standards for how strong they were at their midpoint, but not what would happen if  struck on their ends. After some gruesome ''spearing'' accidents, engineers began twisting the ends of metal guardrails and burying them. This, too, had drawbacks.</p>
        <p>''Turning the rail down at the end eliminated the spearing problem, but it presents the car with a launching ramp,'' Mr. Powers said. ''The driver has no control when the wheels are off the ground.''</p>
        <p>NOW they are built to break away if struck from the end, just as light poles, signposts and other items of roadside ''furniture'' are supposed to break away.</p>
        <p>An improvement that drivers are more likely to have noticed is the addition of rumble strips at the side of the road, either cut into concrete or pressed into asphalt. The road builders have developed machines that cruise down the shoulder at about walking speed, adding a rumble strip at a cost of a few cents per foot.</p>
        <p>The idea is to alert drowsy or inattentive drivers. Drifting off the road causes an estimated 56,000 crashes a year, including 40,000 resulting in injury and 1,550 in death, according to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how many such accidents are prevented by rumble strips, since most accident data do not indicate whether they are present. Still, the anecdotal evidence is encouraging. ''Rumble strips on freeways probably saved me once or twice,'' said George W. Black, a safety engineer who is a member of the National Transportation Safety Board.</p>
        <p>Experts point to a controlled experiment, of sorts, on the New York State Thruway.  After rumble strips were installed on the 641-mile thruway system in 1996, the number of ''run off road'' crashes dropped sharply. In the three years before the strips, there were 1,681 such crashes; in the three years afer, 368 -- a drop to 3.6 percent of the total number of crashes from 18.4 percent.</p>
        <p>A 1997 report by the National Sleep Foundation said that rumble strips prevented from 15 to 70 percent of ''run off road'' crashes, depending on the estimate, and it recommended their use on all rural Interstates and similar highways. (It also warned that the strips on the Interstates might only be postponing an accident until the drivers are on a road without them.)</p>
        <p>Other simple but smart improvements  have great potential, experts say. But the traditional definition of smart highway systems, using microchips, also holds promise. Odetics ITS, a company in Anaheim, Calif., recently announced the invention of a ''virtual rumble strip'' a combination of a computer and a camera that watches the lane markings. When it senses that the car is changing lanes, but the turn signal is not operating, it makes a sound like a rumble strip, on the appropriate side. The company has an order from DaimlerChrysler, which helped develop the system, for 1,000 units.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
