<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Automobilia, a Yearning for the Days of Youth</title>
    <meta content="17ROTH$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothman, Cliff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EEDF1438F934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Automobilia, a Yearning for the Days of Youth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFF ROTHMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothman, Cliff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Cliff Rothman on collectors of automobilia; photo (Special section, Cars) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEILA DUNBAR remembers the family outing to search for old tin automotive signs at the antiques fair in Brimfield, Mass. It was 1973, and she was 12. ''We slept in a borrowed van, right on the side of Route 20, the tractor-trailers rolling by and causing the van to sway all night,'' she said.</p>
        <p>They would spend the two-day fair scouring the field for the handful of road signs for sale, like those for Champion Spark Plugs or Mother's Root Beer. Her dad, she remembers, paid maybe 50 cents for the 1-by-2-foot artifacts from the 1930's and 40's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEILA DUNBAR remembers the family outing to search for old tin automotive signs at the antiques fair in Brimfield, Mass. It was 1973, and she was 12. ''We slept in a borrowed van, right on the side of Route 20, the tractor-trailers rolling by and causing the van to sway all night,'' she said.</p>
        <p>They would spend the two-day fair scouring the field for the handful of road signs for sale, like those for Champion Spark Plugs or Mother's Root Beer. Her dad, she remembers, paid maybe 50 cents for the 1-by-2-foot artifacts from the 1930's and 40's.</p>
        <p>Brimfield now comprises 15 to 20 shows over eight days, with vast sections devoted strictly to automobilia, as the artifacts have come to be known. And those tin signs? They are about $175 to $200 each.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dunbar, who is the director of collectibles and a senior vice president at Sotheby's in New York, has automobilia in her blood. She is not alone. According to Mobilia magazine, a niche publication, an estimated three million fans and collectors are into everything pertaining to the culture of cars, motorcycles, even tractors: toy and die-cast car models, signs, gas station maps, original workshop car manuals and John Deere equipment.</p>
        <p>Industry sales figures for 1998 are estimated at a billion dollars, not including untabulated transactions that involve private sellers, flea markets or garage sales.</p>
        <p>A strong economy and baby boomers, who grew up as the car culture hit its stride, are the twin spark plugs that ignited the hobby, which has exploded since the mid-90's, said Eric Killorin, the publisher of Mobilia. The magazine, a monthly, began as a newsletter with 3,000 readers in 1992 and has grown to more than 88 pages, with 59,000 readers and a popular Internet auction site that recently attracted $6 million in venture capital. The Web site (www.mobilia.com) was introduced in January 1999 with 2,000 items, and within a week had 17,000 items for sale. It now has about 20,000.</p>
        <p>Driving the craze, however, is something less tangible and more potent than potential profit or equity: dreams. ''We're not selling cars; we're selling memories, bringing collectors back to a gentler time in their lives,'' said Lewis Checchia, who develops and markets die-cast miniature cars as director of marketing for the Franklin Mint, which has issued more than 300 castings since the early 1980's. ''They might remember when they were out with their brother, saw a '63 Corvette on the sales lot for the first time and went crazy.''</p>
        <p>Bob Knudsen, a potato farmer in American Falls, Idaho, started collecting full-size vintage Pontiac Super Duty cars. He then bought a closed-down car dealership to house his cars. Then came showroom paraphernalia -- and a new mania. ''I wanted some signs, so I bought some neon, a Pontiac sign with the big Indian, which goes way back to the 30's and 40's,'' Mr. Knudsen said. He said that he has spent about $400,000 in the last five years on signs.</p>
        <p>Stephen Babinsky, who restores antique cars in Bernardsville, N.J., experienced a similar quantum leap. He said he started out with porcelain signs and trinkets. ''Then I got into rarer signs, like car manufacturers from the 1920's, like United Motors, a General Motors subsidiary,'' Mr. Babinsky said.</p>
        <p>His prize? A Cadillac LaSalle authorized sales and service sign from the late 20's, one of only three such signs known in the United States. He still relishes this ''steal'' -- misidentified as a reproduction at a Christie's auction three or four years ago. ''Even back then, it was worth, maybe, $7,500,'' Mr. Babinsky said. ''I paid $2,000.'' The sign is  valued at $10,000.</p>
        <p>Objects that once beckoned travelers or children have gone beyond collectibles to objets d'art. The Museum of Miniatures, across from the Los Angeles County Museum of Art on Wilshire Boulevard, features a 396-piece exhibition of die-cast miniatures from the Franklin and Danbury Mints, on loan from a collector. The collection, with an estimated worth of $64,000, takes up an entire room.</p>
        <p>''Men just love it,'' said Carole Kaye, a cofounder of the museum. ''Actually, women, too. They really study them.''</p>
        <p>But automobilia has humbler roots than the Miracle Mile district of Wilshire Boulevard. ''The original stuff came from gas stations and dealerships that were boarded up,'' Ms. Dunbar said. ''Signs and cans would be stored in people's attics or basements.'' Collectors, she said, ''would scour junkyards and scrap yards, abandoned dealerships and gas stations, and often would be given the items.'' Or they would take them.</p>
        <p>But when items started turning up at yard sales, flea markets and at auctions, a market was created. ''Once it was determined that these pieces had value, less and less were out there for the taking,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Car-memorabilia collecting has been through five cycles, said Ms. Dunbar, who has published three books on the hobby. ''The first generation of collectors were in the automotive business, former dealers, repair or auto-body shops, or worked for a large car company,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The first wave, she said, came in the late 60's and early 70's, when the bulk of collectibles was miniature cars and vintage memorabilia. The second cycle appeared in the late 70's, after the oil embargo. Collectors, Ms. Dunbar said, welcomed to their ranks lawyers, doctors and self-employed business people with disposable income and a passion for automobiles. Toys also entered the mix.</p>
        <p>The third generation, from 1983 to 1985, experienced an influx of collectors, flush with Wall Street money, who drove up prices. As the hobby gained recognition, the next generation, 1988 to 1991, may have exhibited ''the biggest leap in prices,'' Ms. Dunbar said.</p>
        <p>Automobilia was quiet from 1991 to 1995, Ms. Dunbar said. But in 1995, it entered its fifth cycle, and has been rising steadily since, she said.</p>
        <p>Today, collectors are ''anyone from Joe Six-Pack to a doctor,'' said Evie Black-Dykema, a senior industry analyst with Forrester Research, a market research firm in Cambridge, Mass. ''Most prevalent is the lower-than-average-income collector,'' she said. ''They may be willing to spend a few thousand in a weekend that reminds them of their youth.''</p>
        <p>The nostalgia epicenter is the baby boomers, who grew up as cars came into their own as a mass-market, affordable entity. ''Thirty-something is when people start collecting,'' said Mr. Checchia, of the Franklin Mint.</p>
        <p>As collectors age, the epicenter shifts. ''And the next generation will want its own artifacts,'' Ms. Dunbar said. Maybe they will covet replicas of farm equipment.</p>
        <p>Farm collectibles took off at the start of this decade. A leading player is Racing Champions-Ertl, based in Iowa and known for its high-end replicas of the John Deere tractors, balers and such. The company sells about 500 models at any one time. Prices range from $5 to $150, based on size.</p>
        <p>Then there is Nascar collecting. Mr. Killorin, of Mobilia, said he estimated that it constitutes a third of the market. ''It's gone from a standing start to the checkered flag,'' he added. ''I have a 9-year-old boy who cares about Nascar, motorcycles and pickup trucks. I know he's not alone.''</p>
        <p>Cliff Rothman writes on culture from Los Angeles for Vanity Fair and The Nation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Cliff Rothman writes on culture from Los Angeles for Vanity Fair and The Nation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
