<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3M Says It Will Stop Making Scotchgard</title>
    <meta content="Y17GUA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perfluorooctanyl (Chemical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs (Labor)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D91F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3M Says It Will Stop Making Scotchgard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co says it will stop making many of its well-known Scotchgard products, which protect various fabrics from stains and other damage, in wake of discovery that perfluorooctanyl, chemical used to make products, lingers in environment and in humans for years; holds products pose no health risk, but are not environmentally friendly because they do not easily decompose; says line represents about $300 million a year in sales, 2 percent of revenues; does not expect to lay off any of 1,500 workers with jobs tied to Scotchgard (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 3M Company, the giant consumer products company, said today that it would stop making many of its well-known Scotchgard products after tests showed that the chemical compounds used to make the products linger in the environment and in humans for years.</p>
        <p>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing said that Scotchgard, a spray that protects clothing, fabrics, upholstery and carpets from stains and other damage, was  safe and that the chemical compounds pose no health risk to humans. But the company also said the compounds do not easily decompose and therefore are not environmentally friendly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 3M Company, the giant consumer products company, said today that it would stop making many of its well-known Scotchgard products after tests showed that the chemical compounds used to make the products linger in the environment and in humans for years.</p>
        <p>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing said that Scotchgard, a spray that protects clothing, fabrics, upholstery and carpets from stains and other damage, was  safe and that the chemical compounds pose no health risk to humans. But the company also said the compounds do not easily decompose and therefore are not environmentally friendly.</p>
        <p>''These products have been safely used for 40 years and they continue to be safe,'' said William E. Coyne, the head of research and development at 3M, which is based in St. Paul. ''But the best decision we can make now is to stop adding to the environment. This is a corporate responsibility issue. This product does not decompose, it's inert -- it's persistent; it's like a rock.''</p>
        <p>The company, whose products include Scotch tape and Post-it notes, said the Scotchgard line represented about $300 million a year in sales, or about 2 percent of the company's $16 billion in annual revenues. The company, which has 71,000 employees worldwide, said it did not expect to lay off any of the 1,500 workers with jobs tied to Scotchgard.</p>
        <p>The company said that most Scotchgard products, primarily fabric and upholstery protectors, would be phased out by the end of the year. Some Scotchgard fabric and rug cleaners are unaffected.</p>
        <p>The company, which is also known as the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, said that it discovered in 1998 that the chemical compound used to make many Scotchgard products, perfluorooctanyl, was pervasive; it persisted for years in the environment, and could even be found in human blood, at very low levels.</p>
        <p>The company said the presence of the chemical compound in human blood at low levels was not harmful, but Mr. Coyne said that ''with extremely high doses you are going to see effects.'' He also said the production of the compounds had very little effect on the environment.</p>
        <p>Officials of 3M said they ran exhaustive tests on animals and humans and found no adverse health effects. But because the compounds were persistent in the environment and in human blood, the company said it alerted regulators and began working to come up with alternative compounds.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, however, the company said it learned that an alternative would take years, and so it decided to phase out many of the Scotchgard products and focus on creating new lines.</p>
        <p>Linda Greer, senior scientist at the nonprofit environmental group Natural Resources Defense Council in Washington, told Reuters that she applauded 3M's action. Scotchgard ''really is a household name,'' she said. ''It takes guts to do that.''</p>
        <p>The decision to drop Scotchgard is expected to affect many other commercial products that use the chemical compound, including Teflon, which is made by DuPont. Officials of 3M declined to give a list of products made by other companies using the compound. But 3M said many other companies use the compounds found in Scotchgard as soil, oil and water repellent, and as coatings for oil and grease resistance on paper packaging.</p>
        <p>The company said it was striving to be environmentally friendly. ''This was a great product that was made to last, but that's also an environmental problem,'' said Mary Auvin, a 3M spokeswoman. ''We don't want things around that last for a long time.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
