<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discovering the Finer Side of Rum</title>
    <meta content="17WINE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rum</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5D81E3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discovering the Finer Side of Rum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial column on rum; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FELLOW on the Internet says that he has collected 3,688 different rum labels from 81 countries. If he's correct (and he offers to show his collection to anyone interested), then there are probably more rums than there are brands of beer.</p>
        <p>More conservative accounts put the number of rums around the world at about 1,500, which is still impressive. The point is that rum has become, in numbers at least, a major player in the spirits world, more in league with whiskey than with elegant rivals like Cognac, Armagnac and Calvados.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FELLOW on the Internet says that he has collected 3,688 different rum labels from 81 countries. If he's correct (and he offers to show his collection to anyone interested), then there are probably more rums than there are brands of beer.</p>
        <p>More conservative accounts put the number of rums around the world at about 1,500, which is still impressive. The point is that rum has become, in numbers at least, a major player in the spirits world, more in league with whiskey than with elegant rivals like Cognac, Armagnac and Calvados.</p>
        <p>Bacardi alone produces more than 20 million cases of rum a year in distilleries in Puerto Rico, Mexico, Spain and the Bahamas, at least half of them sold in this country. In fact, Bacardi rum from Puerto Rico is the largest-selling single brand of any kind of spirits, with white rum outselling the darker varieties by about three to one.</p>
        <p>Rum leads a double life -- triple, actually. There are dark, aged rums, prized by connoisseurs; there are white, almost flavorless rums, used for mixed drinks; and there are flavored rums, like Seagram's wildly popular Captain Morgan, which are livened up with spices and fruit flavors like banana and mango.</p>
        <p>Light rums, most of them from the Virgin Islands and Puerto Rico, are made in big commercial plants. The connoisseurs' rums are often made in small stills and aged for years in oak barrels. Technically, these rums are brandies, like Cognac and Armagnac, and like fine brandies, they can improve for half a century or more.</p>
        <p>Some of the best include Bacardi Anejo; Appleton Estate Extra 12 Year Old, from Jamaica; Barbancourt 15 Year Old Reserve, from Haiti; Barcelo Grand Anejo, from the Dominican Republic; Mount Gay Extra Old, from Barbados; Flor de Cana Centenario 12 Year Old, from Nicaragua; St.-James Hors d'Age, from Martinique; and Demerara Eldorado, 15 Year Old, from Guyana.</p>
        <p>The price range is $30 to $250, depending on age and scarcity. This year, Bacardi will introduce 8 Millennium, a limited edition rum at $750 a bottle.</p>
        <p>What distinguishes these rums are smoothness, elegance and deep, rich flavor.</p>
        <p>Cuban rums are banned in the United States, but like Cuban cigars, they turn up in private collections.</p>
        <p>All rum is made from sugar or, more precisely and more often, from the molasses that is a byproduct of sugar production. It all started after the Spanish introduced sugar in Cuba, soon after Columbus discovered the island in 1492. Gradually, sugar became the major Caribbean crop. Shipping it as rum was more profitable than shipping it as raw sugar, much as, in the 18th century, whiskey was the most profitable way to ship corn from the American frontier to the Eastern Seaboard.</p>
        <p>Before corn whiskey became the drink of choice, rum, originally known as rumbullion, was America's favorite spirit. In 1769, Thomas Jefferson, then 24, listed the contents of the wine cellar in his new home, Monticello: 15 bottles of Madeira, 4 of ''Lisbon wine for common use,'' 54 bottles of cider and 83 of rum.</p>
        <p>In Colonial days, molasses was shipped to distilleries in Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Connecticut to be made into rum. The colonists drank a lot of it, but much was shipped out as part of the triangular trade, which took New England rum to Africa to exchange for slaves to work in the cane fields, harvesting sugar to make more molasses. New England distillers were, as one historian said, ''the central bankers of the slave trade.''</p>
        <p>Before World War I, rum was the favorite bar drink of Paris cafes. French ports like Bordeaux and Nantes still look back proudly on their long histories in the wine trade but speak less of their profitable years in the rum and slave trade. Like the New Englanders, they traded their rum for slaves in Africa.</p>
        <p>Somehow, rum has survived its unsavory past and in recent years has shown gains on the popular level and among connoisseurs. Today, most rum is distilled in the West Indies, then shipped to this country. Major brands, like Bacardi and Mount Gay, ship much of their production for the American market here for bottling.</p>
        <p>Along with its traditional sources in the Caribbean, rum is now made in Brazil, Reunion, Madagascar, Indonesia, Australia and even New Orleans. An impressive collection of old rums is to be found in, of all places, a Paris fish restaurant, Prunier. There, Jean-Claude Vrinat, who is better known for his other restaurant, Taillevent, has assembled a list of rums, all from Martinique, dating from 1885.</p>
        <p>In this country, almost every major city has at least one shop, usually a knowledgeable wine merchant, that stocks old rums. In New York, it is Park Avenue Liquors. Besides Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands and Barbados, rum producers include Haiti, Jamaica, Hawaii, Guyana, Guadeloupe, Martinique, Venezuela, Trinidad, the Dominican Republic and Guatemala.</p>
        <p>Older rums are invariably darker rums. Some of the color comes from the barrels in which the liquor is aged, but some comes from caramel and other additives. Like Cognac, rum can be darkened with color.</p>
        <p>It's a pity to use fine old rums in mixed drinks. They should be savored with, at the most, a little ice. The favorite drink among Caribbean rum fanciers is the simple rum punch, in which several ounces of a good rum -- not a great rum -- are mixed with the juice of half a lime and some sugar or cane syrup.</p>
        <p>The daiquiris that Ernest Hemingway allegedly drank by the half-dozen at the Floridita in Havana are a Cuban invention. They are named after a town in eastern Cuba but were apparently created with gringos in mind.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
