<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cruiserheads, and the Big, Bare Bruisers They Love</title>
    <meta content="17KATZ$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz, Marty</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6D81738F934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cruiserheads, and the Big, Bare Bruisers They Love</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTY KATZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Katz, Marty</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Marty Katz on Toyota Land Cruiser FJ40 series; car, which was imported into US between 1958 and 1983, has cultlike following; photo (Special section, Cars) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME vehicles beget cultlike followings: the Toyota Land Cruiser, for example. To a generation of explorers, adventurers, mercenaries and photojournalists -- real and would-be -- this is the object of their desire. Not the curvy, comfortable and expensive models of the last decade, but the heavy, ungraceful, boxy bruisers imported to the United States between 1958 and 1990.</p>
        <p>These were vehicles built to last, to be driven over rough terrain and repaired by nonmechanics in the outback. You can abuse these war horses. You can equip them with strong roof racks, grille guards, side bars, big tires, auxiliary lighting and the ultimate badge of off-road intent, winches  front and back. Then, you can gather at some ''Cruiserhead'' oasis -- the Moab desert in Utah is popular right now -- and put your machinery to the test, stopping only to rest a front tire on a boulder while you swap stories about who got stuck, how badly and where.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME vehicles beget cultlike followings: the Toyota Land Cruiser, for example. To a generation of explorers, adventurers, mercenaries and photojournalists -- real and would-be -- this is the object of their desire. Not the curvy, comfortable and expensive models of the last decade, but the heavy, ungraceful, boxy bruisers imported to the United States between 1958 and 1990.</p>
        <p>These were vehicles built to last, to be driven over rough terrain and repaired by nonmechanics in the outback. You can abuse these war horses. You can equip them with strong roof racks, grille guards, side bars, big tires, auxiliary lighting and the ultimate badge of off-road intent, winches  front and back. Then, you can gather at some ''Cruiserhead'' oasis -- the Moab desert in Utah is popular right now -- and put your machinery to the test, stopping only to rest a front tire on a boulder while you swap stories about who got stuck, how badly and where.</p>
        <p>The FJ40 series, imported between 1958 and 1983, is a stubby vehicle that looks a bit like an old Jeep -- but don't even whisper that word around Cruiserheads, who sport ''Friends don't let friends drive Jeeps'' bumper stickers. And for those who drive Cruisers, the ride is more than a trip from here to there.</p>
        <p>''I fold the windshield forward and it feels like a four-wheel motorcycle,'' said Charlie Hunter, an ex-Marine who hauls supplies for his boat up and down the bank by his dock in Annapolis, Md., in his rusty '73 FJ40. ''People pull me over three or four times a month to ask me about it. Nobody ever said a word when I drove my wife's '97.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunter, an airplane broker, keeps an even rustier '73 for its parts.</p>
        <p>Rust-buckets from the FJ40 series can be bought for just a few thousand dollars. But many are bought to be rebuilt, and when a cultist's heart takes over, tens of thousands of dollars can seem like a reasonable price.</p>
        <p>James Asti, who owns the 4 x 4 Connection, a customizing and repair business for four-wheel-drive vehicles, especially Land Cruisers, in Sterling, Va., explains that renovation can mean completely replacing a rusty body, a common 40-series problem. Replacement bodies can be fiberglass or Kevlar, for that bulletproof feeling.</p>
        <p>Tom O'Neill, a lawyer in Arlington, Va.,  has spent about $18,000 rebuilding and outfitting a very rusty 1978 FJ40 that he bought for $1,500. It is a project he works on with his daughter, Koren, 21. ''I drive it around school and off-road whenever I can find a place, but also to parties,'' Ms. O'Neill said. ''I get some funny looks when I get out of a hard-core off-road truck all dressed up. The guys are jealous.''</p>
        <p>Restored FJ40 Cruisers have been offered for $20,000 to $40,000. Easily modified -- tops can be removed and a host of added options, like roll cages and roof racks -- they are sought after by dedicated off-roaders. Their short wheelbase makes them ideal for boulder and crevice crawling.</p>
        <p>The more common finds these days, however, are the larger, later Land Cruisers.  The FJ60 series, imported from '80 to '90, has been described as ''a big shoe box on wheels.'' For a long time, it has been favored by photographers, large suburban families and small third world armies. Now that vehicles of that era are facing expensive repairs, like front-end overhauls, and the original owners' Little League teams have gone to college, FJ60 Cruisers can be snapped up for $5,000 to $15,000.</p>
        <p>Prices, however, do not always correlate with quality. Well-maintained, rust-free 90,000-mile ''moms' taxis'' that have never left the pavement can be bought for $9,500 from a seller who is no longer in love with a Cruiser. Meanwhile, modified and field-repaired Cruisers with 200,000 hard off-road miles might cost $14,000 from a more emotional seller.</p>
        <p>Dangers abound for buyers of used Cruisers, though. Some FJ60 and FJ62 Cruisers can look great, have all their oil-change records and still be black holes into which a lot of money can be thrown.</p>
        <p>Watching Ed Cooke, the head mechanic at 4 x 4 Connection, dissect a clean-looking 1988 FJ62 during a prepurchase evaluation produced an indication of the risks for potential Cruiser owners. That vehicle, it turned out, needed $6,000 of work. Mr. Cooke keeps a photograph on the wall of a cylinder head filled with handfuls of black crud from a new-looking Cruiser that broke a proud buyer's heart when it threw a rod; the oil, it seemed, had never been changed.</p>
        <p>A compression check can help gauge the condition of the engine, which, though clean, could have a warped or a cracked head or a blown gasket. Transmissions and engine seals can be leaking. Steering components might be worn. Fixing parts on a 4,700-pound vehicle that is designed to haul itself and its cargo around rough terrain is more expensive than fixing the same things on a lighter-duty vehicle.</p>
        <p>A glance at how high the body rides over the tires is instructive: only a few inches can signal a tired suspension that needs to be replaced ($2,100 for the best off-road job), while a truck that rides higher than normal could have had a lifted suspension for serious off-road use, which might mean a hard life.</p>
        <p>Before a potential purchase can be inspected, of course, there is the matter of finding it, which is much harder than finding, say, a '93 Honda. But in researching this story, the new way to match buyers and cars became apparent. A number of Land Cruiser Web sites have for-sale ads, and sites like cars.com gather classified ads from around the country -- like the one for a 1989 FJ62 (this is the 1988 to 1990 fuel-injected series) in Ellicott City, Md., 39 miles from my home.</p>
        <p>When I interviewed the owners, they would not let me leave without making an offer. This '89 Cruiser had 107,000 miles, b ut was a tired, faded red and looked like an old car (especially next to the new Mercedes-Benz in the garage), and the owners, two doctors whose children had gone to college, wanted it gone. Other interested parties were on the way -- no time for a compression test or trip to the mechanic.</p>
        <p>I drove it fast on the highway, screeched around some turns and stomped on the brakes. It accelerated and handled surprisingly well, and it made no funny noises in four-wheel drive. When I drove a front wheel onto a curb and looked underneath with a flashlight, I saw no rust, no leaks and good tires. It also had a current inspection certificate. For $8,250, it was mine.</p>
        <p>Luckily, a postpurchase checkup by Mr. Cooke revealed no engine trouble, and the 100,000-mile maintenance was completed for under $1,000. Cruiser fans don't often  follow established roads.</p>
        <p>Marty Katz is a writer and photographer who lives in Baltimore.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marty Katz is a writer and photographer who lives in Baltimore.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
