<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons; The Internet and Schools: A Vision and the Reality</title>
    <meta content="17LESS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DD1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons; The Internet and Schools: A Vision and the Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barnaby Feder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lessons column discusses use of computers as learning tool in schools but says they cannot serve replacements for teachers; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like a new-age Atlas, the computer is primed and ready to carry the world of education on its shoulders, or so it looked in the pamphlets, product demonstrations and displays that some 150 educational technology companies and school systems showed off at a recent exposition in New York.</p>
        <p>The technology promoters see a world where record-keeping is simplified, innovative lesson plans from around the country are freely posted on the Internet, misbehaving children become enthusiastic students and test scores soar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like a new-age Atlas, the computer is primed and ready to carry the world of education on its shoulders, or so it looked in the pamphlets, product demonstrations and displays that some 150 educational technology companies and school systems showed off at a recent exposition in New York.</p>
        <p>The technology promoters see a world where record-keeping is simplified, innovative lesson plans from around the country are freely posted on the Internet, misbehaving children become enthusiastic students and test scores soar.</p>
        <p>The vision includes parents using the Internet to monitor their children's grades, assignments and extracurricular activities, and schools forging lively electronic links to local governments, businesses, clubs and elderly people. Teachers swap creative tips in private electronic chat rooms and on e-mail bulletin boards.</p>
        <p>For a final feel-good twist, there is clever Web-based accounting software that sends a rebate to the school when a student, local business or even distant alumnus goes shopping at popular Internet sites like L. L. Bean, Toys ''R'' Us and Office Max.</p>
        <p>Pieces of this vision are already in place in thousands of schools. Moreover, as a business technology reporter, I've seen enough of the coming innovations in various laboratories to be confident that today's claims will look tame by the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>Still, the reality is far from the vision even in relatively well-off districts. The show did more to fuel my fears than my hopes.</p>
        <p>The problem is not one of access to the technology. So-called Internet ''portals'' like the Family Education Network (www.FEN.com), Lightspan (www.lightspan.com) and Bigchalk (www.bigchalk.com) provide many free Internet services to teachers, parents and students to attract traffic for their advertisers. Impoverished districts like East Orange, N.J., and Lawrence, Mass., have aggressively and successfully pursued grant money for equipment and software.</p>
        <p>But it is hard to shake the feeling that the investment in technology is often Plan B, the option that politicians and administrators go for when no one can figure out how to get the money needed to recruit more and better teachers, reduce class size and repair crumbling schools. Unfortunately, using computers and the Internet effectively is a truly daunting management challenge -- a lesson that corporate America relearns daily at frightful cost. School districts are in way over their heads.</p>
        <p>As many of the technology vendors at the show readily agreed, teachers and students need more time and training than they are getting to exploit the computer's potential. Some of the strongest testimony came in offhand remarks by participants in model programs who displayed their projects at the show.</p>
        <p>''A scattered few teachers outside of the technology teachers know how to take advantage of the capabilities we have,'' said Greg Ordun, a senior at Montgomery High School in Skilman, N.J., who is Webmaster for his school's Internet site. Moreover, although Skilman is a wealthy suburb of Princeton and is bristling with home computers -- the Ordun family has nine, with Internet jacks in every room -- Greg said that ''a small percentage'' of the high school's students pay attention to the Web site, and some do not even know it exists.</p>
        <p>Many teachers and administrators are overwhelmed by the rapidly changing landscape, said David F. Warlick, a consultant based in Raleigh, N.C.</p>
        <p>''We all know the classroom is already full,'' said Mr. Warlick, after running through the problems of large classes and the many demands that teachers face. ''It is an overstressed puzzle. How do we fit more in?''</p>
        <p>The dangers are frequently discussed in education circles. Linking schools to the Internet clearly presents new privacy issues, like controlling access to classroom chat sites and children's records. Teachers have to be sure that students looking for information about the president go to www.whitehouse.gov, not www.whitehouse.com, which is a pornographic site. Safety and decency concerns aside, while the Internet opens new vistas for research, it also creates new opportunities to waste time accumulating false or misleading information.</p>
        <p>Other problems are more subtle. As Jeremy Rifkin says in his new book, ''The Age of Access'' (Jeremy P. Tarcher/Putnam), the Internet may link students to a wider world, but life online needs to be surrounded with physical activity connected to it. Otherwise, students are unlikely to develop empathy for other people or the environment, a connection that Mr. Rifkin rightly singles out as a prerequisite for a healthy society.</p>
        <p>The challenge of getting that balance right is why new technology cannot, in the end, compensate for a shortage of creative, motivated and well-trained teachers and administrators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
