<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eritrean Town Is Empty After Ethiopians Take Control</title>
    <meta content="Y17ETH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Eritrea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Eritrea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Eritrea</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1D81F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eritrean Town Is Empty After Ethiopians Take Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>SHAMBIKO, Eritrea, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ethiopia takes reporters on tour of territory captured since it mounted offensive in border dispute with Eritrea; says it wants to end war quickly because of cost; tour shows fighting continues; Eritrea denies Ethiopia has pushed far into its territory, holding lines remain fluid; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This town apparently picked up and fled in a hurry. Someone even left behind an artificial leg that lay on the main street today along with school books and the empty ration tins of a new occupying army.</p>
        <p>There is little that Ethiopia and Eritrea, former allies at war on the Horn of Africa, can agree on along their disputed border. But no one doubts that this now empty town belongs to Eritrea -- or that Ethiopia now controls it as part of what appears to be a successful drive of its troops into Eritrea in the latest flare-up of fighting in the two-year-old war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This town apparently picked up and fled in a hurry. Someone even left behind an artificial leg that lay on the main street today along with school books and the empty ration tins of a new occupying army.</p>
        <p>There is little that Ethiopia and Eritrea, former allies at war on the Horn of Africa, can agree on along their disputed border. But no one doubts that this now empty town belongs to Eritrea -- or that Ethiopia now controls it as part of what appears to be a successful drive of its troops into Eritrea in the latest flare-up of fighting in the two-year-old war.</p>
        <p>Outsiders rarely travel to the Ethiopian side of the front. But in recent days, Ethiopia has been working to promote what it sees as an early set of victories in a war that it says it wants to end quickly because it costs too much for a poor country where eight million people face severe food shortages.</p>
        <p>Today, the Ethiopian military took reporters around the territory that it says it has captured since opening an offensive on Friday. Ethiopia says some of the area was invaded by Eritrea two years ago and some was plainly Eritrean. A helicopter buzzed above a latticework of trenches and bunkers, some 30 miles long. They were all empty, Ethiopia said, because of a three-pronged assault that led to a major retreat.</p>
        <p>Military officials showed off 471 people who they said were Eritrean prisoners of war. And the officials stopped along a roadside lined with perhaps 15 corpses, bloated in the baking sun, that they said were Eritrean troops.</p>
        <p>But the tour showed, too, that the war, widely considered one of the deadliest, is far from over. Artillery boomed from the direction of Barentu, a town deep in Eritrea that is the scene of the fiercest fighting.</p>
        <p>As an Ethiopian ground commander, Col. Ghebre Kidane, walked up a ridge to a half-dozen Eritrean corpses, a fighter jet streaked overhead, releasing a tail of flares over land that Ethiopia said it securely possessed. A bomb exploded on a nearby hillside. Even the colonel flinched.</p>
        <p>''So far, there has been no Eritrean plane that has penetrated our defenses,'' he said a later, trying to piece together what had just happened. ''At the same time, an Ethiopian plane would not have dropped a bomb.''</p>
        <p>The plane was, in fact, an Eritrean MIG, possibly trying to take out an artillery position.</p>
        <p>Eritrea denies that Ethiopia has pushed far into its territory, saying the lines remain fluid. It also says Ethiopia has suffered huge casualties. ''The victory that Ethiopia is boasting about is proving illusory,'' the Foreign Ministry said in a statement today.</p>
        <p>Despite the Ethiopian gains, in fact, the front here is probably not the most important of the three major combat zones. Ethiopia has yet to make a serious attack on the center front, near Zalembessa, which is far more heavily fortified because it provides a possible route to the capital, Asmara.</p>
        <p>But the Ethiopians do appear to be moving toward it, taking towns along the way and, meantime, cutting off a major western front supply line. Moreover, Ethiopian military officials say they expect a counteroffensive at any moment. ''Still,'' Colonel Kidane said, ''even now, they are trying to regroup to launch a counteroffensive. They will try.''</p>
        <p>Ethiopia and Eritrea had been close allies, whose leaders had fought side by side to oust the military dictatorship of Mengistu Haile Mariam. They succeeded in 1991. Two years later, Eritrea, for years the northernmost province of Ethiopia, officially gained its independence.</p>
        <p>But the close relationship soured, largely because of economic issues. In May 1998, fighting broke out in the Badme region after Eritrean troops had taken over an area that they said was theirs. In their earlier friendship, the two nations had not marked the border.</p>
        <p>It has been an odd war. The fighting has broken out only sporadically. The border, 620 miles long, is remote and practically barren. So it has had little effect on the outside world.</p>
        <p>But the United Nations Security Council and the nations' allies have been nonetheless concerned because of the enormous loss of life. At least 20,000 soldiers are estimated to have died since 1998.</p>
        <p>There was little evidence today of huge casualties, though each nation has claimed to have killed, wounded or taken prisoner 25,000 people since Friday. From the air and the ground, it was possible to see no more than 15 bodies. One explanation may be that Eritrea appears to have called for a retreat fairly early in the fighting, after Ethiopian soldiers had penetrated their trenches from two points and attacked from behind.</p>
        <p>One prisoner of war, Zerai Tesfai, 27, an elementary school teacher, said the trenches were pounded by planes, tanks and mortars on Friday. But he said he only saw three or four dead before he was captured hours later. ''We were not expecting it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Tesfai added, he does not want to keep fighting, saying, ''I want a peaceful solution.''</p>
        <p>Ethiopian soldiers said they had found something in the trenches emphatically not dead, a 1-month-old boy. Many women are in the Eritrean army, and the baby may have indicated just how the war has become a part of normal life in Ethiopia and Eritrea over two years.</p>
        <p>''I got the feeling that he lived there,'' said Ibrahim Suliman, 35, an Ethiopian soldier who saw the baby being carried from the trench on Sunday night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
