<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Helen Thomas, Washington Fixture, Resigns as U.P.I. Reporter</title>
    <meta content="Y17UPI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Press International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">News World Communications Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unification Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Helen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sun Myung Moon (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz, Lee Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DF1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Helen Thomas, Washington Fixture, Resigns as U.P.I. Reporter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Helen Thomas, 79, unofficial dean of White House reporters, abruptly resigns from United Press International after news service is acquired by News World Communications Inc, which was founded by Rev Sun Myung Moon, leader of Unification Church; Lee Michael Katz resigns as UPI's international editor; says Thomas's resignation is due to acquisition; Pres Clinton comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Helen Thomas, a White House reporter since John F. Kennedy was president, abruptly resigned from United Press International today, one day after the news service was acquired.</p>
        <p>Arnaud de Borchgrave, the news service's president and chief executive officer, announced Ms. Thomas's departure ''with great regret and sadness.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Helen Thomas, a White House reporter since John F. Kennedy was president, abruptly resigned from United Press International today, one day after the news service was acquired.</p>
        <p>Arnaud de Borchgrave, the news service's president and chief executive officer, announced Ms. Thomas's departure ''with great regret and sadness.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas broke into journalism in 1943 as a radio writer for the news service. She had enough energy and persistence to overcome a male-dominated journalism field in which women were consigned to write society news while men went after the ''real'' stories and bragged of their exploits later over cigars and whiskey.</p>
        <p>One of nine children of Lebanese-born immigrants, Helen Thomas started working for United Press a year after graduating from what is now Wayne State University in Detroit. She began covering federal agencies in Washington in the 1950's, and in November 1960 she was assigned to cover President-elect John F. Kennedy.</p>
        <p>She was given the White House beat in 1961 and has been there since, becoming the unofficial dean of White House reporters. She has often been seen asking the first question at presidential news conferences and ending the sessions by saying, ''Thank you, Mr. President.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas has traveled around the world with Presidents Richard M. Nixon, Gerald R. Ford, Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, George Bush and Bill Clinton. She became famous for occasionally annoying, and now and then amusing, the chief executives with her questions.</p>
        <p>''Presidents come and go,'' President Clinton said today. ''But Helen's been here for 40 years now.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas, 79, said in a statement released by U.P.I.: ''I do not intend to stay. United Press International is a great news agency. It has made a remarkable mark in the annals of American journalism and has left a superb legacy for future journalists. I wish the new owners all the best, great stories and happy landings.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas's statement said nothing about U.P.I.'s acquisition by News World Communications Inc., which was founded by the Rev. Sun Myung Moon, leader of the Unification Church. News World Communications publishes The Washington Times, a favorite of conservative readers in Washington.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. de Borchgrave and News World Communications said U.P.I. would continue to have editorial independence under the new ownership. U.P.I. said Ms. Thomas planned to pursue new ventures. Ms. Thomas could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>But Lee Michael Katz, who quit today as U.P.I.'s international editor, said he was not surprised by Ms. Thomas's departure and had no doubt about the reasons. ''Look at the timing of this, and Helen's devotion,'' Mr. Katz said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Katz called his own decision to resign ''a no-brainer'' and said, ''I cannot work for the new owners.''</p>
        <p>United Press merged with the International News Service to form United Press International in 1958. In its prime, U.P.I. competed fiercely with The Associated Press and other major news organizations, but in recent years it has been hobbled by dwindling profits and frequent management changes.</p>
        <p>United Press International has closed many of its far-flung bureaus. As of Monday, it had 157 employees, Mr. de Borchgrave said. He added that no layoffs were contemplated. As for Ms. Thomas, he said her name was ''indelibly engraved in the history of our profession.''</p>
        <p>With Ms. Thomas's departure, it is not immediately clear who supplants her as the senior White House reporter, said Susan Page of U.S.A. Today, president of the White House Correspondents Association.</p>
        <p>Not long ago, Ms. Thomas helped Mr. Clinton poke fun at his lame-duck status. In a self-spoofing video he made, Mr. Clinton holds forth in the White House briefing room and asks if there are any questions.</p>
        <p>The camera then focuses on the only reporter present, a sleeping Helen Thomas. Snapping awake, she asks, ''Are you still here?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
