<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Pursuit of Cybercriminals, Real Detectives Rely on Amateurs</title>
    <meta content="17CYBE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D81F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Pursuit of Cybercriminals, Real Detectives Rely on Amateurs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Computer experts outside law enforcement become vital in pursuit of Internet criminals; some have escalated their role from pointing law enforcement officials to leads to accumulating evidence to identify actual suspects, including malicious hackers and virus writers; provide aid in areas where law enforcement officials lack resources and sometimes expertise; police agencies have even deputized cybersleuths and worked with them in key parts of probes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Within hours after a destructive computer program began circulating this month, borne by an e-mail message marked ''I Love You,'' a handful of high-tech detectives around the globe leaped into action.</p>
        <p>Scrutinizing clues left in the programming code, and pursuing evidence accumulated in hidden corners of cyberspace, the detectives homed in on several suspects in the Philippines. And within days, Onel A. de Guzman, whose name the investigators had turned up, came forward and said it was possible he had unleashed the rogue program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Within hours after a destructive computer program began circulating this month, borne by an e-mail message marked ''I Love You,'' a handful of high-tech detectives around the globe leaped into action.</p>
        <p>Scrutinizing clues left in the programming code, and pursuing evidence accumulated in hidden corners of cyberspace, the detectives homed in on several suspects in the Philippines. And within days, Onel A. de Guzman, whose name the investigators had turned up, came forward and said it was possible he had unleashed the rogue program.</p>
        <p>But the detectives are unlikely to testify at trial, or receive official commendation. That is because they are not police officers, but ordinary citizens, like a retired software entrepreneur in Cambridge, Mass., and two Swedish computer security experts.</p>
        <p>They are among a growing number of Net habitues turned cyber-sleuths whose work has become vital to the pursuit of Internet criminals. In the spirit of members of a neighborhood watch program, they protect their turf on the Internet and point law enforcement officials to leads. And some have escalated their role from tipster to sleuth, accumulating evidence to identify actual suspects, including malicious hackers, virus writers and online child pornographers.</p>
        <p>Armed with home computers and technical expertise, the cybersleuths themselves say there are only a few hundred of them. But these amateur detectives have pursued suspects in some of the most highly publicized cybercrimes, assisting in an area where law enforcement officials say they lack resources and sometimes expertise. Police agencies have even deputized cybersleuths and worked with them in the most critical parts of investigations.</p>
        <p>As private citizens, however, the cyberdetectives can also be hard to control and monitor. And law enforcement officials say that sometimes they act less like members of a neighborhood watch than like vigilantes. ''It's like a computer game,'' said Paul E. Coggins, United States Attorney in Dallas. ''They're playing catch the crook.''</p>
        <p>The authorities have relied on citizens with technical expertise for some time. But Mr. Coggins said he now sees a higher proportion of citizens seeking to pitch in on cyberspace-related crime fighting than he does in the physical world, perhaps because cyberdetectives never have to leave home. ''Some people who have come to our attention are spending an inordinate amount of time doing this, then calling law enforcement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And even as federal and state law enforcement agencies are beefing up the personnel and technical resources devoted to investigating computer crime, many say they still welcome the outside assistance.</p>
        <p>''Law enforcement is more and more reaching out to the private sector for knowledge, for training,'' said Michael G. McCartney, special investigator for the high-technology crime unit of the New York State attorney general's office, who said he keeps several high-tech experts on his informant payroll. ''We all have to work together in fighting this thing.''</p>
        <p>Many of the sleuths say that what drives them is not an urge to play police officer, but rather a simple desire to protect cyberspace. ''As computer geeks, we felt the Internet belonged to us,'' said Kevin Patterson, founder of Ethical Hackers Against Pedophilia, a group that works with law enforcement to track down online child pornographers. ''Just like saying, 'You're not going to sell crack on our corner,' we don't want you to distribute child pornography on our Internet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson, a 33-year-old computer network administrator in Knoxville, Tenn., founded Ethical Hackers in 1997 when he came across a lurid picture of a 4-year-old girl in an unrelated discussion forum. ''It reminded me of my niece,'' he said, and he vowed to hunt down online purveyors of child pornography.</p>
        <p>Impassioned foes of child pornography are common in the physical world, too, but what is remarkable in cyberspace is the interaction between citizens and the police, as Mr. Patterson's case illustrates.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the state of New York started Operation Sabbatical, an investigation of a group suspected of circulating child pornography online. Strapped for resources and expertise, the state turned to Ethical Hackers, a group whose members identified themselves online with names like Chalk, Sgt. Rock, Merc, Tattoo Man and Conjure.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCartney, from New York's high-tech crime unit, said he did background checks on the men first. ''We traveled to some of their homes and inspected their computers,'' he said, making sure none of them were child pornographers.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 28, 1998, law enforcement officials obtained 21 search warrants in 14 states and 4 countries, while the members of Ethical Hackers played central roles from their home computers. While warrant-bearing police knocked on doors of suspected members of the ring, the members of Ethical Hackers effectively barred access to a discussion area in cyberspace where child pornographers were known to congregate, flooding it with meaningless data to render it unusable. The idea was that if the members could not communicate, they would not be able to warn one another about the raids.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCartney said the idea of using private citizens in this way was so unusual that the F.B.I. declined to participate. But he said his team decided it needed to employ the technical expertise of the Ethical Hackers. ''I didn't wake up one day and know everything there is to know about high-tech investigations,'' he said. Still, he said the situation was unusual. ''We don't want other vigilantes thinking they can do the same thing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Often, the arrangements between citizens and the police appear to be less formal. Richard M. Smith, a software entrepreneur in Cambridge, Mass., who made a name for himself as a private citizen sleuth who helped track down the author of the Melissa virus in February 1999, said he had periodic discussions with law enforcement officials about cybercrimes, some discussions started by the authorities and others by him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith refused to comment on whether he was contacted by the F.B.I. after the I Love You program began spreading, but he did say he started working on the case minutes after he learned about it on May 4. Mr. Smith looked at the source code -- the instructions and text -- buried inside the rogue program and discovered an e-mail address, ispyder@mail.com. He then got in touch with the president of the company that operates that e-mail service and urged him to contact the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>In the following days, Mr. Smith said he searched Internet news groups and Web sites for key words that he had found in the source code of the program and pieced together evidence suggesting that the program originated in the Philippines. He then publicized his findings in conversations with reporters. Mr. Smith said he had time to devote to these tasks because he was on sabbatical. ''It's fun,'' he said of his motivation. ''It's a game.''</p>
        <p>On May 7, Mr. Smith joined forces with two Swedes, Jonathan James, 19, and Fredrik Bjorck, 27, with whom he had collaborated in the Melissa case. They pursued what Mr. Smith said was a crucial discovery by Mr. James, namely that the name of the hacker group GrammerSoft, which was embedded in the source code, was also embedded in the source code of a virus called Myckl.</p>
        <p>In turn, the Myckl virus included the name of students at Amable Mendoza Aguiluz Computer College in Manila, including Mr. de Guzman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said he did not know whether he and his cohorts were responsible for directing the F.B.I. and Philippine authorities to Mr. de Guzman, who surfaced last Thursday. Jim Margolin, a spokesman for the F.B.I.'s New York office, which is leading the bureau's investigation, said the agency had consulted with the three men and had done so in the past. ''I can't characterize the value of the information or how instrumental it's been in this case,'' he said. ''We've found their information to be useful in the past.''</p>
        <p>But however grateful law enforcement officials may be, the cyber sleuths often leave them uneasy. Some law enforcement officials worry that amateur detectives may break the law themselves when hunting down cybercriminals. Police officers say the concern is particularly acute with child pornography foes, who have been known to shut down pornographic Web sites.</p>
        <p>Kevin A. Della-Colli, director of the Cybersmuggling Center, the online investigative arm of the United States Customs Service, said Customs often receives e-mail messages from people who forward child pornography they have downloaded from the Internet. It is illegal to download child pornography.</p>
        <p>''If you observe criminal activity, we instruct you to take down the license plate,'' Mr. Della-Colli said. ''We don't want you crawling in the back window of the house to give a detailed accounting of what they're stealing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coggins, the United States Attorney in Dallas, said private citizens could also interfere with an actual undercover investigation, or gather evidence in an illegal way that undermines a conviction. ''Any mistakes they make really come back to haunt us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The work of Joel de la Garza, a recent Stanford University graduate who now works for a computer security firm, illustrates the potential pitfalls for amateur cybersleuths, no matter how well meaning or skilled. He was working part time in Stanford's computer security office when he started tracking activities of hackers who were breaking into university computers.</p>
        <p>Among other tactics, Mr. de la Garza created programs to record conversations in chat rooms where hackers were believed to congregate. Then in February, after a spate of attacks that blocked or impeded access to major commercial Web sites, Mr. de la Garza got a tip that someone using the name Mafiaboy, thought by some private sleuths to have been involved in the attacks, was hanging out in an online system called Internet Relay Chat. Once again, Mr. de la Garza logged onto the chat room using an alias, and recorded a discussion. In this one, Mafiaboy took credit for crippling the CNN Web site.</p>
        <p>Mr. de la Garza said he turned the transcript over to the F.B.I., though he cannot be sure if it contributed to the arrest last month of a Montreal teenager in the case. But while potentially valuable evidence, the material that Mr. de la Garza gathered is ''arguably violating two-party consent'' laws that prohibit recording conversations without the other party's assent, said Mr. McCartney of the New York State attorney general's office. ''There's no clear-cut answer,'' he said. ''There are a lot of laws you have to watch out for.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. de la Garza says he never set out to be a crime fighter. ''I don't want to be a cop,'' he said. ''I just want these guys to stop messing with the Stanford computers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
