<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Democrats, Old Tensions and New Alliances</title>
    <meta content="17DUEL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFD71F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Democrats, Old Tensions and New Alliances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at Pepsi Arena in Albany as New York State Democratic Party holds its annual convention; highlight of session is nomination of Hillary Rodham Clinton for post of United States Senate; roles played at convention by leading gubernatorial hopefuls H Carl McCall and Andrew M Cuomo discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So, Assemblyman Jeff Dinowitz was asked, do you plan to attend Andrew Cuomo's reception tonight? ''You mean the one I wasn't invited to?'' he asked. ''You mean the guy whose father forgot to endorse me when I was the only anti-death-penalty Democrat in my race? I don't think so.''</p>
        <p>Two and a half years remain until the 2002 election for governor, but the jockeying for position between two Democratic hopefuls -- Mr. Cuomo, the United States housing secretary, and State Comptroller H. Carl McCall -- was on full display here as their party held its state convention. It played out in and around the Pepsi Arena with all the typical rancor of New York Democratic politics, where no grudge is forgotten and no alliance is without its perils.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So, Assemblyman Jeff Dinowitz was asked, do you plan to attend Andrew Cuomo's reception tonight? ''You mean the one I wasn't invited to?'' he asked. ''You mean the guy whose father forgot to endorse me when I was the only anti-death-penalty Democrat in my race? I don't think so.''</p>
        <p>Two and a half years remain until the 2002 election for governor, but the jockeying for position between two Democratic hopefuls -- Mr. Cuomo, the United States housing secretary, and State Comptroller H. Carl McCall -- was on full display here as their party held its state convention. It played out in and around the Pepsi Arena with all the typical rancor of New York Democratic politics, where no grudge is forgotten and no alliance is without its perils.</p>
        <p>By the night's end, there was no question that this was Mr. McCall's crowd. He has an early, imposing lead in collecting supporters among elected officials and party leaders and, as the sole trustee of the state pension funds, he is a favorite of public employee unions and retirees. As the only black person ever elected to statewide office in New York, he has a devoted following among his party's minority members.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall was one of just three speakers greeted with a standing ovation from the thousands of delegates before he said a word -- the others were Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan and the star of the evening, Hillary Rodham Clinton. By the end, he had the crowd chanting and stomping; when one faction began shouting, ''Run, Carl, run,'' he answered, ''We're going to get to that. My turn will come.''</p>
        <p>The response to Mr. Cuomo, by contrast, ranged from polite to warm, until he reached a rousing finish.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo, son of Mario M. Cuomo, the former governor, found a way to set himself apart, holding a reception after the convention on a boat in the Hudson River, with Tony Bennett providing the entertainment. That seemed to trump Mr. McCall, who had joined with the state party chairwoman, Judith Hope, and others in jointly sponsoring a less splashy event at the same time at the nearby Crowne Plaza hotel.</p>
        <p>But few pols showed up for the event on the boat, most of them opting instead to go to the hotel party, where both President Clinton and Mrs. Clinton spoke. In a sweltering hotel ballroom, party leaders and officeholders cattily handicapped the evening's performances by the potential gubernatorial rivals. It did not go unnoticed that Mr. Clinton referred generally to the crowd of elected officials, including Mr. McCall, on the dais, but singled out ''my good friend Andrew Cuomo for the wonderful job he's done'' as secretary of housing and urban development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinowitz, from the Bronx, gave the tartest of a string of remarks by people who remember long-ago run-ins with Mr. Cuomo or his father, or who have lined up firmly in the McCall camp.</p>
        <p>Assemblywoman Susan John of Rochester said she had been invited to the Cuomo affair, but added, ''I've got an early morning committee meeting tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>''Boat ride?'' State Senator Neil Breslin of Albany asked sarcastically. ''What boat ride?''</p>
        <p>Asked which event he would attend, Assemblyman Martin Luster of Ithaca rolled his eyes and said, ''Whichever one I can stand.'' That meant Mr. McCall's party, he added.</p>
        <p>Peter F. Vallone, the New York City Council speaker, said he intended to make brief appearances at both before driving home. ''I try to stay friends with everyone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Assemblywoman Nettie Mayersohn of Queens said: ''I'm trying to meet with Andrew Cuomo on housing issues. I don't want to meet with him on a boat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's speech provided some of the odder moments of the evening. As always, his speaking style bore an eerie resemblance to his father's -- a double-edged sword if ever there was one. He even borrowed a few of the former governor's lines.</p>
        <p>He talked of class division, a subject that has long since fallen out of favor even in this crowd. Of the poor, he said, ''When we raise you, we raise us all.'' He went on to say, ''When you have 1 percent of the nation owning 40 percent of the wealth, you do not have success, not yet.''</p>
        <p>There was another similarity to his father. The speakers had been given a 5-minute time limit, but Mr. Cuomo spoke for 15.</p>
        <p>The strangest part of Mr. Cuomo's address came when he spoke at length about New York State's taxes being too high. That has long been Republicans' favorite line, one they used to great effect against Mario Cuomo in 1994. In fact, the claim to fame of Gov. George E. Pataki -- the Republican whom Andrew Cuomo wants to replace -- is that he has deeply cut those taxes.</p>
        <p>Saying that taxes are too high is not exactly Democratic dogma, and the audience here tonight responded to that passage with nearly complete silence.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. McCall, too, played to class resentment, but in a different fashion. The Republicans, he said, have a ''members-only agenda,'' their ranks filled with ''people with the same shirt, the same shoes, the same tie, and the same backward view of the future.''</p>
        <p>''We don't know the secret Republican handshake,'' he said. ''We're not on their guest lists. But the difference is, we've got the people with us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall also delivered a pointed reminder of the defeat of the elder Mr. Cuomo, in a campaign that left the state party in shambles. ''You know, back in 1994, there were those who wrote our party's obituary,'' he said. ''We were down, we were in debt. We didn't even have a phone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
