<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Confessor Who Hears It All</title>
    <meta content="17MYJO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MY JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consumer Credit Counseling Service of Southern NY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gartner, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rapp, Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D6103BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Confessor Who Hears It All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GARTNER; Written with Ellen Rapp.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gartner, Walter; Rapp, Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>My Job column profiles Walter Gartner, counselor with Consumer Credit Counseling Service of Southern New York; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before I took this job I was a Nasdaq trader, and before that I was in law enforcement. I came here because I wanted to be more involved in helping people. I listen to their hardships and help them work out a plan so that they don't end up losing everything. I show them that there's hope.</p>
        <p>One client worked in a hospital and was also an actress, and she had about $15,000 in credit card debt. Within one week, her father and brother both died, and she flew to California for the funerals. When she came back to New York, she was fired from her job. She was in such bad shape she admitted herself to a psychiatric hospital and called me from there. I advised her to sell the house her father had left her, and I convinced her creditors to wait for the payments. Eventually she was able to pay them and have money to live on. She pulled through, and she's debt-free now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before I took this job I was a Nasdaq trader, and before that I was in law enforcement. I came here because I wanted to be more involved in helping people. I listen to their hardships and help them work out a plan so that they don't end up losing everything. I show them that there's hope.</p>
        <p>One client worked in a hospital and was also an actress, and she had about $15,000 in credit card debt. Within one week, her father and brother both died, and she flew to California for the funerals. When she came back to New York, she was fired from her job. She was in such bad shape she admitted herself to a psychiatric hospital and called me from there. I advised her to sell the house her father had left her, and I convinced her creditors to wait for the payments. Eventually she was able to pay them and have money to live on. She pulled through, and she's debt-free now.</p>
        <p>Sometimes people come here because they lose their job, their health. Things could be perfect for years, but God forbid something happens.</p>
        <p>I now have 430 clients. The initial consultation is free. I look at everything: debts, net income, expenses -- what they need to live and what they can cut back on. Then we see if it's worthwhile for them to participate in the plan here. Clients pay a fee of $10 to $65 a month for this service. I talk to their creditors about lowering the annual percentage rates, getting rid of late fees. I'm the negotiator. The goal is for them to become debt-free within four to five years.</p>
        <p>The range of people who come here, it blows my mind. Lots of writers, artists, actors. Cops. Executive assistants, doctors, lawyers. Financial advisers. I see a lot of teachers -- professors with Ph.D.'s. Famous models. Everything under the sky.</p>
        <p>Most clients are white collar. They come in wearing great suits. But they're behind at least $500 a month; no savings. They look good but have nothing. I also see college kids: the majority have credit card debts of $20,000 to $30,000, and they don't have a job.</p>
        <p>There are people who are depressed. They've had a layoff or a bad divorce, or they're sick of life. For them, the way to redeem themselves is to spend money. Most of my clients average eight credit cards.</p>
        <p>One woman was spending $80 a day for her lunches. I said, ''Why don't you brown-bag it?'' She said she couldn't. She worked with all these people who had trust funds. ''I have to play the role,'' she said.</p>
        <p>What's rewarding about this job is that when people leave my office they have a more realistic idea about money.</p>
        <p>There are more confessions here than in church. There was one guy who went through all his parents' money. He told them it was for his import-export business, but there was no business. He spent all their money on gambling, women, drugs. He owed well over $100,000. His parents were first-generation Chinese who had worked in sweatshops all their lives.</p>
        <p>Has my job affected me? Well, I'm single, and my thinking is: before you get serious with anyone, check their credit report.</p>
        <p>MY JOB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
