<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Tacos? No Burritos? And This Is a Mexican Place?</title>
    <meta content="17UNDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Casa Mexicana (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4D7103BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Tacos? No Burritos? And This Is a Mexican Place?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov, in $25 and Under column, reviews Casa Mexicana on Lower East Side (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT is a Mexican restaurant? Thankfully, in New York expectations have evolved to the point where this question is no longer easy to answer. From humble taquerias with just a few inexpensive dishes to fancy restaurants with ambitious, creative menus, Mexican restaurants are no longer beholden simply to cliches of burritos and margaritas. And now comes Casa Mexicana, maybe the first Mexican restaurant in New York that owes as much to hip downtown Manhattan as to Mexico City.</p>
        <p>Walk through the front door and, in the dim candlelight of the boxy dining room, you can just make out the warm, rusty orange of the walls. Hostesses in clingy black downtown fabrics show you to tables, perhaps to the large wooden communal table that bisects the room. In the rear is a bar, where patrons pause for sangria and wine before retiring later in the evening to the rosy red lounge area downstairs. A D.J. there spins tunes and burns incense, which, unfortunately, can waft upstairs. Only the patterned silver plates on the tables seem to speak of Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT is a Mexican restaurant? Thankfully, in New York expectations have evolved to the point where this question is no longer easy to answer. From humble taquerias with just a few inexpensive dishes to fancy restaurants with ambitious, creative menus, Mexican restaurants are no longer beholden simply to cliches of burritos and margaritas. And now comes Casa Mexicana, maybe the first Mexican restaurant in New York that owes as much to hip downtown Manhattan as to Mexico City.</p>
        <p>Walk through the front door and, in the dim candlelight of the boxy dining room, you can just make out the warm, rusty orange of the walls. Hostesses in clingy black downtown fabrics show you to tables, perhaps to the large wooden communal table that bisects the room. In the rear is a bar, where patrons pause for sangria and wine before retiring later in the evening to the rosy red lounge area downstairs. A D.J. there spins tunes and burns incense, which, unfortunately, can waft upstairs. Only the patterned silver plates on the tables seem to speak of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Casa Mexicana actually owes something to Paris, too, because the chef, Luis Herrera, studied at the Culinary Institute of America and uses French techniques along with Mexican ingredients. The most surprising thing about the menu is how little it resembles the usual array of Mexican street foods. The 13 main courses include four steak dishes, duck breast, sea bass, halibut and scallops, along with a couple of chicken dishes and a single pork dish. Either this is typical of an upscale Mexican establishment or it is meant to cater to New Yorkers who expect such luxuries.</p>
        <p>Either way, the Azteca steak ($17) and the sirloin Tampiquena ($18) are both fine pieces of beef, thick and crusty yet tender within. The Azteca comes with sauteed cactus paddles, while the Tampiquena comes with pinto beans and a small enchilada in a rich brown mole sauce. The duck breast ($18), served over spinach and red potatoes, is sliced thin like magret and has an excellent smoky flavor, lightly enhanced by a mild ancho chili sauce. Caramelized sea scallops ($16) are likewise perfectly cooked, though I wish the tomatillo sauce had more oomph to it.</p>
        <p>Occasionally the kitchen falls short, especially, I found after several visits, on Tuesdays, when Mr. Herrera is off. The pork tenderloin ($16), moist and shimmering in a ruddy achiote glaze, served in a poblano chili sauce, is instead dry and listless, as is the half chicken with mole poblano. The salsa, made with chipotle chilies and served free with tortilla chips, is ordinarily lively and wonderfully smoky, except on those Tuesdays, when it seems as if it had been sitting in the refrigerator too long.</p>
        <p>Guacamole ($8) is attractive enough, served in its traditional three-legged vessel, yet it was dry and dull whether Mr. Herrera was there or not. Conversely, pellizcadas ($5), little disks of fried cornmeal with toppings like chorizo, chicken or crisp bits of pork, were always lively, as were tiny half-moon quesadillas ($6), made with paper-thin, crisp tortillas, and tamalitos Oaxaquenos ($6), little tamales stuffed with chicken and served in that rich mole with sesame seeds.</p>
        <p>In the end, my feelings are mixed about Casa Mexicana. I love restaurants that don't feel compelled to follow strictures about decor and music, and I appreciate the fusing of French techniques with Mexican spices. Yet I can't help feeling that with all the beef on the menu, Casa Mexicana is playing it too safe, trading the Mexican genre for a downtown genre rather than forging its own way.</p>
        <p>My favorite dessert was a warm chocolate cake ($6) with a liquid center, topped with raspberry sauce and vanilla ice cream and surrounded by raspberries. If you've been to almost any New York restaurant in the last five years, you've no doubt encountered some variation on this dessert. It's certainly not Mexican, but it was very good.</p>
        <p>Casa Mexicana</p>
        <p>133 Ludlow Street at Rivington Street, Lower East Side; (212) 473-4100.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Azteca steak, sirloin Tampiquena, duck breast, caramelized sea scallops, pork tenderloin, pellizcadas, quesadillas, tamalitos, warm chocolate cake.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $5 to $11; main courses, $13 to $21.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Sunday through Wednesday, 11 a.m. to midnight; Thursday through Saturday, 11 a.m. to 1 a.m.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Ramp at entrance.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
