<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loves Fights. And Cliches.</title>
    <meta content="Y17BOSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lycos Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leipziger, Deidre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Robert J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFDF113BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loves Fights. And Cliches.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT J. DAVIS; Written with Deidre Leipziger.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Davis, Robert J; Leipziger, Deidre</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Boss column profiles Robert J Davis, chief executive of Lycos Inc; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I have a T-shirt framed outside my office, saying, ''You let up, you lose.'' I bought it in a barroom in my early days at Lycos. I was meeting at a hotel with some investment bankers and there was a guy playing pool and wearing this shirt. After a bit of haggling, I was able to talk the shirt off his back.</p>
        <p>That T-shirt hanging outside my office isn't just for the rest of the world to see. It's for me -- the first thing I see each morning when I come into work. I have a bunch of cliches I wrap myself around. ''Speed is life'' is another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I have a T-shirt framed outside my office, saying, ''You let up, you lose.'' I bought it in a barroom in my early days at Lycos. I was meeting at a hotel with some investment bankers and there was a guy playing pool and wearing this shirt. After a bit of haggling, I was able to talk the shirt off his back.</p>
        <p>That T-shirt hanging outside my office isn't just for the rest of the world to see. It's for me -- the first thing I see each morning when I come into work. I have a bunch of cliches I wrap myself around. ''Speed is life'' is another.</p>
        <p>I have a quasi-tech background, and I really stumbled into this business. During college, at Northeastern, I had worked at I.B.M. as a sales trainee. I.B.M. wanted to hire me as a systems engineer -- they thought I had too much of a baby face to sell for them. I said ''so long'' and drove across the country with some friends. In the fall, I got a job at G.E. in data communications. From there I went to Wang, selling data processing systems, then to Cambex, which sells disk drives and memory.</p>
        <p>My life as Lycos chief executive -- and sole employee -- began in a cubicle. It was exciting. I felt I was building something, though I wasn't sure exactly what, with an awful lot of opportunity. First, I put a computer on my desktop. Then I learned to use a PC. Meantime, I was trying to start a business. What should a logo look like? Who should the employees be, and what should they do?</p>
        <p>I am driven, single minded. As a good friend likes to say, I've fought all my life, why not one more fight? I guess that's from my inner-city background. I'm intensely competitive. Winning in all I do is very much who I am -- in sports, in business, in a simple debate with a friend.</p>
        <p>I work seven days a week, though I'm not physically in the office all that time. The word ''work'' connotes drudgery to most people; for me it's the opposite -- exhilarating. I have a wife and three kids -- a rose between two thorns, a girl between two boys. My kids' sporting or social events -- school plays, concerts, sporting events -- are important to me, and I try to be there.</p>
        <p>A best work moment is when the ratings books come out and our audience soars. A best moment was the initial public offering of my company. A best moment was when, for one brief moment, we were first. A best moment is when we have our annual employee meeting, and you capture in one room all we're doing and the sense behind it. Taking it further back, my best moment was the first computer system I sold. Every little detail resonates with me to this day.</p>
        <p>Any terrible moments? None I want to talk about.</p>
        <p>I have also been a bit of a prankster. In the old Wang days, in particular, it was rampant. Actually, it probably got out of hand. One prank was to leave a phone message for another salesman saying ''Mr. Lyons called'' and have the return number be the local zoo. We also would move cars around in the parking lot. Did that four, five days in a row, till the person would be totally baffled.</p>
        <p>I still have a bit of the prankster in me, I guess. But I don't pull stunts in the office anymore. Friends are still victims from time to time.</p>
        <p>THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
