<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.A.A. Tape Shows Controllers Searching for EgyptAir Flight</title>
    <meta content="Y17CRAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Egyptair</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Transportation Safety Board</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, James E (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DD1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.A.A. Tape Shows Controllers Searching for EgyptAir Flight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Aviation Administration releases tape of routine last conversation between crew of EgyptAir jet that crashed in Oct 1999 and air traffic controllers; tape shows controllers in New York took unusual step of asking Air France jet to detour to search for plane after jet disappeared from radar; National Transportation Safety Board chairman, James E Hall, says board, which weighed turning case over to Federal Bureau of Investigation to probe possible pilot suicide, will follow its normal probe procedure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last conversation between the crew of EgyptAir Flight 990 and air traffic controllers was numbingly routine, a transcript released today by the Federal Aviation Administration shows. But after the Boeing 767 disappeared from radar, controllers in New York took the unusual step of asking an Air France jet to detour, to see if its crew could hear an emergency signal or spot a plane in the water.</p>
        <p>The Oct. 31 crash killed all 217 people on board, and the sounds captured by the cockpit voice recorder, combined with information from the flight data recorder and from military radar, have led investigators to focus on whether the cause was pilot suicide and led officials at the National Transportation Safety Board to consider turning the case over to the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last conversation between the crew of EgyptAir Flight 990 and air traffic controllers was numbingly routine, a transcript released today by the Federal Aviation Administration shows. But after the Boeing 767 disappeared from radar, controllers in New York took the unusual step of asking an Air France jet to detour, to see if its crew could hear an emergency signal or spot a plane in the water.</p>
        <p>The Oct. 31 crash killed all 217 people on board, and the sounds captured by the cockpit voice recorder, combined with information from the flight data recorder and from military radar, have led investigators to focus on whether the cause was pilot suicide and led officials at the National Transportation Safety Board to consider turning the case over to the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
        <p>But the board's chairman, James E. Hall, said today that he expected the investigation to follow the board's normal procedure, including the release of ''factual reports,'' among them the cockpit voice recorder transcript, which contains crew conversations and cockpit sounds, sometime this summer. The transcript released today covered conversations between the crew and the air traffic controllers, and messages exchanged between control centers seeking to locate the plane.</p>
        <p>Today, in an interview, Mr. Hall said, ''I think the investigation is basically on track.'' The board has ''agreed to readdress'' issues raised by the Egyptian government about whether there could have been a mechanical cause, he said.</p>
        <p>According to the transcript released today by the F.A.A., a controller at the New York Air Route Traffic Control Center, in Ronkonkoma, N.Y., cleared the flight, from Kennedy International Airport to Cairo, to a spot over the ocean called ''dovey,'' at an altitude of 33,000 feet, at 1:41 a.m. New York time, about 20 minutes after takeoff. Thirteen seconds later, a crew member on the plane correctly read back the instructions. Six minutes after that, the  controller told the crew to change radio frequencies, and the crew member repeated that instruction, too. The first part of the crew's last transmission was marked ''unintelligible,'' by the F.A.A., followed by the standard goodbye, ''nine nine zero heavy good morning.''</p>
        <p>At 1:54 a.m., the controller said on the radio frequency that radar contact had been lost, and began trying to raise the plane by radio.</p>
        <p>The controller then checked in with Aeronautical Radio Inc., a company owned by the airlines that maintains radio contact with planes over the ocean, but the operator there said Flight 990 had not checked in.</p>
        <p>Two aircraft in the area, a Lufthansa jet and an Air Force plane, could not locate the EgyptAir flight either.</p>
        <p>The New York controller then asked that an Air France plane be diverted to near the scene, 60 miles south of Nantucket, Mass., but the crew could not see or hear anything either. That was about an hour after the crash.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
