<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Habitual Prevaricator</title>
    <meta content="23SAFI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/opinion/23SAFI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White House Travel Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DA1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Habitual Prevaricator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire Op-Ed column disputes assertions by supporters of Hillary Rodham Clinton that decision by independent counsel Robert Ray not to indict her in so-called Travelgate affair was form of exoneration; says Clinton is habitual prevaricator (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remember all the claims by Hillary Clinton's see-no-evil supporters that the decision by independent counsel Robert Ray not to prosecute her in the travel office affair ''exonerated' her?</p>
        <p>Some exoneration. We now have the full report of this egregious abuse of power and its six-year cover-up, and the evidence that she has been lying all along is damning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Remember all the claims by Hillary Clinton's see-no-evil supporters that the decision by independent counsel Robert Ray not to prosecute her in the travel office affair ''exonerated' her?</p>
        <p>Some exoneration. We now have the full report of this egregious abuse of power and its six-year cover-up, and the evidence that she has been lying all along is damning.</p>
        <p>Lest we forget, the central issue was never whether she had the right to pressure her husband's staff to fire seven longtime White House employees and direct the lucrative travel business to her Hollywood cronies and a Clinton cousin. That's just the spoils system.</p>
        <p>The Travelgate issue was and is: was her sworn denial of any ''role'' or ''input'' in the firings factually false? Did her pressure cause fearful aides to stimulate a besmearing F.B.I. investigation? Did this lead her Justice Department to bring criminal charges against people later found to be innocent? And did she and her White House minions delay, impede and increase the expense of revealing her improper involvement?</p>
        <p>The inescapable answers are yes, yes, yes and yes. Read the evidence and denials in full (oicray.com) and see how her orchestrated lying continues to this day.</p>
        <p>Asked years ago: ''did you have any role'' in the firing? She swore, ''No, I did not.'' Any ''input'' at all? ''No.'' Her testimony under oath to the House was that ''I expressed my concern,'' but ''I had no decision making role.''</p>
        <p>The truth is that Mrs. Clinton leaned on senior White House aides in eight separate conversations. Counsel Vincent Foster wrote down the heat he was getting from Hillary on the travel office: ''HRC generally appeared less than satisfied with timeliness of decision making.'' Chief of staff Mack McLarty noted ''HRC pressure,'' and explained under oath his notation meant ''I felt a pressure from the First Lady to make a decision. . . .''</p>
        <p>The head of White House administration, David Watkins, noted down ''the First Lady's insistence for immediate action'' and added, ''McLarty and I . . . both knew that there would be hell to pay if . . . we failed to take swift and decisive action in conformity with the First Lady's wishes. He then approved the decision to terminate the Travel Office staff.'' Watkins made contemporaneous note of Hillary's actual words: ''We need those people out. We need our people in. We need the slots.''</p>
        <p>Six years later, Mrs. Clinton clings to the fiction that she was blameless. She ''did not knowingly intend to influence the Travel Office decision,'' maintained her lawyer last week, ''and she was unaware that her expressions of concern might impel others to take action.''</p>
        <p>Do you believe that absurdity? Mainly because the boss's wife was not an elected official empowered to give a direct dismissal order, the independent counsel did not think he could get a conviction, but concluded that her sworn denial of a ''role'' was a ''strained interpretation of the language'' and ''is contrary to common sense.'' He notified the court: ''the overwhelming evidence establishes that she played a role in the decision to fire the employees . . . her statement to the contrary under oath to this Office was factually false.''</p>
        <p>She had help in escaping indictment. One confederate in the firings, Jeff Eller, said ''I don't remember'' or its variant 200 times during two hours before the grand jury. The White House failure to produce e-mails to Eller about the firings for four years after their subpoena, noted Ray, ''prevented this Office from using them to refresh Eller's recollection. . . .''</p>
        <p>Was the search for truth worthwhile? Yes; as a result of the white light of publicity focused on the travel office scandal, the F.B.I. director made clear that never again will the federal police power be used in this way by the White House to target and publicly besmear politically unwanted workers.</p>
        <p>Old Nixon hands notice familiar, dark traits in Hillary that The Times, in its endorsement of her candidacy yesterday, called ''a fondness for stonewalling'' and ''a lamentable tendency to treat political opponents as enemies.''</p>
        <p>It may be that as one who tagged her as a habitual prevaricator before that became a widely shared assessment, I am on her enemies list. I hope so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
