<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Push State Off the Fence</title>
    <meta content="Y23MIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/politics/23MICH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="BATTLEGROUNDS: Michigan" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: MICHIGAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DB1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Push State Off the Fence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LANSING, Mich., Oct. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush, who trailed by as much as eight percentage points in Michigan three weeks ago, appears to have pulled even with Vice Pres Al Gore, and surrogates are rushing in to help him; few politicians are venturing prediction as to who will win in most hotly contested big swing state of 2000 campaign; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The moment has come in Michigan for the big boys to push all their chips to the middle of the table. But they are not yet doing it. Not quite.</p>
        <p>Eight points behind in the widely followed Epic-MRA poll a mere three weeks ago, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has caught up with Vice President Al Gore, and few politicians here will venture a prediction as to who will win this most hotly contested of the big swing states in the 2000 campaign. The poll, taken after the final presidential debate and published in The Detroit Free Press, showed Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore with 43 percent each and Ralph Nader with 4 percent, with 10 percent of those surveyed either undecided or backing other candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The moment has come in Michigan for the big boys to push all their chips to the middle of the table. But they are not yet doing it. Not quite.</p>
        <p>Eight points behind in the widely followed Epic-MRA poll a mere three weeks ago, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has caught up with Vice President Al Gore, and few politicians here will venture a prediction as to who will win this most hotly contested of the big swing states in the 2000 campaign. The poll, taken after the final presidential debate and published in The Detroit Free Press, showed Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore with 43 percent each and Ralph Nader with 4 percent, with 10 percent of those surveyed either undecided or backing other candidates.</p>
        <p>''By definition,'' said Bill Ballenger, the Lansing-based editor of Inside Michigan Politics, a newsletter, ''it can't get any closer, can it?''</p>
        <p>The Democrats are pressing hard.  Their trade union allies are working flat out, with multiple mailings and elaborate phone banks, to deliver the votes of up to 70 percent of their members. One Gore surrogate or another visits Michigan every day.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, less than 24 hours after the debate, Mr. Gore himself rolled into downtown Flint, a hard-pressed old car town.</p>
        <p>Now is the time ''to keep creating jobs and make sure no one is left behind,'' the vice president told a crowd of 5,000; many knew from experience what he was talking about. Governor Bush, Mr. Gore warned them, is a dire threat to the well-being of workers.</p>
        <p>Yet one prominent Democrat is missing: President Clinton. Several Michigan Democratic leaders said this week that Mr. Clinton was badly needed to help boost turnout among blacks and union members. But so far the vice president has not asked him to campaign here; Mr. Clinton is scheduled to appear in California, where the race is much less close, but not in this pivotal state. Apparently Mr. Gore fears being overshadowed, or casting new light on old White House scandals, or both.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is also holding one weapon back: Senator John McCain of Arizona, his former rival for the Republican nomination. Mr. Bush's wife, Laura, and his mother, Barbara, kicked off their ''W Stands for Women'' drive here, crossing the state by bus on Wednesday, in an effort to cut into Mr. Gore's lead among women. Mr. Bush's father, former President George Bush, is scheduled to stump in Holland, Grand Rapids and Detroit on Monday. The candidate himself campaigned Friday at a factory in Macomb County, the mostly blue-collar suburban sprawl north of Detroit that has been hard-fought in every election for three decades.</p>
        <p>Using some of the most pointed language of his campaign, the Texan sought to deny Mr. Gore any credit for the nation's current prosperity.  The New Economy, he said in a mocking tone, ''was not created in a Senate subcommittee or vice presidential commission.''</p>
        <p>But Michigan's referendum on school vouchers has complicated things. The voucher question has prompted Roman Catholic parishes, which support vouchers because they could bring state aid to parochial schools, to press their members to turn out to vote. Because many Catholics vote Democratic, this could be to Mr. Gore's advantage. And the voucher issue has apparently kept Mr. McCain from campaigning with Mr. Bush in this state.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain won the Michigan Republican primary on Feb. 22 and remains more popular here than either Mr. Gore or Mr. Bush. He supports vouchers. Gov. John Engler, at least the nominal leader of the Bush campaign in Michigan, opposes them. Mr. Bush, fearful of exacerbating the split in Republican ranks that Mr. Engler's stance has opened, has soft-pedaled his own backing for vouchers, describing them as a matter for state decisions.</p>
        <p>The Bush strategists have been leery of close ties with Mr. McCain here. The senator has made commercials for the voucher proposal, but not for Mr. Bush. He signed up to campaign with Mr. Bush's running mate, Dick Cheney, in Michigan this week, and with Mr. Bush in Maine, but not in Michigan, though the 650,000 primary voters who backed Mr. McCain could decide who ends up with the state's 18 electoral votes.</p>
        <p>Prof. David Rohde of Michigan State University said the McCain voters' intentions were a puzzle.  Those who voted for him on personality grounds, he theorized, might find Mr. Bush more appealing; those who voted for him because of his backing for campaign finance reform might prefer Mr. Gore, who has promised to back the legislation that Mr. McCain is co-sponsoring.</p>
        <p>But what of the Democrats who crossed over into the Republican primary chiefly to give a political black eye to Mr. Engler? No one can say.</p>
        <p>This year, no group is too small to be courted. In the second debate, Mr. Bush said pointedly that the United States should be receptive to Arab nations' views in framing its policies in the Middle East, and he also mentioned Senator Spencer Abraham, Republican of Michigan, a prominent Lebanese-American. The Arab-American Political Action Committee and the Arab-American and Chaldean Leadership Council swiftly issued endorsements. Metropolitan Detroit has the nation's largest concentration of Arab-Americans, centered in Dearborn.</p>
        <p>The Arab groups have mailing lists of about 40,000 names, not many in a state with a population of 10 million. But Michigan elections can be tight -- the 1990 governor's race was decided by 17,000 votes -- and everything points to an exceptionally close finish to the presidential race. .</p>
        <p>So the surrogates keep coming: not only family members but also the Rev. Jesse Jackson for Mr. Gore, hoping to fire up black voters; Energy Secretary Bill Richardson, also for Mr. Gore; Lee A. Iacocca, the former chairman of Chrysler (now DaimlerChrysler), hoping to convince auto workers that Mr. Gore, a foe of the internal combustion engine, is their foe, too; and Charlton Heston, president of the National Rifle Association, for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>There is no need to pore over columns of numbers or count the V.I.P. visitors to get a feeling for how tinglingly tight the race is in Michigan.  A stroll down Griffith, Gardner and Edwards Streets in Berkley, a town of 15,000 in Oakland County, west of Macomb, will do the trick nicely. A few blocks away from the National Shrine of the Little Flower, once served by the demagogic right-wing radio priest of the New Deal era, Father Charles E. Coughlin, it is evenly divided politically and full of habitual ticket-splitters.</p>
        <p>The streets are lined with small, tidy frame houses with tiny gardens, carefully kept, many of them decorated this week for Halloween. Trees arch over the sidewalks. The families who live there are mostly lower middle class, and the neighborhood looks like a fulfillment of the old American maxim ''work hard, save your money and you'll have a place of your own someday.''</p>
        <p>Hurrying to work at a charity resale shop, Roseanne Zielinski paused to tell a visitor that she was for Mr. Gore because she sensed that ''he's for the smaller person like me.''</p>
        <p>''We have my mother in a nursing home we can't afford,'' she said.  ''When you're a little guy you worry about getting through the next day, not about the big, complicated issues.''</p>
        <p>But William Murchison, who retired as a social studies teacher at Warren Mott High School after 31 years, described the choice in less black-and-white terms. He was concerned, he said, about the possible return of big government if Mr. Gore were elected; ''like inflation,'' he added, ''you have to fight it all the time, and Gore seems to have a half-dozen programs for every problem.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Murchison said, ''I'm concerned that Bush may have a vacancy at the center -- he may just not be quite up to the job.''</p>
        <p>In the end, he said, he would probably vote for Mr. Bush, but not with any enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Pauline Jordan, who was out shopping, said she was a Bush backer as well, because of his personality.</p>
        <p>''I like Mr. Bush because he's down to earth and human,'' she said.  ''Mr. Gore is too obnoxious.''</p>
        <p>With the outcome so delicately poised, turnout is crucial. Turnout is always crucial in Michigan, to hear the politicians and union leaders tell it, but this time, said Professor Rohde of Michigan State, ''it might even turn out to be true, because it might give one candidate or another an extra percentage point or two.''</p>
        <p>Ed Sarpolus of the Epic-MRA polling group said that polling detail showed strong crosscurrents. About 3 percent of Republicans who previously seemed likely to sit out the election appear to have been newly energized, he said. The most reliably Democratic voters, African-Americans, seem slightly less motivated to back Mr. Gore than they were to back most Democratic presidential nominees, he said, but Catholic Democrats seem likely to vote in considerable numbers.</p>
        <p>Events abroad, the stock market or other unforeseen developments could change the course of the race everywhere. But there is a special twist here that does not apply in most places: an extra day off for Election Day that the United Auto Workers negotiated for its members for the first time this year. It is myth, as Douglas A. Fraser, the union's retired president, remarked in conversation this week, to suggest that union leaders ''could ever make their members vote in lockstep.'' But the day off might provide badly needed volunteer manpower for the Democrats, whose own party organization is weak here.</p>
        <p>About the Series</p>
        <p>A series of articles last month examined four swing states -- Pennsylvania, Ohio, Wisconsin and Michigan -- that are likely to be critical in the presidential race. This is the third of four articles revisiting the race in those states.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: MICHIGAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
