<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="23DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/nyregion/23DIAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DE1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>The scene is Penn Station, with a jostling crowd of travelers trying to board a Long Island Rail Road train to the Hamptons. Among them is a distinguished-looking man, his well-dressed wife struggling to keep pace, followed by their long-legged teenage son.</p>
        <p>As the woman steps onto the train, right foot first, the teenager accidentally hits her left foot, knocking her shoe into the very deep space between train and platform. The shoe is visible but unreachable. The conductor contacts the stationmaster and is told that the shoe can be retrieved only after the train has left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>The scene is Penn Station, with a jostling crowd of travelers trying to board a Long Island Rail Road train to the Hamptons. Among them is a distinguished-looking man, his well-dressed wife struggling to keep pace, followed by their long-legged teenage son.</p>
        <p>As the woman steps onto the train, right foot first, the teenager accidentally hits her left foot, knocking her shoe into the very deep space between train and platform. The shoe is visible but unreachable. The conductor contacts the stationmaster and is told that the shoe can be retrieved only after the train has left.</p>
        <p>A man steps forward and suggests that a passenger with a fishing rod be enlisted in a retrieval attempt. But the rod would have to be assembled, and time is of the essence -- only five minutes remain before departure.</p>
        <p>Another man steps forward and asks whether anyone has a wire hanger. A woman produces one, and he fashions a hook. By this time passengers are exchanging train stories, and a sense of camaraderie prevails. The ingenious young man struggles into position and lies flat on the train floor to get close. The hanger, however, is too short. Another woman hands over a second hanger, and the two hangers are somehow connected. At this point, an announcement is made that the train will depart in two minutes. The hanger-hook works; the shoe is retrieved, flipped onto the platform and caught. Amid thunderous applause, it is presented to the woman, who had been standing on one foot. The expressions of gratitude are punctuated by the husband's efforts to give the young man $20. The young man refuses, suggesting a Catholic charity instead.</p>
        <p>I was delighted to get my shoe back. St. Francis of Assisi got a donation.</p>
        <p>BEATRICE WILLIAMS-RUDE</p>
        <p>A SUBWAY RIDER'S PLEA</p>
        <p>They enter every morning</p>
        <p>Or perhaps they're already there</p>
        <p>Wearing backpacks the size of pianos</p>
        <p>Though they only paid one fare</p>
        <p>What do they carry, we all wonder</p>
        <p>As every single day</p>
        <p>Into our car they blunder</p>
        <p>And we try to stay out of the way</p>
        <p>Every time they turn or bend</p>
        <p>We passengers get bruised</p>
        <p>From backpack blows without an end</p>
        <p>Our arms and backs abused</p>
        <p>What possible need, we pray,</p>
        <p>Justifies all the bumping?</p>
        <p>Isn't it too early in the day</p>
        <p>To go parachute jumping?</p>
        <p>If this assault we would douse</p>
        <p>We must plead with all our power</p>
        <p>Sure, carry those backpacks -- bring your whole house --</p>
        <p>ONLY NOT DURING RUSH HOUR!</p>
        <p>SHELDON CZAPNIK</p>
        <p>Bonnie Neil is still amused by the story told to her by a friend. The woman and her son, then 4, were on a plane, awaiting takeoff for a long-anticipated trip to Disney World. The child, fearful of flying, was nevertheless chattering excitedly about his soon-to-be-realized adventure when he suddenly fell silent. His mother observed that he had clenched his fists and squeezed his eyes shut. ''What are you doing?'' she asked. ''I'm praying,'' he said. When she inquired, ''About what?'' he replied, ''That if the plane has to crash, it be on the way home.''</p>
        <p>BUT NOT FOR ME</p>
        <p>The microwave sits in the pantry,</p>
        <p>No room on the counter top.</p>
        <p>Don't like to use the cell phone,</p>
        <p>Afraid that it may drop.</p>
        <p>Do e-mail just @ the office,</p>
        <p>And never try to page.</p>
        <p>Give me the 1940's,</p>
        <p>I'm not of this modern age.</p>
        <p>TOBY SHATZOFF FEINBERG</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My son had finished exams and, as we rode the subway, he was sharing with me some of what he remembered of the math problems. A man sitting next to us seemed to be listening, and was smiling to himself, as my son explained each question and answer.</p>
        <p>''There was one that I wasn't sure about,'' my son told me, continuing with what I recall as, ''What is the probability of picking the integer X out of a bag of integers, if X squared is Y,'' and he went on from there. When he finished describing the problem, he said, ''I wasn't sure, but I put down the answer was zero.''</p>
        <p>At that moment, the man next to us picked up his little girl and hurried to leave the train. As he got to the door, he looked back over his shoulder and said approvingly, ''And you were right.''</p>
        <p>MEG AKABAS</p>
        <p>Jim David was standing on a corner talking to a friend about his career. Suddenly, a homeless man came up, stood beside him and started listening. Mr. David ignored him and went on talking, expressing concern that his career was not where he wanted it to be and outlining his hopes for the future. Finally, the two friends parted and as Mr. David started walking away, the homeless man interjected, ''Hey, man, I hope you find your niche.''</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Reading of problems that foreign visitors sometimes encounter in Manhattan brought to mind an experience I had before retiring from the Fire Department.</p>
        <p>I was a battalion chief in Midtown. The alarm bells sounded, and the house watchman yelled out the location -- Broadway and 44th Street. I was the first to arrive -- engine and ladder companies followed -- and I saw standing at the firebox a scared and shaken young Asian couple. The young man rushed to me, bowed his head several times and repeated, ''So sorry, so sorry.''</p>
        <p>In halting English, he explained that he had pulled the alarm thinking that it controlled the traffic signal to cross the street. He was then informed by others in the vicinity what wrong he had done. I told him that he had needlessly brought out all the fire equipment but that I understood it was not an intended false alarm. Still jittery and frightened, he explained in a sad tone that he and his wife had just arrived from Japan on their honeymoon. I reassured him -- we would accept the alarm as an innocent error, and he could forget it.</p>
        <p>That said, the young man regained his confidence and immediately asked, as you might guess, whether his wife could take a picture of us together. She snapped as the New York onlookers, who had witnessed the whole thing, laughed their approval. I didn't know, and still don't, whether officialdom downtown would have seen the humor.</p>
        <p>PAUL J. FEMMEL</p>
        <p>Observations for this column may be sent to Metropolitan Diary, Style Department, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Please include your name, address and daytime telephone number (required); upon request, names may be withheld in print. Letters become the property of The Times and cannot be returned. They may be edited, and may be republished in all media.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
