<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warner Is Injured as Rams Fall From the Unbeaten Ranks</title>
    <meta content="23KANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/sports/23KANS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Chiefs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Kansas City Chiefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D91631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warner Is Injured as Rams Fall From the Unbeaten Ranks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kansas City Chiefs defeat St Louis Rams, 54-34; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kansas City Chiefs believed they could beat the glitzy, fleet and purely offensive-minded St. Louis Rams in only one of two ways -- either stop the Rams from scoring or score more. Simple, right? But so many teams had tried both tactics against the Super Bowl champions and had failed.</p>
        <p>Today, the Chiefs chose the second option -- score, score, score and score some more -- and put severe pressure on the Rams. Kansas City led by 20-0 after the first quarter and that proved the difference in a 54-34 victory at Arrowhead Stadium, where the ball flew up and down the field with ease and where the lights on the scoreboard dazzled like a marquee proclaiming that the circus had come to town.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kansas City Chiefs believed they could beat the glitzy, fleet and purely offensive-minded St. Louis Rams in only one of two ways -- either stop the Rams from scoring or score more. Simple, right? But so many teams had tried both tactics against the Super Bowl champions and had failed.</p>
        <p>Today, the Chiefs chose the second option -- score, score, score and score some more -- and put severe pressure on the Rams. Kansas City led by 20-0 after the first quarter and that proved the difference in a 54-34 victory at Arrowhead Stadium, where the ball flew up and down the field with ease and where the lights on the scoreboard dazzled like a marquee proclaiming that the circus had come to town.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in football terms, it had.</p>
        <p>Eighty-eight points were scored, the most ever in this stadium, as 79,142 enjoyed the spectacle: 12 touchdowns, 45 first downs, 896 yards gained.</p>
        <p>The Rams entered the game unbeaten, but left with a 6-1 record and with an uncertain future. Running back Marshall Faulk (67 yards rushing) bruised his shoulder and could miss next week's game at San Francisco. Quarterback Kurt Warner broke his right little finger, on his passing hand, while receiving a snap from center just before halftime.</p>
        <p>Rams Coach Mike Martz said Warner would be out for four to six weeks. Warner insisted that he might be able to play next week or soon after. ''I'm not ruling out any possibilities,'' Warner said. Trent Green played the second half and will become the Rams' new starter if Warner is sidelined.</p>
        <p>The Chiefs (4-3), lost here a week ago to their bitter rival, the Oakland Raiders, but today they regrouped and then punished the Rams in an intense and rare intrastate, pro football battle for supremacy. The state of Missouri was up for grabs and the Chiefs swiped the bragging rights. It was quite a show.</p>
        <p>''We decided to let it all hang out,'' Chiefs Coach Gunther Cunningham said. ''We went after them. The Rams are every bit as good as everyone said they were. I'll be honest with you, we were going to just make plays. You can't get down when they make plays.''</p>
        <p>You simply make some more.</p>
        <p>And the Chiefs did.</p>
        <p>''The Rams have played other teams and have really gotten up on them,'' Chiefs quarterback Elvis Grbac said. ''It was really our mind-set going into the game that whatever we had to do for four quarters, we had to score as many points as we could. We stayed on the attack. It was kind of funny. We were sitting there on Saturday and they were messing with the clock; I asked one of the coaches what they were doing. Were they checking the light bulbs to see how many points they were going to score and how many we were going to score and making sure every light bulb was there?''</p>
        <p>Those bulbs flashed all game. Kansas City started it by intercepting a Warner pass only seconds into the game, a theft by cornerback James Hasty that set up the Chiefs' first rushing touchdown. Kansas City gained field goals on its next two possessions and then ended the quarter by blocking a punt -- Bracy Walker blocked it and Mike Cloud returned it 6 yards for a touchdown. With 2 minutes 56 seconds left in the first quarter, the rout was on, and Kansas City led by 27-14 at halftime.</p>
        <p>Warner was 15 of 25 for 185 yards with a touchdown and 2 interceptions in the first half. Green in the second half was 15 of 21 for 205 yards with 3 touchdowns and 1 interception. Grbac topped both: 18 of 30 for 266 yards with 2 touchdown and no interceptions. Chiefs back Kimble Anders rushed for 2 touchdowns, produced a 69-yard run and 102 rushing yards on 13 carries.</p>
        <p>''We had an early turnover, an interception, and they stick it in the end zone right away,'' Martz said. ''A blocked punt for a touchdown. Then we're down there right before the half and the snap that breaks Kurt's finger. We dug a hole. Trent's going to be fine; he's an outstanding quarterback. But we've got to fix what's broken and get going.''</p>
        <p>That would be the defense. A singed and torched defense. It has become so awful that Martz has asked the long-time defensive guru Bud Carson to come out of retirement to fix it.</p>
        <p>''I just can't believe what has happened to us, how we are playing out of position and without much confidence,'' said Mike Jones, the Rams linebacker who made the game-saving tackle in the last Super Bowl. That kind of defense for the Rams appears long gone.</p>
        <p>''We've got a lot to fix,'' Jones said. ''There are a lot of places to start, including with me. We've got guys, even when they are in position, not making the plays. And look at that -- 54 points they got. That's unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>That is what players usually say about the Rams after their offense has tagged a team for a lot of points. This time, on this day, in this game, it happened to the Rams.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't feel so good,'' Rams kick-returner Tony Horne said. ''I can see how it feels now. We've done it to a lot of teams and I guess today was our day. It wouldn't matter so much, I mean, the 54 points, if we had played well as a team and that's just how it turned out. I give Kansas City credit, but we didn't play close to our best. That's the problem.''</p>
        <p>Chiefs cornerback Greg Wesley said: ''I don't know what game we got from them; they got our A-game. This is the new Chiefs.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
