<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>10 Hours on the Aegean, Masked and Mythic</title>
    <meta content="23TANT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/arts/23TANT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001024T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Center Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Peter (Sir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Edward</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tantalus (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DF1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>10 Hours on the Aegean, Masked and Mythic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Tantalus, 10-part theatrical treatment of Trojan War, by Denver Center Theater Company; it is directed by Sir Peter Hall and Edward Hall; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the end of Part 6 of ''Tantalus,'' the mammoth 10-part theatrical treatment of the Trojan War and its prelude and aftermath that is being given its world premiere by the Denver Center Theater Company here, the siege of Ilion is over, the city is sacked, Priam and Hector are dead, and the Trojan women have been enslaved and driven onto the ships of the conquering Greeks. About to begin their trip home, Menelaus and Odysseus have a war-weary exchange on the circular, sand-strewn stage that is here the bloodstained shores of Troy but serves the show as the Aegean of both antiquity and modernity.</p>
        <p>''I have waited long,'' Menelaus says, speaking of the recovery of his wife, Helen, whose abduction kindled the war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the end of Part 6 of ''Tantalus,'' the mammoth 10-part theatrical treatment of the Trojan War and its prelude and aftermath that is being given its world premiere by the Denver Center Theater Company here, the siege of Ilion is over, the city is sacked, Priam and Hector are dead, and the Trojan women have been enslaved and driven onto the ships of the conquering Greeks. About to begin their trip home, Menelaus and Odysseus have a war-weary exchange on the circular, sand-strewn stage that is here the bloodstained shores of Troy but serves the show as the Aegean of both antiquity and modernity.</p>
        <p>''I have waited long,'' Menelaus says, speaking of the recovery of his wife, Helen, whose abduction kindled the war.</p>
        <p>''We have all waited long,'' Odysseus rejoins, ''and it's not over yet.''</p>
        <p>For Odysseus this is of course a prescient moment; his Homeric travails have yet to begin. But for the creators, and an audience two-thirds through its 10 1/2-hour sit-down marathon, it is a laugh line. And it is a testament as well to the self-conscious hubris of this theatrical feast of a production, written and staged largely in modern idiom, employing a full expanse of poetics and pyrotechnics in scenes horrific and comic, a gourmand's banquet of virtuosic writing and stagecraft. Divided into nine digestible courses (the final two parts are forged), each about an hour long, it is being presented either over two days or, as it was at its official opening on Saturday, in one gorging and exhausting repast.</p>
        <p>With a six-month rehearsal period and a budget estimated at $8 million -- it was financed largely by the Denver Center for the Performing Arts and its founder and chairman, Donald R. Seawall -- ''Tantalus'' is almost certainly the most expensive and ambitious show ever mounted at an American regional theater. With an international creative team and a British and American company of 27, including 8 principals playing huge multiple roles, the show (which runs through Dec. 2) is a vast, lurching, frequently thrilling amalgamation of pageantry and speechifying that displays, like the Greeks themselves, both a glorious potency and a self-aggrandizing pride in its exhibition.</p>
        <p>Written over nearly two decades by John Barton and directed by his colleague of 50 years, Sir Peter Hall (and by Sir Peter's son, Edward), the show has a scope worthy of mutual, career-crowning ambition, and it arrives with the wounds of an agonizing creative collaboration. During rehearsals, a principal actor resigned in a dispute over Sir Peter's choice to have the actors perform largely in masks, and a third director, Mick Gordon, abruptly quit as well. Most dramatically Mr. Barton and Sir Peter quarreled furiously over the latter's editing and rewriting of the script, and the playwright left Denver during rehearsals as well.</p>
        <p>Drawn from fragments and summaries of material that survive from the era before, during and after the fifth century B.C., when Greek drama flourished, the play cycle purports to tell the story of the Trojan War from its mythical source, the condemnation of Tantalus, a favorite of the Olympian gods who incurred their wrath by stealing their secrets and disseminating them on earth. Zeus sentences Tantalus, a progenitor of the Greek general Agamemnon, to an eternity of hunger and thirst and a life perpetually threatened by a precariously balanced great boulder. This is the grand metaphor of the play cycle.</p>
        <p>''Death is certain, but doom is postponed,'' Mr. Barton writes in a program note. ''The fruits of the earth are ours for the taking, but most people never quite get a real taste of them.''</p>
        <p>That this is meant to resonate through history is communicated through a cheeky, effective narrative frame. The whole of the tale unspools on a modern beach in Greece, where a vendor selling dolls of Greek mythological heroes intoxicates a group of young women with the retelling of a story they say they already know. ''The Epic Cycle of the Lost Bits,'' he calls it, and as the cycle proceeds, the women are drawn into the historical presentation, becoming the proverbial Greek chorus, first arriving, like schoolchildren on a field trip, on the doorstep of the House of Atreus, eventually donning the masks that the historical actors themselves wear and serving, in the end, as the enslaved women of Troy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barton's source material largely concerns events that fall in the interstices of the chronicles of Euripedes, Aeschylus and Sophocles, and beyond some surprising additions to the canonical story -- for example, that the abduction of Helen was retribution for the taking, years earlier, of Priam's sister, Hesione -- the playwright has provided fascinating interpretations of the famous characters and the events their clashing motivations engendered.</p>
        <p>One of the show's most stirring scenes is the re-enactment of Agamemnon's decision to sacrifice his daughter, Iphigenia, to the gods so they will allow the winds to blow for the Greek army's sail to Troy. Tormented, he is finally persuaded to make the sacrifice by his wife, Clytemnestra, and by Iphigenia herself. The roles of women, as both exercisers and victims of power, is a consistent theme, and the scene is chilling in its manifestations of the women's psychic commingling of sex and war.</p>
        <p>Agamemnon, played by Greg Hicks with the eloquent melancholy of a man who has divined and accepted his fate, is at the moral center of the cycle. And he is joined there by Cassandra (a mesmerizing Annalee Jefferies), the daughter of Priam, who has been condemned by Apollo to a seer's vision but a fool's influence. She has been won by Agamemnon, his spoil in the war, and when her thrilling, brittle frustration is melted by her realization that their visionary connection unites them, their erotic and beautifully staged embrace, ironically brought about by violence and tragically sealing their doom, is the dramatic climax of the show. Their struggle is over in an agony of ecstasy, yet another way ''Tantalus'' illustrates that enough is also too much.</p>
        <p>TANTALUS</p>
        <p>An adaptation from the 10-play cycle by John Barton; additional text by Colin Teevan; directed by Sir Peter Hall and Edward Hall; associate director and tour director, Anthony Powell; associate director and production dramaturg, Mr. Teevan; sets and costumes by Dionysis Fotopoulos; lighting by Sumio Yoshii; composer and musical director, Mick Sands; choreographer, Donald McKayle; sound by David R. White; speech and dialect coach, Gary Logan; dramaturg to John Barton, Graham Ley; producing director, Barbara E. Sellers; production manager, Rick Barbour. Sir Peter Hall's production presented by the Denver Center Theater Company, Donovan Marley, artistic director, in association with the Royal Shakespeare Company, Adrian Noble, artistic director. At 1245 Champa Street, Denver.</p>
        <p>WITH: Alyssa Bresnahan (Thetis, Cassandra and Pythoness), Alan Dobie (Odysseus and Calchas), Greg Hicks (Agamemnon, Priam and Menelaus), Annalee Jefferies (Clytemnestra, Andromache, Ilione and Helen), Ann Mitchell (Hecuba, Nurse and Aethra), Robert Petkoff (Achilles, Aegisthus, Neoptolemus and Orestes), David Ryall (Poet, Tyndareus, Peleus, Telephus, Palamedes and Polymestor) and Mia Yoo (Leda Deidamia, Electra, Hermione, Iphigenia and Polyxena).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW  Correction:  October 24, 2000, Tuesday  A theater review yesterday about ''Tantalus,'' a 10-play cycle about the Trojan War, being given its world premiere by the Denver Center Theater Company, misidentified the actress playing Cassandra. As noted in the credit listing, she is Alyssa Bresnahan; Annalee Jefferies played four other parts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 24, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A theater review yesterday about ''Tantalus,'' a 10-play cycle about the Trojan War, being given its world premiere by the Denver Center Theater Company, misidentified the actress playing Cassandra. As noted in the credit listing, she is Alyssa Bresnahan; Annalee Jefferies played four other parts.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
