<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Governors Carry Bush's Message</title>
    <meta content="Y23BUS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/politics/23BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DB1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Governors Carry Bush's Message</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Twenty-eight Republican governors rally in Austin, Tex, with Gov George W Bush in orchestrated display of party muscle, vowing to wage relentless fight to propel him into White House; will barnstorm across 25 battleground states over next three days as part of campaign effort; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an orchestrated display of party muscle and unity, all but one of the nation's Republican governors descended on the Texas capital today, vowing to wage a relentless fight to propel one of their own into the White House.</p>
        <p>At a midafternoon rally for Gov. George W. Bush that kicked off three days of barnstorming across 25 battleground states, the 28 governors stood on a three-tiered stage, laughing as they found their assigned places marked on the floor with tape. It was a gathering intended to reinforce Mr. Bush's theme that he represented a more pragmatic style of leadership distinct from the partisanship of Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an orchestrated display of party muscle and unity, all but one of the nation's Republican governors descended on the Texas capital today, vowing to wage a relentless fight to propel one of their own into the White House.</p>
        <p>At a midafternoon rally for Gov. George W. Bush that kicked off three days of barnstorming across 25 battleground states, the 28 governors stood on a three-tiered stage, laughing as they found their assigned places marked on the floor with tape. It was a gathering intended to reinforce Mr. Bush's theme that he represented a more pragmatic style of leadership distinct from the partisanship of Washington.</p>
        <p>''Some campaigns tend to send out spokespeople,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I'm sending out examples; examples of people who know how to lead; examples of people who have solved problems; examples of people who have made public education the No. 1 priority in their states.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said the governors would carry ''the collective message that the Clinton-Gore administration has been the chief obstacle to reform in America.''</p>
        <p>The group covered the Republican Party's ideological spectrum, from conservatives like Frank Keating of Oklahoma, who opposes abortion, to moderates like Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey and George E. Pataki of New York, who favor abortion rights. Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania called the gathering ''at least unusual and quite possibly unprecedented.''</p>
        <p>''How is it that all of us from our own diverse upbringing, states and backgrounds have traveled here today?'' Mr. Ridge asked in introducing Mr. Bush and his running mate, Dick Cheney. ''How is it that today we set aside every singular agenda of our own to offer our individual and collective energies and efforts in support of your journey to become the next president of the United States?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ridge said the governors believed that Mr. Bush ''would provide a more honorable and more effective kind of leadership,'' adding that they would fight for him ''to the last minute, to the last hour, to the last day of this campaign.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush reveled in the support of the governors, he has studiously avoided any such display with members of Congress, whom he has associated with the gridlock and partisanship in Washington. In contrast, he called the governors pragmatic problem-solvers and said they would reinforce the message that he is a Washington outsider who can reach across party lines to get things done.</p>
        <p>In a sign of that sort of bipartisanship, the group began the rally with a moment of silence for Mel Carnahan, the Democratic governor of Missouri who died in a plane crash last week as he was campaigning for the Senate.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign was counting on a media bonanza from the governors who were divided into seven teams and would be campaigning in 48 cities in 25 states, 23 of which were in President Clinton's column in 1996.</p>
        <p>As soon as the rally ended, the governors were descended upon by reporters, and they had scheduled an additional 40 interviews by satellite in crucial states. The governors signed an advertisement in support of Mr. Bush, which is to run in USA Today on Monday. The one Republican governor not at the rally was Cecil H. Underwood of West Virginia, who is in a tough re-election fight.</p>
        <p>The scene marked the ascendancy of the gubernatorial wing of the Republican Party, which began battling for more sway after the midterm election of 1998 when more than a dozen Republican governors were re-elected, including Mr. Bush. At the same time Republicans in Congress suffered defeat by pinning their hopes on impeachment; it was the first time since 1934 that the president's party had gained seats in the House in midterm elections.</p>
        <p>Time and again today, the speakers struck anti-Washington chords. ''For eight years now, the nation's capital has been a scene of seemingly endless partisanship and ill will,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''But for the same eight years in state capitals all across America, Republicans and Democrats have worked together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush called the governors ''can-do conservatives'' who would carry the message that the Clinton administration had been an obstacle on issues ranging from education to welfare to the environment to health care.</p>
        <p>''Every governor has got their tale about how the federal government has blocked reforms,'' he said, ''because of somehow, some way the folks up there think all wisdom exists in Washington, D.C. It's really one of the fundamental differences in this campaign.''</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign countered that the Clinton administration had helped states, and cited legislation that had provided money for more police officers and more teachers, and for children's health insurance.</p>
        <p>''It's a mystery why these governors would endorse Bush's plan to squander the surplus on a tax cut for the wealthy and neglect issues that affect people in their states,'' said Kym Spell, a spokeswoman for Mr. Gore. ''Why would they want Bush to do to America what he has done to Texas?''</p>
        <p>Several governors argued that they, and not President Clinton, had brought the current prosperity to the nation.</p>
        <p>''If you look at so much of America's prosperity today, this is the real prosperity tour right here: the Republican governors,'' Gov. John Engler of Michigan said. ''They've followed interesting strategies at the state level that are very similar to what Governor Bush talks about at the federal level. We've cut taxes. We've emphasized education. We've strengthened the fundamentals. We've strengthened our state's budgets, reformed the process of doing the budget in many of our states.''</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman offered her support to Mr. Bush, even though the two differ on abortion. In words that might resonate with suburban women, she said that despite Mr. Bush's opposition to abortion, she did not believe the governor or his possible appointees to the Supreme Court would jeopardize abortion rights.</p>
        <p>''I have talked to Governor Bush about this and I believe him when he tells me this is not a litmus test for him,'' she said, referring to whom he would pick for the Supreme Court. ''All you have to do is look at the appointments he has made to the Texas court and you will see those are not extremists.''</p>
        <p>She added that while the two do not agree on abortion, there are many other things ''that I care about and women care about.''</p>
        <p>Several governors from swing states were optimistic that Mr. Bush, who has small leads in several national polls, would prevail. ''I think its doable,'' said Gov. George Ryan of Illinois, citing a recent poll showing Mr. Gore clinging to a small lead in Illinois.</p>
        <p>Asked if Governor Bush could do well in Michigan, the original home to many Reagan Democrats, Mr. Engler said he saw parallels to Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>''Before the debates in '80, just as in 2000, there was this attack levied against Ronald Reagan that all he'd ever been was this two-term governor of California,'' Mr. Engler said. ''Well, that's what they said about George Bush: Gee, he's only a two-term governor of Texas running against this very experienced individual, the incumbent, the vice president. Bush, I think, by doing so well in the debates and by being such an  engaging personality, people have said, 'Not only do I think he's able to do the job, I really like him.' ''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
