<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Feisty Torre Defends Pitcher</title>
    <meta content="23LAPO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/sports/23LAPO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piazza, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED71631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Feisty Torre Defends Pitcher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees Manager Joe Torre and owner George M Steinbrenner discuss incident in which Roger Clemens threw broken bat toward Mike Piazza (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre raised his voice, challenged his questioners and seemed about to walk out on a news conference. The Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, was a little less emotional, but perhaps made the stronger insinuation about the Mets, their opponents in the World Series. Their comments came in defense of Roger Clemens, the hard-throwing pitcher, after the Yankees defeated the Mets by 6-5 last night at Yankees Stadium to take a 2-0 lead in the World Series.</p>
        <p>In a heated news conference, Torre discussed a first-inning incident in which Clemens threw a piece of Mike Piazza's broken bat toward the Mets' catcher, who was running along the first-base line, after the bat shattered following contact with a pitch and parts of it went toward the mound. When someone asked how Torre would react if he managed the other team, Torre replied: ''I would have been angry. No question.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre raised his voice, challenged his questioners and seemed about to walk out on a news conference. The Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, was a little less emotional, but perhaps made the stronger insinuation about the Mets, their opponents in the World Series. Their comments came in defense of Roger Clemens, the hard-throwing pitcher, after the Yankees defeated the Mets by 6-5 last night at Yankees Stadium to take a 2-0 lead in the World Series.</p>
        <p>In a heated news conference, Torre discussed a first-inning incident in which Clemens threw a piece of Mike Piazza's broken bat toward the Mets' catcher, who was running along the first-base line, after the bat shattered following contact with a pitch and parts of it went toward the mound. When someone asked how Torre would react if he managed the other team, Torre replied: ''I would have been angry. No question.''</p>
        <p>But he went on to say: ''And why would he throw it at him? So he could get thrown out of the game? Does that make any sense to anybody? Why would he do it? Because he's angry with him?''</p>
        <p>When someone replied, ''Yes,'' Torre continued. ''That's the reason? Because he's angry?'' Torre then questioned why Clemens would want to hurt his teammates by getting ejected from the game.</p>
        <p>Last night's incident came the first time that Piazza, the Mets' star slugger, had faced Clemens since Clemens hit Piazza in the head with a pitch last July and left him with a concussion. At the time, Piazza said he thought Clemens tried to throw at him; Clemens said he tried to call Piazza and apologize.</p>
        <p>''He's angry at Mike Piazza because he hit Mike Piazza in the head?'' Torre asked. ''Give me an answer to that one, too. Now, wouldn't Mike Piazza be mad at him instead? Why would he hit him in the head? Now, figure, throw a bat and hit him in the knee? I mean, this, we completely disable this kid.''</p>
        <p>The prevailing explanation, offered by Torre, Clemens and Steinbrenner, was that Clemens was emotional coming into the game, partly because replays of the Piazza beaning had been shown on television repeatedly for a week. All three suggested that Clemens did not realize Piazza was running down the baseline when he threw the jagged wood toward foul territory.</p>
        <p>When someone suggested Clemens might have reacted on instinct, Torre retorted: ''Instinct? Pick up a bat and throw it at somebody?''</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner was not as blunt, and he did not ask as many rhetorical questions. But he seemed to suggest the Mets may be using the incident as psychological fuel for the next two games, which will be played before their partisans at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''Maybe if you are down, 0-2, maybe you choose to make more of that than possibly you should,'' Steinbrenner said. Referring to how the Yankees won the 1996 Series from Atlanta after losing the first two games, he said: ''Remember when we were down 2-0 to Atlanta? We just went and played the game. That's all.''</p>
        <p>When a reporter asked if Steinbrenner thought the Mets were ''hyping this'' for a competitive edge, Steinbrenener said: ''No. I did not say that they were hyping this. No way. No way.''</p>
        <p>Both Steinbrenner and Torre said Clemens was acting on emotion.</p>
        <p>Referring to Clemens's history of throwing hard pitches high and tight to batters, Steinbrenner compared Clemens's style to that of Bob Gibson, the Hall of Famer who pitched for St. Louis in the 1960's.</p>
        <p>''If you are a high fastball pitcher, you're going to try to brush them back,'' Steinbrenner said.</p>
        <p>Clemens hit only one Mets batter, Edgardo Alfonzo, on the arm. Torre, in the latter stages of his press gathering, tried to explain his understanding of emotion in a big event.</p>
        <p>''This is the World Series,'' Torre said. ''If you think that you go out there and you are robots and you throw the ball, you catch the ball, and that's what you do, you have to be emotional and you have to be passionate. Am I saying he should have picked up the bat and thrown it? No. I think it was an emotional thing. I think Roger will tell you that he was very surprised when he looked up, that Piazza was where he was.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
