<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barak Formally Declares Timeout in the Peace Effort</title>
    <meta content="Y23MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/world/23MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND? THE ISRAELI LEADERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DC1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barak Formally Declares Timeout in the Peace Effort</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Barak formally declares 'time out' from Israel's peace effort with Palestinians, despite intense criticism from key figures in his government; says Israel needs time to reassess its approach to to seven-year-old, American-brokered effort; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite intense criticism from key figures in his government, Prime Minister Ehud Barak today formally declared a ''timeout'' from the peace effort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak first made this declaration conditionally on Friday, saying he would await the outcome of the Arab League summit meeting in Cairo. Today, after Arab leaders excoriated the Israelis as expected, Mr. Barak said Israel needed time to reassess its approach to the seven-year-old, American-brokered effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite intense criticism from key figures in his government, Prime Minister Ehud Barak today formally declared a ''timeout'' from the peace effort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak first made this declaration conditionally on Friday, saying he would await the outcome of the Arab League summit meeting in Cairo. Today, after Arab leaders excoriated the Israelis as expected, Mr. Barak said Israel needed time to reassess its approach to the seven-year-old, American-brokered effort.</p>
        <p>It remained unclear what Mr. Barak meant by a ''timeout,'' what would bring it to an end, and why he had pinned his formal announcement to the unsurprising end of the Arab meeting. Also, to many, the declaration seemed academic. The daily street clashes, which left at least four more Palestinians dead today, have constituted a de facto suspension of the peace effort anyway.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barak, who is tiptoeing between his diplomatic fate and his political one, initially took few steps to clarify himself. His public statements were Delphic; he was committed to the ''peace of the brave'' and not to the ''peace of ostriches,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Stung by criticism, he then said: ''One would have to be blind to continue with the peace process as if nothing was happening.'' Privately, he seemed to be keeping his options open.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, he told his cabinet this morning that he remained committed to pursuing peace and to the understandings reached with the Palestinians at Camp David in July, ministers said. He minimized the importance of the timeout and outraged some ministers by declaring that he did not need to put his ''technical'' decision to a vote.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, as part of his effort to forge a unity government with the right-wing leader Ariel Sharon, Mr. Barak gave the impression that he was willing to abandon any immediate goal of resuming ''final status'' negotiations with the Palestinians. Mr. Sharon's key condition for joining forces is that Mr. Barak renege on the Camp David understandings, too.</p>
        <p>Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, said on returning to Gaza City from Cairo that he had expected Mr. Barak to suspend Israel's participation in the peace process. He said Palestinians were ''continuing on their road to Jerusalem, the capital of our independent state.''</p>
        <p>''To accept it or not accept, let him go to hell,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the political center of Israel, the fighting sounded particularly close to home tonight. In retaliation for renewed shooting into the Gilo neighborhood of Jerusalem, Israeli helicopter gunships fired rockets on the Palestinian town of Beit Jala next to Bethlehem. The boom of missiles hitting their target -- a tile and marble factory -- resounded in the night, as frightened residents of Beit Jala who did not heed the Israelis' call to evacuate huddled in their homes.</p>
        <p>Many Israeli ministers, furious that Mr. Barak did not consult them before he floated his timeout proposal in television interviews on Friday night, spent a good part of today trying to puzzle out his intentions.</p>
        <p>''To re-assess the situation, I personally would need only 24 hours,'' Amnon Lipkin-Shahak, the transportation minister and a senior peace negotiator, said in an interview. ''Practically, anyway, the violence is still with us, and as people are still shooting at each other, we have plenty of time to think without calling a timeout and giving the impression that Israel is closing the door on peace.''</p>
        <p>Yossi Beilin, the justice minister, said in an interview that he opposed Mr. Barak's decision but understood it. ''There is so much pressure, to talk to people under fire in Jerusalem is not exactly his dream,'' he said. ''There is a feeling that something has to be said and something has to be done,'' Mr. Beilin added. ''And timeout is a way to express that it is not business as usual.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon said Mr. Barak seemed to be espousing contradictory thoughts. ''The prime minister is trying to travel simultaneously on two trains going in opposite directions,'' he told the Israeli radio. ''First, there is one, national unity, that would lead to security and a more correct diplomatic process. Second, there is one going in the direction -- backward -- of Oslo.'' That was a reference to the interim peace agreement of 1993.</p>
        <p>A union between the two leaders would shore up Mr. Barak's faltering minority government and give an extended lease on political life to Mr. Sharon. Both men face opposition to the unity government within their own camps, however, just as both would probably face opposition for party leadership if new elections were to be called.</p>
        <p>The deadline for their political negotiations is believed to be Oct. 29, when Parliament reconvenes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon is reviled in the Arab world, which holds him responsible for provoking the present violence by a heavily guarded, politicized visit to the Muslim compound in the heart of the Old City. The Israelis say the Palestinians used Mr. Sharon's trip as a pretext for a planned uprising.</p>
        <p>Israeli television reported tonight that Mr. Sharon's demands for joining a national emergency government were many. They include a shift in goal to a long-term interim arrangement with the Palestinians rather than resolving all issues in a final accord; a commitment to keep all settlements intact; and an end to ''the policy of restraint'' when reacting to Palestinian rioters.</p>
        <p>Some Israelis today lamented the fact that the state of emergency in which Israel finds itself has become entwined with the political realities of a weak prime minister.</p>
        <p>''This timeout is tantamount to the sacrifice of the peace process for the sake of the prime minister's political future,'' said Taleb el-Asana, an Israeli-Arab lawmaker.</p>
        <p>Moshe Shahal, a former Labor Party minister, said, ''The prime minister's announcement represents more his internal political distress than a considered diplomatic declaration.''</p>
        <p>Martin Indyk, the American ambassador, indicated in a speech that Washington was distressed by Mr. Barak's contingency plan for a broken peace effort: a unilateral separation from the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''Israelis and Palestinians are bound, even condemned, to live together side by side,'' Mr. Indyk said. ''There is no separation that can exist in these circumstances.''</p>
        <p>After the Arab summit meeting ended, many Palestinians expressed deep disappointment at what they saw as the Arab leaders' ''diluted'' endorsement of their struggle.</p>
        <p>The Israeli government's responses to the Arab meeting were muddled, coming in the form of two seemingly contrasting statements and then two separate clarifications.</p>
        <p>First, the government spokesman, Nachman Shai, praised the moderating influence of President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt. But then, in a flurry of clarifications, the Israelis condemned the summit meeting's ''language of threats'' against Israel.</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND? THE ISRAELI LEADERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
