<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arab Statement: 'Criminals of War Who Committed Massacres'</title>
    <meta content="Y23TEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/world/23TEXT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND?"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arab League</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D91631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arab Statement: 'Criminals of War Who Committed Massacres'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from statement issued members of Arab League at end of summit in Cairo freezing all but diplomatic contacts with Israel (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the statement issued today by Arab leaders at the end of their summit meeting as translated by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>The summit salutes the uprising of the Palestinian people in the occupied Palestinian land. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the statement issued today by Arab leaders at the end of their summit meeting as translated by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>The summit salutes the uprising of the Palestinian people in the occupied Palestinian land. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders hold Israel responsible for returning the region back to an atmosphere of tension and violence as a result of the Israeli practices of aggression and its siege of the Palestinian people in violation of its commitments stipulated in Geneva convention, 1949, as an occupying force. . . .</p>
        <p>The Arab leaders confirm that the Aksa intifada erupted as a result of continuing occupation and the Israeli violation of Haram al Sharif, and the rest of the Islamic and Christian holy sites in the Palestinian land. . . . They also affirm the Palestinian people's right to just compensation from Israel for moral, human and material losses. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders demand forming a neutral international committee in the framework of the United Nations that will report to the Security Council, and the Human Rights Committee, on the reasons and the responsibility for the dangerous deterioration in the occupied Palestinian Land, and the massacres committed by the Israeli occupying forces. . . .</p>
        <p>They also ask that the Security Council and General Assembly take charge of providing protection for the Palestinian people under Israeli occupation, through discussing forming a force or any international presence for this purpose. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab Leaders affirm that Arab nations shall pursue, in accordance with international law, those responsible for these brutal practices and demand that the Security Council form an international tribunal dedicated to trying Israeli criminals of war who committed massacres against the Palestinians and the Arabs in the occupied land like the former tribunal formed for criminals of war in Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders express their deep resentment and deprecation of the Israeli escalation in aggression and its provocation in a time when the region was getting ready for comprehensive and just peace, especially after the Arabs decided since the Madrid conference that a comprehensive and just peace is their option and opens the way for a final settlement. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders affirm that a comprehensive and just peace shall not be achieved without the return of Jerusalem to Palestinian sovereignty and without granting the Palestinians legitimate rights including the founding of an independent state with Jerusalem as its capital. . . . And without restoring all Arab land occupied, including a full Israeli withdrawal from the West Bank and Gaza and from Golan to the borders of June 4, 1967, and the completion of the Israeli withdrawal from southern Lebanon to the international borders including Shabaa plantation. And without the release of Arab prisoners held in the Israeli prisons. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders stress that halting of the peace process in its bilateral track will lead to halting of the multilateral track. They also affirm that dealing with the issues of regional cooperation cannot be done without achievement of real peace in the region. . . .</p>
        <p>Arab leaders . . .remind . . . the world not to move embassies to Jerusalem and . . . affirm cutting all relations with countries that . . .  recognize Jerusalem as the capital of Israel.</p>
        <p>Arab leaders affirm that achieving durable peace and security in the region requires Israeli accession to the nuclear non-proliferation treaty. And to submit all Israeli nuclear installations to international inspection system. They stress the importance of making the Middle East free of nuclear weapons and weapons of mass destruction. . . .</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
