<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zagat Survey Reflects Restaurant Boom</title>
    <meta content="23ZAGA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/nyregion/23ZAGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zagat Survey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D91631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zagat Survey Reflects Restaurant Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zagat Survey finds that with New York's restaurant boom showing no signs of abating, record-setting 311 restaurants opened in city in last year; total of 89 restaurants closed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With New York's restaurant boom showing no signs of abating, a record-setting 311 restaurants opened in the city in the last year, according to the latest edition of the Zagat Survey, which is available  today. The average number of openings since 1996 has been 273 a year.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the number of restaurants that closed fell, for the third year in a row. A total of 89 restaurants shut their doors, compared with 136 in 1996, the survey said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With New York's restaurant boom showing no signs of abating, a record-setting 311 restaurants opened in the city in the last year, according to the latest edition of the Zagat Survey, which is available  today. The average number of openings since 1996 has been 273 a year.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the number of restaurants that closed fell, for the third year in a row. A total of 89 restaurants shut their doors, compared with 136 in 1996, the survey said.</p>
        <p>Among the departures were La Reserve in Midtown, Rosemarie's in TriBeCa, Wally and Joseph's in the theater district and the venerable Fraunces Tavern, where George Washington bade farewell to his officers in 1783.</p>
        <p>Tim Zagat, the publisher of the Zagat surveys, said that as many as 20 new upscale restaurants are scheduled to open this fall, all of them planned long before the stock market began to falter.</p>
        <p>''If the economy sours,'' Mr. Zagat said, ''some of the restaurants making a fortune right now will make less money. There won't be a crash, but it will slow the growth.'' He said the increasing number of women in the work force had made eating out a fundamental part of American life.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, the cost of haute cuisine is also rising. The survey counted 21 restaurants with a typical tab of $70 or more (not including the new Alain Ducasse on Central Park South, where the fixed-price menu costs $160,) compared with 9 such restaurants in 1999. The average cost of a restaurant meal was $35, making New York the most expensive of the 39 domestic markets covered by Zagat. The average for the nation was $24.</p>
        <p>Some food critics are skeptical of the value of the  Zagat Survey's ratings, which are drawn from questionnaires distributed at law firms, investment banks and other places with employees who are likely to dine out often. But Malcolm M. Knapp, a New York restaurant consultant, described the guide as ''a pretty good reflection of where things are.''</p>
        <p>About 600,000 copies of the New York survey were sold last year, Mr. Zagat said.</p>
        <p>The data was compiled from 20,424 questionnaires. The respondents ate out an average of 3.6 times a week, an increase of more than 10 percent since last year. Increasingly popular restaurant areas included Brooklyn, Harlem and the meatpacking district.</p>
        <p>People responding to the survey also said they left bigger tips this year, an average of about 18 percent, with half reporting tips of 20 percent or more.</p>
        <p>For the fifth year in a row, Union Square Cafe was voted the most popular restaurant. It was followed by Gramercy Tavern, Gotham Bar and Grill, Aureole and Le Bernardin, which was also voted tops in food.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
