<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Lessons in Tyranny, Repeated in Modern Times</title>
    <meta content="23BERN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/arts/23BERN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Shea, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Perfect Heresy, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D61F3EF930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Lessons in Tyranny, Repeated in Modern Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews The Perfect Heresy: The Revolutionary Life and Death of the Medieval Cathars by Stephen O'Shea; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE PERFECT HERESY  The Revolutionary Life and Death of the Medieval Cathars  By Stephen O'Shea  Illustrated. 333 pages. Walker &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>In early April 1210 the inhabitants of Cabaret in southwestern France saw a strange procession: 100 exhausted and whimpering men marching out of the surrounding countryside, each man holding the shoulder of the man ahead of him. The eyes of all but one of the men had been gouged out, and their noses and upper lips had been sliced off. Only their leader was left with one eye, so as to be able to lead them.</p>
        <p>The 100 were victims of an officially approved soldier of the one true church, a man with God on his side by the name of Simon de Montfort, who was a major figure in the 13th-century suppression of a late medieval heresy known as Catharism. The blinded men, engaged in what Stephen O'Shea calls the ''grotesque march'' to Cabaret, were only a small fragment of the victims of the pure-hearted Simon's campaign to extirpate heresy and heretics. Mr. O'Shea's new book, ''The Perfect Heresy,'' describes numerous other grisly spectacles in the suppression of Catharism, an old subject that he makes new by approaching it with a 21st-century sensibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE PERFECT HERESY  The Revolutionary Life and Death of the Medieval Cathars  By Stephen O'Shea  Illustrated. 333 pages. Walker &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>In early April 1210 the inhabitants of Cabaret in southwestern France saw a strange procession: 100 exhausted and whimpering men marching out of the surrounding countryside, each man holding the shoulder of the man ahead of him. The eyes of all but one of the men had been gouged out, and their noses and upper lips had been sliced off. Only their leader was left with one eye, so as to be able to lead them.</p>
        <p>The 100 were victims of an officially approved soldier of the one true church, a man with God on his side by the name of Simon de Montfort, who was a major figure in the 13th-century suppression of a late medieval heresy known as Catharism. The blinded men, engaged in what Stephen O'Shea calls the ''grotesque march'' to Cabaret, were only a small fragment of the victims of the pure-hearted Simon's campaign to extirpate heresy and heretics. Mr. O'Shea's new book, ''The Perfect Heresy,'' describes numerous other grisly spectacles in the suppression of Catharism, an old subject that he makes new by approaching it with a 21st-century sensibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Shea, a Canadian writer who has lived for long periods in France, demonstrates several aspects of what he describes as a new form of tyranny in European history, a tyranny that not only controlled behavior but thought as well. The 100-year-long extermination of heresy in the Languedoc region of France gave birth to the Inquisition. Its tools were torture, denunciation of neighbor by neighbor and mass execution, by fire and by sword. These methods, as Mr. O'Shea insightfully puts it, ''provide the model for latter-day totalitarian control of the individual conscience.''</p>
        <p>In other words Mr. O'Shea has written an accessible, readable history with lessons, lessons that were not learned by broad humanity until it saw 20th-century tyrants applying the goals and methods of the Inquisition on a universal scale.</p>
        <p>The Cathar heresy was, as Mr. O'Shea describes it, ''a pacifist brand of Christianity embracing tolerance and poverty'' that ''rose to prominence in the middle of the so-called renaissance of the 12th century.'' It took strong root in what is now southwestern France but that was, at the beginning of the Cathar movement, a group of independent principalities stretching from the borders of Provence to the Pyrenees.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Shea, who has mastered the intricacies of medieval social life, religion and religious politics, argues that Catharism was, as he calls it, a perfect heresy because it was ideally suited to the territory in which it flourished. The Languedoc was a region of ''fractured feudalism,'' he writes, whose overlords were often at odds with church authorities and thus often inclined to protect religious sedition.</p>
        <p>At a time when the church was banishing women from active or prominent religious roles, Catharism preached a rough sort of sexual equality; many leading heretics were women. Mr. O'Shea points to an emblematic Cathar conversion in 1204, that of Esclarmonde, the sister of a rugged mountain aristocrat named Raymond Roger, the count of Foix, who applauded as she was ceremoniously inducted into the Cathar faith. The Cathars rejected the sacraments of the church and preached that the trappings of wordly power that surrounded the church belonged to an evil materialism.</p>
        <p>''From the perspective of a newly invigorated Rome,'' Mr. O'Shea writes, ''all of this took on the appearance of an infernal downward spiral, a slippery slope of moral and spiritual degeneracy.''</p>
        <p>Much of Mr. O'Shea's story traces back to the accession to the papacy of the capable Innocent III in 1198.  An unsparing war against the Cathar heresy then became a kind of official crusade, similar in motivation and spirit to the crusades against Muslim control of the Holy Land. But linking the spiritual with more earthly matters, the war against Catharism in the Languedoc became part of a larger international conflict.</p>
        <p>The Cathars' most powerful supporter was Pedro II, King of Aragon, whose armies clashed with Simon de Montfort's inquisitional army at Toulouse in 1213. It was one of the largest armed conflicts of the European Middle Ages and resulted in Pedro's defeat and death at Simon's hands. A consequence of that was an increase in the relative power of the kings of France who, by providing the muscle for the anti-Cathar crusade later in the century, extended their rule all the way to the Pyrenees.</p>
        <p>But while these larger elements are an important part of Mr. O'Shea's story, the moral heart of it is the ferocity of the Catholic crusade against what would appear now to have been a peacable, quietist challenge to the authority of Rome. Innocent and his successors sent to the Languedoc a succession of papal legates and inquisitors whose techniques chillingly prefigured those of the totalitarian monsters of a later century.</p>
        <p>Whole classes of people, entire populations of whole towns, were slaughtered. Thousands were burned at the stake. An offshoot of the campaign against the Cathars was an intensified hatred of the Jews, whom the Cathars and their feudal patrons tended to tolerate. For the first time, as a result of the fourth Lateran Council of 1215, the Jews of Europe were required to wear a yellow circle on their clothing, so that, as Mr. O'Shea writes, ''they would no longer be mistaken for first-class citizens of the medieval polity.''</p>
        <p>He repeats one incident in Toulouse, told in the memoirs of a former Dominican inquisitor named William Pelhisson, that demonstrates the degree to which a blind piety can produce atrocities. In 1234 the household servant of a Cathar woman told the Bishop of Toulouse, Raymond du Fauga, that his mistress lay dying in a nearby home. The servant led the bishop to the woman who, believing her visitor to be a clandestine Cathar, made a full confession of her faith. The woman, lashed to her bed, was promptly carried to the street where she was burned at the stake.</p>
        <p>After her death, Pelhisson recalled, the bishop and his party ''returned to the refectory and, after giving thanks to God and St. Dominic, fell cheerfully upon the food set before them.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
