<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Little Democracy on Wall Street</title>
    <meta content="23GROS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/opinion/23GROS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDF1E3EF930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Little Democracy on Wall Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daniel Gross</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Gross Op-Ed article attributes recent volatility in stock market not only to dropping price of Internet shares, but also to new SEC rule aimed at helping small investor by prohibiting companies from disclosing crucial information about their operations to only few select stock analysts, who would pass information on only to best clients; says volatility is fair price to pay for new rule (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American investors have been riding a roller coaster. Last Wednesday, the Dow Jones industrial average plummeted a sickening 438 points, or 4 percent, in the first hour of trading -- only to recover before the closing bell. The next day, the Nasdaq, after having dropped nearly 30 percent in the previous month, shot up 247 points, or 7.8 percent.</p>
        <p>The strong dollar, the high cost of oil and the dropping price of Internet stocks have all contributed to the instability. But there is another reason for the volatility: the new Securities and Exchange Commission rule, Regulation FD, which is supposed to help the small investor. It prohibits companies from disclosing crucial information about their operations to only a few select stock analysts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American investors have been riding a roller coaster. Last Wednesday, the Dow Jones industrial average plummeted a sickening 438 points, or 4 percent, in the first hour of trading -- only to recover before the closing bell. The next day, the Nasdaq, after having dropped nearly 30 percent in the previous month, shot up 247 points, or 7.8 percent.</p>
        <p>The strong dollar, the high cost of oil and the dropping price of Internet stocks have all contributed to the instability. But there is another reason for the volatility: the new Securities and Exchange Commission rule, Regulation FD, which is supposed to help the small investor. It prohibits companies from disclosing crucial information about their operations to only a few select stock analysts.</p>
        <p>In the bad old days, that is a few months ago, companies were eager to avoid shocking big investors with unpleasant surprise announcements. So as Acme Widget and Die tallied its preliminary sales for the quarter and realized they were running lower than expected, a senior executive would disclose the information in advance to select Wall Street analysts. Regulatory authorities accepted the practice as part of a company's effort to provide analysts with guidance.</p>
        <p>Analysts would pass on the information to their best clients: mutual fund managers, hot hedge funds and wealthy investors. These savvy players would then discreetly trim their positions. Frequently, it was only after the stock had slid substantially that the highly paid analysts would pass the information on to the masses.</p>
        <p>The state of affairs was somewhat akin to that on the Titanic, where the first-class passengers comfortably eased their way onto lifeboats while the common folk in steerage got soaked.</p>
        <p>Last August, in the weeks after the Securities and Exchange Commission announced the new regulation, companies began to conform to the new rule, which is to take effect today. For example, on Sept. 21, when Intel realized its third-quarter revenues would fall short of the expected figures, it didn't simply notify influential analysts. It issued a news release.</p>
        <p>The result was predictable and ugly. The next day, investors of all sizes rushed to dump the shares. Intel fell 22 percent as a record 300 million shares traded hands. Eighty billion dollars -- a sum equal to the current value of General Motors and Ford -- flew off to money heaven.</p>
        <p>In the weeks since, Dell, Apple, Hasbro, United Airlines and Xerox have all issued public warnings about lower than expected earnings. Predictably, the stocks of these market-leading blue-chip companies also plummeted.</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, Wall Street trade groups opposed this new rule. Aside from inducing regular bouts of frightening volatility, they argued, the rule would have a chilling effect on communications between companies and analysts.</p>
        <p>While it will surely bring greater volatility, Regulation FD should also produce some benefits for individual investors. Until recently, many stock analysts were content to act as well-dressed but passive conduits, conveying information from companies to favored investors. And because they feared being left out of the loop of selective disclosure, they hesitated to make negative comments about the companies they were supposed to track. The result was a never-never land where nearly all of the ratings they issued were ''buys.''</p>
        <p>In this new age of full disclosure, analysts seeking an edge will actually have to do some reporting and make gutsy calls. They may have to start earning those seven-figure bonuses by providing investors with more objective and useful reports.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, full disclosure may mean something else entirely to average investors -- a stock market that is as about as stable as an earthquake zone.</p>
        <p>Daniel Gross is the author of ''Bull Run: Wall Street, the Democrats, and the New Politics of Personal Finance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Gross is the author of ''Bull Run: Wall Street, the Democrats, and the New Politics of Personal Finance.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
