<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Time for Napping in Today's Kindergarten</title>
    <meta content="23KIND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/nyregion/23KIND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education (Pre-School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education (Pre-School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DA1631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Time for Napping in Today's Kindergarten</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kindergartens nationwide have become thicket of academic challenges as a result of increased state testing in elementary grades; states and school districts are writing formal curriculums for kindergarten, requiring students to learn reading and math skills that were once taught in first grade; more school districts are offering full seven-hour day of kindergarten after discovering that traditional three-hour programs do not allow time for academics that are becoming standard fare; changes hold true in poor schools as well as rich, and in small suburban schools as well as large urban ones; shift has prompted debate on how much is too much; some teachers, parents and child development experts say increased focus on reading and math has come at expense of play, and risk souring children on school at age when goal has long been to socialize them to it; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's only October, but already Nicky Beldoch is exhibiting symptoms of student ennui. The other day, when his mother asked him the best thing about school, he said lunch. Most boring? Art history.</p>
        <p>No surprise, given that he has homework every night and has been anxious about an oral report he has to deliver in science.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's only October, but already Nicky Beldoch is exhibiting symptoms of student ennui. The other day, when his mother asked him the best thing about school, he said lunch. Most boring? Art history.</p>
        <p>No surprise, given that he has homework every night and has been anxious about an oral report he has to deliver in science.</p>
        <p>But Nicky is 5, and he is in kindergarten. And while his mother, naturally, says that he is smarter than the average kindergartner, his day at Public School 9 on the Upper West Side of Manhattan looks much like the average day in kindergartens across the country.</p>
        <p>Once an idyll of graham crackers, fingerpainting and naps, the ''children's garden'' has become a thicket of academic challenges, a result of increased state testing in the elementary grades that demands students know more, sooner. States and school districts are writing formal curriculums for kindergarten, requiring students to learn skills like simple addition and reading that once were taught in first grade.</p>
        <p>More school districts are offering a full seven-hour day of kindergarten because they found that traditional three-hour programs did not allow time for the math, language arts and science lessons that are becoming standard fare. The changes hold true in poor schools as well as rich, in small suburban schools as well as  large urban ones.</p>
        <p>This month, Gov. Gray Davis of California signed a law raising the eligible age for kindergarten to 5 from 4 1/2, saying that tougher state standards demand more maturity. In well-off communities, principals and teachers say parents are going a step further, delaying their children's entry till age 6 in the hopes that they will be better prepared for the challenges. In 1991, 6.5 percent of parents held back their children one year. In 1995, the last year for which data is available, it was 9.7 percent.</p>
        <p>''The notion that kindergarten is a place where kids come and play is an anachronism,'' said Karen Lang, deputy superintendent of schools in Greenwich, Conn. ''The expectation by the professionals is that whatever children do, it's going to be time that leads to some kind of ultimate achievement. That doesn't mean it's not fun and kindergarten doesn't look at all like it used to, but things are done for a purpose.''</p>
        <p>But the move to a more academic kindergarten has prompted a debate about how much is too much. Some teachers, parents and child development experts say the increased focus on reading and math has come at the expense of play, and risks souring children on school at an age when the goal has long been to socialize them to it. Alarmed at the increased demands on kindergartners, a national association of early childhood educators put out a call to action this year warning against pushing children to read in kindergarten and criticizing the increased use of tests to evaluate how well kindergartners are learning basic skills.</p>
        <p>''With my others there was a progression throughout the year, but this is the first day of school they're doing this,'' said Helen Young, who, after watching six children go through kindergarten in Seneca Falls, N.Y., was amazed this year when her seventh, Katelyn, was asked to write in a journal and brought home books dissecting the parts of bees. ''Never mind the mother-child separation, it's 'Get to work!' ''</p>
        <p>While report cards used to assess kindergartners on whether they could speak in complete sentences and recognize their names, the new requirements demand much more. In detailed standards, California sets out what kindergartners must learn about basic probability and statistics, like gathering and recording data on charts and graphs.</p>
        <p>North Carolina's social studies curriculum suggests kindergartners choose samples of their work and plan how to discuss it with parents at a student-led conference, and requires children to be able to identify facts in nonfiction literature.</p>
        <p>And in Connecticut, the language arts curriculum requires kindergartners to read familiar books out loud with fluency, be able to give written and oral responses to questions about books read to them, and ''make valid inferences about characters and events using supporting details.'' Using check-off lists, and in some cases tests, teachers evaluate students on these skills several times during the year.</p>
        <p>One reason for the sophistication is that researchers now say children learn from a very early age. This same research has parents reading to their children in the crib, and many quote E. D. Hirsch Jr., the author of ''Cultural Literacy,'' (Houghton Mifflin, 1987) who describes kindergartners' minds as little sponges, ready to absorb information.</p>
        <p>In addition, with more and more women having entered the work force, about 60 percent of the nation's four million kindergartners have attended preschool. So most children have already been socialized to school, taking that task away from kindergarten. Some preschools also introduce the prereading concepts that were once left to kindergarten: knowing the alphabet and identifying the sounds letters make.</p>
        <p>''The feeling before was, 'When they're ready, they're ready,' '' said Richard Leadem, an elementary school principal in Fairfield, Conn., where 92 percent of this year's kindergartners attended preschool. ''There's a constant struggle to be sure we don't hurry the child, but the reality is, most of the children have already been in preschool for a full day for two or even three years.''</p>
        <p>There is pressure from above, too. Most states now test students extensively in the fourth grade, and there is almost universal agreement that if students do not read by third grade, they will not succeed in school.</p>
        <p>College admissions have become more competitive, and even that adds to the scurry. When Montgomery County, Md., revised its kindergarten curriculum last year, cutting out art as a separate subject and reducing time in physical education classes so schools could add more reading and math, one school official predicted that the district's SAT scores would ''skyrocket.''</p>
        <p>''In this business, as in any other, everybody looks down,'' said Robert Fiersen, an assistant superintendent in Manhasset, N.Y., where the schools now include beginning conversational Spanish in kindergarten. ''The high schools look to the middle schools, the middle schools look to the elementary schools and the elementary schools look to kindergarten. Ultimately, you're going to end up with prenatal reading.''</p>
        <p>In the kindergarten classrooms at the Osborn Hill School in Fairfield, the teachers' tone is still Mister Rogers, but the agenda is all business.</p>
        <p>Before the 9 a.m. bell rings, students begin with journal-writing. Then, they sit in a circle with one student leading the class to discuss the day. Everything has a purpose. When they discuss what month and day of the week it is, they recite the days of the months and the days of the week it is not. They discuss what color leaf they should place on their calendar according to the pattern of red-yellow-orange established over previous weeks.</p>
        <p>They count, using the concepts of ''tens'' and ''ones,'' to figure out how many days they have been in school. And after discussing the weather, they draw a bar graph of how many cloudy, sunny and rainy days there have been so far this month, analyzing which days are ''the most'' and which ''the least.'' Later, in math time, they use small blocks to build houses or designs, learning how to identify patterns (A-B, A-C, A-B) and identifying shapes like rhombus and hexagon. Asked to name a red block, a 5-year-old replies, ''A trapezoid,'' as if the answer should be obvious.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to bombard them, to come at them from a whole assortment of ways,'' said David Meglathery, the principal. ''We know more about learning; we know ways to make it more enticing. This batch of kids, they're going to be stronger.''</p>
        <p>The debate over kindergarten in Fairfield, in Connecticut's richest county, captures the larger debate over kindergarten. Last year, administrators pushed for a full-day kindergarten, saying they needed more time to teach the expanded curriculum. But parents resisted, saying children were too scheduled already. Ultimately, the town decided to offer both full-day kindergarten and an option to stay late just two days a week. Even then, parents worried that the full day would give some students an unfair advantage later on.</p>
        <p>Teachers prefer the longer day because, as Carol Bertilson at Osborn Hill said, in a half-day program, ''by the time they settled down and took off their coats, it was time to turn around and go home again.''</p>
        <p>But after a full day, some parents report that their children arrive home at 3:45 and promptly put on their pajamas. One student falls asleep in the car on the way home, although he lives only two blocks from school.</p>
        <p>And some teachers say academics have squeezed out some of the fun.</p>
        <p>''We used to do more creative arts and crafts,'' said Trish Tasco, who teaches at Osborn Hill. ''We didn't feel the crunch of the curriculum.''</p>
        <p>That complaint is heard elsewhere among parents. In Manhattan, Nicky's mother, Tracy Beldoch, said that she had been disabused of the notion that kindergarten was all play by the second year of nursery school, which already included some academics. Still, she said, she was surprised that her son's kindergarten  has only 25 minutes for recess in a seven-hour day.</p>
        <p>''The teacher said, 'We have a very busy curriculum, we have a lot to accomplish,' '' Ms. Beldoch said. ''What's to accomplish by the end of kindergarten?</p>
        <p>''There's nothing bad about children being exposed to these things,'' she added. ''But does it have to be at the expense of running around and letting out some energy?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
