<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Have to Be There, Even if They Can't Get In</title>
    <meta content="23SUBW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/23/sports/23SUBW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- TUNNEL VISIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D71631F930A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Have to Be There, Even if They Can't Get In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene outside Yankee Stadium during first two games of World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before Yankee Stadium underwent an extensive renovation in the mid-1970's, any big baseball fan with small resources could take the No. 4 train to 161st Street, walk out to one end of the elevated platform and, with no ticket other than a token, gaze down onto a slice of the emerald  green field where legends were playing.</p>
        <p>But then the outfield wall was raised. Subway platform spectators are now allowed nothing more than a tantalizing view of the upper deck in the distance, the tiptop of the stadium flagpole with its yardarm  shaped like a baseball bat, and the silvery lights reflecting back out of a stadium they cannot see into.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before Yankee Stadium underwent an extensive renovation in the mid-1970's, any big baseball fan with small resources could take the No. 4 train to 161st Street, walk out to one end of the elevated platform and, with no ticket other than a token, gaze down onto a slice of the emerald  green field where legends were playing.</p>
        <p>But then the outfield wall was raised. Subway platform spectators are now allowed nothing more than a tantalizing view of the upper deck in the distance, the tiptop of the stadium flagpole with its yardarm  shaped like a baseball bat, and the silvery lights reflecting back out of a stadium they cannot see into.</p>
        <p>And so the subway crowd that once gathered on the platform for games  has all but disappeared.</p>
        <p>But with the city in the grip of the first Subway Series since 1956, there are once again at least a handful of ticketless fans who believe that it is not enough to watch the game on television or listen to it on the radio.</p>
        <p>They want to be there, to hear ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' echoing out of the park, to hear the names of the batters somberly intoned by Bob Sheppard, the Yankees' public address announcer, and to try to divine from the roars and silences of the crowd what is going on behind that beige wall that is about as far away as a throw to first base.</p>
        <p>''I always like to stand here for a while, just to get the feel of the game,'' said Jose Esquilin, 57, a retired hospital maintenance worker. Mr. Esquilin walked about 20 minutes from his apartment to the elevated station last night, arriving just in time to hear the Ocean Township and Point Pleasant Boro high school bands run through a pounding rendition of ''Louie, Louie'' one last time before filing into the stadium.</p>
        <p>''Maybe some people feel bad, standing here so close and not getting to see anything,'' Mr. Esquilin said. ''But it's the scene, you know. I mean, look around you. Have you ever seen anything like this? I'm probably going to go on down to Manhattan later to watch the rest of the game with a friend of mine. But you've got to come by here for a little while, right? It's the patriotic thing to do.''</p>
        <p>As Game 2 got under way last night, and a biting October wind picked up, only the hardiest among the platform crowd remained, dwindling slowly with each passing No. 4 train. But there remained the left-out spectators who really had no choice but to stay and try to imagine what was going on behind the big wall: the police officers who patrolled the platform, the supervisors who kept the trains rolling and the transit workers who were beginning in earnest to pick up after the crowd that had just surged through.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees just scored,'' announced Glen Shadrick, a train service supervisor, who had cocked his ear to the crowd noise. Then, like a seasoned platform fan, he listened for what came out of the stadium next. ''There it is,'' he said. ''You can tell they scored because they wouldn't play that kind of happy music at Yankee Stadium if the Mets had scored, would they?''</p>
        <p>About 8:30, Martin Terrizzi, another train supervisor, jogged up to the platform and yelled at Mr. Shadrick: ''Hey, you see that thing with Piazza? Oh, my God!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shadrick looked out from beneath the brim of his hat. ''Now how am I going to have seen what happened with Piazza? How did you see what happened with Piazza?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Terrizzi admitted: ''I was downstairs in the office. I saw it on television.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES -- TUNNEL VISIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
