<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup and Chase Post Earnings That Exceed Expectations</title>
    <meta content="Y20CITI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DE1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup and Chase Post Earnings That Exceed Expectations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citigroup, the biggest financial services company, earned more than $3 billion for the second consecutive quarter, despite a sharp drop in the performance of its Salomon Smith Barney securities unit. At Chase Manhattan Bank, the No. 3 United States bank, the drag on earnings came from its investments in private companies.</p>
        <p>Both companies reported second-quarter earnings yesterday that were higher than a year earlier and exceeded analysts expectations. Citigroup shares rose $1.3125, to $68, on the news, while Chase shares slipped 25 cents, to $50.6875.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citigroup, the biggest financial services company, earned more than $3 billion for the second consecutive quarter, despite a sharp drop in the performance of its Salomon Smith Barney securities unit. At Chase Manhattan Bank, the No. 3 United States bank, the drag on earnings came from its investments in private companies.</p>
        <p>Both companies reported second-quarter earnings yesterday that were higher than a year earlier and exceeded analysts expectations. Citigroup shares rose $1.3125, to $68, on the news, while Chase shares slipped 25 cents, to $50.6875.</p>
        <p>Strong growth in its consumer businesses around the world helped Citigroup increase its net income 23 percent, to $3.005 billion, or 87 cents a diluted share, from $2.45 billion, or 70 cents a diluted share, in the second quarter of 1999. That profit was down significantly from Citigroup's first-quarter profit of $3.6 billion, which was the biggest quarterly profit any company has reported, according to First Call/Thomson Financial. Analysts expected earnings of 83 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Earnings at the Salomon unit were down 33 percent from the first quarter and up just 5 percent from the period a year earlier, at $641 million. Salomon was hurt by the downturn in stock market activity and a slowing  in bond trading, caused in part by rising interest rates.</p>
        <p>Sanford I. Weill, Citigroup's chairman and chief executive, noted that the Smith Barney brokerage unit took in $24 billion in new money from United States customers in the quarter, surpassing the $11 billion its bigger rival, Merrill Lynch, reported.</p>
        <p>''Looking at what some of our competitors did, relative to the size of our sales force, we did excellent,'' Mr. Weill said.</p>
        <p>Unlike Merrill, which said this week that it would cut 1,800 jobs in its brokerage unit, Smith Barney has no layoffs planned, Mr. Weill said. ''We run a very efficient retail brokerage business,'' he said. ''We like to run it on a steady-as-you-go basis.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weill said that rising interest rates had not posed a problem for Citigroup's consumer lending businesses. ''We continue to see in the U.S. very strong credit quality trends with delinquencies continuing to decline,'' he said. ''Writeoffs are at the lowest level in five years.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup said it would split its shares on a 4-for-3 basis next month.</p>
        <p>A few blocks away at Chase headquarters, executives sounded upbeat even though Chase's earnings fell 22 percent, to $1.09 billion, or 85 cents a diluted share, from $1.39 billion, or $1.06 a diluted share, a year earlier. Excluding one-time charges, Chase earned 95 cents a share, beating analysts estimates by 12 cents.</p>
        <p>Chase officials attributed most of the decline in profit to the falling value of its private equity investments. Chase had private equity gains of just $298 million, down from $513 million a year earlier.</p>
        <p>''That's a real reassuring number that showed that even in a tough, dislocated market, they can protect their reported earnings,'' said Judah Kraushaar, an analyst at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Investors are more concerned about the bank's expenses rising faster than its revenue, Mr. Kraushaar said. Chase has spent a lot of money hiring people and buying companies to add heft to its investment banking business and, he said, the ''question for investors is can they stay on top of the investments and turn it around quickly?''</p>
        <p>Marc Shapiro, Chase's vice chairman, tried to reassure investors that spending would not outpace revenue growth for long.</p>
        <p>''We don't have what I call a field-of-dreams strategy that says we will spend all of this money and hope that one day the revenues will come in and pay for it,'' he said. ''We intend to pay for things on a pay-as-you-go basis.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
