<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tax Cut in Small Slices</title>
    <meta content="20TAX.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hastert, J Dennis (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D91F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tax Cut in Small Slices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of House Speaker J Dennis Hastert's strategy of substituting series of narrow tax cuts that could rise or fall on their political appeal for one hugely expensive tax package that Pres Clinton would oppose; bills have attracted significant support from Democrats, who are arguing only about size of cuts, but are still opposed by Pres Clinton; both parties seem to be betting that political benefits of conflict outweigh risks of backlash from voters who might prefer compromise (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In early January, Speaker J. Dennis Hastert told the Republican leadership to abandon its effort to pass a single, hugely expensive tax-cut package in the face of opposition from President Clinton. Instead, he ordered up a series of narrow tax measures that could rise or fall not on their price tags but on their political appeal.</p>
        <p>''People understand these in individual bites,'' Mr. Hastert said in an interview today. In one sense his strategy has played out as well as he could have hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In early January, Speaker J. Dennis Hastert told the Republican leadership to abandon its effort to pass a single, hugely expensive tax-cut package in the face of opposition from President Clinton. Instead, he ordered up a series of narrow tax measures that could rise or fall not on their price tags but on their political appeal.</p>
        <p>''People understand these in individual bites,'' Mr. Hastert said in an interview today. In one sense his strategy has played out as well as he could have hoped.</p>
        <p>Following the lead of the House, the Senate has passed the two biggest tax bills of the year, one that would repeal the federal estate tax and another that would provide a tax cut to nearly all married couples. And today the House overwhelmingly passed a measure that would increase the allowable level of tax-deductible contributions to individual retirement accounts and 401(k) retirement programs. [Page A20.]</p>
        <p>In every case, the measures have attracted significant support from Democrats, who at this point are arguing not about whether tax cuts are justified, only about how big they should be. Flush with success, and bolstered by sharp upward revisions in the projected federal budget surplus, Republicans said Mr. Hastert's strategy had proved that tax cuts still packed a political punch.</p>
        <p>But in another sense, Mr. Hastert's strategy has led nowhere.</p>
        <p>With an exception for the legislation that removed the limit on how much people over 65 could earn before losing part of their Social Security benefit, Mr. Clinton has refused to go along, and in recent days the administration has unleashed a sharp attack on the Republican tax cuts as a fiscally irresponsible giveaway to the wealthy. Vetoes are almost certain for the estate tax and marriage tax bills.</p>
        <p>The result is a continuation of the ideological standoff that has defined fiscal policy since the Republicans took control of Congress in 1994. And it has led both parties to bet that the political benefits of conflict in this election year will outweigh the risks of any backlash from voters who might prefer to see compromise.</p>
        <p>Most Republicans seem confident that they will get credit from voters for having passed the tax cuts. They say Democrats in Congress and Mr. Clinton, and by extension Vice President Al Gore, will come off as obstructionist, out of sync with the politics of prosperity and on the side of the Internal Revenue Service.</p>
        <p>''Americans increasingly see the tax code as unfair or even stupid,'' said Frank Luntz, a Republican poll taker.''The context that Republicans are trying to set up is that if George W. Bush is elected president, there will be no marriage penalty, no death tax.''</p>
        <p>But some Republicans, including Mr. Hastert, are concerned that the party not be seen as totally unwilling to compromise. As the House and Senate prepare to hash out the differences between the bills they passed to cut taxes for married couples, Mr. Hastert is pushing for the final legislation to look more like the House bill, which is less expensive and does less for upper-income taxpayers.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to give the president any excuse not to sign it,'' Mr. Hastert said. ''It's not good enough to pass a bill and send it to the president's desk and have him veto it.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts go even further and say that the Republicans have missed an opportunity to get all they could realistically hope to accomplish on tax cuts and to neutralize the charge that they are running a do-nothing Congress. They say that Democrats, nervous about being caught on the wrong side of the changing politics of taxation, have offered alternatives that should have been very attractive to Republicans.</p>
        <p>In debating tax cuts for couples, Democrats in the Senate offered a plan to all but eliminate the marriage penalty paid by many two-income couples, though only for couples earning less than $150,000. Democrats in the House and Senate both offered plans to reduce the estate tax substantially. But Republicans brushed those offers aside.</p>
        <p>Republicans ''won't take yes for an answer,'' said Bruce Bartlett, an economist at the National Center for Policy Analysis, a conservative research group.</p>
        <p>''Democrats have moved a long way in the direction of the Republican agenda,'' Mr. Bartlett said. ''But Republicans seem to have made their plans six months ago and bulled their way through without taking into account any change in circumstances. The makings of a deal are there, but they seem to be rejecting it in favor of an all-or-nothing approach, which is pig-headed.''</p>
        <p>The calculation from the Democratic side is that voters will see that the individual tax bills add up to the same big package that Republicans abandoned last year.</p>
        <p>Taking their cue from the White House, Democrats in Congress are seeking to portray Republicans as working on behalf of a thin slice of the wealthiest taxpayers and ignoring the concerns of lower-  and middle-income people who need tax breaks for child care, health care and college tuition costs.</p>
        <p>''Their base is that rich 2 percent, our base is the rest, and that will be the fight,'' the Democratic leader in the Senate, Tom Daschle of South Dakota, said this week.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of Democrats are siding with Republicans, reflecting both the growing surplus and the fact that their base in the middle class is seeing its tax bill rise as it becomes increasingly affluent. To some extent, Democrats are trying to insulate themselves from assertions that they remain mired in their tax-and-spending past.</p>
        <p>Among the Democrats who voted for both the estate-tax repeal and the tax cut for couples was Senator Robert G. Torricelli of New Jersey, a state where taxes have been a critical political issue. Mr. Torricelli said today that he was interested in running for governor.</p>
        <p>''Tax cutting is not the sole domain of the Republican Party,'' said Richard McGrath, the senator's spokesman. ''Middle-class families with two incomes still have to struggle to pay basic expenses and should be given a break.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
