<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford, Sued in Air-Bag Case, Says Victim Was Strangled</title>
    <meta content="20FORD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Eric (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Tracy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDC1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford, Sued in Air-Bag Case, Says Victim Was Strangled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Company, accused by Dr Eric Thomas of killing his wife when her air bag inflated in crash three years ago, is defending itself by asserting that Tracy Thomas was actually strangled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company, accused by a New Jersey man of killing his wife when her air bag inflated in a crash three years ago, is defending itself by asserting that the woman was actually strangled.</p>
        <p>Ford's assertion has enraged the woman's husband and his lawyers, who are seeking to expand a lawsuit to include defamation charges against the automaker. Ford, the lawyers said yesterday, should pay heavy punitive damages for trying to avoid responsibility for a faulty product by tacitly suggesting that their client murdered his wife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company, accused by a New Jersey man of killing his wife when her air bag inflated in a crash three years ago, is defending itself by asserting that the woman was actually strangled.</p>
        <p>Ford's assertion has enraged the woman's husband and his lawyers, who are seeking to expand a lawsuit to include defamation charges against the automaker. Ford, the lawyers said yesterday, should pay heavy punitive damages for trying to avoid responsibility for a faulty product by tacitly suggesting that their client murdered his wife.</p>
        <p>But Susan Kruzel, a Ford spokeswoman, said the company merely wanted to bring evidence in the case to the prosecutor's attention. ''Our goal is to defend our product,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The case dates from Feb. 9, 1997, when Tracy Thomas, a former ballet dancer who was 37 years old and six months pregnant, died after the Ford Explorer she was driving skidded into a utility pole at about 15 miles per hour, not far from her home in Cape May Courthouse, N.J.</p>
        <p>Her husband, Dr. Eric Thomas, is suing Ford in United States District Court in Camden, claiming that his wife was killed by the force of an air bag deploying at 200 m.p.h. Dr. Thomas was riding in the passenger seat, and the couple's young daughter, who also survived, was in the back seat.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas is seeking unspecified compensatory damages for the loss of his wife in the case.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas's death was ruled an accident by the Cape May County prosecutor's office, which administered a lie detector test to Mr. Thomas at his own lawyer's request. Mr. Thomas passed the test.</p>
        <p>The accident is among 60 low-speed traffic deaths that the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration has investigated since 1990 and has found to have been caused by air bags. Tim Hurd, a spokesman for the highway safety agency, said the cause in the agency's file is taken directly from the coroner's report, and reads ''blunt trauma to neck with asphyxia.''</p>
        <p>But among the evidence presented by Ford during the pretrial discovery phase is a report by a pathologist it hired who concluded that Ms. Thomas was not killed by the air bag. ''In my opinion, Mrs. Thomas died of compression of the neck by the hands of another,'' wrote the pathologist, Dr. Michael M. Baden.</p>
        <p>Tom Mellon, a lawyer for Dr. Thomas, said Dr. Baden's conclusion conflicted with findings of the county prosecutor, the coroner and the Highway Traffic Safety Administration. He also said that Ford tried to persuade the county prosecutor to reopen the case as a criminal investigation in an attempt to intimidate his client into dropping the suit.</p>
        <p>Ford has hired Floyd Abrams, a well-known specialist in First Amendment cases. Mr. Abrams appeared at a pretrial hearing on Tuesday to oppose a motion to expand the suit to include the defamation charge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abrams argued that lawyers should be given broad latitude to say and do things in their clients' defense, even if, in other circumstances, those things might be grounds for defamation or other charges. If the judge allows the defamation charge, Mr. Abrams said, it could set a precedent that ''would chill the bar from doing its job of representing clients.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
