<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If TV's Just Not Enough: Conventions on the Net</title>
    <meta content="20CONV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raney, Rebecca Fairley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3D6113BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1219" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If TV's Just Not Enough: Conventions on the Net</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REBECCA FAIRLEY RANEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raney, Rebecca Fairley</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet coverage of national conventions this year is being compared to television coverage in 1950's, when networks were still learning what cameras could do; in addition to Web coverage by major news organizations, many independent producers and political parties themselves are experimenting with novel ways to follow conventions online, including chatrooms, instant polling, 360-degree cameras, exclusive interviews and e-mail updates; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLITICAL conventions were once smoky back-room affairs. Then they became television events. Now they have moved to the Net.</p>
        <p>Naturally many major news organizations are offering extra coverage online. But in addition, the major political parties and independent Web producers are offering novel ways to follow the conventions online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLITICAL conventions were once smoky back-room affairs. Then they became television events. Now they have moved to the Net.</p>
        <p>Naturally many major news organizations are offering extra coverage online. But in addition, the major political parties and independent Web producers are offering novel ways to follow the conventions online.</p>
        <p>Many Internet experts say that at this point in history, the use of the medium may be like the use of television at conventions in the 1950's, when networks were still learning what the cameras could do.</p>
        <p>The online experiments with convention coverage are ''kind of like 3-D glasses at the movies,'' said Larry Purpuro, deputy chief of staff for the Republican National Committee. ''It's for the fun of the experiment,'' he said, ''but they're not so fun to use.'' Mr. Purpuro is director of the party's e.GOP project, an effort to apply Web-based technologies to the committee's communications, fund-raising and organizing activities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Purpuro said that for party leaders, the Internet meant ''a tremendous opportunity for us to collect a lot of interest that can be developed and enhanced post-convention.'' The Republican convention will be held from July 31 to Aug. 3 in Philadelphia. After the convention ends, Mr. Purpuro said, the party can get in touch with people who have sent in their e-mail addresses.</p>
        <p>For many Web site producers outside the parties, the conventions present an opportunity to test different methods of telling a story and tapping the public's interests.</p>
        <p>During important speeches, producers at America Online will offer chats and instant polling to subscribers. The idea is to provide an outlet for discussion and debate to individuals who are more interested in politics than their families.</p>
        <p>''It's other people who are interested in it, not necessarily the people you live with,'' said Kathleen deLaski, director of political and government planning for America Online. ''That's the large part of the audience''  for America Online's political services, she added.</p>
        <p>AOL will produce a chat show every evening for both conventions. Unlike traditional media outlets, in which editors set the agenda, AOL will poll its members each day on what the topic of the show should be.</p>
        <p>The service is also offering ''delegate diaries,'' daily reports from delegates that will describe what the convention is like for the average delegate and put the procedures of the conventions into easily understood terms.</p>
        <p>Among the dozens of Web sites that plan to offer coverage beyond traditional news, a common idea is to use the Internet to augment the programs offered by the parties.</p>
        <p>Among the biggest problems the parties face when organizing conventions is deciding whom to include on the speaking schedule. FreedomChannel.com, a nonpartisan site (www.freedomchannel.com), doesn't face the same time constraints, so it will offer video clips of prominent political figures who are not scheduled to speak at the convention. For example, the group is working to arrange a speech from Jeb Bush, the governor of Florida and a brother of George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''So many people want to speak at the conventions who never get to the podium,'' said Daniel Manatt, media director of FreedomChannel.com, which is based in Washington. ''So we want to offer an unlimited amount of time on our Web site. The whole idea of the Internet is that it's limitless.''</p>
        <p>Video clips of the conventions will not be hard to find on the Web. Two Internet companies not affiliated with major news organizations have secured skyboxes at both conventions: AOL and Pseudo Programs Inc. The skyboxes, which provide overall camera coverage of the convention floor, are usually reserved for television networks.</p>
        <p>For Pseudo Programs, which has a Web site at www.pseudo.com, the central feature of the convention coverage will be the use of 360-degree cameras. The cameras show whatever surrounds them, and the company's presentation online will allow members of the audience to choose their own views rather than depend on a perspective chosen by a photographer.</p>
        <p>''We're really giving people the opportunity to sit in the control box,'' said Jeanne Meyer, senior vice president of Pseudo Programs. The conventions will give ''a huge illustration of what we can do,'' she said, ''that we're not just television squeezed on the Internet.''</p>
        <p>The company asked Democratic and Republican groups to nominate a few members to cover the convention. The company is letting its viewers select the people who will be sent.</p>
        <p>The Democrats are also planning to use a 360-degree camera to provide nonstop video coverage on their Web site, www.dems2000 .com. Party officials hope that the camera will give ''a free and open perspective'' on their convention, which will run from Aug. 14 to Aug. 17 in Los Angeles, said Peter Ragone, a spokesman for the Democratic National Convention Committee. The Democrats want to offer extensive detail on the Internet about issues, he added.</p>
        <p>''If you happen to be a person whose chief interest is the environment,'' he said, ''we have the ability to talk in depth and in length with the voter.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats have collected the opinions of some members of the public online through a so-called interactive platform. By the deadline earlier this month, 460 people had submitted ideas electronically, and party officials said some of their ideas might be included in the party's platform.</p>
        <p>Joshua King, vice president of external affairs for SpeakOut.com, which built the interactive system for the party, said: ''Is this 460 more people than would have participated otherwise? Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>The Republicans are offering the public the opportunity to become ''dot-com delegates'' through their convention site at www.gopconvention.com. By signing up at the site, the Internet ''delegates'' will be able to see exclusive interviews with convention participants, receive updates from state delegations by e-mail, get a convention screen saver and send in their opinions.</p>
        <p>The success of the conventions online may well depend on how well the parties steer members of their audiences into their electronic dens at important moments.</p>
        <p>Experience has shown that major news articles and splashy events are the most likely factors to drive the public to political Web sites. So campaigns and political groups would do well to be prepared to steer  traffic from the convention sites to related Web sites while the interest is high.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to see how well prepared the parties are to catch a wave,'' said Prof. Michael Cornfield, director of the Democracy Online Project at George Washington University. He said it would be interesting to see if either party posted Web site addresses -- for their own convention sites or related sites -- on their stages.</p>
        <p>By driving traffic to their own Web sites, Professor Cornfield said, the parties can build ways to keep in touch with supporters at a time when voters are interested.</p>
        <p>''Political scientists will tell you,'' he said, ''that post-convention bounce really matters.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
