<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of the Asylum, Into the Rich Club</title>
    <meta content="20CROW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Mary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In Crowd, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DB1E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of the Asylum, Into the Rich Club</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews The In Crowd, film by Mary Lambert; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The In Crowd'' could best be described as some community theater mix of ''Rebecca'' and ''Caddyshack.'' Warner Brothers has asked that the press not reveal the ending of the film, but probably the only people who could be surprised at this movie will be those who wandered into the wrong multiplex theater by mistake.</p>
        <p>Mary Lambert, whose crystalline, dexterous video work of the 1980's made many of us believe she had a career in film ahead of her, directed this impersonal mishmash. Only a vaguely techno score and a pansexual central figure distinguishes it from summer thrillers of years past, back in the days when versions of the song ''The In Crowd'' by Ramsey Lewis or Dobie Gray would have been on the soundtrack. (For those who are about the age of this movie's cast, the song was used during a bank robbery sequence in the 1996 film ''Set It Off.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The In Crowd'' could best be described as some community theater mix of ''Rebecca'' and ''Caddyshack.'' Warner Brothers has asked that the press not reveal the ending of the film, but probably the only people who could be surprised at this movie will be those who wandered into the wrong multiplex theater by mistake.</p>
        <p>Mary Lambert, whose crystalline, dexterous video work of the 1980's made many of us believe she had a career in film ahead of her, directed this impersonal mishmash. Only a vaguely techno score and a pansexual central figure distinguishes it from summer thrillers of years past, back in the days when versions of the song ''The In Crowd'' by Ramsey Lewis or Dobie Gray would have been on the soundtrack. (For those who are about the age of this movie's cast, the song was used during a bank robbery sequence in the 1996 film ''Set It Off.'')</p>
        <p>''The In Crowd'' stars Lori Heuring, who resembles Madonna. Ms. Heuring plays Adrien, who has just been released from a mental asylum, St. Anastasia, and has been placed in a work program at a tony country club. Based on the characters and their poor little rich kids problems, the club must not be far from Melrose Place. Of course that show has been canceled, but those in need of a third-generation Xerox version of Darren Star's patented bitchery can wander into a theater running this film.</p>
        <p>Adrien finds herself caught in the intrigues at the country club, where Brittany (Susan Ward) takes an immediate liking to her. There's an obsessive nature to Brittany's courtship of Adrien as a friend that has something to do with Brittany's vanished older sister, Sandra, who looks just like Adrien. It turns out both women have some deep, dark secrets of their own. Brittany is not to be trusted, according to the herd of underdefined characters who stampede past Adrien. Only someone who was recently released from a movie mental asylum would allow herself to be fooled by Brittany. Sure, Adrien  reaches out to Brittany despite her better judgment because of some big void in Adrien's scarred soul that fuels a desperate need for friendship. But does it really matter?</p>
        <p>No, since the plot must build to a final cat fight that has to take place in a setting with as many lethal implements as a hardware store. Apparently all of the deserted warehouses were being used in other summer pictures, so the climactic battle in ''The In Crowd'' breaks out in a storage room under the country club.</p>
        <p>Some talented veteran actors get a chance to deepen their tans here, among them Daniel Hugh Kelly, Tess Harper and Nathan Bexton, who had a brief but very memorable turn in ''Go,'' where an Ecstasy overdose had him believing he could communicate with cats through telepathy.</p>
        <p>Some portions of ''The In Crowd'' are just as funny as his scenes in ''Go,'' just not intentionally. Many of the younger actors -- Ms. Heuring and Laurie Fortier -- flash a hint of something, but they mostly do their best to stay out of the way of that surprise ending.</p>
        <p>THE IN CROWD</p>
        <p>Directed by Mary Lambert; written by Mark Gibson and Philip Halprin; director of photography, Tom Priestley; edited by Pasquale Buba; music by Jeff Rona; production designer, John D. Kretschmer; produced by James G. Robinson; released by Warner Brothers. Running time: 110 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Susan Ward (Brittany Foster), Lori Heuring (Adrien Williams), Matthew Settle (Matt Curtis), Nathan Bexton (Bobby), Tess Harper (Dr. Amanda Giles), Daniel Hugh Kelly (Dr. Henry Thompson) and Laurie Fortier (Kelly).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
