<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is the Customer Ever Right?</title>
    <meta content="20SERV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumers and Consumption</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hafner, Katie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDC1E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is the Customer Ever Right?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATIE HAFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hafner, Katie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Customer-service satisfaction, as measured by index compiled at University of Michigan, has dropped overall since 1994, and consumers are unhappy with service they are receiving from nearly every sector of the economy; one major cause is technology itself; phone systems and Web sites that are supposed to help can turn into infuriating mazes; also contributing to problem is an overall labor shortage, which has forced companies to hire less qualified workers for what are already low-paying, largely thankless jobs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRENDA WINEGARDNER has been having a nightmare that is increasingly familiar to most consumers. In it she wanders between reality and virtual reality, from voice mail to e-mail to customer service counter, trying to get her computer fixed. But it's not a dream.</p>
        <p>Since January, Ms. Winegardner, who operates a Web-based gift shop and mail-order business from her home in Monte Rio, Calif., about 60 miles north of San Francisco, has been battling CompUSA's customer service department because, she said, the Hewlett-Packard personal computer she bought there regularly slows down, then crashes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BRENDA WINEGARDNER has been having a nightmare that is increasingly familiar to most consumers. In it she wanders between reality and virtual reality, from voice mail to e-mail to customer service counter, trying to get her computer fixed. But it's not a dream.</p>
        <p>Since January, Ms. Winegardner, who operates a Web-based gift shop and mail-order business from her home in Monte Rio, Calif., about 60 miles north of San Francisco, has been battling CompUSA's customer service department because, she said, the Hewlett-Packard personal computer she bought there regularly slows down, then crashes.</p>
        <p>''I got hives from the stress,'' she said after a recent visit to the store's real-world customer service counter, pointing to a telltale splotch on her cheek. She has often lain awake until 3 a.m. The hours she has spent on hold, not just with the store, but also with CompUSA's corporate headquarters and with Hewlett-Packard, she said, are too numerous to count.</p>
        <p>When she does reach a human, she said, she encounters rudeness, incompetence or plain indifference. It's the unpleasantly real version of a well-known sketch from the 1970's British television show, ''Monty Python's Flying Circus.'' In the skit, a man tries to return a dead parrot to a pet store and encounters a clerk who insists that the parrot is ''resting.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Winegardner has had to struggle to have her complaint heard, she added, even though she sprang for CompUSA's $349.99 Premium Gold Service when she bought the computer. The card guaranteed unlimited access to technical support for three years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Winegardner's experience is far from unusual, and CompUSA is no different from many other stores. Customer service that fails to satisfy is increasingly common. As measured by the American Customer Satisfaction Index, compiled at the University of Michigan, customer-service satisfaction has dropped overall since 1994.  American consumers are more unhappy with the service they are receiving for nearly every sector of the economy measured by the index, including the computer industry, hotels, airlines, telephone companies and automobile manufacturers. There are many causes, but one that is widely recognized is technology itself. Phone systems and Web sites that are supposed to help can turn into infuriating mazes.</p>
        <p>''This is a rough time for customer service,'' said Bob Chatham, a Forrester Research analyst who follows customer service.</p>
        <p>One reason, he said, may be a general decline in civility, but he also pointed to technological advances in customer service, or customer care, as it is known in industry parlance. For example, he said, automated phone answering systems can send a caller into a loop, provoking the same explosive anger usually reserved for tailgaters, slowpokes and that idiot with the cell phone driving in front of you.</p>
        <p>And the Web is often no help. For instance, Mr. Chatham said, ''I got an auto-response e-mail once from AT&amp;T Wireless that told me to call the call center.''</p>
        <p>''It's a fascinating paradox,'' said Laurel Pallock, an investigator who runs the complaint mediation program in the San Francisco district attorney's office. ''Here we are in this predicament because of technology, the very thing that is supposed to keep us from being in this predicament.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, Ms. Pallock was the host of a weekly television program on consumers' issues. ''I've gone on the air and said, 'You guys who own these companies, why don't you listen to your own customer service voice mail and see if you can get through to yourselves?' ''</p>
        <p>But even Ms. Pallock is not exempt from criticism. She was a guest on a local radio show recently when a man called in to complain about the automated phone system in Ms. Pallock's office. She apologized on the air, agreed that the office's phone system was ''horrible,'' called him afterward to give him her direct line and set about fixing the problem.</p>
        <p>Add to the phone rage what Mr. Chatham describes as still more dysfunctional aspects of today's customer service systems. More often than not, he said, customers' records on a company's Web sites are not linked with those maintained for the agents working by telephone.</p>
        <p>''There's a self-inflicted phenomenon going on here. Companies got all excited about this technology, so they put it up without thinking about how it relates to everything else they do. Once they opened that Pandora's box, it launched this whole litany of problems.''</p>
        <p>But there is another, less technical, explanation for the decline in service. Mr. Chatham cited the overall labor shortage, which has forced companies to hire less qualified workers for what are already low-paying, largely thankless jobs.</p>
        <p>''Would you look forward to coming to work if you had to spend the day talking to irate cusotmers?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>As a result, turnover on customer service desks runs as high as 100 percent per year, he said.</p>
        <p>One author has even suggested that dissatisfaction has to do with customers' experiences with good service. Dr. Leonard Berry, a professor of marketing at Texas A&amp;M University and author of ''Discovering the Soul of Service'' (Free Press, 1999), agreed that service was not good. ''I give service in America a C minus,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, Dr. Berry added, people's expectations for service are rising. ''We want better service even though we think we'll get worse service,'' he said. ''And part of the reason is because we have experienced excellent service enough to know that it's possible.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the explanation, there seems to be no dispute about the reality of the decline. Complaints to the Better Business Bureau have risen sharply in recent years, said Ron Berry (no relation to Leonard Berry), senior vice president of the Council of Better Business Bureaus in Arlington, Va. Even so, Mr. Berry added, only a small percentage of disgruntled customers actually file formal complaints to bureaus.</p>
        <p>Rachel Barany, an educational consultant in New York, is a conspicuous exception. In March, she bought a Sony VAIO notebook computer at Data Vision, a computer retailer in Manhattan, but she was unable to get the computer to work properly. After several rounds of phone calls and repeated trips to the store, she sent off a raft of letters and cc's to the Better Business Bureau, Sony, The New York Times, Data Vision and American Express, whose card she used to pay for the machine.</p>
        <p>Finally, last month, Data Vision allowed Ms. Barany to exchange her computer for a less expensive I.B.M. Thinkpad. The difference in price was issued as a store credit.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Barany is unhappy with the store credit. She wants a refund.</p>
        <p>Every dispute has at least two sides. Jim Garson, a vice president of Data Vision, said that there was nothing wrong with Ms. Barany's laptop and that all it needed was a software patch for the internal modem. He said that he had offered to install the software for her but that she had declined. By allowing her to trade for the newer computer, he said, he took a loss on the old one.</p>
        <p>''I don't take back a notebook three months later, especially when there's nothing wrong with it,'' he said. ''How much more customer service can you give?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garson said many of the complaints against his store were unfounded. One customer called Mr. Garson to say she had  bought an Olympus camera a year ago and  seldom used it, so she wanted to return it, he said. ''I said: 'Ma'am, there's nothing I can do. Try to sell it on eBay.' '' She complained to the Better Business Bureau.</p>
        <p>Some consumers do not feel satisfied unless they make themselves heard. Julie Kennedy, a corporate lawyer in San Francisco, is a customer service maven if ever there was one. On the phone, she always presses ''0'' immediately to reach a human. She shops only in stores that will give refunds, and she has no qualms about firing off a letter if she is dissatisfied. ''I think there's a social contract that goes beyond courtesy,'' Ms. Kennedy said. ''You pay someone money and you expect to be valued. It ticks me off when I find people so oblivious to that principle.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Kennedy also makes a point of sending a letter when she stumbles upon excellent service.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Ms. Kennedy called United Airlines to reserve a flight to Ireland,  using her free miles. Dodging the thicket of blackout dates made the task look formidable until she found an agent as interested in making the trip work as she was.</p>
        <p>''He was trying everything,'' she said. ''I was on the phone with him for over two hours. He tried every date, every time, and I got to use my free tickets.'' She sent a letter of praise to the airline.</p>
        <p>Another consumer who keeps careful watch over the service he gets is Jim Hobby. He has a professional interest in the subject as well: he is vice president of customer client care at Gateway and has spent 25 years in the customer service business, including time at American Express and Federal Express.</p>
        <p>''My kids call me the client from hell,'' he said. ''They say when they're out with me and I get this look, they run, because they know someone is going to get my lecture on what customer service should be.''</p>
        <p>What customer service should be, he said, is a collection of thoughtfully placed ''pleases'' and ''thank yous,'' combined with careful listening. These are known as soft skills. ''It's showing that you care and you want to work with the customer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Service via live chat is growing in popularity, Mr. Hobby said, and so is the use of e-mail for such interactions. Gateway has also simplified its automated phone system in response to what Mr. Hobby described as a great deal of customer frustration.</p>
        <p>Complaining is getting easier in some places. Many companies that emphasize customer service, like American Express, now let customers dispute charges on line.</p>
        <p>The Better Business Bureau has seen a rise in the number of online complaints it gets. And a growing number of sites dedicated to filing gripes are cropping up online.</p>
        <p>One such site, called uGetHeard.com, allows consumers to send both gripes and praise. Complaints are followed by efforts by uGetHeard.com to resolve the disputes. The average resolution is small -- around $50 -- but the gratification for the customer is beyond measure, said Michael Chen, the site's chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chen said he was inspired to set up the site after a particularly unpleasant experience he had last spring at a private mailing center in the San Francisco Bay Area, where he went to mail a package. After paying, he grew nervous when he saw that no one was wrapping the package, so he decided to do it himself.</p>
        <p>But when an employee demanded that he pay for the sealing tape he was using, he protested. After a while the manager emerged from the back. ''She said: 'You're really irritating. We're too busy to deal with you,' '' Mr. Chen recalled. ''I've never been spoken to like that.''</p>
        <p>That was all the impetus he needed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
