<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Seizes Computer Drive in a China Nuclear Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="Y20NUK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whistle-Blowers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Studies in Intelligence (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Risen, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trulock, Notra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDB1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Seizes Computer Drive in a China Nuclear Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES RISEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Risen, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Bureau of Investigation says it has seized computer hard drive from home of former Energy Department intelligence official Notra Trulock in probe of whether he disclosed classified data about government's investigation into whether China stole United States nuclear secrets; Trulock, whistleblower on handling of espionage case, holds move is aimed at silencing him, interview; at issue is Trulock's unpublished manuscript about case, which he distributed to Congressional aides and former intelligence officials and to Studies in Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency journal that rejected it and suggested to FBI that it represented unauthorized disclosure of classified data (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal Bureau of Investigation agents seized a computer hard drive from the home of a former Energy Department intelligence official in an effort to determine whether he had  disclosed classified information about the government's investigation into whether China had stolen United States nuclear secrets, officials here said today.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. agents removed the computer drive last Friday from the home of Notra Trulock, the Energy Department's former director of intelligence, after questions were raised about an unpublished, 62-page manuscript that he had written.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal Bureau of Investigation agents seized a computer hard drive from the home of a former Energy Department intelligence official in an effort to determine whether he had  disclosed classified information about the government's investigation into whether China had stolen United States nuclear secrets, officials here said today.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. agents removed the computer drive last Friday from the home of Notra Trulock, the Energy Department's former director of intelligence, after questions were raised about an unpublished, 62-page manuscript that he had written.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock, who resigned from the department last year and has been a major critic of the government's handling of the espionage inquiry, said the seizure of the computer drive was an effort to intimidate him into silence.</p>
        <p>''I came to expect this kind of treatment while I was at D.O.E.,'' he said in an interview. ''But I thought by leaving D.O.E. and going into the private sector, I would avoid it. Instead, it's only gotten worse. I have no job, no benefits and I was trying to start a consulting business and all my contact information was on the computer the F.B.I. seized. So I am dead in the water.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock was also questioned by the F.B.I. agents about whether he had kept any classified documents, and whether he believed there was any classified material in the manuscript, Mr. Trulock said.</p>
        <p>He said he told the agents that he had not had access to classified material on the spy case since he left the government and that there was nothing classified in the document.</p>
        <p>The agents also questioned the owner of the suburban Virginia town house where Mr. Trulock lives who is an Energy Department employee. She consented to the search of the house and agreed to the removal of the computer, which she also owns. But the F.B.I. agents did not show a search warrant to either Mr. Trulock or the owner of the town house, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock had acted as a whistleblower on the handling of the nuclear espionage case, revealing that the investigation had not been pursued aggressively within the government.</p>
        <p>In late 1998 he was a secret star witness for the House panel that investigated illegal technology transfers to China and revealed the existence of the long-delayed espionage investigation at Los Alamos National Laboratory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock became a lightning rod for criticism of the way the spy case played out. Scientists and Asian-American groups attacked the F.B.I. and the Energy Department for prematurely making Wen Ho Lee, a scientist at Los Alamos, the focus of the counter-intelligence inquiry.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lee was never charged with espionage, but has been arrested on charges of mishandling classified material.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. now says that the initial inquiry conducted jointly by the bureau and the Energy Department into the possible theft of nuclear data from Los Alamos was flawed, and has broadened the espionage inquiry to look beyond the New Mexico lab.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock wrote the manuscript about the spy case earlier this year, and then distributed a few copies to, among others, Congressional aides and former intelligence officials. One former intelligence official who read it suggested that it be submitted for possible publication in Studies in Intelligence, a C.I.A. journal.</p>
        <p>Studies in Intelligence declined to publish the manuscript and told Mr. Trulock that he should have it checked to determine whether it contained classified material. But at the same time, a C.I.A. official also referred the matter to the F.B.I., informing the bureau that the article represented an unauthorized disclosure of classified material.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. has begun what one official described as a preliminary investigation to determine whether the manuscript revealed secrets.</p>
        <p>''The F.B.I. received information from other government agencies that classified information was subject to a possible compromise,'' said an F.B.I. spokesman, John Collingwood. ''The F.B.I., working with the Department of Justice, has an obligation to at least preliminarily determine the facts and determine if further investigation is warranted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trulock recently wrote a shorter article on the spy case for the conservative magazine National Review, but that article did not prompt the F.B.I. inquiry, officials said.</p>
        <p>By the time he left the government last year, Mr. Trulock had not only become controversial with outside groups angered by the Wen Ho Lee case, but his willingness to speak out and criticize senior administration officials had made him plenty of enemies within the government. He was given a $10,000 award last year by Energy Secretary Bill Richardson for persevering in the espionage case.</p>
        <p>After leaving Energy, Mr. Trulock moved to the Washington office of TRW, a government contractor. But he was dismissed from his job in June. He says that he was told by one official there that he was being let go because TRW had a big contract with the Energy Department, and company officials had received pressure from the Energy Department to dismiss him.</p>
        <p>Both TRW and Energy Department deny the accusation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
