<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Happens After the Whistle Blows?</title>
    <meta content="20TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000807T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whistle-Blowers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bensel-Meyers, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6DF1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Happens After the Whistle Blows?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>KNOXVILLE, Tenn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Linda Bensel-Meyers discusses how her disclosure of alleged abuses in athletic department at University of Tennessee has affected her life; negative reaction to her disclosure from faculty, students and athletic boosters noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The whistle-blower finds comfort in her office these days, surrounded by books about Renaissance drama, her speciality. So long as Linda Bensel-Meyers can keep her mind in the past, she can forget about the lawsuits against her, the damage to her marriage, the anger of University of Tennessee officials and coaches, the threats by local fans who curse her as a traitor to the savage orange.</p>
        <p>But she is reminded of the present by the fat leather briefcase leaning against a leg of her desk. It is stuffed with what she calls her evidence, the paper trails that always lead back to the altered grades, ''friendly'' courses and plagiarized papers that she says the athletic department uses to keep varsity players eligible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The whistle-blower finds comfort in her office these days, surrounded by books about Renaissance drama, her speciality. So long as Linda Bensel-Meyers can keep her mind in the past, she can forget about the lawsuits against her, the damage to her marriage, the anger of University of Tennessee officials and coaches, the threats by local fans who curse her as a traitor to the savage orange.</p>
        <p>But she is reminded of the present by the fat leather briefcase leaning against a leg of her desk. It is stuffed with what she calls her evidence, the paper trails that always lead back to the altered grades, ''friendly'' courses and plagiarized papers that she says the athletic department uses to keep varsity players eligible.</p>
        <p>But now, the evidence is being used against her; one suit implies she has publicly released confidential student information, which she denies. After some five years of being ignored by the administration, she talked to ESPN last September after it began its own investigation of the athletic tutoring system.</p>
        <p>Four football players were suspended for a game pending the school's investigation, and Bensel-Meyers became a well-known pariah on campus. Students taunt her, teachers turn away. She says her office has been broken into, mostly as intimidation, she thinks. She is sitting now with her back to the office window that overlooks the 107,000-seat football stadium.</p>
        <p>''I never feel sorry for myself,'' she says, just a bit too stoutly, ''because I am responsible for my own decisions. I am not a victim. I hate it when people look at me with pity. Sometimes, however, I despair.''</p>
        <p>And then the righteousness of this 47-year-old Methodist church organist pops up. ''It is hard for one good person to live among those who are not good, and to try to make the right choices,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Bensel-Meyers is not alone these days as the American Association of University Professors and another national group of faculty members convened last year at Drake University in Iowa and considered reforms in intercollegiate sports. The Drake Group, in particular, has declared that big-time college sports is basically a corrupting influence on the academic mission of the university. And the Rutgers 1000, a group of professors and students, is calling for that university to divest itself of varsity sports.</p>
        <p>At Tennessee, a 44,000-student university, most members of the administration and the athletic department who speak on the record say Bensel-Meyers, who is a tenured associate professor, has made all the wrong choices, attacking a source of state pride. The Volunteers were national football champions two seasons ago. And, as officials point out, the National Collegiate Athletic Association conducted an investigation of her charges that took months and found no violations.</p>
        <p>''The campus is just weary of reading about all her charges,'' said the university president, J. Wade Gilley. ''We've had 9, 10 investigations in the 11 months I've been here, by the faculty senate, the conference, the National Collegiate Athletic Association, the Federal Bureau of Investigation -- what have I left out? -- and nothing was found that violated rules or laws.''</p>
        <p>Gilley says he thinks Bensel-Meyers may have an agenda, a ''big, pregnant idea,'' about de-emphasizing college sports. If that's it, he chuckles, then there's no better place to start than at a place that ''epitomizes the system, like Notre Dame or Tennessee.''</p>
        <p>Her voice is low. ''This is not my cause,'' she says. She talks into her hand. Her eyes rarely make contact. ''I'm a company person. I thought I'd be here forever. I went through channels. But my options have been limited because no one would listen to what I've been saying.</p>
        <p>''And when they did hear me, the attitude was, just fail the athlete who plagiarized. How can I do that, when the plagiarism was institutional, when the athlete thinks he's supposed to turn in a paper written by one of the hired tutors? How can I sacrifice some poor guy who bought into the dream just like me, to get off the farm.''</p>
        <p>Bensel-Meyers left the family chicken farm in Pendleton, Ore., 30 years ago for a scholarship to the University of Chicago. The third of four children who all became teachers, she always loved sports, she says. She roughhoused with her brothers. She ran track in high school and continued to play basketball and volleyball at the University of Oregon, where her Ph.D. dissertation was on ''The Duchess of Malfi,'' a bloodthirsty revenge tragedy, written by John Webster circa 1613.</p>
        <p>At Tennessee, where she began her first tenure-track teaching job in 1986, she says she has rarely missed a Volunteers football game on television. But she has never taken her three teenage sons to the stadium because she is afraid of crowds and heights.</p>
        <p>In 1989, she became director of composition, a job she loved, she says, because the required first-year writing course gave her a chance to shape a curriculum that would teach critical thinking and ''empower'' the many ''provincial, religious, concrete thinkers,'' who, as she had been, were the first generation in their families to attend college. She borrowed from the Great Books courses created at Chicago and from her own scholarship. She sees parallels between the Age of Gutenberg, when the printing press helped replace ethical reasoning with scientific thought, and the Age of the Internet.</p>
        <p>Among her early tasks was hiring and training the tutors who would help athletes, particularly male football and basketball players. Slowly, over the years, she began to realize, she says, that the athletes were being exploited by a system that did not deliver a real education in return for the millions of dollars the university made from their time and energy. Tutors came back with stories of being sexually harassed by athletes, not to mention having to write their term papers.</p>
        <p>Bensel-Meyers, with access to transcripts, began to notice patterns of grades being altered, of clusters of unusually high grades for athletes in certain courses, of special privileges. She thought there was abuse in the labeling of certain athletes as having disabilities, which could excuse them from having to read or write. She began to send memos to her superiors. She was ignored. She began sending e-mail messages, first to foreign colleagues whom she had met at Renaissance conferences, then to almost anyone who seemed to understand and would respond.</p>
        <p>''Linda is naive, a straight arrow who never understood the power she came up against,'' says Jeffrey Kovac, a 51-year-old chemistry professor and one of Bensel-Meyers's few public supporters at Tennessee. Last week, he quietly announced a legal defense fund to which faculty members could contribute anonymously.</p>
        <p>''Most faculty are cynical about sports,'' Kovac said. ''Athletes get away with murder, so what, just let me concentrate on neutron scattering. But I've also been a professional soccer referee for 20 years, and I've always thought, all we have is our integrity and a whistle.''</p>
        <p>Kovac's fund-raising is welcome news to David L. Buuck, a graduate of Tennessee and its law school who finds himself shunned, as well as underpaid, while defending Bensel-Meyers. The libel suit against  ESPN.com and a former head of the tutoring service, by a former player and a former tutor, does not even name Bensel-Meyers, but she had promised to pay for any of her teachers who were sued. ''I can't let them be punished because someone's trying to get at me,'' she said. ''I worry about my seven doctoral students, working on dissertations, mostly on the Renaissance.</p>
        <p>''What if after all this, my letters of recommendation are poison?''</p>
        <p>An injunction to keep his records private was filed by Spencer Riley, the center on last year's football team who is now trying out for the Buffalo Bills.</p>
        <p>The university's failure to defend her along with itself sent a chill through the faculty; would this be a precedent to punish anyone out of favor who became a target of litigation? Bensel-Meyers finds herself more and more isolated, with fewer responsibilities. She thinks she may be fired. She is afraid of going to her car at night in the campus underground garage. Her children hear remarks about her at school. Her husband, who thinks she is hurting the family, rarely talks to her.</p>
        <p>''I think it's good for my kids to see what I'm doing,'' she says, not sounding absolutely certain. ''Or it will be someday. We can't teach people abuse of the law and not expect it will lead to more crime. We're losing values in this country, and the university may be the only place left to preserve these values.</p>
        <p>''We need to teach kids there's a reason to be on earth and it's not just grabbing off pleasure. I believe if people have all the information they'll choose the right thing. That's why I talk to the media, why I send out all these e-mails. But then I have this image of myself doing cartwheels along the edge of a cliff, blindfolded. I think I'll be all right as long as I don't see where I'm going.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGES  Correction:  August 7, 2000, Monday  An article on July 20 about a University of Tennessee professor who made charges about improprieties in academic work by varsity athletes misstated the number of students at the Knoxville campus. It is 26,000, not 40,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 7, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on July 20 about a University of Tennessee professor who made charges about improprieties in academic work by varsity athletes misstated the number of students at the Knoxville campus. It is 26,000, not 40,000.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
