<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japan and U.S. Reach Trade Pact on Telecommunications</title>
    <meta content="Y20JAPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nippon Telegraph &amp; Telephone Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barshefsky, Charlene (US Trade Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DE1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japan and U.S. Reach Trade Pact on Telecommunications</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US-Japan trade agreement is reached that would likely make telecommunications services in Japan far more affordable, competitive and diverse; agreement comes after nine days of intense negotiations and averts major trade battle between Japan and US on eve of global summit Japanese are hosting; American trade officials, who have been pressing for increased access to $140 billion Japanese market, call it huge victory; its central feature is cuts in fees Nippon Telegraph and Telephone charges other telecommunications companies to use its domestic network, which covers 98 percent of lines to all customers; for other telephone companies, agreement will lower costs of linking up with Nippon Telegraph by average of 35 percent in two years and by at least 40 percent over three yearss; Charlene Barshefsky, US trade representative, comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With its ownership of nearly all telephone lines that go into Japan's homes and businesses, Nippon Telegraph and Telephone has long enjoyed a virtual monopoly in this country. Today, however, a United States-Japanese trade agreement was reached that would likely make telecommunications services in Japan far more affordable, competitive and diverse.</p>
        <p>The agreement came after nine days of intense negotiations and averted a major trade battle between Japan and the United States on the eve of a global summit the Japanese are hosting. American trade officials, who have been pressing loudly for increased access to the $140 billion Japanese market, called it a huge victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With its ownership of nearly all telephone lines that go into Japan's homes and businesses, Nippon Telegraph and Telephone has long enjoyed a virtual monopoly in this country. Today, however, a United States-Japanese trade agreement was reached that would likely make telecommunications services in Japan far more affordable, competitive and diverse.</p>
        <p>The agreement came after nine days of intense negotiations and averted a major trade battle between Japan and the United States on the eve of a global summit the Japanese are hosting. American trade officials, who have been pressing loudly for increased access to the $140 billion Japanese market, called it a huge victory.</p>
        <p>Its central feature is cuts in the fees that N.T.T. charges other telecommunications companies to use its domestic network, which covers 98 percent of the lines to all customers.</p>
        <p>For other telephone companies, the agreement will lower the costs of linking up with N.T.T. by an average of 35 percent in two years and by at least 40 percent over three years, said Charlene Barshefsky, the United States trade representative.</p>
        <p>Those charges have been consuming roughly 40 percent of the revenue of N.T.T.'s competitors stifling competition to provide telecommunications services in the world's second-largest economy.</p>
        <p>''Japan has been placing a tax on the information age by the way it regulates N.T.T.,'' said Richard W. Fisher, Mrs. Barshefsky's deputy, in an interview. ''It's therefore a tax on competition, and that tax is going to come down substantially now.''</p>
        <p>While Japanese officials said the agreement was only modestly different from a proposal they had made in January, their American counterparts noted that it provided for significantly deeper cuts than the 17 percent reduction Japan had offered previously. The agreement also accelerates the timing of the cuts so they mostly happen over two years instead of Japan's original offer of five years.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, Japan agreed to reconsider its methods of setting the fees paid by N.T.T.'s competitors to use its network, which should have a more widespread effect on reducing fees and enhancing competition in 2002 and thereafter. But perhaps the most significant element of the deal is how it came together. That process ruptured longstanding relationships between regulators and politicians and N.T.T., and those rifts may lead to sweeping changes in regulatory structure here and in the structure of N.T.T. itself.</p>
        <p>''By how many percent interconnection fees are cut and whether it takes place over two or three years is not really very important,'' said Harumasa Sato, a professor at Konan University in Kobe and a telecommunications policy expert. ''The important thing is that it may lead to fundamental reform of regulation that will create fair competition in this market.''</p>
        <p>The broader scope of the agreement came about in part because of the way the United States trade representative's office fought for it. United States negotiators moved the debate out of the confines of the Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications, which regulates telecommunications, and into a broader public view.</p>
        <p>Thus, while past United States-Japanese trade fights over issues like film distribution, car parts and flat glass had failed to capture the imagination of ordinary citizens, the public took a major interest in this fight, and Japanese politicians noticed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisher embarked on a calculated campaign to make the issue relevant to consumers in Japan, doing numerous interviews with the Japanese media, using easily understood examples of why high connection fees hurt Japan's prosperity.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly bemoaned that only 10 percent of Japanese elementary and middle school students could connect to the Internet because charges were so high. He asked why his daughter paid less than $9 a month for Internet service in the United States while her Japanese friend in Tokyo paid eight times that amount.</p>
        <p>''Why should a Japanese girl be at such a disadvantage to an American girl?'' he asked over and over again.</p>
        <p>He made his case, apparently, because, with the exception of only one newspaper known for its strong conservative editorial view, Japan's major dailies all supported sharp reductions in connection fees.</p>
        <p>Japanese industry also spoke out. The business federation known as Keidanren, which represents Japan's giant, blue-chip organizations, argued for lower connection fees, and Hiroshi Mikitani, the founder and president of Japan's biggest e-commerce site, Rakuten Ichiba, commissioned a study about the impact of the fees on Japan's ability to harness the information technology revolution, which he then personally used to advocate lower charges.</p>
        <p>N.T.T.'s Japanese competitors weighed in on the side of lower rates, as did European and American companies attempting to break into the market. Even some of the companies under the N.T.T. umbrella, which also pay fees for connecting with the lines owned by the regional telephone companies that are their cousins, complained.</p>
        <p>The concerted effort worked, and around the beginning of the year, influential politicians began to question the postal ministry's arguments for only modest reductions in the connection fees.</p>
        <p>Mindful that its position on fees was now politically unacceptable, N.T.T. officials offered to accede to United States demands in exchange for pledges from sympathetic politicians that they would work to abolish the N.T.T. Law, which restricts the company from entering other types of businesses.</p>
        <p>That proposal appealed to Hiromu Nonaka, who is perhaps the most powerful politician in Japan and the secretary general of the ruling Liberal Democratic Party. Among his many roles, Mr. Nonaka serves as the leader of a large group of politicians with strong ties to the postal ministry and to N.T.T.</p>
        <p>And in the end, Mr. Fisher said, it was Mr. Nonaka who struck the deal on connection fees that emerged today. Mr. Fisher said the breakthrough came when Mr. Nonaka invited him and other United States officials, including Ambassador Thomas Foley, to a Tuesday morning meeting. It began with a 20-minute monologue by Mr. Nonaka on the role that telecommunications plays in a modern economy.</p>
        <p>''He gave me a very erudite and extremely thorough discussion about how Japan needed to come into the I.T. age and needed to restructure N.T.T. to do that,'' Mr. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>One hour after the meeting ended, Mr. Fisher said, the postal ministry called the embassy and asked for a meeting that resulted in the agreement.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
