<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Who Died on Staten Island Is Checked for West Nile Virus</title>
    <meta content="20NILE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D61E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Who Died on Staten Island Is Checked for West Nile Virus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal health authorities are analyzing blood of 71-year-old man who died on Staten Island to see if he was infected with West Nile virus; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal health authorities are analyzing the blood of a 71-year-old man who died on Staten Island yesterday to see if he was infected with the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>The man, whom hospital and government officials did not identify, was taken to St. Vincent's Medical Center on Staten Island on July 5 complaining of a headache, fever and confusion. Those symptoms are sometimes associated with encephalitis, which can be caused by West Nile, a mosquito-borne virus. The man, who was visiting from South Carolina, died early yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal health authorities are analyzing the blood of a 71-year-old man who died on Staten Island yesterday to see if he was infected with the West Nile virus.</p>
        <p>The man, whom hospital and government officials did not identify, was taken to St. Vincent's Medical Center on Staten Island on July 5 complaining of a headache, fever and confusion. Those symptoms are sometimes associated with encephalitis, which can be caused by West Nile, a mosquito-borne virus. The man, who was visiting from South Carolina, died early yesterday.</p>
        <p>City officials said yesterday that it was just as likely that the man died of an illness other than West Nile. ''It is highly premature for people to assume this gentleman was infected with West Nile virus,'' said Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city health commissioner, during a briefing with Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>In fact, several viruses peak in July and August and cause encephalitis, especially among small children and the elderly, health officials said. And the Staten Island patient, Dr. Cohen said, ''had a number of debilitating health conditions that may have been responsible for his illness and his deterioration.''</p>
        <p>But because crows infected with the virus were found on Staten Island earlier this month, Health Department officials took blood and spinal fluid samples from the man Tuesday to be sure that he was not the city's first human case of the virus this year. Last year, the virus sickened 62 people, killing 7 of them.</p>
        <p>The mayor said that test results from the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta were expected today or Friday. ''At this point there are several competing hypotheses for his illness,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''In other words, West Nile is not the only possibility.''</p>
        <p>This summer, 32 mosquitoes with evidence of the virus have been found in Westchester and Suffolk Counties, and 25 birds with confirmed infections have been discovered on Staten Island and in Rockland, Westchester and Suffolk Counties in New York and in Bergen County in New Jersey. But there have not been any confirmed cases in humans; 130 New Yorkers have had their blood tested, but the results were negative.</p>
        <p>The finding of dead birds and animals has led to the resumption of pesticide spraying in several counties, many of which have already taken preventive measures to kill mosquitoes since the spring.</p>
        <p>Staten Island was scheduled to be sprayed with insecticide last night and this morning. Several areas of Westchester County are scheduled for spraying later in the week.</p>
        <p>In Rockland County, officials said yesterday that they would spray next week in Clarkstown, where eight dead birds were found. Clarkstown includes Upper Nyack and parts of Nyack and Spring Valley. Rockland dropped larvicide in tens of thousands of catch basins and storm drains earlier this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
