<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Higher Fuel-Product Prices Barely Affecting Consumers</title>
    <meta content="Y20OIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Oil</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Petroleum Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDF1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Higher Fuel-Product Prices Barely Affecting Consumers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amerian Petroleum Institute says deliveries of gasoline in first half of 2000 were down about 0.7 percent, ending long period of growth; deliveries in 1999 ran 2 percent ahead of 1998, which itself was 3 percent ahead of 1997; group reports similar drop in oil-based fuels, which went down 0.8 percent, first decline in five years of economic expansion; data show that supplies of home heating oil were far lower than usual; Energy Sec Bill Richardson says he is making progress toward establishing reserve of heating oil in Northeast; experts expect few people to make radical changes in driving habits; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing higher fuel prices, motorists are guzzling less gas -- but only slightly less.</p>
        <p>The American Petroleum Institute said today that deliveries of gasoline in the first half of 2000 were down about 0.7 percent, ending a long period of growth. Deliveries in 1999 ran 2 percent ahead of 1998, which itself was 3 percent ahead of 1997. The industry group reported a similar drop in use of all oil-based fuels, which went down 0.8 percent, the first decline in five years of economic expansion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Facing higher fuel prices, motorists are guzzling less gas -- but only slightly less.</p>
        <p>The American Petroleum Institute said today that deliveries of gasoline in the first half of 2000 were down about 0.7 percent, ending a long period of growth. Deliveries in 1999 ran 2 percent ahead of 1998, which itself was 3 percent ahead of 1997. The industry group reported a similar drop in use of all oil-based fuels, which went down 0.8 percent, the first decline in five years of economic expansion.</p>
        <p>The data also showed that supplies of home heating oil were far lower than usual, but Bill Richardson, the energy secretary, said today that he was making progress toward establishing a reserve of heating oil in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The data from the industry group showed that despite the fact that prices have risen nationally by 60 or 70 cents a gallon, and more in the Midwest, the effect on consumption was small.</p>
        <p>And for some consumers, it is accomplished with minor lifestyle adjustments.</p>
        <p>Dennis Virag, an automotive consultant who commutes 40 miles each way from his home in Toledo, Ohio, to his job in Ann Arbor, Mich., said in an interview that he now sets the cruise control on his Mercury Villager minivan to 72 miles an hour instead of 80.</p>
        <p>He figures that the change costs him about five minutes and saves him about 5 percent of the four gallons he needs for his daily commute.</p>
        <p>Other drivers must be slowing down, too, he said: ''I was keeping up with traffic in the past, and I'm keeping up with traffic now.''</p>
        <p>Experts expect that few people will make radical changes. At the National Automobile Dealers Association, Paul C. Taylor, the chief economist, said that a family planning a 2,500-mile driving vacation in a midsize S.U.V., like a Chevy Blazer or a Ford Explorer, rated at 20 miles a gallon, would use 125 gallons. If the price of fuel this summer is 50 cents higher than last, that would cost an extra $62.50. ''That's about two stops at a fast-food restaurant for a family of five,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the American Automobile Association, Geoff Sundstrom, a spokesman, said, ''We've predicted record summer travel.'' And as for everyday travel, he said, ''For most people, driving is not an optional activity.''</p>
        <p>''This notion that people are just sort of driving aimlessly around in their car, and when gas prices go up they can stop driving, is quite mistaken,'' Mr. Sundstrom said.</p>
        <p>The drop of 0.7 percent since last year does imply a significant choice for conservation, though, because the number of vehicles is rising by about 4 million a year, reaching 209.5 million motor vehicles at the end of last year.</p>
        <p>In contrast to gasoline, deliveries of residual oil, used by industries that can often substitute natural gas if that is cheaper, declined by 17 percent in the first half of the year, the petroleum association said. Deliveries of jet fuel rose, pushed up by robust air traffic. And domestic oil production continued to decline, hitting a 50-year low, despite a tripling of crude oil prices, to the range of $34 a barrel recently, compared with around $10 last year.</p>
        <p>The industry group also said that heating oil inventories were sharply lower now than at this time last year, but they said that the significance of this to prices this winter was not clear, because more than 90 percent of heating oil used in a winter comes from production during the winter.</p>
        <p>About 40 industry executives met with the Mr. Richardson this afternoon to discuss heating oil and the two-million-barrel reserve that President Clinton ordered the agency to create earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Red Cavaney, the president of the petroleum institute, said that the reserve might make no difference in total supplies, because its existence would dissuade private businesses from stockpiling fuel.</p>
        <p>''They see no upside, recognizing that the government is probably going to sell it off at some point,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Richardson said, ''I believe I've convinced them that it's for emergency purposes only, and that we have no intentions of using it to manipulate prices or discourage them from increasing their inventories.''</p>
        <p>''The government doesn't want to be in the heating oil business.'' he continued, ''all we want to be able to do is respond in the event of a shortage or a severe price spike.''</p>
        <p>Energy department officials said that the reserve was too small to discourage private inventory-building. They said there was lots of surplus tank space in the Northeast, which they would lease for heating oil storage, bartering for the lease, and for the heating oil itself, with crude oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve on the gulf coast.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
