<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Does Nonfiction Mean Factual?</title>
    <meta content="20BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA1E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Does Nonfiction Mean Factual?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's Making Books column examines whether publishers really care about veracity of material in nonfiction books they publish (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In recent years it seems that there have been more and more blowups over the question of whether book publishers actually care about the veracity of the material in the nonfiction books they publish. Or to put it another way: there appears at times little to indicate that the culture of the industry requires what could be described as a predisposition among editors and publishers to be ferocious at authenticating.</p>
        <p>The explanation for this recurring phenomenon in a profession in which one would think a precision with words and facts would be paramount is complicated and goes to the very rituals of book publishing. As a debate, it erupted once again this past week over a new book about the Clintons in which Mrs. Clinton is accused of having used an anti-Semitic slur during a furious conversation in 1974. She denied the accusation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In recent years it seems that there have been more and more blowups over the question of whether book publishers actually care about the veracity of the material in the nonfiction books they publish. Or to put it another way: there appears at times little to indicate that the culture of the industry requires what could be described as a predisposition among editors and publishers to be ferocious at authenticating.</p>
        <p>The explanation for this recurring phenomenon in a profession in which one would think a precision with words and facts would be paramount is complicated and goes to the very rituals of book publishing. As a debate, it erupted once again this past week over a new book about the Clintons in which Mrs. Clinton is accused of having used an anti-Semitic slur during a furious conversation in 1974. She denied the accusation.</p>
        <p>The book is ''State of a Union: Inside the Complex Marriage of Bill and Hillary Clinton'' (HarperCollins). The author, Jerry Oppenheimer, a former reporter for The National Enquirer, names three sources for his account. But subsequent to its publication this week, the credibility of the sourcing was shredded.</p>
        <p>One of the sources heard the alleged slur while standing outside the door; a second wrote Mrs. Clinton a letter in 1997 apologizing for negative things he had told people who were writing books critical of the Clintons. Moreover, although there had been other reports of the heated conversation, none of those mentioned the ethnic slur, surely a startling moment not likely to be forgotten by anyone who heard the conversation and recounted it.</p>
        <p>No serious news-gathering organization would print or broadcast such an allegation based on this watery testimony; indeed, even if the information was triple checked and irrefutable, most responsible publications and television and radio news programs would at least ponder whether it was fair to report an emotional remark made 26 years earlier.</p>
        <p>So why did HarperCollins, a reputable publisher of many fine nonfiction books, let it go? (It is perhaps too cynical to suggest that the publicity generated by the debate is not entirely unwelcome.) The answer is in the culture of book publishing. James Fox, the general counsel for the publishing house, which is owned by Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation, said: ''I didn't have to have absolute proof of truth. I didn't have any reason to believe it was false or any reason to distrust the author or the information.''</p>
        <p>Journalism has a more rigorous standard: what is printed is believed to be true, not merely unsuspected of being false. The first rule of journalism is don't invent. Except in the most scholarly work, no such absolutes apply to book publishing. Actually the fictitious nonfiction book is not terribly uncommon.</p>
        <p>For starters, this means that the whole process of vetting a nonfiction book is essentially meant to protect against legal action, mostly libel suits, as well as copyright and trademark violations and negligence, i.e., making sure that a recipe in a cook book wouldn't kill anyone who tries it. Basically lawyers go through a manuscript and pick out what is questionable and decide whether it is publishable without consequences.</p>
        <p>Publishers are mindful of the background and reputation and expertise of their writers. But a company that publishes thousands of books a year simply cannot fact-check them. To protect themselves, nearly every author contract requires writers to indemnify the publishers, who also have protective insurance. In short, it's up to the author to be the fact checker. Mr. Fox said: ''You look at material that is problematic and look to be satisfied with the specifics. I hope the reader has a sensitivity to material that could be problematic.'' Thus, publishing's equivalent of caveat emptor.</p>
        <p>One assumes that publishers believe that this same reader beware was applicable to several other books published recently. Simon &amp; Schuster published ''Gone: The Last Days of The New Yorker,'' by Renata Adler, in which she casually dropped into the book that Judge John J. Sirica, who supervised the Watergate trial and who died in 1992, had ties to organized crime. The book included not a driplet of supporting evidence. Seven months later in Harper's magazine she has presented her argument to support the allegation, but finding proof in it was like searching for Robin Hood's barn, which no one ever found. Last year St. Martin's Press shredded an inaccurate biography of George W. Bush. Its vetting failed to uncover that the author, J. H. Hatfield, was convicted of hiring a hit man in an unsuccessful car bombing of his boss. And Random House agreed that significant changes were warranted in Jeffrey Toobin's ''Vast Conspiracy,'' another Clinton book, to correct factual errors. In 1998, Schocken Books, a Knopf imprint, suffered the ultimate absurdity: it printed 50,000 copies of a prize-winning nonfiction book first published in Germany that was entirely fiction. Called ''Fragments,'' it was said by its author, Binjamin Wilkomirski, to be a memoir of his time in Nazi camps. It was a hoax.</p>
        <p>The editing culture of book publishing and the relationship between the author and the publisher assures that such occurrences will regularly enliven the media community. The creation of a book is based on faith and trust between a writer and editor that is developed over the many months it takes to write a book, and the editor becomes the author's advocate and protector within the publishing house. Carol Janeway, who edited the American version of Mr. Wilkomirski's book, put it this way: In the absence of any reason to doubt a writer's honesty, ''if you are his editor, are you going to look at someone who says that's his background and question it?''</p>
        <p>Michael Korda, who edited Ms. Adler's book, was so supportive of his author that he got angry when he was asked about the verification and refused to talk about the book. But her publisher, David Rosenthal, said that when ''you sign up a book, one of the things you take into consideration is reputation and experience of the writer, and I think it's fair to say that in dealing with Renata we were dealing with a well-regarded journalist who made a case for backing up her original claims.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence Ashmead, executive editor of HarperCollins, who edited the new book about the Clintons, said that he was ''convinced that it was true'' that the ethnic slur was made, and that ''I very definitely would do another book with Jerry.'' How's that for author support?</p>
        <p>There are some other things to consider. A book writer is an independent contractor not subject to the same disciplines as a news reporter, for instance, who is an employee and whose integrity is a condition of his employment. Moreover, a newspaper or a television station or a magazine is a brand name, and the reader knows exactly what to expect from the brand. People don't buy books because of the publisher's name. If publishers seem lethargic about whether a book is right or wrong, it maybe because readers will cut books slack they don't give their favorite newspaper.  MAKING BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
