<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenwich's Shifting Line In the Sand; A Town Has Mixed Feelings About a Beach Limited to Its Residents</title>
    <meta content="20BEAC$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leydon, Brenden P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1D91F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenwich's Shifting Line In the Sand; A Town Has Mixed Feelings About a Beach Limited to Its Residents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>GREENWICH, Conn., July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Greenwich, Conn, residents discuss with mixed feelings controversy over residential restrictions of town's beaches and parks; lawyer Brenden P Leydon has successfully filed suit against town seeking to force it to open parks and beaches to all state residents; Greenwich has appealed to Connecticut Supreme Court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An object of persistent envy for those who live outside this well-guarded quarter of privilege and privacy is the town beach, a quarter-mile sliver of dark brown sand.</p>
        <p>It looks much like any other beach in the Northeast, though one in the midst of an attractive and well-maintained park.  The water of Long Island Sound is tranquil, shallow, safe for children. But there is not much else to it. The snack stands serve chili dogs, not caviar. There are bottled Frappuccinos but no chardonnay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An object of persistent envy for those who live outside this well-guarded quarter of privilege and privacy is the town beach, a quarter-mile sliver of dark brown sand.</p>
        <p>It looks much like any other beach in the Northeast, though one in the midst of an attractive and well-maintained park.  The water of Long Island Sound is tranquil, shallow, safe for children. But there is not much else to it. The snack stands serve chili dogs, not caviar. There are bottled Frappuccinos but no chardonnay.</p>
        <p>And yet outsiders are fighting to get in. People have tried to buy beach passes on the black market, only to be thwarted by the police. And a lawyer in neighboring Stamford, Brenden P. Leydon, has sued  -- with considerable success -- to force Greenwich to open its beloved beach to everyone. The town, vowing to fight, has appealed to the Connecticut Supreme Court. For the time being, only residents and their guests can get past the guard at the front gate.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Leydon and his supporters, Greenwich's stubborn effort is a matter of elitism run amok; the town's willingness to spend tens of thousands of its tax dollars on an appeal reflects the arrogance of snobbish people trying to buy their way through life.</p>
        <p>But in recent conversations on the sand, on the blankets and chaise longues, and around the snack stands and parking lots, the people who use the beach revealed themselves to be neither universally snobbish nor universally rich, and certainly not in unanimous agreement that the place should be theirs alone.</p>
        <p>In fact, they said, the really rich in Greenwich could not care less about who uses the town beach. Some of the town's wealthiest neighborhoods, like Lucas Point right next to the town beach, have private beaches. And most of the upper crust in town belong to clubs, where they have tennis, golf and swimming, said William Clark, a writer and 18-year resident who was sitting on a bench reading a biography of Eleanor of Aquitaine.</p>
        <p>''You don't see many of the old Greenwich families down here anymore,'' Mr. Clark said. ''You will not see Mel Gibson and you will not see Rosie O'Donnell. I seriously doubt that you will see Tommy Hilfiger.''</p>
        <p>While the fight-the-snobs element of the dispute has drawn plenty of  attention, dozens of Greenwich residents described a more complex situation that had far more to do with maintaining the quality of life in a fast-growing suburb than with elitism or xenophobia. And while a vast majority said they would like to see the beach remain closed to outsiders, several said they recognized that the dispute also involved questions about public access to public space, and how public space should be defined.</p>
        <p>''If you are quoting us as Greenwich residents,'' Simon Moss said, ''I think it should be completely, only Greenwich. 'We don't want any of these auslanders showing up.' '' Mr. Moss, a British-born software executive, was on the beach with his wife, Cheryl, and their three children. ''But as a human being, I think everybody should just calm down. As long as it maintains some kind of cleanliness, I think everybody should be allowed to come.''</p>
        <p>Town residents said that along with cleanliness, they had concerns about the environment, traffic and parking, and the small-town feeling that Greenwich, even now as a place of 60,000, has preserved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon said these issues were beside the point, and the situation was not complex at all. ''This isn't a country club,'' he said. ''It's a public park by definition. So their attempt to turn Greenwich into a private institution itself has got to fail.''</p>
        <p>Still, many beachgoers seized on the point that the wealthiest do not use the beach in defending the residents-only policy, saying that it protects the interests of average people: working couples with children, longtime residents who own family-run businesses, and even the chefs, nannies and other household employees  of the country club set.</p>
        <p>''It's not for the very rich,'' said Wendi Corcoran, who owns a painting and wallpaper business. ''I was born and raised here and I certainly wasn't raised with money. People are under the delusion that if you live in Greenwich, you have money.''</p>
        <p>Sitting on a beach chair with ''The Wedding'' by Danielle Steel, Ms. Corcoran said out-of-towners had been led to believe that the sand in Greenwich must be better than sand elsewhere. ''I just don't understand what the big appeal is for here,'' she added. ''Some days you can spend a half-hour looking for parking. The water's the same. There's nothing very special about the water.''</p>
        <p>There is good reason to think of Greenwich as rich and exclusive. Average personal income is about $100,000 a year. The beach tends to reflect the town: beachgoers are  overwhelmingly white, with diversity coming mostly from foreigners who live in Greenwich and work for multinationals.</p>
        <p>Greenwich Point Park, of which the beach is a small part, covers 147 acres. The park is a green oasis with nature trails, bike paths, picnic grounds, a launching site for small boats and several fishing holes. Since Greenwich bought the property for $550,000 in 1945, the park has been open only to residents with passes and their guests. Season passes cost $16 for adults and $5 for children.</p>
        <p>There is only about 80 miles of sandy beach on Connecticut's coast, and less than half of that is open to the public. Even some municipalities that allow nonresidents seek to dissuade them by limiting parking and charging higher fees for admission, which can have the same effect as a ban. That course would be open to Greenwich if courts continue to rule against the current arrangement.</p>
        <p>Whatever the draw, nonresidents want in. Last year, the Greenwich police arrested a Stamford man, Victor Consoli, who had advertised in the local paper that he was willing to pay $100 plus expenses for a Greenwich beach pass. Officers arranged to meet him at a McDonald's, and when he handed over $100, the police gave him a summons.</p>
        <p>A similar ad for a Greenwich beach pass appeared in Greenwich Time, the local paper, last month. Investigators are trying to find out who placed the ad, which listed a New York City telephone number.</p>
        <p>And in 1995, Michael Moore organized a multiethnic group of New Yorkers to storm the Greenwich beach by boat for a segment of his Fox television show ''TV Nation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon was a third-year law student at Rutgers University when he sued to overturn Greenwich's beach restrictions in 1995. Several months earlier he had been jogging with a friend when they were barred from Greenwich Point Park. He lost the first round, but triumphed in May when the State Appellate Court ordered Greenwich to open its beach. At the core of his argument is Connecticut's Public Trust Doctrine, which says municipalities hold parks for all state residents.</p>
        <p>It is unclear when the Connecticut Supreme Court will decide whether to hear Greenwich's appeal. If it goes forward, there will be months of paperwork before oral arguments.</p>
        <p>But among beachgoers, the sense that things are destined to change is palpable, and even pervaded the annual sand sculpture contest earlier this month. The piece that won second place was a pair of giant feet, carefully molded to look as if they belonged to a half-buried sunbather, that carried a politically charged title: ''Brenden Leydon's Beach.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon was married late last month and returned last week from his honeymoon in Hawaii where, he acknowledged, the beaches were far more spectacular than the one in Greenwich. ''For me it is primarily about making a point rather than any overwhelming desire to go to this one particular beach,'' he said. ''It certainly is not Hawaii.''</p>
        <p>Here, the water ranges from murky blue to steely gray, and the only excitement comes when lifeguards have to yell at an errant kayaker or when there is an early morning swim race. Because he had competed in one of those races, Rich Delin of South Salem, N.Y., was given the rare chance to enjoy a day on the beach with his wife, Karin, and their three children. ''I can see why they don't want it to be public,'' Mr. Delin said. ''If I lived here I don't think I'd want it to be public either.''</p>
        <p>He said Greenwich appeared to be more welcoming than Westport, also on the sound, where he planned to race the following week. The Westport race form, he said, asked outsiders to leave after the meet.</p>
        <p>Bill Hammock, a money manager for a large New York investment firm, was building a turreted sand castle surrounded by a deep moat with his daughter, Amy, 20, and her boyfriend Aaron Ferguson, also 20.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hammock said the beach was one of the perquisites that made people willing to pay extra to live in Greenwich. ''People, I think, ideally would get what they pay for,'' he said. ''The point of having the town is to have public order.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moss, the software executive, said he saw some humor in Greenwich's beach restrictions. ''I'm English,'' he said. ''By Queen's law the coastline of Britain is public domain, and Britain is supposed to be the most classist society in the world.''</p>
        <p>Smiling, he said Greenwich should be no less egalitarian. ''I think it  should be public for everyone with over $100,000 in disposable income. Forget these passes, show your 401(k). Your W-2.''</p>
        <p>He paused, slightly alarmed. ''I assume you are going to say that I said this in jest,'' he said. ''It's a beach, for God's sake.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
