<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High-Tech Executives Urge Action on World's Digital Divide</title>
    <meta content="Y20DIG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000724T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Economic Forum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mori, Yoshiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High-Tech Executives Urge Action on World's Digital Divide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Economic Forum task force of high-technology executives urges wealthiest nations to act to erase growing digital divide separating developed and developing worlds, news conference; gives Japanese Prime Min Yoshiro Mori series of proposals; Japanese executives say Mori will announce at summit meeting of leaders of seven industrial nations that Japan will commit $12 billion in loans and $3 billion in grants over five years to information-technology initiatives in developing world (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of high-technology executives urged the wealthiest nations today to take action to erase a growing digital divide resulting from the economic chasm separating the developed and developing worlds.</p>
        <p>The perception that the world is increasingly being divided into information technology haves and have-nots is among the topics that the seven leading industrial nations and Russia will take up at their annual summit meeting, which begins on Friday in Okinawa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of high-technology executives urged the wealthiest nations today to take action to erase a growing digital divide resulting from the economic chasm separating the developed and developing worlds.</p>
        <p>The perception that the world is increasingly being divided into information technology haves and have-nots is among the topics that the seven leading industrial nations and Russia will take up at their annual summit meeting, which begins on Friday in Okinawa.</p>
        <p>Today a task force established by the World Economic Forum, a policy organization made up of many of the world's largest corporations that meets annually in Davos, Switzerland, presented a series of proposals on the issue to Japan's prime minister, Yoshiro Mori.</p>
        <p>At a news conference here, members of the task force appeared sensitive to the issue of self-interest on the part of the large corporations backing high-technology spending.</p>
        <p>''This is all about self-interest,'' said Vernon J. Ellis, international chairman of Andersen Consulting, a member of the task force. ''There is nothing wrong with self-interest, as long as it is enlightened, long-term self-interest.''</p>
        <p>The task force, including the chief executives of Sony Corporation and Toshiba Corporation, Japan's two largest consumer electronics companies, proposed a set of principles including telecommunications and Internet deregulation, universal access to education and technology training, as well as support and financing for small entrepreneurs.</p>
        <p>The proposal, prepared at Japan's request this year at the Davos meeting, also includes the creation of a Peace Corps-style volunteer group, the Global Digital Opportunity Corps, and the establishment of local technology community centers.</p>
        <p>Japanese high-technology executives said tonight that Mr. Mori planned to announce at the summit meeting that Japan would commit $12 billion in loans and $3 billion in grants over five years to information-technology initiatives in the developing world. The move is intended to prompt similar commitments from other countries, a Japanese executive said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mori, who acknowledged this week that he is a computer novice who has only recently learned how to use a mouse, appeared today with an international group of high-technology executives to underscore his nation's commitment to the proposal.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to make this an information technology discussion, mainly focusing on the developing nations,'' Mr. Mori said. ''This digital divide issue is a crucial matter.''</p>
        <p>The issue of the a global digital divide has been seized on in the last year by corporate executives, eager to prove they are socially responsible. But there is disagreement over what the divide represents.</p>
        <p>A number of economists and technologists believe that the world income gap created by the industrial revolution may still be the fundamental dividing line between rich and poor nations rather than the question of access to technology.</p>
        <p>One member of the task force said the digital divide should not overshadow traditional issues defining rich and poor nations.</p>
        <p>''It's really not a digital divide, said the participant, Richard T. K. Li, chairman and chief executive of the Pacific Century Group, an Internet company based in Hong Kong. ''It is an education divide, and information technology is only a conduit to promote education.''</p>
        <p>Other companies represented on the task force include Sun Microsystems, Microsoft, Yahoo, 3Com, Motorola, Hewlett-Packard, Novell and Alcatel.</p>
        <p>Sony's chairman, Nobuyuki Idea, acknowledged that his company had struggled with its own internal digital divide and had been slow to deploy information technology among its workers. ''This is a good indication of the problems that will confront us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Klaus Schwab, the founder and chairman of the World Economic Forum, said in an interview this week that he believed that inexpensive digital wireless technology systems would increasingly spread in the third world. ''I personally feel that a breakthrough is coming,'' he said.</p>
        <p>United States officials said on Monday that information technology held promise for creating economic opportunity as well as improving access to health care and education. But they noted that while there are now an estimated 332 million people connected via the Internet around the world, only 1 percent live in Africa. And less than 5 percent of the computers connected to the Internet are in developing countries.</p>
        <p>The officials would not offer any United States commitment or pledge of a specific dollar amount to help bridge the digital divide. But they said they would welcome such proposals from other nations and from the American private sector.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 24, 2000, Monday  An article on Thursday about a call by technology executives for action on the world's digital divide referred incorrectly to two companies represented in the group -- Sony and Toshiba. Ranked by worldwide sales last year, they are the third- and fourth-largest electronics companies in Japan, trailing Hitachi and Matsushita.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 24, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about a call by technology executives for action on the world's digital divide referred incorrectly to two companies represented in the group -- Sony and Toshiba. Ranked by worldwide sales last year, they are the third- and fourth-largest electronics companies in Japan, trailing Hitachi and Matsushita.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
