<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grist for TV: Family Grief Since Killings At Columbine</title>
    <meta content="20NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Littleton (Colo)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klebold, Dylan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Rachel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dateline (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Long Journey Back, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDF1E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grist for TV: Family Grief Since Killings At Columbine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critic's Notebook review of The Long Journey Back, report in NBC's Dateline news documentary program examining efforts of family of Rachel Scott to cope with grief over her death in April 1999 shootings at Littleton, Colo, high school (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the shooting began at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., on April 20 last year, Craig Scott escaped from the library and later said God had told him to lead other students to safety through a back door. After he was safe, he learned that his sister Rachel, at 17 a year older than he was, had been shot in the head; she had been the first to die.</p>
        <p>Just two weeks later, with unsettling speed and thoroughness, ''Dateline'' began filming the Scott family. On and off for 15 months cameras trailed Craig as he struggled with survivor's guilt and flashbacks. They followed his three siblings and his worried parents (who had divorced years before). The family was even given its own camera to record a video diary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the shooting began at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., on April 20 last year, Craig Scott escaped from the library and later said God had told him to lead other students to safety through a back door. After he was safe, he learned that his sister Rachel, at 17 a year older than he was, had been shot in the head; she had been the first to die.</p>
        <p>Just two weeks later, with unsettling speed and thoroughness, ''Dateline'' began filming the Scott family. On and off for 15 months cameras trailed Craig as he struggled with survivor's guilt and flashbacks. They followed his three siblings and his worried parents (who had divorced years before). The family was even given its own camera to record a video diary.</p>
        <p>The hourlong chronicle shaped from this, called ''The Long Journey Back'' (tomorrow night at 9 on NBC), is an intense and deeply sad experience; it is also creepy in its public exhibition of private grief. With its queasy mix of genuine sorrow and careless exploitation, this ''Dateline'' special is a microcosm of what the Columbine television coverage has been from the start.</p>
        <p>The drama of live coverage, which began while students were still trapped inside the school, overshadowed an equally important aspect of the reporting: the speed with which survivors turned up on camera. Almost as soon as they were out of the building, students appeared on television, and in many instances it was impossible to separate the healing, cathartic need to tell the story from an unmistakable element of ''Look, I'm on TV.''</p>
        <p>In the days and weeks that followed a similar tone was evident among some of the victims' parents, whose need to validate their children's lives and their own grief in public was sometimes tinged with self-promotion. It does not deny their tragedy to notice that a few were especially drawn to the network hand-holding of Katie Couric and to town-hall testimonies with Ted Koppel. Though memorial services were broadcast, network anchors were the true ministers in that public mourning ritual.</p>
        <p>The Scotts do not exhibit any of the self-aggrandizement that made watching some of that coverage so distressing. Facing the ''Dateline'' cameras, they appear sincere and direct as they describe their feelings, even as those feelings change over the months from shock to rage to acceptance. And the cameras can't be accused of going where they weren't invited. Sara James, who reports the story, explains why the family allowed this extraordinary intrusion into their lives. Unfortunately it is a stock reason. ''They were determined to transform their grief into a force for good,'' she says, yet precisely what good they hope will come from this is never clear.</p>
        <p>''Dateline'' has obviously made a strategic choice. This is an insiders' view, without social questions or context. That approach allows viewers to share the Scotts' anguish to an exceptional degree, yet it fails to address important questions about the impact of such media attention.</p>
        <p>Rachel's mother, Beth Nimmo, is so concerned about her other children's reactions to the murder that she delays her own grieving, which helps explain her calm demeanor. She quits her job to stay home, which puts the family in debt. On camera she and Rachel's father, Darrell Scott, read from their daughter's bullet-scarred journal, found at the school. ''I'm dying,'' she wrote weeks before she was murdered. ''I consider it homicide. The world you have created for me has led to my death.'' They see these words as divine prophecy, proof that God has a plan for Rachel, though these journal entries seem to be signs of normal adolescent soul-searching.</p>
        <p>Craig is the focus of the hour, though. Before the shootings he was a relentless list maker, so orderly that, as Ms. James says, ''he uses a cardboard template to refold his clothes.'' (No one bothers to ask whether revealing this detail might embarrass an adolescent.) It is especially difficult for someone with such a need for order to deal with the randomness of his sister's murder.</p>
        <p>In the first months after the shootings Craig maintains his composure, speaks of forgiveness and even joins his father, who has gone on the road giving speeches about his daughter's life and death. It is typical of the report's omissions that the ''Dateline'' cameras capture this without commenting on how a personal tragedy became a public speaking tour.</p>
        <p>Though Craig says that talking to large crowds is ''awesome,'' he is soon emotionally and physically exhausted and leaves the tour. After a few months his shock gives way to anger. He begins to question his faith in God. He endures nights of insomnia.</p>
        <p>In the most disturbing sequences he carries the family's video camera along as he walks the streets at dawn, sounding manic and unlike himself. He climbs to the roof in the middle of the night, taking a knife for protection. In the haunting green-tinged light of his video camera's night vision, he is wearing a knit cap and films his face in extreme close-up. As Ms. James points out, ''It looks eerily like 'The Blair Witch Project.' ''</p>
        <p>And in the fall, after one day back at Columbine High, he is unable to return, and his protective mother agrees to have him tutored at home. ''She wants him sheltered here in the privacy of their home,'' Ms. James says as she stands on the front lawn, willfully ignoring the fact that she and the ''Dateline'' cameras are encroaching on that privacy.</p>
        <p>For months after the killing, Rachel's older sister Bethanee found solace by visiting Rachel's bedroom; she posted a note on the door saying only family members could enter. She did not have to spell out, '' 'Dateline,' this means you.'' A year later Bethanee takes the cameras into Rachel's room, a gesture that this report views in the simplest terms, as a sign of healing. It is a sign of healing, but the presence of cameras also means it is not as simple as that. The scene characterizes this emotionally wrenching and troubling report, in which grief played out for the cameras is accepted as the most ordinary rite on earth. In our media-frenzied culture, maybe it is.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
