<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apple Redesigns Computers In Effort to Increase Sales</title>
    <meta content="Y20APP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Computer Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jobs, Steven P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EED61E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple Redesigns Computers In Effort to Increase Sales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Apple Computer introduces new products from restyled mouse to overhaul of its popular iMac desktop computers, whose sales of stagnated in recent months, Macworld exhibition, New York City; chief executive Steven P Jobs comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Apple Computer introduced a flurry of new products yesterday from a restyled mouse to an overhaul of its popular iMac desktop computers, whose sales have stagnated in recent months.</p>
        <p>Apple has enjoyed a remarkable corporate revival the last three years under the leadership of Steven P. Jobs, who returned to take the helm of the company he co-founded in 1975. But lately, industry analysts have pointed to signs that Apple's momentum may be slowing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Apple Computer introduced a flurry of new products yesterday from a restyled mouse to an overhaul of its popular iMac desktop computers, whose sales have stagnated in recent months.</p>
        <p>Apple has enjoyed a remarkable corporate revival the last three years under the leadership of Steven P. Jobs, who returned to take the helm of the company he co-founded in 1975. But lately, industry analysts have pointed to signs that Apple's momentum may be slowing.</p>
        <p>The computer maker, based in Cupertino, Calif., reported strong quarterly profits on Tuesday on a 17 percent increase in revenues, though the increase in sales was less than Wall Street had expected. And sales of iMac consumer desktops slipped to 450,000 machines in the June quarter, down from 487,000 in the year-earlier quarter.</p>
        <p>''The question some people have had about Apple is, 'Can we keep it up?' '' Mr. Jobs, the chief executive, observed in an interview. ''Well, we've answered that question here today. Innovation keeps coming from Apple.''</p>
        <p>The announcements at Macworld, the company's twice-a-year exhibition that began yesterday in New York, continue the game plan Apple has followed since Mr. Jobs took over in 1997: to combine arresting industrial design, homegrown hardware and software technology, competitive pricing and performance.</p>
        <p>Apple's software engineers focus not only on the Macintosh operating system, but also video imaging software. Apple introduced a new version of its iMovie software, which enables people to import and edit home digital video clips on an iMac or a Power Mac. During his presentation, Mr. Jobs pointed to iMovie as an indication of the company's direction and of ''Apple's DNA.''</p>
        <p>The company, he said, is ''not just about making spreadsheets run faster. We want Apple to stand at the intersection of art and technology.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most visually striking innovation announced yesterday was a new line of Power Macintosh called the G4 Cube. The new model packs the power of Macintosh machines used by graphics artists and Web designers into a white plastic cube, eight inches on a side, or about one-fourth the space of most similarly powered computers.</p>
        <p>Apple hopes that the G4 Cube will both expand its sales among media and arts professionals, as well as encourage home users who have Apple's more expensive line of iMac to trade up to the G4 Cube.</p>
        <p>The iMac line was refurbished yesterday with more aggressive pricing, faster processors, more storage capacity and new hues including a white machine -- a color Apple calls ''snow.''</p>
        <p>The least expensive iMac will be priced at $799, or $200 less than the previous entry-level machine. Apple also introduced a line of Power Mac desktop machines with two microprocessors. The dual-processor machines are Apple's response to concerns that the company could not keep pace with industry-standard PC's using Intel microprocessors. Apple demonstrated its machines far exceeding the performance of the fastest Intel machines, whose processors have higher raw calculating speeds measured in megahertz, as both machines did the same multimedia editing.</p>
        <p>In all, Apple introduced new versions of all its desktop machines, which represent 75 percent of its sales. And all of them will come with a redesigned keyboard and a new elongated computer mouse, which uses optical technology for positioning and requires no mouse pad.</p>
        <p>The new mouse's entire housing depresses to click, dispensing with the traditional mouse button. It replaces the round Apple mouse, which was derided by product reviewers as ''an ergonomic nightmare'' and a ''hockey puck.''</p>
        <p>''We have our failings at Apple, but we do listen to customers,'' Mr. Jobs said.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
