<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adkins's Tough Choice: Speed or Stable Moods</title>
    <meta content="20TRAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adkins, Derrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0D81E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adkins's Tough Choice: Speed or Stable Moods</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Derrick Adkins, who won Olympic gold medal in 1996 in 400-meter hurdles, preparing for Olympic trials and berth on US Olympic team for Sydney Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It could not have been a more perfect moment for Derrick Adkins to win an Olympic gold medal in 1996 in the 400-meter hurdles. He won in Atlanta, where he lived and had attended Georgia Tech. His parents and friends were in the stands and as he carried an American flag on a jubilant victory lap around the Olympic Stadium, cameras flashed like thousands of blinding fireflies.</p>
        <p>Four years later, as he attempts to make another Olympic team, Adkins is not the same caliber of hurdler. What no one but his parents and coach knew that celebratory night in 1996 was that Adkins was suffering from severe depression. He had been diagnosed three months earlier, unable to sleep, feeling an overwhelming sense of hopelessness and thinking suicidal thoughts, and had been placed on the antidepressant medication Luvox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It could not have been a more perfect moment for Derrick Adkins to win an Olympic gold medal in 1996 in the 400-meter hurdles. He won in Atlanta, where he lived and had attended Georgia Tech. His parents and friends were in the stands and as he carried an American flag on a jubilant victory lap around the Olympic Stadium, cameras flashed like thousands of blinding fireflies.</p>
        <p>Four years later, as he attempts to make another Olympic team, Adkins is not the same caliber of hurdler. What no one but his parents and coach knew that celebratory night in 1996 was that Adkins was suffering from severe depression. He had been diagnosed three months earlier, unable to sleep, feeling an overwhelming sense of hopelessness and thinking suicidal thoughts, and had been placed on the antidepressant medication Luvox.</p>
        <p>Shortly before the Atlanta Games, without telling anyone, he stopped taking the medication because it left him feeling sedated and fatigued. And when the euphoria of winning a gold medal faded several weeks later, he experienced a depressive episode that led him to drink an entire bottle of wine one evening in Monte Carlo, leaving him hung over and dehydrated and in no condition to run well on the European circuit.</p>
        <p>Two days later, in Berlin, he finished third in a hurdles race and lost a chance at what would have been his biggest payday of the season. Carole Adkins remembers watching the race on television, seeing her son fade over the final hurdles then drop to his knees on the track, his head cradled in his arms.</p>
        <p>''My heart was pounding,'' she recalled. ''I knew it was depression-related. I called the hotel and Derrick said he was all right, just disappointed.''</p>
        <p>But, of course, he was not all right.</p>
        <p>''Because of all the excitement of the Olympics, and living in Atlanta, the depression was pretty much drowned out by what was going on,'' Derrick Adkins said. ''Three weeks after the Olympics, my mood sunk dramatically. I started to feel worse than before. I drank a whole bottle of wine one night. I needed something to anesthetize the pain. I also had some problems with drinking prior to the Olympics. It numbs the emotions for a little while.''</p>
        <p>By January 1997, Adkins resumed taking his daily medication. Over the last three years, he said, he has felt continued emotional stability, but there has been a tradeoff. His track career has slumped dramatically. An Olympic champion in 1996, he could finish no better than eighth at the 1998 national track and field championships and seventh in 1999. In the summer of 1998, at the Goodwill Games in Uniondale, N.Y., only a few miles from his hometown of Lakeview, he ran before several hundred friends and family members and finished dead last. He nearly quit the sport then, and again during a frustrating season last summer.</p>
        <p>He has lost hundreds of thousands of dollars in potential earnings on the track circuit and has been dropped by the shoe company whose apparel he endorsed. Yet he has persevered, and at age 30, he still has hopes of qualifying for the 2000 Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Thursday night, Adkins will run the first round of the 400-meter hurdles here at the Olympic track and field trials. His best time of the season, 49.86 seconds, is more than two seconds slower than his personal best of 47.54 run in 1996. On the face of it, he would seem to have no chance of finishing among the top three at the trials and qualifying for the Summer Games in September. However, with permission from his psychiatrist, Adkins again stopped taking Luvox two weeks ago. His training has improved significantly, and he and his coach, Grover Hinsdale, are more encouraged about his chances.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to make expectations,'' Hinsdale said. ''For a long time he's been erratic. But based on his last two or three weeks of training, there is a chance he may run well. You never say never.''</p>
        <p>Adkins has begun to tell his story in hopes of educating and encouraging others who suffer from depression. Next month, he will self-publish his autobiography, ''Let's All Get High,'' an inspirational book aimed at young adults. The holder of a degree in mechanical engineering from Georgia Tech, Adkins is now studying for a master's degree in divinity at the Atlanta campus of the Christian Life School of Theology. He credits his spirituality and reading of the Bible with helping him pull through his ordeal.</p>
        <p>''I honestly think I am going to make the team,'' Adkins said. ''If I didn't think I could, I wouldn't go out there.''</p>
        <p>Carole Adkins said she was ''totally against'' the temporary stoppage of medication, worried that her son may again begin to feel wild mood swings. While she supports her son's attempt, she said, ''I think a person's health is far greater than any Olympics.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cassandra Wanzo of Atlanta, the psychiatrist who is treating Derrick Adkins, said she endorsed his decision, knowing the side effects that antidepressant medications can cause. Adkins said Luvox causes tendon and muscle weakness, affects his oxygen-carrying capacity and inhibits the adrenaline rush that athletes use to prepare for races.</p>
        <p>Since 1996, he has experimented with different medications and dosages, seeking to achieve both emotional stability and athletic success. He has also begun to use natural supplements, he said. If he makes the Olympic team, he plans to resume taking Luvox, then stop again two to three weeks before the Summer Games to let the medication flush from his system.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a roll of the dice,'' Hinsdale said of Adkins's decision to stop taking Luvox for the trials. The first round of the 400 hurdles is Thursday, the semifinals are Friday, and the final is Saturday.</p>
        <p>''If he gets no sleep, he has no chance,'' Hinsdale said. ''At this point, he's sleeping very well. If he sleeps well, it was a very good decision.''</p>
        <p>The coach said he had become concerned about Adkins in the spring of 1996, when with the Olympic trials approaching, his energy level would suddenly dissipate in practice, ''like the battery of a cell phone going off.'' By that time, Adkins said, he had been suffering severe bouts of depression for three years. From childhood through college, he said, he sometimes felt low moments, but they were submerged beneath an almost obsessive desire to obtain good grades and to become an elite athlete. He was a dean's list student at Georgia Tech, but in 1993, by then graduated from college and competing as a professional athlete, he said he began to get severely depressed for no apparent reason.</p>
        <p>''The more I tried to fight it with mind power and meditation, the more it got worse,'' he said. ''Every waking moment was a moment of emotional pain. I didn't know where it was coming from. All I looked forward to was sleep.''</p>
        <p>Finally, on April 16, 1996, two months before the Olympic trials in Atlanta, Adkins decided to get professional help and visited Dr. Wanzo. ''He was really depressed,'' she said. ''He was at the point where there was no reason to live. He was feeling hopeless. He did express to me that he was thinking of buying a gun.''</p>
        <p>She said her diagnosis was that he was suffering from a major depressive disorder, a chemical imbalance, and immediately placed him on antidepressant medication. Adkins then told Hinsdale, his coach, saying that he had become mentally exhausted, virtually unable to sleep for up to three days at a time. He flew home to tell his parents, and as she picked up her son at La Guardia Airport, Carol Adkins noticed that he had lost considerable weight, that his skin was pale, his eyes hollow and sunken.</p>
        <p>Within several weeks of taking medication, his mood elevated and Adkins recovered sufficiently to win an Olympic gold medal. Four years later he no longer suffers severe bouts of melancholy but also no longer hurdles with the world's best.</p>
        <p>''I've accomplished the highest level of achievement in this sport,'' Adkins said. ''If I don't make the Olympic team, I already have what all the other athletes are searching for. If I accomplish nothing else, I've already had a great career. At the same time, I hope and plan to make the team. Since leaving Luvox, there has been a definite change in my ability and endurance. I knew the drug was holding me back, but I didn't want to go off of it. When you go off for general purposes, it gives me a lot of mood swings. I like my moods to be stable. But since this is the Olympic trials, I've decided to go off of it. A lot of people will be surprised by how fast I am running. If I don't make the team, I'll come close.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
