<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Girl, 10, Dies After Being Hit With Toy at State-Run Camp</title>
    <meta content="20CAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Milford (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benbow, Shadriah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DB1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Girl, 10, Dies After Being Hit With Toy at State-Run Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON, N.J., July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shadriah Benbow, 10, dies after another girl accidently strikes her in head with toy plastic golf club at state-run day camp in West Milford, NJ; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Monday, Shadriah Benbow bounded into her Aunt Denise's apartment, giddy and proud about her new fourth-grade graduation picture and eager to share it. ''We joked and laughed about her getting ready for fifth grade,'' Denise Henderson recalled today. It was the last time she saw her niece alive.</p>
        <p>Shadriah, 10, died at St. Joseph's Hospital here about 6 a.m. today, 19 hours after another girl accidentally struck her in the head with a toy plastic golf club at a state-run day camp in the hills of Passaic County, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Monday, Shadriah Benbow bounded into her Aunt Denise's apartment, giddy and proud about her new fourth-grade graduation picture and eager to share it. ''We joked and laughed about her getting ready for fifth grade,'' Denise Henderson recalled today. It was the last time she saw her niece alive.</p>
        <p>Shadriah, 10, died at St. Joseph's Hospital here about 6 a.m. today, 19 hours after another girl accidentally struck her in the head with a toy plastic golf club at a state-run day camp in the hills of Passaic County, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Detectives in West Milford, where the camp is situated, were questioning children who witnessed the incident, but for now, they believe it was a tragic accident, said Lt. Andrew J. Russo, a spokesman for the West Milford police.</p>
        <p>Shadriah's parents, family members and friends were devastated by the death of a happy, energetic child at the rural camp, about 25 miles from the family's three-story walk-up in this tough neighborhood near downtown Paterson.</p>
        <p>The girl's father, Terry Benbow, said he knew little more about his daughter's death than a doctor's explanation that she had died of a brain hemorrhage caused by blood vessels bursting near her temple. No one, he said bitterly this afternoon, had given him an explanation of how the blow from a toy club had killed her.</p>
        <p>''Was she standing right behind the other girl?'' Mr. Benbow asked. ''Was someone supervising her? Did someone tell her to move back?  They're not telling us nothing. I want to know what went on at the campsite so we can put her to rest nicely.''</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Russo said Shadriah and several other 9- and 10-year-old girls had been standing in line, taking turns hitting a large plastic golf ball off a plastic tee. He said the club was hollow and 21 inches long, with a hollow base that measured 7 inches by 5 inches.</p>
        <p>He said Shadriah was standing directly behind a girl who was addressing the ball, and was struck in the head as the girl drew the club back.</p>
        <p>Shadriah collapsed, unconscious, and a camp counselor called the police on a cell phone at 11:11 a.m., Lieutenant Russo said. The town's emergency medical squad was dispatched, and one of its paramedics, Jill Brickman, said Shadriah was not breathing and had no pulse when she arrived.</p>
        <p>A medical team was called in from Chilton Memorial Hospital in nearby Pompton Plains and the girl was airlifted to St. Joseph's in a state police helicopter. She never regained consciousness, said a hospital spokesman, Robert Lanzetti.</p>
        <p>He said the cause of death, according to preliminary findings, was head trauma. An autopsy has been scheduled by the Passaic County medical examiner, he said.</p>
        <p>The day camp is run as a community service for underprivileged children in Paterson by the Passaic County Probation Department, a branch of the state's court system. Probation officials referred questions to the system's headquarters in Trenton.</p>
        <p>Winnie Comfort, a spokeswoman for the state's Administrative Office of the Courts, which oversees county probation departments, said the girls were being supervised by two women who had volunteered as camp counselors on Tuesday. She said the women, whom she declined to identify, were employees of the Family Court in Paterson.</p>
        <p>''They were watching the girls,'' Ms. Comfort said. ''They were interacting with them.''</p>
        <p>She said 39 children attended the camp Tuesday and were supervised by a staff of 10, including a certified lifeguard, four probation officers, the two Family Court employees and three teenage volunteers.</p>
        <p>Activities at the camp include basketball, arts and crafts and swimming in a pond, Ms. Comfort said. The camp is free, and children are provided with lunch and a snack.</p>
        <p>Ms. Comfort said the camp is not required to have medical personnel on duty.</p>
        <p>Shadriah's father said she had looked forward to playing softball and dancing at the camp. ''She loved dancing,'' Mr. Benbow said. ''That was her heart, that was her dream,.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Henderson, her aunt, said: ''She was a sweet little girl. She was smart in everything and energetic.  It's a shame she had to leave this earth this way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
