<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="20MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6D81F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BUILDING COMPLAINT LINE  The New York City Department of Buildings has opened a special telephone line for complaints about crumbling facades and other potentially dangerous building conditions. The system, which centralizes information for buildings in all boroughs into one center, allows callers to register complaints and gain access to a site's history of violations. Complaints will be forwarded to inspectors who, according to a department spokesman, Paul Wein, are ''ready to be dispatched immediately.'' The number is (212) 227-7000.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BUILDING COMPLAINT LINE  The New York City Department of Buildings has opened a special telephone line for complaints about crumbling facades and other potentially dangerous building conditions. The system, which centralizes information for buildings in all boroughs into one center, allows callers to register complaints and gain access to a site's history of violations. Complaints will be forwarded to inspectors who, according to a department spokesman, Paul Wein, are ''ready to be dispatched immediately.'' The number is (212) 227-7000.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: GIRL, 15, RAPED  Three men forced their way into an apartment in Flatbush, Brooklyn, yesterday afternoon and sexually assaulted two girls and a woman, the police said. A a 15-year-old girl was raped, a 45-year-old woman was sexually assaulted, and a 13-year-old girl suffered attempted rape, the police said. The men, thought to be in their 20's, knocked on the apartment door at about 2:30. When the 13-year-old opened the door, they forced their way in, brandishing a handgun, the police said. Two of the men were masked. After forcing the three occupants into separate bedrooms and attacking them, the men took jewelry and money and then fled, the police said. The victims were taken to King's County Hospital Center, where they were reported in stable condition.</p>
        <p>Shaila Dewan (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: WENDY'S SURVIVOR LEAVES HOSPITAL  Two months after he was shot in the head during a robbery and massacre at a Wendy's restaurant in Flushing that killed five of his co-workers, Jaquione Johnson was released from Jamaica Hospital yesterday. He was taken to an undisclosed rehabilitation center to begin what his family said was his final but lengthy step toward recovery. Under heavy police guard, Mr. Johnson, 18, one of two survivors and a key witness in the murder case, spent seven weeks in the hospital's traumatic brain injury unit.</p>
        <p>Sarah Kershaw (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TEACHER ARRESTED  A Manhattan high school teacher was charged with grand larceny yesterday after the police said he  snatched a woman's purse as he pedaled by on his bicycle. The authorities said the teacher, Ryan Ward, 30, grabbed the bag from Svetlana Novlkava, 21, at 1:35 a.m. on Park Avenue near East 26th Street and was caught a few blocks away with Ms. Novlkava's cellular phone and credit card. Mr. Ward has taught fine arts at the Manhattan Center for Math and Science High School since 1996.</p>
        <p>C. J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: BIAS IN INSURANCE  The State Insurance Department is investigating whether life insurers have written policies that hurt minority groups in New York State. In response to complaints, the insurance superintendent, Neil D. Levin, has ordered all life insurers to document the kinds of policies they carry on New Yorkers, how premiums were calculated, how and where policies were sold and whether there are differences in costs or benefits for minority policyholders compared with white ones.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: SEARCH FOR EDITOR  Senators and representatives from New Jersey sent a petition on Tuesday to the Jamaican government urging it to allow American search dogs into the country to help find Claudia Kirschhoch, a missing travel editor from Queens. The petition, signed by the state's entire delegation, asks Jamaica to lift a three-  to six-month quarantine on incoming animals to allow in specially trained dogs from Oregon. The petition was drafted by Representative Rodney P. Frelinghuysen, a Republican from the 11th District in New Jersey, where Ms. Kirschhoch's parents live.</p>
        <p>Edward Wong (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: POWER DISRUPTED  Ten buildings on East 91st Street between Park and Lexington Avenues lost power yesterday at 4:18 p.m. after a fire in a manhole. By 10:20 p.m., power had been restored, said a spokeswoman for Con Edison. About 50 customers were affected, she said.  Workers had not determined late last night the cause of the fire, she said, but she added that it had nothing to do with the level of electric use. A spokesman for the mayor, who has criticized Con Edison for recent power failures, said the matter would be investigated.  Shaila Dewan (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HAMDEN: NEW POLICE TRAINING  Police Chief Robert F. Nolan said he planned to work with black residents in neighboring New Haven to increase his force's ''cultural diversity training.'' Blacks in New Haven have said Hamden Police officers unfairly single them out for traffic violations. Chief Nolan, who has said his officers are not racially insensitive, met on Tuesday night with New Haven city and police officials to discuss racial issues. ''That is a step toward change,'' said the Rev. W. David Lee of the Varick Memorial A.M.E. Zion Church, which was the host for the meeting.</p>
        <p>Paul Zielbauer (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: CHILD CARE SCRUTINIZED  A child care center run by one of the state's oldest charities will be able to keep its license. Under a consent order from the State Department of Public Health, Hartford Neighborhood Centers Inc. has agreed to allow state workers and consultants to train its workers in supervising young children and in reporting suspected abuse or neglect. Last month, state investigators found the agency ''culpable of potentially placing the children at risk'' by not taking action against a teacher who was suspected of mistreating preschoolers.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>LINDEN: NEW POWER PLANT  P.S.E.G. Power, an affiliate of Public Service Electric and Gas, announced yesterday that it planned to build a  natural-gas power plant in Linden to replace three oil-burning plants at the site. The new plant's capacity of 1,186 megawatts would nearly triple the combined output of the old plants, but because natural gas burns more cleanly than oil, the volume of pollutants would remain the same, officials said. The $590 million plant is scheduled to be finished in May 2003.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>CAMDEN: TEENAGER TO BE TRIED AS ADULT  A 14-year-old boy charged with robbery and sexual assault will be prosecuted as an adult, Lee Solomon, the Camden County prosecutor, said Tuesday. The teenager, whose name was not released because of his age, is accused, along with Ernest Buffaloe, 23, of breaking into a Gloucester Township motel and binding and raping a Blackwood woman, then holding her and her two young sons hostage. Both defendants are also being charged with kidnapping, conspiracy and cruelty to a child. A pretrial hearing is scheduled for Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Natania Blumenkehl (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
