<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Avenue, Off the Avenue: Saks Is Getting an Annulment</title>
    <meta content="Y20SAK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Catalogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proffitt's Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Fifth Avenue</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Direct</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Off Fifth</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">McRae's Department Stores</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parisan Department Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Christina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Brad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDC1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Avenue, Off the Avenue: Saks Is Getting an Annulment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Saks Inc, previously called Proffitt's, announces that less than two years after it acquired Saks Fifth Avenue and renamed itself, its board approves plan to split again into two separate public companies; spun-off entity will be called Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises Inc and will include luxury-oriented stores of Saks Fifth Avenue; the Saks Direct, which includes catalog and Internet operations; and Saks Off Fifth, its upscale outlet business; Saks Inc will retain rest of department store business--including such regional stores as Proffitt's, McRae's and Parisan--and will eventually be renamed; shareholders are expected to receive one share of Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises common stock for every three shares of Saks Inc stock that they own; Philip Miller will continue as chairman of Saks Fifth Avenue; Christina Johnson will remain president and chief executive of Saks Fifth Avenue stores division; department store group will search for new chief executive; Saks Inc chairman R Brad Martin comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The answer to the question of whether a country peasant can marry a Park Avenue swell and live happily ever after appears to be no.</p>
        <p>Saks Inc., previously called Proffitt's, with headquarters in Birmingham, Ala., announced late yesterday that less than two years after it acquired Saks Fifth Avenue and renamed itself, its board had approved a plan to split again into two separate public companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The answer to the question of whether a country peasant can marry a Park Avenue swell and live happily ever after appears to be no.</p>
        <p>Saks Inc., previously called Proffitt's, with headquarters in Birmingham, Ala., announced late yesterday that less than two years after it acquired Saks Fifth Avenue and renamed itself, its board had approved a plan to split again into two separate public companies.</p>
        <p>The spun-off entity will be called Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises Inc. and will include the luxury-oriented stores of Saks Fifth Avenue; the Saks Direct, which includes catalog and Internet operations; and Saks Off Fifth, its upscale outlet business. Saks Inc. will retain the rest of the department store business -- including such regional stores as Proffitt's, McRae's and Parisan -- and will eventually be renamed. Shareholders are expected to receive one share of Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises common stock for every three shares of Saks Inc. stock that they own.</p>
        <p>Since the Proffitt's-Saks merger in September 1998, skepticism had abounded about the logic of combining mid-market department stores, which rely on staple brands like Liz Claiborne and Levi's, and the tony retailer, best known for offerings like Prada and Gucci.</p>
        <p>Many stock analysts and consultants argued that the businesses were too dissimilar to produce real compatibility benefits, and they accused the company chairman, R. Brad Martin, of being blinded by his desire to own a glitzier property -- with opportunities to hobnob with socialites and celebrity designers.</p>
        <p>''It was a mistake to buy Saks Fifth Avenue,'' said Robert F. Buchanan, a retail analyst at A. G. Edwards, ''and it makes sense to undo the mistake.''</p>
        <p>Designers who counted on Saks stores to showcase their newest creations also worried that the corporation was running the upscale emporium like a mundane department store -- starving it of necessary resources for inventory, remodeling and staff training to hit its financial targets.</p>
        <p>''This merger went off because there was a lack of understanding on what it takes to run a first-class luxury operation,'' said Arnold Aronson, a former Saks Fifth Avenue chief executive. ''It is better that the realization came late rather than never.''</p>
        <p>The spinoff is clearly a bid to improve the Saks Inc. sagging stock price. Before acquiring Saks Holdings and changing its name, Proffitt's was an industry leader in buying businesses at a rapid pace and making them profitable. But soon after the purchase, it became apparent that the former Proffitt's had hit a block in integrating the disparate parts of its empire.</p>
        <p>Last summer, the company said it would miss earnings estimates for the fiscal year 1999 by a mile, in part because of disappointing growth in its credit business and because of lower-than-anticipated revenue growth at Mercantile Stores, a chain of bargain-priced apparel stores that it bought from Dillard's Inc. in 1998. Then, this spring, sales were lower than anticipated in the department stores, and the company yesterday forecast an operating loss for its fiscal second quarter, ending July 29.</p>
        <p>Saks Inc. had already missed earnings estimates for three quarters in a row, and its stock price has crumbled by more than 50 percent since the merger was announced. The stock gained 68.75 cents, to $12.50, yesterday ahead of the spinoff announcement, which came after the financial markets had closed.</p>
        <p>The company stopped just short of saying that the purchase had been a mistake but acknowledged that winning Wall Street's favor was a motivating factor in the plan announced yesterday. ''I will let others critique whether I lost my focus,'' Mr. Martin said. But this deal was necessary, he said, ''to get the appropriate focus on each business as well as the appropriate capital structure.''</p>
        <p>Of the two new companies, Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises appears to be in stronger shape, according to stock analysts. Because of a booming economy, the luxury market has been soaring, and sales at Saks Fifth Avenue have been growing at roughly 10 percent a year. The prospects for Saks Inc. and the midlevel department stores in general seem grimmer, reflected yesterday in the news that Mr. Martin will eventually relinquish his position with the department store group to remain on as chairman of Saks Fifth Avenue Enterprises, although he will continue to own a stake in both.</p>
        <p>Philip Miller will continue as chairman of Saks Fifth Avenue, and Christina Johnson will remain president and chief executive of the Saks Fifth Avenue stores division. The department store group will start a search for a new chief executive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
