<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shoot-'Em-Up That Leaves You Laughing</title>
    <meta content="20GAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bioware (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olafson, peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D6113BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shoot-'Em-Up That Leaves You Laughing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER OLAFSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olafson, peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MDK2, computer game created by Canadian company BioWare, evaluated; photos (Game Theory column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MDK2 made me smile. Not quickly, not broadly, and usually not for very long, but my reflection in the monitor screen did occasionally grin back at me for a second or two, and that was unusual.</p>
        <p>It had been years since a game made me smile -- let alone laugh -- with any regularity. I suspect that is a byproduct of the decline in the late 1990's of the adventure game, the genre best equipped for pure storytelling and for the exquisite timing that humor requires. Infocom made me laugh reliably with its text adventures throughout the 1980's, and its spiritual heir, Legend Entertainment, made me laugh with its text-and-graphic adventures in the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MDK2 made me smile. Not quickly, not broadly, and usually not for very long, but my reflection in the monitor screen did occasionally grin back at me for a second or two, and that was unusual.</p>
        <p>It had been years since a game made me smile -- let alone laugh -- with any regularity. I suspect that is a byproduct of the decline in the late 1990's of the adventure game, the genre best equipped for pure storytelling and for the exquisite timing that humor requires. Infocom made me laugh reliably with its text adventures throughout the 1980's, and its spiritual heir, Legend Entertainment, made me laugh with its text-and-graphic adventures in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>I have fond memories of trying to get some mundane object from an uncooperative, monosyllabic sailor in LucasArts' Secret of Monkey Island. The more I tried, the more he said no. The more he said no, the more I tried. I could barely stay in my chair for laughing -- both at myself for my inane persistence and at the game for responding in such detail.</p>
        <p>That was 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>In MDK2, the Canadian game developer BioWare, which showed in 1998's Baldur's Gate that the role-playing genre still has a pulse, demonstrates with a joyful mix of action and whimsy that games can still find subtle ways to amuse us.</p>
        <p>Like Shiny Entertainment's original MDK from 1996, MDK2 is not conventionally funny. (Indeed, when it tries to be conventionally funny, as it does in the animations between its 10 levels, it is the least effective.) Rather, it makes me feel funny, the way I felt after I had sneaked a couple of sips of my dad's Budweiser when I was a kid. Around the third level, through the accrual of minor but telling details, I found MDK2 had kicked me into a kind of giddy reverie.</p>
        <p>That's no mean achievement. Comedy is especially risky in an action game. To paraphrase John Le Carre's George Smiley: If you make your enemy look too foolish, you lose the justification for taking him on.</p>
        <p>At the game's start, the victors of MDK have no sooner toasted their success than they discover that the aliens they thought vanquished have returned. A mine crawler -- a surface-chewing lawn mower operating on a planetary scale -- has appeared in Edmonton, Alberta. (A small in-joke: BioWare is based in Edmonton.) So Kurt Hectic, hero of the first game, goes back into action, diving from the orbiting Jim Dandy spacecraft while dodging missiles.</p>
        <p>Like its predecessor, MDK2 adopts the over-the-shoulder, third-person view familiar from the Tomb Raider games. It preserves the level structure: corridors link stadium-size chambers, typically with a locked door at the far end that is opened by finding and disabling a series of devices. You will still find sub-games that range from directing a tropical fish through pipes to avoiding flying debris. And you'll undertake the conventional business of collecting weapons and supplies.</p>
        <p>But while the pieces will seem familiar, the whole is not quite conventional. Kurt remains an unlikely hero. In his form-fitting coil suit and pointed helmet, he looks as though he should be competing in the Tour de France rather than saving the planet. When he pops open the threadbare parachute that permits him to glide through the immense levels, it looks as though someone has pulled back his suspenders to give them a nasty snap.</p>
        <p>Some of the weapons are rather extravagant. One type of grenade opens a black hole that sucks in everything around it -- especially useful when a resilient enemy absolutely, positively has to be removed to someplace else. The enemies do not all behave like normal, preternaturally aggressive enemies. Some of them appear to be waving at me. And in all honesty, Kurt didn't so much dive from the Jim Dandy as fall from it.</p>
        <p>The original MDK was an all-Kurt affair. (The K in the title stands for Kurt.) Here, he handles only every third level, sharing the spotlight with Max (the M) and Dr. Fluke Hawkins (the D). Max is a six-limbed, cigar-chomping robotic dog who can operate a jet pack, fire up to four weapons simultaneously and destroy a formidable array of scenery.</p>
        <p>As you would expect of a scientist with spectacles and a crown of white hair, Dr. Fluke Hawkins is not much of a fighter. But he possesses a gift for invention: With found items in each hand, he can sometimes combine them to create something new. It's a skill that emphasizes chasing down objects and experimentation and gives his levels a distinctly adventure-game feeling. For instance, the hand dryer retrieved from the spaceship lavatory and some pipes come together as a leaf blower; it sends the giant enemies occupying the leafy lounge bouncing into the maw of a giant, toothy plant on loan from ''The Little Shop of Horrors.''</p>
        <p>But MDK2 tends to celebrate its humor in small touches, from the quiet ''ding'' of the machines that recharge Max's jet pack to the distressed body language of aliens in the sights of Kurt's sniper scope to the little neon labels that appear above the weapons and supplies. The enemies you shoot sometime collapse in extravagant fashion, first spinning around on one foot, as though they are auditioning for a part in a corny western. And advancing through one room requires that Kurt take the stage and dance to entertain aliens in the balcony.</p>
        <p>Individually, few of these little scenes are worth more than a flutter of a comic eyelash. But taken together, they put the player just slightly off balance -- not so wobbly as to jeopardize MDK2's premise, but wobbly enough to enjoy it at a new, silly level. At one point, controlling Max, I stumbled across a wall panel that looked like a false front. I had Max do what he does best -- shoot it -- and the wall panel shattered, only to reveal another wall panel. And behind that one, another.</p>
        <p>That went on for about seven layers, but it never became repetitious. Rather, it made a joke of the repetition, recalling in tone the curtains and doors in classic cartoons that open to reveal another portal, and in its comic persistence, that uncooperative sailor in Monkey Island a decade ago.</p>
        <p>I had to smile, and I did.</p>
        <p>MDK2, published by Interplay; for Windows 95 and 98, and Sega Dreamcast; $34; for teenagers and adults.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
