<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Okinawans Hope Economic Meeting Puts Focus on Art Missing Since War</title>
    <meta content="20TREA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Okinawa and Other Ryukyu Islands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Honan, William H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Okinawa and the Ryukyu Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6DB1E3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Okinawans Hope Economic Meeting Puts Focus on Art Missing Since War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM H. HONAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Honan, William H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leaders on Japanese island of Okinawa will use eight-nation economic summit to help speed recovery of cultural property that disappeared from homes, public buildings and religious shrines when American soldiers seized island in 1945; even though more than 100 artworks have been returned by American veterans, heirs and US Customs Service, nearly 800 objects of Okinawan origin are reportedly in holdings of 21 American museums; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaders on the Japanese island of Okinawa plan to use the eight-nation economic summit conference there this week to help speed the recovery of cultural property that disappeared from homes, public buildings and religious shrines when American soldiers seized the island in 1945.</p>
        <p>To date, more than 100 artworks -- including ancient Buddhist temple bells, statuary and sacred manuscripts -- have been returned by American veterans, their heirs and, in at least one case, forcibly by the United States Customs Service. But one scholar, Peter Kleinen of the German Institute of Japanese Studies, recently reported finding nearly 800 objects of Okinawan origin in the holdings of 21 American museums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leaders on the Japanese island of Okinawa plan to use the eight-nation economic summit conference there this week to help speed the recovery of cultural property that disappeared from homes, public buildings and religious shrines when American soldiers seized the island in 1945.</p>
        <p>To date, more than 100 artworks -- including ancient Buddhist temple bells, statuary and sacred manuscripts -- have been returned by American veterans, their heirs and, in at least one case, forcibly by the United States Customs Service. But one scholar, Peter Kleinen of the German Institute of Japanese Studies, recently reported finding nearly 800 objects of Okinawan origin in the holdings of 21 American museums.</p>
        <p>Since many of these artworks were put on display after World War II, scholars believe they were looted during and immediately after the fighting.</p>
        <p>One of the most cherished objects still missing is the ancient headdress worn by the Ryukyu kings who ruled Okinawa until the island was annexed by imperial Japan in 1879. The headdress is a silk, helmet-shaped crown studded with pearls, gold, jade and other precious stones. It has not been seen publicly since 1945.</p>
        <p>Last month a delegation of six City Council members from Nago, where the economic meeting is to begin tomorrow, flew to Washington and gave President Clinton and other administration officials a council resolution calling on the United States to ''investigate the whereabouts of our lost cultural assets and take relevant steps for their return.''</p>
        <p>Mikio Yabu, the leader of the group, said at a stop in New York, ''We hope the summit conferees will pay attention not only to international economic issues but to the restoration of cultural losses from Okinawa.''</p>
        <p>Speaking by telephone from Naha, Okinawa's capital, Shizuo Kishaba, chairman of the semi-official Ryukyu-American Historical Research Society, who has played a major role in returning stolen objects to Okinawa, took a more forceful position.</p>
        <p>While stopping short of predicting that President Clinton would face a hostile demonstration when he arrives in Okinawa, Mr. Kishaba said, ''The president knows what we are seeking, and if he arrives empty-handed it will certainly sour our relationship with the United States.''</p>
        <p>The State Department, in response to an inquiry, issued a statement saying, ''We recognize the deep concern of the people of Okinawa about artifacts missing since the end of World War II.'' The F.B.I., the statement said, has offered to list missing items in a database available at www.fbi.gov/majcases/arttheft/ art.htm.</p>
        <p>Missing items are also being listed in the national stolen art file, accessible only to law enforcement officials, the statement said.</p>
        <p>A State Department spokesman, however, said that it was unlikely that the American delegation would actually bring any of the artifacts this week.</p>
        <p>In World War II priceless artworks were seized by soldiers in both the Pacific and European theaters and sometimes justified as war trophies. The issue of unreturned works still troubles relations between Germany and Russia. For American servicemen and women theft from conquered territories was prohibited by the Articles of War, No. 93.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kishaba said that many American servicemen who stole objects from Okinawa in 1945 later sold or donated them to American museums. ''The result is that Okinawan treasures are scattered across the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Peabody Essex Museum in Salem, Mass., has a group of six ceramic and pewter objects sold for $75 in 1947 by Cmdr. Carl W. Sternfelt, an American intelligence officer who served on Okinawa during the war.</p>
        <p>Records of this sale are particularly significant, Mr. Kishaba said, because he and many others believe that Commander Sternfelt, who died in 1976, also took the royal Ryukyu headdress in 1945.</p>
        <p>Much of Commander Sternfelt's loot was confiscated by United States Customs agents in 1953 and returned to Okinawa later that year in a ceremony celebrating the centennial of Matthew Perry's historic visit to Okinawa.</p>
        <p>Commander Sternfelt's son, Robert Sternfelt, of Scituate, Mass., denies that his father ever possessed the headdress and said that his father voluntarily surrendered the booty he brought home from Okinawa.</p>
        <p>Christina Hellmich, a spokeswoman for the Peabody Essex Museum, said, ''If we are presented with evidence that Commander Sternfelt stole the objects now in our possession, we would repatriate them.''</p>
        <p>Another point of contention is a 10-inch flat stone from Okinawa incised so as to suggest that it may have been used as an ancient sundial or a navigational instrument. It is now in the collection of the University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kishaba believes the stone was taken by an American soldier after the war and wants it returned to Okinawa, but Gregory L. Posschl, curator of the Asian collection of the museum, said that the provenance of the object was uncertain and that it could not be returned unless Okinawa's rightful ownership was established.</p>
        <p>''We have no desire to keep things that don't belong to us,'' Mr. Posschl said. ''But we have to go through a process that is both rigorous and fair to determine the validity of these claims.''</p>
        <p>In 1945 Okinawa was the scene of the largest land, air and sea battle in history, and the focus of Japan's desperate resort to kamikaze attacks.</p>
        <p>The 81 days of fierce fighting that began on Easter left 12,000 Americans dead or missing and 72,000 wounded, more than twice the numbers from Guadalcanal and Iwo Jima combined.</p>
        <p>Japanese losses were even greater. The Japanese death toll soared to 120,000 combatants and more than 150,000 civilians.</p>
        <p>Few structures on the island were left standing, and looting by American soldiers -- commanders as well as enlisted men -- was widespread.</p>
        <p>''A frenzy of souvenir hunting was part of the terrible strangeness of that battle,'' said George Feifer, author of ''Tennozan: The Battle of Okinawa and the Atomic Bomb'' (Houghton Mifflin, 1992). ''The Marines risked their lives to tear a photograph off of a wall or even to grab a pair of sneakers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kishaba said, ''We were in danger of having our culture erased.''</p>
        <p>Members of the delegation spoke emotionally last month about their sense of loss. Kazunori Nagayama said learning to play the sanshin, a classical Okinawan stringed instrument, had inspired his interest in Okinawan cultural history.</p>
        <p>When he plays his 80-year-old sanshin, he said, he dreams of ancient court life where such instruments were played in the presence of the royal family.</p>
        <p>''But my dreams are frustrating because we have so little to remind us of our roots,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Morio Kohama, 42, said he had learned about the history of Okinawa from his father, who is 86. ''But I have no proof, nothing I can hold in my hands, of the truth of what he is telling me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
