<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; The Crime Fighter</title>
    <meta content="20HERB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Economic Policy Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DC1F3BF933A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; The Crime Fighter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert article holds nationwide decline in crime rate is linked to drop in unemployment rate; cites Economic Policy Institute study that found unemployment and crime rates falling together by region and rising wages and crime rates moving apart; calls for rise in minimum wage and job training for low-wage workers and ex-criminal offenders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An important but frequently overlooked factor in the nationwide decline in crime over the past few years has been the corresponding decline in the unemployment rate.</p>
        <p>Aggressive policing and long prison sentences get most of the attention. Credit is also belatedly being given to the often heroic and usually unheralded crime-fighting efforts of local groups and individuals in poor neighborhoods, and to the many young people who have stepped back from the lure of drugs and antisocial behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An important but frequently overlooked factor in the nationwide decline in crime over the past few years has been the corresponding decline in the unemployment rate.</p>
        <p>Aggressive policing and long prison sentences get most of the attention. Credit is also belatedly being given to the often heroic and usually unheralded crime-fighting efforts of local groups and individuals in poor neighborhoods, and to the many young people who have stepped back from the lure of drugs and antisocial behavior.</p>
        <p>Now we have a study by a pair of Washington economists that appears to confirm a point that has seemed like common sense to a lot of people, but that politicians have never pushed vehemently enough: A job is one of the most effective weapons in the nation's crime-fighting arsenal.</p>
        <p>It's not just common sense but longstanding economic theory that suggests a link between lower rates of joblessness and lower rates of crime. The new study by the Economic Policy Institute looked at crime rates and employment statistics in several regions of the country between 1989 and 1998 and found evidence to support that theory.</p>
        <p>According to the study, ''An examination of unemployment, wages, and crime rates by region shows unemployment and crime rates falling together, and rising wages and crime rates moving apart.''</p>
        <p>Looking specifically at unemployment rates for young men, the study found that since 1992 the jobless rate had fallen by at least four percentage points in each region, with the largest decline in the Northeast, which is also where crime rates fell most quickly.</p>
        <p>The authors of the study, Jared Bernstein and Ellen Houston, wrote:</p>
        <p>''Labor market conditions are not, of course, the only or even necessarily the prime determinant of crime rates. Over the 1990's, the U.S. sharply increased its expenditures on prisons, incarcerating a growing number of the population and passing 'get tough' crime prevention legislation. These interventions have undoubtedly played a large role in lowering crime rates. But the link between crime and labor market opportunity is too often ignored in the current policy debate over crime, which focuses almost solely on longer sentences and prison expansion.''</p>
        <p>The people at highest risk for engaging in crime are young men, primarily from ethnic minority groups, ''with low levels of education and a weak attachment to the labor market,'' the study said.</p>
        <p>Despite the overwhelming employment obstacles faced by individuals in that group, many have found work as a result of the current long-running economic expansion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Houston, in an interview, said, ''As unemployment fell below the level of 5 percent over the last couple of years, you can see that real economic opportunities are being expanded for those who are probably the most disadvantaged low-wage workers in society.''</p>
        <p>There is a hunger among Americans everywhere, including the poor and the otherwise disadvantaged, for meaningful employment. The benefits to be gained from putting people to work are endless, and one of those benefits is a safer society.</p>
        <p>That being the case, Ms. Houston and Mr. Bernstein felt it was important when looking at the problem of crime to pay more attention to labor market policies and the value of employment.</p>
        <p>They say in the study, ''The Federal Reserve can play a decisive role here by focusing on its full-employment mandate with at least the same fervor it devotes to interest rates.''</p>
        <p>And there are other issues -- for example, the importance in a time of unprecedented prosperity of approving a boost in the minimum wage; and the need for no-nonsense education and training for low-wage workers and for ex-criminal offenders, many of whom are released into communities across America each and every day.</p>
        <p>When you consider the factors crucial to building a safe and secure society, employment is right there at the top. The idea is to get as many people working for a decent wage as is humanly possible, rather than searching for excuses as to why this person can't be paid a living wage and that person can't be allowed to work at all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
