<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Start, a Duo That Clicked</title>
    <meta content="07MUSI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DE1E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Start, a Duo That Clicked</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the time the guitarist Joe Beck met the flutist Ali Ryerson in late 1996, the pair had more than 50 combined years in the jazz business. They saw in each other what they wanted and wasted no time forming a musical alliance.</p>
        <p>''Joe was working at Poor Henry's in New Milford with keyboardist Pete Levin,'' said Ms. Ryerson over breakfast recently in a West Redding restaurant. ''Pete, who's an old friend of mine, asked me to stop by to meet Joe and sit in. I did. Musically, it just clicked with Joe.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the time the guitarist Joe Beck met the flutist Ali Ryerson in late 1996, the pair had more than 50 combined years in the jazz business. They saw in each other what they wanted and wasted no time forming a musical alliance.</p>
        <p>''Joe was working at Poor Henry's in New Milford with keyboardist Pete Levin,'' said Ms. Ryerson over breakfast recently in a West Redding restaurant. ''Pete, who's an old friend of mine, asked me to stop by to meet Joe and sit in. I did. Musically, it just clicked with Joe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck, seated beside Ms. Ryerson, finished his partner's thought. ''I called her the next morning. Said we should be working together. That's how it started.''</p>
        <p>Within a month they were touring the East, from Florida to Boston. Ms. Ryerson, who lives in Brookfield, has played the same local clubs as Mr. Beck, a resident of Weston. Through the years they had worked with many of the same artists. Mr. Beck worked with Frank Sinatra, who often recorded in New York with Mr. Ryerson's father, the guitarist Art Ryerson.</p>
        <p>When their paths finally crossed, it was clear to Mr. Beck and Ms. Ryerson that they would not soon untangle. In short order, they have played some of most prestigious clubs in the United States and Europe. Next Sunday they will appear at the Towne Crier Cafe in Pawling, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Their first CD together, ''Alto'' (on the DMP label) has been praised by Downbeat magazine and several other publications. And next week as well, Ms. Ryerson's recent concert with the pianist Billy Taylor at the Kennedy Center will be heard on National Public Radio stations throughout the country.</p>
        <p>''I believe I play my best with Ali,'' Mr. Beck said. ''I don't know why. Neither of us are overpowering players. It's inexplicable.'' Ms. Ryerson  explained it a bit more: ''I think we have similar taste in music. As for why certain musicians work well together, it's often a mystery.''</p>
        <p>Their duo career caught fire so fast because both Mr. Beck and Ms. Ryerson had long since established their solo careers in the studio. Ms. Ryerson, a native of New York City, is from a musical family. She grew up in Armonk, N.Y., where her father could easily commute into the city. In New York, he recorded with Bing Crosby, Perry Como, Fats Waller, Louis Armstrong, Tony Bennett, Elvis Presley, Ella Fitzgerald and Paul Whiteman.</p>
        <p>Like her three brothers, Ms. Ryerson studied music at Western Connecticut State University in Danbury for nearly three years. She left school to tour North America with the Billy Fellows Show as a featured soloist, pianist and arranger.</p>
        <p>Upon her return, Ms. Ryerson resumed her studies at the Hartt College of Music in West Hartford, earning a bachelor's degree in 1979. She performed in jobs ranging from a baroque trio to session work for such jazz labels as Red Baron and Concord. She lived in Belgium and in California before settling in Brookfield in 1993. She has 10 albums and has performed in such events as the Monterey Jazz Festival, the JVC in New York, the Guinness Festival in Ireland, the Edinburgh Festival in Scotland and the Centennial Celebration at Carnegie Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck grew up in New Jersey, the son of ''two amateur musicians.'' In 1963, when he was 18, he moved to New York where he worked with Miles Davis, Duke Ellington, Maynard Ferguson, Frank Sinatra and James Brown, among others. Mr. Beck, who was honored five times with the Most Valuable Player Award by the National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences, spent the better part of 30 years writing, arranging and producing jingles on Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>''I quit three times,'' he said. ''Once in the 60's, a few years later in the 70's and in the early 80's. Each time I moved to a farm and came crawling back. Except the last time.</p>
        <p>''Studio work and real music should never be confused,'' continued Mr. Beck, who also produced recordings for Gloria Gaynor and Esther Phillips, including her hit, ''What a Difference a Day Makes.''</p>
        <p>''You do that work, three or four sessions a day,'' he said, ''and you have no desire to do your own music. I didn't do anything for myself for 20 years.'' Then he met Ali.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck said that regardless how unsatisfying it was his studio work continues to open doors for him. ''Having Miles Davis and Sinatra on your resume certainly helps,'' he said. ''If I came out of nowhere, I wouldn't get into the clubs I get into. I guess, in a sense, it was worth it for that. I'm happier now than I've been in 40 years.''</p>
        <p>The guitarist Joe Beck and the flutist Ali Ryerson perform next Sunday at the Towne Crier Cafe, Route 22, Pawling, N.Y. (914) 855-1300.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
