<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zambian Criticizes Leadership of Sierra Leone Peacekeepers</title>
    <meta content="07ZAMB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zambia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chiluba, Frederick (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zambia</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD61538F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zambian Criticizes Leadership of Sierra Leone Peacekeepers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LUSAKA, Zambia, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zambian Pres Frederick Chiluba says that 200 Zambian peacekeepers taken hostage in Sierra Leone were deployed too quickly into unknown territory, with out-of-date maps and shortage of vital equipment; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of Zambia said today that the 200 Zambian peacekeepers taken hostage in Sierra Leone on Thursday had been deployed too quickly into unknown territory with out-of-date maps and a shortage of other vital equipment.</p>
        <p>The Zambian troops form the majority of the approximately 300 soldiers taken hostage this week in the West African country, where the United Nations is striving to keep peace after eight years of civil war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president of Zambia said today that the 200 Zambian peacekeepers taken hostage in Sierra Leone on Thursday had been deployed too quickly into unknown territory with out-of-date maps and a shortage of other vital equipment.</p>
        <p>The Zambian troops form the majority of the approximately 300 soldiers taken hostage this week in the West African country, where the United Nations is striving to keep peace after eight years of civil war.</p>
        <p>President Frederick Chiluba, speaking to reporters after meeting with members of the United Nations Security Council on a peace mission in Africa, criticized obliquely the commander of the peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone, Maj. Gen. Vijay Kumar Jetley of India.</p>
        <p>''This is not the first time our forces have been in peacekeeping,'' Mr. Chiluba said. ''This is the third or fourth time. We have done very well because whenever we have gone, we have been under some good leadership. That depends on who is in command, who is giving orders to people to do what.</p>
        <p>''This was a little bit of an unfortunate situation,'' the president said, adding that his troops had only recently arrived and had been prepared to go to another region. He also said they were not ''provided with the necessary requisites to carry out their job.''</p>
        <p>Asked to describe the lack of preparation, he answered: ''All sorts of factors. The maps, they were old, et cetera, et cetera.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not making judgment on a commander,'' he said. ''I'm not a military person. But all I know is that I think they were deployed rather prematurely. We hope and pray that everything will come out well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiluba said he did not expect the Sierra Leone experience to drive Zambians or other Africans away from peacekeeping assignments.</p>
        <p>''For peace, we'll do everything,''  he said. ''When you say there is peace in the Middle East, the fighting never stops. When you hear there is peace in Kosovo, suddenly you hear they are fighting and they're killing. So it's not peculiar to Africa. Everywhere where there is war, tempers and tensions rise from time to time, and this is what we have to manage.''</p>
        <p>The crisis in Sierra Leone has dogged the seven-member Security Council delegation traveling around Africa to give impetus to a wobbly peace effort in Congo. The seven ambassadors to the United Nations -- from Britain, France, Mali, Namibia, the Netherlands, Tunisia and the United States -- have spent hours on the phone talking to their governments and to colleagues in New York, aware that resolution of the Sierra Leone problem is key to the hopes for any operation in Congo.</p>
        <p>''This is the most important issue now before the Security Council in the short term,'' said Sir Jeremy Greenstock, Britain's representative. ''It's a big blow for peacekeeping in Africa.''</p>
        <p>He said that the Security Council would have to look at how to deal with Foday Sankoh, whose troops from the Revolutionary United Front rebel movement have created havoc in Sierra Leone a year after signing a peace pact in return for concessions that other nations were reluctant to approve -- but finally had no alternative but to accept. One gave Mr. Sankoh a ministry in the government of Sierra Leone's elected president, Ahmed Tejan Kabbah.</p>
        <p>''There isn't a court, as in Yugoslavia or Rwanda,'' said Sir Jeremy, who has taken the lead in the Security Council on Sierra Leone, a former British colony. ''But he will pay for this in due course. Sankoh's made his political position, his international position, untenable for the future.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
