<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 17, She Finds Herself Already on Top of the Acting Game</title>
    <meta content="07MATT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Popular Entertainers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Heather Matarazzo</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matarazzo, Heather</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Konig, Susan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Now and Again (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DE1E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 17, She Finds Herself Already on Top of the Acting Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN KONIG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Konig, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Long Island actress Heather Matarazzo, 17, who stars as Heather Wiseman on hit television series Now and Again; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1990, at age 7, Heather Matarazzo won the part of a Munchkin in a local production of ''The Wizard of Oz'' to benefit children with AIDS. Though it was hardly a starring role, she intended to give it her all. And when she noticed in rehearsal that her cast mates did not share her enthusiasm, she took matters into her own hands.</p>
        <p>''I grabbed a microphone and essentially told everyone off,'' Ms. Matarazzo recalled. ''I told them we were working for a good cause, and that everyone should get with it, do their parts and put smiles on their faces.'' At least one person was paying close attention: a woman in the audience who happened to be a talent scout. Before long, Ms. Matarazzo had an agent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1990, at age 7, Heather Matarazzo won the part of a Munchkin in a local production of ''The Wizard of Oz'' to benefit children with AIDS. Though it was hardly a starring role, she intended to give it her all. And when she noticed in rehearsal that her cast mates did not share her enthusiasm, she took matters into her own hands.</p>
        <p>''I grabbed a microphone and essentially told everyone off,'' Ms. Matarazzo recalled. ''I told them we were working for a good cause, and that everyone should get with it, do their parts and put smiles on their faces.'' At least one person was paying close attention: a woman in the audience who happened to be a talent scout. Before long, Ms. Matarazzo had an agent.</p>
        <p>Now 17, Ms. Matarazzo, who grew up on the North Shore, where she still lives with her parents, stars as Heather Wiseman on the hit television show ''Now and Again,'' which airs Friday nights at 9 p.m. on CBS. Since its debut in September, ''Now and Again'' has consistently tied with ''Dateline NBC'' for first place on Friday nights among 18- to 49-year-olds, according to TV Guide.</p>
        <p>The show's basic premise is pure science fiction: After Michael Wiseman, a Manhattan insurance man played by John Goodman, is pushed in front of a subway train, his brain is scientifically engineered into a flawless new body, and he becomes a government agent, played by Eric Close. But there are strings attached: He is warned by his boss, played by Dennis Haysbert, that his wife, Lisa, portrayed by Margaret Colin, and his teenage daughter, Heather, cannot know he is alive. That challenging and often painful contingency renders ''Now and Again'' an action suspense drama and a sentimental love story as well.</p>
        <p>The show was the brainchild of Glenn Gordon Caron, who created the series ''Moonlighting.'' A TV Guide critic, Shawna Malcolm, describes it as ''a seamless and smart blend of genres,'' and ''a refreshing alternative to the rash of teen dramas and formulaic sit-coms currently cluttering the TV landscape.''</p>
        <p>The show is taped at Silver Cup Studios in Long Island City, where the first season wrapped last month. While the character of Heather Wiseman is a plucky suburban teenager who can be sarcastic and a bit rebellious, Heather Matarazzo seems much more thoughtful and mature than the character who shares her first name. Though she considers herself ''a pretty normal 17-year-old,'' Ms. Matarazzo comes across as bright, articulate, disciplined and down-to-earth.</p>
        <p>Acting does not run in Ms. Matarazzo's family. ''Ever since I was very young, I took dance lessons and was involved in musical theater,'' she said. But neither her parents nor her older brothers -- Mark, a lawyer, or Todd, a mortgage broker -- were ever bitten by the performing bug, said Ms. Matarazzo, who has never taken professional acting lessons. ''Still, they're all very supportive of what I do,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her first major acting role came when she played a victim of child molestation in a New York University short film titled ''A Children's Story.'' It won the Mobil Award in 1993 and earned Ms. Matarazzo an award from N.Y.U.'s Film Division.</p>
        <p>In 1994, at age 11, she took the independent film world by storm, playing Dawn Weiner, a junior high outcast in ''Welcome to the Dollhouse,'' Todd Solondz's dark comedy about coming of age in suburban New Jersey. The film, which was released two years later, won the Grand Jury Prize at the 1996 Sundance Film Festival and earned Ms. Matarazzo the Independent Spirit Award for Best Debut Performance.</p>
        <p>After that, her career soared. She earned guest-star and repeat roles on top-rated television series like ''Roseanne,'' ''E.R.'' and ''Law and Order'' and parts in feature films like ''The Devil's Advocate,'' ''54,'' ''Strike,'' ''Cherry,'' ''Getting to Know You'' and ''Scream 3.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Caron began casting ''Now and Again'' last April, Ms. Matarazzo was high on his list for the part of Michael Wiseman's then unnamed daughter. ''Glenn called me in to audition, and I was really sick,'' Ms. Matarazzo recalled. ''I had a double ear infection and tracheitis and, after about five minutes with me, he sent me home to get some rest. A few days later, I got a call saying I'd gotten the part.''</p>
        <p>Still, for Ms. Matarazzo, having ''as normal a life as possible,'' remains a priority. She attends high school on Long Island as often as she can, which is usually at least two full days a week. If she finishes work early enough (her hours vary from episode to episode, she says), she heads to school after hours and spends time catching up on classwork. ''I'm managing pretty well, because I don't have that many classes this year,'' she said. ''And my work day typically isn't as long as the others' on the show.</p>
        <p>''I've always been as much of a full-time student as I could. Even when I was 7 or 8, I'd schedule auditions for later in the day. After school, my mother and I would rush for the train into the city. No one knew what I was doing. I didn't want the other kids to view me as being different.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes we did that two or three times a week, and it was exhausting. But I've never been one for the tutoring aspect of education. I don't think you learn much about socialization that way. And I like hanging out with kids my own age.''</p>
        <p>But with the release of ''Welcome to the Dollhouse'' came the end of her relative anonymity. ''After that, everyone at school knew exactly what I did,'' Ms. Matarazzo said. ''They knew what films I was in and when they would appear. Some people criticized me and some praised me. But I think that just comes with the territory.''</p>
        <p>Though she has less free time than most Long Islanders her age, she spends it pretty much as they do. ''I love going to Starbucks, to the movies, talking on the phone and playing pool with my friends,'' Ms. Matarazzo said. ''But I don't really have time for a steady boyfriend right now.'' Like many of her peers, she has household chores to tackle, as well. ''I take out the garbage, do my laundry, fold the towels, clean my room and shovel the driveway when it snows. There's no star treatment in my house.''</p>
        <p>At the moment, her favorite leisure-time pursuit is driving her 1997 Mitsubishi Galant around Long Island. Like many of her classmates, she took driver's education in school and recently got her license, though she stresses, ''My car isn't as nice as a lot of the other kids' at school. There are plenty of Lexuses, Saabs and Mercedes in the parking lot. But I love my little car -- it's my baby.''</p>
        <p>While she does get recognized tooling around the Island, Ms. Matarazzo said: ''It's not insanity. So, I just go with it. I don't want to be one of those actors who says, 'I don't sign autographs,' because the people who come up to you and say nice things are the people who put you where you are. And I'm grateful.''</p>
        <p>On being both a television star and a ''regular kid,'' Ms. Matarazzo said: ''I don't consciously balance my life, I just live it. I think I have the best of both worlds. I'm doing what I love, and yet I still maintain a simple, private life.''</p>
        <p>With ''Now and Again'' finished shooting for the season, Ms. Matarazzo is free for more typical teenage pursuits like planning for her senior prom, and preparing for college in the fall (she will attend college in New York State, though she would not divulge where). She plans to study directing and producing, and despite her television role, she expects to be a full-time student. ''I haven't really worked out my schedule with the show's producers yet,'' she said. ''But I think college is easier to work around than high school, because you do a lot more work outside the classroom.''</p>
        <p>Her plans to remain in New York may be necessary for her career, but they also meet her personal preferences. ''I'm very close to my mom,'' Ms. Matarazzo said. ''We go so many places together. She often comes to the set with me, and hopefully that will continue. I'm also very much a city girl. Living on Long Island is great because of the proximity to Manhattan. In fact, I wouldn't have taken the role of Heather if it required me to live in L.A. I can't ever see myself living there -- I'm a true New Yorker.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
