<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Question: The Legacy Of a Winner</title>
    <meta content="07RILE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riley, Pat</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DB1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Question: The Legacy Of a Winner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coach Pat Riley, preparing for playoff series between his Miami Heat and New York Knickerbockers, recalls mistake he made as Knicks coach that helped cost Knicks last game of 1994 finals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When people ask if he needs to beat the Knicks to feel whole again -- if he needs another title so he can escape the awful purgatory of this unforgiving game -- Pat Riley answers with a laugh.</p>
        <p>''One time I felt that way,'' he said. ''But as you get older, you get out of that.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When people ask if he needs to beat the Knicks to feel whole again -- if he needs another title so he can escape the awful purgatory of this unforgiving game -- Pat Riley answers with a laugh.</p>
        <p>''One time I felt that way,'' he said. ''But as you get older, you get out of that.''</p>
        <p>But there are laments. Some run almost as deep as his resolve to win a championship for the Miami Heat. As he prepares for the fourth consecutive Heat-Knicks playoff crucible, he has let go of countless tough losses, moved on.</p>
        <p>But one still haunts him. Game 7 of the 1994 finals, in which he came so close to bringing the Knicks their first title in more than 20 years.</p>
        <p>''I really made a coaching mistake,'' Riley said after practice on Friday afternoon. ''I stayed with John for too long. I did. I say that now because he was so cold. At the time, he was also pressing.''</p>
        <p>John Starks shot 2 for 18 against the Houston Rockets that June night, chucking up long jumpers, trying in vain to shoot himself out of a slump, shot after missed shot after missed shot. Believing in Starks to a fault, Riley failed to pull the shooting guard he had plucked from obscurity and molded into a starter. The Knicks went down, 90-84.</p>
        <p>''If I had to do it over again, the guy that I would have given some quality minutes to and I didn't was Rolando,'' he said of the more experienced Rolando Blackman. ''I always to this day regret that.</p>
        <p>''I always look back and think about it because we were so close. It was right there, for the championship.''</p>
        <p>He shakes his head. A rueful smile passes across his tanned, lined face.</p>
        <p>''We were up, 3 to 2. Just got to win one game. Couldn't get it done.</p>
        <p>''Five years later, I wouldn't let a man miss six in a row without giving him a rest. I'll probably live to regret saying that, but I think you just learn as you go along.''</p>
        <p>Resting his right arm against a pushed-in wood-stained bleacher -- the tiny diamonds from his 1987 Lakers world championship ring gleaming -- the 55-year-old coach had just finished practice. He reflected on his career, retirement, a championship lost and paradise almost found.</p>
        <p>The Starks story has a parallel. The Heat is flawed -- two consecutive first-round playoff eliminations before this year -- yet Riley believes in his team's ability to win a title.</p>
        <p>''I think the franchise is in good shape,'' he said. ''We have a great arena and more season tickets. But it really comes down to winning. Can we win a championship? And that's where, to this point, I've failed in New York and I've failed here.''</p>
        <p>Failed? With 999 victories, he will become next season only the second coach in history to record 1,000 victories. In 18 years, his teams have won their division 16 times. No coach has won more playoff games (149). He won four championships in Los Angeles. He resuscitated franchises in New York and Miami. He said that was not enough.</p>
        <p>''I think both those franchises benefited, but they didn't get what they thought they were going to get from me,'' Riley said. ''And that bothers me.</p>
        <p>''It bothers me, it just really bothers me. I'd like to leave my career with one more title and leave some other players with one, so when they look at me, they say: 'You know what? You're the real deal. You know what? They were right about you.' They can't say that.''</p>
        <p>He has been chastised for not upgrading the Heat's roster with younger players. Riley the coach does not buy the argument that his loyalty to players has undermined Riley the team president.</p>
        <p>''I think the coach should say: 'Look it, it's time. Now,' '' he said. ''I know this team and when it's time to move in another direction with some guys, and I also know when it's not. And I don't think last year's bounce by Allan Houston was the time to say, 'This is a bad deal here.'</p>
        <p>''We've got a great, great group of guys. Hard-working, good men. Are they good enough to win? That's going to be the ultimate tragedy if they're not. Because they'll know they're not good enough.''</p>
        <p>The Heat players say Riley has mellowed; he is not as critical and listens more often to them.</p>
        <p>''He's still Riles, the coach who gets more out of you than anyone,'' Dan Majerle said. ''But there is a personal side you get to see now and then.''</p>
        <p>Riley has been characterized as a tortured soul, someone who cannot leave his home or fathom life without another championship ring.</p>
        <p>''I used to fear the consequences a lot more, but I don't anymore,'' he said. ''I have had nothing but good things happen to me in my career. I've had some downs. Leaving New York was a very difficult time. A lot of people thought it was very easy for me to leave. The departure was one that was very ugly and consistent for a couple of years. I never wanted that to happen anywhere in my career. But it did.''</p>
        <p>The conversation shifted toward retirement. Last summer, he signed a contract extension through 2004-5, but admitted on Friday that he thinks about leaving the game sooner.</p>
        <p>''I might not even make it through that,'' he said. ''I'm at the beginning of the end. I don't feel the same pressure I felt when I went to New York. I don't feel the same pressure I felt when I first came here. I know the ship is good.''</p>
        <p>He said he has managed to spend more time with his wife, Chris, and their children, James, 15, and Elisabeth, 11.</p>
        <p>''James is a don't-do-sports kid,'' he related about his children, who were adopted as infants. ''He's a computer kid and a musician. And Elisabeth is very well-rounded. They're good kids. Like any other kids, we have our problems. It's hard to parent today.</p>
        <p>''James had a difficult time with being James Riley, because he would get kidded. But he's over it. Elisabeth sort of likes it.</p>
        <p>''But they don't want to share me with anybody. They get annoyed when people come up and ask for autographs.''</p>
        <p>He also admitted to being somewhat superstitious. One of the rumors around New York was that he and Chris had their Greenwich, Conn., home exorcised when he coached the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''Exorcised?'' he said. ''My wife is a devout Christian. She used to go in with holy water to Boston Garden. When she went to Madison Square Garden, she did the same thing, made sure this place was blessed for 'my husband.'</p>
        <p>''No, we didn't have an exorcist come in. My wife is strong enough to do that herself. Her and her mother would walk around with the Bible and go in the closet. They'll take care of the exorcism. I'm not kidding.''</p>
        <p>Riley plans to write a definitive book on coaching and something on pro basketball, and beyond his best-selling motivational books has six screenplays in the works.</p>
        <p>''They haven't been made yet, but I produced the work,'' he said. ''I've sold them to all of the studios.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm a half-decent thinker. I'm going to get a ghost writer, help me organize it. And I'm going to continue to speak. I like that stuff.''</p>
        <p>One of his scripts is titled ''The Seventh Game.''</p>
        <p>A renowned storyteller in the locker room, he still uses drama and metaphor to spur the troops.</p>
        <p>''I talked a little bit today about 'U-571,' '' he said, referring to the World War II submarine film that he took his players to see last week.</p>
        <p>''Some of my players the other day didn't know the meaning of it. You cannot make an analogy with 'U-571' and the Heat and what that whole movie is about?''</p>
        <p>He answered his own question, talking about what he believed was the first message of the film: leadership.</p>
        <p>''The first officer was expecting a command,'' he said. ''He didn't get it and he asked his captain why. And the captain said, 'You're a good leader but you can't command this fleet.'</p>
        <p>'' 'Why? I'd give my life for these men.'</p>
        <p>'' 'I know you would, but you don't know what it takes in warfare to be able to go up to another man and make him give his life, order him to give his life for the sub.'</p>
        <p>''He couldn't do that. He was faced with that dilemma at the end of the movie. He was faced with the dilemma of ordering one of the sailors down to release the dormant torpedo in the tube.</p>
        <p>''To me, the Miami Heat has been depth-charged two years in a row,'' he said, his voice rising. ''We have a dormant torpedo tube. And we have to have a sense of urgency of opening this damn thing, O.K.? Do you guys understand that? In other words, do your job. Be a sailor. Do your job.''</p>
        <p>Riley collects himself. He takes his arm off the bleachers and steps back.  ''That was my symbolic message,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
