<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Meal With, on Some Nights, Live Jazz</title>
    <meta content="07DINE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ernaccio's 17 Main (Mount Kisco, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DA1F39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Meal With, on Some Nights, Live Jazz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT KISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Ernaccio's 17 Main restaurant in Mount Kisco, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST year, new ownership of Ernaccio's 17 Main ran an uneven course. This handsome restaurant had some rocky moments in both food and service. But diners who had then been disappointed or annoyed might take another look. Both food and service have improved markedly. But for the kitchen's careless gaffe or two, the rating would have been higher.</p>
        <p>The place is easy to like. Silk shades soften the lighting, lending a gauzy glow to brick and beige walls; pin lights in swagged sheers at the front window and in trees at the back lend a festive touch. Furthermore, on Thursday nights, diners who are also early risers can hear good live jazz before their bedtime. Night owls pack in much later on Fridays and Saturdays. And then there is the food, some of it delightfully inventive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST year, new ownership of Ernaccio's 17 Main ran an uneven course. This handsome restaurant had some rocky moments in both food and service. But diners who had then been disappointed or annoyed might take another look. Both food and service have improved markedly. But for the kitchen's careless gaffe or two, the rating would have been higher.</p>
        <p>The place is easy to like. Silk shades soften the lighting, lending a gauzy glow to brick and beige walls; pin lights in swagged sheers at the front window and in trees at the back lend a festive touch. Furthermore, on Thursday nights, diners who are also early risers can hear good live jazz before their bedtime. Night owls pack in much later on Fridays and Saturdays. And then there is the food, some of it delightfully inventive.</p>
        <p>Both lunch and dinner menus were short and manageable, with a few dishes available (in slight variation) on both. Small, plump envelopes of phyllo enclosed snails and wild mushrooms; the packages were doused with garlic butter still bubbling hot when brought to the table. Served on a bed of greens, generous fillets of mild gravlax were draped around a crisped potato pancake so good we wished for two or three more. A drizzle of creme fraiche smoothed and bound the flavors.</p>
        <p>Wild mushrooms reappeared grilled, the warm shiitakes, portobellos and criminis gently wilting a balsamic-touched mesclun salad beneath -- an appealing combination. For something plainer, try Greek salad, a toss of feta, black olives, fresh herbs, romaine and nicely balanced vinaigrette. At the other end of the line was a train wreck called Rhode Island fish chowder, a stew of big, mushy overdone chunks of fish in court-bouillon overwhelmed by the taste of peppercorns and bay leaf.</p>
        <p>Apart from a winning, clean-tasting tuna seared without and rare within, fish entrees needed some rethinking. Fresh salmon would have been better than the listed smoked salmon, which was heavily smoky and tepid as well. But blackened grouper proved awful. The charring and a ladleful of spicy hot salsa brought this delicate fish, which needs only a bit of oil or butter to shine, to an undignified end.</p>
        <p>Go for the fine meat dishes and savory vegetarian selections. Judging by our order of boneless, marinated chicken -- wonderfully juicy and flavorful -- other chicken dishes would be well worth a try. Cut into double chops, rack of silky lamb also delivered the goods deliciously.</p>
        <p>Served on a mountain of shoestring potatoes, double-cut pork chop was left a few moments too long over the flame. More carefully timed and much more interesting was special loin of pork stuffed with cheese and softened sun dried tomato.</p>
        <p>Vegetarians and those who are not will enjoy excellent vegetable-rich, comfortably spicy chili. Chili heads should probably request more heat.</p>
        <p>Two diners could share rich, ultra-dense 17 Main chocolate cake topped by at least an inch of thick fudge and nuts. Peach sorbet was fragrant, fruity and refreshing; As served in some other places, however, it came packed in the frozen shell of the fruit, a silly affectation that has long outlived its novelty. Although covered by a lovely crackling skim of nutty burnt sugar, creme brulee seemed watery. And someone forgot to bake fruit pie; the exotic fruits were luscious, but the crust was raw.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $29 without drinks, tax and tip. Ernaccio's is north of and diagonally across from the train station.</p>
        <p>Ernaccio's 17 Main  17 Main Street, Mount Kisco. 244-1974.</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Smart, sophisticated dining room and bar carved into a long, narrow storefront. Live Jazz from about 7:30 on Thursday nights and 9 p.m. on Fridays and Saturdays. Pleasant welcome and efficient service.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Snails with mushrooms in phyllo, gravlax with potato pancake, wild mushrooms on salad greens, rack of lamb, seven-bean chili, seared tuna, boneless chicken, stuffed loin of pork, peach sorbet, 17 Main chocolate cake.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Lunch, main dishes, $7.50 to $18.50. Dinner, main dishes, $16.50 to $21.50; $10 and $14.50 for vegetarian dishes.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch, Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 2:30 p.m. Dinner, Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 5 to 10 p.m. Thursdays through Saturdays, 5 to 11 p.m. Sundays, beginning May 21, 3 to 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Necessary on weekends.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
