<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Rising From Ashes, Bookstore Closes Doors</title>
    <meta content="07BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WESTCHESTER &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Kisco (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mount Kisco Book Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hersch, Irwin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D91E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Rising From Ashes, Bookstore Closes Doors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT KISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Irwin Hersch, owner of Mount Kisco Book Co, bookstore in Mount Kisco, NY, nearly destroyed by 1996 fire and resurrected with help of loyal customers, announces closure; local retail stores, many run by same families for generations, have become all but extinct as rents rise and national chains move in; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BACK in 1996, when fire nearly destroyed the Mount Kisco Book Company, local people refused to let their beloved bookstore die.</p>
        <p>Dozens of loyal customers and store owners rallied to the cause, volunteering their labor and materials to help the store get back on its feet. The Chamber of Commerce announced a fund for out-of-work employees of the bookstore and several smaller shops that burned, and residents promptly sent in $3,000, mostly in small sums. The episode became a symbol of Mount Kisco's pride in and loyalty to its small independent retailers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BACK in 1996, when fire nearly destroyed the Mount Kisco Book Company, local people refused to let their beloved bookstore die.</p>
        <p>Dozens of loyal customers and store owners rallied to the cause, volunteering their labor and materials to help the store get back on its feet. The Chamber of Commerce announced a fund for out-of-work employees of the bookstore and several smaller shops that burned, and residents promptly sent in $3,000, mostly in small sums. The episode became a symbol of Mount Kisco's pride in and loyalty to its small independent retailers.</p>
        <p>But when the store, owned by Irwin Hersch, announced last month that it would be closing for good on May 31, no effort was made to save it.</p>
        <p>For many, the bookstore's demise seemed to signal the end of an era in Mount Kisco, a middle-class village of 10,000 surrounded by the wealthier estate country of Chappaqua, Bedford and Armonk. The town's small retail stores, many of them run by the same families for generations, have been disappearing for years, and now they seem all but extinct. In the last few months two other independent stores in the downtown area have been forced out by high rents: the Mount Kisco Pharmacy, a longtime fixture, and the Chrysalis clothing store. Many other small retailers are struggling.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, we're losing the independent stores,'' said Mary Lee Fox Roe, the chairwoman of Mount Kisco's Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the chain stores have moved in. Among the first were the Gap and Borders Books, which may have contributed to the Mount Kisco Book Company's demise. Then Banana Republic and Rite Aid arrived last summer.</p>
        <p>All this is changing Mount Kisco, many store owners and residents say.</p>
        <p>''It's losing the flavor of the small town,'' said Robert Ambrosio, who runs a tobacco shop on South Moger Street. ''It's becoming a mall. All the stores you see are big corporations. Those stores are the only ones that will survive.''</p>
        <p>Many small retailers are seething with resentment at the town and its larger landlords, whom they regard as insensitive to their needs. ''The town has never done anything for any of the retailers except cause problems,'' Mr. Hersch said.</p>
        <p>The main issue is the parking lot behind South Moger Street, which has been under reconstruction since last August. Although the new space, known as Shoppers' Park, may ultimately benefit all the shops in the area, the protracted construction work has deterred shoppers, who don't know where to park. And that has hurt business.</p>
        <p>''What they've basically done is ruined the whole downtown area of Mount Kisco,'' said Nancy Swenson, co-proprietor of the Consignor's Closet, a women's clothing store on South Moger. ''The question is, What can the town do to help, so we don't have to go out of business?''</p>
        <p>In a sense, Shoppers' Park itself illustrates the difference between the old Mount Kisco and the new. Until about a decade ago, most of the stores adjoining the lot were owner occupied. But gradually, investors started buying up those properties.</p>
        <p>When Mark Farrell took over as mayor in 1995, the lot was a mess. He convinced the property owners to grant the village an easement for parking purposes and to let it take over maintenance of the area.</p>
        <p>That arrangement left the small retailers with the feeling that they had been locked out by their landlords and the town -- particularly when the parking lot failed to materialize. Hurricane Floyd, which damaged most of the stores in Mount Kisco and further slowed the Shoppers' Park project, only made things worse.</p>
        <p>Mayor Patricia Reilly acknowledged that there had been problems with the parking lot and that construction should have been started after the Christmas holiday season, not before. ''We're working as quickly as we can,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the arrival of chain stores in Mount Kisco has been a challenge for the small retailers. Mr. Hersch cited the arrival of Borders as one reason that his bookstore failed. And Melvin Berger, the owner of the Mount Kisco Pharmacy, mentioned the arrival of Rite Aid as one of the reasons he chose to sell out, along with the 30 percent rent increase his landlord imposed.</p>
        <p>In recent years, towns throughout the country have tried to nurture their independent stores and keep out chains. Their methods have included enacting size limits to keep out larger stores; requiring community impact assessments for proposed stores; and imposing formula business bans, whereby towns bar any store built on a nationwide formula, as chain stores are.</p>
        <p>Mount Kisco has not considered any of these approaches, and most of its retailers go out of their way to say that they are not against chain stores. Some say the chain stores help them by bringing more shoppers to town.</p>
        <p>''The town is nicer because of the new stores,'' said Rosemary Wanderer, who is the co-owner with her husband, Paul, of Whippoorwill East, a small gourmet housewares shop on South Moger. ''And I'd rather be next to Macy's or something than off in New Canaan. They bring in business.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the customers themselves are an important factor in the decline of the independent stores. With more options on the Web and in catalogs as well as at larger stores, shoppers are less likely to stick to their local store, no matter how much they may like it.</p>
        <p>''I think the time has unfortunately passed. A store like that just can't exist any more,'' Walter Joyce, a Mount Kisco resident, said. He said he loved the Mount Kisco Book Company but had often shopped at Borders in the past year because its prices were lower and the stock larger.</p>
        <p>Westchester's rapid growth has added another burden for small retailers, since newcomers don't know the old stores and have no reason to be loyal to them.</p>
        <p>''Old customers continue to buy, but you have to come up with new ones, and they're more interested in dollars and cents than being loyal,'' said Don Ford, the owner of Crane's furniture, the oldest business in Mount Kisco.</p>
        <p>Yet experts say the small retailers may rally, so long as they are willing to adapt to a more competitive market. ''To the extent that these smaller stores take the hint and update themselves,'' Kurt Barnard, publisher of the Barnard Retail Trends Report, said, ''they're likely to give the big sellers a run for their money.''</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
