<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grier's Career Finishes in New England as a Reign Starts</title>
    <meta content="07NFLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grier, Bnbby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belichick, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDC1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grier's Career Finishes in New England as a Reign Starts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Football Notebook article focuses on career of New England Patriots' player personnel director Bobby Grier, who has been dismissed by Bill Belichick, team's new coach; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There will be debates about his drafts -- did they produce stars or busts? There will be debates about his eye for talent -- did he go after the right free agents or not? When someone like Bobby Grier leaves the game, a longtime football man who has survived four owners and eight head coaches, his career goes under the microscope, and everyone takes a turn with the scalpel, picking and dissecting.</p>
        <p>Grier is someone many people outside of the Boston area may not know. And when he was fired in his capacity as director of player personnel by New England Patriots Coach Bill Belichick last week, it made little news around the country, in direct contrast to the retirement of San Diego General Manager Bobby Beathard, another person who has dedicated his life to football.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There will be debates about his drafts -- did they produce stars or busts? There will be debates about his eye for talent -- did he go after the right free agents or not? When someone like Bobby Grier leaves the game, a longtime football man who has survived four owners and eight head coaches, his career goes under the microscope, and everyone takes a turn with the scalpel, picking and dissecting.</p>
        <p>Grier is someone many people outside of the Boston area may not know. And when he was fired in his capacity as director of player personnel by New England Patriots Coach Bill Belichick last week, it made little news around the country, in direct contrast to the retirement of San Diego General Manager Bobby Beathard, another person who has dedicated his life to football.</p>
        <p>Grier's quiet disposition will not allow him to state what should be said: that he was one of the league's most dedicated workers and in a rarity in the sport, a man who was a scout, coach and executive in a career that spanned almost three decades.</p>
        <p>Grier declined to comment on his dismissal. Others in the Patriots organization were saddened by his firing and said Grier was somewhat surprised because two years remained on his contract.</p>
        <p>Grier's fate, however, was very likely sealed when Belichick hired a close friend of his, Scott Pioli, a former director of pro personnel for the Jets.</p>
        <p>A further indication that Belichick has anointed himself the Patriots' football guru came on the same day Grier was fired, when Dave Uyrus, the team's director of pro scouting since 1997, was also dismissed. Grier's son, Chris, a scout with the team, will most likely be asked to leave.</p>
        <p>''This is an unpleasant thing for me to do,'' Belichick said in a statement. ''I recognized that Bobby Grier has made significant contributions to the New England Patriots over many years, in various capacities, as has Dave Uyrus. I enjoyed a good working relationship with Bobby in preparation for the recent draft, as I did in 1996.</p>
        <p>''This decision is unrelated to any specific event, performance or personal relationship,'' Belichick continued. ''It is more a reflection of my general feeling to proceed in a new direction with regard to the structure and operation of our personnel department.''</p>
        <p>There were some black coaches who were outraged that Grier, one of the few black general managers in the National Football League, was not allowed to exit with grace, the way Beathard did in San Diego. That anger may be legitimate, or it may not, but over all this has nothing to do with race. It is about control. Does a team give final say on all personnel matters to the head coach or the general manager?</p>
        <p>What happened to Grier reflects a continuing bitter argument on the issue. Bob Kraft, the owner, decided to give Belichick final say on all personnel matters. He is among the owners who believe a head coach can simultaneously handle the duties of coaching and evaluating college and pro personnel. Other owners and general managers say it is impossible for a head coach to do both.</p>
        <p>Kraft's decision to give Belichick total control may stem from an incident that involved Bill Parcells, his longtime nemesis and former coach. In the 1996 draft, Parcells wanted to pick defensive end Tony Brackens while Grier wanted wide receiver Terry Glenn. Kraft sided with Grier, and Parcells, frustrated with his lack of total control, bolted for the Jets. The rift led to Parcells's infamous statement: if he wanted to cook the meal, he should be allowed to shop for the groceries.</p>
        <p>Kraft may have wanted to avoid any potential future divisions by consolidating the power behind Belichick, who joins the likes of Atlanta's Dan Reeves, Seattle's Mike Holmgren, Denver's Mike Shanahan and Minnesota's Dennis Green as coaches who have the last word.</p>
        <p>Grier had been a Patriots employee since 1981, director of player personnel since 1995 and vice president in charge of player personnel since 1997. As a leader in the team's personnel department, Grier was a key part of two questionable drafts (1997 and 1998) and two solid ones (1995 and 1996). The 1995 draft brought Ty Law, Ted Johnson, Curtis Martin, Jimmy Hitchcock and Dave Wohlabaugh.</p>
        <p>Grier is deciding if he wants to stay in football or simply retire. There have been rumors that the league office may be interested in him. No matter what Grier does next, his reputation as a hard and loyal worker is forever secure.</p>
        <p>Sparks's Value Cools</p>
        <p>At the end of last season Giants cornerback Phillippi Sparks told several teammates he was certain he would be one of the hottest free agents on the market. Well, it's May, and Sparks, unfortunately for him, has drawn little interest.</p>
        <p>Some teams think Sparks, at 30 years old, is on the downside of his career. Other teams looking for cornerbacks got them through the draft while yet others may take a look at Deion Sanders once he finishes his baseball season with the Cincinnati Reds.</p>
        <p>Whether Sparks re-signs with the Giants or goes elsewhere, it simply will not be for the megabucks he was expecting.</p>
        <p>Links With Past Dolphins</p>
        <p>In Miami, Coach Dave Wannstedt is doing something quite smart -- surrounding himself with familiar and friendly faces from the Dolphins' past.</p>
        <p>At the April draft, Jimmy Johnson, the former head coach, gave Wannstedt advice about choosing players. Last weekend Don Shula made an appearance at a practice for the first time since he retired in 1996. And Wannstedt turned the locker of retired quarterback Dan Marino into a shrine.</p>
        <p>''They're all a part of the Dolphins organization,'' Wannstedt said. ''When you say 'Miami Dolphins' you think of Don Shula, Dan Marino, Jimmy Johnson. I'm not intimidated by what this organization has done in the past.''</p>
        <p>The Dolphins have been a somewhat fractured franchise recently. Shula and Johnson did not truly get along. Marino and Johnson were also not great pals. And the team has endured its share of bad off-field news, including the accusations against the former running back Cecil Collins, who was accused of breaking into a woman's apartment.</p>
        <p>Wannstedt is simply trying to create a more unified, even homey, atmosphere, and having keen football minds around like Shula and Johnson certainly cannot hurt.</p>
        <p>Cowboys' Hike Coakley's Pay</p>
        <p>Last week, Cowboys linebacker Dexter Coakley signed a one-year deal worth $1.27 million, becoming the first Dallas linebacker in the 11 years Jerry Jones has owned the team to earn more than $1 million a year. . . . Tampa Bay Coach Tony Dungy spoke to prisoners in a Florida correctional facility, telling them to never give up on life. They applauded Dungy, then questioned him. ''Why do you keep running Warrick Dunn up the middle?'' one asked. . . . In minicamp last week, the Washington Redskins worked cornerback Champ Bailey at wide receiver but do not plan on using him for punt and kick returns next season.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
