<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Threat to Nassau Residents' Taxes</title>
    <meta content="07TAX.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1DD1E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Threat to Nassau Residents' Taxes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article assesses possible adverse impact on local homeowners if lawsuit filed by 38 Nassau County commercial property owners, who allege they are being assessed more than their fair share of taxes, succeeds; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Homeowners in much of Nassau County have already begun to dread Jan. 1, 2003, the deadline by which the county has agreed to reassess all residential property and revise tax rolls that are currently based on 1930's values. The agreement, reached in March, ended a high-profile lawsuit charging that the system discriminated against minorities.</p>
        <p>But if near-term impact is what counts, there's another, less-publicized case that homeowners should be worrying about: a lawsuit by 38 Nassau County commercial property owners who allege they are being assessed more than their fair share of taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Homeowners in much of Nassau County have already begun to dread Jan. 1, 2003, the deadline by which the county has agreed to reassess all residential property and revise tax rolls that are currently based on 1930's values. The agreement, reached in March, ended a high-profile lawsuit charging that the system discriminated against minorities.</p>
        <p>But if near-term impact is what counts, there's another, less-publicized case that homeowners should be worrying about: a lawsuit by 38 Nassau County commercial property owners who allege they are being assessed more than their fair share of taxes.</p>
        <p>If their suit is upheld -- and last month it survived a state and county effort to dismiss it -- more county taxes will have to be paid by all residential owners, steepening the 2003 tax increase in well-off neighborhoods and reducing or eliminating the post-assessment tax break expected in low-income areas.</p>
        <p>''If Nassau County wants to reach a final resolution to its financial problems, it's going to have to resolve our case also,'' said one of the plaintiffs, Bennett L. Rechler, a principal of the We're Group in Jericho. ''If we succeed in court, the county will lose a lot of revenue.''</p>
        <p>No court date has been set, but last month's ruling has the plaintiffs talking up an out-of-court settlement that could hit taxpayers a lot sooner than the 2003 revaluation.</p>
        <p>Roger Tilles, co-director of the Tilles Investment Company in Woodbury and another plaintiff in the case, said one of the reasons for filing the suit was that county officials, fearing the political repercussions of revamping residential property taxes, would try to shift even more of the burden onto commercial property owners. ''It's politically easier to raise the taxes on businesses that can't vote,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In his decision last month rejecting the state and county challenges to the commercial owners' lawsuit, state Supreme Court Justice John DiNoto in Mineola pointed out that Nassau applied 1938 construction costs and 1964 land values to determine value when assessing residential property, but applied values derived from a 1986 revaluation when assessing commercial property. And he noted that though the county had imposed caps on annual residential property assessment increases, there were no such caps on commercial property.</p>
        <p>''The result is that Nassau commercial property owners allegedly pay the highest effective tax rate in the state, namely $38.94 per thousand dollars of market value of property, as compared with the median for all counties, which is $25.82,'' he wrote. ''Although commercial property represents only 16 percent of the market value of all property in Nassau County, commercial property owners purportedly pay 27.5 percent of the tax burden.''</p>
        <p>Justice DiNoto ruled that the ''evidence was sufficient to raise a substantial issue as to whether the stated reason for singling out Nassau and New York City for Article 18 treatment was, and continues to be, rational.''</p>
        <p>Article 18, a state law passed in 1981 that applies only to New York City and Nassau County, allows commercial property to be taxed differently from commercial property. Delores Fredrich, special counsel for Nassau County, said that in seeking dismissal of the suit, the county argued that all it was doing was levying taxes in a manner prescribed by state law.</p>
        <p>''The plaintiffs are not complaining that the law has been applied incorrectly,'' Ms. Fredrich said. ''Their remedy is to change the law. If they do, we will abide by the change.''</p>
        <p>The attorney for the plaintiffs, former state Attorney General G. Oliver Koppell, said the judge had ''sustained our principal contentions.''</p>
        <p>''We claim that there is no rational basis for creating a separate system and no reason to discriminate against Nassau commercial ratepayers, and the judge said we have a good claim,'' Mr. Koppell said. ''The county and state are likely to appeal. But we think the county should consider settling with us. This is an opportune time because it has to complete its reassessment by 2003. So let's solve the whole problem and deal with the disparities of the commercial sector.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rechler said there were various ways to correct the disparities, which he said had grown appreciably. He said commercial property owners would still end up with a greater tax burden than residential property owners, but ''it would be less than what we are paying now.''</p>
        <p>A recent study by the Taub Urban Research Center at New York University found that effective real property tax rates increased in Nassau by 13.06 percent from 1997 to 1998, but declined during that period by 11.2 percent in Suffolk. Nassau's increase was the largest of the eight downstate counties.</p>
        <p>''The residential effective tax rate in Nassau County was $18.40 per $1,000 of full value in 1998,'' said Thomas Conoscenti, a coauthor of the study. ''That same year, the commercial effective tax rate was $44.03 per $1,000 of full value. In 1997, the residential rate was $17.45 and the commercial was $38.94. The difference between them that year was $21.20; a year later, it had increased to $26.63.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, the disparity in Suffolk was considerably less and actually declined in 1998, Mr. Conoscenti found.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conoscenti said he believed there was merit to the assertion of Nassau's commercial property owners that they were bearing a disproportionately greater share of the tax burden in the county. He said his study found that the median effective real property tax rates for residential property owners in 1998 was $23.70 statewide, $20.17 in Suffolk and only $18.40 in Nassau.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the median rates for commercial property owners were $27.67 in the eight downstate counties, $22.84 in Suffolk and $44.03 in Nassau.</p>
        <p>''When you make those comparisons, you really see the striking differences,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bernard Hyman, a real estate evaluation specialist, said the tax burden on Nassau's commercial property owners had become ''so onerous that it has made Nassau County a less desirable place for commercial owners to do business. The tremendous increase in the tax rate in recent years is because we have had very little new development to add to the tax base.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tilles, whose company is one of the biggest developers in the region, said he had just put up a building in Woodbury where the taxes were about $6 per foot, fully assessed. But ''just three miles down the road in Melville, I'm going to build a comparable building where the taxes will be under $3 a foot. And with the rent about $30 in both places, those in Woodbury will be paying 10 percent more. That's a huge disadvantage.''</p>
        <p>He said that because of a severe shortage in rental office space on Long Island, the higher rent had not made it more difficult to find tenants for the Woodbury property. But, he warned, ''as soon as we go back to normal conditions, it will make a difference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyman, managing partner of the powerful Certilman Balin Adler &amp; Hyman law firm in East Meadow, said his firm represented nearly every major developer on Long Island and that they were all expanding in Suffolk because that county was ''more amenable to development than Nassau. They are also providing all kinds of incentives. Nassau County is impossible.''</p>
        <p>But Carolyn Fahey, a business development specialist in the Suffolk County Department of Economic Development, said Suffolk was not trying to take advantage of the disparity by offering incentives different from Nassau's.</p>
        <p>''We have a nonwritten verbal agreement that we are not going to do a direct hit on Nassau County,'' she said. ''We're not going to raid each other's businesses. A company in eastern Nassau is as profitable to us with jobs and its whole economic impact as if it were in Melville.''</p>
        <p>And Lee E. Koppelman, executive director or the Long Island Regional Planning Board, questioned Mr. Hyman's assertions, saying that ''every site that is available in Nassau County is at some stage of being developed. Fortunoff just completed The Source, Roosevelt Field is in the process of expanding, and there are proposals for new growth at the Roosevelt Raceway site. I haven't heard from any major developer who has said he is not building in Nassau because of the taxes.''</p>
        <p>He said it was natural for rents in Nassau to be more expensive than those in Suffolk because of Nassau's proximity to New York City. ''With commercial development, location is everything,'' Dr. Koppelman said. And he added that there was more building going on in Suffolk because there was more available land there.</p>
        <p>But he conceded that the ''assessment situation in Nassau County is so anachronistic that it makes Nassau vulnerable to these suits. And the litigants have some legitimacy to their argument because the whole assessment system is out of whack. So the angels aren't just on one side of the argument.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
