<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revealing the Strength of Segal as Sculptor and Draftsman</title>
    <meta content="07SEGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Segal, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adelson, Fred B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7D61F39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revealing the Strength of Segal as Sculptor and Draftsman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED B. ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Adelson, Fred B</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fred B Adelson reviews retrospective by contemporary figurative sculptor George Segal on view at Locks Gallery in Philadelphia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEORGE SEGAL, a master of 20th-century figurative sculpture, has been living and working on what was once a poultry farm in South Brunswick for more than 50 years. His tableaux of contemporary American life made in his studio, a former chicken coop, bring together elements of both sculpture and painting, high art and consumer culture. No history of the Pop Art movement could be complete without a discussion of his assemblages. In the early 1960's, the innovative white plaster casts of ordinary people doing ordinary things in a realistic environment had earned Mr. Segal an international reputation. At their best, these sculptures are more than representations of anecdotal situations; they evoke feelings of ennui and alienation, reflecting a deep concern for the human condition.</p>
        <p>Eight sculptures and 16 drawings by Mr. Segal are presently on display here at the Locks Gallery. With works from 1983 to 1999, the show becomes an intimate retrospective exhibition of the artist in his late years. ''Helen Next to Window'' makes use of the familiar features that go back to his earliest environmental sculptures; the piece is a signatory white plaster torso in a real-world architectural setting. The artist directly cast his wife in the plaster-soaked Johnson &amp; Johnson medical bandages that he had first used as an unprecedented sculptural material in the summer of 1961. Since the early days of his career, it has been very common for Mr. Segal to rely on family, friends and neighbors as models. Helen Segal has been a frequent subject, posing repeatedly for her husband of 54 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEORGE SEGAL, a master of 20th-century figurative sculpture, has been living and working on what was once a poultry farm in South Brunswick for more than 50 years. His tableaux of contemporary American life made in his studio, a former chicken coop, bring together elements of both sculpture and painting, high art and consumer culture. No history of the Pop Art movement could be complete without a discussion of his assemblages. In the early 1960's, the innovative white plaster casts of ordinary people doing ordinary things in a realistic environment had earned Mr. Segal an international reputation. At their best, these sculptures are more than representations of anecdotal situations; they evoke feelings of ennui and alienation, reflecting a deep concern for the human condition.</p>
        <p>Eight sculptures and 16 drawings by Mr. Segal are presently on display here at the Locks Gallery. With works from 1983 to 1999, the show becomes an intimate retrospective exhibition of the artist in his late years. ''Helen Next to Window'' makes use of the familiar features that go back to his earliest environmental sculptures; the piece is a signatory white plaster torso in a real-world architectural setting. The artist directly cast his wife in the plaster-soaked Johnson &amp; Johnson medical bandages that he had first used as an unprecedented sculptural material in the summer of 1961. Since the early days of his career, it has been very common for Mr. Segal to rely on family, friends and neighbors as models. Helen Segal has been a frequent subject, posing repeatedly for her husband of 54 years.</p>
        <p>''Woman on White Wicker Rocker'' is made from bronze with a white patina to replicate the characteristic features of a plaster figure with its very textural, expressionist surface. Cast at the Johnson Atelier in Mercerville, this sculpture of a seated female model makes the precious metal look deceptively like the common bandages that are typically associated with his earlier pieces. Working with a foundry not far from his home, the artist had an ideal and easily accessible opportunity to make sculpture in limited editions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segal's involvement with bronze casting began in the late 1970's as a result of commissions he received for public sculptures. Several of his outdoor bronze works may be seen around New Jersey: ''In Memory of May 4, 1970, Kent State: Abraham and Isaac'' (1978) at Princeton University; ''Toll Booth Collector'' (1980) at the Newark Museum; ''The Constructors'' (1987) at 200 West State Street in Trenton; and ''The Depression Bread Line (1999) at Grounds for Sculpture in Hamilton.</p>
        <p>Two of the artist's most recent sculptural installations are ''Swan Motel'' and ''McDonald's.'' Both tableaux are large-scale nighttime scenes that deal with the commercial culture of the American roadside, a recurrent theme in Mr. Segal's career. Set against a black wall with the suggestion of distant lights (Light-Bright pegs from a child's toy) and illuminated signs that are rather painterly in their execution, a solitary life-size cast figure in very dark colors walks mysteriously into the viewer's real space. A planar image seems to become three-dimensional. Nearly three decades earlier in 1970, Mr. Segal had used this same concept in ''Times Square at Night'' (Joslyn Art Museum in Omaha). His latest works have a more disquieting, haunting and dramatic cinematic quality. Although the figures are meant to be anonymous, the man in ''McDonald's'' is a cousin; and the woman in ''Swan Motel'' is Rena, the artist's daughter. One of the signs directly behind her reads: ''Rena's Deli,'' an actual establishment that her father had seen in the South.</p>
        <p>Above all, the exhibition has a strong emphasis on two-dimensional work. The earliest art on display is a group of pastel drawings representing either cans and sundry items seen on the shelves of the artist's studio or tabletop arrangements of apples that are directly inspired by Cezanne, one of Mr. Segal's heroes. In many ways, these still-life images are overpowered by the intensely strong faces watching from the other side of the gallery. The 50-by-38-inch portrait drawings, dating from the spring to autumn of 1998, are powerful compositions that bring the artist back to his origins as an expressionist figure painter. These close-up faces represent himself, his family and public figures, like Willie Nelson and Abba Eban, a longtime friend. The gestural markings and the strong handling of chiaroscuro make the pastel and charcoal works on paper particularly compelling. They may not break new ground, but they reveal masterful draftsmanship and have an honesty of purpose. As a humanist, Mr. Segal is placing himself in the tradition of Rembrandt and Eakins, creating portraits that have an intensity of photographic observation and psychological penetration.</p>
        <p>In 1973, Mr. Segal said: ''I want to evoke emotions. My ultimate objectives are a feeling of revelation and of psychological truth.'' At 76, New Jersey's most celebrated artist demonstrates that he remains true to his vision, whether it is sculptural or pictorial.</p>
        <p>GEORGE SEGAL: NIGHTSCAPES</p>
        <p>Locks Gallery, 600 Washington Square South, Philadelphia.  Though May 27. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.  (215) 629-1000</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
