<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Muscular Icon Now Touts Gray Matter</title>
    <meta content="07JOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Checkers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Woodmere Park (Long Island, Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lurie, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apelast-Weinberg, Effie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDD1039F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Muscular Icon Now Touts Gray Matter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Dan Lurie, 77, three-time America's Most Muscular Man and former checkers champion who has organized first Five Towns Checker championship for May 21 at North Woodmere Park open to teenmasters and grandmasters who live in Nassau County; Effie Apelast-Weinberg, 71, who took up singing at age 65 and now performs at retirement homes, community centers and libraries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAN LURIE recently came up with a new slogan: ''Develop the most important part of your body -- your brain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lurie, 77, is best known for the less cerebral parts of his body. He was the Arnold Schwarzenegger of his day, three times named ''America's Most Muscular Man.'' This was the bodybuilder who challenged President Ronald Reagan to an arm-wrestling match in the Oval Office and ''let'' the commander-in-chief win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAN LURIE recently came up with a new slogan: ''Develop the most important part of your body -- your brain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lurie, 77, is best known for the less cerebral parts of his body. He was the Arnold Schwarzenegger of his day, three times named ''America's Most Muscular Man.'' This was the bodybuilder who challenged President Ronald Reagan to an arm-wrestling match in the Oval Office and ''let'' the commander-in-chief win.</p>
        <p>A strongman on several television shows, Mr. Lurie lifted 100-pound dumbbells with each hand before a weekly live audience on the 1950's CBS series ''The Sealtest Big Top Circus,'' one of the first color programs. In 1945, he did 1,665 push-ups in 90 minutes. The feat earned him a mention in the Guinness book of world records.</p>
        <p>But in his retirement, Mr. Lurie is pushing checkers, not pumping iron. A sometime snowbird, he takes his checkerboard down to the pool at his condominium in Florida, picks up games in the park and plays with his 14 grandchildren in the North Woodmere house he's called home for nearly 40 years.</p>
        <p>''I can close one eye, put one arm behind my back and still make the moves,'' Mr. Lurie kidded recently, still looking broad and powerfully built. ''You play because you enjoy it. You play with the grandchildren because it makes them think. The most important thing is to let them win.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lurie is more then just the world's strongest checkers player. He has organized the first Five Towns Checker Championship for May 21 at 11 a.m. in North Woodmere Park. The tournament is open to teenmasters ages 13 to 19 and grandmasters from 20 to 120 who live in Nassau County.</p>
        <p>''Whoever enters gets a free T- shirt and a trophy just for entering,'' Mr. Lurie said.</p>
        <p>To get a little notice, on Saturday he plans to build build the world's largest checkboard set -- 16 by 16 feet and 5,000 pounds -- Each checker will be a 200-pound barbell plate. Two professional wrestlers, two female wrestlers and two midget wrestlers have been invited to lift the checkers and play a round.</p>
        <p>In 1936, before he ever lifted a weight, Mr. Lurie was the New York State checkers champion. He was 13 and living in Brooklyn. The Board of Education ran the tournament. About a dozen youngsters entered.</p>
        <p>''It was a nothing-with-nothing contest,'' he recalled. ''But when I won, they sent me to other places to play.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lurie got his checkers smarts from an uncle who was a champion. They visited a man known as the Farmer in Coney Island, a checkers legend known to circle the table and play 20 people at a time, betting 10 cents, maybe a quarter a game. His uncle couldn't beat the Farmer. But Mr. Lurie learned to beat his uncle.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea is setting up traps,'' he advised, setting out red and black checkers on a board. ''You have to think five to seven moves ahead at times.''</p>
        <p>He tells an opponent: ''You have 12 men. I have two men. I'll stop you from getting a king.'' Without hesitating, she quickly jumps his two men. Game over.</p>
        <p>''See, I stopped you from getting a king,'' Mr. Lurie said with a chuckle.</p>
        <p>After taking the 1936 title he never competed formally again. Even so, checkers provided a life lesson.</p>
        <p>''When I started my business, everything I did, I was thinking about my checkers,'' he said. ''How many moves do you have in checkers, eight or nine moves sometimes. The thinking I did in my business was the same. Maybe it had no connection but it made me think a lot.''</p>
        <p>Was he successful?</p>
        <p>''In business yes, but not in checkers,'' he said, realizing as he got older and read books on draughts that he didn't have the makings of a master player. He was able to capitalize on his other hobby, body building, producing a line of dumbbells and weights and later publishing six fitness magazines.</p>
        <p>He claims to have sold Regis Philbin his first set of exercise equipment. Mr. Lurie was presenting Mr. Reagan with a plaque for being ''The Most Physically Fit President of All Time'' when the opportunity to test his biceps arose.</p>
        <p>The president pummeled Mr. Lurie in 30 seconds flat the first round. When Mr. Lurie screamed for a rematch, Mr. Reagan pinned him in 40 seconds.</p>
        <p>Once president of the World Body Builders Guild, Mr. Lurie also presented awards to Joe Louis, Johnny Weismuller and Mae West, who trained every day with 10-pound chrome barbells.</p>
        <p>But back to retirement, to checkers. Working with the Five Towns Community Chest, Mr. Lurie is arranging one-on-one challenges at four local restaurants. If a challenger puts up $100, Mr. Lurie will put up $1,000. If they put up $1,000, he'll boost his bid to $10,000. He donates the winnings -- he claims he never loses -- to charity.</p>
        <p>''I enjoy it,'' Mr. Lurie said. ''I've been a musclehead all my life. They don't expect people with muscles to have a brain. I have to prove that besides having muscles I have a brain.''</p>
        <p>Late-Life Vocalist</p>
        <p>The theater bug can strike at any age. Just ask Effie Apelast-Weinberg. She can't get enough applause.</p>
        <p>Her voice crackling like an old 78-rpm record, arms stretched stiffly in front of her, Ms. Apelast-Weinberg  stood on the stage at the Long Beach Public Library recently, singing her signature tune, ''The Impossible Dream.''</p>
        <p>The mostly geriatric crowd swooned and nodded their heads to the familiar song.</p>
        <p>Ms. Apelast-Weinberg, a lyric soprano, is 71. She doesn't have a demo tape, can't land a role as an ingenue and snags her gigs by telling her tale. She calls herself ''the Senior Diva.''</p>
        <p>''I'm known as a late bloomer,'' she said earnestly after crooning ''If I Loved You'' from Rodgers and Hammerstein's ''Carousel.'' ''My life is a garden of late blooming flowers.''</p>
        <p>A petite, green-eyed blonde who claims a slight resemblance to the opera singer Beverly Sills, Ms. Apelast-Weinberg took up singing at age 65.</p>
        <p>Four years' worth of voice lessons later, against her coach's advice, she rented out Columbia Artists Management Incorporated, a Manhattan music hall across the street from Carnegie Hall. Inviting everyone she knew, Ms. Apelast-Weinberg gave her first recital to 125 guests on a Sunday afternoon last year. She performed a medley of Puccini arias, German lieder, Italian art songs, Gershwin and pop in the bel canto tradition -- without a microphone.</p>
        <p>''Now I'm a professional singer,'' she said, having since strutted her stuff in retirement homes, community centers and libraries. ''When I get too old for that, I'm going to be a professional tennis player.'' She plays tennis five to six times a week. Being in shape, she said, makes it easier to sing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Apelast-Weinberg has had several careers and three husbands. At 22, she was a personnel manager in a factory. She did secretarial work, then entered the advertising field. In her 50's, she returned to school, earning a master's degree in nutrition.</p>
        <p>After moving to Great Neck when she married Norbert Weinberg eight years ago, Ms. Apelast-Weinberg decided to audition for a part in ''Fiddler on the Roof'' at their synagogue, Temple Israel of Great Neck.</p>
        <p>She won the role of Grandma Tseitl. But what she really wanted  was a lead. So she signed up for voice lessons with the tenor Nino Tello.</p>
        <p>''As a youngster, I didn't want to put myself out there,'' she said, recalling how her older sister had unsuccessfully taken voice lessons but she didn't dare ask. ''Now I can't get enough people to see me.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Apelast-Weinberg's father was an usher in a synagogue and she learned all the liturgical music, singing along with the organ and the choir.</p>
        <p>''I used to think if I could sing so beautifully, my voice would go to heaven,'' she said. ''That's what's been buried inside of me for such a long time.'' But after joining the choir in college, she didn't belt out a tune for 35 years. Not even in the shower.</p>
        <p>Those days are over. She sings at her temple and with the Great Neck Choral Society. Last fall, Ms. Apelast -Weinberg performed, but didn't place, as one of 15 contestants in the Ms. Senior America New York pageant.</p>
        <p>She hasn't been able to find an agent who will take on an up-and-coming over-the-hill singer. But she successfully pitched her story to News 12, WPIX-TV and WINS radio.</p>
        <p>''It's wonderful,'' she gushed. ''It's marvelous. I shine from it. It's keeping me young. I handle audiences very well, except at my first concert at the Mayfair in Great Neck where half the audience fell asleep.''</p>
        <p>The library concert was scheduled to last an hour. Because she sang too fast, Ms. Apelast-Weinberg finished 20 minutes early. No problem, she said, striding backstage to pick up notes to yet another song.</p>
        <p>''I can go on singing forever,'' she told the audience. '' Now I'm really doing what I dreamed of.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
