<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: The U.S. and Africa; Extending a Trembling, Hesitant Hand</title>
    <meta content="07PERL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DA1538F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: The U.S. and Africa; Extending a Trembling, Hesitant Hand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debacle of UN peackeeping force in Sierra Leone and hesitant US response reviewed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR most of a year now, the United States has been proclaiming its intention to get more involved in the fate of Africa -- in calming its wars, in building its economies.</p>
        <p>The 11,000 men of the United Nations peacekeeping force sent into Sierra Leone, and the helicopter gunships reinforcing them, were the first tangible sign that this intention would amount to more than words. The soldiers were from third-world countries but their assignment was being paid for in part with $70 million from the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR most of a year now, the United States has been proclaiming its intention to get more involved in the fate of Africa -- in calming its wars, in building its economies.</p>
        <p>The 11,000 men of the United Nations peacekeeping force sent into Sierra Leone, and the helicopter gunships reinforcing them, were the first tangible sign that this intention would amount to more than words. The soldiers were from third-world countries but their assignment was being paid for in part with $70 million from the United States.</p>
        <p>And another peacekeeping force has been waiting in the wings to try to pacify the even more embattled Congo. Together, the Clinton administration has been hoping, these two forces would forever refute the notion that the international community has been eager to right wrongs in Europe and Asia, but has another set of rules for Africa.</p>
        <p>But now the Sierra Leone mission is in trouble. By Friday night, more than 300 of the force's troops were  hostage, 4 were missing and presumed dead and rebels were riding in captured United Nations armored vehicles.</p>
        <p>That debacle and the hesitant response to it in Washington -- several days of teleconferences among officials of the Central Intelligence Agency, the Pentagon and the National Security Council but no action, no decisions -- demonstrate yet again that doing good in Africa takes more than good intentions.  Now the likelihood of deployment of even the modest force for Congo -- 500 monitors protected by 5,000 soldiers -- looks more distant, despite a formal agreement last week from the Congo leader, Laurent Kabila.</p>
        <p>The second track of the administration's Africa policy -- economic partnership -- was also delivering less than had been promised. Even as the House of Representatives approved a trade bill granting some new trading privileges to Africa, there were doubts whether many countries on the continent have the economic capacity to take advantage of it. And on the much-discussed subject of AIDS, the bill sent a singular snub: In the final version, bowing to American pharmaceutical companies, Congress dropped a provision intended to make AIDS drugs more affordable by lowering the licensing fees for African drug manufacturers.</p>
        <p>THE Clinton administration has experienced two defining moments in Africa, barely six months apart. The first was the slaughter of 17 American soldiers in Mogadishu, Somalia, in October 1993 and the dragging of one of the bodies  through the streets. The following spring, the administration remained largely silent as a genocide unfolded in Rwanda after the United States agreed to the removal of a United Nations military force there.</p>
        <p>After Mogadishu, President Clinton chose to shy away from risking such casualties or humiliation again; after Rwanda, he said genocide could not be tolerated again.</p>
        <p>But those are incompatible goals, and in its twilight months, the Clinton administration is strangled by its own constraints as it contemplates the options in places like Sierra Leone, Congo, Angola, Ethiopia, Eritrea and Zimbabwe.</p>
        <p>A collapse of the peacekeeping mission in Sierra Leone could portend far more than just the loss of a military effort in a small, desperate West African country. At stake,  some officials argue, is the prestige of the United States within the United Nations. The American representative there, Richard C. Holbrooke, has worked hard to fix the frayed United Nations-United States relationship, lobbying Congress to restore funding and urging foreign diplomats to understand the American political mood. Last week he was in Congo with United Nations colleagues trying to assess whether it is peaceful enough to send in the peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations, Mr. Holbrooke needs the 54 votes of African nations, many of whom have been  willing to suspend their disillusionment with Washington if the Sierra Leone and Congo peacekeeping missions can be made to work.</p>
        <p>But many also still resent the evident Western view that Africa deserves to be marginalized because its problems run so deep.  They argue that some hope should be gleaned from democratic elections here and there, from economic turn-arounds. They point to Mozambique, strengthened by investment from neighboring South Africa; to Kenya, where President Daniel arap Moi has taken steps that could reduce corruption; to Nigeria, whose new president, Olusegun Obasanjo, has assumed the mantle of a regional leader (although his troops, which Western countries wouldn't finance, pulled out of Sierra Leone after being roughed up by rebel thugs).</p>
        <p>Most important to hopes for peacekeeping, some African countries now have armies that are willing to take part in international forces on the continent. But it is also clear that African states are not capable of dealing with big crises like Congo or Sierra Leone. For these, they look to the United Nations, and thus the United States.</p>
        <p>The difficulty in Sierra Leone is that the big powers on the Security Council won't use their own forces, and this has left the United Nations  relying on frightened soldiers from less capable armies -- the kind who sometimes give up their armored personnel carriers when confronted  by teenagers with rifles at a roadblock.</p>
        <p>The minister of state for foreign affairs of Uganda, Amama Mbabazi, put it this way earlier this year: ''When it is Kosovo you are there in one minute and spend billions. When it's East Timor you are there. When it is Africa, there are all sorts of excuses.''</p>
        <p>So the basic problem of what to do about Africa remains, despite the administration's determination to get more involved. ''There are huge stakes'' if the Sierra Leone operation fails, said one official. ''We have to play pretty tough. Otherwise we are going to walk away yet again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
