<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Couple of Homeboys With the Gentrification Blues</title>
    <meta content="07BAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fort Greene (Nyc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Melendez, Eric J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D91738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Couple of Homeboys With the Gentrification Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chulo, 21, whose given name is Eric J Melendez, decries gentrification of Fort Greene section of Brooklyn, NYC, which is forcing black middle class to move out; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fort Greene, Brooklyn, has always been home to a black middle class, but the Ave belonged to the broke and the bus drivers. The playground belonged to the tough kids like Chulo, who wear flannel and sneakers and whiskers.</p>
        <p>That was before the Change. The Caucasian invasion, they call it; before the police and the block associations, the bars, cafes and the artistic bubbleheads. They and their money took over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fort Greene, Brooklyn, has always been home to a black middle class, but the Ave belonged to the broke and the bus drivers. The playground belonged to the tough kids like Chulo, who wear flannel and sneakers and whiskers.</p>
        <p>That was before the Change. The Caucasian invasion, they call it; before the police and the block associations, the bars, cafes and the artistic bubbleheads. They and their money took over.</p>
        <p>The Ave, as it is known to locals, is the block bounded by DeKalb, Lafayette and Carlton Avenues and Adelphi Street. In the middle is a playground. Along the perimeter are the new bars and the brownstones. Rows and rows of beautiful brownstones. One stop from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Gentrification doesn't just happen, said Chulo, 21, whose given name is Eric J. Melendez. These new people have to be helped, and he was one who helped them. Now he regrets it.</p>
        <p>A couple of Europeans opened cafes on the Ave not long ago, and Chulo was attracted to them. They were something different, and good-looking women went there. He now works hustling plates at a French joint called Chez Oskar. He keeps the neighborhood kids off the owner's back and out of her till. He makes $300 a week. He spends evenings at the bar. He now sees possibilities beyond the streets.</p>
        <p>''They been good to me,'' Chulo said. ''I been good to them.''</p>
        <p>But things have gone too far, as far as Chulo's concerned. There is a South African restaurant on the Ave named Madiba, owned by a white man. A few weeks ago, according to Chulo, some white South Africans started a ruckus there with the black employees and left, leaving a racial stink the air. ''It bugged me out,'' Chulo said the other afternoon at Madiba over a beer. ''I thought this was still Brooklyn.''</p>
        <p>His story is Brooklyn to the bone. His mother died young. His father is locked away. He bounced around in foster homes until he was adopted. He was 14 when his second mother died, 14 when his second father died and 14 when he moved into the playground on the Ave.</p>
        <p>The park became his home, the bench his mattress, the boys there his family. He drifted from $6-an-hour jobs to street-corner hustling until the white people came with a job and he got an apartment.</p>
        <p>It hasn't worked out so well for the others, Chulo said, shading his eyes as he sat on one of Madiba's outside tables. Last week, Chulo said, he watched the light go out in a second-floor apartment on the Ave and saw a friend come down the stairs with the last of his possessions.</p>
        <p>''I guess you ain't coming back here no more for real?'' Chulo asked.</p>
        <p>''Ain't no one to come back to,'' answered the friend, W. P.</p>
        <p>The young men sat in the U-Haul, under the street lamp, drinking Corona and smoking menthols.</p>
        <p>W.P. was moving to East New York, a neighborhood of vacant lots and cheaper rents and a growing number of economic outcasts from Fort Greene. The landlord had raised W.P.'s rent again. The liquor store closed for the same reason, and W.P. can't afford the drinks in the new bars.</p>
        <p>''Man, what happened to the old neighborhood?'' W.P. asked. He said it as if he'd been sneaked up on in the dark and beaten with a wet pillow.</p>
        <p>''Not even a good grocery no more,'' Chulo said.</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
