<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Five Keys to Turning Down the Heat</title>
    <meta content="KNI7" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DB1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Five Keys to Turning Down the Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Key factors for New York Knickerbockers in their playoff series against Miami Heat discussed; tables; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. HOUSTON'S OTHER SIDE</p>
        <p>Allan Houston eventually proved he could create shooting space against the long-armed Bruce Bowen in his second meeting against him this season, so his offense shouldn't be an issue. He shot 49.2 percent against the Heat -- including a remarkable 6 for 10 from 3-point range -- but Houston allowed Bowen and Dan Majerle to exploit his defense this year. The two Heat guards combined to hit 11 of 21 3-pointers. If Houston is to carry on his role as last year's hero against the Heat, he'll have to tighten up his lazy perimeter defense.</p>
        <p>2. SURVIVING THE MASH UNIT</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. HOUSTON'S OTHER SIDE</p>
        <p>Allan Houston eventually proved he could create shooting space against the long-armed Bruce Bowen in his second meeting against him this season, so his offense shouldn't be an issue. He shot 49.2 percent against the Heat -- including a remarkable 6 for 10 from 3-point range -- but Houston allowed Bowen and Dan Majerle to exploit his defense this year. The two Heat guards combined to hit 11 of 21 3-pointers. If Houston is to carry on his role as last year's hero against the Heat, he'll have to tighten up his lazy perimeter defense.</p>
        <p>2. SURVIVING THE MASH UNIT</p>
        <p>Fresh off his success against Toronto's Vince Carter, Latrell Sprewell is faced with a very different challenge. Without regular double-teams to come to his aid, Sprewell will have to guard the bulky Jamal Mashburn solo. In the past, Mashburn has given Sprewell problems in the post. Now, Mashburn is more of a threat to shoot over Sprewell than drive past him. As he did against Carter, Sprewell has to stay in Mashburn's air space. Sprewell, who shot 37 percent against the Heat this season, also has to find a way to create his own offense. One thing on the Knicks' side: Mashburn is prone to disappear in big games; Sprewell typically rises to the occasion.</p>
        <p>3. EWING BRAGGING RIGHTS</p>
        <p>Patrick Ewing has already established high expectations for his performance against his Georgetown buddy Alonzo Mourning by proclaiming himself every bit as great as the Heat's star center. It might be false bravado on Ewing's part, but it does seem as if Mourning is rattled and nervous when he plays against his mentor. Ewing's mental edge has served him well over the years, particularly in the deciding Game 5 of last year's playoff series. And last year, Ewing was in pain. This year, he is fresh, healthy and ready. If he can resist the temptation to try to take over every game, and focus on defense, rebounding and playing his role, Ewing could successfully dilute Mourning's impact.</p>
        <p>4. FINDING THE X-FACTOR</p>
        <p>In the tension that often exists in Heat-Knick affairs, there is usually one unlikely hero who emerges to help decide the outcome. Two years ago, Charlie Ward scrambled for loose balls, handed out 14 assists and delivered a pivotal 3-pointer in the deciding Game 5. Last year, Marcus Camby began to emerge as an impact player in the series. So far this postseason, Larry Johnson has been the X-factor with his big 3-pointers against Toronto. This series may come down to one 3-pointer, one loose ball or one blocked shot. In winning the last two of three straight playoff series with the Heat, the Knicks have usually found that little extra in their roster.</p>
        <p>5. WHAT'S THE POINT?</p>
        <p>The Knicks are preparing for Tim Hardaway (sprained foot) but aren't dismissing Anthony Carter. When healthy, Hardaway has devastated the Knicks over the years. This season, Hardaway shot just 40 percent on Charlie Ward and Chris Childs but delivered the big shots when the games grew tight. Hardaway played in all four regular-season games against the Knicks and led his team to a 3-1 record. In three games as the backup point guard, Carter hit just 1 of 11 shots. If Hardaway cannot play effectively, the Knicks may be on their way to the conference finals without much of a sweat in this four-of-seven-game series.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
