<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is This Marriage on the Rocks</title>
    <meta content="07WEISST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="61" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0D91339F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is This Marriage on the Rocks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip Weiss</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'This won't hurt. It'll feel like a cat's tongue,'' the research coordinator said, swabbing an exfoliant on the ribs near my heart, the same spot on which she'd drawn a little Magic Marker X a minute before. Soon several electrodes were dangling off my body, and the technicians left the room. My wife sat across from me, similarly wired, shoes off, legs gathered on her seat. I was a lot more nervous.</p>
        <p>Then the green light went on atop the television, and my wife said, ''All right,'' looking up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'This won't hurt. It'll feel like a cat's tongue,'' the research coordinator said, swabbing an exfoliant on the ribs near my heart, the same spot on which she'd drawn a little Magic Marker X a minute before. Soon several electrodes were dangling off my body, and the technicians left the room. My wife sat across from me, similarly wired, shoes off, legs gathered on her seat. I was a lot more nervous.</p>
        <p>Then the green light went on atop the television, and my wife said, ''All right,'' looking up.</p>
        <p>The issue was my failure to listen. My wife accused me of being adoring of her, like a character in light opera, rather than being truly attentive. She was her usual forceful self, and I danced away from her jabs before saying crisply that I'd registered her concern and would try to be more thoughtful.</p>
        <p>There was a knock on the door. Ten minutes of disagreement had flown by in a few seconds. Sybil Carr re, a director of the Family Research Lab, stood in the doorway. ''Define a word for us: 'Uxorious.' ''</p>
        <p>''Loving your wife too much,'' said my wife, who had thrown the word at me in criticism.</p>
        <p>My wife, Cynthia, and I had crossed the country to have an argument in Seattle because the University of Washington had gained an international reputation for the scientific assessment of relationships. The Love Lab, as everyone called this unit of the psychology department, had reportedly come up with tests so deadly that after staging a 10-minute discussion of the sort my wife and I had just enacted, it could predict with 90 percent accuracy if you were going to divorce.</p>
        <p>Before exposing the hidden tissue of my marriage to the Love Lab's X-rays, I had had to overcome some resistance in my household. My wife at first found it mortifying to open our inner lives to the scrutiny of scientists. Yet the idea appealed to our vanity. My wife and I thought we had a great relationship -- knock wood -- and (secretly) held our marriage over other people's. And, like the Love Lab itself, we were endlessly curious about marriage; it was our subject. We had often talked about Iris Murdoch and John Bayley's understanding, about Leonard Woolf's role in protecting Virginia's temperament. My wife was a keen critic of an institution into which she had twice been recruited. Marriage, she said, was advertised falsely -- the myth of enduring romantic love -- and its responsibilities sharply limited a woman's growth. Mistresshood, she said, offered a woman far more freedom. And so it was not long before Cynthia and I grew eager to pit our literary understanding of one of society's mysteries against the scientist's, on his turf.</p>
        <p>We met the professor, John Gottman, the night before our electronically monitored spat, in another of the University of Washington's petri dishes, a Motel-6-like chamber called the Apartment Lab. He walked in a few minutes late, his red wool vest draped over a purple shirt, and doffed a black leather seaman's cap to reveal a bright blue yarmulke. Gottman, a small man of 57, had a mane of silver hair, a neatly shaved beard, a high forehead, a potbelly and the most soulful eyes I had ever seen.</p>
        <p>He is a rabbi's son who trained as a mathematician at M.I.T., and rabbi and mathematician have reached an uneasy truce in him. Indeed, Gottman made his reputation by bringing hard science into a field -- the ordinary marriage -- that had long been the province of therapists.</p>
        <p>Other social scientists have made empirical forays into the analysis of romantic relationships, but Gottman is at the forefront thanks in large part to a paper he, Carr re and two others published in The Journal of Marriage and the Family in 1998. The study declared that the Love Lab was able to distinguish ''happy'' from ''unhappy'' couples through statistical analysis of observed interactions: disagreements lasted on average five seconds longer in the unhappy cases; successful wives were softer in their criticisms; successful husbands were more willing to accept their wives' influence.</p>
        <p>''Marriages will work to the extent that they provide for soothing of the male,'' the authors ventured. Females had to avoid critical ''start-up.'' And the males had to be willing to share power with females by validating their concerns. Gentleness was important to Gottman. In a recent best-selling book, he writes darkly of the ''four horsemen'' of divorce: criticism, defensiveness, contempt and stonewalling.</p>
        <p>I found him to be enormously personable. When my wife accused him of promoting an institution with a nearly 50 percent failure rate, he sidestepped deftly, saying that marriage conferred many healthful benefits. He had merely come up with primitive maps of the interior life of marriage, like the Portuguese maps of the world that Columbus used. ''With sea dragons,'' he added charmingly.</p>
        <p>After that exchange, Gottman shut the Apartment Lab door on us, and we made dinner under his remote observation. For an eerie hour and a half, three cameras made their insect noises, following us around the room, and microphones at our belts picked up our conversation. We were a little self-conscious. When my wife plucked a crumb of cheese off my sweater, she knew she would score well for grooming, she told me later.</p>
        <p>Gottman's technique was to pore over the resulting videotape, rating each spouse's ''facial affect'' from second to second according to a system that categorized a wide range of emotions -- from anger, defensiveness, contempt and belligerence to validation, humor, joy and surprise. Still, our jaded New York ironies (''Is this marital Apgar?'' I joked at one point) seemed to go over the heads of the West Coast audience. Later I'd see on the scientific coding chart that we each scored 0 for Play. But for Negativity, Cynthia scored 8 -- and I scored 12. Things didn't look promising.</p>
        <p>If the previous night's experiment was a fluid simulation of playing house, the morning offered a more structured encounter, one that was to be the official basis of our assessment. I got a foretaste of our conflict driving up Interstate 5 to the university when I exclaimed over the sudden appearance through the fog of Lake Washington. My wife had been talking. She went coldly silent and refused to finish her point.</p>
        <p>''But I was moved -- that's where Kurt Cobain killed himself,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''It was my turn. You're like that huge fat guy from 'Saturday Night Live' who killed himself because he didn't know what to do when the audience went home.''</p>
        <p>''Chris Farley,'' I said defeatedly, and parked outside a wood-frame building called Guthrie Annex 2.</p>
        <p>Gottman was on the second floor. We filled out questionnaires on marital satisfaction, then Gottman conducted an oral history, interviewing us about our marriage and our conflicts as we sat on a futon and cast wary glances at the office chairs on wired jiggle pads so reminiscent of electric chairs. For a while the conversation couldn't have been more pleasant: our highly romantic first meeting, our early years, our difficulties overcoming ethnic differences, our great intellectual rapport. But he pressed ahead for a fault line, and suddenly my wife was crying and the silvery guru in his cable-knit sweater and Day-Glo shirt and yarmulke was bent halfway out of his chair, asking where it hurt in the sweetest, most empathetic way you could imagine. The issue was my dismissal of my wife's insecurities as irrational, my failure to empathize when she felt inadequate, my inability to, as she put it, ''get down behind my eyeballs.''</p>
        <p>Gottman sat up with a glimmer of pride, like a fisherman whose reel has gone taut. We were asked to enter the Love Lab and discuss my failure of empathy, and I was to really listen this time. Electrodes were affixed. The door was closed.</p>
        <p>''You're uxorious in a Gilbert and Sullivan way,'' my wife said, ''because I don't feel like you hear me, you just love the sound of your voice. So I think, Who's he in love with?''</p>
        <p>''Cyn -- ''</p>
        <p>''No. Seriously. I'm saying this with complete sincerity. I feel like you have created an image which you adore and I do fuel that image but it's not me. I don't feel heard.''</p>
        <p>I often feel like a piker when my wife is describing our emotional terrain -- so I went for the high-minded dodge.</p>
        <p>''But don't you have an existential belief that no one listens to anybody?''</p>
        <p>''Dr. Gottman was listening to me.''</p>
        <p>''Huh?''</p>
        <p>''He wasn't telling me it was dumb; he wasn't telling me it wasn't true.''</p>
        <p>''But communication is a becoming, not a being.''</p>
        <p>''And I feel like if you do listen, but then you don't do what I ask you to do -- what is that?''</p>
        <p>My left flank was gone. I counterattacked. ''What about your dramatic arts, are they in play today?''</p>
        <p>The soft knock. Gottman came in with a troubled look. It appeared that something had gone terribly wrong.</p>
        <p>''I have to do some repair,'' he said. He turned gravely to my wife: ''You have a lot of real strong feelings about being married and not being married. I think you took a risk and tried to let Philip hear you. But I don't think he did.''</p>
        <p>He sat down on the futon, the rabbi in him now at the helm. ''I think this is very important,'' he said, gazing at my poor, fragile wife. ''I felt what you are feeling. I feel it's important for him to feel it.''</p>
        <p>Well, I felt awful. In the endless siege of issues that is marriage, this issue was a new one. My general policy in those cases is to ''mull'' it -- never to fold and agree. But now I was called upon to talk about it, in front of a bunch of prescriptive strangers. Gottman wanted to lock us in for another 10 minutes. My wife was to be less critical, me less defensive.</p>
        <p>Again we sat for two minutes of silence, again the green light went on over the television. This time the conversation went more smoothly, also more softly. I'm not a soft or sweet person, so it felt a little funny. But Gottman was greatly relieved. My wife had been tender this time, and I had seemed to actually hear.</p>
        <p>We all went out for lunch to a Thai restaurant -- my wife under protest, as she doesn't care for Thai food. The talk was spirited. Gottman told of the sacred cows he had taken on. He had enraged marital therapists by dismissing ''active listening'' -- in which partners parrot back each other's feelings -- as meaningless to a good marriage. He'd rankled fellow psychologists by studying ordinary people's issues rather than embarking on studies of schizophrenia or other disorders.</p>
        <p>After the meal, my wife and I got an hour off before we were to meet Gottman back at his offices. The rental car had a CD player, so we went disc shopping, then duly showed up at a second academic building, a short walk from the Love Lab.</p>
        <p>I glimpsed a garish orange leather chair, yet another in Gottman's spectrum of bright colors, before he gathered his papers and led us into a conference room with a somber look on his face. My heart began to sink. He sat down at a large table and shuffled the papers around, avoiding eye contact. My wife and I sat across from him and I looked at the photograph on the wall of Einstein riding a bicycle.</p>
        <p>First the good news. In the Apartment Lab, there was a lot of affection, rapport. Gottman liked the way my wife had flicked the cheese off my sweater. But when we came to Friday morning, Gottman moved through our questionnaires in a clinical way. ''Both of you were high on separateness rather than We-ness,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I want to know what our grade is,'' my wife said.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to get to that. Phil is more happily married than you are. His score is higher than yours in marital satisfaction. You frequently wish you'd never married. This being married/not being married issue is not an easy issue. There's some sadness, some fear on Philip's part.''</p>
        <p>Then there was our demeanor during the argument. Boy, had we done badly. In the course of our session, I'd chalked up 1 flash of Contempt, my wife 5. She had experienced 2 moments of Belligerence, 130 of Criticism (balanced by about 46 moments of Low Validation). I had 11 moments of Tension -- and 132 moments of Defensiveness. No Surprise, no Joy for either of us. Not one point for Humor. ''And your heartbeat went from 88 to 120,'' Gottman said to me. ''You became very aroused.''</p>
        <p>Gottman showed us a graph that plotted the data using mathematical equations that identified the ways that spouses influenced one another. The five intersections of our lines were ''steady states.'' Gottman said these were the planets of a couple's solar system -- emotional zones of gravitational pull, to which couples naturally returned. Our planets were not propitious. We had met three times in negative territory, either my wife being negative affect or myself being negative affect, or both of us being negative affect (and only twice had we met in dual positive). And the numbers revealed that our interaction had strong ''inertia'' to stay in those places. ''Neither of you is very flexible and neither one of you is drawn to a very positive place.''</p>
        <p>The only good news was that after Gottman had performed his ''intervention,'' we'd both improved. ''You started off quite affectionate and tender,'' he said approvingly to my wife. ''And Phil, your heart rate is lower. It's still aroused. This is not an easy discussion for you. But you're nowhere near as defensive.''</p>
        <p>''What's our grade?'' my wife demanded.</p>
        <p>Gottman coughed.</p>
        <p>''Zero to one hundred,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''If you ignore the relationship, there's a 20 percent chance of success.''</p>
        <p>Far to my left, I heard my wife laugh.</p>
        <p>''But if you work on it, it's more like 80 percent. You're capable of soothing one another and really connecting.''</p>
        <p>When I reached out to shake his hand, Gottman gave me a big consoling hug.</p>
        <p>We went back to the hotel and changed, to go over to the guru's house for dinner. I was in shock. I wondered if Gottman hadn't shone his light into deep fracture lines I was not even conscious of. The talk of my wife's dissatisfaction reminded me of coming across her journal a few weeks back (she'd left it open by the phone, so my snooping was legal under the Geneva Convention) and reading the line ''I can't believe how much I hate him sometimes.'' My wife had explained that away as a genuine but fleeting feeling. Now she held my hand in the car.</p>
        <p>''This doesn't change my opinion of our marriage one iota,'' she said. ''I know the surface of the relationship better than anybody. I know where the big old mountain is, where the crevices are. He's not telling me anything I didn't know. But it's always helpful to have someone validate them.''</p>
        <p>When we got to Gottman's house, a modern place with a view of Rainier, Gottman's wife, Julie, a psychologist herself, brought me wine. ''After your harrowing day,'' she threw in, and I felt he had clued her in on the wreckage. I sat apart from my wife at dinner, too prideful to even attempt to show off our intimacy to Gottman and his wife, who seemed to look on us as star-crossed. Once, when I said that my wife and I were hard-boiled about having our marriage scrutinized, Gottman corrected me. She's sensitive, he said. As if he knew her.</p>
        <p>The Gottmans had a warm home and a happy marriage. We-ness abounded. Their daughter did some kind of cartwheel in the next room. Gottman described a friend's gravestone that said, ''He Filled Our Lives With Laughter,'' and wondered if anyone would ever say that about him, and Julie held his hand, lovingly.</p>
        <p>My wife and I cared too much about self-awareness to indulge in such a fishing trip, I thought. Score another point for Contempt.</p>
        <p>We left right after dinner.</p>
        <p>My wife slept fine. I couldn't. At 5 o'clock I got up to walk around the Seattle harbor. The market opened and I had coffee and read through the thick file of papers Gottman had given us.</p>
        <p>When I came back my wife was in the bathtub and gave me a pep talk. ''He doesn't really listen,'' she said. ''He knew I didn't like Thai food and we went out for Thai food. I said that I don't like marriage and they read that as deep dissatisfaction. Well, dissatisfaction is one of the keys on my piano. I'm not satisfied with anything. Yes, I have a lot of problems with marriage. But I love our relationship.''</p>
        <p>''Well, what's the difference?''</p>
        <p>''Sort of the difference between religion and spirituality. I don't like the institution.''</p>
        <p>I asked her about the six ''Trues'' on the questionnaire as to whether she had considered divorce and such. Any more than four was a high predictor of divorce, Gottman said.</p>
        <p>'' 'Have you ever discussed divorce with a friend?' ''my wife said, recalling one question. ''I don't think I know a woman who hasn't discussed breaking up and leaving her husband with her girlfriends. Come on!''</p>
        <p>We were back on safe ground, pride. ''I'm insulted that you take so seriously the opinion of someone who's met us for an hour,'' my wife said. ''How many people like us do you think he has in his studies? He compares himself to Columbus. Well, the biggest mistake Columbus made was calling the Indians Indians because of his frame of reference. Gottman sees us as Indians.''</p>
        <p>In the afternoon my wife and I went for a hike in the foothills of the Cascades. By then I'd halfway recovered, and amid an unfamiliar terrain of giant firs and electric green rain-forest mosses, I was able to dissect the lab's paperwork for her.</p>
        <p>The heart of Gottman's method was a coding of not just our facial expressions but also our statements, performed by a young technician -- and we were sophisticated people in our 40's, who between ourselves had been in therapy a million years. The technician had, in my view, taken our honest dialogue for dissatisfaction. Looking at her code sheet, I wondered how she could have agreed with the statement ''Husband sounds bitter, hopeless or sad about his marriage.'' That reading was at the very least an interpretation. These interpretations were dressed up with hard science, but the only reference anyone had made to physiological data was to my heart rate. As Julie told me, ''When the heart rate is above 95, a person cannot cognitively process what they're hearing, consequently discussion is useless until they calm themselves down.'' Maybe. Still, the emphasis on calmness seemed very West Coast to me.</p>
        <p>Soothing was something that obviously worked for the Gottmans, but my wife and I embraced contention, volatility. The coder gave us low points on ''We-ness.'' What if self-knowledge and independence were higher gods than We-ness? What if you saw honest criticism from your partner as a key to your growth? There was something prescriptive and homiletic about Gottman's system. And they didn't even know the meaning of ''uxorious''! Moreover, the Love Lab showed a stunning indifference to a couple's sex life. There had been almost no questions about sex.</p>
        <p>In no time, my wife and I had successfully reduced the Love Lab's findings to a pathetic mound of feathers. Even so, I knew I was still racking up big defensive points.</p>
        <p>Was the psychologist alive to something I had no inkling of? Had his machines detected some creeping ailment that would knock us apart in two or three or four years, right on schedule? Some vital measure that made everything we said so much pretentious New York cross talk?</p>
        <p>''You know, this has helped our marriage,'' my wife declared, stopping on the trail on the way down. ''I'm damned if I'm going to get divorced. I don't want him to be vindicated.''</p>
        <p>We flew back early the next morning. At check-in, my wife asked to be seated separately from me so she could lie down. But the clerk said, ''I'll have to seat you next to someone else,'' and my wife said, ''Well, then, I'll sit next to him.''</p>
        <p>I counted that as a victory till the plane was in the air and my wife moved to an empty row toward the rear. Now and then I looked back, longingly.</p>
        <p>Philip Weiss is a frequent contributor to the magazine. His last article was about Fred C. Trump.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Philip Weiss is a frequent contributor to the magazine. His last article was about Fred C. Trump.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
