<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Molly Confer, John Aboud III</title>
    <meta content="07CONF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONFER, MOLLY BRIDGET (MOLLY BRIDGET ABOUD)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABOUD, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DB1738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Molly Confer, John Aboud III</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Molly Bridget Confer and John Aboud III were married yesterday by the Rev. Dr. Otis Young at First Plymouth Congregational Church in Lincoln, Neb.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is the deputy editor of Teen People Online, the America Online site of Teen People magazine. She is a daughter of Laurie and Rodney Confer of Lincoln. Her mother is a docent for the Sheldon Art Gallery, the University of Nebraska's art museum. Her father is managing partner in Knudsen Berkheimer, a law firm in Lincoln.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Molly Bridget Confer and John Aboud III were married yesterday by the Rev. Dr. Otis Young at First Plymouth Congregational Church in Lincoln, Neb.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is the deputy editor of Teen People Online, the America Online site of Teen People magazine. She is a daughter of Laurie and Rodney Confer of Lincoln. Her mother is a docent for the Sheldon Art Gallery, the University of Nebraska's art museum. Her father is managing partner in Knudsen Berkheimer, a law firm in Lincoln.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, also 27, is a co-founder and co-editor of ModernHumorist.com, a Web site based in New York. His parents, Mr. and Mrs. Aboud Jr., live in Richmond, Va. His mother, Jo Ann Aboud, is the office manager for his father's business, Organization Dimensions, a management consulting firm.</p>
        <p>The couple got to know each other in October 1992, when they were in the same literature class at Harvard University. Ms. Confer recalled that she felt intimidated by the material. But Mr. Aboud, who spoke frequently in class, would encourage Ms. Confer by saying, ''Just to expand on Molly's point. . . .'' Ms. Confer remembers thinking, ''That's really sweet.''</p>
        <p>But she refused Mr. Aboud's invitations to dinner. And another obstacle, at least for Mr. Aboud, was a longstanding campus face-off. He was a writer for Harvard Lampoon and she was an editor at The Crimson, the daily student newspaper and a rival publication. ''The people there are staggeringly uncool,'' Mr. Aboud said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he reasoned, if he wrote funny articles for Fifteen Minutes, The Crimson's weekly magazine, he might maintain his own loyalties while still being able to woo Ms. Confer. As it happened, Mr. Aboud considered Ms. Confer a superb editor. ''I never tore his work apart, '' she recalled.</p>
        <p>Finally, Ms. Confer accepted one of Mr. Aboud's numerous movie invitations. They went to see ''The Joy Luck Club,'' a family drama, and cringed. ''We bonded over our mutual hatred of sentiment,'' Mr. Aboud said.</p>
        <p>In 1996, after the Lampoon writer and the Crimson editor had graduated with bachelor's degrees in history and literature, they moved in together in Manhattan. By May 1999, Mr. Aboud was ready to propose. Ms. Confer was tickled to find a note posted on their apartment door: ''Molly, won't you say 'si' to our Festival Cubano?'' Below it was a handwritten menu describing dishes, including fried plantains.</p>
        <p>As she entered, Mr. Aboud said: ''I have good news and I have bad news. The bad news is the ginger-sherry pork roast will take another half hour. The good news is I would love for you to marry me.'' He then presented her with a ring. Ms. Confer was shocked. ''I made a bizarre, almost barking sound,'' she recalled.</p>
        <p>Still, the gap between Lampoon and Crimson remains. Mr. Aboud jokes that he may have to divide the church in Nebraska into a Lampoon side and a Crimson side. Ms. Confer said, ''Our friends are already calling it the Rumble on the Prairie.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
