<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burt Lancaster's Brawny Melancholy</title>
    <meta content="07MARI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lancaster, Burt (1913-94)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDD1039F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burt Lancaster's Brawny Melancholy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marin, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Marin article appraises Burt Lancaster's career as movie actor; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN many ways, Burt Lancaster is the antithesis of the modern leading man. Today's young actors build themselves the bodies of athletes. He was an athlete who built himself into an actor. They come from the schools of soft knocks (Harvard, Yale). He graduated from De Witt Clinton High School, in Hell's Kitchen. They went to the circus. He was in the circus.</p>
        <p>Lancaster was both of his time -- a golden-age Movie Star -- and way ahead of it. As an independent producer, he helped sabotage the studio system that made him, at one time, the highest-paid actor in the world. And yet, when he died, in 1994, at the age of 80, there was no funeral or memorial service. That was his choice. But there wasn't much in the way of public epitaph, either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN many ways, Burt Lancaster is the antithesis of the modern leading man. Today's young actors build themselves the bodies of athletes. He was an athlete who built himself into an actor. They come from the schools of soft knocks (Harvard, Yale). He graduated from De Witt Clinton High School, in Hell's Kitchen. They went to the circus. He was in the circus.</p>
        <p>Lancaster was both of his time -- a golden-age Movie Star -- and way ahead of it. As an independent producer, he helped sabotage the studio system that made him, at one time, the highest-paid actor in the world. And yet, when he died, in 1994, at the age of 80, there was no funeral or memorial service. That was his choice. But there wasn't much in the way of public epitaph, either.</p>
        <p>In the final episode of ''Seinfeld,'' Kramer looks up into the sky and says with even more than his usual brio: ''There's something in the air. I can feel it!'' To which Jerry snidely retorts, ''You know you're turning into Burt Lancaster?'' The man who inspired such awe and trembling had become a punch line.</p>
        <p>A decade after his last appearance on the screen, attention is being paid. Kate Buford's new biography, ''Burt Lancaster: An American Life'' (Knopf), wants to reclaim relevancy for its protagonist in all kinds of ways: as actor, indie producer, possible bisexual. More straightforward proof of Lancaster's lifetime achievement, as they say on the awards shows, is on view at the Walter Reade Theater through May 18, in the Film Society of Lincoln Center's retrospective, ''American Dreamer: Burt Lancaster.'' Both the biography and filmography are overdue tributes to what Vincent Canby once called ''Mr. Lancaster's remarkable -- though not often remarked about -- career.''</p>
        <p>In a way, Lancaster's remarkable body and equally energetic mind did him the disservice of lasting too long. His cap-toothed charisma and immaculate diction seemed square once mumbling method men like James Dean and Marlon Brando changed the game. After his years as a prime specimen of hunkus Americanus -- Pauline Kael's cutting coinage -- the movies didn't quite know what to do with him, nor he with them. The nadir on this score may have been his unfortunate foray into the disaster genre, ''Airport'' (1970), justifiably spoofed in ''Airplane!''</p>
        <p>But he had an impressively long run, documented in the Film Society's series, from his debut in ''The Killers'' (1946) and the even more noir follow-up, ''Criss Cross'' (1947), the swashbuckling of ''The Crimson Pirate'' (1952), ''From Here to Eternity'' (1953), the Indians-and-cowboy reversal ''Apache'' (1954) and the double whammy of ''Sweet Smell of Success'' and ''Gunfight at OK Corral'' (both 1957), then ''Elmer Gantry'' (1960), which won him his first and only Oscar.</p>
        <p>The 60's and 70's -- Lancaster's middle period -- were less sure-footed. The cerebral ''Birdman of Alcatraz'' (1962) gave way to ill-advised experiments with facial hair and neckwear. A bid for so-called international stardom was bracketed by two pictures directed by Luchino Visconti, ''The Leopard'' (1963) and ''The Conversation Piece'' (1974). Out of these years came many would-be classics and one true one, ''The Swimmer'' (1968), an underrated adaptation of John Cheever's short story of the same name.</p>
        <p>Late Lancaster started with ''Atlantic City'' (1980) and peaked with ''Local Hero'' (1983). These lion-in-winter years are how many younger moviegoers first got a load of him: a big, white-haired, wild-eyed geezer or, as Ms. Buford more kindly suggests, ''like a famous uncle who was once a great athlete.'' But as Ms. Buford so extensively demonstrates, he was much more than that.</p>
        <p>The fourth of five children, Burton Stephen Lancaster was born in 1913. His father worked at the post office, sang Irish songs and took the kids to the zoo and Coney Island. His mother went from black-Irish beauty to 250-pound terror. They lived on the second floor of a narrow brownstone in East Harlem. After high school, young Burt joined the circus with his gym buddy and lifelong crony, Nick Cravat. Lancaster was good, not great, on the horizontal bar, carneys later recalled. A marriage in 1935 to a female acrobat also ended in 1935. World War II beckoned, and the U.S.O. When the war ended, he went West and made ''The Killers,'' Richard Siodmak's hard-boiled elaboration on Ernest Hemingway's story about a washed-up boxer with a price on his head.</p>
        <p>''Picture met with really great reception and seems pretty close to what we dreamed about,'' the producer, Mark Hellinger, cabled him after the first press screening. ''I'm afraid you're destined to be a big star, you poor guy.''</p>
        <p>Picture was also the ideal Lancaster showpiece. It played to his two sides: explosive physicality and melancholy. Three sides if you count mixing it up with Ava Gardner. (Jackie Bone, Lancaster's companion for many years, once described watching him on a golf course, in repose, and thinking, ''there is one unhappy man.'') In ''Criss Cross'' he was again a good guy doomed to a bad end, if a little too commanding and charismatic a presence to convincingly play a loser. As Lancaster strides through an early scene in the movie, the bartender mistakes him for a G-man liquor inspector, a ''checker.'' Disappointed, a female barfly gives Lancaster a surprised once-over, purring, ''Swell looking, nicely built man like that, a checker!''</p>
        <p>THE 6-foot-1 build would remain nice, lovingly preserved and on display for many years to come. Hard to believe the lean, and very mean, warrior hero of ''Apache'' was being played by a 40-year-old man. In the new Technicolor print at Lincoln Center, the contrast between his greasepaint Indian skin and blazing blue eyes almost looks like a special effect.</p>
        <p>''Burt Lancaster is 52,'' Cheever wrote in a letter when ''The Swimmer'' went into production in 1967. ''Lithe, comely and somewhat disfigured by surgical incisions and he looks both young and old, masterful and tearful.'' Lancaster could barely swim when he took the part of Ned Merrill, a Connecticut suburbanite with an unspoken secret who swims home through his neighbors' pools as the weather -- and neighbors -- get colder and darker. But he trained scrupulously (as he had for ''Jim Thorpe: All-American''), hiring the coach of the U.C.L.A. men's water polo team because he didn't want to ''insult'' real smimmers in the audience.</p>
        <p>He never tried to disown the action-man stuff but was always eager to play against type, on the screen and off. By 1947, he already had his own production company, Norma Productions (named after his second wife). Work with the producer Harold Hecht led to a new entity, Hecht-Lancaster. Their partnership contributed to the seismic power shift from the studios to the actors or, more accurately, their agents. Lancaster's agent was the godfather himself, MCA's Lew Wasserman. With Mr. Wasserman advising and wetting his beak, Hecht and Lancaster made serious, sometimes political films in black and white while living large in offices decorated with El Grecos and adjustable waterfalls.</p>
        <p>Their big-screen version of Paddy Chayefsky's television drama ''Marty'' swept the 1956 Oscars -- the same year Lancaster starred in ''Trapeze,'' a sentimental ode to the big top co-starring Tony Curtis. The two movies might as well have been made on different planets.</p>
        <p>These two stars had worked together before: Mr. Curtis had an uncredited bit part as a gigolo in ''Criss Cross.'' But the collaboration people remember is ''Sweet Smell of Success,'' produced by Hecht-Hill-Lancaster. (James Hill, a writer, producer and world-class hanger-on, made the company a troika.) Too gimlet-eyed for moviegoers and many critics when it came out, ''Sweet Smell'' ruthlessly unmasked the unholy alliance between journalism and publicity at a time when people did not speak of such things. We're still in that time, come to think of it.</p>
        <p>The principal characters are J. J. Hunsecker, an all-powerful columnist modeled on Walter Winchell, and Sidney Falco, the ambitious press agent in the great man's thrall. Lancaster is in full cerebral mode as Hunsecker, physically almost inert, while Curtis dances around him. In many of the most famous scenes, he is sitting down, staring up through glasses smeared with vaseline to further fog the windows to a darkened soul. Based on a novella by Ernest Lehmann, a former press agent who had been one of Winchell's gofers, the screenplay was taken to the next level of crackling cynicism by Clifford Odets. Odets, in full ''Barton Fink'' mode, was on his last legs career-wise but still able to dash off on-set rewrites like Falco's ''the cat's in the bag and the bag's in the river.''</p>
        <p>Almost every line in the movie seems memorable, either because of the words or their delivery. Hunsecker's exultation, ''I love this dirty town.'' Falco announcing, ''From now on the best of everything is good enough for me,'' and, to his naive secretary: ''This is life. Get used to it.'' Originally, the partners had thought of Orson Welles for Hunsecker until Lancaster said, ''What about me?'' It wasn't a stretch. He had already become a maniacal control freak, with a reputation as ''one of the rudest individuals in Hollywood,'' Look magazine reported in 1953. He womanized -- and manized, if we are to believe the rumors. His mean streak could reduce huge stars to tears. He supposedly made his friend and fellow ex-acrobat Kirk Douglas cry by making fun of the lifts in his shoes.</p>
        <p>ALEXANDER MACKENDRICK, imported from England to direct ''Sweet Smell,'' bore the brunt of Lancaster's rages. One choice incident that Mackendrick relates in Ms. Buford's book:</p>
        <p>''We'd been drinking a little. Burt started shouting at me -- and he's scary. Then he came at me across the room with that coiled-spring animal energy, like a panther, and vaulted over a sofa in one of the most graceful movements I've ever seen, [as if] to attack me. I stood up and said, 'No, Burt,' and he stopped. That took every atom of performance possible. The reason I had the strength was that just as he came across the sofa I thought, 'He's beautiful!' ''</p>
        <p>It was a turning point. '' 'Sweet Smell of Success' destroyed us all,'' Mackendrick said near the end of his life. Lancaster was never quite that beautiful or powerful again, even though he had yet to turn down the unprecedented offer of $1 million for ''Ben-Hur'' and was still three years away from his Oscar.</p>
        <p>Louis Malle got a taste of Bad Burt two decades later when he cast him as the broken-down old gangster in ''Atlantic City.'' But this time, Burt was in no position to be hurdling furniture. In 1980, Lancaster was 63, and his big, broad style could not have been more out of style. Early requests by Malle to tone down line readings drew tantrums. ''O.K., we'll do it the way the little froggie wants it, and then we'll do it the way it should be done,'' Lancaster railed on the set one day, in front of the director. To his credit, he realized Malle was right, modulated his performance and was nominated for an Oscar.</p>
        <p>How sad that the Buford biography has to play the sex card to validate Lancaster's currency -- as if bisexuality makes him modern. The naked rear-view still from ''The Swimmer'' seems like a fairly obvious and cheesy plea for publicity. You want current? Watch the movies. There is no sadder statement about suburbia than ''The Swimmer,'' no inmate in HBO's ''Oz'' as complex as the Birdman, and no villain more hep than J. J. Hunsecker.</p>
        <p>FILM Rick Marin is a Style reporter for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 21, 2000, Sunday  An article on May 7 about Burt Lancaster referred incorrectly to the location of DeWitt Clinton High School, from which he graduated. It moved from Hell's Kitchen to the Bronx in 1929, before his senior year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on May 7 about Burt Lancaster referred incorrectly to the location of DeWitt Clinton High School, from which he graduated. It moved from Hell's Kitchen to the Bronx in 1929, before his senior year.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rick Marin is a Style reporter for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
