<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/1411 Broadway, Between 39th and 40th Street; In Changing Garment District, a Fashion Holdout</title>
    <meta content="07COMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trizechahn Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holusha, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDE1039F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/1411 Broadway, Between 39th and 40th Street; In Changing Garment District, a Fashion Holdout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holusha, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TrizecHahn, which bought office tower at 1411 Broadway in Manhattan, is intent on maintaining building as center for clothing trade; says as more buildings in changing Garment District are being converted to general office use, value of having concentration of showrooms in one building is allowing company to charge premium rents to tenants who want to be near heart of action; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE changes that have taken place in the Garment Center in recent years have been so broad and so swift -- a recent survey found that less than half the space is now occupied by apparel concerns -- that, with a nod to the revitalized neighborhood to the north, some real estate executives have begun referring to the area from 35th Street to 41st Street to the west of the Avenue of the Americas as Times Square South.</p>
        <p>But the managers of the building at 1411 Broadway, between 39th and 40th Street, say they are intent on maintaining it as a center for the clothing trade. Indeed, they say that as more buildings in the area are being converted to general office use, the value of having a concentration of showrooms in one building is allowing them to charge premium rents to tenants who want to be near the heart of the action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE changes that have taken place in the Garment Center in recent years have been so broad and so swift -- a recent survey found that less than half the space is now occupied by apparel concerns -- that, with a nod to the revitalized neighborhood to the north, some real estate executives have begun referring to the area from 35th Street to 41st Street to the west of the Avenue of the Americas as Times Square South.</p>
        <p>But the managers of the building at 1411 Broadway, between 39th and 40th Street, say they are intent on maintaining it as a center for the clothing trade. Indeed, they say that as more buildings in the area are being converted to general office use, the value of having a concentration of showrooms in one building is allowing them to charge premium rents to tenants who want to be near the heart of the action.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, the manufacturing part of the industry has left New York,'' said Douglas Winshall, senior vice president for the northeast region for TrizecHahn, a Toronto-based company that purchased the property in 1997. ''But the showrooms and marketing department and other front-office functions still need to be here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Winshall said that consolidation in the apparel industry, with larger companies driving smaller competitors out of business or absorbing them, had increased the value of buildings considered to be at the heart of the district. ''This is an industry building,'' he said. ''There is a value to both the landlord and tenants to operating it as a dedicated garment-industry building.''</p>
        <p>He said that the principal advantage is that when buyers for retail chains arrive in New York for seasonal purchasing sessions, they have to go to only a few locations to see a full line of wares.</p>
        <p>''It is imperative that we be located here,'' said Bobby Reiss, chief executive officer of Worldwide Apparel Resources, a designer of clothing sold under private labels and a tenant at 1411 Broadway. ''When retailers come to town they want to go to one general location. If you are in a different part of town you could be eliminated from the schedule.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiss said the principal Garment District buildings are known worldwide in the apparel business. ''If you are in Hong Kong or Shanghai and you mention 1411 Broadway or 1407 Broadway,'' he said, ''people know what you are talking about.''</p>
        <p>Joe Harary, who rents 40,000 square feet at 1411 Broadway for his company, Jacques Moret, a producer of women's sportswear and underwear, said: ''This is the heart of the Garment District today. This is a location we have aspired to be in and where I hope we can stay.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Harary said that Jacques Moret uses most of its space for showrooms and offices, with only a small amount devoted to sewing samples for display to buyers.</p>
        <p>The influx of general office-space users such as advertising agencies, law firms and Internet-related businesses has only increased the importance of the major buildings identified with the apparel business, said Neil Weiss, the chairman of KSK International, another garment-industry tenant at 1411 Broadway.</p>
        <p>''Places like this are more important than ever to the remaining high-end apparel companies,'' he said. ''Buyers have told me they like the idea of going into a few buildings and seeing all the vendors.''</p>
        <p>David Winokur, executive vice president of Winokur Realty, a broker specializing in the Garment District, said that the addition of new types of tenants was pushing rent levels higher. He said that rents in the area were typically in the mid-$30's per square foot annually, ''and going up from there.''</p>
        <p>HE said he felt that TrizecHahn's decision to market 1411 Broadway as an apparel center, despite the industry's overall decline, made sense. ''I've always thought that the movement of other tenants into the area would make the premier garment buildings even stronger,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Barbara Randall, executive director of the Fashion Center Business Improvement District, said that a recent survey confirmed that apparel tenants had fallen below 50 percent of the space occupied in the district.</p>
        <p>''There has been a huge change in just the last two years,'' she said. ''The change in Times Square has made the real estate community willing to look here as a place to locate their clients.''</p>
        <p>As a result, she said, apparel companies are consolidating in specific buildings, naming 525, 530 and 550 Seventh Avenue as core garment buildings in addition to 1411 and 1407 Broadway. And, she said, some design companies are moving their showrooms to side-street locations that were once populated by suppliers.</p>
        <p>''The building at 205 West 39th Street is all showroom now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winshall said TrizecHahn is not concentrating on luring apparel-industry tenants to much of its 8.5 million square feet of property in the New York metropolitan area, including buildings in Stamford, Conn., and Jersey City. He said the location of 1411 Broadway and the characteristics of the 1.145 million-square-foot structure made it suitable for such an approach.</p>
        <p>''This building is 30 years old, but it is the newest in the area by 20 years,'' he said. ''Unlike most Garment Center buildings it has rectangular floor plates, with 40,000-square-foot floors in the base and 14,000 square feet in the tower.''</p>
        <p>He said that a 200,000-square-foot TrizecHahn building at 1460 Broadway, at 41st Street, that had been largely occupied by textile tenants was being converted to office use because of its proximity to Times Square.</p>
        <p>''We went out and found Skadden, Arps which is going to use it as a back office for 4 Times Square,'' he said, referring to the law firm that is one of the principal tenants of a new building at the intersection of 42nd Street and Broadway. Mr. Winshall said he had been able to empty out 100,000 square feet of the building by July 1998, with the firm scheduled to take over the rest of the building as leases expire over the succeeding seven years.</p>
        <p>Another building in the TrizecHahn portfolio, the 600,000-square-foot structure at 111 West 40th Street, is similarly being converted from largely textile-industry use to general office space, to take advantage of its location across the Avenue of the Americas from Bryant Park. It has been renumbered as 1065 Avenue of the Americas to emphasize its location and it has attracted tenants such as Yahoo, the big Internet referral service, which has rented 50,000 square feet for its New York headquarters.</p>
        <p>''We still have some textile/apparel tenants in the building, but it's about 60-40 office to apparel now,'' Mr. Winshall said. ''And we're moving that toward 80-20.''</p>
        <p>Tenants at 1411 Broadway run the gamut from Jones Apparel Group, which occupies 200,000 square feet, to small producers that have a 1,000-square-foot showroom, said Bruce J. Crawford, TrizecHahn's vice president for leasing in the northeast region.</p>
        <p>The building has more than 200 tenants  who are constantly expanding, shrinking, coming and going, which makes for a lot of work, Mr. Crawford said. He said a tenant with a 1,000-square-foot showroom might suddenly need to double that space if it develops a hot line of clothing.</p>
        <p>''If we have a 1,000-square-foot tenant who needs 2,000 square feet, we try to move him to where we have space,'' he said. ''Most want to expand showrooms, which does not involve a lot of capital cost.''</p>
        <p>He said there are typically 40 new lease transactions a year involving about 175,000 square feet of space. ''It's not like you are locking things up forever,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
