<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ordinary People, Extraordinary Crimes</title>
    <meta content="507SPOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="59" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPOTLIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Margolis, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tabish, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Sandy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcveigh, Timothy James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franklin, Joseph Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Resendiz, Angel Maturino</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MugShots (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDB1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ordinary People, Extraordinary Crimes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MARGOLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Margolis, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Court TV's criminal biography series MugShots; program has featured Rick Tabish, Sandy Murphy, Timothy McVeigh and Joseph Paul Franklin; profile of Angel Maturino Resendiz will have its premiere this week; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''HOW are you supposed to act if you've killed people?'' wonders Joseph Paul Franklin on a segment of Court TV's criminal biography series ''MugShots'' (Mondays through Thursdays at 7 p.m.). ''You supposed to have blood dripping from your mouth? Fangs?'' Mr. Franklin is clean- cut, almost genial, even when videotaped through a plate glass partition on death row. He could be your friendly neighborhood mailman or trusted accountant. In fact he was responsbile for more than 20 murders in 12 states, targeting mostly mixed race couples. Two of his victims who survived were Vernon Jordan, then president of the Urban League, and Larry Flynt, the publisher of Huslter magazine. It is the very ordinariness of Mr. Franklin, the absence of fangs, that makes his ''MugShots'' segment so eerie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''HOW are you supposed to act if you've killed people?'' wonders Joseph Paul Franklin on a segment of Court TV's criminal biography series ''MugShots'' (Mondays through Thursdays at 7 p.m.). ''You supposed to have blood dripping from your mouth? Fangs?'' Mr. Franklin is clean- cut, almost genial, even when videotaped through a plate glass partition on death row. He could be your friendly neighborhood mailman or trusted accountant. In fact he was responsbile for more than 20 murders in 12 states, targeting mostly mixed race couples. Two of his victims who survived were Vernon Jordan, then president of the Urban League, and Larry Flynt, the publisher of Huslter magazine. It is the very ordinariness of Mr. Franklin, the absence of fangs, that makes his ''MugShots'' segment so eerie.</p>
        <p>Exploring why seemingly ordinary people commit extraordinary crimes is the mission of ''MugShots,'' a spinoff from another Court TV documentary series, ''Crime Stories.'' ''Viewers of 'Crime Stories' came away with the same types of questions,'' said Art Bell, Court TV's executive vice president for programming and marketing. ''What makes someone who seems so normal become a killer? What makes a killer tick? On 'MugShots' we try to show that these people had family and friends; they had biographies.''</p>
        <p>''MugShots'' went on the air in January with a segment on the Boston Strangler. Other one-hour episodes have profiled people like the Branch Davidian leader David Koresh and the Teamster president Jimmy Hoffa. This week a new segment has its premiere. Its subject is Angel Maturino Resendi, known as the Railway Killer, who stalked and murdered at least nine people beginning in 1998. The only thing his victims have in common was that their homes were accessible by train. During a pretrial court appearance shown on ''MugShots,'' Mr. Resendiz was unfailingly polite, answering the judge's questions with demure yes sir's and no sir's. No fangs here either.</p>
        <p>Mr. Resendiz's trial was due to begin last week, wit Court TV reporting the opening statements, closing arguments, verdict and penalty phase. The network's Web site features daily commentary on the trial and additional information about the case.</p>
        <p>Trial coverage during daytime, documentary coverage during prime tie and continuous Web access are the embodiment of what Mr. Bell calls ''Judgment days, sleepless nights,'' the network's new positioning. This model was introduced in March with the showing of ''Ted Binion: Murder Las Vegas Style'' on ''MugShots.'' Lonnie Binion (known as Ted), a Nevada casino millionaire, was murdered in 1998 - or was he? His accused killers, Sandy Murphy and Rick Tabish, maintain that he died of an accidental drug overdose. ''MugShots'' broadcast the segment the same week Ms. Murphy and Mr. Tabish went on trial. During the day, Court TV provides live coverage of the trial, while its Web site offers features like videotapes of the crime scene taken by Ms. Murphy the day after the alleged murder, and articles with titles like ''Binion Died, Murphy Cried, but Were the Tears Real?''</p>
        <p>Many ''MugShots'' subjects, including Mr. Koresh and Timothy McVeigh, have been exhaustively reported on elsewhere. Why rehash their stories yet again? ''We'll only do a well-known subject if we have something new to offer,'' said Doc Jarden, vice president for documentaries and specials at Court TV. ''With McVeigh, we had access to prison letters and photographs that no one else had.'' And, as with all segments, the goal is to understand the criminal, not merely document the crime.</p>
        <p>''We're after the why,'' said Jonathan Greene, who wrote, directed, and produced the Resendiz episode. ''It's investigation versus just storytelling.''</p>
        <p>The stated objective of ''MugShots'' may be to understand the criminal mind, but the producers rarely shy away from the lurid, making generous use of dramatizations and crime-scene footage, the camera panning slowing across bloody sheets or knives. Narration tends to be hard-boiled: ''Coming up,'' in tones the narrator of the Binion segment, just before a break, ''we'll meet the woman police say snuffed out the heir to the Binion fortune.''</p>
        <p>Above all, the producers are always on the lookout for what Mr. Bell called ''the Hannibal Lecter moment,'' when the camera peers directly into the eyes of a killer. Those eyes inevitably look rather ordinary; sometimes they even seem familiar.</p>
        <p>SPOTLIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
