<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>. . . and a Quiet Closing for a Crossroads of the Palate</title>
    <meta content="07CHIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CHELSEA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sam Chinita (Nyc Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DB1738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>. . . and a Quiet Closing for a Crossroads of the Palate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sam Chinita, restaurant at 19th Street and Eighth Avenue opened in 1970 by four Cuban exiles of Chinese descent, closes suddenly and without explanation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If New York is a mosaic, few places exemplify that spirit better than Sam Chinita at 19th Street and Eighth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which was opened in 1970 by four Cuban exiles who happened to be Chinese, served traditional Spanish food alongside familiar Chinese specials in a 1950's American diner on an strip that has since become a center of gay life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If New York is a mosaic, few places exemplify that spirit better than Sam Chinita at 19th Street and Eighth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which was opened in 1970 by four Cuban exiles who happened to be Chinese, served traditional Spanish food alongside familiar Chinese specials in a 1950's American diner on an strip that has since become a center of gay life.</p>
        <p>''It was part of what I call the patchwork quilt of Chelsea,'' said Tim Gay, the local Democratic district leader. ''Where else could you get fried plantains and egg drop soup in one order? Or fried pork chops and brown rice?''</p>
        <p>But after serving its last order of mofongo (mashed green plantains), the diner abruptly closed a few weeks ago.</p>
        <p>It was not immediately clear why the restaurant had closed. The owner could not be reached for comment, but Catherine Krickellas, a Brooklyn resident who owns the property, said of him, ''I guess he got older and wanted to retire.'' Others in the neighborhood suggested that rising rents may have also played a part.</p>
        <p>Steve Antonapos, the owner of the Galaxy Cafe next door, has already signed a lease for the 1,500-square-foot space and plans to raze the stainless steel structure to build a Greek restaurant with a mahogany and brick facade. ''The walls and ceilings are coming down,'' he said last weekend after inspecting the space.</p>
        <p>News that the diner might be torn down brought moans from residents and elected officials.</p>
        <p>''With its metal streamline looks and classic diner interior, this building has long been a neighborhood landmark,'' Councilwoman Christine C. Quinn and State Senator Thomas K. Duane wrote in a letter to Mr. Antonapos. ''Its loss would certainly be greatly regretted.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Zilka, president of the American Diner Museum in Providence, R.I., said the structure is one of 20 traditional diners left in Manhattan. He pointed out that old diners are often restored and suggested that this structure might be worth as much as $100,000.</p>
        <p>Some residents described the closing as emblematic of the area's gentrification. ''When I came here, I couldn't get a good meal,'' said Edward Kirkland, a member of Community Board 4, who has lived in the area for 37 years. ''Now I can't get a cheap one.''</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CHELSEA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
