<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Knicks-Heat: Battle Lines Are Set, but First, a Group Hug, Please</title>
    <meta content="07ARAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD61538F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Knicks-Heat: Battle Lines Are Set, but First, a Group Hug, Please</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times humorous column on history of previous playoff series between New York Knickerbockers and Miami Heat (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WELCOME to another installment of the National Basketball Association's premier rivalry, our main playoff event. New York versus Miami, brunchtime basketball served today with your bagels, rated PG (for Please, Guys, we need the ratings).</p>
        <p>Herewith, our historical primer on the Knicks-Heat series, now into its fourth hit season, based on interviews over the previous week with players and coaches from both teams, edited by N.B.A. Entertainment and narrated by Ahmad Rashad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WELCOME to another installment of the National Basketball Association's premier rivalry, our main playoff event. New York versus Miami, brunchtime basketball served today with your bagels, rated PG (for Please, Guys, we need the ratings).</p>
        <p>Herewith, our historical primer on the Knicks-Heat series, now into its fourth hit season, based on interviews over the previous week with players and coaches from both teams, edited by N.B.A. Entertainment and narrated by Ahmad Rashad.</p>
        <p>YEAR I, 1996-97 -- Seldom did any opposing coach in the history of professional team sports ever receive the unadulterated love that Madison Square Garden showered Pat Riley with before a second-round series between his former team, the Knicks, and his new Eastern Conference power, the Miami Heat.</p>
        <p>During the thunderous pregame ovation, Riley blew kisses to the Garden faithful and thanked them again for attending the fan appreciation gala he threw at his Connecticut estate upon his amicable departure from the Knicks two years before.</p>
        <p>''May the best man win,'' Riley said, smiling, while meeting the handshake of his former boss, the Garden president, Dave Checketts, who proceeded to pull Riley from the back of the neck and say, ''Come on over, Riles, and let's have a hug.''</p>
        <p>In Game 5 of a stirring series that was already being hailed by critics for its high level of aesthetic, sportsmanlike play, a strange incident occurred late in Game 5 with the Knicks leading, 3-1. Lined up for a free throw, Knicks point guard Charlie Ward had an untimely fainting spell and staggered into the knees of Miami forward P. J. Brown. Brown wrapped his arms around Ward, flipped him over as he would a baby and laid him gently behind the baseline.</p>
        <p>''Somebody, help!'' Brown cried as Ward lay still.</p>
        <p>Closest to the scene, several Knicks responded to Brown's frantic plea, forgetting that they were in violation of the league's rule against leaving the bench during a game. Although Riley pleaded with the league to consider the extenuating circumstances, Commissioner David Stern insisted the rules must be abided by. Several Knicks were suspended, and the Heat rallied to win the series in seven.</p>
        <p>YEAR II, 1997-98 -- In a shooting slump for much of the season, John Starks caught fire in the second half of Game 2 in Miami, as the Knicks evened the first-round series, heading back to New York.</p>
        <p>The following day, Starks and his teammate Chris Childs were both the unfortunate victims of media fiction. Childs, in fact, was scratching a rash on his neck, not making the slash gesture, as it appeared to several misguided newsmen. Meanwhile, Starks, a longtime road arena favorite, was so excited by his clutch shooting, he wanted to remain on the floor and sign autographs for the South Florida fans. Holding up a pencil that would later be mistaken for his middle finger, Starks began advancing toward the admiring fans, but Larry Johnson grabbed him around the neck.</p>
        <p>''John, we have a plane to catch and interview obligations to meet,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>''Sorry, fellas,'' Starks said. ''Rain check.''</p>
        <p>Back in New York, Heat guard Eric Murdock caught Childs's rash, and couldn't stop himself from scratching after making a big basket in Miami's Game 3 victory. Game 4 was a Knicks-Heat classic, except for another bizarre development in the final seconds of a series-tying Knicks victory.</p>
        <p>While trying to cleanly establish inside position on Alonzo Mourning along the baseline near the Knicks bench, Johnson lost his balance and accidentally pushed Mourning into Jeff Van Gundy. The diminutive Knicks coach was knocked horizontal and tried to keep himself from falling by grabbing Mourning's leg. It took several players and both team doctors to detach Van Gundy from Mourning, who had such cramps in his legs from Van Gundy's grip that he couldn't play in the Knicks' series clincher two days later.</p>
        <p>''That's a lucky one for us, and one for you,'' Riley told his protege, Van Gundy, after fighting through crowds of reporters and fans to shake the winning coach's hand.</p>
        <p>''I am disgraced with myself for injuring your player,'' Van Gundy said. ''I owe you. Big Macs on me, after the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>YEAR III, 1998-99 -- The Knicks had made a key addition to their roster for another first-round battle with Miami, Latrell Sprewell, the fearless guard well known for heroically pulling several dangerous ticks from the neck of his former coach, P. J. Carlesimo, at Golden State.</p>
        <p>After more critically acclaimed displays of offensive skill, the Knicks won the decisive Game 5 in Miami again, on Allan Houston's runner just before time expired. Charlie Ward called it a divine act of preordainment, and Riley said he couldn't possibly argue with him. Riley invited both teams to his home for a barbecue and swim party, and they all sat around reminiscing about the happy times they had shared -- Riley with Van Gundy, Mourning with Johnson and Patrick Ewing, Tim Hardaway with Sprewell, Brown with Childs, and so on and so forth.</p>
        <p>Then Riley stood up, raised his glass and said, ''A toast to the winners!''</p>
        <p>''To good sportsmen,'' Van Gundy said, ''and to getting together again next year.''</p>
        <p>Next year is now. Come on over, everyone, and let's have a hug.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
