<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corey Johnson Has Provided Support to All</title>
    <meta content="Y07LIP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BACKTALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DB1438F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corey Johnson Has Provided Support to All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Lipsyte column on Corey Johnson, first high school football captain to publicly declare his homosexuality; cites support he got at his Massachusetts school; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time Corey Johnson came out to the world last week, he had already come out to most everyone who mattered to him -- his parents, sister, best friend, teachers, football coach and teammates -- in a gradual, sometimes orchestrated process that lasted more than a year.</p>
        <p>So, the hundreds of thousands who cheered the linebacker at the Millennium March for Equality in Washington last Sunday were just another big-game crowd. Of course, they all seemed to want to shake his hand and tell him their life stories, if not option his life story, date him or sign him up as spokesman for their gay organization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time Corey Johnson came out to the world last week, he had already come out to most everyone who mattered to him -- his parents, sister, best friend, teachers, football coach and teammates -- in a gradual, sometimes orchestrated process that lasted more than a year.</p>
        <p>So, the hundreds of thousands who cheered the linebacker at the Millennium March for Equality in Washington last Sunday were just another big-game crowd. Of course, they all seemed to want to shake his hand and tell him their life stories, if not option his life story, date him or sign him up as spokesman for their gay organization.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was chasing me,'' Johnson said in the middle of last week, sounding tired but still floating on a celebrity high. It was late at night in his Middleton, Mass., home and he was just back from one of his part-time jobs, as a secretary in a real-estate agency. ''I'm weighing offers. After I graduate next month, I'd like to travel, check out some colleges for the year after and think about the book and movie.''</p>
        <p>Ten days ago, Johnson turned 18, and he is the activist equivalent of the teenage National Basketball Association draftee, a Kobe with a mission. As the first high school football captain to declare his homosexuality so publicly, he immediately proved, as he put it, that ''you don't have to do drama or be a drum major to be gay.''</p>
        <p>The early response to his formal coming-out announcement, on the front page of The New York Times last Sunday, was an avalanche of e-mail messages to the Times Web site or to me at, as you must remember, Thelipsite@aol.com (all of them were forwarded to Coreyjohnson2000@aol.com). Most expressed appreciation to Johnson for giving them hope; some had been closeted high school athletes and remembered the pain and shame of secrecy. Johnson's high school, Masconomet, was singled out for the quality of its teachers, coaches and students, not to mention its long-term commitment to diversity training.</p>
        <p>There is a feel-good aspect to this story for straights, who can feel big-hearted and progressive, and for gay men and lesbians, who can feel that their world is becoming safer. Without diminishing those feelings, it's also useful to remember that Corey's Coming Out didn't just happen. A high school community (not quite unanimously) rallied around a handsome, popular star jock, not a scrawny, vulnerable band member. The school had a Gay Straight Alliance in place with two advisers, one of them a lesbian.</p>
        <p>The Masconomet administration brought in the Gay Lesbian and Straight Education Network, which has a contract with the Safe Schools program of the state of Massachusetts (which has two openly gay members of Congress). The stars were in their courses on this one; think about a star football player even trying to come out under Friday night lights in Texas. Or in a New York City public high school.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Dan Woog, a 47-year-old openly gay assistant soccer coach at Staples High School in Westport, Conn., where he once played, thinks that Corey Johnson will ''give courage to the kid out there'' who may someday really shatter the stereotype.</p>
        <p>''I think the one who will make the difference is going to be a superstar who comes out in high school, and the country follows him to Division I, then to the pros, and the all-star game and the league championship,'' Woog said.</p>
        <p>Woog, author of ''Jocks: True Stories of America's Gay Male Athletes,'' published two years ago by Alyson Books, was on the Gay Lesbian Straight Education Network panel led by Jeff Perrotti where Johnson first asked for help in coming out. He thinks Johnson's story brings up an important coaching issue.</p>
        <p>''If you've got an athlete in the closet, you've got an athlete who can't fully concentrate,'' Woog said. ''Coaches have to make a safe, accepting environment for all kids, gay kids, poor kids, kids with the wrong sneakers, fat kids. In my workshop, I try to convince coaches it's not just the right thing to do, it'll show up in their wins and losses.''</p>
        <p>Ed Gallagher, 43, who was a star at Valhalla (N.Y.) High and a varsity tackle at the University of Pittsburgh, thinks he would have been a far better football player if he had been able to come to terms with his sexuality. He might even have done better in his Jets tryout, although he was up against Mark Gastineau. He certainly would not have, at the age of 28, after his first homosexual experience, climbed to the top of the Kensico Dam, overlooking his high school field, and thrown himself off. Gallagher's neck was broken. He is a quadriplegic.</p>
        <p>Gallagher, founder of Alive To Thrive (aliv2thriv@aol.com) and author of the semiautobiographical ''Johnny In The Spot'' (1stBooks, 1998), often speaks at high schools. He says he sees too many kids struggling.</p>
        <p>''That coach you idolize tries to motivate you with antigay slurs,'' Gallagher said, ''and you wonder what he's telling you, if he's seeing through you. This Corey is a pioneer, a leader, but he's up against the hypocritical right-wing hatemongers who want to punish people for being human. I say there are no straights or gays, just 'strays.' ''</p>
        <p>BACKTALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
