<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="07CHOICE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDB1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Warren Beatty won the best director Oscar for REDS (1981), none other than Orson Welles stood onstage and praised him. A lot of people had been comparing Mr. Beatty's film to Welles's ''Citizen Kane,'' and the older man just wanted to say that he'd be honored to have his work compared to ''Reds.'' Beatty's thrilling epic is about the Bolshevik Revolution as seen through the eyes of the idealistic, eventually disillusioned young writer John Reed (Beatty) and Louise Bryant (Diane Keaton), the woman he loves but frequently leaves. It's also a smart, funny portrait of optimistic young bohemians in New York not long after the turn of the last century. Jack Nicholson is unforgettable as Eugene O'Neill, particularly in his scenes with Ms. Keaton. And Maureen Stapleton received the best supporting actress Oscar as the antiwar activist Emma Goldman, holding on to her dream -- Thursday at 8 p.m., Thursday/Early Friday at 2.45 a.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Capturing the wit and pathos of Dorothy Parker and her journalistic-literary colleagues -- who are now famous mostly for having had drunken, boisterous lunches at a large table at the Algonquin Hotel in the 1920's -- is no easy task. Alan Rudolph only partly succeeds in MRS. PARKER AND THE VICIOUS CIRCLE (1994), but the film is a fascinating failure. Jennifer Jason Leigh is mannered but touching as Parker herself, barging through marriages, career crises and one heartbreaking affair, with Charles MacArthur (Matthew Broderick). Campbell Scott is outstanding as Parker's close friend Robert Benchley, the man she really loves; their relationship is the emotional center of the story. The film is swarming with celebrities playing celebrities. Look for Gwyneth Paltrow in a tiny part -- Sunday at 10 p.m., Sunday/Early Monday at 2:05 a.m. on IFC.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Warren Beatty won the best director Oscar for REDS (1981), none other than Orson Welles stood onstage and praised him. A lot of people had been comparing Mr. Beatty's film to Welles's ''Citizen Kane,'' and the older man just wanted to say that he'd be honored to have his work compared to ''Reds.'' Beatty's thrilling epic is about the Bolshevik Revolution as seen through the eyes of the idealistic, eventually disillusioned young writer John Reed (Beatty) and Louise Bryant (Diane Keaton), the woman he loves but frequently leaves. It's also a smart, funny portrait of optimistic young bohemians in New York not long after the turn of the last century. Jack Nicholson is unforgettable as Eugene O'Neill, particularly in his scenes with Ms. Keaton. And Maureen Stapleton received the best supporting actress Oscar as the antiwar activist Emma Goldman, holding on to her dream -- Thursday at 8 p.m., Thursday/Early Friday at 2.45 a.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Capturing the wit and pathos of Dorothy Parker and her journalistic-literary colleagues -- who are now famous mostly for having had drunken, boisterous lunches at a large table at the Algonquin Hotel in the 1920's -- is no easy task. Alan Rudolph only partly succeeds in MRS. PARKER AND THE VICIOUS CIRCLE (1994), but the film is a fascinating failure. Jennifer Jason Leigh is mannered but touching as Parker herself, barging through marriages, career crises and one heartbreaking affair, with Charles MacArthur (Matthew Broderick). Campbell Scott is outstanding as Parker's close friend Robert Benchley, the man she really loves; their relationship is the emotional center of the story. The film is swarming with celebrities playing celebrities. Look for Gwyneth Paltrow in a tiny part -- Sunday at 10 p.m., Sunday/Early Monday at 2:05 a.m. on IFC.</p>
        <p>Charles Boyer never does say ''Come with me to the Casbah'' to Hedy Lamarr in John Cromwell's ALGIERS (1938). Why should he? They're already there, in the ''native quarter'' of the city (''rotten with vermin and decay and the filth of centuries''), where Pepe Le Moko (Boyer), notorious thief, has been hiding from the police for two years. But love -- for a breathtakingly beautiful young Frenchwoman (Lamarr, in her American film debut), who is engaged to a wealthy man -- may draw him from his hiding place. Anyway he's really homesick for Paris. At times, the film seems about 60 seconds away from the silent era, with its quick-cut see-the-emotion closeups. But it's classic melodrama, and it certainly establishes what all the fuss about Boyer, as a young man, was about -- Saturday at 4 p.m. on CUNY.</p>
        <p>Faye Dunaway's on-target portrayal of Joan Crawford at the height of her prewar movie fame may be high camp, but Frank Perry's MOMMIE DEAREST (1981) is more than that. Based on the book by Crawford's adopted, abused daughter, Christina, it's the horrifying story of one woman's idea of motherhood (wire hanger tirades, middle-of-the-night gardening and all). It's also a fascinating look at Hollywood in the 1930's and 40's, a world in which the trappings of publicity somehow consumed real life -- Tuesday at 8 p.m., Tuesday/Early Wednesday at 12:30 a.m., Wednesday at 1 p.m., Saturday at 8 p.m. and Saturday/Early Sunday at 12:30 a.m. on Bravo.</p>
        <p>Not that real life is always so great, especially if you're single, in your 20's and don't know your own heart. Ben Stiller's breezy, just-cynical-enough romantic comedy REALITY BITES (1994) is about people like that. Winona Ryder, Ethan Hawke and Mr. Stiller are the love triangle. Psychic hot lines, bad television shows, jobs at the Gap and group renditions of ''Conjunction Junction'' are the daily grind -- Saturday at noon, Saturday/Early Sunday at 1 a.m. on USA.</p>
        <p>ANITA GATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
