<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: John Montgomery; Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio</title>
    <meta content="07INVO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montgomery, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3D61738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: John Montgomery; Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on John Montgomery, who manages $42 million Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio; Montgomery comments; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Sunday mornings, John Montgomery plays the flute with a folk-rock group at St. Andrew's Presbyterian Church in Houston. On Tuesday evenings, he rehearses for three hours with the group's vocalists and other musicians. ''We could really use a drummer,'' he complains.</p>
        <p>A former research engineer at M.I.T., Mr. Montgomery, who is 44, sees his music as complementary to  the computer-based calculations he uses to pick stocks for the $42 million  Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio. ''Math is the underlying language of music,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Sunday mornings, John Montgomery plays the flute with a folk-rock group at St. Andrew's Presbyterian Church in Houston. On Tuesday evenings, he rehearses for three hours with the group's vocalists and other musicians. ''We could really use a drummer,'' he complains.</p>
        <p>A former research engineer at M.I.T., Mr. Montgomery, who is 44, sees his music as complementary to  the computer-based calculations he uses to pick stocks for the $42 million  Bridgeway Ultra-Small Company Portfolio. ''Math is the underlying language of music,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Ultra-Small fund has turned in some sweet results, returning 23.3  percent a year, annualized, for the three years through April 30, versus 8.2 percent for its peers in the small value category, according to Morningstar Inc., and 15.2 percent for the Russell 2000 index of small-capitalization stocks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery came to money management by an unlikely route. In 1985, he joined the Houston transit system as a senior budget analyst and during his off-hours developed computer models to manage his investments. He said that in 1990 and 1991, his last years there, his investment earnings far exceeded his modest salary. In 1993, he started Bridgeway Capital Management, which now manages a total of $135 million in four actively managed funds, two index funds and a dozen private accounts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery's background in budgeting leads him to run his firm economically. The firm does not advertise, for example. And because Mr. Montgomery does not allow personal trading by his firm's seven employees, Bridgeway has no need for a compliance officer to monitor their investments.</p>
        <p>Moreover, by negotiating with brokerage firms, he has trimmed the average commission the fund pays to just a penny a share. The average such expense is 6 cents.</p>
        <p>MANAGERS of successful small-cap stock funds generally face a problem: their funds are flooded with cash, forcing them to buy bigger stocks. In Mr. Montgomery's view, a small-cap fund is easily managed as long as its total assets do not exceed the average market capitalization of the stocks it owns. So he closed the fund to new investors in June 1998, when assets reached $27.5 million; he plans to shut it to all new investments, including those by existing shareholders, when assets hit $55 million, the fund's current average market capitalization.</p>
        <p>That market cap is still far smaller than that of the typical small-cap fund. Mr. Montgomery focuses his search for stocks on the smallest 10 percent of issues on the New York Stock Exchange, but also picks from among 2,000 very small stocks in an index created by the Center for Research in Securities Prices, which tracks the smallest stocks traded on the Big Board, the American Stock Exchange and the Nasdaq.</p>
        <p>In choosing stocks, Mr. Montgomery never visits companies or meets with their management. Instead, he uses five proprietary computer models, the details of which he is loathe to discuss.</p>
        <p>He does say, however, that four of the models review fundamental data like per-share earnings growth and cash flow; the fifth analyzes technical factors like trading volume and relative price appreciation. Each model is used to pick a list of 10 stocks; the names sometimes overlap.</p>
        <p>''We're a black box shop,'' he said in a slight Texas drawl. ''We put the data in and the computer cranks it out.''</p>
        <p>The portfolio is filled with cheap stocks: its typical price-to-earnings ratio is in the low to mid-teens, though its three-year earnings growth rate averages 36 percent a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery runs the technical model monthly. Three of the fundamental screens highlight value-oriented stocks and are run weekly. The fourth, which looks for attractive growth stocks, is run daily.</p>
        <p>The fund owns about 160 stocks,  giving it a degree of diversification that dampens the inherent risks of investing in the smallest stocks, he said. Typically, he sells stocks when they no longer meet his models' criteria, or when the models produce better candidates.</p>
        <p>AMONG the stocks he likes is Team America, a Worthington, Ohio, company that provides payroll, retirement plan management and other human resources services to business. Its per-share earnings, cash flow and sales have been strong, he said, but the company's share price is ''dirt cheap,'' in part because of an acquisition-related charge taken last year.</p>
        <p>As the company moves forward, Mr. Montgomery said, the share price could double in the next 12 months. He bought shares in May 1999 at $4.78; they closed at $4.50 on Friday, 16 times his 2000 earnings estimate of 28 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Another favorite is the Howell Corporation, an integrated oil and gas company in Houston. ''Oil prices are way up, and its stock price is dead in the water,'' he said. But because its cash flow was $3 a share last year, he said, ''you could earn your price back with cash flow alone in less than three years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery, who bought shares last July at $6.50, predicts three-year earnings growth of 15 percent a year, on average. The shares closed Friday at $7.1875, or 4.5 times his earnings estimate of $1.60 a share this year.</p>
        <p>He also likes Lifemark, a health maintenance organization in Phoenix. ''The industry as a whole is cheap,'' he said, ''but this company is doing great.''</p>
        <p>He noted that the company has doubled its annual per-share earnings for three consecutive years.  Wall Street expects earnings growth to average 30 percent a year for the next five years.</p>
        <p>He bought shares in October 1998 at $4.375; it closed Friday at $4, or 6 times analysts' consensus earnings of 65 cents a share for the fiscal year ending in May 2001.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
