<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="07FSUM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DB1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>I.R.A. Pledges to Open Arsenal to Inspection  The Irish Republican Army offered to open its secret arsenal of weapons to international inspection as a way of meeting peace negotiators' demands that it ''completely and verifiably'' put its arms beyond use.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>I.R.A. Pledges to Open Arsenal to Inspection  The Irish Republican Army offered to open its secret arsenal of weapons to international inspection as a way of meeting peace negotiators' demands that it ''completely and verifiably'' put its arms beyond use.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Japan Re-evaluates System  Japanese politicians and commentators have begun to speak of the end of a style of factional politics that has been in force for 45 years, after the incapacitating stroke suffered by a sitting prime minister, and the retirement of a former prime minister who was his mentor.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Political Wind Favors Serbs  Ten months after they fled the province in the face of revenge attacks from Kosovo Albanians, the Serbs of Kosovo and other minorities are seeing international political will swing in their favor.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Foreigners Leave Sierra Leone  Foreigners and officials with international relief groups left Sierra Leone, as the United Nations reported no progress in obtaining the release of peacekeepers from rebels.</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Mbeki Admits AIDS Cause  South Africa's president, Thabo Mbeki, said that he knows the human immunodeficiency virus causes AIDS, but that he is interested in alternative AIDS theories because he wants to know why AIDS appears so differently in sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>Sudan Leader Halts Ex-Ally  Sudan's president, Omar al-Beshir, issued directives to ''freeze'' the activities of the ruling party's secretariat general, after accusing his former ally of trying to overthrow the government.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>24-40</p>
        <p>Clinton Plays Crucial Role Behind Campaign Scenes  President Clinton has become a crucial behind-the-scenes player in the 2000 campaign, serving as a tactical adviser for House, Senate and gubernatorial candidates. Prominent Democrats portray Mr. Clinton's role as that of a valuable Strategist in Chief. They describe him as a sponge for absorbing statistics, with well-honed political instincts -- plus the power of the presidency.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>New Role for Drug Managers  Pharmacy benefit management companies are being assigned an important role in proposals to add a drug benefit to Medicare. The companies are also coming under increasing scrutiny by the Justice Department and state regulators.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Overnite Strike Tests 2 Sides  The Teamsters' six-month-long strike against the Overnite Transportation Company has become a battle of wills that is tough for both sides. Many union members are struggling to pay their bills, while the company has had its bottom line hammered.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Genome Race Nears End  The 10-year project to decode the human genome is nearing an end amid a fractious exchange of claims and countercharges by two competing teams. Within a few weeks, each side plans to declare victory under different terms, and each side sees the other as flawed.</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Reversal in Iraqi's Case  An Iraqi doctor who worked with the Central Intelligence Agency against Saddam Hussein, then was jailed in California for nearly four years on the basis of secret C.I.A. evidence, may soon be free.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>45-54</p>
        <p>As the Rich Move In, Locals Find Space Is Scarce  The Hamptons has always been a place of contrasts: of workers and wealth, of masons and millionaires, and more recently, of carpenters and kings of dot-coms. Now in the country's wealthiest enclaves, like the Hamptons, increasing costs are forcing many out.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A Cardinal's Vocal Legacy  Cardinal John O'Connor's death last week is a reminder of the degree to which a confrontational style helped make him the best-known and perhaps the most influential voice in the American Catholic Church. But it also underlines the difficulties facing whoever tries to put on his leadership mantle.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>50</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>55-56</p>
        <p>Harold Lloyd Patton  A stage manager for Ray Charles who assembled more than 20,000 rare books by African-American authors, he was 71.</p>
        <p>56</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>54</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>57</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>50</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
