<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comments Revive St. Petersburg-Moscow Rivalry</title>
    <meta content="07PETE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000513T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mori, Yoshiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D91538F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comments Revive St. Petersburg-Moscow Rivalry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Russia, May 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Old rivalry between Moscow and St Petersburg is revived with Pres Vladimir Putin's attention to old czarist capital on the Baltic, setting for Putin's recent metings with Prime Min Tony Blair and Japanese leader Yoshiro Mori; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first time Vladimir V. Putin deserted Moscow and staged a meeting with a visiting head of state here, Russians hardly noticed.</p>
        <p>That was in March, when Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain came to the city that Peter the Great built and that served as Russia's capital for two centuries. The Russian and British leaders strolled with their wives into the Mariinsky Theater and from the imperial vantage point of the czar's former box they watched the gala opening of the opera ''War and Peace.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first time Vladimir V. Putin deserted Moscow and staged a meeting with a visiting head of state here, Russians hardly noticed.</p>
        <p>That was in March, when Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain came to the city that Peter the Great built and that served as Russia's capital for two centuries. The Russian and British leaders strolled with their wives into the Mariinsky Theater and from the imperial vantage point of the czar's former box they watched the gala opening of the opera ''War and Peace.''</p>
        <p>But the second time it happened, when Mr. Putin again abandoned the capital last week and flew here to meet Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori of Japan in the splendor of the Winter Palace, tongues started wagging that Mr. Putin was raising the status of his hometown in a manner that touched the historical chord of rivalry between Moscow and St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>''This is a very big conflict, not only a conflict of cities, but a conflict of psychologies,'' said Anastasia Kuryokhina, one of the city's cultural promoters and the widow of Sergei Kuryokhin, a well-known poet and musician here.</p>
        <p>''Many people in Moscow do not like St. Petersburgers,'' she added. ''There are strong feelings. There are cultural differences. Muscovites are practical and pragmatic. St. Petersburg tends to be more romantic, more philosophical.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Muscovites have their own views. St. Petersburgers have been disparaged for putting on airs, or regarded as dandies who hold their inland countrymen in low esteem while living in their own micro-culture of excessive intellectualism or, in imperial times, just excess.</p>
        <p>Still, no one took Mr. Putin's image-making very seriously. After all, it was natural that this river city of canals and splendid baroque architecture that is home to the Kirov Ballet, a lively theater district and some of the world's great art collections, would receive some favor from Russia's new leader, the first to come from here since the end of the Romanov dynasty.</p>
        <p>As long as Mr. Putin was just engaged in gestures such as hanging a portrait of Peter the Great in his Kremlin office no one seemed threatened. Until now.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Putin was meeting here with the Japanese prime minister, the speaker of Russia's Parliament, Gennadi Seleznyov, a moderate Communist who was also visiting the city, surprised an audience of politicians and reporters by saying he favored moving Russia's Parliament, or Duma, out of Moscow and relocating it here on the banks of the Neva River.</p>
        <p>That move would effectively reverse the shift made by Vladimir I. Lenin, who put a symbolic stamp on the Communist triumph over czarism by shifting the capital back to Moscow and renaming St. Petersburg Petrograd. After he died in 1924, this city was called Leningrad in his honor -- another move to extirpate memories of the czarist past.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seleznyov said that Russia's members of Parliament currently suffer ''considerable inconvenience,'' working in ''ill-adapted rooms'' across from the Kremlin in the nondescript former headquarters of the Soviet state planning agency Gosplan since troops loyal to former President Boris N. Yeltsin destroyed the former Parliament building while quashing an attempted coup in 1993.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seleznyov sketched a proposal for a new Parliament building, pledged to bring the issue to debate this month and concluded that ''the next Duma,'' to be elected in 2003, ''could be meeting in St. Petersburg.''</p>
        <p>The man standing beside Mr. Seleznyov -- and beaming -- was St. Petersburg's governor Vladimir Yakovlev, who has advocated moving all or part of the Russian government here to enhance both the restoration of the city and its long-term economic development. Mr. Yakovlev told Mr. Seleznyov that a large tract of land was reserved for a new Parliament building near Smolny Cathedral in the center of the city and plans could be drawn up for modern offices and elegant chambers for the upper and lower houses.</p>
        <p>The next day, Mr. Putin said it was an ''interesting'' idea, but from Moscow, there was only scoffing.</p>
        <p>Mayor Yuri M. Luzhkov attacked the idea as ''mostly politicking'' and insisted that all major government institutions be located in Moscow, the capital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Luzhkov predicted that while Mr. Seleznyov might succeed in scheduling a parliamentary debate in the lower house, it would be dead on arrival in the upper chamber whose members include Mr. Luzhkov and Russia's governors and regional leaders, who are unlikely to see any interest in spending huge sums of scarce national resources to relocate the Parliament.</p>
        <p>The leader of Mr. Seleznyov's own Communist Party, Gennadi Zyuganov, and other influential voices said Russia's economic woes would only deepen if the three branches of government were split up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seleznyov certainly succeeded in gaining extensive coverage and reawakening a rivalry dating back to the founding of St. Petersburg at the outset of the 18th century, when Peter sought a toehold on the Baltic Sea and a window to Europe, sending thousands to their death through his insistence on building a grand new capital on a swamp and forcing the xenophobic nobles of Moscow to haul building stones in their carriages and move their households here. Resentment against the city has simmered ever since.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 13, 2000, Saturday  Because of an editing error, an article on Sunday about renewed rivalry between Moscow and St. Petersburg misstated the history of St. Petersburg's name and referred incompletely to the shift of the Russian capital from St. Petersburg to Moscow. St. Petersburg was renamed Petrograd as a patriotic gesture after war broke out with Germany in 1914; it was not renamed by Lenin. In 1918, Moscow was made the capital in part because it was easier to defend than St. Petersburg, not solely as a symbolic stamp of the triumph of Communism over the czar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 13, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Sunday about renewed rivalry between Moscow and St. Petersburg misstated the history of St. Petersburg's name and referred incompletely to the shift of the Russian capital from St. Petersburg to Moscow. St. Petersburg was renamed Petrograd as a patriotic gesture after war broke out with Germany in 1914; it was not renamed by Lenin. In 1918, Moscow was made the capital in part because it was easier to defend than St. Petersburg, not solely as a symbolic stamp of the triumph of Communism over the czar.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
