<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making History</title>
    <meta content="07BREENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pocock, J G A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Breen, T H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Barbarism and Religion (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDC1E30F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By T. H. Breen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Breen, T H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>T H Breen reviews books Barbarism and Religion by J G A Pocock: Volume One: The Enlightenments of Edward Gibbon, 1737-1764, and Volume Two: Narratives of Civil Government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BARBARISM AND RELIGION</p>
        <p>By J. G. A. Pocock.</p>
        <p>Volume One: The Enlightenments</p>
        <p>of Edward Gibbon, 1737-1764. 339 pp.</p>
        <p>Volume Two: Narratives</p>
        <p>of Civil Government. 422 pp.</p>
        <p>New York: Cambridge University Press.</p>
        <p>$49.95 each; boxed set, $90.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BARBARISM AND RELIGION</p>
        <p>By J. G. A. Pocock.</p>
        <p>Volume One: The Enlightenments</p>
        <p>of Edward Gibbon, 1737-1764. 339 pp.</p>
        <p>Volume Two: Narratives</p>
        <p>of Civil Government. 422 pp.</p>
        <p>New York: Cambridge University Press.</p>
        <p>$49.95 each; boxed set, $90.</p>
        <p>''In the second century of the Christian era,'' Edward Gibbon announced, ''the empire of Rome comprehended the fairest part of the earth, and the most civilized portion of mankind.'' Few educated readers in 1776 could possibly have missed the irony of Gibbon's opening sentence. However powerful Rome may once have appeared, it failed to sustain the civic values that had produced greatness in the first place, and in six imposing volumes titled ''The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire,'' Gibbon recounted how this dominant civilization proved incapable of resisting barbarian invasion and the spread of militant Christianity. Although his skeptical account of the early church fathers shocked contemporary reviewers, the work became an instant best seller, changing forever how historians go about the business of imagining the past.</p>
        <p>Gibbon was an appealing figure. Born to a respectable landed family, he lived as much as circumstances permitted within a world of books. He was a voracious reader, and his major complaint about his instructors at Oxford University was their utter indifference to his unquenchable intellectual curiosity. He rebelled against the complacent Anglican society of his college tutors by converting to Roman Catholicism, but after being exiled by his family to Switzerland, where he studied under a demanding Protestant scholar, Gibbon returned, albeit with serious doubts, to the Church of England. As he matured, he gracefully accepted the responsibilities incumbent on an English gentleman -- military service and election to Parliament -- seldom whining about financial or romantic disappointments. He seems to have been a genuinely happy person who fully appreciated those rare moments when he was able to give himself over to ''the pleasures of reading and thinking.''</p>
        <p>In ''Barbarism and Religion,'' J. G. A. Pocock, a historian at Johns Hopkins University, rehearses the familiar details of Gibbon's life. But he has no interest in traditional biography. His goals are far more ambitious. This is not surprising. His ''Machiavellian Moment'' (1975) reinterpreted the entire history of political ideology in early modern England and America. In these two monumental volumes, Pocock seeks to explain how a studious boy fashioned himself into a genuinely ''enlightened'' thinker.</p>
        <p>The ''Decline and Fall'' provides an anchor for Pocock's complex and subtle reflections about the intellectual transformation of 18th-century Europe. Pocock's first volume traces the education of Gibbon -- a rugged regimen largely of Gibbon's own design, during which he sorted out radical, often conflicting Enlightenment ideas about the credibility of revealed religion and the character of modern civil society. His second volume situates the ''Decline and Fall'' within an enlightened historiography -- the writings of the Italian antipapal historian Pietro Giannone, Voltaire and Hume, for example -- that attempted to solve many of the same interpretive problems that perplexed Gibbon. Pocock manages to place Gibbon within these larger cosmopolitan movements without diminishing the historian's extraordinary accomplishment.</p>
        <p>After completing the ''Decline and Fall,'' Gibbon wrote a memoir, which is a minor classic. Although the manuscript went through many drafts and was not published during Gibbon's lifetime, it raised hard questions about his remarkable career. ''I know by experience that from my early youth I aspired to the character of an historian,'' he wrote. The claim undoubtedly reflected what he had come to believe. As a boy growing up in rural Hampshire, however, he would have had a difficult time explaining exactly what it meant to be a historian. In a sense, he set out to prepare himself for a vocation that did not yet exist, at least not in a form that a precocious student like Gibbon would have found compelling.</p>
        <p>To be sure, before Gibbon entered the field learned people had produced history for many centuries. Most of this scholarship, however, lacked the interpretive balance that we take for granted today. The histories that Gibbon encountered in English libraries seemed narrowly antiquarian, shrilly partisan or stiflingly parochial. Much of this literature amounted to little more than hagiography. Few so-called historians even showed much interest in the distant past, preferring to dwell on recent political events. Before he could confront the history of the Roman Empire, Gibbon had to invent a more complex form of historical analysis, one that successfully wove careful research and philosophical argument into a sustained, readable narrative.</p>
        <p>Pocock's account of Gibbon's intellectual development forces him to take on what he sees as the problem of ''the'' Enlightenment. It is not that Pocock doubts that reason and skepticism undermined traditional modes of thought during the 18th century. Rather, he dismisses the claim that the Enlightenment was a monolithic movement, a radical orthodoxy that united thinkers as dissimilar as Rousseau and Hume, Voltaire and Adam Smith. Pocock is a splitter, not a lumper; he explains that as Gibbon tried to define a new kind of history, he encountered several different Enlightenments, each of which more or less influenced the interpretive strategies that shaped the ''Decline and Fall.''</p>
        <p>In Switzerland Gibbon developed a lifelong respect for what Pocock labels the ''Protestant Enlightenment,'' a critical reading of religious texts based on impeccable erudition. Gibbon also absorbed the writings of the Parisian philosophes, particularly the work of d'Alembert, which Gibbon attacked in 1762 in his first book-length publication. Later in life, he expressed admiration for the giants of the Scottish Enlightenment. Pocock insists that over time Gibbon fabricated a distinct approach to the life of the mind that might best be described as an English Enlightenment. It was a different form of analysis from that championed by the French or the Scots, and yet, despite its suspicion of general laws of human behavior, it represented a major contribution to what Pocock terms ''a family of Enlightenments.''</p>
        <p>As Gibbon sorted out the various meanings of enlightenment, he searched for a historical topic worthy of investigation. Different topics were taken up, only to be rejected. He contemplated a life of Sir Walter Raleigh but concluded that he had nothing original to say about Elizabethan politics. A more serious possibility was ''The History of the Liberty of the Swiss,'' and although Gibbon did not read German, he sketched out an enlightened history of Switzerland. Nothing came of it. At the end of the day, his own involvement in contemporary religious controversy and his growing mastery of Latin sources drew him almost irresistibly toward Rome.</p>
        <p>Gibbon described as epiphany what was in fact probably the culmination of a long deliberation on a suitable master narrative for an enlightened English gentleman. ''It was at Rome,'' he declared many years later, ''on the 15th of October 1764, as I sat musing amidst the ruins of the Capitol, while the barefooted friars were singing vespers in the Temple of Jupiter, that the idea of writing the decline and fall of the city first started to my mind.''</p>
        <p>WHATEVER occurred during that memorable Italian visit, Gibbon did not publish the first volume of the ''Decline and Fall'' for another 12 years. And once the volumes began to appear, he shifted his attention away from the city of Rome, tracing to Constantinople the long history of the corruption within the empire. As Pocock explains, it was this decision that set him apart from other enlightened historians of his generation, from Hume, Voltaire and William Robertson, the great Scottish scholar, for while they concentrated on Europe's liberation from feudal monarchy and papal domination during the second millennium, Gibbon chose to burrow ever deeper into an earlier Eastern world torn apart by the uncompromising ambitions of Christianity and Islam.</p>
        <p>However impressive Pocock's accomplishment, ''Barbarism and Religion'' is not recommended for the intellectually faint of heart. The style is demanding, the references occasionally obscure. But even when one questions some of his conclusions -- how many Enlightenments can there be before the concept becomes simply a collection of fragments? -- one admires the breadth of his erudition. Indeed, like Gibbon, he is a truly enlightened historian, one who takes ideas seriously and who has no patience for those of our own age who would ''deny the reality of authors and the readability of texts.''</p>
        <p>T. H. Breen teaches history at Northwestern University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">T. H. Breen teaches history at Northwestern University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
