<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Nightmarish Drop Through the Safety Net</title>
    <meta content="07COLM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dobelle, Gladys</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2D61738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Nightmarish Drop Through the Safety Net</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia Lee Coping column on plight of upper-middle-class New York City public relations entrepreneur Gladys Dobelle, 57, who fell on hard times and fell through cracks of city's welfare system; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHE remembers the last moments of her old life. It had turned into a bright May afternoon and she was on Broadway, feeding quarters into a pay telephone on which she called friend after friend asking to spend the night. She could not reach anyone.</p>
        <p>''At the first shelter I went to, they couldn't put me up because I didn't have a child,'' she recalled of that day. ''I didn't fit into any of the categories for the other shelters, either. I wasn't on drugs, I wasn't pregnant, handicapped or a teenager. I didn't have AIDS or abuse alcohol.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHE remembers the last moments of her old life. It had turned into a bright May afternoon and she was on Broadway, feeding quarters into a pay telephone on which she called friend after friend asking to spend the night. She could not reach anyone.</p>
        <p>''At the first shelter I went to, they couldn't put me up because I didn't have a child,'' she recalled of that day. ''I didn't fit into any of the categories for the other shelters, either. I wasn't on drugs, I wasn't pregnant, handicapped or a teenager. I didn't have AIDS or abuse alcohol.</p>
        <p>''I ran out of billable hours.''</p>
        <p>Gladys Dobelle took a long, hard tumble: from the life of an upper-middle-class entrepreneur to the life of a jobless, homeless woman. As she begins her climb back, some people want to make her a metaphor: for welfare system flaws, for grief, for fickle friends. Perhaps, as an old friend who recently discovered her circumstances suggests, Ms. Dobelle is just a reminder of how fragile life can be.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dobelle, 57, who retains the chirpy yet dulcet tones of the public relations person she used to be, walked out on her life on May 18, 1999, after a series of catastrophes. With huge blue eyes, an eager-to-please smile and a relatively unlined face, she looks determined but a bit shell-shocked as she approaches this sad anniversary.</p>
        <p>Between 1971 to 1988, every member of Ms. Dobelle's immediate family died from various illnesses: her mother, her father, her sister and her brother. She divorced a well-regarded research scientist. As she sought to rebuild the business she had neglected while caring for her ill mother, she was hit with staggering financial problems.</p>
        <p>The last lick was a fire in her building near Lincoln Center. It damaged her apartment, from which she operated her public relations business.</p>
        <p>''I just walked out the door, I was so overwhelmed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Friends lent her money, but no one was aware that things had gotten so bad that she could not pay her rent. Ms. Dobelle acknowledges that she does not reach out for help easily or let others inside her feelings. When her mother died, she went to the funeral alone. It was her and the rabbi.</p>
        <p>''She died on July 4 and I didn't want to bother people on their holiday weekend.'' she said.</p>
        <p>After spending the first night in a shelter in an Upper West Side church, Ms. Dobelle tried reaching out to friends.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'I spent the night in a shelter,' and they said, 'I wish I could help you,' and my thought was, 'Why can't you?' '' she said. ''Another comment was, 'You really need to work this out.' ''</p>
        <p>So Ms. Dobelle moved from shelter to shelter every three weeks for a year.</p>
        <p>Her clothes were stolen. She had trouble finding and keeping even small jobs, like working in a bookstore.</p>
        <p>When she sought public assistance, she was turned down twice. They did not believe her story and wanted more documentation.</p>
        <p>''I'd be sitting in a welfare office and the person to the left of me had lost a limb and the person to the right was a mother with a baby wearing an oxygen mask because she had asthma,'' Ms. Dobelle said. ''If only two out of three people can get welfare, who would you give it to?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Dobelle took her case to the New York Legal Assistance Group, which affirmed her right to public assistance, Medicaid and food stamps. The legal group, which represents poor people, had filed a class action suit against the city last October. The suit charged that the city's Eligibility Verification Review Office illegally denied welfare benefits to countless New Yorkers without explanation, as it did with Ms. Dobelle.</p>
        <p>She won her case. Things are a bit better these days for Ms. Dobelle. Since last year, she has lived in a tidy room at a privately run East Side shelter that allows long-term stays. She has made friends and is dealing with her grief (along the way, one grief counselor died). She has a stable environment and the medical care to tackle the skin cancer that was first diagnosed last year.</p>
        <p>Taylor Hallman, the shelter's social work supervisor, said many people of Ms. Dobelle's social class have trouble asking for and receiving help. Ms. Dobelle's account of her troubles is documented by the agency.</p>
        <p>''When someone is of a certain social position -- upper middle class here -- people turn away,'' Mr. Hallman said. ''It's sort of that fear of it happening to them. Or they wonder, are they going to ask me for money? And people have a hard time asking for help.''</p>
        <p>Jean Grillo, a long-time friend who rediscovered Ms. Dobelle two months ago, said many friends looked for holes in Ms. Dobelle's story. Others expressed dismay because they did not know how bad things had become and have tried to help. Ms. Grillo, a writer, is talking with Ms. Dobelle about writing a book about her experience.</p>
        <p>''It has been a foreign land for me,'' Ms. Dobelle said the other day. ''I had to find the road maps. Maybe I can provide a map.''</p>
        <p>''I hope no one has to go through what I had to go through with no one believing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Then she wept.</p>
        <p>COPING  Correction:  May 21, 2000, Sunday  The Coping column on May 7, about a public relations woman who became homeless, misstated the year in which her apartment building was damaged by fire. It was 1998, not 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Coping column on May 7, about a public relations woman who became homeless, misstated the year in which her apartment building was damaged by fire. It was 1998, not 1999.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
