<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Producers Strutted The Earth</title>
    <meta content="07MARK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merrick, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Alexander H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0DD1039F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Producers Strutted The Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Marks on David Merrick and Alexander H Cohen, brilliant theatrical producers who flourished in golden age of American drama; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE day, in the long-ago time when larger-than-life showmen reigned on Broadway, the producer Robert Whitehead had the idea of putting on staged readings in the Belasco Theater on Sunday nights, when the Odets play he was producing there was dark.</p>
        <p>''So I called Tennessee and I called Arthur, and I said, 'Do you have a play hidden away somewhere that you're working on and you'd like to see done?' '' Mr. Whitehead recalled the other day. The writers he rang up were, of course, Tennessee Williams and Arthur Miller. And while Williams had nothing to offer, Mr. Miller sent along a script called ''Submarines,'' a term for illegal immigrants who were spirited into the country to work on the Brooklyn docks and elsewhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE day, in the long-ago time when larger-than-life showmen reigned on Broadway, the producer Robert Whitehead had the idea of putting on staged readings in the Belasco Theater on Sunday nights, when the Odets play he was producing there was dark.</p>
        <p>''So I called Tennessee and I called Arthur, and I said, 'Do you have a play hidden away somewhere that you're working on and you'd like to see done?' '' Mr. Whitehead recalled the other day. The writers he rang up were, of course, Tennessee Williams and Arthur Miller. And while Williams had nothing to offer, Mr. Miller sent along a script called ''Submarines,'' a term for illegal immigrants who were spirited into the country to work on the Brooklyn docks and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''Submarines'' later became ''A View From the Bridge,'' which Mr. Whitehead would produce with Kermit Bloomgarden and Roger L. Stevens. But all these years later, what seems extraordinary about Mr. Whitehead's recollection is the fluidity of the transaction: that a producer could so easily get these lions of the American theater on the horn and slip the machinery of American culture into gear.</p>
        <p>''It is the relationship of a writer and a producer that came out of another time,'' the 84-year-old Mr. Whitehead said. He was speaking just days after two other great producers of that time, David Merrick and Alexander H. Cohen, had died, and with their passings within days of each other, the remoteness of that theatrical era was made eminently plain. Mr. Merrick, 88, died in London on April 26; Mr. Cohen, 79, in New York on April 22, and while there was no love lost between those roguish rivals, they flourished in a golden age for the American drama, the American musical and, by extension, the American impresario.</p>
        <p>I met both men late in their lives, long after they had done their most memorable work, Mr. Merrick as the generator of such hits as ''Hello, Dolly!'' and ''42nd Street,'' Mr. Cohen as the importer of impeccable British theater and as major-domo of the early Tony Awards telecasts. By the mid-1990's, when Broadway had been conquered by the mega-musical and independent producers all but supplanted by colorless entertainment conglomerates, alliances of producing entities and ambitious nonprofit institutions, Mr. Merrick and Mr. Cohen were still at the producing game against the odds of infirmity and an even more insidious obstacle: the sense that their time had passed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitehead knew Mr. Merrick as a ruthless adversary and a brilliant practitioner of the art of spin: ''David was not a beloved competitor,'' he said. The David Merrick I met in March 1996 was a poignant shadow of the fearsome entrepreneur of old. Incapacitated by a stroke, unable to speak, he was rolled into our ''interview'' in a wheelchair by Natalie Lloyd, who would become the last of his wives and who claimed to understand his attempts at communication. The reclusive Mr. Merrick had come to the rescue of a financially troubled stage version of the Rodgers and Hammerstein movie musical ''State Fair,'' the ostensible reason for our meeting.</p>
        <p>He gazed at me in dark silence. The encounter was awkward and a bit sad; at one point, he hobbled mutely around the room, as if to show how able-bodied he still was. It occurred to me later that this showman, renowned for pulling the wildest of publicity stunts, was now making himself -- or was being made -- the stunt. But when I mentioned another show on the boards at the time, ''Victor/Victoria,'' and the rumors I had heard that he had declined to invest in it, his manner changed. His eyes fixed on mine as he struggled to be understood. Ms. Lloyd explained that Mr. Merrick was trying to deliver an old producer's final verdict: the musical would never make it into the black.</p>
        <p>MR. COHEN, a polished raconteur, was as lavish with words as Mr. Merrick was robbed of them. Over long lunches, he would dish his colleagues in the fraternity, rage against what he saw as the theater owners' greed, pronounce himself exhausted with the business and, oh, had he mentioned the five productions he had in the pipeline? (His last, ''Waiting in the Wings,'' is still running on Broadway.)</p>
        <p>He made a habit of sending prickly notes to theater writers that also diplomatically included self-deprecating allusions. He was bitter at the way, he said, he was removed as producer of the Tony Awards after many years of running them, and gleeful at the headaches he gave the American Theater Wing and the League of American Theaters and Producers as a result of a dispute over rights to the archival material on the Tony broadcasts he oversaw.</p>
        <p>In other words, a character, from an era when Broadway tolerated true individualists, and a producer whose body of work, like that of Mr. Merrick, an audience came to know. Neither man ever really left the stage, which makes one wonder: don't old theater types ever simply buy a condo somewhere and retire?</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitehead roared at the question. ''We always feel there might be another show that will give us that kick,'' he said. ''I once ran into Josh Logan on the street, and he started complaining about all the things that were happening to the theater. And then he looked me, sort of sadly, and said, 'Oh, God, it would be so good to have one more.' ''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
