<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Sheen of Municipal Bonds</title>
    <meta content="07BOND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFDE1438F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Sheen of Municipal Bonds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long-term municipal bonds are yielding almost as much as their federal government counterparts; short-term munis are attractive also as investors sacrifice little return while increasing their flexibility; drawing; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY so often, most strikingly when Congress gets agitated about the nation's tax structure, the market for municipal bonds sags, driving yields to lip-smacking levels. Challenges to the bonds' tax-exempt status typically loom much larger in investors' eyes than a possible benefit from the scarcity that would be created by action in Washington.</p>
        <p>This time, however, returns on municipals have been elevated by economic fundamentals -- mainly the necessity of competing with the stock market and the near certainty that interest rates -- already raised five times by the Federal Reserve since mid-1999 -- will climb even further.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY so often, most strikingly when Congress gets agitated about the nation's tax structure, the market for municipal bonds sags, driving yields to lip-smacking levels. Challenges to the bonds' tax-exempt status typically loom much larger in investors' eyes than a possible benefit from the scarcity that would be created by action in Washington.</p>
        <p>This time, however, returns on municipals have been elevated by economic fundamentals -- mainly the necessity of competing with the stock market and the near certainty that interest rates -- already raised five times by the Federal Reserve since mid-1999 -- will climb even further.</p>
        <p>The federal government's budget surplus, meanwhile, is shrinking the supply of Treasury bonds even as growing numbers of refugees from stock-market gyrations are seeking a haven; both forces are driving down returns on Treasury debt.</p>
        <p>A result is the unusual situation of long-term municipal bonds that pay tax-free interest yielding just as much, or even a bit more, than taxable Treasury bonds.</p>
        <p>''Long-term munis and long Treasuries are basically yielding the same thing,'' said William Hornbarger, fixed-income strategist at A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons in St. Louis. For many investors, he added, ''that's a no-brainer'' situation.</p>
        <p>To be sure, no municipality or other tax-exempt issuer matches the United States Treasury for credit quality, but the difference is less than many investors imagine. In fact, roughly half of municipals carry insurance, making credit comparisons of little practical consequence.</p>
        <p>Until about a year ago, according to Alexandra Lebenthal, president of a family-owned New York firm that specializes in municipal bonds, municipals were considered attractive when long-term yields as measured by the Bond Buyer's Index reached 85 percent of those on Treasury bonds. Now, with the ratio above 90 percent for the highest-quality debt and approaching 100 percent for lesser but still investment-quality bonds, ''it's a fantastic time for the individual'' buyer to scoop up tax-exempts, she said.</p>
        <p>For example, a recently marketed New York State Dormitory Authority issue rated Baa-1 and BBB+ yields about 6 percent in a maturity as short as 10 years. That return is equivalent to a taxable investment generating 9.34 percent for a New York resident earning $150,000 and filing a joint return. Ten-year triple-A bonds yield 5.25 percent, equal to a taxable 8.17 percent.</p>
        <p>Most people, though, don't bother with fancy calculations even when sophisticated, state-specific translation tables are available, like the one at the Bond Market Association's Web site, investinginbonds.com.</p>
        <p>''The individual investor looks at absolute yield,'' said Dan Keating, a senior managing director at Bear, Stearns.</p>
        <p>A 6 percent coupon is ''magic,'' Ms. Lebenthal added.</p>
        <p>Moreover, quality ''has probably never been better,'' according to a study by Merrill Lynch, whose analysts found that upgrades by rating agencies have far exceeded downgrades for the last four years as city, state and authority budgets improved, with the best performance in 1999.</p>
        <p>Although mutual funds that invest in municipal bonds had substantial outflows in the second half of last year -- aggravated by redemptions to establish losses for tax savings, of all things -- specialists say the appeal of municipal bonds is broadening.</p>
        <p>''It's not just 70-year-old people'' any longer, said Jane Trust, who runs four tax-exempt funds for Legg Mason Trust in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hornbarger concurred, pointing to stock-market and entrepreneurial profits being redirected to the tax-free market. ''We're seeing more and more younger people in their 30's and 40's,'' he said. ''It's part of their asset allocation strategy.''</p>
        <p>And municipals have become easier to buy, with many state and local issuers insisting on a special retail order period to give individuals first crack at bonds. Moreover, increasing competition has sharply cut insurance premiums, reducing the cost to 10 or 15 basis points (or $1 to $1.50 per $1,000), from 40 or 50 a decade ago. The savings have mostly been passed on to investors in the form of higher yields.</p>
        <p>Yet another attraction of munis is their ability to provide portfolio ballast when stocks are in turmoil. ''Their volatility is significantly lower -- that is the real edge to municipals,'' said Michael Shamosh, chief fixed-income strategist for Tucker Anthony Inc. Throughout financial history, he said, munis swing only one-fourth as widely as stocks and half as widely as Treasury bonds, he said.</p>
        <p>But what is the smart strategy, given that most analysts expect the Federal Reserve to keep tightening the monetary screws at least through midyear, a trend that overwhelms the downward pressure on rates from a shrinking supply of new bonds?</p>
        <p>Most experts suggest deferring purchases of longer-term bonds and buying only those that come due fairly soon, say within a year or two but perhaps in as little as a few weeks or months. The idea is to preserve the chance to reinvest at progressively higher rates rather than being locked into current levels.</p>
        <p>It doesn't take much to persuade most investors of the wisdom of that approach, since the municipal yield curve -- the progression of rates through the maturity spectrum -- provides relatively little extra payment for lengthening one's commitment.</p>
        <p>''I like the short term if you have to put money to work,'' Mr. Keating said. ''I'd stay within one to five years' maturity.''</p>
        <p>BUT Mr. Shamosh takes a different view. ''You want to get out of the Fed's reach,'' he said. This suggests buying maturities that are affected relatively little by the Fed's rate increases, those due, say, between 6 and 20 years, in the conviction that the central bank will eventually succeed in slowing down the economy. This, in turn, would reassure the market that inflation -- the worry of long-term investors -- will be kept in check.</p>
        <p>Investors should always have some short-term investments for liquidity, Mr. Shamosh said, but longer-term munis are what should be added to a sensible person's portfolio. ''The Fed,'' he said, ''doesn't have any control over the long rates, which could come down,'' enhancing the value of such bonds.</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
