<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Address</title>
    <meta content="07DINE$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Twenty Eight (Montclair, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D71F39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Address</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Twenty Eight restaurant in Montclair, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a beautiful spring night in Montclair, it felt right choosing Twenty Eight for dinner. Ducking under the bowing, flowering pear trees, I entered the restaurant feeling confident and unencumbered, for it has a clear sense of style and ease. It allows you to relax and makes you pleased to be doing so. Twenty Eight is just that -- just right.</p>
        <p>Which is interesting. The restaurant is the brainchild of Raymond Badach, a former garment district player who inherited his Sicilian mother's love of food. Aside from the homey Raymond's cafe down the street, Mr. Badach has had no training. But he has watched the food scene for years. A native New Jerseyan, Mr. Badach is urbane and calm, apparently picking up on the New York pulse but not necessarily racing along with it. And Mr. Badach gave Montclair Twenty Eight in 1994.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a beautiful spring night in Montclair, it felt right choosing Twenty Eight for dinner. Ducking under the bowing, flowering pear trees, I entered the restaurant feeling confident and unencumbered, for it has a clear sense of style and ease. It allows you to relax and makes you pleased to be doing so. Twenty Eight is just that -- just right.</p>
        <p>Which is interesting. The restaurant is the brainchild of Raymond Badach, a former garment district player who inherited his Sicilian mother's love of food. Aside from the homey Raymond's cafe down the street, Mr. Badach has had no training. But he has watched the food scene for years. A native New Jerseyan, Mr. Badach is urbane and calm, apparently picking up on the New York pulse but not necessarily racing along with it. And Mr. Badach gave Montclair Twenty Eight in 1994.</p>
        <p>The town couldn't be happier.</p>
        <p>The copper sheeting, black-and-white tiles, curving booths, muted lighting, antique mirrors, huge bar and lofty ceiling reminded me immediately of a scene from a 40's movie.  In fact, the thick wooden blinds up front transported me to an upscale coffee shop in Los Angeles. I almost expected Roger and Jessica Rabbit to flitter by. Rarely do restaurants in New Jersey remind me of Soho, much less of swanky California.</p>
        <p>Then there's the service. It's B.Y.O., but if you haven't brought wine the staff will get some for you down the street; just give them your preference and range. Need to know the local movie schedule in town?  Just ask.</p>
        <p>And the food! Six years ago Mr. Badach cold-called his favorite restaurant in Manhattan, Jean-Claude, and persuaded one of its chefs, Bruce Johnson, to join him at Twenty Eight.  When Mr. Johnson left, Mr. Badach went back to Jean-Claude to track down William Prunty, (who had moved on to open Liam on Sullivan Street). Like his predecessor, Mr. Prunty constructs a short menu that changes seasonally. It still works.</p>
        <p>The main ingredient for the corn soup was grilled in its husk (and playfully garnished with a section of corn on the cob), making this first glimpse at the menu wonderfully smokey. The clean, raw Taylor Bay scallops, garnished with marinated cucumber noodles, jalapeno and orange rind, were sweet and bright going down. A tower of shredded endive, jicama and apple stood up to the flavor and weight of a covering of finely grated gorgonzola, the whole creation studded with brilliant nuggets of chopped fines herbes. And then there's the braised short rib timbale, a smart way to present the salty, tender meat off the bone, seasoned with ground dried porcinis and mushroom juice and served over roasted shiitake mushrooms. The shower of parsley juice over this  wintry ensemble quickly reminded me that it was spring.</p>
        <p>Atlantic Salmon in a potato crust, served over thin disks of candied beets beside belly tartar and bursts of pea shoots, was slightly greasy and bland, however. The fricassee of manila and cockle clams, while filled with such promising ingredients as curried coconut milk, Thai basil, serrano chilis, lemongrass and steamed baby bok choy, was overpowered by  lime, which made the whole stew surprisingly bitter.</p>
        <p>Just the presentation of Mr. Prunty's entrees could carry the place.  Sexy five-spice roasted squab lay over potato mascarpone ravioli sprinkled with fresh fava beans and sunny pearl onions; frisee- salad with lardons added texture and sparkle. The rack of lamb with a spinach-stuffed leg emanated rosemary and it was balanced over a smattering of delicate baby carrots, fennel, white turnips, and asparagus tips in an herby lamb jus. The grilled dry-aged prime rib steak was straightforward yet classy, served atop sliced shallots softened in red wine, paired with an aluminum cup filled with French fries. And roasted chicken, utterly tender, sunk comfortably into horseradish-spiked potatoes and buttery, silken spinach.</p>
        <p>The fish at Twenty Eight, provided by Wild Edibles in New York, was a bit more hit or miss. Pan-roasted halibut was fabulous, served over a loose pile of spaghetti squash and topped with a layer of goat cheese-gratineed cauliflower and dark slivers of woodsy black trumpet mushrooms. The New England wild striped bass, seared to a golden brown, lay over baby potatoes and broccoli rape, whose usual bitterness was magically erased. Sadly, the  monkfish wrapped in prosciutto di Parma and the napoleon of steelhead trout fell slightly short: the monkfish's texture did not contrast enough with the pureed eggplant, and I wished the napoleon with its proliferation of vegetables was was solely vegetarian. The fish in each dish was not only overcoddled but overcooked.</p>
        <p>The desserts were -- you guessed it -- just right. Vahlrona fallen chocolate cake oozed into the accompanying espresso creme anglaise. Lavender creme brulee was creamy, crunchy and redolent of a dried bouquet. I was certain that the ginger spiced cake would have been better suited to a fall menu, but the warm, soft, spicy mound drew me in. It could have been a fine ending to my meal. But then I dug my spoon into the oven-roasted pineapple tart, bubbling with a champagne sabayon and held in place by a firm, tasty butter cookie. I could return just for this delicacy.</p>
        <p>You'd think that Mr. Badach's plan to mimic successful restaurateurs while flying by the seat of his pants might work for a little while, but would most likely fizzle in the long run. Not so. Twenty Eight has been packed since it opened. It's not hard to figure out why.</p>
        <p>Twenty Eight  28 Church Street, Montclair  (973) 744-9263</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>Atmosphere -- L.A. in N.J.  Service -- Helpful but slow.  Smoking -- Not allowed.  Wine List -- B.Y.O.  Recommended Dishes -- Taylor Bay scallops; endive and apple salad; roasted corn soup; braised short rib timbale; five-spice roasted squab; rack of lamb with spinach-stuffed leg; grilled dry-aged prime rib steak; roasted chicken; New England wild striped bass; pan-roasted halibut; Valhrona fallen chocolate cake; lavender creme brulee, sorbet trio; oven-roasted pineapple tart.  Price Range -- Appetizers: $7.50 to $11; entrees: $17.50 to $25; desserts: $7.  Credit Cards -- Visa and MasterCard.  Reservations -- Recommended on Fridays and Saturdays.  Hours -- Tuesdays to Fridays, 6 to 10 p.m.; Saturdays, 5:30 to 10 p.m.; Sundays 5 to 9.  Wheelchair Access -- All on street level.</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
