<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Gurney's Hands, It's a Play. Or Is It?</title>
    <meta content="07GEOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurney, A R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saint, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ancestral Voices (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6DD1638F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Gurney's Hands, It's a Play. Or Is It?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein article on Ancestral Voices, A R Gurney's semiautobiographical account of three generations in one family, directed by David Saint, which is set to open with four different casts, at George Street Playhouse in Livingston, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE play's the thing, as Shakespeare said. But can the thing be a play?</p>
        <p>That is the question being asked about ''Ancestral Voices'' at the George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE play's the thing, as Shakespeare said. But can the thing be a play?</p>
        <p>That is the question being asked about ''Ancestral Voices'' at the George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick.</p>
        <p>A. R. Gurney, who wrote the thing, which has been variously called a staged reading, a hybrid, a radio drama, a concert performance, even a fluke, said, ''I think it's a play.''</p>
        <p>Eddie, the narrator of ''Ancestral Voices,'' says the story ''started to be a play, but it went too many places for the stage.'' Eddie is Mr. Gurney's alter-ego in what the author admits is a semi-autobiographical account of three generations in one family.</p>
        <p>It ''tried to be a book but people kept wanting to talk,'' Eddie tells the audience.</p>
        <p>In a telephone conversation, Mr. Gurney said: ''I first wrote it as a book. But nobody wanted to publish it.'' Then, he was asked to appear at the 92 Steet Y in Manhattan. ''They said, 'Read whatever you want,' '' he said. ''And I thought, damn it, I'm going to read a piece of this, and the audience seemed interested, and people asked, 'What comes next?' and I knew it, 'This works!' ''</p>
        <p>What came next was Mr. Gurney's realization that however ''Ancestral Voices'' was labeled, it was certainly a form of theater. And Mr. Gurney, who has written so many stage works that are indisputably called plays, is known for the invention of new theater forms. For example, ''Love Letters,'' an epistolary reading involving two actors, sitting at a table. With starry combinations of actor-readers, ''Love Letters'' has established an annuity in perpetuity for its creator.</p>
        <p>Perhaps dreaming of another annuity, Mr. Gurney recast ''Ancestral Voices'' into seven roles for five actors and handed the script to Dan Sullivan who directed ''Far East'' by Mr. Gurney, which was then playing at the Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater in Lincoln Center. ''Let's squeeze this in on Sunday and Monday nights,'' the theater's dark nights, Mr. Gurney suggested. ''We're paying rent anyway.''</p>
        <p>''Ancestral Voices'' went on long enough to be played in front of the sets for three plays and with three changes in casts.</p>
        <p>At George Street, the first staging since it closed at Lincoln Center on April 3, four different casts are scheduled, including George Grizzard and Frances Sternhagen, both during the first week, which concludes today.</p>
        <p>''Every cast approaches it in a different way, doing their own riffs, like jazz,'' Mr. Gurney said. Because the play requires no long-term commitment, a quintet of actors can come and go, just as couples have been doing in ''Love Letters'' for the past 13 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurney has been a ''Love Letters'' partner, ''but this one requires real acting,'' he said of ''Ancestral Voices.''</p>
        <p>But what about direction?</p>
        <p>''There's more than you would think,'' said David Saint, the director of this and a coming Connecticut production. ''This one is more complex. It's like orchestrating a chamber piece, a tone poem. You have to be sure everyone is in the right world; they can't appear too strident.''</p>
        <p>''Ancestral Voices'' is not a happy story, but rather an ambiguous one. Eddie is the grown-up grandson, looking back at the time his grandmother left his grandfather for another man. ''Shock waves reverberate through three generations,'' Mr. Saint said.</p>
        <p>Can ''Ancestral Voices,'' with its time leaps and 40 location shifts be played as a full-out play? That would diminish its allure for actors who, Mr. Gurney pointed out, are used to and like readings.</p>
        <p>Besides, the imagination of the audience is called upon. ''You have to dignify the audience, bestow upon them respect for their intelligence,'' Mr. Gurney said. ''This is about a story, it is not scenery obsessed, it's easy to do,'' Mr. Gurney said. He does not argue with calling ''Ancestral Voices'' a portable play.</p>
        <p>''It's a family story,'' Mr. Saint added. ''So it's like storytelling.''</p>
        <p>Yet the conflict in Mr. Gurney's work is eternal -- and theatrical, Mr. Saint pointed out. ''The struggle to hold onto cherished traditions clashes with the iconoclast wanting to bash them,'' Mr. Saint said. ''And then there are all these wonderful actors. Yes, it definitely is a play. And now there is a reason to see it every week.''</p>
        <p>ANCESTRAL VOICES</p>
        <p>George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick.</p>
        <p>Through May 28. Today at 2 and 7 p.m., Tuesday through Friday at 8 p.m., Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>(732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
