<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expectations, Over the Rainbow</title>
    <meta content="07STRA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulbert, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Strategies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D81738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expectations, Over the Rainbow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK HULBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulbert, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Mark Hulbert, editor of financial newsletter, explains why he does not think technology companies have any chance of meeting their investors' optimistic expectations; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is fair to say that technology investors have high expectations about the future growth of companies in their portfolios. But I bet that those companies have almost no chance of meeting those optimistic expectations.</p>
        <p>Why am I so downbeat? It all comes down to the issue of whether huge growth rates can be sustained.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is fair to say that technology investors have high expectations about the future growth of companies in their portfolios. But I bet that those companies have almost no chance of meeting those optimistic expectations.</p>
        <p>Why am I so downbeat? It all comes down to the issue of whether huge growth rates can be sustained.</p>
        <p>Consider a star of the new economy, Cisco Systems. Sure, its gear is essential to the growth of the Internet. But it is unlikely that Cisco will perform well enough over the next five years to satisfy the earnings expectations that I believe are implied by its current price-to-earnings multiple of 188.</p>
        <p>To gauge those expectations, we first need to calculate how much Cisco's earnings are likely to grow over the next five years.</p>
        <p>If Cisco follows the typical pattern of growth companies, its multiple will drop as it grows and matures. So assume that five years from now, Cisco's P/E will be 50 -- still well above the market's long-term historical average of about 15.</p>
        <p>Next we need to postulate the company's stock performance. Cisco's stock has climbed 105 percent, annualized, over the last five years. So, to be conservative, we will guess that it will grow just 22 percent a year -- still double the stock market's long-term average.</p>
        <p>Given these cautious assumptions, Cisco's stock will be at $183 in May 2005, up from $67.5625 on Friday. And many investors would be happy to get that kind of return.</p>
        <p>But here is the rub: Cisco's earnings will have to grow by nearly 60 percent a year, on average, over the next five years to meet those expectations. And if we assume that Cisco's P/E is below 50 in 2005, or that its price is higher than $183, the requisite earnings growth rate will have to be even higher. To put this in perspective, consider that the earnings growth rate of the median technology company has been just 13 percent, annualized, over the last five decades.</p>
        <p>So if you buy Cisco today, expecting that it will hit $183 in five years, you are making an implicit bet that its earnings will grow five times faster than those of the average technology company. And new research suggests that the odds of that are very low.</p>
        <p>Josef Lakonishok and Louis K. D. Chan, finance professors at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, studied nearly every technology stock from 1951 to 1999. In particular, they sought companies whose earnings growth rates were consistently above the median of all publicly traded companies.</p>
        <p>They found that over periods of five years or more, just 4.7 percent of companies, on average, had earnings growth that beat the median during all years of the period. The number is statistically insignificant because, assuming that earnings growth was random, 3.3 percent of the companies would have beaten the median each year in any case.</p>
        <p>Then the professors loosened up a bit, and searched for technology companies whose earnings growth rates exceeded the median in four out of five years. The results were almost identical. Their conclusion: Sustaining consistent, above-average earnings growth over five years is so rare as to approach statistical insignificance.</p>
        <p>Of course, the professors were looking only for those technology companies that would beat the median earnings growth rate. The analysis of Cisco suggests that investors are betting, in effect, that the company will beat the median earnings growth rate by a factor of five.</p>
        <p>I DO not mean to pick on Cisco. It is unlikely that any company's earnings can grow 60 percent a year for the next five years.</p>
        <p>But analysts are forecasting such growth for many companies. According to First Call/Thomson Financial, nearly 280 of the nearly 6,200 companies it tracks have consensus five-year projected earnings growth rates of 60 percent or more, annualized.</p>
        <p>Some people say earnings don't matter in  the new economy. But the professors foresaw that argument: They reached nearly identical results when they looked at sales growth rather than earnings growth.</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week. E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week. E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
