<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are We as Happy as We Think?</title>
    <meta content="07EHRE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehrenhalt, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benhamou, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5D81438F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are We as Happy as We Think?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Ehrenhalt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ehrenhalt, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Ehrenhalt Op-Ed speculation about whether Americans are really as happy as they think they are in these times of calm and plenty; suggests that best way to raise issue of societal inequality in current climate is to frame it in electronic terms; quotes computer pioneer Eric Benhamou's warning that in ten years society will have 75 percent population extremely well connected and 25 percent completely adrift (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is a good time to be many things: a software designer, a suburbanite putting a five-bedroom house on the market, a cook or a carpenter in a service economy where jobs are chasing workers. But it is a bad time to be a social critic.</p>
        <p>While most of us drift languidly through the prosperous spring of the new century's first year, one relatively small segment of the American elite is approaching a state of crisis. The keepers of the nation's social conscience are grasping for a role to play at a moment when the society does not feel much like pondering its fate. They are befuddled by a mass contentment they were never trained to cope with.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is a good time to be many things: a software designer, a suburbanite putting a five-bedroom house on the market, a cook or a carpenter in a service economy where jobs are chasing workers. But it is a bad time to be a social critic.</p>
        <p>While most of us drift languidly through the prosperous spring of the new century's first year, one relatively small segment of the American elite is approaching a state of crisis. The keepers of the nation's social conscience are grasping for a role to play at a moment when the society does not feel much like pondering its fate. They are befuddled by a mass contentment they were never trained to cope with.</p>
        <p>This happens every once in a while, and it happens most noticeably when there is a presidential campaign going on, and we are at least nominally charged with the task of examining our national values and goals.</p>
        <p>In certain interesting ways, the year 2000 is a lot like 1928, or 1960. Most of the country is doing pretty well. One political party has presided rather benignly over the White House and the executive branch for the past eight years. An heir apparent seeks to keep the presidency in that party's hands. There is a common perception that the election may mark a turning point of some sort, but no one is quite sure how, and the entire prospect excites very little interest. And pacing irritably on the sidelines is a cadre of nervous critics struggling to persuade us that we are not as contented as we might think.</p>
        <p>They have said this before. ''The prosperity of the Eisenhower Age is a deceptive sign of vigor and health,'' Norman Podhoretz wrote in Commentary as the 1960 campaign opened. He pointed to ''the boredom one senses on all sides, the torpor, the anxiety, the listlessness.''</p>
        <p>The literary critic Dwight Macdonald, writing in Dissent, felt the same way. ''We are an unhappy people,'' he insisted, ''a people without style, without a sense of what is humanly satisfying. There is a terrible shapelessness about American life.'' He proclaimed his intention to abstain in the election of 1960, no matter what the candidates said or did.</p>
        <p>Turn back another generation, replace Richard Nixon and John Kennedy with Herbert Hoover and Al Smith, and you pick up the same sort of intellectual refrain. The voters seem happy, critics concede, but they are actually in the midst of a deep-seated spiritual crisis. As the 1928 campaign year began, Walter Lippmann was completing ''A Preface to Morals'' and agonizing as usual about the unwillingness of the American people to take issues seriously. What the situation demanded, Lippmann wrote, was a statesman who could be ''successful in converting his constituents from a childlike pursuit of what seems interesting to a realistic view of their interests.'' Unfortunately, no such statesman was to be found.</p>
        <p>H. L. Mencken was considerably less gentle. He charged the American people not merely with complacent inattention, but with woeful ignorance. He returned from one campaign swing and wrote that the voters he encountered ''prefer nonsense to sense'' and ''they have gone so far into the darkness that every light terrifies them and runs them amuck.''</p>
        <p>Coping with a contented electorate is not easy for any social critic, but there are strategies for doing it -- arguments that can be used to try to burst the bubble of seeming widespread satisfaction.</p>
        <p>One such argument is that the middle class may be doing well but that the bottom rungs of the society are suffering more than ever. In 1960, Michael Harrington was the foremost exponent of this view, warning repeatedly in a series of magazine articles that the grinding poverty of ''forgotten Americans,'' in Appalachia and in the housing projects of the northern inner cities, lay just beneath the surface of prosperity.</p>
        <p>No critic will be able to startle the electorate this year by discovering poverty in our midst; now we know all about it. But there does seem to be a year 2000 equivalent: the digital divide. The best way to raise the issue of societal inequality in the current climate is to frame it in electronic terms, and this is already being done.</p>
        <p>If steps are not taken to close the divide, the computer pioneer Eric Benhamou warned a few weeks ago, in 10 years we will have ''a society with 75 percent of the people extremely connected and 25 percent completely adrift.'' He proclaimed it ''a crisis of phenomenal proportions in the making.'' The presidential candidates have picked up on this. Whether the voters care much about it is another question.</p>
        <p>Another approach is to argue that things are indeed comfortable but are about to crash. This year's most outspoken crash critic is Kevin Phillips. Drawing analogies between excessive highway speed and stock market recklessness, he warns that ''the country is exceeding so many speed limits that you have to wonder if some big pile-up is coming.''</p>
        <p>The advantage of crash criticism is that if you keep predicting economic disaster, and survive long enough, sooner or later you will be right. The disadvantage is that by then, you may have acquired a reputation as a Chicken Little. People have an appetite for reading prophecies of disaster retrospectively, after the disaster occurs. They nearly always ignore them at the time they are made, as prophets throughout history have discovered.</p>
        <p>During the summer of 1928, Sinclair Lewis warned that ''within a year, this country will have a terrible financial panic.'' It was a remarkable prediction little noted by anyone.</p>
        <p>Then there is the ''quiet desperation'' approach. At the end of the 1950's, the sociologist C. Wright Mills declared that what appeared to be contentment masked widespread individual despair over the moral bankruptcy of the society. The problem was that the unhappy individual didn't realize he had millions of fellow sufferers all around. The job of the intellectual and social critic, in Mills's view, was to point this fact out to him, to translate ''personal troubles into social issues.''</p>
        <p>In the fall of 1960, as Kennedy and Nixon were arguing about steel production capacity and America's prestige abroad, Mills was seeking to make the case for a much simpler proposition: We're not as happy as we think. It was a tough sell.</p>
        <p>It would be an equally tough sell now. There are campaign years in which the electorate genuinely seems to be searching for meaning. Both 1968 and 1980 fit in that category. This is not one of them. This is the sort of year that drives intellectuals of the sophistication of Walter Lippmann or H. L. Mencken to label the electorate, as Mencken did in 1928, ''hopelessly uneducable.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, as the Old Testament makes clear, it is precisely when no one wants to listen that prophets are needed most. It takes relatively little courage or skill to wring one's hands at a moment of genuine crisis. Doing it in flush times is the real challenge.</p>
        <p>So as we go about ignoring the social criticism of the year 2000, we still might want to pause to offer the critics a few words of consolation: Don't be discouraged. Cheer up. Things are bound to get worse.</p>
        <p>Alan Ehrenhalt is the executive editor of Governing magazine and author of ''The Lost City.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Ehrenhalt is the executive editor of Governing magazine and author of ''The Lost City.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
