<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Forgotten Threat: Free Trade in Population</title>
    <meta content="07CONT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DA1738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Forgotten Threat: Free Trade in Population</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst column says those seeking to derail forces of globalization assail global trade, importing of goods, but ignore immigration, importing of people; says immigration keeps increasing supply of labor, seriously suppressing low-end wages, but foes of globalization do not oppose immigration because that stance would be politically incorrect (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN their determination to derail the forces of globalization -- a process in which dastardly capitalists provide employment to impoverished people all over the world -- protesters in Washington focused recently on a pair of plump targets, the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>Yet they directed none of their ire at the Washington headquarters of another notorious agent of globalization, the Immigration and Naturalization Service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN their determination to derail the forces of globalization -- a process in which dastardly capitalists provide employment to impoverished people all over the world -- protesters in Washington focused recently on a pair of plump targets, the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>Yet they directed none of their ire at the Washington headquarters of another notorious agent of globalization, the Immigration and Naturalization Service.</p>
        <p>Of course, the I.N.S. is not really responsible for America's decision to tolerate consistently high levels of legal and illegal immigration, or for the nation's indifference to the age, training or skill level of most of the immigrants it admits.</p>
        <p>But the protesters seemed mainly to want a symbol. So why assail global trade (the importing of goods) but ignore immigration (the importing of people)? After all, economists across the political spectrum agree that the growing volume of world trade yields economic, social and even geopolitical benefits to Americans and foreigners alike, making the world more peaceful and more affluent. There is no such consensus on current immigration policy.</p>
        <p>Many of the protesters claimed to be environmentalists. Surely the arrival of large numbers of immigrants, who will soon begin consuming land, fuel and other resources at gargantuan American levels, is an environmental issue.</p>
        <p>Other protesters profess a concern for American jobs. Yet unemployment in this country is negligible.</p>
        <p>The real problem for American workers is that immigration keeps increasing the supply of labor, seriously suppressing low-end wages. George J. Borjas, a Harvard professor of public policy specializing in immigration, calls this ''an astonishing transfer of wealth from the poorest people in the country, who are disproportionately minorities, to the richest.''</p>
        <p>John Micklethwait and Adrian Woolridge, in their exhaustive new book about globalization, ''A Future Perfect'' (Crown Business Books) state flatly that ''immigration has a much more direct impact on American wages than trade does.''</p>
        <p>What's more, immigration holds down wages in exactly the kinds of low-skill jobs that are not easy to shift overseas -- the only ones, in other words, that are likely to remain available in the long run to the poorest Americans. Many of the poor -- often immigrants themselves -- generally take a much dimmer view of high immigration rates than does the latte-and-S.U.V. crowd, which mainly sees cheap child care and great new ethnic restaurants.</p>
        <p>Certainly, immigration has played a role in the declining fortunes of organized labor. Consider the drywallers of Southern California. In the 1970's, installing gypsum wallboard there was highly paid union work. But at the end of that decade, contractors began using nonunion Mexican immigrants, many of them from a single village. By the early 1980's, union drywallers had been completely displaced, and wages had plummeted.</p>
        <p>Eventually, after a struggle, the immigrant drywallers formed their own union and won raises, but their pay remains far below what their predecessors earned -- perhaps because there are more immigrants waiting to take their places.</p>
        <p>In the rhetoric of its opponents, global capitalism has a prominent failing: income inequality. But in the United States, that inequality is almost certainly exacerbated by immigration; indeed, it is becoming common again for the bourgeoisie to employ servants, though no one uses the term in polite company.</p>
        <p>Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve and bete noire of anticapitalists everywhere, recently called for more immigration of skilled workers. Software companies, of course, love that idea. They want more immigrant programmers, even though there is no great shortage of homegrown software labor, at least according to Norman Matloff, a computer scientist at the University of California at Davis who also studies immigration. There is only a shortage, he says of cheap software labor.</p>
        <p>IT would be more logical for foes of globalization to also oppose immigration, but such a stance is, of course, politically incorrect. While supporting both free trade and immigration may be more consistent,  I'm not sure it is any more right. If we are to continue reaping the benefits of globalization, we must do more to help those who suffer the heaviest cost -- America's working poor, who should, at the least, receive decent pay and health insurance for their labors. The nation is unlikely to make much headway on this or many other important fronts (like income inequality, suburban sprawl or social cohesion) until we reassess which people, and how many of them, can enter the country. In the past, big influxes have often been followed by long periods of digestion in which fewer newcomers were admitted.</p>
        <p>The time may be right for another such breather.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
