<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zuckerman's Alter Brain</title>
    <meta content="07MCGRAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roth, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgrath, Charles</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Human Stain, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5DD1639F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zuckerman's Alter Brain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles McGrath</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philip Roth discusses his new book The Human Stain, interview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philip Roth, who seldom gives interviews, agreed recently to talk about his new novel, ''The Human Stain.'' The conversation took place in Roth's wood-paneled studio, behind his house in rural Connecticut, where he has lived since 1973. It's a place, he says, where ''there's not much else to do except write.''</p>
        <p>You've said that you see ''The Human Stain'' as the third part of a trilogy, starting with ''American Pastoral'' and ''I Married a Communist.'' But it's not a trilogy in the obvious ways -- it's not sequential or chronological.</p>
        <p>I think of it as a thematic trilogy, dealing with the historical moments in postwar American life that have had the greatest impact on my generation. I'd say the greatest impact on me, except I don't believe my response is singular. Which moments? The first was the McCarthy era. You read the newspapers even as a student and you were frightened, you were mesmerized, you were outraged. Even more potent was the impact of the Vietnam War. That was the most shattering national event of my adulthood. A brutal war went on and on -- went on longer even than that other great milestone, World War II -- and brought with it social turbulence unlike anything since the Depression. The third moment was 1998, the year of the presidential impeachment. In 1998 you had the illusion that you were suddenly able to know this huge, unknowable country, to catch a glimpse of its moral core. What was being enacted on the public stage seemed to have the concentrated power of a great work of literature. The work I'm thinking of is ''The Scarlet Letter.''</p>
        <p>Another element linking the three books is the character of Nathan Zuckerman -- your alter ego, some people have said.</p>
        <p>Alter brain.</p>
        <p>Your alter brain. He's been with you since ''The Ghost Writer,'' right?</p>
        <p>A long time. I thought I had abandoned him after ''The Prague Orgy.'' But in ''American Pastoral'' this mediating intelligence named Nathan Zuckerman solved the problem of how to launch the book. Only when I got Zuckerman in there thinking could I get the story of the Lvovs going. I'd begun the book some 20 years earlier, near the end of the Vietnam War. I wrote about 70 pages but never knew how to proceed after the daughter blew up a building to protest the war. Each time I'd finish another book I went back and reread the 70 pages, but only after finishing ''Sabbath's Theater,'' when I'd had Mickey Sabbath up to here -- you know, I too had to live with the great disorder that is this man, longer even than the poor reader -- only then did I think, Well, here's this orderly man, moderate, kindly, decent by every conventional standard, everything that Sabbath isn't, and what a change it would be to start imagining him. That's how the Swede became everything to me, and how I came to present him -- as I hadn't the first time around -- as though Zuckerman had known him as a boyhood idol. Zuckerman was my insider, my knowledgeable wedge into the Swede's life, who somehow gave me the freedom to know him. On Page 90 I jettisoned Zuckerman -- he was no longer necessary.</p>
        <p>In the next book, ''I Married a Communist,'' Zuckerman's not just a mediating presence. He's a real character in that story.</p>
        <p>He's a real ear in that story, at least half the time. He listens to the story of Ira Ringold being told by his brother, Murray Ringold, as Murray knows Ira's story. Then, in alternate chapters, more or less, Zuckerman tells the story as he knows it. Murray and Zuckerman pass the narrative ball back and forth down the court until the story of Ira's failure is recorded unto the last betrayal -- betrayal being the book's subject, since it was, in every conceivable way, the master obsession of the McCarthy era. It's a very different subject from ''American Pastoral,'' and it sparks a different kind of storytelling.</p>
        <p>In the new book, Zuckerman has yet a different role.</p>
        <p>Yes, he's more of an actor in the ongoing events than he is in the previous two books. He's a friend, Coleman Silk's friend. He's lonely and he makes a friend of Coleman and then he loses him. And when he sets out to reconstruct the lost friend's story, he discovers a secret biography unknown not just to him but to virtually everyone else.</p>
        <p>To get back to the subject matter of ''The Human Stain,'' the events of 1998 certainly get talked about, but the most obvious thing is that this is a book about a black man who passes as a white man, as a Jew. It's a book, you could say, about issues of race and of Judaism and where the two intersect.</p>
        <p>Not race and Judaism. There's nothing about Judaism in this book.</p>
        <p>Well, he does choose to take on a Jewish identity.</p>
        <p>As a means of deception, as a social disguise, as a pretext for his appearance. He doesn't want to be a Jew for anything like the reasons that Frank Alpine, say, in Malamud's novel ''The Assistant'' wants to be a Jew. Coleman's choice has nothing to do with the ethical, spiritual, theological or historical aspects of Judaism. It has nothing to do with wanting to belong to another ''we.'' It's a cunning choice that successfully furnishes him with a disguise in the flight from his own ''we.'' The choice is strictly utilitarian -- as so much is for this man.</p>
        <p>Where did the idea come from?</p>
        <p>It goes back to Chicago, where I went to graduate school in the middle 50's and where I returned to live for a couple of years after the Army. Chicago furnished me with my first look at the big world. It was the first time I really felt, saw, registered, the black presence in an American city or, in the slightest way, became personally engaged with blacks. When I was growing up in Newark in the 30's and 40's, we were all -- Irish, Italians, Slavs, blacks, Jews -- settled and secure in different neighborhoods. There was barely any social overlap and the black population was, in fact, relatively small in those days. Newark didn't begin becoming the preponderantly black city that it is today until about 1950, the time I was leaving for college. But the Chicago I landed in was something else. And when I was a graduate student at the University of Chicago I met a girl from another Chicago college whom I had a little graduate-student fling with, and who was, as we then said, a Negro -- moreover, a Negro from a professional family. I don't think I'd understood before then that a black middle class of any size existed, and her family came as news to me -- as I surely did to them. Anyway, we began to go out, and I met the family, who were very pale Negroes, decidedly so on her mother's side. And I never forgot her mother saying that there were relatives of hers who'd been lost to all their people. That was the phrase she used -- lost to all their people.'' The girl explained to me later what her mother was talking about -- that these relatives, who could physically pull it off, had given up identifying themselves as Negro, had moved away and had joined the white world, never to return. And that I never forgot, though I certainly never imagined that in such a story there was a subject for me. Yet both the story and the people made a lasting impression. Self-transformation. Self-invention. The alternative destiny. Repudiating the past. Powerful stuff.</p>
        <p>What does the trilogy say about us? If it's a sort of report card about America, how are we doing?</p>
        <p>That's a question worth asking, but not of me. We're talking about more than a thousand pages of fiction. I just wanted these historical debacles to enter into and pass through the characters -- I just wanted to find out what that would be like. Mostly I wanted to find out what a novel would have to be like in order not to be a report card about America but a work of fiction about America.</p>
        <p>What's next? You've said that one book often spurs the next one.</p>
        <p>I want to get off the grand kick. I want to clear my head of all this seriousness.</p>
        <p>You're working on a comic novel?</p>
        <p>(Laughing.) No, I want another voice for now. For six months, a year, I'd like to look at things another way. I'm trying to shake loose of the dark Zuckerman take on American life.</p>
        <p>There was a time in your life when you were spending a certain amount of energy writing about other writers, especially Eastern European writers. Is there something analogous to that now?</p>
        <p>No. I edited the Other Europe series for Penguin from '74 until '89. I was reading all these Eastern European novels in translation, I was meeting Eastern European writers, some over there, some in exile, and all of this was news to me. I was also, at this time, living some seven months of each year in London, and so, without much trouble, I was in Paris frequently, and in Prague, and I was in Jerusalem a lot. When I came home from England for good in '89, it was really my rediscovering America as a writer. I came back, in fact, because I felt out of touch. Not that I didn't know what was going on here from reading the paper, but what was missing was the daily immediacy of what people were saying and thinking -- missing was everything that was going on by the way. If, for instance, I had been living elsewhere in 1998 I never could have written ''The Human Stain.'' From afar I couldn't have responded as viscerally as I did to the moral atmosphere of 1998, which had much to do with my imagining the story of how Coleman Silk gets done in. When I look back now, I see that ''Sabbath's Theater'' is the real turning back to American stuff. Mickey Sabbath's is such an American voice. And after him, if not out of him, came the American trilogy. And I see from what I'm writing right now that even if I try, I can't steer clear of our common history creeping thematically into my work. This is a result of growing older, I suppose. You don't have a historical perspective for a long time. A historical perspective requires time. Then, alas, time passes, you've got one and you're stuck with it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Philip Roth, who seldom gives interviews, agreed recently to talk about his new novel, ''The Human Stain.'' The conversation took place in Roth's wood-paneled studio, behind his house in rural Connecticut, where he has lived since 1973. It's a place, he says, where ''there's not much else to do except write.''</p>
        <p>You've said that you see ''The Human Stain'' as the third part of a trilogy, starting with ''American Pastoral'' and ''I Married a Communist.'' But it's not a trilogy in the obvious ways -- it's not sequential or chronological.</p>
        <p>I think of it as a thematic trilogy, dealing with the historical moments in postwar American life that have had the greatest impact on my generation. I'd say the greatest impact on me, except I don't believe my response is singular. Which moments? The first was the McCarthy era. You read the newspapers even as a student and you were frightened, you were mesmerized, you were outraged. Even more potent was the impact of the Vietnam War. That was the most shattering national event of my adulthood. A brutal war went on and on -- went on longer even than that other great milestone, World War II -- and brought with it social turbulence unlike anything since the Depression. The third moment was 1998, the year of the presidential impeachment. In 1998 you had the illusion that you were suddenly able to know this huge, unknowable country, to catch a glimpse of its moral core. What was being enacted on the public stage seemed to have the concentrated power of a great work of literature. The work I'm thinking of is ''The Scarlet Letter.''</p>
        <p>Another element linking the three books is the character of Nathan Zuckerman -- your alter ego, some people have said.</p>
        <p>Alter brain.</p>
        <p>Your alter brain. He's been with you since ''The Ghost Writer,'' right?</p>
        <p>A long time. I thought I had abandoned him after ''The Prague Orgy.'' But in ''American Pastoral'' this mediating intelligence named Nathan Zuckerman solved the problem of how to launch the book. Only when I got Zuckerman in there thinking could I get the story of the Lvovs going. I'd begun the book some 20 years earlier, near the end of the Vietnam War. I wrote about 70 pages but never knew how to proceed after the daughter blew up a building to protest the war. Each time I'd finish another book I went back and reread the 70 pages, but only after finishing ''Sabbath's Theater,'' when I'd had Mickey Sabbath up to here -- you know, I too had to live with the great disorder that is this man, longer even than the poor reader -- only then did I think, Well, here's this orderly man, moderate, kindly, decent by every conventional standard, everything that Sabbath isn't, and what a change it would be to start imagining him. That's how the Swede became everything to me, and how I came to present him -- as I hadn't the first time around -- as though Zuckerman had known him as a boyhood idol. Zuckerman was my insider, my knowledgeable wedge into the Swede's life, who somehow gave me the freedom to know him. On Page 90 I jettisoned Zuckerman -- he was no longer necessary.</p>
        <p>In the next book, ''I Married a Communist,'' Zuckerman's not just a mediating presence. He's a real character in that story.</p>
        <p>He's a real ear in that story, at least half the time. He listens to the story of Ira Ringold being told by his brother, Murray Ringold, as Murray knows Ira's story. Then, in alternate chapters, more or less, Zuckerman tells the story as he knows it. Murray and Zuckerman pass the narrative ball back and forth down the court until the story of Ira's failure is recorded unto the last betrayal -- betrayal being the book's subject, since it was, in every conceivable way, the master obsession of the McCarthy era. It's a very different subject from ''American Pastoral,'' and it sparks a different kind of storytelling.</p>
        <p>In the new book, Zuckerman has yet a different role.</p>
        <p>Yes, he's more of an actor in the ongoing events than he is in the previous two books. He's a friend, Coleman Silk's friend. He's lonely and he makes a friend of Coleman and then he loses him. And when he sets out to reconstruct the lost friend's story, he discovers a secret biography unknown not just to him but to virtually everyone else.</p>
        <p>To get back to the subject matter of ''The Human Stain,'' the events of 1998 certainly get talked about, but the most obvious thing is that this is a book about a black man who passes as a white man, as a Jew. It's a book, you could say, about issues of race and of Judaism and where the two intersect.</p>
        <p>Not race and Judaism. There's nothing about Judaism in this book.</p>
        <p>Well, he does choose to take on a Jewish identity.</p>
        <p>As a means of deception, as a social disguise, as a pretext for his appearance. He doesn't want to be a Jew for anything like the reasons that Frank Alpine, say, in Malamud's novel ''The Assistant'' wants to be a Jew. Coleman's choice has nothing to do with the ethical, spiritual, theological or historical aspects of Judaism. It has nothing to do with wanting to belong to another ''we.'' It's a cunning choice that successfully furnishes him with a disguise in the flight from his own ''we.'' The choice is strictly utilitarian -- as so much is for this man.</p>
        <p>Where did the idea come from?</p>
        <p>It goes back to Chicago, where I went to graduate school in the middle 50's and where I returned to live for a couple of years after the Army. Chicago furnished me with my first look at the big world. It was the first time I really felt, saw, registered, the black presence in an American city or, in the slightest way, became personally engaged with blacks. When I was growing up in Newark in the 30's and 40's, we were all -- Irish, Italians, Slavs, blacks, Jews -- settled and secure in different neighborhoods. There was barely any social overlap and the black population was, in fact, relatively small in those days. Newark didn't begin becoming the preponderantly black city that it is today until about 1950, the time I was leaving for college. But the Chicago I landed in was something else. And when I was a graduate student at the University of Chicago I met a girl from another Chicago college whom I had a little graduate-student fling with, and who was, as we then said, a Negro -- moreover, a Negro from a professional family. I don't think I'd understood before then that a black middle class of any size existed, and her family came as news to me -- as I surely did to them. Anyway, we began to go out, and I met the family, who were very pale Negroes, decidedly so on her mother's side. And I never forgot her mother saying that there were relatives of hers who'd been lost to all their people. That was the phrase she used -- lost to all their people.'' The girl explained to me later what her mother was talking about -- that these relatives, who could physically pull it off, had given up identifying themselves as Negro, had moved away and had joined the white world, never to return. And that I never forgot, though I certainly never imagined that in such a story there was a subject for me. Yet both the story and the people made a lasting impression. Self-transformation. Self-invention. The alternative destiny. Repudiating the past. Powerful stuff.</p>
        <p>What does the trilogy say about us? If it's a sort of report card about America, how are we doing?</p>
        <p>That's a question worth asking, but not of me. We're talking about more than a thousand pages of fiction. I just wanted these historical debacles to enter into and pass through the characters -- I just wanted to find out what that would be like. Mostly I wanted to find out what a novel would have to be like in order not to be a report card about America but a work of fiction about America.</p>
        <p>What's next? You've said that one book often spurs the next one.</p>
        <p>I want to get off the grand kick. I want to clear my head of all this seriousness.</p>
        <p>You're working on a comic novel?</p>
        <p>(Laughing.) No, I want another voice for now. For six months, a year, I'd like to look at things another way. I'm trying to shake loose of the dark Zuckerman take on American life.</p>
        <p>There was a time in your life when you were spending a certain amount of energy writing about other writers, especially Eastern European writers. Is there something analogous to that now?</p>
        <p>No. I edited the Other Europe series for Penguin from '74 until '89. I was reading all these Eastern European novels in translation, I was meeting Eastern European writers, some over there, some in exile, and all of this was news to me. I was also, at this time, living some seven months of each year in London, and so, without much trouble, I was in Paris frequently, and in Prague, and I was in Jerusalem a lot. When I came home from England for good in '89, it was really my rediscovering America as a writer. I came back, in fact, because I felt out of touch. Not that I didn't know what was going on here from reading the paper, but what was missing was the daily immediacy of what people were saying and thinking -- missing was everything that was going on by the way. If, for instance, I had been living elsewhere in 1998 I never could have written ''The Human Stain.'' From afar I couldn't have responded as viscerally as I did to the moral atmosphere of 1998, which had much to do with my imagining the story of how Coleman Silk gets done in. When I look back now, I see that ''Sabbath's Theater'' is the real turning back to American stuff. Mickey Sabbath's is such an American voice. And after him, if not out of him, came the American trilogy. And I see from what I'm writing right now that even if I try, I can't steer clear of our common history creeping thematically into my work. This is a result of growing older, I suppose. You don't have a historical perspective for a long time. A historical perspective requires time. Then, alas, time passes, you've got one and you're stuck with it.</p>
        <p>INTERVIEW Charles McGrath is the editor of the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles McGrath is the editor of the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
