<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Outing Ends in Tragedy and a Hail of 'If Onlys'</title>
    <meta content="07RIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Great Adventure Amusement Park (Jackson Township, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pace, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDD1E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Outing Ends in Tragedy and a Hail of 'If Onlys'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on tragic death of Riverhead High School senior Robert D Pace, whose body was found near railroad tracks east of Bethpage, Long Island; teen, possible suicide, was arrested on drug possession charges during chaparoned school trip to Great Adventure amusement park; police released him in his own custody but charter buses returned to Riverhead without him; school officials, chaparones and police deny responsibility; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNTIL three weeks ago, Karen and Robert Pace had been eagerly looking forward to the graduation of their son, Robert D. Pace, from Riverhead High School. Now they are setting up a memorial fund in their son's name dedicated to preventing what happened to him from happening to anyone else's child.</p>
        <p>Robert, a National Honor Society member who planned to study physical therapy at Quinnipiac College in Hamden, Conn., this fall, had gone with more than 80 classmates and 8 chaperons on a school-sponsored bus trip to Great Adventure in Jackson, N.J., on April 14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNTIL three weeks ago, Karen and Robert Pace had been eagerly looking forward to the graduation of their son, Robert D. Pace, from Riverhead High School. Now they are setting up a memorial fund in their son's name dedicated to preventing what happened to him from happening to anyone else's child.</p>
        <p>Robert, a National Honor Society member who planned to study physical therapy at Quinnipiac College in Hamden, Conn., this fall, had gone with more than 80 classmates and 8 chaperons on a school-sponsored bus trip to Great Adventure in Jackson, N.J., on April 14.</p>
        <p>That Friday was a special day at the sprawling amusement park. An event called Physics 2000, opened only to school groups, was intended to allow students to study laws of physics as they applied to the park's rides.</p>
        <p>But when Robert, who turned 18 in January, went through a metal detector at the gate, his keys set off a security alarm, and a nightmare began to unfold.</p>
        <p>Park security guards found a small amount of drugs in Robert's backpack and turned him over to the Jackson Township police. He was arrested and held for three hours, then was released in his own custody, all without having made contact with his parents or his chaperons.</p>
        <p>At 5:30 the next morning, 14 hours after Robert was last seen in the lobby of the Jackson Township police department and 9 hours after the charter buses had returned to Riverhead without him, a detective for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority reached Robert's parents, who had been desperately trying to locate their son after belatedly learning of his arrest. Robert's body, the detective told them, had been found by the railroad tracks east of Bethpage.</p>
        <p>The Nassau County Medical Examiner's Office said last week that the cause of death had not been determined pending test results and police investigation. But a Metropolitan Transportation Authority official, speaking on condition that he not be identified, said Robert had jumped between the cars of the moving train after leaving a suicide note expressing remorse for letting his parents down.</p>
        <p>Flags were lowered to half staff and activities canceled at the high school the Monday after Robert's death, and students and friends of the Pace family filled St. John the Evangelist Roman Catholic Church for funeral services the next day. At the Paces' home at the end of a quiet residential street in Riverhead, the walls quickly filled with photos of Rob, as he was called, and poignant messages penned on poster boards by classmates.</p>
        <p>The Paces, whose oldest child is a teacher in California, said they had been overwhelmed by the support. But they said they also want to know how school officials and the trip chaperons could have let the buses leave New Jersey without Robert, or without making sure, at least, that Robert knew that his parents were on the way.</p>
        <p>The result, they said, was that their son was abandoned at a police station far from home after events that may have left him devastated, ashamed and in an emotional tailspin.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to point fingers at all,'' Mr. Pace said. ''My wife and I have been nothing but supporters of the school and we know there are human errors. But I want the truth.''</p>
        <p>Last week, an awful story of failures in communications, missed opportunities and tragic circumstances had emerged, but many questions  remained.</p>
        <p>It was still not clear how hard the park or the police tried to inform Robert's chaperons of his arrest, nor when the message finally got through. It was unclear whether the chaperons were duly diligent in trying to contact Robert in custody.</p>
        <p>Also unclear was how Robert got from Jackson, where there is no public transportation, to Manhattan, where he boarded a Long Island Rail Road train to Ronkonkoma at Penn Station on Friday night after making a call to a friend who was not home, but whose phone recorded the incoming number.</p>
        <p>For Karen Pace, torn by feelings of anger and sorrow, one question stands out. Why, she asked, hadn't anyone gone the extra yard that might have saved her son, and assured that ''when he was released into that lobby there was someone there.''</p>
        <p>''Even an extra foot would have prevented this whole thing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>It was not a view shared by the Riverhead school superintendent, Robert J. Holmes, or by the Jackson police and officials at Great Adventure, who said Robert's death was a tragedy but that they had not only acted properly but had gone out of their way to help him.</p>
        <p>The chaperons, Dr. Holmes said, ''did everything possible to assure the young man's safety,'' but had been stymied by the Jackson police, who he said blocked contact with Robert and strongly discouraged the chaperons from going to the police station.</p>
        <p>Dr. Holmes said that when the Riverhead buses left the park at 5:30 p.m. Friday with all students except Robert, the chaperons believed that the police would only release Robert to his parents and that the parents were on the way to pick him up.</p>
        <p>''It's unthinkable for anyone to imply that we would leave a kid somewhere,'' he said. ''That absolutely would never happen.''</p>
        <p>But the Jackson police released an audio tape and transcript of a call in which they said an associate high school principal from Riverhead, Joseph E. Ogeka, told Robert's arresting officer, Anthony Salisbury, that ''I don't want him going back on the bus with our kids'' and that he would have to be picked up by his parents or make other arrangements. Last week Mr. Ogeka acknowledged that he had also told the chaperons that Robert was no longer on the trip.</p>
        <p>Contradicting the assertion by Dr. Holmes that chaperons tried repeatedly to make contact with Robert at the police station, the police said there was no record of calls from any chaperon. All school contact was with Mr. Ogeka, they said.</p>
        <p>The Paces said the school's failure to bring Robert home broke a sacred trust.</p>
        <p>''We strongly believe that when you send your child on a school field trip, the school should make sure that child arrives home safely,'' Mrs. Pace said. ''I have been a chaperon many times, and I knew I was responsible for bringing every child back.''</p>
        <p>Instead, she said, she and her husband learned of Robert's arrest from Mr. Ogeka after 3 p.m., more than four hours after it occurred, and were informed only then that they would have to pick him up. But before they could leave, they said, they learned he was no longer at the police station.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ogeka defended his decision barring Robert from the bus, saying that once Robert was arrested for drug possession it became ''a police matter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ogeka said he had called the Jackson police as soon as he learned of the arrest -- he says he got word from the chaperons between 2 and 3 p.m., though a Great Adventure guard, Agnes Whitfield, said it was about 12:50 -- and then made many efforts to call the Paces at home, without success. Then, after getting a work number for Mrs. Pace from the Jackson police, Mr. Ogeka began dialing again. But the police tape reveals that the police gave Mr. Ogeka a work number for Mrs. Pace that had an incorrect last digit.</p>
        <p>With the help of a school employee who knew where Mrs. Pace worked, Mr. Ogeka eventually got the right number. Had he reached Mrs. Pace sooner, her subsequent call to the police asking that Robert stay at the station might have been made before he was released.</p>
        <p>Also, Officer Salisbury had made a request to a local judge that Robert, described by the police as polite, clean-cut and cooperative, be released in his own recognizance rather than held on $1,000 bail.</p>
        <p>Had bail been imposed, Robert would have been held at the jail until his parents arrived. But because at 18 Robert was legally an adult, once the judge freed him the police had no authority to hold him for his parents.</p>
        <p>These were only two of the misfortunes that befell Robert after he was stopped at the Great Adventure entrance gate at 11:13 a.m.</p>
        <p>A classmate who later gave a statement to a private investigator hired by the Pace family said Robert looked at her and shook his head as he was led away. She said two of Robert's friends told her that ''Rob got his bags searched and they found drugs.'' But news of the arrest evidently did not reach the chaperons until nearly two hours later, at the earliest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitfield said a search of Robert revealed substances that prompted a call to Jackson police. ''He told us this couldn't be happening to him, he was already on probation,'' said Ms. Whitfield.</p>
        <p>In fact, marijuana-related charges Robert faced when still a minor had resulted in an action in contemplation of dismissal, meaning charges would be dropped if there were no subsequent offenses. The legal trouble Robert found himself in at Great Adventure jeoparized that outcome.</p>
        <p>''He saw his whole life flash before his eyes and he thought it was over,'' his mother said.</p>
        <p>The police arrest report said that Robert was in possession of two-and-a-half marijuana cigarettes, four Ecstasy pills and a small amount of cocaine, and that he told the police he ''was going to use it later.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitfield said she asked Robert for the name of the head chaperon and had him paged at 15-minute intervals on the park's public address system, but to no avail. The chaperons and four of the students, according to the school and the Paces' private investigator, said they never heard any such page.</p>
        <p>When the chaperons appeared at security -- shortly before 1 p.m., according to Ms. Whitfield; after 2, according to Dr. Holmes -- Robert had already been taken away from the park, alone and in handcuffs, by the Jackson police.</p>
        <p>One of the chaperons called Mr. Ogeka in Riverhead to report the arrest, and Mr. Ogeka contacted Robert's mother.</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Pace called Officer Salisbury at 3:30 p.m. asking directions for the more than three-hour trip from Long Island and requesting that Robert be told they were on the way, the officer, who was going off duty, consented. But after hanging up, Officer Salisbury reported, he discovered that Robert, who had already been released, had left the lobby.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pace, a secretary at a doctor's office in Southampton, said she called the Jackson police again several minutes later after arriving home from work, asking them to tell Robert to call home.</p>
        <p>By then Officer Salisbury had left for the day and another officer told her Robert was gone. According to Mrs. Pace, the police also told her incorrectly that Robert had taken a taxi back to Great Adventure, 15 miles from police headquarters.</p>
        <p>Hoping that Robert might return to the bus, the Paces then tried unsuccessfully to learn if he was on board. But, she said, a chaperon with a cell phone had turned it off and the bus company said the buses were out of range for radio communications.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pace said she was seized by ''a motherly instinct that I had to get a hold of him as soon as possible.'' So at about 6:30, the Paces left Riverhead for Jackson, carrying a cell phone and a gnawing fear that their son was not on the bus coming in the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>On the bus, the female classmate told the Pace family in her written statement, ''It was kind of like Rob wasn't ever on the trip, kind of like they didn't even try hard enough to find out what was happening and make sure he was O.K.''</p>
        <p>Still en route to Jackson, the Paces learned that they had guessed right: the buses had arrived in Riverhead at 8:30 p.m. without Rob.</p>
        <p>A short time later, Mrs. Pace said, she and her husband arrived at the Jackson police headquarters.</p>
        <p>''The Jackson police need some sensitivity training,'' she said. ''When we got there, we felt that they weren't taking this as seriously as they should. They kept saying to me, 'He's 18.' And I said, 'I don't care that he's 18.' ''</p>
        <p>At the Paces' urging, the Jackson police began searching the area for Robert. But between 10 and 11 p.m., Mrs. Pace said, a detective from the Metropolitan Transportation Authority called to inform them that Robert's book bag had been found on a Ronkonkoma-bound train.</p>
        <p>The Paces drove back to Riverhead, hoping to find Robert at home. When they arrived at 3 a.m., the house was empty. ''We then made up 'missing person' flyers and drove to Ronkonkoma, planning on putting them up at each train station, hoping for some news,'' she wrote.</p>
        <p>At Ronkonkoma, they received a call from a railroad detective who was at their home in Riverhead. ''He asked us to wait for him there and we then discovered the news that will change our lives forever,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Young people who knew Robert described him as popular and anxious to move on to college. His serious purpose showed in the volunteer work he did at a physical therapy treatment center in Wading River. He was also a founding member of the Riverhead Youth Court, a peer court in the schools, and worked five days a week at a marina in Flanders. His parents said he was an avid snow-boarder, loved baseball and studied tae kwon do.</p>
        <p>''He had tremendously high aspirations for himself,'' said Mrs. Pace. Her husband added: ''Rob was the one who was always ready to give of himself. He was and is my role model.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
