<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bitter 6-Month Strike at Overnite Poses a Test for Teamsters' Chief</title>
    <meta content="07TEAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Overnite Transportation Company</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Teamsters</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffa, James P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DA1538F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bitter 6-Month Strike at Overnite Poses a Test for Teamsters' Chief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, May 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Teamsters' bitter six-month strike against Overnite Transportation Company has left union members struggling to pay bills, hammered company's bottom line, and become major test for James P Hoffa in his first year as union leader; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wayne Smith, a loading-dock worker who has been on strike since last October, was unmistakably glum as he picked through the union's food bank for tomato sauce, pasta and breakfast cereal to feed his five young daughters.</p>
        <p>Despite his family's hard times, Mr. Smith, a large, barrel-chested man, vowed to hold out as long as it takes in the grueling strike that has become James P. Hoffa's biggest labor battle in his first year as Teamsters' president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wayne Smith, a loading-dock worker who has been on strike since last October, was unmistakably glum as he picked through the union's food bank for tomato sauce, pasta and breakfast cereal to feed his five young daughters.</p>
        <p>Despite his family's hard times, Mr. Smith, a large, barrel-chested man, vowed to hold out as long as it takes in the grueling strike that has become James P. Hoffa's biggest labor battle in his first year as Teamsters' president.</p>
        <p>So far the six-month war looks like a draw, a very painful draw, that has many Teamsters struggling to pay their bills, while the union's adversary, the Overnite Transportation Company, has had its bottom line hammered.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of tough getting by, but the company, they're still not treating people right,'' Mr. Smith said as he and his wife, Tamyko, stuffed 20 pounds of free groceries into a large box at Teamsters' Local 728. ''The food bank helps a lot, but it's hard when you have five kids.''</p>
        <p>The Overnite fight has become not only one of the nation's most closely watched labor showdowns, but also a brawl between a union renowned for its toughness and a scrappy company that is showing just as much grit. Neither Mr. Hoffa nor Overnite's parent company, Union Pacific, has offered the slightest hint of blinking.</p>
        <p>''Eventually Union Pacific is going to get the message that they have to come to terms with the workers at Overnite,'' Mr. Hoffa said.</p>
        <p>To raise the stakes, Mr. Hoffa said the union was planning a federal racketeering lawsuit that would charge Overnite with breaking the law hundreds of times, by, for example, firing many union supporters, as part of a strategy to do anything to avoid a union contract. The company denies using illegal tactics.</p>
        <p>That would follow a racketeering lawsuit that Overnite has brought against the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, accusing its members of firing shots at drivers who have crossed the picket line. In the most serious incident, an Overnite trucker was shot in the stomach while driving outside Memphis. Teamster officials deny advocating violence and say Overnite is exaggerating the incidents to win sympathy.</p>
        <p>Mark Goodwin, a senior vice president at Overnite, said: ''It's true no one has proven yet that they are responsible for the shootings, but we never had any shootings before. For them to deny the violence is ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa has much at stake. He wants to show that the Teamsters can increase membership in its core freight division. That division was his father's base, and his father, James R. Hoffa, boasted that his crowning achievement while running the union was securing a nationwide freight agreement that greatly improved drivers' wages and benefits.</p>
        <p>Many teamsters say the younger Hoffa, with an eye to next year's re-election campaign, hopes to be able to boast by then that he has signed a contract with Overnite and unionized most of its 166 terminals. With 8,200 drivers and dockworkers, Overnite is the nation's largest nonunion company that specializes in carrying less than full truckloads.</p>
        <p>The broader labor movement sees major stakes in the Overnite dispute. Many labor leaders say it is the most flagrant example of how unions, after surmounting numerous obstacles to get workers to vote in a union, then face a hard time getting companies to sign a first contract.</p>
        <p>At several Overnite terminals the drivers and dockworkers voted to unionize more than five years ago, but they still do not have a contract. The union says it represents 3,600 workers at 37 terminals, but the company says that because of legal challenges the union represents only 1,800 at 22 sites. The company estimates that 700 workers are on strike, while the union puts the number at 1,700.</p>
        <p>For one of those strikers, Eddie Dunn, at Overnite for 24 years, the stakes are highly personal and boil down to regaining dignity at work.</p>
        <p>While walking the picket line in front of Overnite's large terminal in Atlanta, Mr. Dunn talked about how managers there  sought five years ago to force the most senior workers to take early retirement or to work part time without benefits. He also complained that no matter how hard he worked unloading trucks, a manager always questioned why he could not work faster.</p>
        <p>''They treated you like you weren't a human being,'' he said. ''They want to intimidate you. They always want you to do more and more and more. Sometimes after the way they treat you, you feel like crying. They want to rile you, and if you say something, you're fired, you're gone.''</p>
        <p>Almost half of the 200 workers at the  terminal here are on strike, walking the picket line since October. Members of the  clergy have walked with them and other unions have donated $50,000 to help with their food bills and mortgage payments.</p>
        <p>''We went through Thanksgiving, Christmas and New Year's out here, and they thought once the first snowfall came, we would fold,'' Mr. Dunn said. ''We're serious here. We're fighting for a better future. If we don't win, our kids will face a future with jobs paying $5 or $6 an hour, subcontracting, no benefits, no nothing.''</p>
        <p>On the picket line, some 30 strikers poured out tales about how they felt mistreated by Overnite. One truck driver said he felt insulted when a manager called his doctor to ask whether a note saying he was sick was forged. Another driver said that after going for 10 years without a critical write-up, he got a notice putting him at the brink of dismissal, just days after signing a petition favoring a union.</p>
        <p>Frank Williams, a driver for 27 years, said: ''The main reason we're striking now, it's not for benefits or money. It's about Overnite not being fair to the workers.'' Overnite drivers earn nearly $18 an hour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams, a wiry man wearing an Atlanta Falcons shirt, said something was profoundly amiss when a majority of the 200 workers at the Atlanta terminal voted to unionize in 1995, and Overnite has still not signed a contract with the union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa said: ''The fact is they're not negotiating in good faith. We have had 163 negotiating sessions with little or no progress. That tells you the story of whether or not they really want a contract.''</p>
        <p>But Overnite officials insisted that they were bargaining in good faith and blamed the union for often postponing negotiating sessions. Mr. Goodwin held out little hope for a settlement, saying the company would never accept the union's demand to place Overnite workers in the Teamsters' pension fund. He said Overnite's pension fund was in excellent shape, while the Teamsters' pension fund was underfinanced.</p>
        <p>''We've worked diligently at trying to reach an agreement with them,'' Mr. Goodwin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa sees a more fundamental reason behind the failure to reach a settlement: a visceral anti-union animus. He said the dispute had cost the company far more than a settlement would have. Overnite has spent tens of millions of dollars fighting the walkout, its financial performance over the last half year has been considerably worse than that of its major competitors, and many analysts say the dispute has hurt Union Pacific's stock price.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Goodwin asserted that Overnite's revenues were growing and that it returned to the black in the first quarter. He said that the cost of a union contract would make the company less competitive and would far outweigh whatever costs the company had suffered because of the walkout.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
