<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; Sit Right Back and Hear A Tale of TV Gone Insane</title>
    <meta content="07MACG$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macgregor, Jeff</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gilligan's Island (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5D61438F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; Sit Right Back and Hear A Tale of TV Gone Insane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF MacGREGOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macgregor, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on television program Survivor imagines script of Gilligan's Island, with Skipper voted off the island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE camera TILTS DOWN to reveal seven people, castaways perhaps, sitting on the beach of an uncharted desert island. They seem stranded. They also look familiar. Gentle trade winds fan the palm trees behind them.</p>
        <p>THEME MUSIC UP AND OUT.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE camera TILTS DOWN to reveal seven people, castaways perhaps, sitting on the beach of an uncharted desert island. They seem stranded. They also look familiar. Gentle trade winds fan the palm trees behind them.</p>
        <p>THEME MUSIC UP AND OUT.</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: Now let me get this straight. CBS says we can vote each other off the island?</p>
        <p>THE PROFESSOR: Yes, Skipper, that's right.</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: So we can vote against people we don't like? But why?</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: Well, it's part of the new trend toward what you might call ''reality-based game programming,'' Skipper. They maroon a group of real people, contestants, on an island like this. They keep hundreds of cameras and microphones pointed at them 24 hours a day to record everything they say and do. People are voted out of the group one by one. After a few weeks their small society, a microcosm of the world at large if you will, devolves into something out of ''Lord of the Flies.'' CBS awards the final contestant a million dollars or something.</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: Gee, Skipper, a million dollars!</p>
        <p>SKIPPER (Hits Gilligan hard with his hat): Pipe down!</p>
        <p>GINGER: I don't think that's entertaining at all!</p>
        <p>MARY ANN: Neither do I! It's just mean. And discourteous.</p>
        <p>THURSTON HOWELL III: A million dollars? Hah! I carry more than that folded in my cummerbund.</p>
        <p>LOVEY HOWELL: It does seem, well, rather uncharitable.</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: It was originally produced in Europe. . . .</p>
        <p>ALL: Ohhhhhhhhhh.</p>
        <p>They sit quietly for a few moments, the only SOUND the WAVES LAPPING AT THE SAND.</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: And television in general is becoming more Darwinian, I venture, ''survival of the fittest'' now defining both content qua content and the larger issues of vertically integrated corporate performance vis-a-vis media gigantism and economies of relative scale --</p>
        <p>SKIPPER (interrupting): I vote the Professor off the island!</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: But I was just . . .</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: Do you have any idea how sick to death we are of your endless lectures? Of your crypto-intellectual condescension?</p>
        <p>ALL: Yeah!</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: You're useless to us! You can make a linear particle accelerator out of two mangos and a clam shell, but in 35 years you couldn't patch the hole in a wooden boat?</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: Yes, well, I tried several times. . . .</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: It's some boards and a hammer, Brainiac.</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: And don't think we don't know about you and Ginger down at the lagoon.</p>
        <p>PROFESSOR: Oh my. (Takes coconut cell phone and EXITS.)</p>
        <p>MARY ANN: You too, Suzie Floozy, hit the bricks. And leave me that blue gown with the bugle beads.</p>
        <p>GINGER: But, but . . . Oh Gillie, help me!</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: Pound sand, baby. It's over. (GINGER EXITS.)</p>
        <p>As twilight comes to the little island, SKIPPER lights the Tiki torches.</p>
        <p>THURSTON: I never liked them. Common, really.</p>
        <p>LOVEY: I don't know how to say this, dear, but I think you should go too.</p>
        <p>THURSTON (sputtering): Me? Lovey! Why?</p>
        <p>LOVEY: You've been bringing a teddy bear to bed with us for nearly half a century, dear, and you need to ask why? You packed a cummerbund for a three-hour tour? You're clinically insane.</p>
        <p>MARY ANN: And he's miserly, don't forget miserly!</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: He treats us all like servants! Capitalist oppressor!</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: Wall Street lickspittles! They should both go! Eat the rich!</p>
        <p>ALL (chanting now): Eat the rich! Eat the rich! (They advance on the HOWELLS with sharpened sticks. LOVEY and THURSTON scurry into the jungle.)</p>
        <p>MARY ANN: Good riddance to Lord and Lady Pinchpenny, I say.</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN (Smearing his face with blood red berries in the primal firelight): Now we are three. Two men and a woman alone. Night comes to the jungle.</p>
        <p>MARY ANN: Yikes! (She flees.)</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: Heh, heh. You're laying it on a little thick there, Little Buddy, don't you think?</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: Don't ''Little Buddy'' me, you abusive blubbersack. You touch me with that hat again and I'll kill you. Just how long did you think I was going to be your scapegoat, your dimwitted sidekick? Who put you in charge, anyway? It's your fault we're still here! Good god, man, we've been visited by four cosmonauts, two super-intelligent chimps and the Harlem Globetrotters! We could have built 20 space shuttles out of what washed up on this very beach! You couldn't find a way to get us home?</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: But Little Buddy, I --</p>
        <p>GILLIGAN: Shut your snackhole, fatty, I'm not done yet. To think of the years I've wasted putting up with your bullying, your insults, your impotent, passive-aggressive rage. . . . Don't blame me for your low self-esteem, roundboy, it's not my fault you've been living on nothing but fruit and fish since 1964 but haven't lost an ounce! And don't think I don't feel your eyes on me at night in the hut. . . .</p>
        <p>SKIPPER: Aw, Gilligan. (A stone the size of a fist whizzes past his head.) Yikes! (He flees.)</p>
        <p>As the camera CRANES UP we see GILLIGAN, naked now in the dying light of the fire, grotesque and mud-covered, roasting the bones of a small animal and talking to himself.</p>
        <p>ANNOUNCER: Join us again next week when the former cast of ''Fantasy Island'' plays ''Celebrity Survivor'' here on CBS! FADE TO BLACK.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
