<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martinez Fans 17, But Loses</title>
    <meta content="AM7" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DA1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martinez Fans 17, But Loses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tampa Bay Devil Rays defeat Boston Red Sox, 1-0; other American League games noted; tables (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Pedro Martinez tried to support his teammates, he got suspended. When they failed to support him, he picked up a loss.</p>
        <p>The Boston Red Sox ace matched a career-high with 17 strikeouts yesterday, but was outdueled by Steve Trachsel, who pitched a three-hit shutout to lead the Tampa Bay Devil Rays to a 1-0 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Pedro Martinez tried to support his teammates, he got suspended. When they failed to support him, he picked up a loss.</p>
        <p>The Boston Red Sox ace matched a career-high with 17 strikeouts yesterday, but was outdueled by Steve Trachsel, who pitched a three-hit shutout to lead the Tampa Bay Devil Rays to a 1-0 victory.</p>
        <p>''He goes out there and pitches that way, and we can't score one run to support him,'' Red Sox first baseman Brian Daubach said. ''I feel almost as bad as last year, when we lost in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>The loss ended Martinez's 13-game winning streak, and he'll have an extra day to stew over it: The Red Sox announced in the ninth inning that he had withdrawn the appeal of his five-game suspension and will start serving it today. He is scheduled to pitch Friday, one day later than normal.</p>
        <p>''Probably the best thing to do is move on, put things behind us,'' Boston Manager Jimy Williams said. ''Go ahead and serve the five games and then pitch.''</p>
        <p>Martinez (5-1) fanned six batters through two innings and had 12 strikeouts after five. The 17 strikeouts were the most in the majors this season and matched Martinez's 17-strikeout one-hitter against the Yankees on Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>''When he took the mound, he decided he wasn't going to give an inch,'' said Trachsel (2-2), who walked three and struck out a career-high 11 for his third career shutout. ''I knew it was going to be a tough game.''</p>
        <p>Martinez struck out Miguel Cairo to start the eighth for No. 16, then Gerald Williams grounded out before Dave Martinez singled and stole second. Vaughn worked the count full before singling to center.</p>
        <p>Martinez was making his scheduled start despite receiving a five-game suspension on Wednesday, three days after he hit Cleveland's Roberto Alomar with a pitch. He was allowed to pitch pending the appeal.</p>
        <p>''He decided to do that because this allows him to take his regular turn Friday in Baltimore,'' said Dan Duquette, the Red Sox general manager. ''It's better for us that Pedro is focused on his next start rather than go through the process.''</p>
        <p>INDIANS 8, BLUE JAYS 6: Catcher Einar Diaz hit a go-ahead two-run single in the eighth inning and Cleveland ended its six-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Diaz is hitting .447 (21 for 47) since replacing Sandy Alomar in the starting lineup. Alomar, who is on the 15-day disabled list with a strained right hamstring, could rejoin the Indians on Monday.</p>
        <p>Homer Bush's run-scoring double gave Toronto a 6-5 lead in the seventh, but the Indians rallied for two runs on Diaz's single. Toronto starter Chris Carpenter left after walking Jim Thome. Reliever Paul Quantrill then gave up a hit to Richie Sexson and walked Travis Fryman before Diaz singled to right.</p>
        <p>Quantrill (0-1) took the loss. Ricardo Rincon (1-0) pitched one-third of an inning for the victory.</p>
        <p>TWINS 6, TIGERS 1: The return of Manager Phil Garner and third baseman Dean Palmer didn't help Detroi.</p>
        <p>Mark Redman pitched seven strong innings as host Minnesota beat Detroit in the first game following the end of a pair of eight-game suspensions imposed on the two Tigers.</p>
        <p>Garner and Palmer were penalized by the commissioner's office for their roles in a bench-clearing brawl against the Chicago White Sox on April 22.</p>
        <p>Palmer went 1 for 4 and committed a two-out error on Cristian Guzman's routine grounder in the fourth, leading to the Twins' third run.</p>
        <p>Detroit's Juan Encarnacion extended his major league-leading hitting streak to 18 games with an infield single in the sixth inning.</p>
        <p>Redman (2-0), making his first start this season, allowed one run and eight hits, striking out six and walking none.</p>
        <p>ROYALS 11, WHITE SOX 5: Johnny Damon hit a pair of two-run homers and went 4 for 5 for host Kansas City, which sent Chicago to its fifth loss in six games.</p>
        <p>Every Kansas City starter had at least one hit, and reliever Jerry Spradlin (1-1) allowed two hits in four shutout innings.</p>
        <p>Kansas City (15-15) reached .500 for the first time since it was 8-8 on April 19. The Royals, 13-4 at home this season, finished with a season-high 18 hits, including Mark Quinn's eighth-inning homer off Kelly Wunsch.</p>
        <p>Damon tied the score at 2-2 in the third with a homer off Mike Sirotka (2-3).</p>
        <p>Mike Sweeney singled with two outs and scored the go-ahead run on Jermaine Dye's triple, and Quinn followed with an RBI single.</p>
        <p>MARINERS 1, ANGELS 0: Mark McLemore's ninth-inning single gave host Seattle a victory over Anaheim.</p>
        <p>McLemore, who hit .274 for Texas last season, singled to center off Mike Holtz (0-1) after David Bell opened the inning with a single, Charles Gipson came in to run and Dan Wilson sacrificed.</p>
        <p>Seattle won its first 1-0 game this season, while the Angels lost their second 1-0 game.</p>
        <p>McLemore went 2 for 3 to raise his average to .218.</p>
        <p>RANGERS 11, ATHLETICS 10: Luis Alicea's run-scoring single in the ninth inning gave host Texas a victory over Oakland, the second straight game the Rangers won with both teams scoring in double figures.</p>
        <p>A day after blowing a 15-7 lead and losing by 17-16, the Athletics wasted leads of 6-1 in the third, 8-6 in the seventh and 10-9 in the ninth yesterday.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
