<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Orchestra Without the Grand Drama</title>
    <meta content="07MET.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Performing Arts Center (Newark)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levine, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kandell, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDE1638F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Orchestra Without the Grand Drama</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KANDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kandell, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Metropolitan Opera artistic director James Levine, who has instituted local and touring free-standing symphony concerts, including upcoming one at New Jersey Performing Arts Center in Newark; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the orchestral programs in Newark next week is all 20th-century music. After a concert version of Bartok's brooding one-act opera ''Bluebeard,'' comes Milhaud's saucy ''Le Boeuf sur le Toit,'' Debussy's ''Danse sacree et danse profane'' and Ravel's sexy ''Bolero.'' It's all performed by the Met Orchestra. Met, that is, as in opera house.</p>
        <p>An opera orchestra that functions symphonically, winning prizes for recordings, is only one development in James Levine's 29-year tenure. Mr. Levine, the Metropolitan Opera's first artistic director, has extended the premise of performing different operas each night. Now the ensemble plays free-standing symphony concerts, locally and on tour. The Newark concert is one of five to be heard in Carnegie Hall this week and next, as the opera season concludes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the orchestral programs in Newark next week is all 20th-century music. After a concert version of Bartok's brooding one-act opera ''Bluebeard,'' comes Milhaud's saucy ''Le Boeuf sur le Toit,'' Debussy's ''Danse sacree et danse profane'' and Ravel's sexy ''Bolero.'' It's all performed by the Met Orchestra. Met, that is, as in opera house.</p>
        <p>An opera orchestra that functions symphonically, winning prizes for recordings, is only one development in James Levine's 29-year tenure. Mr. Levine, the Metropolitan Opera's first artistic director, has extended the premise of performing different operas each night. Now the ensemble plays free-standing symphony concerts, locally and on tour. The Newark concert is one of five to be heard in Carnegie Hall this week and next, as the opera season concludes.</p>
        <p>The orchestra's success results from a cluster of initiatives. Conducting, it has been seen, can turn flat over a long period of unchanged leadership, but Mr. Levine's mastery has grown as he focuses on core musical and technical matters. ''There's an expression he uses,'' said Raymond Gniewek, the concertmaster. ''He says, 'You have to remember that people are hearing this for the first time. It can't sound like the fifth or sixth. It has to be as lively and vital as the first.' ''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Levine leads Wagner's ''Ring'' cycle, for which the recordings (on Deutsche Grammophon) received three consecutive Grammy awards, he paces himself, sober, head down, impassively watching the score, his beat enlarging only for the curse motif. Hour after hour, the spacious music rolls out in an ocean of sound.</p>
        <p>By now, almost every orchestra member is his hire. Sections have two principals who can alternate solos, or perform in the chamber concerts Mr. Levine has instituted. Some concerts showcase particular sections, like strings with solo harp, as in next Friday's Debussy.</p>
        <p>In his spare time, as it were, Mr. Levine plays piano in recital for many of the country's renowned singers, and uses the concert orchestra to accompany others, as he does in ''Bluebeard'' for the bass Samuel Ramey and the mezzo-soprano Anne Sofie von Otter.</p>
        <p>Whether perspiring and blowing kisses after a seven-hour tribute to his 25 years at the Met, on tour with the Three Tenors or playing piano for Beverly Sills and Miss Piggy at a PBS fund-raiser, Mr. Levine makes everyone feel that it's their show, when it's usually his.</p>
        <p>Voice teachers may encourage students to emulate the fluid line of the violin, or the cello's resonance, but the Met Orchestra is praised for its singing tone, which comes from 30 weeks a year of listening to singers. ''One tires of having to find new ways to say how well the Met Orchestra plays for James Levine,'' Bernard Holland wrote in The New York Times, ''but one does not tire of listening to them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gniewek (pronounced NYEH-vik), who points out that the organization is theatrical and not fundamentally symphonic, is retiring after 43 years as concertmaster. As part of Mr. Levine's intermission broadcast tribute to him two weeks ago, Mr. Gniewek was heard in famous ''Thais'' and ''I Lombardi'' violin solos. ''Every night we play different repertory,'' he said. ''It keeps concert performances fresh. They're never routine, though the extra work drives some people crazy. We don't know what goes on behind the scenes, but we know Jimmy fights hard to get funding.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Met and affiliated projects, Mr. Levine, former music director of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra's Ravinia Festival, has been appointed chief conductor of the Munich Philharmonic. His absence doesn't worry Mr. Gniewek, who said: ''Levine can do things with us he can't do with anybody else. He spends more time with the home team than other conductors do.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Valery Gergiev, director of the Mariinsky Theater, which includes the Kirov Opera and Ballet, has become the Met's principal guest conductor. Orchestra members admire his charisma, spirit and ability to communicate, particularly in Russian operas, though assessments of his technique are more cautious. At this point, the orchestra plays its best despite external shortfall, but it is agreed that Mr. Levine doesn't hinder. ''He doesn't believe in plateaus,'' said Mr. Gniewek. ''You're getting better or worse. Things happen because of momentum.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levine has shown himself to be brilliant at managing people's talent. ''He won't say too much,'' Mr. Gniewek said, ''but you start to phrase the way you know it will appeal to him.''</p>
        <p>Some 15 years ago, sitting in his office, he mused on what to expect as he turned 40: ''People have dreams, but I've already gone beyond anything I ever dreamed. I don't know what to dream next.'' Now, he focuses on musical accomplishments. His philosophy, as one player put it, is, ''What a great place to begin.''</p>
        <p>THE MET ORCHESTRA  James Levine, conductor.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark.  May 19, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>(888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
