<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thousands Line Up in Heat To Pay Their Last Respects</title>
    <meta content="07DAY.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE RITES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">St Patrick's Cathedral (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DD1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thousands Line Up in Heat To Pay Their Last Respects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of mourners from across New York region and nation converge on funereal St Patrick's Cathedral to pay last repsects to Cardinal John O'Connor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of mourners from across the New York region and the nation, including many children and disabled people, converged on a funereal St. Patrick's Cathedral yesterday to pay their last respects to Cardinal John O'Connor with prayers, hymns and the ancient rites of Roman Catholicism.</p>
        <p>On a sun-washed spring day with temperatures that climbed into the high 80's, crowds stood for hours in long, slow lines on Fifth Avenue and 50th Street to enter the great cathedral's double doors, draped in black and purple bunting, for a last glimpse of the cardinal, lying in state at the altar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of mourners from across the New York region and the nation, including many children and disabled people, converged on a funereal St. Patrick's Cathedral yesterday to pay their last respects to Cardinal John O'Connor with prayers, hymns and the ancient rites of Roman Catholicism.</p>
        <p>On a sun-washed spring day with temperatures that climbed into the high 80's, crowds stood for hours in long, slow lines on Fifth Avenue and 50th Street to enter the great cathedral's double doors, draped in black and purple bunting, for a last glimpse of the cardinal, lying in state at the altar.</p>
        <p>Streaming under the arched Gothic pillars almost all day and into the evening, a double line of mourners filed past the bier, which was flanked by white-gloved police officers at attention. Many people wept softly and murmured prayers for the cardinal, who died Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The crowds also filled the 2,300-seat pews to overflowing for a morning Mass in Spanish, for an afternoon Mass in English that was organized for children and disabled people, and later for vespers and rosary services. For many it was a day of reflection as well as sorrow for the death of the cardinal, who was 80.</p>
        <p>''He was a wonderful man, a model for Catholicism,'' Frank Rusch, an airline pilot from the West Coast, said after viewing the body cloaked in scarlet and white vestments and lying in a red-velvet-lined mahogany coffin. ''He is very well thought of. I speak of him in the present because he is still with us.''</p>
        <p>As preparations for the cardinal's funeral tomorrow went forward, there was no word from the Vatican on the selection of his successor as the archbishop of New York, although speculation continued to focus on Bishop Edward M. Egan, of the Diocese of Bridgeport, Conn.</p>
        <p>While the selection process is secret, with harsh penalties for anyone who breaks the silence, some church officials have virtually confirmed Bishop Egan's appointment, saying that an announcement as early as Tuesday or Wednesday is likely.</p>
        <p>''It is Egan,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>''I think it's pretty evident,'' another senior church official involved in the early stages of the selection process said. He indicated that the church's highest officials in New York and the Northeast had already been notified, but said they would keep silent out of respect until after the cardinal's funeral.</p>
        <p>President Clinton was to lead a host of dignitaries at the funeral -- 3,500 invitations have gone out -- and the Vatican secretary of state, Cardinal Angelo Sodano, was to represent Pope John Paul II and officiate at tomorrow's 2 p.m. Mass.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's events -- the second of three days of Masses and other services leading to the funeral and burial in the crypt under the altar at St. Patrick's -- gave striking testimony once more to the admiration and respect that millions accorded the cardinal, America's most influential Catholic leader.</p>
        <p>By 10 a.m., when the cathedral opened, the crowds waiting to get in were already enormous. The lines snaked around into 50th Street, then back to Madison Avenue, where they doubled back again to Fifth Avenue and redoubled back toward Madison. And they kept getting larger.</p>
        <p>For some, the day's heat was a torment. About 11:30 a.m., a man in his 70's fainted on the sidewalk. People went to his aid, giving him sips of water and orange slices. He revived a bit and said he had been in line for 90 minutes after walking about a mile to the cathedral from the Port Authority Bus Terminal at 40th Street and Eighth Avenue. Firefighters took him away on a stretcher.</p>
        <p>Some people had flown in from Puerto Rico and other Caribbean islands. Some had come by airplane and bus from other states. Many residents of the metropolitan area  took buses or subways to pay tribute to a man they said had been a friend of the poor, the sick and immigrants struggling to make a new life in America.</p>
        <p>''I loved the cardinal so much, I just had to come,'' said Minnie Stinson, a Bronx homemaker.</p>
        <p>Joel Rosado, 21, a cashier at the Candado Plaza Casino in Old San Juan, P.R., said he had flown to New York with his family for the Mass in Spanish. ''I am really, really Catholic, was raised in a Catholic house,'' he said. ''The cardinal gave so much to the poor and the rich.''</p>
        <p>Maximo Mendoza had come with 18 others from his Bronx church because of the cardinal's support for Hispanic immigrants. ''He opened the door for Mexicans,'' Mr. Mendoza said.</p>
        <p>Joe Doyle, 76, came by bus from Scranton, Pa., where he said he had known John O'Connor as a bishop. More than personable, he recalled, Bishop O'Connor had known many of his parishioners by their first names.</p>
        <p>Marie Kaatz, who drove 77 miles into town from upstate Wingdale, N.Y., with her two children, said: ''It was important to see him. It was very important for the children.'' Alluding to the cardinal's eight-month struggle with brain cancer, she added, ''I feel happy for him because he is at peace, and is where he always wanted to be.''</p>
        <p>Ivan Vasquez, who brought his wife and child from the Bronx, said sadly, ''He meant a lot to us as Catholics.''</p>
        <p>People from Mexico, the Dominican Republic, Cuba and other Caribbean and Latin American nations, as well as many non-Hispanic people, attended the Mass in Spanish, which was celebrated by the Most Rev. Francisco Garmendia, auxiliary bishop of the archdiocese.</p>
        <p>''From the politicians, to the police, to all the nationalities represented here today, we are all brothers today in respect for the cardinal,'' Monsignor Garmendia said. ''We want to thank you, cardinal, for all you did for us in New York.''</p>
        <p>In his homily in Spanish, the Rev. Josu Iriondo, director of the office of Hispanic affairs for the archdiocese, spoke of the cardinal's warm relationship with Hispanic people, of his two visits to Cuba and of his sending food and other aid to hurricane victims. ''He was a lover of life, a defender of life, of the sick, of the poor,'' Father Iriondo said.</p>
        <p>About 40 percent of the 2.4 million Catholics in the archdiocese are of Hispanic descent, church officials say, and about 100 of its 413 parishes are predominantly Hispanic.</p>
        <p>After the Mass, Esperanza Morales, an official of the Tepeyac Association of New York, which represents Mexican immigrants, said: ''He always talked to us in Spanish, and always wanted to help us. We loved him. We want to tell him 'thank you' for all he did for us.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after noon, dozens of buses drew up around the cathedral carrying hundreds of elderly and disabled men and women, many of them in wheelchairs or moving with the aid of walkers, canes or crutches. Also on board were hundreds of children, many mentally or physically disabled. They were helped into the cathedral by counselors and aides from hospitals and nursing homes.</p>
        <p>For the 1 p.m. Mass, pew after pew was filled. Those in wheelchairs sat in the aisles and made new rows. Many in the audience were neither young nor disabled.</p>
        <p>It was relatively cool inside, out of the sun and in the subdued light from the lofty chandeliers and the high, arched stained-glass windows on either side of the nave. Organ music swelled and a choir sang. Many in the crowd fingered rosaries, and some cried softly as the Mass unfolded.</p>
        <p>It began with a processional hymn, ''Sing With All the Saints in Glory,'' followed by a psalm, ''We Shall Go Up With Joy to the House of Our God.'' The Most Rev. Robert A. Brucato, apostolic administrator of the archdiocese, read from the Gospel of John.</p>
        <p>The Mass was sponsored by the archdiocesan Office of Education and its Office of Persons with Disabilities, and Monsignor Brucato spoke of the cardinal's devotion to the disabled and to young people.</p>
        <p>''He was a very concerned man, with a hands-on approach,'' Monsignor Brucato said. He also spoke of the cardinal's friendship with a police officer, Steven McDonald, who was shot and paralyzed in 1986.</p>
        <p>While those in the pews could not see the cardinal, television monitors positioned here and there provided close-up views of the body.</p>
        <p>After the homily, the Mass continued with the Liturgy of the Eucharist and the preparation of the altar for communion. A hymn, ''On Eagle's Wings,'' was sung by Michael Joncas. The Eucharist prayer, including the acclamation ''Holy, Holy, Holy,'' was followed by the communion rites.</p>
        <p>Another hymn, ''I am the Bread of Life,'' was sung by Suzanne Toolan. The concluding rites were the Prayer after Communion and the recessional hymn ''For All the Saints.''</p>
        <p>As the last bars of the recessional faded and the aroma of incense drifted through the cathedral, lines to view the cardinal formed again and moved solemnly forward. One could hear the shuffling of many feet, the creak of wheelchairs, the clink of coins in a poor box. People crossed themselves at the sight of the cardinal and again on the way out.</p>
        <p>Back in the sun's glare on Fifth Avenue, Tanya Melendez, an East Village resident, asked her sons Devon, 10, and David, 9, both students at Our Lady of Pompei School, to reflect on the cardinal.</p>
        <p>''At least he's in a better place,'' Devon said.</p>
        <p>''I think he's in a better place too,'' David said. ''What he's been through has been a great life for him. He lived the way he wanted to live.''</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE RITES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
