<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreigners Leaving Sierra Leone; More Troops Missing</title>
    <meta content="07LEON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DD1238F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreigners Leaving Sierra Leone; More Troops Missing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Foreigners and aid workers leave Sierra Leone as UN reports no progress on freeing more than 300 peacekeepers kidnapped by rebels; 200 more Zambian peacekeepers are also missing (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Foreigners and officials with international relief groups left Sierra Leone today, as the United Nations reported no progress in obtaining the release of more than 300 of its peacekeepers and civilians kidnapped during clashes last week with the rebel Revolutionary United Front.</p>
        <p>Two hundred more Zambian peacekeepers are missing, United Nations officials in New York said, though it was not clear whether they had been taken hostage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Foreigners and officials with international relief groups left Sierra Leone today, as the United Nations reported no progress in obtaining the release of more than 300 of its peacekeepers and civilians kidnapped during clashes last week with the rebel Revolutionary United Front.</p>
        <p>Two hundred more Zambian peacekeepers are missing, United Nations officials in New York said, though it was not clear whether they had been taken hostage.</p>
        <p>Here in the capital, as most people waited to see whether the crisis would prove a bump toward a difficult peace or a descent back into the chaos that engulfed the West African country in recent years, rebel officials gave no indication of yielding to  diplomatic pressure.</p>
        <p>Foday Sankoh, the leader of the Revolutionary United Front, has steadfastly denied his organization's involvement in the kidnappings and the deaths of at least four Kenyan peacekeepers, accusing the United Nations of causing clashes after trying to force some of his men to lay down their weapons. The rebel organization, which is nominally part of a power-sharing national government, repeated its denials today after Mr. Sankoh met with officials from Nigeria and Mali.</p>
        <p>''You now have a lot of fabrications, tall tales about the R.U.F.,'' Eldred Collins, the spokesman for the rebel group, said in an interview at Mr. Sankoh's compound today.  Denying that the group was holding any peacekeepers hostage, he added, ''They are scattered in the bush because they do not know the terrain.''</p>
        <p>Outside Freetown, the Kamajors, a militia that supported the government, was reportedly rearming in its stronghold in the south. Many Kamajors, like many rebels, had refused to lay down their weapons as required by a nine-month-old peace pact.</p>
        <p>Of the estimated 45,000 combatants in the country's nine-year war, half are said to have given up their weapons. The actual figure is probably a lot lower, and widespread fighting could resume quickly.</p>
        <p>Given that history, and the fierce fighting in Freetown in which thousands were killed or had their hands chopped off during a rebel attack in January 1999, the capital's airport and helipads were busy today. Scores of officials of international relief groups, including the World Food Program, and Lebanese and Nigerian families were seen leaving.</p>
        <p>At a helipad just next to the United Nations' main building here, 11 flights had carried passengers away. Most foreigners were reportedly headed to neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>''It's good for business today,'' said Solomon Johnson, an official at the heliport. ''But it's not good for the country. It's just one way. No coming back.''</p>
        <p>Under the accord signed in July, all combatants should have voluntarily given up their weapons months ago. But the warring parties, and the Revolutionary United Front in particular, refused to do so at several camps across the country.</p>
        <p>While the United Nations provided a $300 incentive, there was little reason for the combatants to stay inside the camps for the expected three months. Activities that were supposed to teach them skills and help them reintegrate into society were never put into place.</p>
        <p>In recent months, United Nations peacekeepers had finally been deployed into most areas of the country -- though never in the diamond mining district of Kono to which the Revolutionary United Front still clings. The peacekeepers encountered frequent obstacles erected by the rebels; it was clear that the rebels remained in control of at least half the country.</p>
        <p>Last week's incidents occurred just as the United Nations was building up a presence -- with 8,300 soldiers already here -- on a continent that the international community had avoided in recent years, after failed missions in Rwanda and Somalia. The trouble in Sierra Leone was expected to have a negative effect on the West's willingness to send peacekeepers to Congo, a country involved in a far more complex war.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, United Nations officials today continued to seek support in speeding up troop deployments to Sierra Leone. The force had been scheduled to reach its full strength of 11,000 by July.</p>
        <p>The United States, France and Britain, the former colonial power, have said they will not send ground troops, though they are considering technical and logistical help.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
