<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plugging a Hole in the Reservoir of Memory</title>
    <meta content="07LORE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CITY LORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservoirs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aqueducts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Croton Aqueduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegal, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D71738F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plugging a Hole in the Reservoir of Memory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegal, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Croton gatehouse at 119th Street and Amsterdam Avenue in Manhattan, newly designated historic site that was important part of New York City's 19th-Century drinking water system known as Old Croton Aqueduct; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE that you are a drop of water falling from a cloud over the Croton River in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>The year is 1848. The New York Water Company has just put the finishing touches on the city's first aqueduct, drawing fresh, potable water from upstate New York and carrying it to the lower reaches of Manhattan. If the drop lands near the river's mouth, it would begin a 41-mile journey through Ossining, Tarrytown, Dobbs Ferry and other towns, traveling across the Bronx and traversing the Harlem River by bridge. From there, the drop would flow into one of a number of underground siphons, moving southward underneath Amsterdam Avenue and through a series of water mains, arriving ultimately in the city's distributing reservoir on 42nd Street, where the New York Public Library now stands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE that you are a drop of water falling from a cloud over the Croton River in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>The year is 1848. The New York Water Company has just put the finishing touches on the city's first aqueduct, drawing fresh, potable water from upstate New York and carrying it to the lower reaches of Manhattan. If the drop lands near the river's mouth, it would begin a 41-mile journey through Ossining, Tarrytown, Dobbs Ferry and other towns, traveling across the Bronx and traversing the Harlem River by bridge. From there, the drop would flow into one of a number of underground siphons, moving southward underneath Amsterdam Avenue and through a series of water mains, arriving ultimately in the city's distributing reservoir on 42nd Street, where the New York Public Library now stands.</p>
        <p>In the 19th century, the city's drinking water took this course through a system now known as the Old Croton Aqueduct. Today, in the portion of the system that is in Westchester County and the Bronx, the path can be traced through the pastoral landscape of the Aqueduct Trailway, a state park.</p>
        <p>But once you cross into Manhattan, it is difficult to find the trail. While the Westchester and Bronx sections of the Old Croton Aqueduct have been listed on the New York State and national registers of historic places, the part in Manhattan has not been.</p>
        <p>Preservationists and other aqueduct enthusiasts have long asked the city Landmarks Preservation Commission to designate important stops along the Croton Aqueduct's Manhattan portion. On March 28 they scored a success. The commission voted to designate a Croton gatehouse, one of the important Manhattan markers, at 119th Street and Amsterdam Avenue.</p>
        <p>Andrew S. Dolkart, a city historian who teaches at Columbia University's School of Architecture, said the gatehouse, an unassuming but sturdy little granite structure with a slate shingle roof, was one of the last three remnants of the water system in Manhattan. The other two are a similar blocky gatehouse at 113th and Amsterdam, built in 1876, and a much larger, and significantly more ornate, castlelike structure at 135th Street and Convent Avenue, completed in 1890.</p>
        <p>Although apparatus for routing water was housed underneath each gatehouse, none of the three structures served any practical purpose above ground, Mr. Dolkart said.</p>
        <p>''It's a symbol, like the fortress gates of a medieval city,'' he explained. ''It signifies the importance of the water system to the city. It's protecting this lifeline to the city.''</p>
        <p>It is impossible to imagine the city functioning today without a huge system to guarantee a ready supply of potable water. But until the Old Croton Aqueduct was completed, the city relied on local waterways, springs and wells for this necessity.</p>
        <p>In the early 19th century, however, the growing city faced two crises. Its poor system of sewage and drainage contaminated many water sources, leading to repeated outbreaks of disease. Second, fires plagued the city because the available water was insufficient to put them out and because there was no pressure to propel water to the tops of four- or five-story buildings.</p>
        <p>Prompted by an epidemic of Asiatic cholera in 1832, a committee of the Common Council, a city agency, asked an engineer to investigate new water sources. He suggested a system of dams and pipes, modeled on the Roman aqueducts, to transport water from the Croton River to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>But despite widespread interest in such a system, construction did not begin until 1837. John B. Jervis, one of the nation's leading engineers, oversaw the construction, which was disrupted by several insurrections by Irish immigrant workers who  were paid 75 cents for their 10-hour days. The final hurdle, getting the water across the Harlem River, was cleared when the High Bridge, an impressive Roman-style promontory connecting the Bronx to Manhattan at West 174th Street, was completed in 1848.</p>
        <p>When water began to pour through the elaborate system that year, throngs gathered in City Hall Park to celebrate, reading poems to commemorate the event, and singing anthems of lavish praise.</p>
        <p>The Old Croton Aqueduct remained the city's principal source of water until 1890, when the New Croton Aqueduct, which incorporated updated technology, supplemented it.</p>
        <p>Today, the entire city's water is furnished by the New Croton system, the Delaware system and the Catskills system. The latter two, more recent systems are far larger than the Old Croton Aqueduct.</p>
        <p>In 1981, the city landmarks commission designated the gatehouse at 135th Street and Convent Avenue, which was part of the New Croton Aqueduct. In 1990, neighborhood preservationists lost a fight to designate the gatehouse at Amsterdam and 113th Street, when the city auctioned off the structure to the Amsterdam Nursing Home Corporation, which slightly altered it for use as a day care center for elderly patients.</p>
        <p>Early this year, upon hearing a rumor that the city was planning to auction the 119th Street gatehouse, Bob Roistacher, chairman of the Morningside Heights Residents' Association, asked the landmarks commission to consider its designation. The commission responded swiftly. Mr. Roistacher said he was saddened that the Manhattan portion of the Old Croton Aqueduct was never listed as a national historic landmark, when the Bronx and Westchester portions were.</p>
        <p>''But it's the city designation that offers the highest level of protection,'' he added. ''So we're elated to have that, and to know that nobody and no institution is going to come along and try to significantly change it or demolish it now.''</p>
        <p>CITY LORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
