<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Islanders' Unlikely Saviors; Wang and Kumar, Computer Executives, Say a Love for Long Island Has Made Them Sports Owners</title>
    <meta content="07WANG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Computer Associates</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wang, Charles B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kumar, Sanjay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toy, Vivian S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DE1E39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Islanders' Unlikely Saviors; Wang and Kumar, Computer Executives, Say a Love for Long Island Has Made Them Sports Owners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toy, Vivian S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Computer Associates International chairman Charles B Wang and associate Sanjay Kumar, self-described 'computer nerds' who have purchased New York Islanders and hope to revive troubled hockey team to its former glory; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES B. WANG, the chairman of Computer Associates International, was waiting in line with his wife at Nassau County's traffic court last week so she could take care of a five-year-old speeding ticket, when for the first time in his life, someone asked for his autograph.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang knew that when he and Sanjay Kumar, his No. 2 man at Computer Associates, bought the New York Islanders last month, they were entering uncharted territory. But it did not really dawn on him how uncharted until that hockey fan approached him with pen in hand asking for a keepsake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES B. WANG, the chairman of Computer Associates International, was waiting in line with his wife at Nassau County's traffic court last week so she could take care of a five-year-old speeding ticket, when for the first time in his life, someone asked for his autograph.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang knew that when he and Sanjay Kumar, his No. 2 man at Computer Associates, bought the New York Islanders last month, they were entering uncharted territory. But it did not really dawn on him how uncharted until that hockey fan approached him with pen in hand asking for a keepsake.</p>
        <p>''Who knew?'' said Mr. Wang. ''You buy an almost defunct team and your recognition value shoots through the roof. I told Sanjay we should have bought more broken teams a long time ago.''</p>
        <p>A billionaire who runs the world's third-largest software company and who gives away millions of dollars each year to charity, Mr. Wang has enjoyed a fair amount of renown for some time. But now, suddenly, everybody knows who he is. Strangers call him Charles. Shoppers at his favorite local seafood store stop him to wish him good luck with the team. ''This is a whole new different world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is.</p>
        <p>Fans, who saw themselves as hockey's most abused fans, rejoiced at the news that Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar had bought the troubled hockey team for $187.5 million last month. The new owners have said they want to bring the team back to its glory days of the early 1980's, when it won four straight Stanley Cup championships and when Long Islanders were proud to call the team their own. They also want to make Nassau Coliseum, where fans sometimes sit under umbrellas because the roof leaks, a place that they and Islanders fans can be proud of.</p>
        <p>But some wonder how two self-described computer nerds who had not even been to a hockey game until last year can turn around a franchise that has not made it to the playoffs since 1994, has lost $40 million in the last two years and can barely muster a crowd of 7,000 in an arena that fits 16,000.</p>
        <p>To these skeptics, Mr. Wang (pronounced WONG) has two words: ''Watch us.''</p>
        <p>As a team, Mr. Wang, 55, and Mr. Kumar, 38, built Computer Associates into a company with $6.3 billion in revenues in 1999. And they believe that as a team, they can oversee the resurgence of the Islanders.</p>
        <p>They say that they expect to lose tens of millions of dollars in the process, but that they are committed to the mission because they cannot fathom a Long Island without a major league franchise.</p>
        <p>Computer Associates has more than 20,000 employees in 160 offices worldwide, but its headquarters is in Islandia. Both Mr. Wang, a Chinese immigrant, and Mr. Kumar, an immigrant from Sri Lanka, call Long Island home and recognize that Long Island will not be taken seriously until it can boast a winning major league team or two. (Big basketball fans, they originally hoped to buy the New Jersey Nets and do not rule out the possibility that Long Island will someday get its own basketball team.)</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, the Coliseum is a dump, and the team, well, they're losers,'' Mr. Wang said. ''It's a real shame. We want to see it change because this is our home. We all deserve better.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar say they are willing to sustain significant financial losses not just because they can afford to, but also because they strongly believe in giving back to the community. (Business Week listed Mr. Wang as the highest-paid executive of 1999 when he earned $655 million in stock options, and Fortune put Mr. Kumar on its list of America's 40 Richest Under 40 last year, pegging his worth at $335 million.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar said he believed he and Mr. Wang share a strong work ethic and a sense of responsibility to the community because they also share an immigrant experience in which they started their lives in America with little and yet have been blessed with so much.</p>
        <p>They both said their mothers reacted like typical immigrant moms at their latest endeavor. Mrs. Wang said she worried her son would be spreading himself a little too thin. And Mrs. Kumar told her son he should be saving for his children's education and shouldn't be spending so much. ''I told her, 'Mom, I don't think they need to worry,' '' Mr. Kumar said.</p>
        <p>''When you start with nothing, you realize you could live without a lot,'' Mr. Kumar said. ''Having is nice, but there comes a point where having is meaningless and you have to do what you know is right.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang was born in Shanghai in 1944. With his parents and his two brothers, he fled China shortly after the Communist takeover when he was 8 years old. They settled in Queens Village, moving into a small apartment, which Mr. Wang described as ''basically the projects.''</p>
        <p>His father, a judge in Shanghai, became a law professor at St. John's University, and his mother became a head librarian in the Queens library system. They are both retired now and live in a house their son built for them on his 60-acre estate in Oyster Bay.</p>
        <p>''I wanted them nearby so I wouldn't have to worry about them, but I also wanted to make sure we all had our privacy,'' Mr. Wang said.</p>
        <p>His parents both spoke fluent English when they arrived in America and stopped speaking Chinese at home because they worried that their sons would grow up speaking English with an accent.</p>
        <p>''But I do have an accent,'' Mr. Wang said impishly. ''It's a Brooklyn accent.'' He has a tendency to drop his r's -- as in ''see you la-tuh'' -- something he picked up while at Brooklyn Technical High School.</p>
        <p>He said he wished his parents had forced him to go to Chinese school as he is now forcing his children because he only has what he calls ''restaurant Chinese,'' where he can order a meal easily and carry on a simple conversation in both Cantonese and Mandarin.</p>
        <p>The Wang boys adjusted to life in America well. Charles's two brothers became lawyers, and he went into computers after graduating from Queens College with a degree in mathematics. For 10 years he worked as a computer programmer and a software salesman. Then, in 1976, he and three friends bought the American subsidiary of a Swiss company, Computer Associates International. They eventually took over the mother company and took the company public in 1981. It hasn't stopped growing since.</p>
        <p>Computer Associates, known as C.A. in the industry, has bought many competitors, and Mr. Wang has developed a reputation as ''a very ruthless business competitor,'' said Brian Goodstadt, an investment officer at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>''He built C.A. from scratch through some very tough practices,'' Mr. Goodstadt said. ''Mostly by acquiring struggling companies, gutting them, firing people to make them more profitable and in the process adding to C.A.'s product line.''</p>
        <p>Computer Associates now carries more than 500 different software products. It is the world's leading developer of system management software -- what is known as ''the plumbing'' that helps manage computer networks for thousands of corporations all over the world.</p>
        <p>On a personal level, Mr. Wang has a quick smile, blunt talk and a casual style. He carries to and from work a Benetton knapsack made up of panels of bright primary colors. But on a business level, people in the industry have long feared him. Even customers have been at odds with his business practices, frequently ending up in court over licensing agreements.</p>
        <p>The company's reputation for playing dirty on the corporate playing field has been tempered by the way it treats its employees, offering perks like subsidized on-site child care and fitness centers in its offices worldwide. Computer Associates has been repeatedly named a ''Best Place to Work'' by Computerworld and Fortune magazines.</p>
        <p>The company's image has mellowed somewhat since Mr. Kumar was made president and chief operating officer in 1994. ''Sanjay balances Charles's tough side,'' Mr. Goodstadt said. ''He's been the protege and is supposedly treated like Charles Wang's son. He's the softer, nicer side of C.A..''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar joined Computer Associates in 1987 when Mr. Wang acquired the Dallas-based Uccel Corporation, where Mr. Kumar was director of software development. Mr. Kumar moved quickly up the ladder at Computer Associates.</p>
        <p>''I've been very fortunate to have someone like Charles to be a mentor,'' Mr. Kumar said. ''Sometimes I'm more analytical from a business perspective and I think I'm a bit more patient. But in many ways, we're interchangeable, which to me is a great compliment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar immigrated to South Carolina with his parents and two younger sisters from Colombo, Sri Lanka, in 1976, before civil war broke out on the island nation. His father is an animal husbandry expert ''who does things like make chickens lay twice as many eggs,'' he said, and his mother is a Montessori school teacher. His parents now live outside of Atlanta, as do his sisters -- one is a molecular biochemist and the other an environmental chemist.</p>
        <p>He entered Furman University and ''like all good Asian immigrant kids'' planned to become a doctor and enrolled in the pre-med program. But he also ran a successful computer software company and dropped out of college in his third year. ''That was not a popular decision with my parents,'' he said. ''But I never looked back. I was self-taught in software and back then college did not have that much to offer in that field.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar, like Mr. Wang, spends nearly half his time traveling to meet with clients all over the world. He went back to Sri Lanka a few years ago while in India on business and made a pilgrimage to his old home and grade school. ''I remembered everything,'' he said. ''It's amazing how your mind comes alive even after not being there for more than 20 years.''</p>
        <p>His street seemed much narrower, especially since every house had built a wall and solid gate in its front yard to keep the war out. He took loads of pictures, including one of him holding a sign with a message to his wife that reads: ''Sylvia, wish you were here.'' He said his daughters, now ages 10 and 6, ''were blown away by the pictures, especially how tiny the house was; they said, 'Dad, your closet's bigger than that.' ''</p>
        <p>It is that immigrant experience, he said, that has ingrained in him the need to give back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar have an easy and jovial relationship. Mr. Kumar marvels at Mr. Wang's ''phenomenal outside jump shot'' on the basketball court and says, ''when it comes to ideas and the ability to execute them, Charles is a genius.'' And Mr. Wang clearly has confidence in Mr. Kumar.</p>
        <p>They both jealously guard their privacy and are devoted to their families. Mr. Kumar drops his girls off at school in the morning and will squeeze a business trip to London into a single day to limit his time away from his home in Oyster Bay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang rides to and from work with his wife, Nancy Li, the company's chief technology officer. He makes sure he is home in time to cook dinner for his two younger children, a 7-year-old daughter and an 18-month-old son. He has a 28-year-old daughter from a previous marriage who now owns a horse farm in Hawaii. One of the company's most popular products, Jasmine ii, is named for his younger daughter.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar have focused their charitable efforts on work that helps children because they believe it has ''high impact.'' They both support the Smile Train, a group established by Mr. Wang that helps children with cleft lips and palates and other facial deformities.</p>
        <p>''In places like China and India, these children are completely ostracized, and all it takes is a $200 operation to change their lives,'' Mr. Kumar said.</p>
        <p>They also support the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children and the Make-A-Wish Foundation. And Mr. Wang raised his profile locally in 1997 when he donated $25 million to the State University at Stony Brook for a high-tech Asian-American Center.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar see a revitalized Islanders team as a way to give something to Long Island's kids. ''The idea that there are 100,000 kids within a 10-mile radius of the Coliseum who have never been to an Islanders game is unconscionable,'' Mr. Kumar said.</p>
        <p>Joe Micheletti, the Islanders' broadcast analyst on Fox Sports New York, said that the new owners' eagerness to make the Islanders a part of children's lives again is crucial for bringing fans back.</p>
        <p>''I think it's wonderful that they keep referring to the importance of becoming partners with the community,'' he said. ''Once you have players out in the community more and you build a good rapport with the people who are buying the tickets, then when you go through lean times, those people will stick with you.''</p>
        <p>Members of the Save the Islanders Coalition, a group of about 3,000 Islanders fans, is so heartened by the new ownership that they plan to soon change their name to Support the Islanders. The fact that Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar are Long Islanders instantly put them in a league high above previous, out-of-town owners, who dropped the player payroll down to $16 million, the lowest in the league. The new owners plan on changing that, but have not made any specific decisions yet.</p>
        <p>''Their reputation precedes them,'' said Steve Ellers, the coalition's president. ''And they've already talked more about the fans than anybody who's been there. I think we got a good shot with these guys.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar and Mr. Wang do not believe that the fact they both recently had to read ''Hockey for Dummies,'' by John Davidson, the New York Rangers' television analyst, will be much of a handicap for them. Mr. Wang said they would ''let the hockey people run things,'' but added that they would not be absentee owners. ''We'll give them the responsibility and the authority to do things, but if they can't do it, we'll find someone else who can,'' he said.</p>
        <p>John McMullen, the 81-year-old owner of the New Jersey Devils, said he didn't think that Mr. Wang and Mr. Kumar would be much handicapped by their lack of hockey knowledge. He said he had little more when he bought the Colorado Rockies 18 years ago and transplanted the team to the Meadowlands. He was a ''hockey father'' and owner of the Houston Astros at the time. ''I wish them luck, because they're going to need it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In recent years, as price tags for sports franchises have skyrocketed, more new owners are novices and their success has been mixed, said to Glenn M. Wang, a professor of sports management at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst.</p>
        <p>''People believe that their business skills are easily transferable, but that's not always the case,'' he said. The world of sports makes for a very different kind of business environment because even as teams compete furiously on the field or on the ice, teams must work together to some extent because they share television revenues, Mr. Wang said.</p>
        <p>Another difference between running a corporation and a sports team is that every decision will be made under a microscope, Glenn Wang said. ''Even a publicly held corporation is not going to have the kind of scrutiny that a sports franchise has,'' he said. ''There's no talk radio in the computer business.''</p>
        <p>All the attention may be more than they wished for, and they know the honeymoon will not last forever. ''It's kind of like, no good deed goes unpunished,'' Charles Wang said. ''But we know any time you take a lead in the community, you're going to take some heat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang said most new owners say at the beginning that they plan to let sports people run the team, and cautioned that only those who keep that promise find success. He said that given the Islanders' obvious need for a new arena and its complicated lease arrangement with SMG, the Coliseum's landlord, and Nassau County, it would probably be years before team made money.</p>
        <p>Not a problem, Mr. Wang said.</p>
        <p>''We're not going anywhere,'' he said. As for multimillion dollar losses, Mr. Wang said he supposed he could use them as a tax write-off. ''I don't know how my accountants will do it, but I'll be O.K.,'' he said. ''I won't be at the poorhouse.''</p>
        <p>That is not to say that he and Mr. Kumar view the Islanders as another one of their charity efforts. They see owning the team as a challenge, and the competitive streak that runs in both of them is likely to drive them to build a winner, on the ice and financially, as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>They also know that as the first Asian-Americans to become principal owners of a major league franchise, they are breaking ground for Asians and immigrants.</p>
        <p>''I know putting our faces with a hockey uniform seems a little different,'' said Mr. Wang. ''But I can't think of anybody more American than us. We got where we are the classic American way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar said he and his partner were proud to be doing something that had not been done before. ''That's not why we're doing it,'' he said. ''But at the end of the day, being a good Asian role model is important to us because it lets any kid know that if you set your mind to something, it can happen.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 14, 2000, Sunday  Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about the new owners of the New York Islanders misspelled the surname of a professor of sports management at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst who commented on the obstacles the new owners face. He is Glenn M. Wong, not Wang.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 14, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about the new owners of the New York Islanders misspelled the surname of a professor of sports management at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst who commented on the obstacles the new owners face. He is Glenn M. Wong, not Wang.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
