<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Father Is Also a New Champion</title>
    <meta content="21GYMN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: GYMNASTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nemov, Aleksei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yang Wei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beresh, Oleksand</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6D6123BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Father Is Also a New Champion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aleksei Nemov (Russia) wins gold medal in men's All-Around gymnastics competition at Sydney Olympics; Yang Wei (China) wins silver medal and Oleksandr Beresh (Ukraine) wins bronze medal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aleksei Nemov hadn't seen his newborn son, not even a picture in the 18 days since his birth, but the idea of being a father took up every spare inch of his thoughts.</p>
        <p>As he walked into the Super Dome tonight, the Russian with the biceps of an action hero didn't see the other competitors in the men's Olympic all-around final. As he calmly walked away from each captivating routine, the 24-year-old with a mapmaker's attention to detail didn't notice the cameras documenting his every idle moment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aleksei Nemov hadn't seen his newborn son, not even a picture in the 18 days since his birth, but the idea of being a father took up every spare inch of his thoughts.</p>
        <p>As he walked into the Super Dome tonight, the Russian with the biceps of an action hero didn't see the other competitors in the men's Olympic all-around final. As he calmly walked away from each captivating routine, the 24-year-old with a mapmaker's attention to detail didn't notice the cameras documenting his every idle moment.</p>
        <p>Instead, Nemov was fixated on his son. One day, he would tell him a story about tonight; and he wanted it to be a fairy tale.</p>
        <p>''An important thing was my son; that was my major motivation,'' Nemov said through a translator. ''I wanted to do my best for Russia, for my family and loved ones.''</p>
        <p>No one was let down. Once considered an inconsistent talent in gymnastics, Nemov calmly unveiled a remarkable mix of grace, strength and daredevil nerve in his approach to every event. He was a detached tactician on each apparatus. Only when he punctuated his last routine of the night with a twisting dismount on the parallel bars did Nemov finally allow emotion to seep into his expression.</p>
        <p>He had tears in his eyes, and a quiver in his chin. The evidence of his joy was still there as he stepped onto the medal stand, bowed his head and allowed himself to be draped with a gold medal. Although the silver medalist, Yang Wei of China, pushed Nemov, and Oleksandr Beresh of Ukraine posed a peripheral threat, Nemov's score of 9.775 on the parallel bars left no doubt as to who would own the coveted title as the world's best gymnast.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Nemov lost the Olympic all-around title to Li Xiaoshuang of China by only 0.049 points at the Atlanta Games, where he won six medals. With a bronze in the team competition, he has a chance to win seven medals here, having qualified for five apparatus finals that will be contested Sunday and Monday.</p>
        <p>''He has the best feel for the aesthetics of the sport,'' said Peter Vidmar, an NBC analyst and former Olympic gold medalist for the United States. ''He doesn't just do a skill; he makes it look gorgeous. Some gymnasts think if their arm is bent a little it doesn't matter, but Nemov understands it matters. He's not the strongest gymnast, but he's the best.''</p>
        <p>That was clear from his opening routine on the high bar. He approached the apparatus as if he were a trapeze artist. Whirling his body around the bar in swift revolutions, he would repeatedly release, flip high into the air and then catch the bar on his way down, all without a hint of hesitation. A score of 9.787 brought a roar from the crowd. After the first of six events, he was in first place. He never gave up that spot.</p>
        <p>To most, it was a dominating, mesmerizing performance. But at least one competitor in red, white and blue was not impressed. It wasn't the wholesome, freckle-faced teen from Wisconsin, Paul Hamm, but the irascible Blaine Wilson.</p>
        <p>''Anybody could be as good as Nemov,'' Wilson said. ''Yeah, he's a great gymnast, but anyone can be that good.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, Wilson wasn't. While he finished sixth with the help of a spectacular 9.8 on the vault -- making a handspring to a double-front look easy -- the Olympics has not been the coming-out party for Wilson. He still has an apparatus final to compete in, but that's another individual event.</p>
        <p>Perhaps feeling the pressure to carry the Americans, he suffered a couple of uncharacteristic meltdowns in the team competition. On Monday, the United States finished a disappointing fifth, and Wilson left the floor without a word.</p>
        <p>Tonight, he said: ''I don't think I have to redeem myself at all; I walked into this having done more for U.S. gymnastics than any other gymnast out there,'' perhaps forgetting the Bart Conners, Vidmars and even the John Roethlisbergers who came before him. ''I don't have to explain myself to anyone, not to you, not to my family, not to anyone.''</p>
        <p>Wilson, 26, could return for another Olympics, but, by then, the American team's promotional star will most likely be Hamm. The 17-year-old Hamm, whose twin, Morgan, is also on the team, showed impressive poise tonight. Hamm was not only performing in his first Olympic all-around competition, but, by the luck of the draw, he was in the same rotation as Nemov.</p>
        <p>Even more unsettling, he had to follow Nemov on every apparatus but one. It was like a finger painter trying to top Picasso. But the inexperienced Hamm pressed onward. Although he began with a fall on the high bar, and found himself in 34th place after the first event, he showed the resilience of youth. By the end of the competition, Hamm had moved up to 14th place.</p>
        <p>''It was great learning things as far as dealing with the pressure,'' Hamm said. ''I don't think you can have any more pressure than following an Olympic champion all night.''</p>
        <p>Nemov embraced that title. From the moment he arrived, he looked like a man who wanted it more than anyone else. With the thought of his son to keep him focused, he went after the gold medal without a trace of doubt in his demeanor. Underneath, though, Nemov admitted that his nerves were jangled.</p>
        <p>''I could fall at any moment; that's how I felt,'' Nemov said. ''Destiny was on my side. God was on my side. I ended up with the gold. That's it.''</p>
        <p>DISMOUNTS</p>
        <p>STEPHEN McCAIN of the United States qualified for the all-around but did not compete because of swelling in his ankle. He hurt it in practice last week, but aggravated it when he landed badly on a vault in the team competition Monday night.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: GYMNASTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
