<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A LACK OF EVIDENCE IS CITED IN CASE INVOLVING CLINTONS</title>
    <meta content="21WHIT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/politics/21WHIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHITEWATER INQUIRY ENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arkansas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitewater Development Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Madison Guaranty Savings &amp; Loan Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Robert W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DE103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A LACK OF EVIDENCE IS CITED IN CASE INVOLVING CLINTONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special counsel Robert W Ray puts end to six-year Whitewater probe, holding there is insufficient evidence to show that either Pres Clinton or Hillary Rodham Clinton committed any crimes in connection with Arkansas real estate venture, concealed data from investigators or obstructed justice; report's conclusions largely undercut concerns that it was unfair to Mrs Clinton, Senate candidate in New York, for Ray to issue statement summarizing it only weeks before election; Ray has not yet submitted detailed report to three-judge panel; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An independent prosecutor today put an end to the six-year Whitewater investigation, saying he had concluded that there was insufficient evidence to show that either President Clinton or his wife, Hillary Rodham Clinton,  had committed any crimes in connection with the Arkansas real estate venture that vexed his presidency through two terms.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Ray, the prosecutor, said he could not prove that the president or Mrs. Clinton had been involved in any criminal behavior in connection with a set of complicated Whitewater-related financial and legal transactions in Arkansas. Nor, he said, could he prove that they had concealed information from investigators or obstructed justice in any manner related to Whitewater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An independent prosecutor today put an end to the six-year Whitewater investigation, saying he had concluded that there was insufficient evidence to show that either President Clinton or his wife, Hillary Rodham Clinton,  had committed any crimes in connection with the Arkansas real estate venture that vexed his presidency through two terms.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Ray, the prosecutor, said he could not prove that the president or Mrs. Clinton had been involved in any criminal behavior in connection with a set of complicated Whitewater-related financial and legal transactions in Arkansas. Nor, he said, could he prove that they had concealed information from investigators or obstructed justice in any manner related to Whitewater.</p>
        <p>In saying he did not have evidence to charge either the president or Mrs. Clinton with a crime, Mr. Ray was notably spare in his language.  On each of the accusations, he said only that ''the evidence was insufficient to prove to a jury beyond a reasonable doubt'' that they had committed any crime. [Text, Page A23.]</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Ray's statement  was a definitive legal conclusion on the issue and thus was regarded by the White House and its supporters as a significant victory, especially for Mrs. Clinton, who is running for the Senate from New York.</p>
        <p>The report's conclusions also appeared to largely undercut concerns that it was unfair to Mrs. Clinton for Mr. Ray to issue a statement only weeks before she faces Representative Rick Lazio, a Republican congressman from Long Island, in the Senate voting. The Ray statement seemed to provide little ammunition for Mrs. Clinton's opponents.</p>
        <p>The Whitewater investigation began in January 1994 when President Clinton, under increasing pressure, asked for a special prosecutor to be named to investigate his Whitewater land dealings. That investigation began with accusations that the Clintons had received special treatment from their fellow investors in the land venture on the White River, James B. and Susan H. McDougal, because he was the governor of Arkansas, a subject that was first raised in a news article in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>From that narrow beginning, the investigation expanded several times to cover a wide range of accusations that eventually came to include whether Mr. Clinton lied under oath about his relationship with Monica Lewinsky when she was a White House intern. That issue resulted in Mr. Clinton's impeachment by the House in 1998 and his acquittal by the Senate last year.</p>
        <p>Joe Lockhart, the White House spokesman, issued a statement saying, ''Robert Ray is now the latest investigator to complete an examination of the transactions related to Whitewater Development Company and conclude that there are no grounds for legal action.''</p>
        <p>The five-page statement from Mr. Ray is a summary of his final report on the matter, which will contain far more detail on the investigation. Mr. Ray said he had not yet submitted that report under seal to a special panel of three federal judges, as the law required.</p>
        <p>He said was waiting to wrap up loose ends, notably an investigation as to whether anyone in the White House concealed e-mail messages from investigators. That investigation is not expected to involve the president or Mrs. Clinton directly, law enforcement officials have said.</p>
        <p>That leaves as Mr. Ray's principal remaining task a decision about whether to indict Mr. Clinton after he leaves office over his sworn statements in connection with his relationship with Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ray has said that he and a recently empaneled grand jury would announce that decision shortly after the new president is inaugurated next January.</p>
        <p>Underlying the investigation of the Clintons' investment in Whitewater was the question of whether Mrs. Clinton, as a lawyer in Arkansas,  worked to prop up a failing savings and loan association, Madison Guaranty, which was used to keep the Whitewater investment afloat.</p>
        <p>Madison Guaranty eventually collapsed at a cost to the federal government of $73 million, according to a federal bank regulatory agency.</p>
        <p>One of the issues investigated by Mr. Ray was the unexplained disappearance of Mrs. Clinton's billing records when she was an Arkansas lawyer. They were initially sought by investigators to determine how much Mrs. Clinton might have known about real estate transactions that were eventually deemed a sham to deceive federal regulators.</p>
        <p>A copy of the records was found in the family quarters of the White House in January 1996, some 18 months after they were first subpoenaed by investigators. Mr. Ray said his investigation of the records' disappearance was inconclusive.</p>
        <p>The statement on Whitewater was the third by Mr. Ray, who succeeded Kenneth W. Starr last October.</p>
        <p>Last March, Mr. Ray investigated how the White House came to improperly acquire hundreds of confidential personnel files kept by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, many of them files of prominent Republicans, and concluded that it had been the result of unwitting mistakes by low-level White House officials.</p>
        <p>He was generous in his language then, saying there was ''no credible evidence'' that either the president or Mrs. Clinton had secretly collected the files to gather intelligence on Republican opponents.</p>
        <p>In his second report last June, Mr. Ray cleared Mrs. Clinton of charges that she had engineered the dismissal of seven longtime employees of the White House travel office and their replacement with friends and relatives of the Clintons. In contrast to the previous report, Mr. Ray seemed to criticize Mrs. Clinton, saying her sworn statements that she had not been involved were misleading but did not warrant criminal prosecution.</p>
        <p>The statement today used similar narrow language. Mr. Ray declined to declare as he did six months ago that there was no credible evidence to support the allegations.</p>
        <p>''This office determined that the evidence was insufficient to prove to a jury beyond a reasonable doubt that either President or Mrs. Clinton knowingly participated in any criminal conduct involving Madison Guaranty, C.M.S. or Whitewater Development or knew of such conduct,'' he wrote. C.M.S. was Capital Management Services Inc., operated by an Arkansan, David Hale, who had dealings with Madison Guaranty.</p>
        <p>In Albany, where she was campaigning, Mrs. Clinton said, ''I'm just glad that this is finally over.''</p>
        <p>She said at a meeting in Albany of state members of The Associated Press, ''I think that most New Yorkers and Americans had made up their minds a long time ago about this.'' She added, ''Now everybody can just move on and be focused on issues.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the issue of the billing records, Mr. Ray investigated several other Whitewater-related allegations that he effectively divided into two categories: the Clintons' involvement in Whitewater and whether they had attempted to cover up information from investigators.</p>
        <p>In the first category, Mr. Ray investigated the accusations that Mrs. Clinton telephoned an official in her husband's administration to obtain  preferential treatment for Madison Guaranty. Mrs. Clinton said she could not remember having made such a phone call.</p>
        <p>In the category of whether Mr. Clinton or Mrs. Clinton gave misleading testimony or blocked investigators, Mr. Ray investigated several other issues, concluding that the evidence was insufficient to convince a jury a crime had been committed.</p>
        <p>Among those issues was whether President Clinton knowingly gave false testimony in 1996 at the fraud trial of Mr. McDougal and Gov. Jim Guy Tucker of Arkansas when he said that he had never sought to borrow any money from Madison Guaranty and when he said that he was unaware of a $300,000 loan made to C.M.S. by Madison Guaranty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ray said he had also investigated how Mrs. Clinton came to represent Madison Guaranty. Mrs. Clinton had said several times that a young associate in the law firm, Richard J. Massey, had brought in the concern as a client. Mr. Massey testified that while he tried to bring in Madison he was not responsible.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Ray investigated whether either the president or Mrs. Clinton helped arrange employment for Webster L. Hubbell, a former associate attorney general, ''as a criminal quid pro quo'' to buy his silence and prevent him from testifying about their involvement in a variety of issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hubbell, a longtime friend of the Clintons who served in the Justice Department's No. 3 position in the early Clinton years, was convicted of defrauding his former law firm. After he left office, he was given lucrative consulting contracts by Clinton supporters.</p>
        <p>WHITEWATER INQUIRY ENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
