<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dueling Scholars Join Fray Over a Constitutional Challenge to Gun Control Laws</title>
    <meta content="Y21GUN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/national/21GUNS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cummings, Sam R (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Emerson, Timothy Joe (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD6133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dueling Scholars Join Fray Over a Constitutional Challenge to Gun Control Laws</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Appeal of Federal Judge Sam R Cummings' dismissal of gun possession charges against Dr Timothy Joe Emerson on grounds that individual citizens have right to possess guns spurs bitter academic dispute; decision, major challenge to gun control laws, relied heavily on 1990's scholarship holding Second Amendment was intended to guarantee individual right to arms; other scholars, including some leading constitutional history experts, have seized on case as cause and are challenging 1990's scholarship as distortion of history; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal appeals court case that offers the strongest constitutional challenge to gun control laws in decades has provoked a bitter academic dispute that could help shape rulings on whether Americans have an unfettered right ''to keep and bear arms.''</p>
        <p>The case involves a federal district judge's decision last year to dismiss gun possession charges against a Texas doctor because, he ruled, individual citizens have a constitutional right to gun possession. The judge relied largely on scholarship in the 1990's holding that the drafters of the Second Amendment meant to give individuals the unfettered right to arms, even though the Supreme Court suggested in 1939 that the amendment guarantees only a collective right for states to arm their militias.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal appeals court case that offers the strongest constitutional challenge to gun control laws in decades has provoked a bitter academic dispute that could help shape rulings on whether Americans have an unfettered right ''to keep and bear arms.''</p>
        <p>The case involves a federal district judge's decision last year to dismiss gun possession charges against a Texas doctor because, he ruled, individual citizens have a constitutional right to gun possession. The judge relied largely on scholarship in the 1990's holding that the drafters of the Second Amendment meant to give individuals the unfettered right to arms, even though the Supreme Court suggested in 1939 that the amendment guarantees only a collective right for states to arm their militias.</p>
        <p>Now other scholars, including some leading experts on constitutional history, have seized on the Texas case as a cause and are challenging the 1990's scholarship as a distortion of history. Saying the Supreme Court seems likely at some point soon to consider the right to arms for the first time since 1939, these experts are touching off an extraordinary battle that has scholars flinging insults at one another over such arcana as the meaning of stray comments during English parliamentary debates in the 1600's.</p>
        <p>''The intellectual equivalent of a check-kiting scheme,'' is how Saul Cornell, an Ohio State University historian who has written about the issue, described the arguments of those who say the founders meant to provide an individual right to own guns.</p>
        <p>Don B. Kates, a California lawyer who has been a prolific proponent of an individual right, said it was the other side that had stooped to invented history. ''Some of the stuff is so bad, it's difficult to believe anybody would publish it,'' Mr. Kates said.</p>
        <p>A new book by an Emory University historian, Michael A. Bellesiles, that is receiving wide attention is part of the debate. In ''Arming America: The Origins of a National Gun Culture,'' Professor Bellesiles says that contrary to myth, records show few people in early America owned guns. His assertion supports the argument that the drafters of the Second Amendment were not thinking about guaranteeing an individual right to guns.</p>
        <p>Professor Bellesiles' book and other new research are infuriating some individual-right scholars who were so confident a few years ago that they labeled theirs the ''standard'' interpretation of the Second Amendment and said any serious dispute about the amendment's history was over. Even some liberal experts on constitutional law said they had been persuaded.</p>
        <p>But much of the newest scholarship, including some being published this month, is an argumentative re-examination of the writing during the 1990's that influenced, among others, the federal judge in the Texas case, Sam R. Cummings, in his Second Amendment ruling in favor of Dr. Timothy Joe Emerson of San Angelo, Tex.</p>
        <p>Judge Cummings wrote, ''A historical examination of the right to bear arms, from English antecedents to the drafting of the Second Amendment, bears proof that the right to bear arms has consistently been, and should still be, construed as an individual right.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department appealed, and more than 50 groups on all sides of the issue filed friend-of-the-court briefs. A three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit in New Orleans heard arguments in the case in June.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the academics have been busy parsing old letters by the drafters of the Bill of Rights and deconstructing proposals for the wording of the Second Amendment. The version that became part of the Constitution reads, ''A well regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.''</p>
        <p>This month, Lois G. Schwoerer, a professor emeritus of history at George Washington University in Washington, is publishing an academic article that attacks the work of another history professor, Joyce Lee Malcolm of Bentley College in Waltham, Mass. Professor Malcolm is one of the most influential scholars to argue that history proves the Second Amendment was intended to guarantee an individual right to arms. Professor Malcolm's work was one of Judge Cummings' sources for his conclusions in the Second Amendment ruling.</p>
        <p>Professor Malcolm's 1994 book, ''To Keep and Bear Arms: The Origins of an Anglo-American Right''  (Harvard University Press), argues that an individual right to weapons goes as far back as the English Declaration of Rights of 1689. That guarantee, she said, was imported to America and adopted in the Second Amendment.</p>
        <p>Not so, says Professor Schwoerer, an expert on the English Declaration of Rights. Her new article says the right to bear arms in England was limited by class and religion and was always subject to regulation. Professor Malcolm's conclusions, Professor Schwoerer said in an interview, were ''unthinkable'' and ''very bad history'' that involved ''errors in interpretation and handling of evidence.''</p>
        <p>Professor Malcolm was incensed but not surprised by Professor Schwoerer's remarks, she said. Gun-control advocates have been looking for scholars to criticize her work, she said. ''She's been courted as a historian of English history they could use to discredit my work,'' Professor Malcolm said of Professor  Schwoerer.</p>
        <p>Professor Schwoerer's article says her sleuthing in 17th-century records raised questions about Professor Malcolm's evidence and conclusions. Professor Malcolm's book says, for example, that one Heneage Finch, a Tory, ''pressed'' in a 1689 parliamentary debate for a right to ''private possession of weapons to restrain the crown.''</p>
        <p>Finch's remarks, Professor Schwoerer said, ''really didn't have anything to do with whether you could have arms or not.'' In response, Professor Malcolm said, ''It is possible to misinterpret one speech.'' But that hardly threw into question her conclusion that the English wanted and won an individual right to arms, she said.</p>
        <p>The American debate over the Second Amendment in 1789 is also getting a rigorous new examination.  This month's Chicago-Kent Law Review, which includes Professor Schwoerer's article, carries a broadside by a Stanford University historian, Jack N. Rakove, a Pulitzer Prize winner. Professors Rakove and Schwoerer and seven other scholars  first presented their findings at a conference in April organized by Carl T. Bogus, a gun-control proponent and a law professor at Roger Williams Law School in Bristol, R.I.</p>
        <p>Professor Rakove said scholars who advocate an individual right to arms have ''abused and misused'' historical sources. When the Second Amendment was proposed, he said, the debate centered on the powers of the states as opposed to those of the federal government and ''never reached the question of individual ownership'' of weapons.</p>
        <p>That has not stopped some scholars from implying that it did, Professor Rakove said. His article cites as an example a law professor at the University of Tennessee, Glenn Harlan Reynolds, a leading proponent of the individual-right interpretation.</p>
        <p>Professor Rakove and Professor Reynolds are facing off over exactly what James Madison intended the Second Amendment to mean, a difficult topic because Madison's pronouncements on the subject are sparse and subject to interpretation.</p>
        <p>Professor Reynolds has written, for example, that Madison approved the individual-right interpretation of the Second Amendment. Madison did so, Professor Reynolds argued, by responding warmly to a 1789 letter from an essayist named Tench Coxe.</p>
        <p>''Preposterous,'' Professor Rakove's article says. Coxe did say the Second Amendment confirmed a right to keep ''private arms.'' But Madison's answer merely thanked a supporter for backing the Bill of Rights and made no comment on the meaning of the Second Amendment, Professor Rakove writes.</p>
        <p>Professor Reynolds said he disagreed about the meaning of Madison's letter but added that ''it's all a side issue'' because Madison publicly stated his support for an individual right elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Professor Rakove disagreed with that, saying misstatements about Madison's letter to Coxe showed how  proponents of an individual right to arms distorted history. ''I'm just looking at how these guys use evidence,'' Professor Rakove said.</p>
        <p>Scholars on both sides of the debate said their own recent evidence should finally end the discussion about the meaning of the Second Amendment. But others conceded that was unlikely. ''So long as scholars walk the earth,'' Professor Bogus said, ''the debate will continue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
