<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DD103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>China Girds for New Role In the Global Marketplace  China greeted its imminent status as a permanent American trade partner with official applause, but is already shifting its focus, with private trepidation, to future membership in the World Trade Organization. Many Chinese worry that their country is ill prepared to face the global competition that membership entails.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>China Girds for New Role In the Global Marketplace  China greeted its imminent status as a permanent American trade partner with official applause, but is already shifting its focus, with private trepidation, to future membership in the World Trade Organization. Many Chinese worry that their country is ill prepared to face the global competition that membership entails.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Candidate Rallies in Belgrade  President Slobodan Milosevic, indicted for war crimes by an international tribunal after the Kosovo war, delivered slashing attacks on opposition leaders and criticized their loyalty to NATO. His main opponent in Yugoslavia's presidential election, Vojislav Kostunica, urged crowds to vote for his vision of ''a normal European democratic country.''</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Attack on British Spy Agency  The police in London said a ''small missile'' struck the eighth floor of the headquarters of Britain's M.I. 6 intelligence agency, causing some damage but no casualties.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Plight of Refugees on Timor  Tens of thousands of East Timor refugees living in squalid camps on the West Timor border face starvation by the end of the month, government officials and aid workers said. International aid groups have withdrawn since the killings of three United Nations workers by militiamen.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Taliban Seeking U.N. Seat  The Taliban movement, which controls most of Afghanistan, sent a high-level delegation led by Deputy Foreign Minister Abdur Rahman Zahid to lobby for the country's United Nations seat, which is now held by a coalition opposed to the Taliban.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Art Donations Challenged  Two graffiti artists whose works were given to the Brooklyn Museum of Art by heirs of the art dealer Sidney Janis said the works were never the property of the Janis estate and it had no right to give them away.</p>
        <p>E3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-27</p>
        <p>Prosecutor Closes Book On Whitewater Inquiry  The independent counsel Robert W. Ray, the successor to Kenneth W. Starr, said he had concluded that there was insufficient evidence to show that either President Clinton or Hillary Rodham Clinton had committed any crimes in connection with the Arkansas real estate venture that vexed the Clinton presidency.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cheney Faults Clinton on Iraq  Dick Cheney, the secretary of defense during the gulf war, accused the Clinton administration of letting Saddam Hussein ''slip off the hook'' by avoiding weapon inspections.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>A principal author of Gov. George W. Bush's Medicare plan, Dr. Gail R. Wilensky, is on the boards of eight health care companies that could be affected by the proposal. She said her board memberships were a matter of record and posed no conflict.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Gore Chastises Drug Makers  Vice President Al Gore accused pharmaceutical companies of gouging elderly people, citing as examples several people he said were having problems paying for their medicine. He omitted any reference to his mother-in-law's situation, details of which Republicans and some news reports have challenged.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>William J. Bennett, a Republican who has often joined forces with Senator Joseph I. Lieberman in assailing violence and vulgarity in popular culture, accused Mr. Lieberman of retreating from that cause.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>U.S. to Accept Survivors  Eight Cuban survivors of a plane crash at sea were being taken to Florida, a move that will let them apply for United States residency.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>No Charges in Airline Death  Federal prosecutors will not file charges in the death of a man beaten by fellow passengers after he tried to break into the cockpit of a flight to Salt Lake City from Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Deal to Avoid Suit on Police  Los Angeles city officials accepted a federal court agreement that would require a series of changes in police management and training. The deal heads off a threatened civil rights lawsuit over what the Justice Department calls a systemic pattern of abusive conduct by officers.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-13</p>
        <p>First Lady Gains Ground Against Lazio, Poll Shows  A New York Times/CBS News poll found that voter attitudes toward Rick A. Lazio turned markedly more negative since June, with suburban women moving solidly to Hillary Rodham Clinton and many New Yorkers saying Mr. Lazio appeared harsh and inexperienced in his debate with Mrs. Clinton, who leads the Senate race, 48 to 39 percent.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio said he had pledges from 14 groups supporting him not to raise or spend money on his behalf, provided Mrs. Clinton agreed to the same. She responded that she was now more willing to discuss the banning of soft money from the race.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Immigration Lawyer Indicted  Federal prosecutors accused a New York City immigration lawyer, Robert E. Porges, and his firm of working with smugglers who bring illegal immigrants to the United States from China and then keep them as virtual indentured servants until the price of their passage is paid.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>West Side Arena Proposal  Mayor Giuliani said he wanted to build a domed indoor-outdoor arena on the West Side that would seat up to 100,000 people for concerts, conventions and sports events. His plans were supported for the first time by Governor Pataki, who controls the agency that owns the land. The mayor indicated the arena could be used by the Jets, the Yankees or, if the city got them, the 2012 Olympics.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-12</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
        <p>S1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Ewing Heading to Seattle  The Knicks sent their 15-year center, Patrick Ewing, to the SuperSonics in a four-team, 12-player trade. The Knicks get Glen Rice from the Los Angeles Lakers and Luc Longley from the Phoenix Suns.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-26</p>
        <p>Minor Behind Stock Scheme  The S.E.C. said a 15-year-old New Jersey boy, Jonathan G. Lebed, had masterminded a stock manipulation scheme on the Internet that earned him almost $273,000 in illegal gains. The boy settled the civil complaint without admitting guilt but agreed to give the money to the S.E.C. plus interest, for a total of $285,000. He was not fined or otherwise penalized.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rating Rollover Tendencies  Senator Richard Shelby, chairman of a Senate panel on transportation, dropped objections to a plan to begin providing consumers with data on sport utility vehicles' stability.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Straight to the Moon, Alice  Executives at three television networks pondered an offer to start a network-style space race by creating a program to rival an NBC show that would send a contestant into space aboard a Russian-built rocket.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B14</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-20</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Whitewater verdict; speedier trains; Spain's battle against terrorism; Verlyn Klinkenborg on fashion.  Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E11  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E13  Crossword</p>
        <p>E11  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
