<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's All Archery All the Time For Gold and Silver Medalists</title>
    <meta content="21ROUN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brink, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fairweather, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wunderle, Victor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">van Alten, Wietse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Archery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D6123BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's All Archery All the Time For Gold and Silver Medalists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL BRINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brink, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Simon Fairweather (Australia) wins gold medal in men's individual archery competition at Sydney Olympics; Victor Wunderle (US) wins silver medal and Wietse van Alten (Netherlands) wins bronze medal; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Australia-United States rivalry that has become a thread through the Olympic Games surfaced again today in the men's individual archery finals. But it was less a story of fervent nationalistic competition than the tale of two single-minded athletes who met for the ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>Australia's Simon Fairweather won the gold medal, defeating Vic Wunderle of Mason City, Ill., in the final, 113-106. Afterward, both men acknowledged that archery was a consuming passion that left room for little else, and neither seemed particularly distressed by that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Australia-United States rivalry that has become a thread through the Olympic Games surfaced again today in the men's individual archery finals. But it was less a story of fervent nationalistic competition than the tale of two single-minded athletes who met for the ultimate prize.</p>
        <p>Australia's Simon Fairweather won the gold medal, defeating Vic Wunderle of Mason City, Ill., in the final, 113-106. Afterward, both men acknowledged that archery was a consuming passion that left room for little else, and neither seemed particularly distressed by that.</p>
        <p>''I've had 12 years of shooting internationally,'' said Fairweather, who turned 31 earlier this month. ''It's pretty much all I've been doing.'' He has lived in Canberra training at the national sports institute there for the last two and a half years.</p>
        <p>Wunderle, 24, has been shooting since he was a boy. His father, Terry, who coached archery, made a bow out of a willow branch and had young Vic take aim at a distant tree. He is rigorous about training, sometimes shooting up to 10 hours a day.</p>
        <p>''Pretty much, from the time I get up to the time I go to sleep, I work on my shooting in one way or another,'' he said. He acknowledged that he took time out for certain things: ''Eating and opening mail.''</p>
        <p>With his father to help teach him and his sister, Sally, once an international competitor, to show him the way, Wunderle developed rapidly. He won the junior world championships in 1991 and 1994. He has studied at Texas A&amp;M, but took a year off to train, and said he planned to complete his degree after the Games.</p>
        <p>Financed by the United States archery federation, he has lived and trained with other athletes at Chula Vista, Calif., and was clearly the United States' top shooter at the Olympic trials when he blew away the competition.</p>
        <p>In today's final, Fairweather took a 4-point lead over Wunderle after the first three arrows, and over all he hit 6 bulls-eyes out of 12 arrows, each worth 10 points, despite a shifting breeze. Wunderle had only two bulls-eyes. Fairweather shot superbly, recapturing for one day the form he showed when he won the world championship in 1991. As a joyous home crowd cheered and waved flags, Fairweather said that he thought he would retire from competition. ''Probably,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He didn't sound too convincing, not nearly as convincing as the 12 arrows that flew through the air toward gold.</p>
        <p>WEIGHT LIFTING  Bulgaria Wins 2, Loses 1</p>
        <p>Two Olympic medals, two world records. Bulgaria's weight lifters will take this over a tarnished medal any day. Galabin Boevski won a showdown of world record-holders in Sydney with his Bulgarian teammate Georgi Markov to take the gold medal at 152 pounds (69 kilogram). Boevski won a few hours after Ivan Ivanov, a former Olympic champion and a silver medalist Saturday at 123 pounds (56 kilograms), lost his medal after testing positive for a diuretic, a banned substance. (AP)</p>
        <p>CANOE-KAYAK  Shipley Denied a Medal</p>
        <p>A 2-point penalty for touching a gate on his first run kept the nine-time United States champion kayaker, Scott Shipley, from winning his first Olympic medal in Penrith, Australia. Shipley, a Seattle-area native,  finished fifth with a score of 226.67. Without the infraction, he would have finished ahead of Italy's Pierpaolo Ferrazzi, who took third with 225.03.</p>
        <p>Thomas Schmidt of Germany won the gold with a score of 217.25. The reigning world champion and the gold-medal favorite, Paul Ratcliffe of Britain, got the silver.</p>
        <p>In the two-man canoe finals, the Slovak brothers Pavel and Peter Hochschorner took the gold with 237.74 points. (AP)</p>
        <p>BADMINTON  South Korean Denied Gold</p>
        <p>Kim Dong Moon's quest for a third badminton gold ended two victories short of the mark in Sydney. Kim and her partner, Ha Tae Kwon, lost to the world's top-ranked duo, Tony Gunawan and Candra Wijaya of Indonesia, 15-3, 15-10, in the men's doubles semifinals. (AP)</p>
        <p>JUDO  Huizinga Wins Gold</p>
        <p>An injury to the reigning world champion, Hidehiko Yoshida of Japan, opened the door for Mark Huizinga of the Netherlands to become a gold medalist in Sydney.</p>
        <p>Yoshida was defeated by Brazil's Carlos Honorato, the other gold-medal finalist, in a preliminary match of the men's 90-kilogram event and was taken to a hospital after apparently breaking his right elbow. Frederic Demontfaucon of France and Ruslan Mashurenko of the Ukraine shared the bronze medal.</p>
        <p>Sibelis Veranes of Cuba defeated Kate Howey of Britain to win the women's 70-kilogram. (AP)</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
