<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burned Out but Not Down for the Count</title>
    <meta content="21BOXI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/arts/21BOXI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Richard (Playwright)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Boxing 2000 (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D6123BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burned Out but Not Down for the Count</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Boxing 2000, play written and directed by Richard Maxwell; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The characters of the young director-playwright Richard Maxwell are not what you would call an excitable lot. Their voices are as uninflected as a refrigerator's drone, their postures those of exceptionally passive people who have been parked somewhere and told to wait. In Mr. Maxwell's breakthrough work of two years ago, ''House,'' a couple of them were murdered, and it was hard to distinguish the dead from the living.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Maxwell -- who has previously considered such American phenomena as cowboys and Indians and mall rats -- has moved into the world of amateur prizefighting in a play called ''Boxing 2000.'' It is probably safe to say that no sporting event, even in the current Olympics, has generated less adrenaline than the match shown here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The characters of the young director-playwright Richard Maxwell are not what you would call an excitable lot. Their voices are as uninflected as a refrigerator's drone, their postures those of exceptionally passive people who have been parked somewhere and told to wait. In Mr. Maxwell's breakthrough work of two years ago, ''House,'' a couple of them were murdered, and it was hard to distinguish the dead from the living.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Maxwell -- who has previously considered such American phenomena as cowboys and Indians and mall rats -- has moved into the world of amateur prizefighting in a play called ''Boxing 2000.'' It is probably safe to say that no sporting event, even in the current Olympics, has generated less adrenaline than the match shown here.</p>
        <p>Well, among the fighters, anyway. Audience members for ''Boxing 2000,'' which runs at the Present Company Theatorium through Sept. 30, are likely to feel a wide-awake energy in the presence of these somnambulists. They may also experience the quickened, hopeful heartbeat that comes from watching that rare phenomenon, a genuinely original new talent at work.</p>
        <p>It's a sensation that's felt all too rarely these days. Watching Mr. Maxwell's work makes you think of what it must have been like to stumble upon the baffling but seductive creations of the young Sam Shepard in the early 1960's in the East Village. A Richard Maxwell play is unlikely ever to show up on Broadway or even on the institutional stages of the Public Theater or the Manhattan Theater Club.</p>
        <p>This author's style is anti-polish, even to the point of deliberately seeming amateurish. Read cold, the texts of his scripts are unlikely to have much resonance. It's the whole mise-en-scene, under the control of one artistic imagination, that makes ''Boxing 2000'' so effective. To take it out of its calculatedly crude, experimental realm and spruce it up would be fatal. In the meantime, in its own context, this dramatist's voice -- seemingly as flat and thin as pasteboard -- is sending off depth charges that keep vibrating.</p>
        <p>Like many artists of his generation, Mr. Maxwell is a connoisseur of cliches. None of the nine characters in ''Boxing 2000'' have anything remotely fresh to say. Their conversations, if you overheard them on the street or in a supermarket, would inspire glum thoughts that people as a whole are not an interesting species. These are folks that seem bored even with themselves.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Maxwell, who achieves his distinctive tone as much through his direction as his writing, is listening hard to his characters and demands that we do, too. By slowing down rhythms of speech and inflating pauses, he parses the banalities of everday talk and finds the whispering fear and confusion beneath. It makes you grateful that there is nothing like a slow-motion instant-replay device monitoring your own life.</p>
        <p>''Boxing 2000'' begins with three men planted motionless in a naked space in front of a corrugated metal wall. There is Jo-Jo (Gary Wilmes, a Maxwell veteran), who wears an industrial uniform and many keys on his belt; his younger brother, Freddie (Robert Torres), who has the deadest stare this side of a morgue, and a fellow identified as Promoter (Christopher Sullivan), who is silent for so long that he might be mistaken for a George Segal statue.</p>
        <p>The dialogue emerges slowly and in spurts, like a car being started with an undercharged battery. It is repetitive and circular. There is talk of what Jo-Jo should buy his father for a birthday present; of some arcane mishap at work involving the confusion of room numbers. Suddenly Jo-Jo announces, with no change of tone, that he is ''looking for that one moment of goodwill'' in his life.</p>
        <p>The declaration is thrown away; it registers as just another instance of someone's repeating something he has heard and vaguely feeling it might be appropriate to the occasion. Yet Mr. Maxwell isn't sneering at his creations any more than Flaubert was sneering at that most famous receptacle of received ideas, Emma Bovary. Platitudinous these people may be, but there is a genuine yearning that emerges, despite itself, from their numbness.</p>
        <p>This becomes even clearer as the play's focus shifts to Freddie, who has agreed to participate in the boxing match organized by Promoter and who has a girlfriend, Marissa (Gladys Perez), who talks in the language of spiritual self-help books. Freddie is Mr. Maxwell's 21st-century answer to Clifford Odets's ''Golden Boy,'' a smaller-time, even more manipulable boxer who doesn't even know what to do when he finally gets into the ring or whether he has won or lost at the end.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torres's Freddie manages to come across as both stolid and highly impressionable. It may not look like it, but he's paying attention when the Promoter talks about investing in IRA's instead of Lotto or when Marissa tells him to find his inner voice. ''I'm thinking a lot of what was just said now by him,'' Freddie in a typical declaration. Unlike his older brother, whom Mr. Wilmes portrays with as much heartiness as a monotone allows, Freddie still has a shred of an attention span left. In Mr. Maxwell's world, this is not necessarily a blessing.</p>
        <p>More than most of Mr. Maxwell's plays, this one conspicuously features physical movement. There is a dance sequence in which Freddie and Marissa slowly move in circles, wanly shifting their weight. The spirit of stunted passion here seems of a piece with Freddie's idea of foreplay, which is to brush at Marissa's breasts and then quickly withdraw his hand.</p>
        <p>Then there is the boxing match itself, for which an authentic ring has been provided. (Stephanie Nelson is the set and costume designer.) Mr. Maxwell, needless to say, milks every ounce of anticlimax from this climactic event, as Freddie listlessly takes on the older, marginally more animated Jerry (Jim Fletcher).</p>
        <p>Nobody in the ring or out of it seems to know how things should proceed, including the Referee (Lakpa Bhutia). The usual ringside patter that is the staple of boxing films is here delivered with the conviction of old porn stars simulating sex. ''I like it when you hurt each other,'' urges the Promoter blandly. Freddie's father (Benjamin Tejeda) materializes to express, in Spanish, his disappointment with his son's performance. Marissa appears briefly to beg Freddie to withdraw.</p>
        <p>This is the sort of material that has been parodied for years in spoofs like the 1978 film ''Movie Movie.'' Mr. Maxwell, however, isn't sending up an established genre. His characters are in a realm where even the energy of satire is beyond them.</p>
        <p>The delivery of the actors, many of whom are nonprofessionals, flattens speech to the point that distinctions between irony and sincerity, between questions and exclamations are erased. Mr. Maxwell's burned-out, overprogrammed Americans are one step shy of becoming automatons. The playwright's great accomplishment is to make us care about them nonetheless; it's that last flickering spark of humanity that makes them so funny and so sad.</p>
        <p>BOXING 2000</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Richard Maxwell; producing director, Barbara Hogue; sets and costumes by Stephanie Nelson; technical director, Billy Burns; stage manager, Louis Puopolo. Presented by New York City Players. At the Present Company Theatorium, 196-98 Stanton Street, Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>WITH: Gary Wilmes (Jo-Jo), Robert Torres (Freddie), Christopher Sullivan (Promoter), Gladys Perez (Marissa), Jim Fletcher (Jerry), Lakpa Bhutia (Referee), Candido ''Pito'' Rivera (Corner), Alexander Ruiz (Afleck) and Benjamin Tejeda (Father).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
