<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Valentine Speaks, Folks Start Scribbling</title>
    <meta content="21CURR$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/sports/21CURR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3DB103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Valentine Speaks, Folks Start Scribbling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses problems besetting New York Mets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took one question about himself to make Bobby Valentine's eyes bulge, to make words spew out of his mouth and to convince him to make the same curious move that he made last season. One question for Valentine to suddenly declare that he does not deserve a contract extension if the Mets do not make the postseason. There should have been an echo.</p>
        <p>It was a bizarre and riveting scene. Valentine talked to about two dozen reporters in the cramped visiting manager's office at Turner Field before last night's game with the Braves as if he were talking to a psychologist in a private room. Valentine rambled, but at least he did not use notes from the comments he uttered in Philadelphia 12 months ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It took one question about himself to make Bobby Valentine's eyes bulge, to make words spew out of his mouth and to convince him to make the same curious move that he made last season. One question for Valentine to suddenly declare that he does not deserve a contract extension if the Mets do not make the postseason. There should have been an echo.</p>
        <p>It was a bizarre and riveting scene. Valentine talked to about two dozen reporters in the cramped visiting manager's office at Turner Field before last night's game with the Braves as if he were talking to a psychologist in a private room. Valentine rambled, but at least he did not use notes from the comments he uttered in Philadelphia 12 months ago.</p>
        <p>''If we don't make the playoffs, I'll gladly take Fred off the hook, if we have to get into that nonsense again,'' Valentine said. ''But if we do, what does that mean?''</p>
        <p>Valentine was referring to Fred Wilpon, the co-owner who has said that he has a good feeling about Valentine returning as manager next season. But the Mets had dropped 12 of the 18 games before last night's 6-3 relief of a victory over the Braves, and they have endured three straight forgettable Septembers to underscore Valentine's failures in the second-most pivotal month of the season.</p>
        <p>Valentine is the common denominator in the funks and it bothers him and makes him defensive.</p>
        <p>There is a difference between Valentine's words this year and last year because he has a lot more wiggle room. Last September, Valentine seemed daring and maybe foolish. The Mets had lost five straight games and were tied with the Cincinnati Reds for the wild-card spot when Valentine, who had a year remaining on his contract, said, ''If we don't get to the playoffs, I shouldn't come back.''</p>
        <p>This time, the Mets had a five-game cushion for the wild card, so Valentine was not being too bold. Still, why did he bother to say it?</p>
        <p>''I got to retract that silly thing I said here,'' Valentine said. ''I cut to the chase and jumped to a conclusion that someone was going to ask it. I don't think Fred's on any hook.''</p>
        <p>The events that led to Valentine's weird behavior are the events that have turned the Mets into a mystifying team that crumbles in September. Mike Piazza stopped hitting and everyone else followed. Ordinary pitchers like Elmer Dessens and Tony Armas Jr. stifled the Mets. Turk Wendell and Pat Mahomes have been the biggest villains in a suspect bullpen.</p>
        <p>The Mets lost twice apiece to the Philadelphia Phillies and the Montreal Expos and then the Braves invaded their minds and tortured them on the field and off.</p>
        <p>Last night, the Mets finally conquered the Braves and exhaled. Al Leiter had a perfect game into the sixth inning, and Piazza, Todd Zeile and Edgardo Alfonzo had homers. Leiter, John Franco and Armando Benitez pitched out of bases-loaded situations in the sixth, seventh and eighth, as the Mets survived to win for only the third time in their past 23 games at Turner.</p>
        <p>Before feeling relief, Valentine had watched and seethed. He saw the Mets embarrass themselves while losing, 12-4, on Tuesday and he vented. He told the players they are too good to let this season vanish. Then, because Valentine cannot restrain himself, he portrayed himself as a victim.</p>
        <p>''It's the same old thing,'' Valentine said. ''If the team's going good, I know who it's about, and when they're not going good, I know who it's about. It's not going good, so let's make it about me.''</p>
        <p>Valentine talked about being able to ''take a punch'' and almost sounded like someone about to be fired. Even when Valentine was reminded about how Wilpon had said he wanted him back, the manager said: ''But that has changed. We haven't played well in September.''</p>
        <p>September with the Mets and Valentine is playing out like a dreadful late-night movie. Remember a night when you eschewed your pillow to watch a movie and you wound up angry because you lost sleep and were not entertained? Watching the Mets flounder and watching Valentine trying to deal with it is like being forced to sit through it again.</p>
        <p>Valentine started squirming as soon as he was asked if this season should be viewed as a referendum on his future. If the Mets recover, then Bobby stays. If the Mets fizzle, then Bobby goes. Valentine seized upon that question like a pit bull attacking a steak and sarcastically said that he should get a lifetime contract if the Mets rebound.</p>
        <p>As Valentine continued his discourse, he kept asking reporters about the ''flip side.'' Valentine claimed there are no questions about what happens if the Mets rumble past their troubles, as they did last year and as he vowed ''we will'' in 2000. When someone mentioned there have been several supportive columns about re-signing Valentine, he said, ''I'm not talking about stories. I'm talking about the outcome.''</p>
        <p>The outcome was that Valentine did not get a contract extension. He told Wilpon that he deserved one, but Wilpon disagreed. Wilpon studied Valentine in 2000 and mostly saw a reliable manager who won often and rarely said the wrong thing. Until last night. Another strange September continues.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
