<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Euro Britons Feeling Vindicated; But Nation's Currency Isolation Is Still Seen as Threat by Many</title>
    <meta content="Y21POUN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/business/21POUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Denmark</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greece</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Autofil Worldwide</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heck, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ullmann, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DB133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Euro Britons Feeling Vindicated; But Nation's Currency Isolation Is Still Seen as Threat by Many</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>SHERWOOD PARK, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British opposition to joining European single currency, the euro, has intensified as Britain's economy has continued to hold up well even as value of the euro has dropped badly against other major currencies; but with British trade closely tied to rest of Europe, euro supporters warn that nation's industries will suffer if Britain's interest rates and currency remain out of step with rest of Europe; debate is intensively political and emotional, with few indisputable economic facts to sway argument either way in what is by far largest of three holdouts against euro--Britain, Denmark and Sweden; Greece, which was left out originally because of its weak economy, is scheduled to join the euro in January; Anthony Ullmann and Michael Heck, co-managing directors of Autofil Worldwide, which makes yarn used in car upholstery, say their company has been hurt by weak euro; graphs; charts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Europe's single currency was introduced in 11 countries last year Britain stood aloof, refusing to abandon its venerable pound. It brushed aside domestic critics and business leaders who said their land might be setting misplaced nationalism ahead of the opportunity to participate in the Continent's greatest financial revolution.</p>
        <p>Now, 21 months later, with the euro staggering against the American dollar, the European currency's misfortunes seem only to have strengthened those convictions. Still aloof -- and proud of it -- many Britons seem to feel vindicated in their belief that the smart money was on abstention after all, while the costs of isolation from the euro-zone have been limited.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Europe's single currency was introduced in 11 countries last year Britain stood aloof, refusing to abandon its venerable pound. It brushed aside domestic critics and business leaders who said their land might be setting misplaced nationalism ahead of the opportunity to participate in the Continent's greatest financial revolution.</p>
        <p>Now, 21 months later, with the euro staggering against the American dollar, the European currency's misfortunes seem only to have strengthened those convictions. Still aloof -- and proud of it -- many Britons seem to feel vindicated in their belief that the smart money was on abstention after all, while the costs of isolation from the euro-zone have been limited.</p>
        <p>''We have moved against the grain of European opinion for centuries,'' said Lord David Owen, one of several political grandees linked with business groups opposed to Britain's joining the euro at this stage. ''It's been happening over a long period of time, and we mustn't be afraid of it.''</p>
        <p>It is not only politicians who sense that the euro is out of favor here. Business and financial interests were once largely united in favoring the euro. But a survey in mid-September by Merrill Lynch found that for the first time a majority among British fund managers had ''lost their enthusiasm'' for the euro, arguing that it would not be in the country's long-term economic interests to join. As recently as March 1999, the survey said, 60 percent of British fund managers had favored British membership. That figure slid to 40 percent in  early September.</p>
        <p>Not only that, Denmark, which rejected the treaty establishing the single currency several years ago, is set to vote again on whether to join the euro in a referendum on Sept. 28. With opinion among Danes shifting against membership, the British fund managers said a Danish ''no'' would not only make British membership less likely but perhaps damage the currency throughout Europe.</p>
        <p>''An upset in Denmark could be the next shock that triggers euro selling,'' said Trevor Greetham, global strategist at Merrill Lynch in London.</p>
        <p>Business groups skeptical of the euro -- assembled in a newly begun campaign called ''Euro No'' that depicts the European currency as a set of handcuffs -- declared in full-page newspaper advertisement: ''Our economy hasn't been so healthy in our lifetime.''</p>
        <p>The debate is intensely political and emotional, with few indisputable economic facts to sway the argument either way in what is by far the largest of three holdouts against the euro -- Britain, Denmark and Sweden. Greece, which was left out originally because of its weak economy, is scheduled to join the euro in January.</p>
        <p>While Britain's trade with the Continent has started to suffer, the nation has nonetheless survived a hint of recession with flying colors. It has also suppressed inflation and achieved more robust growth than Continental Europe largely because the Bank of England, free of the euro-zone's control by a ponderous and indecisive European Central Bank in Frankfurt, has been able to massage interest rates to shield the economy from its own boom-to-bust history.</p>
        <p>From that perspective, said Ian Stewart, an economist with Merrill Lynch in London, ''the benefits of being outside outweigh the benefits of being inside.''</p>
        <p>The City of London, Europe's financial district, has made brisk business from the euro, both in the eurobond market and from Europe's record-setting wave of cross-border consolidations. ''This is one area where there has been no sign of any losses,'' said Alasdair Murphy, a director of the pro-euro Center for European Reform.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the ledger, as the British pound has strengthened mightily against the euro, it has made British exports to Continental Europe -- half of its trade -- far more expensive. That has inflicted pain on manufacturers, who have shed hundreds of thousands of jobs since the euro's inception.</p>
        <p>Still, despite complaints from auto industry giants like Ford, BMW, Nissan and Toyota about the pound's strength, Britain has maintained its lead as the principal target for foreign corporations seeking a toehold in Europe's 15-nation single market. Government figures released in July showed that Britain's attractiveness has pushed the total value of overseas investment here to $382 billion, up a stunning 25 percent from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Those arguments form pillars of the anti-euro case. But more distant horizons seem less sparkling. Many overseas investors have come to Britain not just for its low labor costs and easy hire-and-fire laws, but because they assume that sooner or later Britain will join the euro.</p>
        <p>Indeed, with the pound weakening against the dollar, and long-term interest rates in Britain and the euro-zone looking set to converge, some economists argue that Britain is heading for a de facto alignment with the euro-zone that would make its membership simpler to achieve economically, if not politically.</p>
        <p>''The assumption is that we will be in at some stage, so there's no need to take short-term measures or to start rethinking strategic considerations,'' said Graham Bishop, an independent economic consultant.</p>
        <p>But if Prime Minister Tony Blair's tentative schedule to call a referendum on joining the euro within the next couple of years begins to slip -- as it now might with Mr. Blair's government facing a sudden loss in popularity -- ''then that begins to make people nervous,'' Mr. Bishop said.</p>
        <p>Lodged, moreover, between Europe and the United States -- more by economic culture than by geography -- Britain has in recent months suffered a double whammy of volatile exchange rates, with the strength of the United States economy pushing the pound to 14-year lows against the dollar just as sterling's strength against the euro makes British exports more expensive to sell in leading European markets.</p>
        <p>The peril of high oil costs, a strong dollar and a weak euro is troubling European business as a whole, of course. But in Britain that confluence of economic forces has once again illuminated the fault line running through Britain's economy. While the bulk of Britain's wealth is rooted in the quick-paced service-driven economy around London, a traditional manufacturing sector further north is grappling not only with its own historical decline but with the difficulties of exporting into the euro-zone from factories that count their costs in pounds.</p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, a small company like Autofil Worldwide, a manufacturer of yarn used in car upholstery, with a cavernous plant perched on a blustery hill in this industrial park north of Nottingham in the British Midlands. With annual revenue of $22 million, 80 percent of its sales of yarn are conducted in euros. It does the bulk of its business with suppliers, including those in Britain, in euros as well. The euro, Anthony Ullmann, a co-managing director, said, ''is a fact of life for us.''</p>
        <p>This tale of euro-centricity, though, has a flaw. While most of its revenue is in less valuable euros, Autofil's wages for 130 employees and its utility bills are fixed in pounds. Its main raw material, polyester derived from petroleum, is priced ultimately in dollars, pushing up the company's own costs. To counter these forces, the company has been forced to trim its profit margins.</p>
        <p>''We have the worst of both worlds,'' said Michael Heck, the other co-managing director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ullmann is convinced that this division must be erased to ensure the competitiveness of British industry. ''The question of losing the pound is an inevitability,'' he said. ''It's a question of when rather than if.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, though, companies like Autofil say sterling's volatility has cost them dearly. This year, for instance, Mr. Heck said, the company will increase sales by 30 percent, but earn no more than it did last year. And, Mr. Ullmann said, his European competitors ''don't do what I do when I get to the office every morning: check the price of the euro'' to work out how to adjust for currency shifts. ''It's very time consuming,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For all the economic disputes, however, the decision on joining the euro will ultimately be a political one. Mr. Blair's government, which is guardedly in favor of the euro, has promised that it will not move until after the next election, and will hold a referendum on joining the currency before abandoning the pound. And, alarmingly for those who support the euro, Mr. Blair's Labor Party has suddenly and surprisingly been overtaken in the opinion polls by the staunchly anti-euro Conservative opposition, raising questions about the government's fortunes at the next election for Parliament, which it is expected to call next year and cannot delay past May 2002. The mood swung against Labor over its handling of blockades by protesting truckers and farmers that threatened to paralyze the economy; sentiment could well swing back again before the vote is held.</p>
        <p>But Labor's loss of support could have wider ramifications. The Conservatives have placed their visceral and now united opposition to the euro at the center of a populist election campaign that can only become stronger if Labor is unable to win back popularity at home. And the anti-euro forces could gain further ground if other omens abroad -- particularly the Danish vote and the euro's swoon on foreign exchange markets -- reinforce their argument that the single currency is turning into a failure.</p>
        <p>In setting out the arguments for and against, hard economic data is scarce and ambiguous, hinging thus far on three questions. Has Britain's isolation from the euro damaged foreign investment? Has it been a setback for the City of London as one of the world's mightiest financial centers? And has Britain suffered from the swings in the euro's value against the pound?</p>
        <p>Only in the latter category can manufacturers and exporters trace losses that have cost jobs -- 200,000, according to Kitty Usher, the chief economist of the pro-euro Britain in Europe group. Against that, though, Britain's overall unemployment figures have declined since the introduction of the euro, suggesting that other jobs have been created over the same period.</p>
        <p>Among foreign investors, particularly the vocal Japanese automakers who have established major operations in Britain, the picture remains murky. Honda has announced a doubling of capacity at its plant at Swindon, west of London. But Toyota is set to open a new factory in France next year, and Nissan could move production of a new subcompact to the French installations of its partner, Renault.</p>
        <p>BMW and Ford both cited the pound's strength against the euro as reasons for their decisions to close assembly lines in Britain.</p>
        <p>That could deepen what some pro-Europeans see as a trend.</p>
        <p>''Globally, our share of foreign investment is falling,'' Ms. Usher said, arguing that while still at a record level, Britain's overall slice of the world's accumulated foreign investment had declined to 24 percent from 28 percent.</p>
        <p>Three million jobs, or one in nine, are directly or indirectly linked to exports to the euro-zone, Ms. Usher said. ''Those jobs could be affected by anything that would weaken our trading links with the euro-zone,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, she added, it did not really matter whether the exchange rate was defined by the euro's weakness or the pound's strength. ''It's all semantics,'' she said, ''if you are the person whose job is threatened.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
