<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official at Pension Agency Faces Scrutiny</title>
    <meta content="Y21PEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/business/21PENS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pension Benefit Guaranty Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Integrated Management Resources Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagans, Bennie L Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooks, Myrna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grassley, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bond, Christopher S (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D8133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official at Pension Agency Faces Scrutiny</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional investigators are set to testify before joint meeting of two Senate committees that Bennie L Hagans Jr, top executive of Pension Benefit Guaranty Corp, improperly steered $40 million worth of contracts to minority owned Integrated Management Resources Group, owned by Myrna Cooks; Hagans's boss David Strauss, executive director of agency, says his own inquiries found nothing even mildly inappropriate; says Hagans and Cooks are victims of racists who have fed misleading information to investigators; all key players on issue are white except for two people under suspicion, both of whom are black; Sens Charles E Grassley, chairman of committee on aging, and Christopher S Bond, chairman of small-business committee, have been examining operation of corporation, which takes over failed pension plans and pays benefits to retirees in the plans; inquiry includes not just contracts at issue but whether agency's computers are secure and sometimes years-long delays in telling workers how much they will get when they turn 65; allegations are being forwarded to Justice Department; Sens Bond and Grassley comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top executive of the federal agency that guarantees pensions improperly steered $40 million worth of contracts to a minority-owned company, Congressional investigators are set to testify this morning before a joint meeting of two Senate committees. The allegations, they said, are being forwarded to the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>But the executive's boss, David  Strauss, executive director of the agency, the Pension Benefit Guaranty Corporation, said his own inquiries found nothing even mildly inappropriate. He said the targets of the investigation -- Bennie L. Hagans Jr.  and Myrna Cooks, who owns the company that won the contracts -- are victims of racists who have fed misleading information to investigators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A top executive of the federal agency that guarantees pensions improperly steered $40 million worth of contracts to a minority-owned company, Congressional investigators are set to testify this morning before a joint meeting of two Senate committees. The allegations, they said, are being forwarded to the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>But the executive's boss, David  Strauss, executive director of the agency, the Pension Benefit Guaranty Corporation, said his own inquiries found nothing even mildly inappropriate. He said the targets of the investigation -- Bennie L. Hagans Jr.  and Myrna Cooks, who owns the company that won the contracts -- are victims of racists who have fed misleading information to investigators.</p>
        <p>All the key players on the issue are white except for the two people under suspicion, both of whom are black.</p>
        <p>Two Republican senators, Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, who is chairman of a committee on aging, and Christopher S. Bond of Missouri, who is chairman of a small-business committee, have been examining the operation of the Pension Benefit Guaranty Corporation, which takes over failed pension plans and pays benefits to retirees in the plans. Their inquiry includes not just the contracts at issue but whether the agency's computers are secure and the sometimes years-long delays in telling workers how much they will get when they turn 65.</p>
        <p>Senator Bond said last night that he was troubled by the findings of the Congressional investigators about the contract.</p>
        <p>''This is a matter that the Department of Justice will review seriously and then take appropriate action on the allegations that contracts worth $40 million were steered during Mr. Strauss' watch,'' Mr. Bond said.</p>
        <p>Senator Grassley said that other witnesses would detail how the agency fails to supervise private contractors, who have replaced government employees in many positions at the pension agency. ''One of our witnesses says this agency created an 'unbelievable mess' for his mother,'' he said. ''I'd borrow his words and say this agency is an unbelievable mess. Contractors do most of the work, yet nobody looks over their shoulder.''</p>
        <p>For more than a year, Mr. Strauss has been saying privately, often with great anger, that he believes Mr. Hagans and Ms. Cooks are the victims of racism.</p>
        <p>The $40 million of contracts were awarded beginning in 1997 to the Integrated Management Resources Group, even though it was not the low bidder. The company was created early that year by Ms. Cooks. She had been an executive of another company, Office Specialists Inc., which at the time had the contract with Mr. Hagans's office to administer some failed pension plans, including those of Pan American World Airways, which failed in 1991.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cooks was not the low bidder, but she won the contract partly on the recommendation of Mr. Hagans, who oversees the pension corporation division that pays out benefits to retirees.</p>
        <p>Robert H. Hast, the assistant comptroller general for special investigations, is expected to testify that Mr. Hagans showed favoritism and created the appearance of impropriety in helping Ms. Cooks win the contract.</p>
        <p>The comptroller general has no authority over the pension agency, but its investigators were brought in to assist the General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of Congress, at the request of the two senators.</p>
        <p>In addition to talking to a banker who was considering a $1 million loan that Ms. Cooks needed to start her business, Mr. Hagans also spoke to employees of Office Specialists who were being solicited by Ms. Cooks to work for her firm.</p>
        <p>To qualify as a bidder, under federal contracting rules, Ms. Cooks did not need to have people already on her payroll, but she did need to submit resumes to establish that she could provide experienced staff if she was awarded a contract. At the time, she was the only employee of her company, which operated out of the basement of her Maryland home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hast is expected to detail how Mr. Hagans came to the aid of Ms. Cooks when she was trying to recruit co-workers to join her firm, taking a trip to Atlanta, where the Pan Am pensions are administered, in July 1997 and speaking to the workers.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Cooks came in as the high bidder, a committee was appointed by Mr. Hagans to review the bids. One of the three people on that committee was Wilmer Graham, who works directly under Mr. Hagans and lives next door to Ms. Cooks. Ms. Graham's evaluation was not a significant part of the decision to award the contract to Ms. Cooks, Mr. Strauss said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagans, in an interview yesterday, said he did nothing wrong and that the Senate hearings were ''an insult.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cooks's lawyer, David W. Kuhnsman, said his client and her company had acted properly ''but they have been getting harassed for three years'' because she is black.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
