<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Appears Ready to Tackle Vehicle Rollover Problem</title>
    <meta content="Y21AUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/business/21AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelby, Richard C (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2DF103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Appears Ready to Tackle Vehicle Rollover Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Congress appears ready to tackle vehicle rollover problem in wake of 103 deaths attributed to defective Firestone tires, most of which occurred in Ford Explorers that flipped when their tires failed; automakers have blocked federal action on problem for 27 years; Sen Richard Shelby, chairman of Approppriations Subcommittee on Transportation, drops his objections to plan put forward by regulators last May to begin providing customers with information this winter on stability of many 2001 models; regulators have chosen to rate all family vehicles, giving them one to five stars, with highest ratings going to vehicles, like cars, that are very wide in proportion to height of their center of gravity; method does not take into account new electronic suspension systems that can improve stability; National Academy of Sciences will conduct nine-month study on ways to improve rating methods, and regulators will be required to reconsider their method based on academy's recommendations; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 103 deaths now attributed to defective Firestone tires, most of which occurred in Ford Explorers that flipped when their tires failed, have galvanized Congress to tackle a far larger traffic safety problem: vehicle rollovers.</p>
        <p>Automakers have blocked federal action on the problem for 27 years, but the last obstacle appeared to fall today. Senator Richard Shelby, Republican of Alabama, dropped his objections to a plan put forward by regulators last May to begin providing consumers with information this winter on the stability of many 2001 models.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 103 deaths now attributed to defective Firestone tires, most of which occurred in Ford Explorers that flipped when their tires failed, have galvanized Congress to tackle a far larger traffic safety problem: vehicle rollovers.</p>
        <p>Automakers have blocked federal action on the problem for 27 years, but the last obstacle appeared to fall today. Senator Richard Shelby, Republican of Alabama, dropped his objections to a plan put forward by regulators last May to begin providing consumers with information this winter on the stability of many 2001 models.</p>
        <p>The annual number of deaths involving rollovers has been inching up since 1993 as sport utility vehicles have become more popular, according to an analysis by The New York Times of a federal database that includes all fatal crashes across the country. Rollovers were a factor in 10,657 of the 35,806 deaths that occurred in vehicles of all types last year, the analysis found.</p>
        <p>As chairman of the Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Transportation, Senator Shelby had used his power over the Department of Transportation's budget this summer to block regulators from spending money to rate vehicles' stability. The senator's spokeswoman, Andrea Andrews, said late this afternoon that the senator had reached a tentative deal with other House and Senate lawmakers that would allow regulators to proceed with the ratings.</p>
        <p>Regulators have chosen a very simple method to rate all family vehicles, not just sport utilities: giving them one to five stars, with the highest ratings going to vehicles, like cars, that are very wide in proportion to the height of their center of gravity. But this method does not take into account new electronic suspension systems that can improve stability, which are being introduced on some luxury models.</p>
        <p>Under the tentative agreement, the National Academy of Sciences will conduct a nine-month study on ways to improve the rating method, and regulators will be required to reconsider their method based on the academy recommendations. Those changes could lead to even more stringent vehicle tests, Ms. Andrews said.</p>
        <p>Although the tentative agreement is subject to approval by a vote on Thursday of lawmakers involved in the transportation budget, Senator Shelby has been the only one publicly opposed to letting regulators proceed immediately with their original plan. Most safety groups, like Public Citizen and the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, have favored allowing the ratings to proceed. But Consumers Union, which publishes Consumer Reports, opposed the ratings,  asserting that any government evaluation should be based on more stringent tests.</p>
        <p>The entire increase in fatal rollovers in recent years has come from sport utility vehicles, for which the number of deaths has doubled since 1993, to 1,898. Most rollovers still involve cars and pickup trucks, because they make up the most vehicles on the road.</p>
        <p>The central problem facing policy makers is this: although the average frequency of deadly rollovers per million sport utilities has declined somewhat in recent years, these vehicles remain much more likely than cars to flip over. Further their numbers are increasing rapidly.</p>
        <p>The increase of nearly 1,000 in annual rollover deaths in sport utilities since 1993 has been mirrored by virtually identical increases in the annual number of people killed in rollovers over all, and the annual number of people killed by all types of crashes. Other accident fatalities involving sport utilities have also risen as sport utilities have become more common.</p>
        <p>Some other categories of deaths, meanwhile, like those attributed to drunken driving, have declined sharply.</p>
        <p>The tire-related rollover deaths that have occurred in Ford Explorers accounted for just 3 percent of all rollover deaths in sport utility vehicles in 1999. Even with the tire problems, drivers of Ford Explorers were only half as likely to die in a rollover in 1998 as were drivers of Chevrolet Blazers and Toyota 4Runners, according to insurance industry figures.</p>
        <p>Every indication is that the number of rollover deaths will keep climbing, even as automakers take steps to make sport utilities less prone to rolling over, and to make them protect their occupants better when they do. But the sales figures for sport utilities are climbing.</p>
        <p>Sport utilities account for almost 20 percent of new vehicles being sold, but still make up only 8 percent of all registered vehicles. As the cars of the 1970's and 1980's are scrapped, sport utilities will come to represent a much higher proportion of vehicles in use.</p>
        <p>''Unless sport utility vehicles are redesigned and go through some comprehensive engineering changes, we're going to see more rollovers in the future,'' said Sally Greenberg, the senior product safety counsel at Consumers Union.</p>
        <p>Still, there have been a few signs of improvement. The number of rollover deaths involving sport utilities has not risen as fast as the number of sport utilities on the roads, according to vehicle registration figures from the Polk Company, a market research firm. From 1993 to 1997, the number of sport utilities in use rose 75 percent, while the number of sport utilities occupants who died in rollovers rose 55 percent.</p>
        <p>This means that the likelihood of a fatal rollover for any single sport utility has inched down. Throughout the 1990's, automakers built ever larger, heavier sport utility vehicles, which are somewhat less prone to rolling over because of their greater weight, although even full-size sport utilities still roll over more often than midsize sedans. The first owners of large sport utilities also tend to be middle-aged families, consisting of more cautious drivers.</p>
        <p>But safety groups are not satisfied. ''Doing something about rollovers is a high priority because there is a significant number of deaths, and we are making progress in frontal and side crashes,'' said Brian O'Neill, the president of the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, a trade group bankrolled by insurers seeking to reduce the cost of crash claims.</p>
        <p>Automakers say that they are addressing the rollover problem, by lowering the center of gravity of some sport utilities, installing electronic stability systems in some luxury models and even putting in air bags that deploy from the ceiling, to reduce the risk that passengers will smash through the side windows during rollovers.</p>
        <p>An auto industry computer simulation, demonstrated for auto engineers at a closed-door meeting in late 1997, shows that when a sport utility vehicle rolls over, an unbelted rider tends to be thrown through a side window in the direction of the roll, and is then crushed by the vehicle.</p>
        <p>''I know you've heard about people being thrown clear in an accident, but believe me, that's an old husband's tale,'' said Helen Petrauskas, Ford's vice president for environmental and safety issues, at a news conference last January, when the company announced that it would start offering the ceiling-mounted air bags on the 2002 Explorer, which goes on sale in January.</p>
        <p>Sport utilities, particularly the larger models that have been popular since the mid-1990's, also do tremendous damage to cars that they hit. Some safety experts have expressed additional concern about what will happen when these vehicles begin to age, start suffering mechanical problems and are resold to younger drivers. Many automakers have announced plans this year to build sport utilities that will be less dangerous to other motorists, through design changes that will make them less likely to ride over cars' bumpers and door sills.</p>
        <p>The public image of rollovers, shaped by television footage of vehicles weaving at high speed through slalom courses of safety cones, is that vehicles tip over when drivers swerve too sharply trying to avoid road hazards. But federal regulators say, and auto industry engineers tend to agree, that fewer than 10 percent of all rollovers happen purely because of sharp maneuvers on a paved road.</p>
        <p>Federal studies have found that as many as 92 percent of rollovers occur when a vehicle is ''tripped.'' This can happen either because the vehicle strikes a car, curb, guard rail or other low object, or because one side of the vehicle starts traveling over a surface that slows it down, like a muddy shoulder of the road.</p>
        <p>The Times's analysis found that a vehicle rollover was the first thing that went wrong in 4,125 of the 10,657 rollover deaths last year. Sport utilities accounted for a quarter of all crashes that started with rollovers, even though sport utilities still make up only one-twelfth of all vehicles in use.</p>
        <p>The federal database does not provide enough information to determine how many of these rollovers involved vehicles that tripped over an object. The rest of the rollover deaths occurred in vehicles that flipped over only after a crash had begun with some other event, such as striking another vehicle.</p>
        <p>One of the best answers would be to persuade more people to wear seat belts. A data review by regulators in 1998 found that only 327 of the 1,482 people who died in sport utility vehicle rollovers in 1997 were wearing their seat belts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
