<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Garden, It's Lights Out For a Superstar</title>
    <meta content="21ROBE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/sports/21ROBE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phoenix Suns</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Glen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longley, Luc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dudley, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Vernon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Travis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Horace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DB103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Garden, It's Lights Out For a Superstar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Selena Roberts</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers trade Patrick Ewing to Seattle SuperSonics in four-team deal; Knicks receive Glen Rice from Los Angeles Lakers, Vernon Maxwell from Seattle SuperSonics, Luc Longley from Phoenix Suns and Travis Knight from Lakers plus four draft selections; other players involved in trade noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was early last November when Patrick Ewing was sprawled on the floor of a locker room, flexing old knees that resembled stripped lug nuts, testing a slow-healing Achilles' tendon that left him in dark moods.</p>
        <p>All the while, he was craning his neck, eavesdropping on a conversation. A few feet away, Chris Childs was providing an innocent detail of Ewing's progress toward his return from injury. Just a harmless update. That is when the 7-foot curmudgeon turned to Childs and snapped, ''Don't be talking about my business.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was early last November when Patrick Ewing was sprawled on the floor of a locker room, flexing old knees that resembled stripped lug nuts, testing a slow-healing Achilles' tendon that left him in dark moods.</p>
        <p>All the while, he was craning his neck, eavesdropping on a conversation. A few feet away, Chris Childs was providing an innocent detail of Ewing's progress toward his return from injury. Just a harmless update. That is when the 7-foot curmudgeon turned to Childs and snapped, ''Don't be talking about my business.''</p>
        <p>This was Ewing the Knick. There was always a No Trespassing sign posted on his life, and very few gained entrance into his personal space. For the players who were loyal props for his bravado -- like John Starks and Herb Williams -- he made an exception. Otherwise, it was Keep Out.</p>
        <p>For years, the Madison Square Garden management and the Knicks' coaching staff were the enablers to his rock-star behavior. The Garden's president, Dave Checketts, paid him to extremes, Coach Jeff Van Gundy praised him to no end and everyone allowed Ewing to separate himself from the rest.</p>
        <p>Under the Ewing rules, he picked the luxury hotels and gave the nod to the flight plans. His high maintenance was legendary. At least once, he demanded that a flight attendant shake his orange juice for him on the team plane.</p>
        <p>As long as he was the franchise player, everyone accepted Ewing's supreme existence, including his teammates. But when Ewing's guarantees became increasingly hollow last season, when he failed to grasp the reality of his own decline, his teammates became less reverent and more resentful.</p>
        <p>Now, with the trade of Ewing to Seattle, there will be a silent cheer from his former teammates. They may not voice it publicly, but Allan Houston, Latrell Sprewell, Larry Johnson, Childs and a few others found Ewing's stubborn inability to see himself as a role player inhibiting to the team's success.</p>
        <p>By the time the Knicks were eliminated in six games at the hands of the Indiana Pacers' Reggie Miller, Ewing's teammates were not hailing his greatness; they were quietly questioning his presence. Just two years earlier, Ewing stood in the Knicks' locker room and playfully proclaimed, ''This is my Garden.''</p>
        <p>Last season, he was more like a stranger on the scene. Here is how desperate things had become for him: his only close friend on the team, the forgettable Mursad Turkcan, was gone by year's end.</p>
        <p>''He chose to be a loner,'' one Knick teammate said when the trade speculation began this summer. ''He wanted everyone to say, 'Yeah, Pat, you're still great.' And no one did.''</p>
        <p>So it was not a surprise when Ewing consented to be traded. It was just jarring. When the Ewing-free Knicks step on the Garden floor this year, it will be like going to an old neighborhood and finding a Best Buy on the site of the corner market.</p>
        <p>It will seem strange.</p>
        <p>But for some Knicks, it will feel liberating. In some ways, Van Gundy is included in that group.</p>
        <p>Although Ewing believed he was unappreciated by the organization, and led astray by the medical staff about his Achilles' tendon tear, he may have been most disappointed in Van Gundy.</p>
        <p>As last season unfolded, Van Gundy still pumped up Ewing's greatness, but usually in the past tense. At times, Van Gundy benched Ewing in the fourth quarter, called game-ending plays for others on the floor and began the process of moving beyond their post-up style.</p>
        <p>In the end, those close to Ewing say he felt betrayed by Van Gundy. But as Van Gundy often said, one of the most difficult tricks in sports is coaching a superstar on the decline. Ultimately, Van Gundy's preseason prediction came true, ''It could really end ugly for Patrick.''</p>
        <p>It did. Players saw him as an outdated part in the scheme, a horse-and-buggy to their fast-lane ways. They whispered that Ewing held them back, cramped their style and weighed down the offense.</p>
        <p>And then there was the playoff stat that became a catch phrase: the Knicks were 5-1 over two playoff runs against the Pacers without Ewing. When brought to his attention, the candid Sprewell was honest enough to say what other Knicks were thinking: ''Numbers don't lie.''</p>
        <p>But the numbers really didn't matter. Even before their final playoff series, the players already had a love-hate relationship with Ewing. Although they constantly looked for Ewing to bail them out at the shot clock and relied on their aging center to grab the rebounds while they eagerly escaped the contact, some players believed he was an albatross around their neck. Upon elimination, after what ended up to be Ewing's final crestfallen exit from the Garden, there was only halfhearted sympathy for him.</p>
        <p>''It's unfair for people to criticize him, but that's life,'' Houston said. ''You do the best you can, and that's what Patrick does.''</p>
        <p>Ewing's effort was always there. No one disputed that. But at some point, perception became the reality. Once the players believed Ewing suppressed their chances of victory, the losses seemed to occur almost subconsciously.</p>
        <p>Now, the alibi has been removed, the target of blame is gone. As Ewing exits, he will turn over the keys to the team. This is what the Knicks wanted. And in many ways, with Ewing's animosity toward the organization growing, with his teammates carefully trying to step around his fragile ego, this is the way it had to end.</p>
        <p>But at some point, as the clock winds down on a game in April, the same teammates who privately resented him will be looking for the irascible No. 33.</p>
        <p>Stubborn as he was, ego-driven as he remained, he would take the last shot, absorb the criticism and never shrink from a challenge. At some point, the Knicks will miss the grumpy old man.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
