<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Military Backs Ex-Guard Pilot Over Pvt. Gore</title>
    <meta content="21MILI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/politics/21MILI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: SUPPORT OF THE MILITARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott (Former Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DE103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Military Backs Ex-Guard Pilot Over Pvt. Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush, who joined Texas National Guard and did not go to Vietnam, has far more support among military personnel than Vice Pres Al Gore, who enlisted in Army and went to Vietnam; interviews indicate Bush enjoys some automatic credibility with military because of his party affiliation, policy positions, running mate, Dick Cheney, advisers and his father, former Pres George Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore enlisted in the Army and went to Vietnam. George W. Bush joined the Texas National Guard and did not. But for many people in uniform, that makes little difference. It is Mr. Bush, not Mr. Gore, who seems to enjoy some automatic credibility with the military because of his party affiliation, his policy positions, his running mate, his advisers -- and his father.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Gore hoped his own military record would make him more palatable to the nation's 1.4 million men and women in uniform -- and by extension the 24 million who are veterans -- he might be disappointed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore enlisted in the Army and went to Vietnam. George W. Bush joined the Texas National Guard and did not. But for many people in uniform, that makes little difference. It is Mr. Bush, not Mr. Gore, who seems to enjoy some automatic credibility with the military because of his party affiliation, his policy positions, his running mate, his advisers -- and his father.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Gore hoped his own military record would make him more palatable to the nation's 1.4 million men and women in uniform -- and by extension the 24 million who are veterans -- he might be disappointed.</p>
        <p>Eight years after President Clinton's lack of a military record and his advocacy for gays in the military set the stage for his roiling relations with the Pentagon, Mr. Gore appears to have far less support in the military, especially among the officer corps, than his opponent. Mr. Bush, who did not serve in Vietnam but trained as a fighter pilot during his National Guard stint, has wide support.</p>
        <p>In about 20 interviews in recent weeks, those in uniform or recently retired from service expressed overwhelming, though not universal, support for Mr. Bush -- not only as the Republican presidential candidate, but as a veteran and the son of former President Bush, who many said served ably as commander in chief during the military's shining moment after Vietnam, the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>They cited Governor Bush's policy proposals, his accusations that the Clinton administration had overseen a ''military in decline,'' and his high-profile military advisers, including his vice-presidential running mate, Dick Cheney, a former secretary of defense, and Gen. Colin L. Powell, the former chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff who Mr. Bush has all but said would be a member of his cabinet.</p>
        <p>''People are just more comfortable with the idea of a Bush-Cheney-Powell team in the White House again,'' an Army colonel said. (Even an Air Force colonel inclined to vote for Mr. Gore said he wished he could still cast a vote for General Powell as secretary of state.)</p>
        <p>And when it comes to military service, an issue that dogged Mr. Clinton's campaign in 1992, many of those interviewed gave Mr. Bush the benefit of the doubt for his time in the National Guard, which attracted thousands of young people trying to avoid going to war in Vietnam. And they offered only grudging respect for Mr. Gore's decision to volunteer.</p>
        <p>By contrast, it is not hard for Mr. Bush's supporters in uniform to find something to admire in his service flying F-102 Delta Dagger fighters for the Guard, even if he never went to war. ''Anybody who was willing to take the risks to learn to be a fighter pilot is worthy,'' said one Army general, himself a Vietnam combat veteran. ''He made a contribution.''</p>
        <p>Several military men noted that Mr. Gore was an Army journalist -- a profession of ill repute to many in uniform even if he was toiling on behalf of the Pentagon -- and served an abbreviated tour in Vietnam. ''If he had served in combat and brought home a Purple Heart,'' an Army colonel said, ''the contrast might have been greater.''</p>
        <p>Instead, as another officer put it using the sort of colorful language often heard in the military, ''He was a public affairs puke.''</p>
        <p>The men and women in the military, of course, have traditionally been more conservative than the general electorate, especially those in the officer corps. In recent years, more of its members than ever have identified themselves as Republican. A survey last year by the Triangle Institute for Security Studies, a nonprofit foundation based in North Carolina, found that 64 percent of young officers were Republicans, compared with only 8 percent who were Democrats.</p>
        <p>So support for Mr. Bush from those in uniform is not altogether surprising. Throughout his campaign, Mr. Bush has surrounded himself with so many retired generals and admirals, including General Powell and Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf, that some Gore advisers have taken to envious sniping.</p>
        <p>''This is the kind of thing you see in the Third World -- all these generals lining up behind the politicians,'' one Gore adviser said.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Cheney announced the endorsements of an array of retired military leaders, including several senior officers who served in influential positions under Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore, a fact the Bush campaign was careful to emphasize.</p>
        <p>One of those endorsing Mr. Bush, Gen. Anthony C. Zinni, who recently stepped down as commander of American forces in the Persian Gulf, said he did not agree with some of the harshest accusations that Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore had deliberately run down the military.</p>
        <p>Still General Zinni said a changing world and mounting problems with readiness, including shortages of spare parts and problems with recruiting and retaining quality troops, needed more attention than they had received.</p>
        <p>''We've have these problems for a couple years and they haven't been addressed,'' General Zinni said. He, too, praised Mr. Bush's advisers, including Richard L. Armitage, a senior Pentagon official in President Reagan's administration.</p>
        <p>''To think that people like Cheney and Powell and Armitage will be part of a Bush administration,'' he added, ''encourages me that there might be answers.''</p>
        <p>The military is not monolithic, of course. And Mr. Gore has several high-ranking military retirees supporting him. Gen. John M. Shalikashvili, a former chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and Adm. William Owens, a former vice chairman, have both advised the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>Several of those interviewed said Mr. Gore had stronger support among the enlisted ranks, which are more racially and economically diverse than the officer corps. One Army officer said that Mr. Gore was seen as more likely to be supportive of expanding the presence of women in uniform, noting that the Republican platform calls for separating new recruits by sex in basic training, something many women in uniform do not support.</p>
        <p>''I think women and minorities will look at who is giving them the best opportunities,'' the Army officer said.</p>
        <p>Still, it was clear that Mr. Gore -- despite his own record, his service on the Senate's Armed Services Committee and his relatively more hawkish views on defense issues compared with other Democrats -- suffered from his association with Mr. Clinton, whose relations with the military, especially early in his first administration, were tumultuous.</p>
        <p>Under the Uniform Code of Military Justice, people still serving in the military are prohibited from making disparaging remarks about civilian leaders, and the Pentagon's policy forbids overtly partisan political activities, so all of those interviewed in recent weeks spoke only if they would not be identified by name and, in some cases, rank, service and base.</p>
        <p>Several said concerns about military readiness, which Mr. Bush has relentlessly raised, had grown on Mr. Gore's watch.</p>
        <p>They also cited one of Mr. Gore's early missteps. During the primaries Mr. Gore said he would make support for gays serving openly in the military a condition for officers being considered for a position on the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Mr. Gore reversed himself within days, but to many the damage was done.</p>
        <p>''That was a disaster,'' a Navy officer said.</p>
        <p>Leon S. Fuerth, a senior adviser to Mr. Gore, said that Mr. Gore had built enormous credibility on defense issues as a senator and as vice president. Mr. Fuerth also said Mr. Gore's service as an Army private would give him ''some insight and understanding of military life'' that would help him in dealing with the Pentagon's brass.</p>
        <p>''President Clinton developed an excellent rapport with the armed services as time went on, but at the very beginning of the first Clinton administration, that wasn't yet in place,'' Mr. Fuerth said. ''In the very beginning of a Gore administration, it would be in place.''</p>
        <p>Even one of Mr. Bush's staunchest supporters -- the former commandant of the Marine Corps, Gen. Charles C. Krulak -- agreed.</p>
        <p>''All the people I talk to in the military, both those serving today and those who like me have retired,'' General Krulak said, ''they're just happy to have somebody who knows how to salute.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: SUPPORT OF THE MILITARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
