<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cruelties of Apartheid, Chronicled by a Child</title>
    <meta content="21SYRI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/arts/21SYRI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gien, Pamela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Syringa Tree, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DE133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cruelties of Apartheid, Chronicled by a Child</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews The Syringa Tree, one-woman play written and performed by Pamela Gien at Playhouse 91; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her delicate appearance notwithstanding, Pamela Gien, the gifted writer and performer of ''The Syringa Tree,'' has an unyielding spine as a storyteller. Her show, presented at Playhouse 91 on the Upper East Side, is an evocative and difficult monologue about a childhood, presumably her own, spent in South Africa in the darkest days of apartheid.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gien, who grew up in a suburb of Johannesburg, plays a dozen or more roles, and in the end the play spans 20 years. Still, this is a painful and deeply personal piece (or so it seems, and that's really all that matters) that is largely concerned with bigotry and the senseless violence it engenders, seen through the eyes of a little girl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her delicate appearance notwithstanding, Pamela Gien, the gifted writer and performer of ''The Syringa Tree,'' has an unyielding spine as a storyteller. Her show, presented at Playhouse 91 on the Upper East Side, is an evocative and difficult monologue about a childhood, presumably her own, spent in South Africa in the darkest days of apartheid.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gien, who grew up in a suburb of Johannesburg, plays a dozen or more roles, and in the end the play spans 20 years. Still, this is a painful and deeply personal piece (or so it seems, and that's really all that matters) that is largely concerned with bigotry and the senseless violence it engenders, seen through the eyes of a little girl.</p>
        <p>The innocence of children is instantly engaging, of course, their powerlessness a natural source of sympathy. But as the source of a narrative, a child is not powerless, not over an audience, and the responsibilities of power -- to entertain us, to carry us along, to move us -- obtain in youth as much as in maturity. With its earnest discoveries, uninformed perspectives and limited locutions, a child's point of view is difficult enough to present credibly and compellingly on the page; on the stage, the problems are compounded. Few actors can manage a preadolescent voice without descending into cloying treacle, or a child's physical enthusiasms without making you want to send them to their rooms. Most often, adults acting children's roles don't seem childish at all, just retarded, and anyone who makes the attempt risks a quick alienation of an audience.</p>
        <p>This is the difficulty that Ms. Gien addresses with remarkable, even stubborn audacity; against a curved, sand-colored backdrop with only a swing hanging from the ceiling as a stage prop, Ms. Gien, barefoot and wearing a plain shift, introduces us to the world of Elizabeth, 7 years old as the story begins. Speaking in the  wondering and adorable tones of a loved and privileged girl -- ''Did you know, you can tell how lucky you're going to be when you look at those little white spots on your nails?'' -- Ms. Gien adopts the persona that will control more than half the evening.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth has a youngster's brief attention span, and her narrative is nearly bereft of conventional exposition. The language is idiomatic (''I'm a very lucky fish!''), the cultural references often exotic. In fitful episodes that fill in the backdrop of South Africa in the 1960's in impressionistic bits, we are introduced to Elizabeth's parents (her father is a doctor, her mother runs a home bustling with black help) and several of the servants, including Salamina, Elizabeth's devoted nanny, who very early on gives birth to a daughter, Moliseng. Elizabeth witnesses the delivery, and it is her complex, sisterly bond with Moliseng that eventually forms the story's arc.</p>
        <p>None of this is easy to assimilate. The persona of Elizabeth challenges the audience to challenge her authority. Even when Ms. Gien switches parts, which she does seamlessly  with a pivot and adjustments in posture and voice, the effect is that the new character's anger, delight or concern is Elizabeth's perception of it. But if you're tempted, as I was from time to time, to think ''Grow up, already'' -- well, anyone interested in the rudiments of storytelling will admire Ms. Gien's courage and considerable skill.</p>
        <p>When a narrator is unreliable -- biased, silly or, as here, very young -- it is a precarious enterprise for the author to negotiate the boundary between the teller of a tale and its controlling intelligence. But when this is accomplished with surety and control -- think of, say, ''The Catcher in the Rye'' -- it is the author's wisdom that seeps through the cracks of the presumed author-ity of the narrator. The root of the word is significant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gien's persona may try your patience, but it's a risk she takes willfully, and the payoff is a thoroughly persuasive transport to a time and a place. Most in the audience will be as new to the experience the play describes as Elizabeth is; that, of course, is the idea behind Ms. Gien's narrative strategy. And as we witness the evocation of a society where cruelty is both legislated and psychologically ingrained, the effect is deeply shocking.</p>
        <p>The indignities perpetrated on Salamina and Moliseng and the other blacks in Elizabeth's world, not to mention the genuine terrors that apartheid brings about -- among other things, a baby mysteriously and carelessly disappears from a hospital, and Elizabeth's grandparents are murdered -- may be disclosed obliquely, through the uncomprehending vision of a child, but they stun with the power of a gut punch.</p>
        <p>THE SYRINGA TREE</p>
        <p>Written and performed by Pamela Gien; directed by Larry Moss; sets by Kenneth Foy; costumes by William Ivey Long; lighting by Jason Kantrowitz; sound by Tony Suraci; production stage manager, Fredric H. Orner; general management, Soloway/Levy. Presented by Matt Salinger. At Playhouse 91, 316 East 91st Street, Yorkville.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
