<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Adviser Tied to Companies</title>
    <meta content="Y21ADV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/politics/21ADVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDICARE STRATEGIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Citizen (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilensky, Gail R (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D7133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Adviser Tied to Companies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Gail R Wilensky, principal author of Gov George W Bush's Medicare plan, serves on boards of eight health care companies that would be affected by Bush proposal and holds stock and stock options in companies worth $4 million to $5 million; she says ties to health care concerns are matter of public record and denies any conflict of interest, interview; says she has recused herself from decisions of panel that advises Congress on Medicare policy while serving as Bush health adviser; Public Citizen, which will release report on her health care holdings, charges she advocates plan that favors providers over consumers and stands to profit personally if plan is enacted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A principal author of Gov. George W. Bush's Medicare plan, Dr. Gail R. Wilensky, serves on the boards of eight health care companies whose fortunes could be affected by the Bush proposal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky, a former administrator of the government office that runs Medicare and the current chairwoman of the panel that advises Congress on Medicare policy, holds stock and stock options in the companies worth $4 million to $5 million today, according to company documents and Dr. Wilensky's own estimates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A principal author of Gov. George W. Bush's Medicare plan, Dr. Gail R. Wilensky, serves on the boards of eight health care companies whose fortunes could be affected by the Bush proposal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky, a former administrator of the government office that runs Medicare and the current chairwoman of the panel that advises Congress on Medicare policy, holds stock and stock options in the companies worth $4 million to $5 million today, according to company documents and Dr. Wilensky's own estimates.</p>
        <p>She said her relationships with the health care concerns were a matter of public record and denied that there was any conflict between her service on the corporate boards and her role as a health policy adviser to Governor Bush.</p>
        <p>''I behave in an open and public manner and don't try to hide what I am doing,'' Dr. Wilensky said in an interview. ''I might be opinionated, I might be wrong, but I'm not carrying anybody else's water.''</p>
        <p>She said she has recused herself from decisions of the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission, the Congressional policy panel, while she serves as a health adviser to Governor Bush to avoid the appearance of a conflict.</p>
        <p>And she asserted that there was no way to calculate the direct or indirect financial effect of the health plans of Mr. Bush or Vice President Al Gore on individual companies. Nor does her service on those boards in any way affect the public policy positions she advocates, she said.</p>
        <p>But Public Citizen, a research group founded by Ralph Nader, charged that Dr. Wilensky represented drug and managed-care interests directly affected by Mr. Bush's plan and called her financial relationship to numerous health care concerns ''wholly inappropriate.''</p>
        <p>Frank Clemente, director of Public Citizen's Congress Watch, said that Dr. Wilensky advocated a health care proposal that favored providers over consumers. And he contended that she stood to profit personally if the Bush plan were enacted.</p>
        <p>''Here is a central health care adviser to Bush who is a major representative of pharmaceutical and insurance interests, which is why the Bush prescription drug program is so favored by the industry and so opposed by consumers,'' Mr. Clemente said. ''It is just wholly inappropriate and a direct conflict of interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's health care proposal leaves much medical decision-making to private industry, including insurers and health maintenance organizations. The government would still pay most costs and would supervise insurers, approving or disapproving all plans.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky wrote much of the plan and explained it to reporters when it was released. The proposal is consistent with Dr. Wilensky's longstanding views on the most efficient means of delivering medical services to consumers.</p>
        <p>Public Citizen is planning to release a report this week detailing Dr. Wilensky's holdings in health care companies and accusing her of designing a health plan that could enrich her. The report, which the group made available to The New York Times, contends that her financial stake in the medical industry is more troubling than the Halliburton Company stock options of Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's running mate. Mr. Cheney might shape energy policy some time in the future in a Bush administration, the report states, while Dr. Wilensky is already drafting proposals for the campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said this month that if elected he would forfeit stock options worth about $3.5 million in Halliburton, the energy services company that he left to run for office.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign reacted angrily to Public Citizen's charges and defended Dr. Wilensky.</p>
        <p>''This is a ridiculous assertion by a left-leaning group which supports more government control over health care,'' said Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Democrats and Republicans in Congress believe she has high integrity and trust her to advise them on health care policy and we believe she is an added asset to our campaign,'' Mr. Bartlett said. ''The policy that Governor Bush implements or promotes will be based on what's best for America and will be based on consultation from a wide range of advisers from a wide range of backgrounds.''</p>
        <p>Vice President Gore's health policy advisers are chiefly full-time Democratic campaign aides or government officials. The group includes Elaine Kamarck, Mr. Gore's top domestic policy adviser; Sarah Bianchi, a Gore campaign health policy specialist; Donna E. Shalala, the secretary of Health and Human Services; Chris Jennings, the White House's senior health affairs adviser; and Dr. David A. Kessler, the dean of the Yale University Medical School.</p>
        <p>None appear to hold any outside employment or corporate directorships, according to the Gore campaign and public records.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky, 57, who holds a doctorate in economics, is the John M. Olin Senior Fellow at Project HOPE, an international health foundation, her only full-time position. She is taking leave and vacation time from Project HOPE to advise the Bush campaign, she said.</p>
        <p>She served in the White House under President Bush in 1992 as deputy assistant for policy development, working on health care and welfare issues. Dr. Wilensky's largest single holding is in the United HealthCare Corporation, one of the nation's leading managed-care companies.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky has a total of 70,750 shares and stock options in United, which closed at $92.31 a share today. She exercised her option to acquire 16,000 of the shares at $49.50 a share in May, yielding a paper profit of nearly $700,000.</p>
        <p>The face value of all securities of companies she serves as a director is more than $12 million, corporate filings show. But Dr. Wilensky said that because many of her holdings were in stock options granted her as compensation for her board service -- and many had not yet vested -- their actual value was less than $5 million today.</p>
        <p>Company disclosure documents generally do not reveal the price at which the options were granted so it is impossible to calculate precisely the value of Dr. Wilensky's holdings. She said she has disclosed all of her directorships and outside interests under Congressional ethics rules. However, she added, ''I don't feel I have an obligation to disclose asset accumulation.''</p>
        <p>As a result of her board service, Dr. Wilensky holds thousands of shares and options in Gentiva Health Services, Syncor, Advanced Tissue Sciences, Shared Medical Systems, St. Jude Medical Care, Quest Diagnostics and Manor Care. The companies provide a variety of medical services from human tissue replacements to nursing care to data management.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for several of the companies said that they took no position on the Bush or the Gore health care proposals.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky said that the drug industry has the most to gain or lose from the presidential candidates' competing health plans.</p>
        <p>The industry's trade association, the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers Association, has been critical of the Gore plan because, the group contends, it will lead to government price controls. The industry has been more sympathetic to the Bush proposal because it leaves drug purchasing for Medicare largely in the private sector.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky said that she is not a director of any drug company or member of the industry's trade association.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE MEDICARE STRATEGIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
