<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Send Ewing to Sonics As 4-Team Deal Ends an Era</title>
    <meta content="21KNIC$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/sports/21KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phoenix Suns</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Glen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Travis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longley, Luc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Vernon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borrell, Lazaro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stepania, Vladimir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dudley, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Horace</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Emanual</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Person, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Layden, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DB103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Send Ewing to Sonics As 4-Team Deal Ends an Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers trade Patrick Ewing, cornerstone of franchise for past 15 years, to Seattle SuperSonics in four-team, 12-player deal largely orchestrated by Knicks and Ewing; Knicks will get Los Angeles Lakers forward Glen Rice, Lakers center Travis Knight and Phoenix Suns center Luc Longley; will also get guard Vernon Maxwell, forwards Lazaro Borrell and Vladimir Stepania and draft picks from Seattle and Lakers; also send center Chris Dudley and draft pick to Phoenix; Lakers will get Horace Grant, Greg Foster, Emanual Davis and Chuck Person from Seattle; Knicks general manager Scott Layden says Ewing sought trade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After one embarrassingly botched trade attempt and several other false starts, the Knicks last night finally parted with Patrick Ewing, the cornerstone of the franchise for the past 15 years.</p>
        <p>A four-team, 12-player deal that was largely orchestrated by the Knicks and Ewing's agent, David Falk, will send the future Hall of Fame center to the Seattle SuperSonics, Knicks General Manager Scott Layden announced last night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After one embarrassingly botched trade attempt and several other false starts, the Knicks last night finally parted with Patrick Ewing, the cornerstone of the franchise for the past 15 years.</p>
        <p>A four-team, 12-player deal that was largely orchestrated by the Knicks and Ewing's agent, David Falk, will send the future Hall of Fame center to the Seattle SuperSonics, Knicks General Manager Scott Layden announced last night.</p>
        <p>In return, the Knicks will receive the sharpshooting Los Angeles Lakers forward Glen Rice, the Lakers backup center Travis Knight and Phoenix Suns center Luc Longley.</p>
        <p>In addition, they will receive several peripheral players -- guard Vernon Maxwell, forwards Lazaro Borrell and Vladimir Stepania -- and a first-round draft pick and two second-round picks in 2001 from Seattle, as well as the Lakers' first-round pick in 2001. The Knicks also sent Chris Dudley, their backup center, and a first-round pick in 2001 to Phoenix.</p>
        <p>The Lakers will also receive Horace Grant, Greg Foster, Emanual Davis and Chuck Person from Seattle.</p>
        <p>The blockbuster deal was Layden's first significant move with the Knicks, and it appeared that Ewing, who desperately wanted out of New York, forced his hand.</p>
        <p>''It became clear that he was looking for a change, and when he requested a trade, we respected his request,'' Layden said in a statement last night. ''It was important in doing so, however, that we had the ability to add value, and with Glen and his All-Star credentials, as well as two veteran big men and draft picks, we believe we have done that.''</p>
        <p>The trade represented the insuperable gap that had developed between the 38-year-old Ewing and the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Ewing, the former Georgetown all-American who was the No. 1 draft pick in 1985, toiled admirably, if fruitlessly, for 15 years in search of a National Basketball Association championship.</p>
        <p>It is not likely that he will win his elusive title with the Sonics, who have the superior Lakers and Portland Trail Blazers to conquer.</p>
        <p>Nor is he likely to receive the two-year contract extension he reportedly wanted the Knicks to give him.</p>
        <p>The Knicks realize that this is not a good deal for them, either. If they do not complete another trade -- one that would land them a frontline power forward or a top-flight center -- they will enter training camp on Oct. 3 having dropped several notches.</p>
        <p>Longley, a 7-foot-2-inch veteran who won three championships with Michael Jordan's Chicago Bulls, is mediocre at best. He averaged just 6.3 points, 4.5 rebounds and 19.7 minutes as the Suns' starter last season.</p>
        <p>If the Knicks do not follow with another more attractive move, their starting lineup could look something like this: Longley at center; Larry Johnson and Latrell Sprewell at the forwards; and Allan Houston and Charlie Ward at the guards. Rice apparently would come off the bench.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to imagine Rice being happy in that role because he complained about his lack of involvement in the Los Angeles offense during the Lakers' march to the championship last June.</p>
        <p>Rice, a three-time All-Star, has averaged 20.2 points a game over his 11-year career and is third on the all-time 3-point shooting list. Despite starting and averaging 15.9 points and earning his first N.B.A. title, Rice was unhappy as the club's third offensive option behind Shaquille O'Neal and Kobe Bryant.</p>
        <p>Rice's complaints, plus the fact that the Knicks hardly need another All-Star swingman to go with Latrell Sprewell and Allan Houston, have fueled speculation that they will make a second trade with the Atlanta Hawks involving one of their stars. The most prominent theory is that the Knicks will send Houston and perhaps Marcus Camby to the Hawks for Dikembe Mutombo. But one Eastern Conference official who spoke on condition of anonymity said yesterday he understood that the Knicks would trade Sprewell instead of Houston to Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Both the Knicks and the Hawks have denied that such a trade is in motion, and, in a statement, Coach Van Gundy said he looks forward to playing the three perimeter stars together.</p>
        <p>''Glen Rice has had a tremendous career and we are happy to have him,'' Van Gundy said. ''We look forward to Allan, Latrell and Glen forming a very dynamic perimeter.''</p>
        <p>The acrimony between Ewing and the Knicks reportedly began earlier this summer when the club refused to grant him a two-year contract extension. Layden said last month that the two parties had never discussed an extension and that Ewing and the Knicks would work together to find a trade that benefited both the player and the organization.</p>
        <p>Several people close to Ewing and the Knicks said that Ewing was uncomfortable as the third star behind Sprewell and Houston and that he had grown tired of being blamed for the Knicks' inability to win a championship.</p>
        <p>The gulf between Ewing and the news media and fans was never more apparent than last month, when it was first announced that he would be traded to Seattle in the foiled four-team, 13-player deal. After he was criticized heavily by the media and fans, it seemed nearly impossible for Ewing to return for this season.</p>
        <p>''Patrick Ewing will forever be a New York Knick in the minds of everyone associated with this franchise -- his contributions to this team have been unparalleled,'' Layden said.</p>
        <p>This trade is a spinoff of that earlier deal that also involved the Knicks, Sonics and Lakers and collapsed when the Detroit Pistons pulled out at the last moment. That trade, which was supposed to take place on Aug. 22, also would have sent Ewing to Seattle, but the Knicks would have received Seattle's Vin Baker and Rice in return.</p>
        <p>After that fell apart, the Knicks, along with Ewing and Falk, worked feverishly to put together another trade. After exploring a possible Ewing-for-Juwan Howard trade with the Washington Wizards, the Knicks rekindled talks with Seattle and Los Angeles two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>The discussions began with the Sonics and Lakers proposing a three-team deal in which the Knicks would receive Rice and Knight, Seattle would get Ewing and the Lakers would get Grant. The Knicks would not accept the deal as it was proposed, and immediately began searching for a fourth team that would enable them to secure a more established big man.</p>
        <p>Since Rice was a key part of the deal, any semblance of the first proposed trade seemed dead as recently as yesterday afternoon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
