<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Political Wallflower Has a Full Dance Card</title>
    <meta content="Y21BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GOVERNOR'S WIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED7133BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Political Wallflower Has a Full Dance Card</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>MEDIA, Pa., Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush's campaign, seeking to win over female voters polls say are leaning toward Vice Pres Al Gore, is counting on Laura Bush to carry political appeal of her own; she has begun taking center stage while campaigning at husband's side, introducing him and answering questions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Gov. George W. Bush and his wife, Laura, toured a Chicago classroom earlier this week, a sixth grader asked him how he would feel if he were running for election against his wife.</p>
        <p>''I'd come in second,'' he said. For even though Mr. Bush still likes to tell audiences how his wife, a former school librarian, married him years ago on the condition that she would never have to make a political speech, those days are long gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Gov. George W. Bush and his wife, Laura, toured a Chicago classroom earlier this week, a sixth grader asked him how he would feel if he were running for election against his wife.</p>
        <p>''I'd come in second,'' he said. For even though Mr. Bush still likes to tell audiences how his wife, a former school librarian, married him years ago on the condition that she would never have to make a political speech, those days are long gone.</p>
        <p>Now, with Mr. Bush in a drive to win back some of the female voters who polls say are leaning toward Vice President Al Gore, the governor's campaign is counting on Laura Bush to carry political appeal of her own. And all this week, she has been center stage at her husband's side, holding her own microphone and taking her own questions.</p>
        <p>In this era when candidates may be judged by how they smooch with their wives, she is the one who introduces the Republican presidential nominee at his town hall meetings. Her adjectives make clear that the campaign is a joint endeavor.</p>
        <p>''Our favorite events are these where we actually get to meet with people and talk to people about what their hopes are for our country,'' Mrs. Bush told an audience of loyal Republicans as the couple's campaign day began at around 8:30 a.m. in the Great Hall in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Bush portrays her as a reluctant convert to politics, Mrs. Bush has become a seasoned campaigner after all her years in the Bush clan. With her twin daughters now off to college, she said she planned to stay on the trail this fall.  ''I am very comfortable with campaigning,'' she said in an interview in the back of his campaign plane. ''I've been the first lady of the state for six years.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush suggested that reporters show a ''certain cynicism'' when they think that ''candidates and candidates' families are trying to act a certain way to appeal to voters.'' She said: ''People are more natural than that. George is more natural than that, and I am too.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's aides do not disguise their belief that she is a particular asset with swing voters, independents as well as women.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush can sound like a political pro as she recounts how her husband's television appearance with Oprah Winfrey allowed him to get around the ''press filter.'' And introducing her husband at the town hall meeting today, she stuck faithfully to the message of the day.</p>
        <p>''Today he's going to talk about taxes and the way that the marriage penalty affects married couples,'' she said. ''When a man and woman say 'I do' and they put their two incomes together, they get into a higher tax bracket.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush took over the microphone, he once again told the tale about promising that she would never have to make a speech. ''If all goes well, she'll make a fabulous first lady for the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He accused Mr. Gore of hypocrisy over his appearance at a Hollywood fund-raiser at which he muted his criticism of the entertainment industry. ''Seems like he must be auditioning for a Broadway play,'' Mr. Bush said. ''He keeps changing his tune.</p>
        <p>''At the beginning of the week, he sounded awfully tough on Hollywood. He talked about six months, sanctions. He talked a tough line. After a couple of fund-raisers, he's changed his tune. Go out there to Hollywood to collect some money, no longer is it six months and tough talk.''</p>
        <p>Most of the audience's questions played directly into Mr. Bush's campaign themes. The only query that stumped the governor came from a woman who asked him if he supported the Violence Against Women Act, but referred to it only by an acronym. ''What?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>She then gave the full name of the measure and told him its reauthorization was being held up by Congressional Republicans. Mr. Bush asked her to send him information on the legislation. Later his spokeswoman, Karen P. Hughes, said that he supported the reauthorization.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush is not always at her husband's side. Sometimes she peels off for her own events. On Thursday, when Mr. Bush campaigns in Cincinnati, she is to go to a school in Columbus. When he is in Tampa, Fla., on Friday, she will go to Orlando.</p>
        <p>At other moments Mrs. Bush leads the George Bush cheering section. When her husband bantered with Ms. Winfrey in Chicago this week, Mrs. Bush sat in a restaurant across the street watching the show on television with Lt. Gov. Corrine Wood, and a group of female supporters. A banner proclaimed ''W stands for women.''</p>
        <p>Reporters were invited in as the show came on and the crowd of women tapped their watches and chanted, ''It's time for us to win.'' When Ms. Winfrey said she had interviewed Mr. Gore, too, the group booed.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush says she is often asked who she more resembles -- Hillary Rodham Clinton or Barbara Bush. ''I say I am like myself,'' she said on the campaign plane. On the stump, she speaks of the importance of education or of how Americans for all their diversity have ''so much in common'' such as ''sacrifices we make for our loved ones.''</p>
        <p>Today, when a questioner wanted to know her favorite books, she used the moment to plug Texas authors, recommending ''Gates of the Alamo'' by Steve Harrigan, ''Goodbye to a River'' by John Graves and ''House on Mango Street'' by Sandra Cisneros.</p>
        <p>But Texas is not a swing state. So when she mused, ''Let's see who I can think of who isn't a Texas writer,'' her husband chimed in that perhaps she should find ''a Pennsylvania writer.''</p>
        <p>In His Own Words  GEORGE W. BUSH</p>
        <p>Remarks at a town hall meeting yesterday in Pittsburgh:</p>
        <p>''I noticed my opponent went out to Hollywood yesterday. It seems like he must be auditioning for a Broadway play because he keeps changing his tune.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the week he sounded awfully tough on Hollywood. He talked a tough line.  After a couple of fund-raisers he's changed his tune. Go out there to Hollywood, collect some money, and no longer is it tough talk.</p>
        <p>I've been saying all along we shouldn't censor. I don't think that's the American way, but I think we ought to remind our parents to be mindful of what our children are watching. . . .</p>
        <p>We need to call in these captains of the entertainment industry and explain to them loud and clear that our country needs to do a better job of raising our children.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GOVERNOR'S WIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
