<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Free Fall Grows, and It's Also Growing Serious</title>
    <meta content="21YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/sports/21YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DC103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Free Fall Grows, and It's Also Growing Serious</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toronto Blue Jays defeat New York Yankees, 7-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They plead guilty to their manager's charge of lethargy, but now that the Yankees consider themselves rehabilitated, they need a break to regain their place on the straight and narrow path that leads to the playoffs. Somebody needs to get a big hit, somebody needs to pitch a good game.</p>
        <p>But David Cone was not that somebody. The Toronto Blue Jays ripped the right-hander tonight and blew out the Yankees early in a 7-2 victory, the Yankees' sixth loss in seven games. They have been outscored by 57-18 during that span.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They plead guilty to their manager's charge of lethargy, but now that the Yankees consider themselves rehabilitated, they need a break to regain their place on the straight and narrow path that leads to the playoffs. Somebody needs to get a big hit, somebody needs to pitch a good game.</p>
        <p>But David Cone was not that somebody. The Toronto Blue Jays ripped the right-hander tonight and blew out the Yankees early in a 7-2 victory, the Yankees' sixth loss in seven games. They have been outscored by 57-18 during that span.</p>
        <p>The Yankees can still take solace in their solid lead of five and a half games over Toronto in the American League East, and gain a sense of calm from their vast wealth of experience. But they have at least compromised their playoff plans, and with a few more losses, they would begin courting complete disaster.</p>
        <p>Just a week ago, the Yankees were closing on the Chicago White Sox for the best record in the league, a distinction that merits home-field advantage throughout the playoffs. But the Yankees (85-65) are now four games behind the White Sox (89-61) and probably won't catch them, and Seattle (86-66) is only one game behind the Yankees in the loss column, one ahead in victories; if the Mariners pass the Yankees, then the Yankees would open the playoffs on the road. That might not necessarily shake their confidence, but in light of their recent malaise, it would be an incredible waste.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernandez dressed quickly after tonight's game and left the quiet clubhouse. He will start Thursday here against David Wells. Maybe it will be El Duque who will, to use the phrase of Manager Joe Torre, ''take the bull by the horns.''</p>
        <p>Torre called a meeting after Tuesday's 16-3 loss and chastised the players for their poor effort, and Derek Jeter and Andy Pettitte and others agreed completely with his assessment.</p>
        <p>They returned to the Skydome today appearing relaxed and as confident as always. A few of them sung along to the clubhouse stereo before tonight's game -- to the tune of the old TV show ''Good Times'' coincidentally -- while others gawked at the most recent shipment of maple bats. They laughed before their workout while Charlie Wonsowicz, their batting practice pitcher, uncannily imitated some of the players.</p>
        <p>Torre immediately sensed a different level of intensity when the game started, the players ''scratching and clawing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the Blue Jays quickly jumped all over Cone, who was totally ineffective, allowing six hits, two walks and seven runs before being knocked out two outs into the fourth inning. ''It wasn't very good,'' Cone said.</p>
        <p>He missed only one start after dislocating his nonthrowing shoulder Sept. 5, but Cone's stuff is not nearly as good as it was before the injury. The velocity on his fastball is down from 88-89 to 85-86 miles an hour, and the lack of zip makes it easier for opposing hitters to handle his offspeed stuff: Of the 67 pitches he threw tonight, the Blue Jays -- who have a lot of free-swingers in their lineup -- swung and missed only five times.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to rely on my off-speed stuff,'' said Cone, ''and it caught up to me.''</p>
        <p>Cone worked from the stretch constantly, having allowed the leadoff batter to reach base in three of the four innings he started. Shannon Stewart doubled to start the first and was hit by a pitch to open the third, and Cone walked Tony Batista to lead off the fourth, with the Yankees trailing, 3-1.</p>
        <p>After Darrin Fletcher singled to advance Batista to third base, Dwight Gooden began stretching in the bullpen, and the coach Tony Cloninger rose from his seat and stood by the bullpen phone, waiting for it to ring. It did after Mickey Morandini singled home Batista. Two batters later, Alex Gonzalez bounced a line drive over the wall in left-center field, and Cone was removed.</p>
        <p>As Cone fielded questions after the game, a radio reporter hit the wrong button on his recorder and Torre's voice resonated about some player: ''He's having a hell of a year.'' Cone, now 4-13, quickly cracked, ''It wasn't me.''</p>
        <p>Only Torre knows how he feels about having to pick between Cone and a handful of rookie pitchers for his playoff roster.</p>
        <p>Saddled with the huge deficit early, the Yankees' offense sputtered, failing to capitalize on a couple of chances to get back into the game against Esteban Loaiza (10-11).</p>
        <p>First baseman Tino Martinez is hitless in his last 21 at-bats, and his average is down to .258; he was ejected before the start of the ninth inning for arguing with the home plate umpire about his interpretation of the strike zone. Third baseman Scott Brosius does not have a run batted in over his last nine games. Center fielder Bernie Williams, nagged for the better part of a month by injury, has one homer since Aug. 11.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have slumped in September in each of the last three years, knowing they were headed for the playoffs. When spring training begins, their goal is winning the World Series, not the regular season.</p>
        <p>''When we go to spring training, we get ready for the season,'' said catcher Jorge Posada. ''But when the end of July comes, and in August, we're focused on going to the playoffs. When it gets to September, I think guys just want to get September over with and get the playoffs started. Most of the guys have aches and pains, and when the playoffs come, those things go away, because it's a different life.''</p>
        <p>''We've still got 13 days here to go,'' Posada continued. ''We've got to get everybody healthy and get everybody swinging. If the playoffs started today, we'd be ready. We know how to play there, and when it comes down to the playoffs, it's all about the team winning and I think we know how to do that.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>PAUL O'NEILL took batting practice on the field early Wednesday afternoon, and Manager JOE TORRE indicated that O'Neill (hip pointer) probably will be in the everyday lineup Friday, when the Yankees begin a four-game series against Detroit in Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
