<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Law Firm Charged In Aiding Smugglers Of Chinese to U.S.</title>
    <meta content="21SMUG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/nyregion/21SMUG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Mary Jo (US Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porges, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porges, Sheery Lu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peng, Rity Sulan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">He, Heidi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liu, June</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shan, Jin Wen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tse, Jeffrey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DB103BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Law Firm Charged In Aiding Smugglers Of Chinese to U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Atty Mary Jo White charges Robert E Porges's New York City immigration law firm worked hand in hand with smugglers who bring illegal immigrants from China and keep them as virtual indentured servants in United States until price of their passage is paid; calls firm racketeering enterprise and charges Porges, his wife, Sheery Lu Porges, and six current and former employees got $1.2 million in fees from unnamed smugglers over last seven years; says firm advised smugglers on best points of entry into US, arranged transportation to New York City and helped smugglers seize and hold immigrants hostage until they paid $40,000 to $50,000; Porges is freed and given two weeks to post bond; Mrs Porges, central figure in indictment, is ordered held until bond is posted; others charged are Rity Sulan Peng, Heidi He, June Liu, Jin Wen Shan and Jeffrey Tse; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors yesterday accused one of the city's busiest immigration law firms of working hand in hand with the smugglers who bring illegal immigrants from China and then keep them as virtual indentured servants in the United States until the price of their passage is repaid.</p>
        <p>In a 44-count indictment filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, the government described the Manhattan law firm of Robert E. Porges as a racketeering enterprise and accused Mr. Porges, his wife and six current and former employees of receiving $1.2 million in fees from unnamed smugglers over the last seven years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal prosecutors yesterday accused one of the city's busiest immigration law firms of working hand in hand with the smugglers who bring illegal immigrants from China and then keep them as virtual indentured servants in the United States until the price of their passage is repaid.</p>
        <p>In a 44-count indictment filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, the government described the Manhattan law firm of Robert E. Porges as a racketeering enterprise and accused Mr. Porges, his wife and six current and former employees of receiving $1.2 million in fees from unnamed smugglers over the last seven years.</p>
        <p>Mary Jo White, the United States attorney, said that in return for that money, the firm acted as an adviser to smugglers, even suggesting the best points of entry into the country to avoid detection and arranging transportation to New York City for immigrants who succeeded in sneaking into the country by land or sea.</p>
        <p>She also said some law firm employees, mainly under the direction of Mr. Porges's wife, Sheery Lu Porges, helped the smugglers seize the illegal immigrants upon arrival in the city and hold them as ''hostages'' until the $40,000 to $50,000 they promised to pay for their passage was paid.</p>
        <p>After a brief hearing yesterday after the grand jury indictment was unsealed, Mr. Porges, 62, was released and given two weeks to post a $2 million bond on behalf of himself and his wife. She was ordered to be held until the bond was posted.</p>
        <p>No pleas were entered at the hearing, and Mr. Porges did not speak to reporters. He appeared pale and shaken.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Kaiser, his lawyer, said, ''We're confident that after a speedy trial, Mr. Porges will be shown to have represented his clients honestly and ethically for over 40 years.''</p>
        <p>Although the law firm and some of its employees are accused of having direct contact with smugglers and of helping them ''abduct'' illegal immigrants, no one is named in the indictment as a smuggler. While there have been many cases around the country of lawyers being charged with defrauding immigrants and racketeering charges have been brought against lawyers involved in drug smuggling or organized crime, the charge that a law firm aided immigrant smugglers is highly unusual.</p>
        <p>Ms. White said that at least one person already charged and convicted of immigrant smuggling in the last few years in the Manhattan district was connected to the Porges firm.</p>
        <p>But she refused to provide specifics or explain the genesis of the case. She would not say whether any more people would be charged with actually smuggling, abducting or holding immigrants hostage in connection with the case.</p>
        <p>Many of the Chinese men and women who enter the United States illegally end up in New York sweatshops and restaurants, where they work long hours in sometimes dangerous conditions for years to pay back the smugglers -- often called ''snakeheads'' -- who brought them from their homeland.</p>
        <p>Failure to pay the snakehead or attempts to escape from a smuggler's control, according to social service groups and academics who work with Chinese immigrants, can bring retribution against family members back in China.</p>
        <p>The central figure in the indictment was Mrs. Porges, 47. Prosecutors called her the ''chief of staff'' of the operation and charged her with aiding snakeheads in the kidnapping of 17 Chinese immigrants since 1997.</p>
        <p>Her husband, however, who has represented Chinese immigrants in many of the country's most high-profile asylum cases, was not accused of participating in the seizure of immigrants who owed money to the smugglers.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Porges worked as much as possible from behind the scenes,'' Ms. White said. ''Porges's wife allegedly functioned as the enterprise's chief of staff and liaison to the Chinese community.''</p>
        <p>Others charged with membership in the racketeering operation are Rity Sulan Peng, 26, a paralegal; Heidi He, 34, office manager; June Liu, 37, a translator; Jin Wen Shan, 37, a member of the support staff; and a staff member identified only as Michael, whose last name was not known by the prosecutors.</p>
        <p>A separate indictment charging two former law firm employees with aiding in immigrant smuggling named Ms. Peng and Jeffrey Tse, 45.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porges, while charged with racketeering, is accused mainly of directing his staff to concoct stories of past persecution on behalf of clients who were seeking asylum to remain legally in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Porges firm, which employed about 40 lawyers and paralegal workers, has handled thousands of such cases over the years. Mr. Porges represented many of the Chinese who survived the Golden Venture shipwreck off the Rockaway peninsula in Queens in 1993 in their asylum applications, as well as some of those who were caught off New Jersey in 1998 after their smugglers' boat ran aground.</p>
        <p>He also represented several Chinese teenagers abducted from foster homes in Seattle in 1995 and held for ransom in connection with an unpaid debt to a snakehead.</p>
        <p>The grand jury indictment against the Porgeses, and a separate indictment charging two former employees of the firm with aiding illegal immigrants, followed a 30-month investigation led by the immigration service.</p>
        <p>The commissioner of the Immigration and Naturalization Service, Doris Meissner, described the indictment as a significant blow to what has become a multibillion-dollar business of smuggling illegal immigrants. The accused lawyers and legal assistants, she said, may be ''Manhattan attorneys in three-piece suits.''</p>
        <p>''But the people indicted today,'' she said, ''are just as ruthless and unscrupulous as the snakeheads with whom they collaborated for profit.''</p>
        <p>In addition to direct payments from unnamed smugglers, the Porges law firm was charged with receiving about $12 million since 1993 from about 6,000 asylum seekers whose applications, according to the indictment, contained false information.</p>
        <p>That number does not represent all the asylum cases the firm handled, officials from the immigration service said, and not all of the Porges cases are suspect.</p>
        <p>But the issue of how lawyers help and even coach an asylum-seeker, as Mr. Porges is accused of doing, to make a case is a difficult one.</p>
        <p>Most immigration lawyers, as well as many charitable and social service agencies, also handle large caseloads of asylum applications from Chinese immigrants and others.</p>
        <p>Some said that illegal immigrants are often prepared by the smugglers, even before they see a lawyer, to offer a false or too-pat story of persecution and that they do not know their rights.</p>
        <p>That makes them doubly vulnerable, said Jacqueline Baronian, chairwoman of the New York chapter of the American Immigration Lawyers Association, who added that she did not know Mr. Porges or the details of the charges against him.</p>
        <p>''One of the biggest problems with these people who abuse immigrants and take advantage,'' she said, ''is that unfortunately there are times when some of these aliens have very, very valid asylum claims. They are frightened, they don't know what to say, they may have been told to say one thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
