<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raw Rap and Film May Stir a Fuss, but Hist'ry Shows 'Twas Ever Thus</title>
    <meta content="21HEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/arts/21HEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D6123BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raw Rap and Film May Stir a Fuss, but Hist'ry Shows 'Twas Ever Thus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David E Rosenbaum article says today's debate over violence in the movies, television, music and video games mirrors pattern of adult dismay over youth culture that goes back for centuries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first English novels, by Henry Fielding and Samuel Richardson in the 18th century, were filled with debauchery, and the London establishment was convinced that this new form of literature was debasing the country's youth.</p>
        <p>In the 19th century cartoons and vivid drawings were in fashion in the popular press. Illustrations of Jack the Ripper's crimes were said by the high-minded in England to be contributing to crime. ''Imagine,'' intoned Punch magazine in 1888, ''the effect of gigantic pictures of violence and assassination by knife and pistol on the morbid imagination of an unbalanced mind.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first English novels, by Henry Fielding and Samuel Richardson in the 18th century, were filled with debauchery, and the London establishment was convinced that this new form of literature was debasing the country's youth.</p>
        <p>In the 19th century cartoons and vivid drawings were in fashion in the popular press. Illustrations of Jack the Ripper's crimes were said by the high-minded in England to be contributing to crime. ''Imagine,'' intoned Punch magazine in 1888, ''the effect of gigantic pictures of violence and assassination by knife and pistol on the morbid imagination of an unbalanced mind.''</p>
        <p>In the United States at the turn of the 20th century the first motion pictures were offered in peep shows at penny arcades. The arbiter of moral values and culture at the time was Anthony Comstock, organizer of the New York Society for the Suppression of Vice. Working with the postal authorities, he sent agents into arcades to arrest teenage boys looking at pictures of women in bloomers, pictures less risque than those on billboards and in newspaper ads today. By the time he died in 1915, Comstock was responsible for the destruction of 160 tons of literature and pictures.</p>
        <p>This pattern of adult dismay over youth culture is being repeated today in the debate here over violence in the movies, television, music and video games.</p>
        <p>''Every generation believes that the one coming up behind it is being corrupted by popular culture,'' said Francis G. Couvares, a social historian who is dean of freshmen at Amherst College.</p>
        <p>Todd Gitlin, a professor of culture, journalism and sociology at New York University and an authority on the 1960's, said that the phenomenon of adults' anxiety over their children's culture was deeply rooted in the human psyche, in the adults' denial that the culture of their own generation could become passe.</p>
        <p>''Every culture passes sooner or later, but we don't want to believe that what we like is just provisional,'' Mr. Gitlin said. ''This is in the human condition. I can't help but think it has always been so.''</p>
        <p>It was certainly true throughout the 20th century. Ragtime, vaudeville, jazz and burlesque. Movies about gangsters and fallen women. Dime novels and comic books. Elvis Presley and James Dean. Playboy and Penthouse. Janis Joplin and Jimi Hendrix.</p>
        <p>All of them caught on with young people and were deplored by their parents. And the politicians of the day often tried to restrain them in the name of preventing youth from going to hell in a handbasket.</p>
        <p>The Federal Trade Commission, in a report last week, carefully avoided the content of culture and limited itself to examining the marketing of entertainment rated for adults. The commission found that a vast majority of films, recordings and electronic games, including movies whose R rating specifies that children under 17 must be accompanied by a parent or adult guardian, were advertised to appeal to children. One studio even convened focus groups of 10- and 12-year-olds to test an R-rated film, the commission reported.</p>
        <p>At a Senate hearing on the topic the politicians denounced the content of the entertainment as well as the marketing.</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, the Democratic vice presidential nominee, declared that the shootings last year at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., indicated that ''the violence our children are being bombarded with by the media had become part of a toxic mix turning some of them into killers.''</p>
        <p>Lynne V. Cheney, whose husband, Dick, is the Republican candidate for vice president, said of the lyrics to one rap song: ''It is despicable. It is horrible. This is dreadful. This is shameful. This is awful.''</p>
        <p>Senator Ernest F. Hollings, Democrat of South Carolina, noted that this was the 21st hearing the Senate Commerce Committee had held since 1960 on violence and the media. Before 1960 other committees considered the matter. In today's light the topics of some of those examinations seem so tame as to be laughable.</p>
        <p>At a memorable moment in a 1954 hearing on whether comic books contributed to juvenile delinquency, Senator Estes Kefauver held up the cover of one comic book and said to its publisher, who was the witness: ''This seems to be a man with a bloody ax holding a woman's head up, which has been severed from her body. Do you think that is in good taste?''</p>
        <p>Yes, the publisher replied, explaining that it would be ''in bad taste if, for example, the severed head was held higher, and blood was shown dripping from it.''</p>
        <p>The latest television commercial for American International Group, the giant financial conglomerate, makes light of the notion in the 1950's that Elvis Presley was a corrupting influence on young people, and underscores just how much the limits of culture have changed.</p>
        <p>At one point in the commercial a heavy man with a Southern accent says, ''This town will not put up with the vulgar body movements of Elvis Presley.'' Then a woman in 1950's garb with two small children at her side yells out in disgust: ''I saw him gyrate his body and wiggle his hips! He should not be on television!''</p>
        <p>The commercial ends with a shot of Presley onstage before a huge audience, and the voice-over proclaims the conglomerate's slogan: ''The greatest risk is not taking one.''</p>
        <p>In modern America, political intervention at the national level never reached the point of censorship, but in some cases it had a considerable effect on the culture.</p>
        <p>In the 1930's politicians put so much pressure on movie studios that they adopted industry codes that led to the demise of movies glorifying gangsters, like those with James Cagney and Edward G. Robinson, and movies like those starring Jean Harlow in which the heroine was a so-called wanton woman.</p>
        <p>By current standards the moral outrage arising from photos of women in bloomers and comic books and gangster movies is hard to understand. In an interview, Mrs. Cheney, a former chairwoman of the National Endowment for the Humanities, said that looking back at Elvis, ''it all seems so innocent.''</p>
        <p>But she argued that matters were much worse today. She mentioned ''Kill You,'' a rap song by Eminem. Although he spends long stretches on his album ''Marshall Mathers LP'' telling listeners not to like him, not to act like him and not to expect him to act like the person in his songs, ''Kill You'' contains images of the rapper raping and killing his mother.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to imagine how it could be much worse,'' Mrs. Cheney said. ''We've reached some sort of outer limit here that I don't think other cultures have had to deal with.''</p>
        <p>Historians and sociologists -- all of whom of course are adults -- tend to agree with Mrs. Cheney that the depiction of violence in today's popular culture is worse than what has come before, though they disagree on whether it leads to violence or the extent to which it might.</p>
        <p>''I hate this stuff,'' said Mr. Gitlin of N.Y.U. ''It's disgusting.''</p>
        <p>Erich S. Goode, a sociologist who teaches criminology at the University of Maryland and who has written widely on what he calls ''moral panics'' of earlier years, said: ''There is a qualitative difference in the kinds of threats children face today, and I think culture is a big part of it. To parents today, the threat from the media seems to be something they can't stop. It's not like telling their kids not to take candy from a stranger.''</p>
        <p>David Nasaw, who teaches cultural history at the graduate center of the City University of New York, said, ''The more freedom to consume children and adolescents have, the more difficult it is for parents to regulate what they see and what they hear.''</p>
        <p>The question that needs to be asked, said James B. Gilbert, a social historian at the University of Maryland, is the extent to which each generation's culture exceeds the prevailing standards of the day.</p>
        <p>''The things you see today are unbelievably vulgar,'' he said. ''But are they more of a shock compared with the standards of the day than, say, rock 'n' roll in the 50's was compared with the standards of that day? I'm not sure.''</p>
        <p>''People accept the idea that times now are worse,'' he added. ''I think you have to be awfully cautious of that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
