<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Satellite Web Links Let Indian Tribes Take a Technological Jump</title>
    <meta content="21INDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/technology/21INDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hopi Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navajo Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Havasupai Tribe</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grand Canyon (Arizona)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starband Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sink, Mindy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Grand Canyon National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DA123BF932A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Satellite Web Links Let Indian Tribes Take a Technological Jump</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MINDY SINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sink, Mindy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>One hundred twenty locations on Navajo, Hopi and Havasupai reservations throughout Arizona, New Mexico and Utah are supplied with new satellite dishes and computer equipment for two-way, high-speed Internet service; one delivery is made by caravan of pack mules down eight miles of trails to the bottom of the Grand Canyon; three-year pilot project is first commercial venture for Starband Communications, which plans to begin selling two-way saatelite Internet service to the general public later in 2000 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE reach of the Internet has now made it to the floor of the Grand Canyon and several other remote places on American Indian reservations in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month 120 locations on Navajo, Hopi and Havasupai reservations throughout Arizona, New Mexico and Utah were supplied with new satellite dishes and computer equipment for two-way, high-speed Internet service. In one case that meant the state-of-the-art satellite dishes had to be carried down eight miles of trails to the bottom of the Grand Canyon by a caravan of pack mules to reach the Havasupai tribe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE reach of the Internet has now made it to the floor of the Grand Canyon and several other remote places on American Indian reservations in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month 120 locations on Navajo, Hopi and Havasupai reservations throughout Arizona, New Mexico and Utah were supplied with new satellite dishes and computer equipment for two-way, high-speed Internet service. In one case that meant the state-of-the-art satellite dishes had to be carried down eight miles of trails to the bottom of the Grand Canyon by a caravan of pack mules to reach the Havasupai tribe.</p>
        <p>''They are jumping generations of technology in a couple of hours and into the 21st century,'' said Ed Groenhout, vice president for strategic initiatives at Northern Arizona University in Flagstaff. ''They have gone from dial-up service that didn't work very well to this.''</p>
        <p>Starband Communications (formerly Gilat-to-Home Inc.) of McLean, Va., worked with Northern Arizona University and the Southwest Navajo Nation Virtual Alliance to create the connections.</p>
        <p>The three-year pilot project is the first commercial venture for Starband, which plans to begin selling two-way satellite Internet service to the general public later this year. The company made significant donations of hardware and subsidized the installations, and the tribes obtained additional money in the form of federal and other grants.</p>
        <p>The service offers download speeds of up to 500 kilobits per second, or about 10 times faster than a 56K modem, although Starband officials said that 300 to 400 kbps might be more realistic. Uploading would be at about 150 kbps.</p>
        <p>Each tribe and reservation had different needs and priorities for the Internet, depending on its geographical location. The police department at the First Mesa Consolidated Villages, on the Hopi reservation northeast of Phoenix, wanted to have access to the F.B.I.'s National Crime Information Center. Students at the Selba Delkai Boarding School near Winslow, Ariz., needed greater access; they had to rotate Internet use because there was only a single copper wire line for data.</p>
        <p>Dozens of the computers and satellite dishes were distributed to chapter houses -- meeting halls and community centers -- throughout the far-flung reservations, where simple telephone service is often still a luxury.</p>
        <p>The Havasupai Indians hope that some of their tribal members can get college degrees through online education courses and remain on the reservation to teach the next generation.</p>
        <p>''This is a turning point for our community,'' said Sally Tilousi, director of the Havasupais' Head Start School. ''It's hard for people on the outside to understand how isolated we are from so much technology.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tilousi said that phone service deep inside the canyon could be intermittent and that all calls were long-distance, making landline connections unaffordable.</p>
        <p>Starband officials note that the availability of Internet services has been spotty.</p>
        <p>''Satellite is ubiquitous, and they could not get D.S.L. or cable modems,'' said Sandy Colony, vice president for corporate communications at Starband Communications. ''In some of these cases, this was their first Internet connectivity. It allows more people access to all of the benefits of the Internet with high-speed delivery, long-distance learning, and it's always on.''</p>
        <p>Now the Havasupai court clerk can correspond regularly with the circuit judge who typically visits only once a month. Tourism is the primary source of income for the Havasupai, and they depend on the 20,000 or so tourists who hike, ride horseback or visit by helicopter. The lodge now has a computer and dish so current weather conditions can be made available and frequently asked questions can be handled through e-mail on the tribe's site.</p>
        <p>But for Ms. Tisouli, benefits for the 600-member tribe's children are the most important reason for the upgrades.</p>
        <p>''What has happened is we're sending children ill-prepared into the outside world,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The tribe's children are sent to boarding school after eighth grade.</p>
        <p>''They're not socially exposed,'' Ms. Tisouli said. ''We're hoping this might better prepare them academically and we'll be able to communicate with them when they do leave.''</p>
        <p>As for the idea of the modern world encroaching on a seemingly simpler culture, Ms. Tisouli said the new technology could only be beneficial.</p>
        <p>''It will only strengthen our community, helping us grow and learn with our children and our families,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
