<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Lanes Are Needed For Car Tests, Firm Says</title>
    <meta content="08EMIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parsons Infrastructure and Technology Group</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED71738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Lanes Are Needed For Car Tests, Firm Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parsons Infrastructure and Technology Group, company that runs New Jersey's troubled auto emissions inspection system, says program will require construction of additional inspection lanes, at a cost of millions of dollars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When New Jersey's troubled automobile inspection system completes its switch to a more stringent emissions test on Aug. 1, what should have been achieved last December will finally be realized, state officials say: a smoothly operating program that results in cleaner air.</p>
        <p>But despite widespread improvements in the system's performance since its disastrous debut last winter, the company that runs the system says that keeping it running smoothly will eventually require construction of additional inspection lanes, at a cost of millions of dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When New Jersey's troubled automobile inspection system completes its switch to a more stringent emissions test on Aug. 1, what should have been achieved last December will finally be realized, state officials say: a smoothly operating program that results in cleaner air.</p>
        <p>But despite widespread improvements in the system's performance since its disastrous debut last winter, the company that runs the system says that keeping it running smoothly will eventually require construction of additional inspection lanes, at a cost of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Carl Golden, a spokesman for the company, Parsons Infrastructure and Technology Group, said yesterday, ''At some point or other down the road, there's going to have to be some serious discussions of expanding the system.''</p>
        <p>The inspection program, intended to help the state meet its emissions reduction goals under the Federal Clean Air Act, has been a persistent headache for Gov. Christine Todd Whitman. Equipment failures and long delays in inspection lanes prompted the state to suspend the new tests in January, and an investigation revealed that some state officials had ignored warnings that the testing system would fail.</p>
        <p>But noting yesterday that the problems were practically all resolved, officials said they had no plans to build more inspection lanes. The average waiting time at the state's 32 inspection stations in June was down to just nine minutes, they said, compared with 26 minutes in January.</p>
        <p>Of the state's 129 testing lanes, all but 15 have begun using the new method, known as a dynamometer test. Ten of those 15 lanes, which will also go back to the stricter test on Aug. 1, are at 7 small inspection stations in densely populated areas of the state where the waits had been particularly long.</p>
        <p>Waiting times dropped to about the state average at those stations when they reverted to an old, faster emissions test, said Dana Sullivan, a spokesman for the Division of Motor Vehicles. So to keep the lines short when the new test returns next month, those stations will begin requiring drivers to make an appointment for the inspection. The seven stations are in Montclair, Ridgewood, Westfield, Washington Township in Warren County, Bridgeton, Cape May and Salem.</p>
        <p>The point is to spread out the tests, which because of drivers' work schedules and procrastination are now bunched during lunch hours and at the end of the month. Mr. Sullivan said that drivers would be encouraged to schedule their tests during off-peak hours.</p>
        <p>''We are not considering, at this time, adding more lanes,'' he said. ''We're going to have that appointment system in place and we're going to see how those seven stations handle the load. It would be irresponsible to spend millions of dollars adding lanes when we're not sure the current lanes are being used to capacity.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Golden, the Parsons company spokesman, said that population growth, particularly in areas with the smaller stations, would eventually make a lane increase unavoidable. The state inspection system was established in 1938, and while most of the testing sites have not changed since then, the population around them has grown at disparate rates. Those continuing differences in growth will mean a heavier demand for inspections at some stations, Mr. Golden said.</p>
        <p>Another reason the state will need more inspection lanes, he said, is the way it underestimated the number of private service stations that would elect to participate in the new system. Drivers can choose to have their vehicles inspected free at the state's centralized stations, or for a fee at a private station.</p>
        <p>When the state developed bid specifications for the inspection contract, which called for a total of 129 lanes, that number was based on an estimate that 2,400 owners of private stations would voluntarily invest $50,000 or so in the new equipment needed to perform the enhanced inspections, Mr. Goldman said. The actual number of participants, however, turned out to be about 1,400.</p>
        <p>Another reason inspection lines were so long when the new testing began in December, Mr. Golden said, is that only around 800 private service stations were certified to do inspections. More than 3,200 private inspection stations had participated in the old program.</p>
        <p>William Dressler, president of the New Jersey Gasoline Retailers Association, which represents the 1,400 service station owners, criticized the state's new appointment system as doomed to failure, because it essentially tries to dictate the schedules of drivers who may not have time for inspections at times other than their lunch hour.</p>
        <p>''I think that's pretty much going to be an exercise in futility,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
