<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Seeks to Retire As Charges Are Supported</title>
    <meta content="Y08GEN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Claudia (Lt Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Larry G (Maj Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E0DD1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Seeks to Retire As Charges Are Supported</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maj Gen Larry Smith requests early retirement after military investigators endorse sexual harassment charges brought against him by Lt Gen Claudia Kennedy; there are no plans to reduce his rank or retirement benefits through a Grade Determination Review Board; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two-star general accused of sexually harassing the Army's highest-ranking woman has requested early retirement after military investigators endorsed the charges against him, Pentagon officials said today.</p>
        <p>The accused officer, Maj. Gen. Larry G. Smith, has denied any wrongdoing, but he asked to step down after a letter of reprimand was entered into his personnel file, the officials said. He is to retire on Sept. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two-star general accused of sexually harassing the Army's highest-ranking woman has requested early retirement after military investigators endorsed the charges against him, Pentagon officials said today.</p>
        <p>The accused officer, Maj. Gen. Larry G. Smith, has denied any wrongdoing, but he asked to step down after a letter of reprimand was entered into his personnel file, the officials said. He is to retire on Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>The Army's inspector general determined that he harassed and assaulted Lt. Gen. Claudia Kennedy in her Pentagon office in 1996. But officials said there were no plans to reduce his rank or retirement benefits through a Grade Determination Review Board.</p>
        <p>General Kennedy, whose high-profile accusations were closely followed throughout the armed services and by advocates of women's rights, released a statement expressing satisfaction at the conclusion of a case she had reluctantly pursued.</p>
        <p>''I am satisfied with the Army's action in this case,'' she said. ''As far as I am concerned, this matter is closed.''</p>
        <p>In a statement released by the Army, General Smith said: ''I have always and continue to maintain that I did not commit these allegations and I am deeply disappointed with the decision to substantiate them. However, for the good of my family and the Army, we have elected to put it behind us and move on with our lives.''</p>
        <p>The action against General Smith, a 55-year-old veteran of three tours in Vietnam, ended the first instance of sexual harassment charges lodged by one Army general against another. The case embarrassed the Army, which has been roiled by a series of sex scandals and has sought to appeal to women by insisting it will not tolerate sexual harassment.</p>
        <p>In a heavily edited report that was released today under the Freedom of Information Act, the Army's inspector general, Lt. Gen. Michael Ackerman, concluded that General Kennedy, who is 52, told the truth about the encounter with General Smith even though only the two generals were present.</p>
        <p>At the time of the incident, the two were of equal rank, and they both said that they had met in General Kennedy's office and that the encounter ended with a hug, the report said.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, they ''were in total disagreement as to what happened when they were alone,'' it said.</p>
        <p>General Smith testified that he gave General Kennedy ''a hug and possibly a 'cheek kiss,' '' the report said, but he ''strongly denied any wrongdoing.'' Before her accusations, General Smith said he had considered General Kennedy a ''family friend,'' it said.</p>
        <p>But the inspector general concluded that General Smith's actions amounted to assault and battery and sexual harassment. The evidence did not support a more serious charge of indecent behavior to gratify sexual desires, the investigation found.</p>
        <p>''By holding her and kissing her against her will,'' the report said,  General Smith displayed conduct that ''was unbecoming of an officer and a gentleman.''</p>
        <p>The inspector general largely based his conclusions on the strength of General Kennedy's testimony and the belief that she had more to lose than gain by making her charges public.</p>
        <p>General Kennedy filed charges against General Smith only last year, three years after the incident. She pressed the case after General Smith was named to become the Army's deputy inspector general, a post that would have given him responsibility for investigating charges of sexual harassment, among other types of misconduct.</p>
        <p>''Evaluating the allegations came down to a question of credibility,'' the report said. ''There appeared to be no motive for'' General Kennedy ''to jeopardize her career and reputation by making false allegations against'' General Smith.</p>
        <p>''They were not in competition for assignments,'' the report said. ''She did not arrange the office call. There was no apparent incentive for her to ruin his unblemished career and destroy their friendship with false allegations.''</p>
        <p>The inspector general concluded: ''When one weighed all the testimony and considered all the evidence, coupled with the lack of motive to lie, the preponderance or greater weight of the evidence was sufficient to substantiate'' General Kennedy's allegations against General Smith.</p>
        <p>Eugene R. Fidell, president of the National Institute of Military Justice, said there was nothing unusual about the inspector general's approach to the sort of dispute frequently dismissed as ''he said, she said.''</p>
        <p>''They found her a credible witness based on her demeanor,'' Mr. Fidell said. ''They decided she's telling the truth and one of the factors that decided it is she doesn't have a motive to lie.''</p>
        <p>General Smith asserted that he had been treated unfairly. He provided 52 character witnesses in his defense. The inspector general's office interviewed seven of those references and six others before determining that there were no other known reports of prior misconduct by General Smith, whom it called ''a highly respected officer.''</p>
        <p>General Kennedy did not formally pursue the case against General Smith until last year, the inspector general said, but she referred to the incident in 1997, five months after it occurred.</p>
        <p>Without providing details, the report noted: ''The complainant, in an open forum, cited it as an example of how she had been sexually harassed'' by General Smith.</p>
        <p>The report said she eventually decided to report the incident ''out of loyalty to the Army.''</p>
        <p>In a ceremony in May honoring her 31 years of military service, General Kennedy, who is scheduled to retire next month, urged women in uniform to report incidents of harassment or ''misconduct will continue to harm us.''</p>
        <p>Speaking at the memorial to Women in Military Service to America at Arlington National Cemetery, she exhorted the crowd of 100 well-wishers to heed the advice of French novelist Emile Zola to ''live out loud.''</p>
        <p>''Living out loud begins by telling a friend and then later by telling people in authority who care,'' General Kennedy said. ''Our army is filled with women and men who care and are in a position to change and improve the conditions in which we serve.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
