<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hill Plans to Join Orlando</title>
    <meta content="Y08AT.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2DA1738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hill Plans to Join Orlando</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grant Hill will announce intentions to sign six-year, $67.5 million contract with Orlando Magic (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grant Hill may have been flattered by the parade of teams that flew to Detroit this week to attempt a courtship, but he was not swayed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grant Hill may have been flattered by the parade of teams that flew to Detroit this week to attempt a courtship, but he was not swayed.</p>
        <p>Next week Hill will announce his intentions to sign a six-year, $67.5 million contract with the Orlando Magic, said Joe Dumars, the Pistons' president.</p>
        <p>Dumars, a former teammate of Hill's, received the news in a telephone conversation with Hill on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>''He said he would be announcing sometime Monday or Tuesday his intentions to head south to Orlando,'' Dumars told reporters in the Detroit area yesterday. ''He reiterated to me that it was an opportunity he could not pass up, and I told him I understood. We're going to wish him well. It's not going to be an antagonistic parting. Only when we're playing the Orlando Magic will we try to be true opponents.''</p>
        <p>Hill's decision was no surprise as he acknowledged that he was ''leaning strongly'' toward joining the Magic after visiting Orlando last weekend. Still, his choice left many disappointed suitors. The Knicks, the Nets, Miami, San Antonio and chicago visited the forward on Wednesday and Thursday and tried to sell him on their teams.</p>
        <p>Hill, who averaged 21.6 points, 7.9 rebounds and 6.3 assists in six seasons with the Pistons, is the first secured piece of what could become a monumental makeover for the Magic. San Antonio power forward Tim Duncan, who visited Orlando with Hill last weekend, is deciding between the Spurs and the Magic, and Toronto's Tracy McGrady has often said that Orlando is hip top choice.</p>
        <p>Many executives around the league believe Hill's decision is a percurosr to Duncan's, but Gregg Popovich, the Spurs' coach and general manager, insisted yesterday that Duncan had not made up his mind and that he and Hill were not necessarily a package deal.</p>
        <p>''He is a separate individual from Grant Hill,'' Popovich said. ''Whatever Tim decides to do, it'll be because he thinks it's best for him. It has absolutely nothing to do wit Grant Hill or any other free agent.''</p>
        <p>CHRIS BROUSSARD</p>
        <p>PLUS: PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
