<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y08CAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2D91738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE POLLS</p>
        <p>NEW EVIDENCE OF NADER'S IMPACT  When Michigan voters consider a three-way presidential race among George W. Bush, Al Gore and Patrick J. Buchanan, the expected Reform Party nominee, Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are statistically tied, with Mr. Buchanan coming in a very distant third, a new poll indicates. But when the name of Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, is added, Mr. Gore slips well behind Mr. Bush, trailed by Mr. Nader and then Mr. Buchanan. Mr. Nader appears to draw some labor support at Mr. Gore's expense because of differences over trade issues. In a statewide telephone poll conducted for The Detroit Free Press by the research group EPIC/MRA, a research group in Lansing, Mr. Bush drew the support of 45 percent of likely voters, Mr. Gore 40 percent and Mr. Buchanan 4 percent. When Mr. Nader was added, Mr. Bush was the choice of 46 percent of the voters, Mr. Gore 34 percent, Mr. Nader 8 percent and Mr. Buchanan 3 percent. The poll has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>Janet Elder (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE POLLS</p>
        <p>NEW EVIDENCE OF NADER'S IMPACT  When Michigan voters consider a three-way presidential race among George W. Bush, Al Gore and Patrick J. Buchanan, the expected Reform Party nominee, Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are statistically tied, with Mr. Buchanan coming in a very distant third, a new poll indicates. But when the name of Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, is added, Mr. Gore slips well behind Mr. Bush, trailed by Mr. Nader and then Mr. Buchanan. Mr. Nader appears to draw some labor support at Mr. Gore's expense because of differences over trade issues. In a statewide telephone poll conducted for The Detroit Free Press by the research group EPIC/MRA, a research group in Lansing, Mr. Bush drew the support of 45 percent of likely voters, Mr. Gore 40 percent and Mr. Buchanan 4 percent. When Mr. Nader was added, Mr. Bush was the choice of 46 percent of the voters, Mr. Gore 34 percent, Mr. Nader 8 percent and Mr. Buchanan 3 percent. The poll has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>Janet Elder (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE CONVENTIONS</p>
        <p>WORK DISPUTE IN PHILADELPHIA  The mayor of Philadelphia has agreed to try to resolve an intensifying dispute between local unions and the network news divisions that is threatening to disrupt preparations for the Republican National Convention, several people with knowledge of the negotiations said. The fight, they said, has to do with whether the locals have jurisdiction in network work spaces at the First Union Center, where the convention will be held. Network officials, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said they had their own employees to do wiring and installation and thus had no need for local workers. Barbara Grant, a spokeswoman for Mayor John F. Street, said, ''The mayor was approached to try to step in and sort things out.'' Tim Fitzpatrick, a convention spokesman, said work had not been delayed so far.</p>
        <p>Peter Marks (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>A CAMPAIGN SPENDING LIMIT  The California Legislature, worried that special-interest contributions to campaigns for state offices have gotten out of hand, has passed a bill intended to limit them. Should Gov. Gray Davis sign the bill, as he has indicated he probably will, the proposal will be put before California voters in November. Under the measure, individuals could give no more than $20,000 to a candidate for governor, though political parties could still contribute unlimited amounts. Other statewide candidates could get up to $5,000 per election from most sources, including individuals and businesses, and $10,000 from ''small-contributor committees'' -- groups of at least 100 people who each chip in no more than $200 a year and donate to at least five candidates. For legislative candidates, the limits would be $3,000 from most sources and $6,000 from small-contributor committees.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>GORE'S TENANTS MOVING ON  The family renting a Tennessee home from Vice President Al Gore is moving to Ohio -- with the help of seven volunteer movers and officials from the Tennessee Republican Party. The moving team arrived yesterday at the home in Carthage to load two trucks with the household goods of Charles and Tracy Mayberry and their four children. Mrs. Mayberry called Mr. Gore a ''slumlord'' last month, saying she wanted to get his attention so much-needed repairs would be made. Mr. Gore promised to get the repairs done, but Mrs. Mayberry contends that nothing has happened. A Gore spokesman, Douglas Hattaway, said that all the repairs requested had in fact been made.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
