<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Valentine Has the Better New York Team and It's Time to Show It</title>
    <meta content="08BASE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDB1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Valentine Has the Better New York Team and It's Time to Show It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Curry On Baseball column discusses day-night doubleheader between New York Mets and New York Yankees; holds both teams are in position to reach postseason; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He buzzed through the Mets' dugout. He stood behind the batting cage. He skipped up and down the steps of the box seats. He talked to stadium employees. It was four hours before last night's game with the Yankees and Bobby Valentine looked as if he were playing host to a barbecue as he hustled around Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Valentine wanted to make sure everything was right, including jumping into the box seats to find out where his mother would be sitting. For a few minutes, the manager was like every other person who had a precious ticket and wondered how good his family's seats were for this New York, New York affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He buzzed through the Mets' dugout. He stood behind the batting cage. He skipped up and down the steps of the box seats. He talked to stadium employees. It was four hours before last night's game with the Yankees and Bobby Valentine looked as if he were playing host to a barbecue as he hustled around Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Valentine wanted to make sure everything was right, including jumping into the box seats to find out where his mother would be sitting. For a few minutes, the manager was like every other person who had a precious ticket and wondered how good his family's seats were for this New York, New York affair.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to make more of this,'' said Valentine. ''This is big. This is exciting.''</p>
        <p>There were already dozens of police officers ringing the parking lot, even though John Rocker was in Boston, not in Flushing. There were eight satellite trucks outside Shea, six or seven more than usual. And there was one manager wearing blue shorts and a black T-shirt who pranced around before the grounds crew even had the field ready for batting practice.</p>
        <p>''For a lot of people who live in this area,'' Valentine repeated, ''it's very big.''</p>
        <p>This series is big for the Mets and the Yankees, too, not just for their fans. Both teams are still in position to reach the postseason, but they have already teetered so much that the doubts have escalated. Can the Mets surpass the Braves or secure the wild card? Can the Yankees right themselves and salvage a disappointing season? Everyone awaits the answers, doubting that 2000 can match a memorable 1999 for intensity.</p>
        <p>For one night, it did. Orlando Hernandez helped the Yankees stand tall as he silenced the Mets over eight innings in a tidy 2-1 victory. Hernandez deftly speared Benny Agbayani's liner in the fifth inning to start a crucial double play and he was saved when Paul O'Neill robbed Derek Bell of a potential game-tying two-run homer in the eighth. Bell stood at first base with a look of disbelief, Hernandez pumped his fist, Valentine cringed. Once again, the Mets were staring up at the Yankees in amazement, yearning to be one step, one run ahead of them.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a great game,'' said Valentine. ''Our at-bats were good, our pitching was good, our defense was good. They scored a run more than us.''</p>
        <p>Today, Valentine's Mets are better than Joe Torre's Yankees, on the field, in the standings, and, unless El Duque, Roger Clemens and a sagging rotation can provide a boost, perhaps in the future, too. But Valentine knows the Mets must show that this weekend and for many more weekends.</p>
        <p>Valentine doubted if the Mets have been in first place for more than one week since interleague play began in 1997, and the Yankees have won three of the last four World Series titles while flicking the Mets aside like a mosquito in nine of 15 subway series games. Even as the Yankees have looked more human and more dysfunctional, they are back in first by one-half game.</p>
        <p>''We have to do a lot more before we're better than the Yankees,'' said Valentine.</p>
        <p>The Mets are a proud team that came within two victories of playing the Yankees in the World Series last season, but they sounded lame as they lamented the bloops that fell for the Yankees and the liners that found Yankee gloves. Al Leiter thought he struck out Derek Jeter on a check swing in the first, but Jeter wound up getting a single that started a two-run rally. The more the Mets talked about this loss, the tighter the Yankees' grasp got around their neck.</p>
        <p>''We aren't trying to prove anything to anyone, the Yankees or the Braves,'' said Leiter, something he admitted he was trying to do in 1999.</p>
        <p>Valentine claimed that these four games would not have a permanent impact on the Mets and that having a better record or higher status than the slumping Yankees does not influence anyone in uniform. Sure, Bobby. Still, as someone who spends a lot of time touring the city -- Valentine was shrewd enough to talk his way out of a ticket after he failed to wear a helmet while riding his bicycle there on Thursday -- he senses there are more Met fans in town.</p>
        <p>''It's just easier to be a Met fan when the Yankee fan isn't telling them to be quiet and sit down,'' said Valentine. Does that mean there are fewer Yankee fans? Valentine said, ''Yeah, I think, a little.'' That was before Hernandez's show, before O'Neill's catch, before the Yankees foiled the Mets again.</p>
        <p>Valentine knows the Mets will be fatigued after losing and then playing a day-night doubleheader at Shea and Yankee Stadiums today. But Valentine said the only other option would have been to schedule the makeup game at the end of the regular season if it mattered. Imagine if the Mets had the chance to spoil the Yankees' season or vice versa?</p>
        <p>''How fun would that be?'' said Valentine, a little sarcasm in his voice. Valentine would relish it unless there was another result like last night, another night where the Yankees prevailed.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
