<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doesn't She Look Familiar? Why, It's Sandra Feldman</title>
    <meta content="Y08LIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Sandra Feldman</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Teachers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feldman, Sandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA1738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doesn't She Look Familiar? Why, It's Sandra Feldman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Sandra Feldman, the brash, blunt president of American Federation of Teachers, who has just gone blond; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESPLENDENT in her brand-new heathery indigo pantsuit, adrenaline still pumping from her keynote address an hour before, Sandra Feldman, the president of the American Federation of Teachers, strode through the gleaming convention center, surrounded by her members, her teachers, her people. They stopped her for snapshots. They called out congratulations. They waved, and she smiled that outsized Sandy Feldman smile.</p>
        <p>''I've taken a poll, and we all agree,'' Nat LaCour, the federation's No. 2, whispered as he walked up. ''Blond is beautiful.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESPLENDENT in her brand-new heathery indigo pantsuit, adrenaline still pumping from her keynote address an hour before, Sandra Feldman, the president of the American Federation of Teachers, strode through the gleaming convention center, surrounded by her members, her teachers, her people. They stopped her for snapshots. They called out congratulations. They waved, and she smiled that outsized Sandy Feldman smile.</p>
        <p>''I've taken a poll, and we all agree,'' Nat LaCour, the federation's No. 2, whispered as he walked up. ''Blond is beautiful.''</p>
        <p>Yup, Sandy Feldman has dyed her hair blond. Brash, blunt, Brooklyn-Jewish Sandy Feldman, whose saucy voice and straightforward manner -- perhaps whose very soul -- practically ooze brunette, has gone blond.</p>
        <p>She tried to minimize it, brushing off questions about her salon by suggesting that a male leader would never be asked such things. She called it ''highlights,'' though the entire top layer of her shoulder-length bob has been colored. Then later, loosening up a little, she admitted that when she first saw her lightened locks in the mirror, she almost redyed them brown.</p>
        <p>Maybe Ms. Feldman is right, and it is a superficial -- even sexist -- detail hardly worth mentioning. Or maybe making such a bold change two weeks before your organization's biennial convention -- your big chance to bond with your members and shine in the media spotlight -- maybe that suggests a comfort and confidence level that means something.</p>
        <p>''I just thought I'd try it,'' she said with a shrug over a hotel breakfast of poached eggs, whole wheat toast and coffee with ''as much caffeine as you have.''</p>
        <p>''It was summertime,'' she said. ''It was a lark. I might not keep it.''</p>
        <p>It has been more than three years since the legendary Al Shanker died and Ms. Feldman, his protegee, replaced him at the federation's  helm. The smaller but scrappier of the two national teachers' unions, the A.F.T. has swelled under Ms. Feldman's leadership by more than 100,000 members, to top one million, over the last two years. And there has rarely been a moment when education, particularly the question of teacher quality, has been higher on the national political agenda.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feldman is seizing the opportunity to talk about increasing her members' salaries and professionalizing their jobs, but also about educating the poorest and hardest to teach of America's children. If there is one thing that best defines her leadership, it is the obvious nature of her passionate commitment to the children. ''We are at a moment when the kids who have really been left out can really get help,'' she said. ''I want to fix those schools. I know those schools are not what they should be. If we don't prevail, I'm afraid they're going to be abandoned.</p>
        <p>''This is who I am,'' she added. ''I'm a poor kid from Coney Island. I couldn't have had a life of any success if I didn't have education.''</p>
        <p>FAMILIAR to those who have been watching since she became president of the United Federation of Teachers, the A.F.T.'s New York local, in 1986, Ms. Feldman's  story is an education fairy tale.</p>
        <p>The daughter of a milkman and a sickly woman who sometimes worked in a bakery, Ms. Feldman grew up in a dirty tenement and then a public housing project. Her second-grade teacher at P.S. 188 gave her books like ''A Child's Garden of Verses,'' which she devoured, often while at home in bed with asthma. She won a creative writing award at James Madison High School, studied English at Brooklyn College and, while pursuing a master's degree in literature at New York University, taught first and fourth grades at P.S. 34 in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Feldman went to join the union at her school, there wasn't one. So she built it.</p>
        <p>''I'm a believer,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Married after her first year of college and divorced 17 years later, Ms. Feldman never had children of her own but has spent her life surrounded by them, doting on her nieces and nephews and visiting schools three times a week during the three decades she worked for the New York union. Now married to Arthur Barnes, a businessman, she exults in his 6-year-old grandson, who just finished first grade at a Brooklyn public school.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feldman, 60, lives primarily at her home near Gramercy Park, commuting to union headquarters in Washington. When she is not traveling to assist local leaders with negotiations or connect with teachers' unions abroad, she and Mr. Barnes, 70, go salsa dancing and frequent jazz clubs.</p>
        <p>As president of the New York local, Ms. Feldman emptied schools of time clocks, successfully sued the district over decrepit conditions and helped pick chancellors -- even mayors. Since becoming national president, she has called for shutting down failing schools, tough tests for entry into the teaching profession and, this week, an optional fifth year of high school for students lacking basic skills.</p>
        <p>Though it makes some in the rank and file bristle, she supports the wave of new standardized tests that have come along with higher academic expectations over the last decade, and is open to suggestions about compensating teachers in part on the basis of performance. It is a funny balance, running a trade union of college-educated professionals.</p>
        <p>The enemy, she says, is the growing legion of entrepreneurs eyeing the $3 billion educational industrial complex, and the Republicans who want to give parents public money for private-school tuition. ''If they get power and dismantle the public schools -- or, over a period of time, decide that we won't educate all our kids -- then we will be a different country,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Look at me, I've got this in my gut,'' she added, reflecting on the day her second-grade teacher first handed her a book. ''Look at me. If that school wasn't there, I wouldn't be here.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
