<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Episcopalians Near Alliance With Biggest Lutheran Group</title>
    <meta content="Y08EPI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lutheran Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Episcopal Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lutheran Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D81738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Episcopalians Near Alliance With Biggest Lutheran Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Episcopal House of Bishops votes to enact agreement to create formal alliance with Evangelical Lutheran Church in America in which the two churches would recognize each other's traditions and share resources; Episcopal House of Deputies is also set to approve agreement, known as 'Called to Common Mission'; delegates to policy-making body of the Lutheran denomination approved accord in 1999; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Episcopal Church and the nation's largest Lutheran denomination moved closer today to creating a formal alliance in which they would recognize each other's traditions and share resources.</p>
        <p>Overwhelming approval of an accord known as ''Called to Common Mission'' by the Episcopal House of Bishops at the church's annual convention here left only a vote by the church's other chamber, the House of Deputies, to enact the agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Episcopal Church and the nation's largest Lutheran denomination moved closer today to creating a formal alliance in which they would recognize each other's traditions and share resources.</p>
        <p>Overwhelming approval of an accord known as ''Called to Common Mission'' by the Episcopal House of Bishops at the church's annual convention here left only a vote by the church's other chamber, the House of Deputies, to enact the agreement.</p>
        <p>The 800 deputies, who are lay people and clergy, were expected to approve the accord in a vote scheduled to be held no later than Saturday.</p>
        <p>Delegates to the policy-making body of the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, the nation's largest Lutheran denomination with 5.2 million members, approved the accord last year.</p>
        <p>Leaders of both churches said today that final passage would reflect a historic accomplishment, ending 30 years of conversations between the two churches, which have similar theological positions and liturgies but significant differences about the role and authority of bishops. In the Episcopal Church, bishops are regarded as progeny of Christ's disciples and are elected for life. Lutheran bishops serve six-year terms, largely as administrators, before returning to their roles as pastors.</p>
        <p>The alliance is an indicator that the ecumenical movement may have regained momentum after several decades in which it was declared all but dead. The Lutheran church voted in 1997 for full communion with three churches in Protestantism's Reformed tradition: the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.), the United Church of Christ and the Reformed Church in America. Other longtime efforts are under way to unite Christian churches, with supporters citing the prayer of Jesus in the Gospel of John 17:11 that all his followers ''may be one.''</p>
        <p>Concerning the alliance with the Episcopal Church, ''it has been a long process, and I'm delighted,'' Lowell Almen, the secretary of the Lutheran group and a guest at the Episcopal convention, said after the 204 bishops voted, with only a dozen or so dissenting. ''God is doing a new thing in the life of the church. This represents a moment in church history that is very significant.''</p>
        <p>Chris Epting, the Episcopal Bishop of Iowa who played a major role in writing the accord, called it ''an ecumenical breakthrough'' that could help encourage similar agreements between his church and other denominations. Already, he said, the Episcopal Church had begun conversations with the Moravian Church in America, a Protestant denomination, and the Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>The vote by the deputies would align two churches that represent nearly eight million congregants and would end years of bumpy negotiations in efforts to bring the two denominations closer. After an initial proposal was written by members of both churches in 1990, it came up for its first votes of approval in 1997. The Episcopal Church passed it overwhelmingly, but the Lutherans failed by six votes to reach the majority needed for passage.</p>
        <p>A committee with representatives from both churches wrote a compromise document; that proposal was approved today.</p>
        <p>In effect, the accord, though it does not combine the two churches, allows each to recognize and embrace the other to the extent they can share ministers, places of worship and other resources. In addition to the symbolic significance, church leaders said, the arrangement would benefit urban and rural regions where one church is hard-pressed to serve all its members because of inadequate buildings or lack of personnel. Churches in such areas, for example, could share one pastor.</p>
        <p>Church leaders said the accord would also encourage local churches to work together on projects they would perform separately, like relief and missionary efforts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
