<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wild Card in Police Oversight Talks</title>
    <meta content="08POLI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DB1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wild Card in Police Oversight Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News Analysis: New York City, facing potential federal lawsuit charging police brutality and systematic violations of civil rights, is in negotiations with Justice Department, and appears close to agreeing on basic policy reforms and the appointment of an ouside auditor to measure compliance; but city appears to be balking at entering into a consent decree, which would make any disputes over compliance subject to review, and sanctions, by federal judge; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police departments vary greatly in size and in the issues they face. The communities they serve are just as diverse: the small city of Steubenville, Ohio, the large city of Pittsburgh and the entire state of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But in each of these places, the federal government has found that the police force engaged in systemic violations of civil rights. And each local government, to avoid a federal lawsuit, agreed to accept federal oversight to ensure that changes would be instituted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The police departments vary greatly in size and in the issues they face. The communities they serve are just as diverse: the small city of Steubenville, Ohio, the large city of Pittsburgh and the entire state of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But in each of these places, the federal government has found that the police force engaged in systemic violations of civil rights. And each local government, to avoid a federal lawsuit, agreed to accept federal oversight to ensure that changes would be instituted.</p>
        <p>New York City, which is now facing a similar lawsuit, has said it will consider accepting some form of federal oversight as well, and the looming question is whether the city will accept the established model of monitoring or forge some new method.</p>
        <p>Already there are indications that the breach between what the city and the Justice Department will accept  is so large that it may undermine any success in reaching an agreement that would forestall the suit.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors in Brooklyn have said for months that they are prepared to sue the city to force changes in what they characterize as the ineffective way the Police Department investigates and disciplines officers accused of brutality. Their findings, which the city disputes, were based on a two-year inquiry begun after the August 1997 torture of Abner Louima in a Brooklyn station house.</p>
        <p>In negotiations in other places, the federal government has insisted on largely similar types of oversight.</p>
        <p>In each, the parties signed an agreement that detailed the basic reforms and standards that were needed, like new training regimens. In each, they agreed to the appointment of an outside auditor who would measure the police force's compliance. And in each, the written agreement was filed in federal court as a consent decree so that any disputes over compliance would be subject to the review of a federal judge, who could levy sanctions.</p>
        <p>Based on interviews with people who have been involved in or briefed on the negotiations in New York, it appears that the city and the federal government are close to agreeing on some policy changes needed and on the appointment of an outside auditor. But the city appears to be balking at entering into a consent decree.</p>
        <p>City lawyers have said they are, in general, reluctant to enter into consent decrees because such decrees transfer power over city agency matters to a federal judge who may be less versed in the operations of the agency and the needs of the city.</p>
        <p>But one federal official involved in the negotiations said it was difficult to envision any settlement that would not involve the parties signing a consent decree, or some legal agreement like it. ''It comes down to the fact that there has to be enforceability that respects the agreement between the parties,'' the official said, ''that permits the aggrieved party to go in and get compliance.''</p>
        <p>Although they are negotiating possible reforms, New York officials have consistently said the police force is a model of restraint and does an effective job of disciplining officers who use excessive force.</p>
        <p>Settlements in other places were tailored to address particular problems. For example, the Steubenville agreement called for the city to set up a system to allow residents to file complaints against officers, a procedure already in place in New York.</p>
        <p>But all three settlements call for the appointment of an outside auditor, whose selection is ratified by a federal judge. The auditors are paid by the local governments, and they prepare reports that measure police compliance with the consent decrees.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh, for example, is paying Public Management Resources, a Texas consulting firm, $400,000 to serve as the auditor for five years. The auditors measure the city's compliance with 70 provisions in a 40-page consent decree, including its progress in putting in place a computer system to track officer histories for evidence of excessive force or racial prejudice.</p>
        <p>Each settlement calls for the auditors' reports to be forwarded to the Justice Department. If prosecutors believe that there is evidence of noncompliance, they can bring an action in federal court to have the local government held in contempt.</p>
        <p>The length of oversight varies, depending upon the agreement. Pittsburgh signed its consent decree in 1997, and its oversight will last at least five years. It can be lifted if a judge finds that the Police Department has been in substantial compliance with the consent decree for at least two years.</p>
        <p>If New York were to refuse to sign a consent decree, both parties could still sign a simple contract that would not require court approval. But if the city failed to keep the agreement, the federal government's recourse would be to sue for breach of contract, experts said, instead of bringing a contempt motion in federal court.</p>
        <p>Witold J. Walczak, executive director of the American Civil Liberties Union chapter in Pittsburgh, said the settlement there needed to be a consent decree. ''Everybody realizes,'' he said, ''that without the threat of an enforcement action by a federal judge, none of the reforms would have taken place.''</p>
        <p>Gary DuFour, the city manager in Steubenville, said a settlement in New York would have to be considerably different from the one that covers his city of 22,000 on the West Virginia border. ''You have almost twice as many officers as we have citizens,'' he said. ''Some of the issues are going to be very different.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
