<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="08DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DF1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China Backs Linux System  Over Microsoft's Windows Chinese leaders are concerned that the country is growing overly dependent on Microsoft's Windows operating system, which controls computers running everything from banks to President Jiang Zemin's e-mail box.</p>
        <p>But the Chinese government, itself a master at monopoly, is taking its case against Microsoft not to the courtroom but to the marketplace, albeit with a bit of administrative fiat. It is backing the Linux operating system, which was created by a Finnish university student in 1991 and is distributed free to anyone who wants it. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China Backs Linux System  Over Microsoft's Windows Chinese leaders are concerned that the country is growing overly dependent on Microsoft's Windows operating system, which controls computers running everything from banks to President Jiang Zemin's e-mail box.</p>
        <p>But the Chinese government, itself a master at monopoly, is taking its case against Microsoft not to the courtroom but to the marketplace, albeit with a bit of administrative fiat. It is backing the Linux operating system, which was created by a Finnish university student in 1991 and is distributed free to anyone who wants it. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>F.T.C. Set to Challenge Heinz Deal  H. J. Heinz's proposed $185 million purchase of the closely held Milnot Holdings, maker of Beech-Nut baby foods, was challenged by antitrust enforcers who said the transaction would hurt competition. The Federal Trade Commission voted 3 to 2 to challenge in court the combination of Heinz with Beech-Nut, the No. 2 United States baby food producer. The F.T.C. said the combination would mean just two companies, Heinz and Gerber, a unit of Novartis, would control 98 percent of the United States market for prepared baby foods. Shares of Heinz rose 31.25 cents, to $45.50 on the New York Stock Exchange. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Lessons From Nevada for Congress  Nevada has adopted a prescription drug program for the elderly very similar to one approved last month by the House of Representatives, but the program is off to a rocky start. Insurance companies have spurned Nevada's invitation to provide coverage. Nevada's experience offers ominous lessons for Congress, especially Republicans, who want to subsidize insurance companies to entice them into providing drug benefits to elderly and disabled people on Medicare. [A1.]</p>
        <p>World Bank Representative Cleared  The World Bank said this week that an eight-month investigation found no evidence to support accusations that a former Russian representative at the World Bank passed confidential information to a Russian commercial bank in 1993. The bank did conclude that the representative, Leonid Grigoriev, had established a business relationship with the defunct Inkombank, and that he received $13,000 for out-of-pocket expenses from the bank in 1993. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Students Learn Art of Negotiating  A group of some 50 students from two dozen countries participated in the second Model W.T.O. 2000 -- an idea that the World Trade Organization hopes to export to universities worldwide. The students, sequestered in a conference room in the W.T.O.'s building with spectacular views of Lake Geneva, concentrated on long and tough negotiations on the most sensitive trade issues, oblivious to the sunny weather outside. The mock negotiators were able to spend some time with the trade group's director general, Mike Moore, who told them they were lucky that they did not have to ''go home and sell'' their trade proposals to their parliaments. [C2.]</p>
        <p>A Contempt Ruling Is Overturned  A federal appeals court in Richmond, Va., has overturned a criminal contempt citation against a reporter who disclosed details of a sealed legal settlement after documents describing the agreement were inadvertently handed to her by a court clerk. The judges found there was no evidence that Kirsten B. Mitchell, a reporter for The Morning Star in Wilmington, N.C., intended ''to violate a court order or confidentiality,'' and that she acted ''wholly innocently.'' [C2.]</p>
        <p>Ex-G.M. Official to Fight Extradition  In an appearance before a Spanish judge, the former General Motors executive Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua said he would fight extradition to the United States. A grand jury in Detroit indicted Mr. Lopez in May on six criminal counts related to accusations that he stole company secrets from G.M. when he went to work for a rival, Volkswagen. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
