<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernandez Is Lucky, but Also Good</title>
    <meta content="08PINS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDB1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernandez Is Lucky, but Also Good</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher Orlando Hernandez is healthy again and pitches complete game against New York Mets, giving bullpen much-needed rest before doubleheader; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim Palmer extended his right hand to shake that of Orlando Hernandez in the Yankees' clubhouse the other day. The Hall of Fame pitcher pulled El Duque closer, and with his left index finger, Palmer tapped a spot near Hernandez's elbow.</p>
        <p>''Right there?'' Palmer asked, guessing the source of Hernandez's recent elbow trouble like an internist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jim Palmer extended his right hand to shake that of Orlando Hernandez in the Yankees' clubhouse the other day. The Hall of Fame pitcher pulled El Duque closer, and with his left index finger, Palmer tapped a spot near Hernandez's elbow.</p>
        <p>''Right there?'' Palmer asked, guessing the source of Hernandez's recent elbow trouble like an internist.</p>
        <p>''Si, si,'' Hernandez said, nodding, feinting a grimace through his smile.</p>
        <p>''What do you expect when you're 50 years old?'' Palmer joked, and Hernandez laughed and laughed.</p>
        <p>El Duque is healthy again and, as always, especially dangerous when the stands are filled and the game is important and he is the center of attention. He surrendered a run on five hits and a walk over eight innings last night as the Yankees edged the Mets, 2-1. In the process, Hernandez gave the bullpen a much-needed rest the night before their doubleheader.</p>
        <p>He and the Yankees -- who have a three-game winning streak for the first time since early May -- were fortunate, as the Mets kept blistering line drives all over the park, right at the Yankees. But when Paul O'Neill backed against the fence in the bottom of the eighth inning and reached high to rob Derek Bell of a home run, Hernandez's expression never really changed. He pumped a fist, which he did almost every out.</p>
        <p>''I threw my pitches where I wanted to throw them,'' Hernandez said, shrugging his shoulders. ''If I throw 20 pitches where I want to throw them, and they hit 20 line drives, then I am satisfied.</p>
        <p>''That is simply the game.''</p>
        <p>Elementary: Hernandez (8-6) pitched ahead in the count, using his fastball more than he usually does, throwing breaking balls to the less experienced Mets like Jay Payton. ''I didn't like it too much,'' Payton said. ''To me, he was nasty. I could've swung at his curveball twice. It was like a Bugs Bunny curveball.''</p>
        <p>Of the Mets' first 22 batters, 11 saw only one or two pitches, swinging early in the count. Hernandez required just 103 pitches over eight innings.</p>
        <p>Mark Carlson, the home plate umpire, called a fair but inconsistent strike zone, calling out Edgardo Alfonzo and Mike Piazza on fastballs just off the  plate in the fourth inning, then becoming more stingy the next inning, when Hernandez walked Todd Zeile to open the fifth.</p>
        <p>El Duque turned and glared into the Yankees' dugout after his first pitch to Payton, the next hitter, sharing his displeasure with his teammates. When the count went to 3-0 -- on another close pitch -- El Duque smirked.</p>
        <p>Payton walked, as well, and Hernandez jammed Benny Agbayani with a fastball. Agbayani fisted a line drive right back at Hernandez, over El Duque's head, to his right. Hernandez jumped and whirled and reached across his body to snare the ball with the webbing of his glove.</p>
        <p>The play would have been tough enough if he were left-handed, but Hernandez is right-handed and made the catch anyway. With his momentum turning him in the direction of second, he threw toward the bag, seeing Zeile off the base. Payton was far off first. For an instant, it looked as if there would be a triple play.</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter caught Hernandez's throw, stepped on second and threw to first, slightly off line and a little late to get Payton. ''It was a difficult play,'' Hernandez said, through an interpreter, ''but it was hit right at me.''</p>
        <p>Teammates recalled the play Hernandez made against the Mets last year, when a one-hopper hit back to the mound lodged in his glove. He sized up the situation immediately, then ran with the glove toward first before lobbing it perfectly to first baseman Tino Martinez for the out.</p>
        <p>Even after Melvin Mora tripled with one out in the eighth and O'Neill made his catch against the fence, Hernandez still appeared in control, Yankees Manager Joe Torre remarked.</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera was ready in the bullpen, but Hernandez glanced into the Yankees' dugout, and in this way, Torre said, Hernandez convinced him he would retire the next batter, Alfonzo, who flied out to end the inning.</p>
        <p>Hernandez waited for O'Neill at the top of the dugout steps and congratulated him on the catch, not shaken in the least by the near-misses. No, whether Hernandez's elbow is 35 or 31 or 50, he is meant to pitch well in big games, so long as he throws the ball where he wants. This is what El Duque believes.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
