<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y08BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFD91738F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: EX-REBEL LEADER SHOT  A former Kosovo Liberation Army commander was wounded in a shootout with supporters of a Kosovo Albanian political rival, witnesses said. Ramush Haradinaj, who now leads Kosovo's third-largest party, was traveling with a relative when the two were attacked in the village of Streoce. United Nations police officers were investigating.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: NO TO SECRET POLICE MONUMENT  In a sign of the waning influence of Communists and their allies, the lower house of Parliament voted down a measure calling for the restoration of a monument to the father of the Soviet secret police. A similar bill passed in 1998, but was ignored by Moscow city authorities. The new bill called for the restoration of a Stalin-era bronze statue of Felix Dzerzhinsky, founder of the ruthless Cheka secret police, which evolved into the N.K.V.D. and K.G.B. security forces, responsible for the death of millions. The statue, above, was torn down by jubilant crowds in 1991.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: EX-REBEL LEADER SHOT  A former Kosovo Liberation Army commander was wounded in a shootout with supporters of a Kosovo Albanian political rival, witnesses said. Ramush Haradinaj, who now leads Kosovo's third-largest party, was traveling with a relative when the two were attacked in the village of Streoce. United Nations police officers were investigating.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: NO TO SECRET POLICE MONUMENT  In a sign of the waning influence of Communists and their allies, the lower house of Parliament voted down a measure calling for the restoration of a monument to the father of the Soviet secret police. A similar bill passed in 1998, but was ignored by Moscow city authorities. The new bill called for the restoration of a Stalin-era bronze statue of Felix Dzerzhinsky, founder of the ruthless Cheka secret police, which evolved into the N.K.V.D. and K.G.B. security forces, responsible for the death of millions. The statue, above, was torn down by jubilant crowds in 1991.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: GAY UNIONS BILL  The government presented Parliament with a bill to permit ''gay weddings'' in which same-sex partners could officially register their relationship and gain the same tax and inheritance rights as married couples. It could also give foreigners in homosexual relationships with Germans a right to German residency. The bill now goes to a parliamentary committee.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: ACQUITTALS IN BORDER SHOOTINGS  Three former members of East Germany's Politburo were acquitted on manslaughter charges related to the killings of people trying to defect across the Berlin Wall. The court said it had not been proved that Siegfried Lorenz and Herbert Haber, both 69, and Hans-Joachim Bohme, 70, could have stopped the killings. Prosecutors said they would appeal.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>BRAZIL: ANTI-VIOLENCE DEMONSTRATIONS  Several million people in cities across the country marched in the largest citizen protest against violence in this nation of 175 million, wearing white and organizing silent vigils in an effort to pressure the government to take a tougher stance against both criminal gangs and police brutality.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: AID DECISION POSTPONED  The European Union has delayed action on a Colombian request for economic and social assistance to supplement the $1.3 billion in largely military aid that the United States will supply as part of an effort to curb drug trafficking and finance a peace deal with leftist guerrillas. At a donors' meeting in Madrid, the United Nations said it would supply $130 million and lending agencies agreed to kick in $300 million, but the European group postponed a decision until September.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>CANADA: ABORTION PILL TESTS  Canada's first clinical trials of RU-486, the French abortion pill, have started in four cities: Vancouver, Toronto, Quebec City and Sherbrooke, Quebec. Dr. Ellen Wiebe, the Vancouver doctor who is directing the study, won a $35,000 government grant to study the pill's health effects on 1,000 women. She hopes the trial will pave the way for government approval for the drug.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: CLAMPDOWN ON MARINES  United States Marines in Okinawa will not be allowed to drink alcohol during the Group of 8 economic meeting this month. The alcohol ban was ordered after the arrest on Monday of a drunken Marine who the police said entered a private home and molested a 14-year-old girl who was sleeping there. The Marines will also be required to be in uniform at all times during the July 20-24 meeting, which President Clinton is to attend.</p>
        <p>Calvin Sims (NYT)</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: OUSTED LEADER'S ALLIES HELD  The police arrested dozens of supporters of former Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif in Punjab province in an effort to prevent his wife, Kulsoom Nawaz, from leading a procession from Lahore to Peshawar. Punjab officials said that large political rallies are outlawed, but Ms. Nawaz insisted that her march was to support victims of drought. Mr. Sharif was overthrown in an October coup and is serving a life prison sentence.</p>
        <p>P. J. Anthony (NYT)</p>
        <p>SOUTH KOREA: MISSILE PROGRAM ON AGENDA  The assistant secretary of state for nonproliferation, Robert Einhorn, will visit South Korea next week to discuss Seoul's attempt to build longer-range missiles, officials said. The United States and South Korea have held a series of talks over the last two years about Seoul's wish to increase the range of its missiles, now set at 112 miles under a 1979 agreement.</p>
        <p>Samuel Len (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: STUDENT MEMORIAL  Students said they would hand out flowers in Tehran's streets and light candles today to commemorate a raid on a Tehran University dormitory a year ago in which one student was killed and scores were injured. The pre-dawn raid by hard-line security forces and vigilantes, which came hours after students rallied against the banning of a liberal newspaper, set off six days of nationwide protests by tens of thousands of students -- the worst unrest in Iran since the 1979 Islamic revolution.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ERITREA: U.N. TEAM ARRIVES  A United Nations team making preparations for the deployment of peacekeepers to monitor the cease-fire between Ethiopia and Eritrea arrived in the Eritrean capital, Asmara. The team is scheduled to spend four days in Eritrea before returning to Ethiopia, a government spokesman said. Under the terms of the truce signed by Eritrea and Ethiopia on June 18, an unspecified number of peacekeepers are to be deployed in a security zone along the Eritrean side of the border, which is about 620 miles long.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
