<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ominous Start for a Drug Prescription Plan for the Elderly</title>
    <meta content="08ELDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DA1438F93BA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ominous Start for a Drug Prescription Plan for the Elderly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>CARSON CITY, Nev., July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Insurance companies reject Nevada's invitation to provide prescription drug coverage to the eldery in a program very similar to one approved by US House of Representatives; say risks and costs are too high and state's subsidies are too low; Nevada's experience offers ominous lessons for Congress, especially Republicans, who want to subsidize insurance companies to entice them into providing drug benefits to elderly and disabled people on Medicare (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nevada has adopted a prescription drug program for the elderly very similar to one approved last month by the United States House of Representatives, but it is off to a rocky start.</p>
        <p>Insurance companies have spurned Nevada's invitation to provide coverage. The risks and the costs are too high, they say, and the subsidies offered by the state are too low.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nevada has adopted a prescription drug program for the elderly very similar to one approved last month by the United States House of Representatives, but it is off to a rocky start.</p>
        <p>Insurance companies have spurned Nevada's invitation to provide coverage. The risks and the costs are too high, they say, and the subsidies offered by the state are too low.</p>
        <p>Nevada's experience offers ominous lessons for Congress, especially Republicans, who want to subsidize insurance companies to entice them into providing drug benefits to elderly and disabled people on Medicare.</p>
        <p>States often portray themselves as the laboratories of democracy where good ideas originate and are tested, and Nevada's governor, Kenny Guinn, a Republican, was far ahead of Washington in trying to address the needs of the elderly in buying prescription drugs. Governor Guinn signed the legislation creating the program on June 9, 1999, three weeks before President Clinton unveiled his proposal to add drug benefits to Medicare. But Nevada officials say Mr. Guinn's ideas may need more work in the laboratory before they can be put into effect nationwide.</p>
        <p>Nevada was prepared to use 15 percent of the $1.2 billion it expected to receive over the next 25 years from the settlement of its lawsuit against tobacco companies -- $4.6 million this year, $37 million over six years -- to subsidize drug benefits for elderly people with incomes of less than $21,500 a year.</p>
        <p>In March, the state invited hundreds of insurance companies to bid for its business, providing drug coverage for 10,000 to 14,000 people age 62 or older. Only one company responded, but it was ineligible because it was not licensed to sell insurance in Nevada. The state revised its invitation and reissued it on June 29, with an Aug. 29 deadline for submission of proposals.</p>
        <p>Barbara E. Buckley, a state assemblywoman who is co-chairwoman of a task force monitoring use of the money, said: ''I have my doubts that an insurance company will be able to offer meaningful drug benefits under this program. If an insurance company does bid on it but the benefits are paltry, senior citizens will be up in arms.''</p>
        <p>The task force has refused to authorize the release of any money until it sees details of a drug program, like the eligibility criteria, premiums, deductibles, co-payments and benefit limits. Most of those details will be decided by the successful bidder.</p>
        <p>Ed Fend, a retired Navy captain who serves on the task force, said he was surprised at the insurance industry's failure to respond to the state's initial invitation. Asked why insurers did not show more interest, Mr. Fend said: ''Probably because they don't think they can make any money.''</p>
        <p>The Nevada program, created by the State Legislature last year at the governor's request, resembles the Republican plan approved in the United States House of Representatives on June 28 by vote of 217 to 214, largely on party lines.</p>
        <p>Representative Shelley Berkley,  Democrat of Las Vegas, said she did not understand why Congress would try to copy a troubled state program.</p>
        <p>''Why in the world, when it is not yet functioning'' for low-income seniors in Nevada, ''would we try to replicate it for the millions of seniors who are desperately in need of affordable prescription medications?'' Ms. Berkley asked.</p>
        <p>Governor Guinn said he remained ''fully committed'' to carrying out the program, known as Senior Rx. He complained that Ms. Berkley had made ''a bitter partisan attack on a program which will benefit thousands of Nevada's low-income senior citizens.''</p>
        <p>Under the Nevada program, state officials say, premiums should be in the range of $45 to $60 a month. The state would pay up to $40 of that amount, based on the patient's income; the patient would pay the rest.</p>
        <p>In Washington, the Health Insurance Association of America has repeatedly told Congress that its members are not interested in selling ''drug only'' insurance to the elderly. House Republicans have insisted that if Congress provides the money, insurers or other companies will offer coverage. Nevada's experience raises questions about that argument.</p>
        <p>The state offered millions of dollars in subsidies, but insurers were skittish.</p>
        <p>''They didn't understand what we were looking for,'' said Scott Scherer, chief of staff to Governor Guinn. ''They were confused by the first request for proposals.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Nevada's experience tends to confirm a point made repeatedly by Republicans in Congress: private insurers need freedom to design drug benefits as they think best.</p>
        <p>Denice L. Miller, senior policy adviser to Governor Guinn, summarized the lesson this way: ''Let the insurers be creative. Let them be flexible. Let seniors have some choices.''</p>
        <p>Medicare generally does not cover prescription drugs for people outside a hospital. Democrats in Congress want to offer the same drug benefits, with the same premiums, to all Medicare recipients. Republicans reject that approach. Under the House-passed bill, premiums, benefits and co-payments could vary from one private drug plan to another, so long as the overall value was equivalent to that of a standard policy defined by the federal government.</p>
        <p>At least 14 states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, have programs to help older people obtain prescription medicines. In most cases, the state itself is the insurer, reviewing claims, paying pharmacies and deciding which drugs a patient may receive. Nevada, rather than paying for drugs outright, is the first state to develop a program that uses subsidies to help people buy private drug insurance of the type envisioned by many Republicans in Congress.</p>
        <p>Here, as in Washington, insurers worry that the people who buy drug coverage will tend to be the sickest, those who need it most. State Senator Raymond D. Rawson, a Republican, said insurance companies were ''very worried'' about this phenomenon, known as adverse selection.</p>
        <p>Marie H. Soldo, executive vice president of Sierra Health Services of Las Vegas, the largest managed care company in the state, said: ''Insurers are unwilling to bear the entire financial risk of drug coverage. The rapidly rising cost of pharmacy benefits does not allow that.''</p>
        <p>The only company that responded to the state's first solicitation was Mature Rx Plus of Nevada. It was set up this year by FFI Health Services, a privately held company based in Macedonia, Ohio. James J. Mindala, chief executive of FFI, said the company was seeking a Nevada license and still hoped to participate in the program here. FFI was acquired this week by Advance Paradigm of Irving, Tex., a provider of health-benefit management services.</p>
        <p>The Nevada program had broad bipartisan support when it was created under a bill passed unanimously by both houses of the Legislature in May 1999. But since then, prescription drugs have become a major issue at the national level defining philosophical differences between the parties, and specifically between the Republican and Democratic candidates for Nevada's open seat in the United States Senate.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Democratic candidate for the Senate, Ed Bernstein, has made prescription drugs the central issue of his campaign against John Ensign, the Republican, who served in the House from 1995 to 1999.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein, a lawyer, flew to Tijuana, Mexico, last month to call attention to the lower prices charged for prescription drugs south of the border. Back in Reno, he dumped $100,000 in cash on the ground in front of a drug company distribution center; it was, Mr. Bernstein said, a symbol of the campaign contributions that Mr. Ensign has taken from drug manufacturers. Mr. Bernstein has toured the state in a recreational vehicle, the ''Rx R.V.,'' talking about the need to make medicines more affordable.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Ensign says the Nevada program should be given time to work.</p>
        <p>The insurers' role in the Nevada program is similar to that provided in the House Republican bill. In its invitation to insurers, the state said it wanted them to ''provide prescription drug and pharmaceutical services'' to the elderly, to market the approved insurance policies and to set up a network of drugstores to fill prescriptions. The insurers are also expected to offer mail-order pharmacy services and could establish a list of preferred drug products.</p>
        <p>Nevada officials, like federal officials, hope to use the leverage of their purchasing power to obtain discounts on drugs. Insurers could set monthly or annual limits on benefits, but subscribers could still buy drugs at a discount after they reached the limit covered by their insurance.</p>
        <p>The population of Nevada is the nation's fastest growing. The number of Nevadans age 65 and older now exceeds 210,000, an increase of more than 60 percent since 1990.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
