<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23GUID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDE1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Horses in Artist's Eyes</p>
        <p>The horses in ''Horseplay,'' an exhibition of sculptures, drawings and prints by Leslie Enders Lee, represent some 40 plays on the word horse and mostly variations on a single design. The exhibition will remain at 100 Pearl Gallery in Hartford through Aug. 19.</p>
        <p>A metal War Horse head is hinged like a knight's armored visor. The Hobby Horse head is wooden, attached to a stick that a child would straddle. Pegasus appears as a pair of horseshoes with wings, and a line drawing called Quarter Horse is sectioned into four parts, reminiscent of instructional diagrams for butchering cattle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Horses in Artist's Eyes</p>
        <p>The horses in ''Horseplay,'' an exhibition of sculptures, drawings and prints by Leslie Enders Lee, represent some 40 plays on the word horse and mostly variations on a single design. The exhibition will remain at 100 Pearl Gallery in Hartford through Aug. 19.</p>
        <p>A metal War Horse head is hinged like a knight's armored visor. The Hobby Horse head is wooden, attached to a stick that a child would straddle. Pegasus appears as a pair of horseshoes with wings, and a line drawing called Quarter Horse is sectioned into four parts, reminiscent of instructional diagrams for butchering cattle.</p>
        <p>A book reproducing the items in the show has a whimsical text by Ms. Lee connecting the works with one or more literary, mythological or show business sources. The Trojan Horse, of course, relates to Virgil, a Horse of a Different Color is from the Land of Oz, and a horse head of feathers was inspired by the Marx Brothers film, ''Horsefeathers.'' Viewing hours are Monday through Friday, from 9 a.m. to 8 p.m., Saturday from 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. The number to call for more information is (860) 233-1932.</p>
        <p>Model Yacht Regatta</p>
        <p>Mystic Seaport will hold its first J Challenge Cup Model Yacht Regatta on Friday, Saturday and next Sunday, with a dozen boats competing. Practice begins on Friday at 10 a.m.; the national champion will be crowned on Saturday after competition from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m., and match races re-creating the America's Cup races of the 1930's are scheduled for next Sunday from noon to 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>The radio-controlled sailboats measure about 8 feet long, 10 feet tall and weigh some 65 pounds. Some are replicas of the Shamrock, the Enterprise and the Endeavour.</p>
        <p>Throughout the weekend a display of several world-class models will be on display, from the 1899 Columbia to the 1990's Intrepid. The event is sanctioned by the American Model Yachting Association and United States Vintage Model Yacht Group.</p>
        <p>Admission to the seaport grounds, all exhibitions and the regatta is $16, $8 for children 6 through 12, free for those under 6. Restaurants are on the premises and parking is free. The grounds can be reached by taking Exit 90 from Interstate 95 and proceeding south for one mile to the entrance at 75 Greenmanville Avenue. The number to call for more information is (888) 973-2767.</p>
        <p>Gardeners Offer Advice</p>
        <p>Homeowners in or near Bethel have a handy service available at the University of Connecticut Cooperative Extension System, 67 Stony Hill Road. Expert advice on diseased or poorly growing shrubs, trees and flowers will be dispensed by master gardeners on Monday through Thursday from 9:30 a.m. to noon and 1:45 to 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>People planning to bring in samples of troublesome plants should call first, but walk-ins are welcome and a phone call from anywhere in the state to (203) 207-3262 may solve the problem without making the trip.</p>
        <p>Help with spiders and ticks is not included in this program, but help in identifying them and general information about them are available by calling the Agricultural Extension Station in New Haven at (877) 855-2237.</p>
        <p>Tutorials in Crafts</p>
        <p>The Brookfield Craft Center on Route 25 in Brookfield has instituted personal tutorials, a boon for amateurs and professionals who cannot attend the center's regularly scheduled classes.</p>
        <p>Private one-on-one sessions are also valuable to people working on unusual projects and those who need to expand quickly into new areas. Currently, the center is offering tutorials on the potter's wheel, welding, bas-relief, glass beads, glass-blowing and jewelry.</p>
        <p>Since the program began a year ago, former students who were unable to complete projects as far back as 1993 have returned to do so in private tutorials. Others who were not getting the attention they needed in a class of 10 to 15 people say that tutorials have solved the problem.</p>
        <p>The fee is $50 an hour, with three to six sessions recommended for various subjects. Sessions take place in the instructors' studios on days and at times agreeable to both parties. The number to call for more information is (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>New Milford Fair</p>
        <p>New Milford's annual Village Fair Days draw about 28,000 people to the town's spacious village green. The 33rd edition is scheduled on Friday from 10 a.m. to 10 p.m. and Saturday from 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. Exhibitors will be coming from throughout New England, New York and New Jersey, from Tennessee, Kentucky, Missouri, Ohio, Kansas, New Mexico, Louisiana, Florida and Washington state.</p>
        <p>Among merchandise to be found are leather goods, wooden clocks and toys, specialty foods, jewelry, quilts, puppets, Adirondack-style furniture,  American Indian carvings and paintings, dolls and clothing.</p>
        <p>More than 25 of the 140 booths on the middle and north green will be devoted to antiques -- furniture, glass, china, linens, sterling flatware and hollowware, cameos, prints and paintings. On the south green 100 other booths will feature various goods and services.</p>
        <p>Continuous entertainment and a wide selection of foods will be available under tents, and to complete the agenda there will be a Shriners Parade and a marathon on Saturday. The number to call for directions or more information is (860) 354-6080.</p>
        <p>Things Nautical</p>
        <p>Pasquale Montesi emigrated from Italy in 1898 and opened a fish market on West Main Street in Norwich. That was his day job. His real passion was ships. Having been a sailor in the Italian navy with a talent for woodcarving, he began to fashion ship models from memory.</p>
        <p>Seventeen of his intricately carved models, ranging from a tugboat to a fully rigged 12-foot-long, 10-foot-high clipper ship are in an exhibition called ''The Montesi Ships: Maritime Folk Art,'' on view at the Lyman Allyn Art Museum of Connecticut College in New London through April of 2002.</p>
        <p>A second exhibition, entitled ''The Sailing Coast Guard,'' consists in part of oils, watercolors and etchings from the Coast Guard's collections. Pennants, sextants, wardroom china and uniforms from Coast Guard vessels, biographies and portraits of the naval architects who designed them, photographs and ship plans will also be on display through Sept. 10.</p>
        <p>The museum is at 625 Williams Str  eet. The number to call for more information is (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
