<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Patrons Can Watch the Sunset</title>
    <meta content="23DINE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saratoga Grill (South Salem, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5DE1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Patrons Can Watch the Sunset</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH SALEM</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Saratoga Grill in South Salem, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DINERS who frequented Coolmore on this pretty spot in the Vista section here will feel at home at the newly named Saratoga Grill. Excepting the name, not too much has changed. A half-hearted racing motif persists in racing silks hanging about and racetrack related photographs and posters, but this theme is still a bit of a stretch, conflicting as it does with terra cotta tiles, stonework and arches, which were custom made to reflect the Tuscan interior of an Italian restaurant that once occupied this site.</p>
        <p>The attractions, however, remain in the handsome, roomy bar -- in wintry weather a corner fireplace adds a cozy, romantic note -- and the decks, a reason to come here. These overlook a splendid pond, a favorite with ducks, geese and other winged wildlife, as well as with earthbound, sunglassed patrons who come to watch the bird antics and the sunset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DINERS who frequented Coolmore on this pretty spot in the Vista section here will feel at home at the newly named Saratoga Grill. Excepting the name, not too much has changed. A half-hearted racing motif persists in racing silks hanging about and racetrack related photographs and posters, but this theme is still a bit of a stretch, conflicting as it does with terra cotta tiles, stonework and arches, which were custom made to reflect the Tuscan interior of an Italian restaurant that once occupied this site.</p>
        <p>The attractions, however, remain in the handsome, roomy bar -- in wintry weather a corner fireplace adds a cozy, romantic note -- and the decks, a reason to come here. These overlook a splendid pond, a favorite with ducks, geese and other winged wildlife, as well as with earthbound, sunglassed patrons who come to watch the bird antics and the sunset.</p>
        <p>We wish the food were better. Except for a few items, most offerings seem to be produced by a kitchen that takes little care or has little interest in the art. But if you go for the sunset or the bar's charm, there are a few dishes to look for.</p>
        <p>Diners betting on a sure winner will most likely collect on one of the refreshing salads. Arugula and endive came topped with goat cheese, sweet roasted peppers and balsamic dressing. The Travers salad of romaine (not the promised mixed greens), bacon strips and blue cheese was satisfactory, and judging from Saratoga's fresh greens, the less ornate house salad would have been almost as satisfying.</p>
        <p>For a risky long shot, try Kentucky Rose, a huge onion that cooks and opens like a flower when dunked in hot fat. Preparing this offering takes more skill than one might think. Inadequate cooking will result in a raw product.</p>
        <p>Standard steamed littlenecks in white wine and garlic proved tender and tasty; and mussels, a special, were pristinely fresh, with not a clinker in the batch.</p>
        <p>Deserving a dipping sauce more interesting than teriyaki and ginger, big sea scallops would have been as luscious without a stiff bacon wrap. But considerably less appealing, stuffed mushrooms arrived hard, bland and barely warm, and chicken tenders might have come from the supermarket freezer, the crust, double thick and overcrisped, and the dip, a no-brainer: mayonnaise with a bit of spice.</p>
        <p>To judge from dull penne ala vodka (flavorless marinara sauce seemed to be the culprit), other pasta dishes could be risky. The ribbons went to plain grilled red meats. Both filet mignon and prime rib proved juicy, beautifully textured and done to a rosy medium rare, as we requested. Slices from grilled top round of lamb were equally succulent and full of meaty taste. And although baby back ribs might have been a tad too smoky, a full rack was listed and a full rack arrived. Mere mortals might share the daunting portion.</p>
        <p>Entrees could have used more carefully prepared vegetables. Fusty rice and weary mashed potatoes and garlic didn't cut it. Large spinach leaves were awkward to eat.</p>
        <p>Grilled shrimp, however, might be avoided altogether. They were dehydrated, tough and old. Cut too thin, special swordfish spent too much time over the flame and arrived dry.</p>
        <p>Set over a votive candle, overly sweet chocolate fondue overrode the flavors and inherent sweetness of fresh fruits, cut for dipping. Take the fruit and let the chocolate go. Cakes were like those displayed in diners, ornate creations based on air and sugar: ho-hum chocolate-chip cake and Key lime pie, chalky cheese cake, bland peach caramel cake and tiramisu, which was almost all custard.</p>
        <p>From a wide price range, a three-course dinner averages $29 without drinks, tax and tip. Saratoga Grill is south of Route 35, in the Oakridge Shopping Center.</p>
        <p>Saratoga Grill  Route 123, South Salem (Vista),  (914) 533-1115.</p>
        <p>SATISFACTORY</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Arched, lofty main dining room with half-wall dividers. A far room has a view, as do the decks, which overlook a lovely pond. Large, convivial bar with fireplace. Untrained service runs from flighty to overly friendly.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- Smoking section available.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Steamed clams, steamed mussels, filet mignon, prime rib, grilled lamb, cut fresh fruit assortment (without melted chocolate).</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Dinner, main dishes, $13 to $29; $7.50 to $11.50 for burgers and sandwiches.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Dinner, Mondays through Saturdays, 5 to 10 P.M.; Sundays, 5 to 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
