<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tangled Sex and Identity in 'Twelfth Night'</title>
    <meta content="23SHAK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Discher, Joseph</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Twelfth Night (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DC163AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tangled Sex and Identity in 'Twelfth Night'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews New Jersey Shakespeare Festival production of Twelfth Night, directed by Joseph Discher, at F M Kirby Shakespeare Theater in Madison; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is hard to think of any play  comical, historical or tragical -- that confronts the profound issues of who and what a person is, and who that person will be attracted to, with a greater sense of absurdity than ''Twelfth Night.''</p>
        <p>Because it is a comedy, no one is disoriented for long, and all problems are resolved. But everyone knows happy endings are theatrical devices; in life, nothing is so pat. How then does a director deal with the mysteries of identity and sexuality in ''Twelfth Night'' so that they go unanswered. It is shallow to do otherwise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is hard to think of any play  comical, historical or tragical -- that confronts the profound issues of who and what a person is, and who that person will be attracted to, with a greater sense of absurdity than ''Twelfth Night.''</p>
        <p>Because it is a comedy, no one is disoriented for long, and all problems are resolved. But everyone knows happy endings are theatrical devices; in life, nothing is so pat. How then does a director deal with the mysteries of identity and sexuality in ''Twelfth Night'' so that they go unanswered. It is shallow to do otherwise.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare's resolutions only served the purpose of bringing down the curtain; he knew the ambiguities went on; listen to the lines.</p>
        <p>''Our play is done, And we'll strive to please you every day.'' That's how the ballad of Feste, the singing fool, wraps it all up. In the New Jersey Shakespeare Festival staging here, James Michael Reilly's air of melancholy in the final moments, will not send you out on wings of mirth. The actor truly plays a ''reluctant jester,'' as the character has been described by the author Harold Bloom. If it is director Joseph Discher's concept to gradually unfold the dark side, not only of the jester but of what is perceived as Shakespeare's merry prank, it works fitfully.</p>
        <p>Few ''Twelfth Night'' stagings strike the finely tuned balance between the play's lunatic lovers and its lowdown buffoons. All too many interpretations seem to favor antic humor and horseplay over romantic entanglements.</p>
        <p>But, at heart, Mr. Discher appears to be going for neither. Feste does a somersault, Sir Toby Belch, taking his surname literally, never lacks for a spare flask and Sir Andrew Aguecheek, a caricature for openers, is overly dandified. But that does not mean comedy -- or vaudeville -- has overtaken the play's real concerns. Their schtick is part of a subplot, silly intrusions except when performed by master clowns and superb stylists.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Reilly effectively juxtaposes rueful moments with an audience singalong, Malcom Tulip's sloshed Sir Toby and Jeffrey M. Bender's fey Sir Andrew are little more than two stooges turned into sadists, given their mistreatment of the enigmatic Malvolio, the maligned steward, social climber and snob.</p>
        <p>In Malvolio (Edmond Genest), Mr. Discher's ideas peer through. Mr. Genest's performance starts ineffectually, building to pathos, and to a potent exit ''in his rage and in his wrath.''</p>
        <p>In a variable cast, Caralyn Kozlowski personifies Olivia's ''sovereign cruelty'' to the Duke who professes to love her, the actress is a vision of heaven walking on earth -- what pressure -- and she seems bafflingly enslaved by a sudden love for Cesario, who is really Viola in disguise.</p>
        <p>Lauren Lovett is erotic and sly in the double role, but when the real Sebastian (the twin brother Viola is impersonating) enters, in the guise of Kevin Henderson, the actor misses every chance to make something ardent or comic of the obsessed Olivia's brazen overtures.</p>
        <p>The Duke can get no satisfaction from another; his passion for Olivia is a coverup for all-consuming self-love. Tom Delling's performance is all talk, making none of these plot inconsistencies or psychological complexities clear. It is up to Ms. Kozlowski and Ms. Lovett to turn Shakespeare's nonsensical out-of-control views of love into rational portrayals of the irrational. They do. Make of the rest of ''Twelfth Night'' what you will.</p>
        <p>TWELFTH NIGHT  F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater, 36  Madison Avenue, Madison.</p>
        <p>Through July 30. Tuesday through Friday at 8 p.m., Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m.  (973) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
