<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Comes the Hard Part</title>
    <meta content="23CELL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.J. LAW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Signs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Marlboro Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DE163AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Comes the Hard Part</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>MARLBORO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on legal challenges facing Marlboro, NJ, as it starts issuing warnings under law banning motorists from using hand-held cell phones while driving; law will not be enforced until residents are notified and signs are posted, which should take about three months; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marsha Blitshtein had no sooner had climbed from her 1998 Honda Accord in the Marlboro Plaza shopping center here than she got on her cell phone. Walking across the parking lot as she talked, Ms. Blitshtein asked her father whether she had received her housing assignment at the University of Delaware, where she is a sophomore.</p>
        <p>A 19-year old resident of Manalapan, Ms. Blitshtein said she had read about the ordinance recently approved here banning the use of hand-held cell phones, and conceded she herself had been guilty of the practice..</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marsha Blitshtein had no sooner had climbed from her 1998 Honda Accord in the Marlboro Plaza shopping center here than she got on her cell phone. Walking across the parking lot as she talked, Ms. Blitshtein asked her father whether she had received her housing assignment at the University of Delaware, where she is a sophomore.</p>
        <p>A 19-year old resident of Manalapan, Ms. Blitshtein said she had read about the ordinance recently approved here banning the use of hand-held cell phones, and conceded she herself had been guilty of the practice..</p>
        <p>''I agree with it,'' she said of the law, the first in the state and one of a handful nationwide. ''But people aren't going to follow it. Technology has become everybody's focus in life.''</p>
        <p>It was a telling observation. Indeed, the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration announced at a public hearing in Washington last week that it would study the threat posed by drivers using cell phones and other electronic devises.</p>
        <p>One agency official said there had been ''a dramatic change in driver behavior'' because of them, a statement bolstered by a study showing that inattentive motorists were involved in a quarter of the nation's 6.3 million auto accidents each year.</p>
        <p>Yet efforts to ban electronic devices in cars have failed in state legislatures around the country. Since 1995, 33 states -- including New Jersey, New York and Connecticut -- have rejected such efforts. And municipalities have had mixed success as they have wrestled with the legal complexities.</p>
        <p>In the Philadelphia suburb of Hilltown Township, which approved limits on cell phones, the law was struck down by a county judge only two days before passage of the Marlboro ordinance, casting uncertainty on the laws in several Pennsylvania towns and raising questions as to whether state motor vehicle laws preclude municipalities from enforcing the measures. For now, Hilltown is considering whether to appeal.</p>
        <p>Frank Askin, who founded the constitutional law clinic at Rutgers University, said there was nothing unconstitutional about the ban, although he questioned whether New Jersey would let it stand.</p>
        <p>''They can't do it without the approval of the state Department of Transportation,'' Mr. Askin said. ''And I can't imagine the state approving it, because it's a statewide policy that needs uniform regulation throughout the state.''</p>
        <p>But for its part, the state Department of Transportation is not sure it has jurisdiction in the matter. ''At this point we haven't made that determination nor have we seen the ordinance, said John Dourgarian, a department spokesman.</p>
        <p>In fact, Marlboro officials are asking transportation officials for approval to post  signs on state roads in the municipality -- 9, 18, 34 and 79 -- and help with the wording, not for approval of the ordinance.</p>
        <p>Mindful of Hilltown's experience, Marlboro -- whose township attorney is John O. Bennett 3rd, the majority leader of the New Jersey State Senate -- drafted the measure not as a traffic ordinance but under the police powers of the state that take in health, safety and welfare, said Councilman Barry D. Denkensohn, the bill's sponsor.</p>
        <p>''We designed the ordinance to regulate behavior or conduct in a motor vehicle, not equipment,'' Mr. Denkensohn said. ''The key thing here is the statute is under general police powers and as such, pre-emption should not apply. And therefore I think this statute will hold up in court.''</p>
        <p>Under Marlboro's ordinance, which carries a $250 fine, using a hand-held cell phone while driving is a primary offense, meaning the police can stop a motorist purely for using the phone. Only two other municipalities have such a law, Brooklyn, Ohio, and Lebanon, Pa.</p>
        <p>Hilltown, Conshohocken and West Conshohocken in Pennsylvania have secondary laws; the police can't pull over a driver for using a cell phone, but only for committing another offense, like speeding.</p>
        <p>Marlboro's law will not be enforced until residents are notified through such measures as newsletters and after up to 75 signs are posted, which should take about three months, said Stephanie Luftglass, director of public information.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, motorists are receiving  warnings, said Capt. Danny Schick. As he studied the placement of signs one recent morning, he said the major concern was fair enforcement of the law. ''Marlboro Township is in a central location and has so many roadways passing through that we want to make sure all travelers are aware of the ordinance,'' Captain Schick said.</p>
        <p>Officials of this town of 36,000 are trying to avoid the fate of Hilltown, which did not post signs, a possible factor in the rejection of its measure by a Bucks County judge. A 27-square-mile exurban community of 12,500 residents, Hilltown passed its ordinance last December in response to the death of 2-year old Morgan Lee Pena at the hands of a driver using a cell phone.</p>
        <p>Hilltown was the second municipality in the country to enact a ban, and its manager, Greg Lippincott, said the governing body planned to meet this week to discuss whether to appeal the ruling. Mr. Lippincott said eight tickets had been given out so far, the first of which resulted in the case that overturned the law.</p>
        <p>Philip J. Berg, a lawyer from Lafayette Hill who represented the driver in that case and spoke at the public hearing here, said he considered such bans unconstitutional. In West Conshohocken, the town solicitor, Edmund Campbell, said its ordinance, which was enacted in May, was being suspended until the council decided its fate next month.</p>
        <p>And in Conshohocken, where the ban went into effect in February, one ticket had been handed out in an unusual case, said Jack Heleniak, the borough manager. ''The driver ran three stop signs and went up a one-way street, all the time talking on a cell phone,'' Mr. Heleniak said. Enforcement there has been suspended until a review by the solicitor is completed.</p>
        <p>So far, the ordinance in Brooklyn, Ohio, the first in the nation, has not been challenged since its adoption in March 1999; officials said that 250 tickets had been given out. The majority of them -- 210 tickets -- were written by Patrolman Rich Hovan, who said he made it a personal crusade after a friend narrowly missed being struck by a driver using a cell phone.</p>
        <p>Meeting Morgan Pena's mother, Patricia, on the Oprah Winfrey show in February made him even more of a crusader. ''I write every one of those tickets in her memory,'' said Patrolman Hovan, who puts Morgan's initials on each summons.</p>
        <p>Legal challenges aside, most people questioned in Marlboro and Hilltown said they were not against hands-free cell phones but  favored a ban of hand-held cell phones. Yet  a study by Toronto researchers that appeared in the New England Journal of Medicine in 1997 indicated that it was the conversation and not just holding the phone that distracted motorists.</p>
        <p>''I try to cut the conversation short,'' said Teresa Gallo of Manalapan, a hairdresser in the Marlboro Plaza mall. ''And if it's not going to be short, then I pull over.''</p>
        <p>But Larry Granoff of Warminster, Pa., a Penn State student and National Guardsman who works as a cell phone salesman, said he opposed to a ban. ''You really need a cell phone when driving for many reasons,'' said Mr. Granoff.</p>
        <p>Then there is Theresa O'Hara of Hilltown, who lives near the site of Morgan Pena's death. Ms. O'Hara said she favored a state law that would make enforcement more uniform. The problem now, she said, is ''you can go from one town to the next and not know where you're at.''</p>
        <p>N.J. LAW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
