<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>33 Years of Jethro Tull, And Still Going Strong</title>
    <meta content="23KYLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jethro Tull (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>33 Years of Jethro Tull, And Still Going Strong</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Ian Anderson, leader of Jethro Tull, who comments on band, his career and upcoming performance at Ives Concert Park in Danbury, Conn; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE leader of Jethro Tull, Ian Anderson, has never bought into the idea that rock musicians are all a mix of artistry and financial idiocy.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that musicians aren't as stupid as people like to think; if you treat them like they have a brain, they just might rise to the occasion,'' said Mr. Anderson, who, with the other members of Jethro Tull, performs at the Ives Concert Park in Danbury this Saturday evening. The tour is in support of the band's new release, ''j-tull Dot Com'' (Fuel Records).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE leader of Jethro Tull, Ian Anderson, has never bought into the idea that rock musicians are all a mix of artistry and financial idiocy.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that musicians aren't as stupid as people like to think; if you treat them like they have a brain, they just might rise to the occasion,'' said Mr. Anderson, who, with the other members of Jethro Tull, performs at the Ives Concert Park in Danbury this Saturday evening. The tour is in support of the band's new release, ''j-tull Dot Com'' (Fuel Records).</p>
        <p>Few in the industry are smarter than Mr. Anderson. He and his band have been successful for virtually all 33 years of Jethro Tull's existence. The band, which is named after an 18th-century English agricultural pioneer who invented the seed drill, has survived personnel changes, lulls in record sales and pop music trends that have claimed many of the band's early contemporaries. The main reason for the band's financial success, Mr. Anderson said, was that the band manages itself.</p>
        <p>''We took control of our office in the early 70's,'' said Mr. Anderson. ''Before that, it wasn't as organized as it should have been.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson and his band mates took over the managerial reigns during the band's tour of ''Aqualung,'' its most successful album. Henceforth, the band always turned a healthy profit on the road during a period when many rock bands were fortunate to break even.</p>
        <p>''I heard that some bands were not making money and, quite frankly, they must have been stupid,'' Mr. Anderson said. ''If they watched where their money went, they wouldn't have allowed themselves to be mismanaged.''</p>
        <p>''I've always had a hunger to learn how things go,'' he said. ''Since we do it ourselves, we understand how the business works. It also gives me the freedom from the worry that I'm getting ripped off.''</p>
        <p>When Jethro Tull released its first album in 1968, ''This Was,'' the band was a perfect candidate for exploitation by any major record company. Jethro Tull was an instant success in Europe and America, only to see its stock rise with the release of ''Stand Up'' (1969), ''Benefit'' (1970), ''Aqualung'' (1971) and ''Thick As A Brick'' (1972). Jethro Tull had instantly established itself as a pioneer of art rock, or blues-rock, as some called it. Mr. Anderson, the band's primary songwriter, weaves folk-like tales with unusual characters. He was known as a consummate showman, playing his flute while standing on one foot, balancing over the apron of the stage. His decision to take up the flute is in itself evidence of a pragmatic mind at work.</p>
        <p>''I first learned the guitar,'' Mr. Anderson said, ''but I later picked up the flute because I noticed that Eric Clapton and Jimmy Hendrix couldn't play it.''</p>
        <p>When the band's record sales failed to maintain the feverish pitch of its early years, Jethro Tull didn't fold. One reason is that Mr. Anderson now retains control over the rights to his music. The band has maintained a steady touring schedule even when it didn't have a new album to promote. Mr. Anderson, who turns 53 in a few weeks, doesn't seem to tire of the travel.</p>
        <p>''I don't O.D. on other people's music,'' he said. ''I try to keep in touch, but I try to save my music for when I'm doing it. Secondly, the kind of music I make is fairly rich in improvisation. It's not the same, night to night.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson also keeps fresh between shows by writing ''doodles and noodles'' that eventually become songs. He writes every day, he said. ''Writing good songs requires discipline. It's easy to write a mediocre song. The discipline comes in when you try to make a mediocre song a good song.''</p>
        <p>Jethro Tull performs at 8 p.m. on Saturday at the Ives Concert Park on the Western Connecticut State University westside campus in Danbury. Tickets are $10 to $50. The numbers to call for further information are (203) 744-8100 or (203) 624-0033.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
