<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Co-op Board's Powers</title>
    <meta content="23QAQA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFDB1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Co-op Board's Powers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Housing Q&amp;A on cooperative rules</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: Do co-op boards have the right to unilaterally make decisions such as cutting down trees without consulting other members of the co-op?  What recourse do I have? Can I take out an injunction? . . . Kathryn M. Mets, Forest Hills</p>
        <p>A: Eliot H. Zuckerman, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that unless the proprietary lease or bylaws of a co-op contain unusual provisions, the board of directors generally has the right to make all decisions regarding the operation and maintenance of the co-op's property.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: Do co-op boards have the right to unilaterally make decisions such as cutting down trees without consulting other members of the co-op?  What recourse do I have? Can I take out an injunction? . . . Kathryn M. Mets, Forest Hills</p>
        <p>A: Eliot H. Zuckerman, a Manhattan co-op lawyer, said that unless the proprietary lease or bylaws of a co-op contain unusual provisions, the board of directors generally has the right to make all decisions regarding the operation and maintenance of the co-op's property.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman said that under what is known as the ''business judgment rule,'' decisions by boards will not be upset by the courts unless there is strong evidence that the board acted in a manner that it knew was not in the co-op's best interest.  As a result, he said, it is unlikely that a court would grant an injunction barring the removal of the trees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman pointed out that if a significant number of shareholders are opposed to cutting down the trees -- and make their feelings known to the board, preferably in writing -- it would behoove the board to take those feelings into account.  But at the same time, he said, the board has no legal obligation to change its decision, even if virtually all the shareholders want it to.</p>
        <p>''The shareholders could, of course, elect new directors,'' Mr. Zuckerman said, adding that most bylaws permit calling a special meeting for just that purpose if the meeting is requested by shareholders holding a certain percentage of the co-op's stock, typically 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Insuring a Co-op That Is Rented Out</p>
        <p>Q: I live in a co-op that my mother owns. I do not pay my mother rent, but I do pay the monthly maintenance. I carry renter's insurance on my furniture, electronics and personal items. Does my mother also need to carry any type of insurance on the co-op itself? . . . Anne Mosca, Farmingdale, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A: Andrew M. Schutzman, an insurance consultant in Rockville Centre, said that since your mother is the owner, she could be held liable for injuries or property damage sustained by a someone visiting the apartment. So, Mr. Schutzman said, your mother should have personal liability insurance on the apartment.</p>
        <p>''The simplest, and probably the most inexpensive method for the mother to be protected is to be named as an additional insured under the liability portion of the daughter's renter's policy,'' Mr. Schutzman said. Alternatively, he said, if your mother has personal liability coverage on another residence, either under a homeowner's policy or a renter's policy, the co-op could also be insured for liability coverage on the existing policy.</p>
        <p>''This may be the preferred method since it would provide the mother with separate liability coverage that is not shared with the daughter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another type of insurance your  mother might want to consider is coverage for improvements that have been made to the apartment.  Mr. Schutzman pointed out that since improvements are not considered personal property -- and would not be covered by the co-op corporation's policy -- it is generally wise for a shareholder to purchase such additional coverage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
