<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Habitats/West Village; From West Coast to East With Hardly a Hitch</title>
    <meta content="23HABI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000730T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Phil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Trish</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D61F3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Habitats/West Village; From West Coast to East With Hardly a Hitch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hall, Trish</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats column on how lawyer Phil Walker relocated from San Francisco to New York with little trouble, surprising himself by finding West Village apartment quickly on Internet; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR 19 years, Phil Walker had been working in San Francisco as a lawyer, defending companies against lawsuits filed by workers who claimed they had been injured on the job, either physically or psychologically. For a long time, he was fascinated by the stories they told, but finally, the job became repetitive and annoying. He wanted a change.</p>
        <p>He wasn't sure what he was going to do, but he thought that he'd like to live in New York and that if he started looking, he would probably find something after six or seven months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR 19 years, Phil Walker had been working in San Francisco as a lawyer, defending companies against lawsuits filed by workers who claimed they had been injured on the job, either physically or psychologically. For a long time, he was fascinated by the stories they told, but finally, the job became repetitive and annoying. He wanted a change.</p>
        <p>He wasn't sure what he was going to do, but he thought that he'd like to live in New York and that if he started looking, he would probably find something after six or seven months.</p>
        <p>But before he could get around to starting his job search, a friend who worked for Douglas Elliman, the New York real estate company, mentioned that it was looking for someone to be in charge of relocation services. Mr. Walker knew nothing about relocation -- or real estate, for that matter, after living in a rent-controlled apartment in San Francisco for 19 years. But since he was going to New York on business anyway, he figured he should interview at Douglas Elliman. What could he lose?</p>
        <p>''The interviews were fabulous,'' he said, ''and a week later, they hired me.'' His success in interviews is hardly surprising given that he is the host of a talk show in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The great appeal to Mr. Walker -- and apparently to Douglas Elliman -- was that he was an outsider with a fresh perspective on an increasingly competitive business. ''They realized it was time to really start bringing in people from other disciplines who could think about it in a completely different way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Suddenly and unexpectedly, he had a new job and a new career. The problem, of course, was that he was in San Francisco, the job was in New York, and he had to move fast. Knowing that New York was a tough place to find apartments, he made plans to live in a variety of temporary places for the first six weeks, trying out different neighborhoods. ''I told friends I had decided to make an adventure of this,'' he said. ''That's why I wasn't totally stressed out.''</p>
        <p>But in the end, he needed his room at the Vanderbilt Y.M.C.A. on East 47th Street for only a week. Strange as it may sound for a new real estate executive, he found his place not through a broker, but through the Internet.</p>
        <p>The weekend before he was moving to New York, anticipating a long search, he decided to sit down at the computer and type in ''gay roommates New York,'' because in San Francisco, he said, ''everyone does everything on the Internet.'' He wanted to find roommates as a way to build a social life in his new city (necessary, he said, because he knew ''only'' 41 people in New York at the time). As a gay man, he wanted to live with other gay men. ''I thought, it's one thing making friends when you're 25 years old,'' he said. ''It's different when you're 45. I wanted to hedge my bets.''</p>
        <p>His search led him immediately to a Web site, www.gayroommate.com, which asks a series of questions about the seeker's requirements, then, for $50, sends an e-mail list of prospective roommates and their phone numbers. That day, May 19, he called five that looked promising. One called back right away and said the spare room had been rented; three didn't respond; the fifth possibility arranged to meet with Mr. Walker two days later.</p>
        <p>After his ''transition party'' -- which was not a total farewell, because he kept that valuable rent-controlled apartment -- he left for New York.</p>
        <p>AT the appointed time, he found himself in an apartment in the West Village on 10th Street near Hudson, spread out on four levels, with the kitchen on the entry level, the available bedroom up a flight of stairs, the living room down a half flight, and below that, another bedroom and an office. ''The first thing I saw was a poster of 'Chorus Line,' '' he said. ''I thought, 'This is good.' '' He sat down with the two other men -- a couple -- who lived there, shared a bottle of wine, talked about their common love of the theater and decided it was a match.</p>
        <p>On June 1, eight days after starting his new job as the executive vice president for relocation services and corporate development, he moved in. His new roommates, he said, have been everything he hoped for, inviting him to join them in some of their social activities, making him part of their family. His roommates are just a few years younger than he is, a plus in his view. ''I didn't necessarily want to live with 20-year-olds,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sitting in the comfortable living room slightly above street level, which makes for a strangely absorbing and voyeuristic view of the passing pedestrians, just enough above the sidewalk to feel private, Mr. Walker said he hoped to use the experience of his own search to make real estate relocation easier at Douglas Elliman.</p>
        <p>His rent is $1,400 a month, not including utilities. Naturally, given his new job, he has already started looking for a place to buy. So far, he is most intrigued by Harlem, and by Battery Park City. In New York, he said, it's hard not to be interested in real estate. People here ''are completely obsessed with where everyone lives and how much they paid for it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''In San Francisco, when you meet people, they ask where you've been to eat,'' he went on. ''In New York, the first thing they ask is what you do, and the second thing is where you live.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker, who grew up in Florida and moved to San Francisco after law school ''on a whim,'' said he expects the Internet to become far more important in all kinds of real estate transactions: ''I think the computer is going to be used to explain the possibilities for people. What real estate brokers are going to sell is experience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker returns to San Francisco about once a month to tape his television talk show, ''Out and Beyond With Phil Walker,'' for a cable access channel. ''I'm the gay Oprah,'' he said. A cheerful and friendly man, he contends he was born to be a talk-show host, but he didn't discover that until one day about two years ago, when working as a lawyer was driving him crazy. ''I was about to throw myself off a building,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Instead, he went to one of those career counselors who give psychological tests and then suggest jobs that would be ideal. One of the top five recommendations for him was that he be a talk-show host. Fortunately for his new employer, another of the top five was marketing.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 30, 2000, Sunday  The Habitats column last Sunday, about an executive's move to New York, misidentified the Web site he used to find roommates. It was that of the Gay Roommate Information Network (http://home.earthlink.net/gayroommate/).</p>
        <p>(Gayroommate.com is the site of another service, Rainbow Roommates NYC.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 30, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Habitats column last Sunday, about an executive's move to New York, misidentified the Web site he used to find roommates. It was that of the Gay Roommate Information Network (http://home.earthlink.net/gayroommate/).</p>
        <p>(Gayroommate.com is the site of another service, Rainbow Roommates NYC.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
