<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And Bear In Mind</title>
    <meta content="23BEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDD173BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And Bear In Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>(Editors' choices of other recent books of particular interest)</p>
        <p>FREUD'S ''MEGALOMANIA,'' by Israel Rosenfield. (Norton, $21.95.) The author provides a fictional past and a fictional last book for Freud in this wonderfully contrived novel that evokes Freud's ambition as well as his self-deception.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>(Editors' choices of other recent books of particular interest)</p>
        <p>FREUD'S ''MEGALOMANIA,'' by Israel Rosenfield. (Norton, $21.95.) The author provides a fictional past and a fictional last book for Freud in this wonderfully contrived novel that evokes Freud's ambition as well as his self-deception.</p>
        <p>LIVING TO TELL, by Antonya Nelson. (Scribner, $24.) A whole family -- the Mabies of Wichita, Kan. -- is the protagonist of this novel of wry, obsessive self-observation, beginning with the return of a son from a prison sentence for killing his grandmother in a drunken car crash.</p>
        <p>THE NAME OF THE WORLD, by Denis Johnson. (HarperCollins, $22.) A sparely realized worldscape, from the Midwest to Iraq, zips by the protagonist of this novel, an academic who has lost his wife and child in a road accident and whose job prospects aren't so hot either.</p>
        <p>THE RIVER KING, by Alice Hoffman. (Putnam, $23.95.) Hoffman's 14th novel concerns the death by drowning of Gus Pierce, a freshman at the haughty Haddan School, and the efforts of a Haddan police officer to solve what appears to be a murder, with the convenient assistance of the deceased's ghost (the River King of the book's title).</p>
        <p>THE CHIEF: The Life of William Randolph Hearst, by David Nasaw. (Houghton Mifflin, $35.) An absorbing, scholarly biography showing Hearst as a larger, more talented, more generous and less dangerous figure than looms (with the help of Orson Welles and ''Citizen Kane'') in legend.</p>
        <p>ROADS: Driving America's Great Highways, by Larry McMurtry. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) This door sparingly opened on the private life of the author of 22 novels is an occasion for reminiscence and commentary on whatever pops up in the windows or in his mind as he crisscrosses the country: enigmatic glances at the Western past, salutes to hundreds of literary and historical figures.</p>
        <p>THE SOOTERKIN, by Tom Gilling. (Viking, $23.95.) A vigorous first novel, and a very nervy one; surely the first picaresque novel whose hero, Arthur Dyer, born in Van Diemen's Land (now Tasmania) in 1821, is wet, slippery, covered with fur and otherwise indistinguishable from a baby seal. His mother loves him, but others intend to exploit his entertainment value; a chase results, accompanied by debates about human nature and the like.</p>
        <p>LA GRANDE THERESE: The Greatest Scandal of the Century, by Hilary Spurling. (HarperCollins, $20.) Of the late 19th century, that is, when Therese Humbert rose from poverty to great wealth and influence by lying, cheating and swindling French investors for 20 years.</p>
        <p>THE SLEEP-OVER ARTIST, by Thomas Beller. (Norton, $23.95.) Not a novel so much as a set of interconnected short stories, this second collection by the author of ''Seduction Theory'' follows its hero, the narcissistic Alex Fader, from the age of 6, when he throws water on people from Upper West Side windows, to about 25, when he returns to the neighborhood having matured through exposure to pot, girls and a few grown-up complications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
