<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Big Idea About Money</title>
    <meta content="23HENRIQT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henriques, Diana B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gleeson, Jane</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Millionaire (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0D91F38F930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Big Idea About Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Diana B. Henriques</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henriques, Diana B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diana B Henriques reviews book Millionaire: The Philanderer, Gambler, and Duelist Who Invented Modern Finance by Jane Gleeson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Millionaire</p>
        <p>The Philanderer, Gambler, and Duelist Who Invented Modern Finance.</p>
        <p>By Janet Gleeson.</p>
        <p>303 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Millionaire</p>
        <p>The Philanderer, Gambler, and Duelist Who Invented Modern Finance.</p>
        <p>By Janet Gleeson.</p>
        <p>303 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
        <p>THE buzz surrounding the American publication of Janet Gleeson's book probably owes much to Regis Philbin. After all, the British edition of ''Millionaire,'' published last year, was called simply ''The Moneymaker.'' But that small editorial tweak+and the savvy marketing instincts behind it+speak volumes about just how drunk with dreams of instant wealth Americans are these days.</p>
        <p>And it is precisely that delirium -Who wants to read about a millionaire?' -- that makes this rollicking tale so captivating and potentially so instructive. John Law was a charismatic Scottish playboy with a flair for finance who wielded extraordinary influence in the French court in the early 1700's. No history of banking or finance is complete without some anecdotal account of the man who introduced the French both to paper currency and to the stock-market form of ''irrational exuberance.''</p>
        <p>The object of the mad desire was a banking and investment conglomerate that was supposed to enrich its shareholders by colonizing French territory in the vast Mississippi River basin. Frenzied speculation in the company's shares, a Gallic parallel of the South Sea Bubble that puffed up the British market over the same period, generated so much paper wealth in Paris that the French coined a word for the newly rich hordes: ''millionaire.''</p>
        <p>But, unfortunately for Law and the investors, few Frenchmen wanted to leave their Bordelais hamlets and Parisian slums for the distant, inhospitable wilderness. When the bubble burst in 1720, Law took many of the freshly minted millionaires down with him and reinforced the hard-money bias that the French bourgeoisie carried well into the 20th century. The company's collapse allowed the American government to acquire the territory later, in the Louisiana Purchase. (It is sobering to realize that but for John Law, folks would be speaking French in Little Rock.)</p>
        <p>This is not the first account of Law's life. Indeed, a biography was in print in 1824, less than a century after Law's death in 1729, and an account of the bubble was included in Charles Mackay's 1841 classic, ''Memoirs of Extraordinary Popular Delusions and the Madness of Crowds.'' Since then, everyone from John Kenneth Galbraith (in his 1975 book, ''Money: Whence It Came, Where It Went'') to James Buchan (in his quirky but elegant 1997 meditation, ''Frozen Desire: The Meaning of Money'') has described this enigmatic Scotsman's brief moment of fame.</p>
        <p>They have all built their stories from the same promising timber.+John Law was born in 1671, the pampered eldest son of a wealthy Edinburgh goldsmith. He came into his inheritance at the age of 12, developing over the next decade into a handsome but headstrong young lounge lizard who would have squandered his entire legacy at the gaming tables in London if his sensible mother had not rescued him. He came to his senses, after a fashion, continuing to gamble heavily but trying to reduce his risks by mastering and applying some early treatises on the laws of probability.</p>
        <p>His self-indulgent life as a minor-league ladies' man and major-league gambler in London came to a shocking end in 1694 when he killed a man in a duel, was convicted of murder and somehow cheated the hangman by escaping from prison. Gleeson deftly analyzes the arcane court rulings and political forces that beset Law's defense, and she offers a plausible explanation for Law's seemingly miraculous deliverance from his dungeon.</p>
        <p>Law made his way to the continent, gravitating toward Amsterdam and Italy, both fertile centers of financial innovation as well as attractive playpens for the idle rich who were his usual prey at the gaming tables. As early as 1609, the Bank of Amsterdam was receiving deposits of precious metal coins of all sorts and exchanging them for paper notes that could be used as legal tender in trade -- an important forerunner of today's paper currencies. Documentation is scarce, but Gleeson assumes that Law studied and embraced these revolutionary concepts during his travels.</p>
        <p>By 1697, as Gleeson tells it, Law had drifted to Paris, where he spent time ''in stylish salons mingling with the elite, gaining their confidence with his insinuating charm and impeccable manners before fleecing them at faro and basset, two of the most fashionable and high-rolling games of the day.'' The fleeced French apparently did not ban Law from their salons because he was simply so attractive -- tall, intelligent, supremely self-possessed and always elegantly in fashion.</p>
        <p>But just as he scandalized London society with his fatal swordplay, Law shocked the jaded Parisians too -- by eloping to Venice with another man's wife, Katherine Knowles Seigneur, who left her French husband and became Law's lifelong companion and the mother of his children.</p>
        <p>Gleeson's narrative lags a bit as she follows her hero back to Scotland, where his growing fascination with practical economics produced a 120-page pamphlet in 1705 called ''Money and Trade Considered With a Proposal for Supplying the Nation With Money,'' which called for the creation of a national bank that could issue paper currency backed by Scotland's supply of land. But his life and Gleeson's book surge into overdrive when Law returns to Paris a few years later and gradually attracts the attention, then the patronage, of Philippe, Duc d'Orleans, the French regent after the death of Louis XIV in 1715.</p>
        <p>Despite the successful Amsterdam bank and the fledgling Bank of England, the French were resistant to the notion of a national bank issuing paper currency at the whim of an absolute monarch. Law initially compromised with a private shareholder-owned bank. But he later sold the bank, and its subsidiary Mississippi venture, to the royal government, enriching shareholders (himself and the French regent among them) but ensuring that the bank's problems would be painfully shared by the crown. When disaster came, he narrowly escaped the gallows once again by fleeing France, leaving his adored wife and virtually all his once-dazzling wealth behind.</p>
        <p>''Millionaire'' does not throw much new light on Law's motivations, and the occasional forays into psychoanalysis are inconsistent and unpersuasive. Some historians may also argue that this account overstates Law's contributions to modern finance, given the more solid contributions of Amsterdam and British bankers. But Gleeson, whose book ''The Arcanum'' managed to infuse drama into the search for the industrial formula for porcelain, makes excellent use of this much more significant historic material. Her obvious passion for her story carries the reader along from crisis to crisis, and her eye for sensual detail allows her to recreate vividly the opulent world of French regency society, a world whose hunger for easy wealth and willingness to suspend common sense in pursuit of it emerges finally, chillingly, as very like our own.</p>
        <p>Diana B. Henriques is a financial reporter at The New York Times. Her most recent book is ''The White Sharks of Wall Street: Thomas Mellon Evans and the Original Corporate Raiders.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Diana B. Henriques is a financial reporter at The New York Times. Her most recent book is ''The White Sharks of Wall Street: Thomas Mellon Evans and the Original Corporate Raiders.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
