<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dylan's Still Going Strong With His Magic</title>
    <meta content="23DYLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grateful Dead (Band)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dylan, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lesh, Phil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DD163AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dylan's Still Going Strong With His Magic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robbie Woliver reviews concert at which Bob Dylan opened for former Grateful Dead bassist Phil Lesh in Camden, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOB DYLAN might represent something different to each fan, but it is what he means to the collective society that sets him apart. He has continually reinvented himself, and now that he tours so often, the audience sees a different Bob Dylan each time.</p>
        <p>In his current incarnation, he is the secure icon, willing to open for Phil Lesh, the former Grateful Dead bassist. Mr. Dylan is a businessman, and he knows that tapping into the Dead jam-band subculture will ensure him touring immortality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOB DYLAN might represent something different to each fan, but it is what he means to the collective society that sets him apart. He has continually reinvented himself, and now that he tours so often, the audience sees a different Bob Dylan each time.</p>
        <p>In his current incarnation, he is the secure icon, willing to open for Phil Lesh, the former Grateful Dead bassist. Mr. Dylan is a businessman, and he knows that tapping into the Dead jam-band subculture will ensure him touring immortality.</p>
        <p>But it is not all business, and aligning with a jam band is a natural course for this larger-than-life performer. Most contemporary music was influenced by Mr. Dylan, and jamming is at the heart of his musical being. His roots run deep -- whether jamming with the bluegrass-folkie Greenbriar Boys, the blues man John Lee Hooker, country music's Johnny Cash, Paul Butterfield's electric band or even with the Dead.</p>
        <p>In a 90-minute set, Mr. Dylan easily proves his genius as writer, musician and performer. Attending a Dylan performance is a surreal experience for those who appreciate his legacy. Although one is transported by his artistry, the pervading thought is, ''This is Bob Dylan!''</p>
        <p>This preeminent spokesman for a generation had humble beginnings. He was a self-taught musician inspired by diverse influences, especially rockers like Elvis Presley, Buddy Holly and Little Richard. Like a wizard concocting a magical brew, he added a dash of Hank Williams and a dose of the blues. He eventually obsessed on traditional folk singers like Woody Guthrie and Ramblin' Jack Elliot. Once Mr. Dylan moved east to New York's Greenwich Village in 1961, he became deeply immersed in folk music and its romantic accouterments. Culled from these influences, a new Bob Dylan was about to change the rules of popular music.</p>
        <p>His first albums presented a complex singer/songwriter/interpreter anchored in folk standards, protest music and powerful folk-oriented originals. In 1964, on ''Another Side of Bob Dylan,'' a transitional body of work was introduced; an appealing album with material so full of pop potential, it would quickly be gobbled up by other performers. Many 1960's folk-rock artists, from Peter Paul and Mary to Cher to the Turtles, recorded his songs, like ''All I Really Want To Do'' and ''It Ain't Me Babe.'' The more sophisticated ''My Back Pages,'' recorded by the Byrds, displayed intricate, lyrical poetry that was embraced by the psychedelic folk-rock crowd.</p>
        <p>Many of Mr. Dylan's early songs, like ''All I Really Want to Do,'' typified the structure he employed so masterfully: uncomplicated, engaging wit, structured around a simple melody and primitively strummed rhythm. Using several rhyming schemes, his great sense of fun is often evidenced by a chorus's yodel or mid-song laugh. Many of his songs in this period catalogued grievances, aspirations and musings.</p>
        <p>Other early songs, like ''Spanish Harlem Incident,'' were precursors of the descriptive, textured lyricism found decades later in albums like 1976's ''Desire.'' Sung with abandon, these songs featured the poet's quicksilver phrasing and exotic narrative style. Classic recordings from ''Bringing It All Back Home'' and ''Highway 61 Revisited'' to ''Blonde on Blonde'' and ''Blood on the Tracks'' had countless devotees scouring and studying every word, image and symbol in the lyrics.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Dylan moved away from the Woody Guthrie-clone image, he continued to include musical styles that influenced him, as witnessed by his many talking-blues songs. And he remained the generation's social conscience. Many of his political songs revealed his passion for mankind, and an ability to effectively execute a difficult style (political folk). His songs dripped in metaphor, persuasive in their passion and politics. But he was also funny and self-deprecating (''Yipee! I'm a poet, and I know it, hope I don't blow it'').</p>
        <p>Although his vocals are far from subtle, his songs brim with accessibility; flowing cadences, metaphorical fearlessness, and control of both the message and the form. He was criticized at times for his caricature-like vocals and Beat, anarchistically-constructed lyrics. But unlike many of his peers, he and his music have survived.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, Mr. Dylan writes simpler songs, and as he experiments (gospel, blues, stark folk, raging rock) he becomes more a part of the communal culture.</p>
        <p>At 59, Mr. Dylan has remade himself as a jam-band leader, and he seems to be enjoying himself. Decades ago, before the weight of the world was on his celebrity shoulders, there was a kick in his step, and it has returned. Sometimes acting like Charlie Chaplin, sometimes as hip and cool skinny Elvis, other times he could easily be a Rolling Stone.</p>
        <p>In concert, Mr. Dylan's band is tight yet impromptu, always finding a taut groove in the guitar jams, which embellish almost every song. And Mr. Dylan, again, displays his virtuosity whether it is through blues, rock, country, jazz or Tex-Mex.</p>
        <p>The band begins with a long acoustic set, starting with Leadbelly's ''Duncan and Brady'' and moves on to a low-key ''The Times They Are A-Changin'.'' ''It's All Over Now, Baby Blue,'' enjoys a little vocal play on its choruses, but it is not until ''Tangled Up in Blue,'' where the hypnotic rhythms and slowed-down groove begin to build.</p>
        <p>The electric set also joggles the memory: ''If Not for You,'' a Byrds-y ''Like a Rolling Stone,'' a boogie version of ''Highway 61 Revisited,'' ''Country Pie'' served up as a torpid country shuffle, and a greasy roadhouse-blues version of ''Leopard-Skin Pill-Box Hat.'' In the past he has treated audiences to ''Just Like Tom Thumb's Blues,'' ''Love Minus Zero/No Limit.'' ''Positively Fourth Street,'' ''Like a Rolling Stone,'' a subdued ''A Hard Rain's A-Gonna Fall'' and ''Rainy Day Women No. 12 &amp; 35'' (and with lyrics like ''Everybody must get stoned,'' one would think it a must for the Deadhead crowd). But remember, this is the mercurial Mr. Dylan, and the show could end up with him performing songs exclusively from ''Nashville Skyline.''</p>
        <p>It is difficult to comprehend the impact of Mr. Dylan's songs. He spoke for a generation, and through his eternal and definitive repertory, he still connects with listeners, from baby-boomers to their grandchildren.</p>
        <p>BOB DYLAN AND PHIL LESH</p>
        <p>Blockbuster Sony Entertainment Center, Harbour Boulevard, Camden.  Friday at 7 p.m., (856) 365-1300.  Waterloo Village, 525 Waterloo Road, Stanhope.  Next Sunday at 8 p.m., (973) 347-0900.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
