<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great American Novel, on Dime Store Paper</title>
    <meta content="23MAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fitzgerald, F Scott (1896-1940)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fitzgerald, Zelda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skemer, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDF1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great American Novel, on Dime Store Paper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Don Skemer, curator of manuscripts at Princeton University Library Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, answers questions on Firestone Library's archive of manuscripts and correspondence of F Scott Fitzgerald and wife, Zelda; Firestone is one of first recipients of Save Our National Treasures grant from National Park Service; photo (On the Map column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Firestone Library at Princeton University is the archive of the manuscripts and correspondence of F. Scott Fitzgerald. The library also has other collections relating to the writer, including his personal library; the manuscripts of his wife, Zelda, and her correspondence with Fitzgerald; and the archives of Charles Scribner's Sons (including the correspondence between Fitzgerald and his editor, Maxwell Perkins). Fitzgerald attended Princeton but left in 1917 to join the Army. Recently, the library became one of the first recipients of a Save Our National Treasures grant from the National Park Service to preserve and restore about 30,000 items written in Fitzgerald's hand. Don C. Skemer, curator of manuscripts, Princeton University Library Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, Library, spoke about the collection..</p>
        <p>Q. How do you preserve these papers?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Firestone Library at Princeton University is the archive of the manuscripts and correspondence of F. Scott Fitzgerald. The library also has other collections relating to the writer, including his personal library; the manuscripts of his wife, Zelda, and her correspondence with Fitzgerald; and the archives of Charles Scribner's Sons (including the correspondence between Fitzgerald and his editor, Maxwell Perkins). Fitzgerald attended Princeton but left in 1917 to join the Army. Recently, the library became one of the first recipients of a Save Our National Treasures grant from the National Park Service to preserve and restore about 30,000 items written in Fitzgerald's hand. Don C. Skemer, curator of manuscripts, Princeton University Library Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, Library, spoke about the collection..</p>
        <p>Q. How do you preserve these papers?</p>
        <p>A. By de-acidfying the paper. Fitzgerald didn't always use the best papers. When things were going badly he would go to Woolworth's and buy a note pad. To deacidify something you spray a chemical solution that neutralizes the acidity and leaves an alkaline residue. This has been a heavily used archive for a half-century. Papers get damaged, the corners turned and there are little tears that have to be mended.  We do that with heat-set tissue. The papers will be put in Mylar sleeves and re-boxed.</p>
        <p>Q. How long will the project take?  A. Eighteen months. We started two months ago. We are working our way through the manuscripts now. We just finished ''Tender is the Night.''  Currently we're working on ''This Side of Paradise,'' much of which takes place in New Jersey.  Q. What do his manuscripts look like?  A. He wrote by hand, generally in pencil. The short stores and his articles for magazines were typed. He wrote 250 articles in The Saturday Evening Post.  Q. Who donated his papers?  A. Everything that he left was donated by his daughter, Scottie Fitzgerald Lanahan. The Zelda Sayre Fitzgerald Papers arrived with his.  We have more of her letters to him because she died in a fire and many of her papers were lost.  Q. Do you still get items for the collection?  A. Not long ago we got a fascinating letter in which Fitzgerald wrote a poem for his commanding officer in the Army, John J. Mathieson in 1918. The officer asked him to write a poem to his fiancee, Mildred McNally. Her nickname was Mid. It was a four-page poem in the form of a letter. It began, ''Dear Mid or Midsummer or Midnight, Perhaps in the cool of the evening, twist mess calls or taps.''  Q. Can anybody use the collection?  A. You have to be engaged in research. It can't be just, ''I love Fitzgerald and I just want to see one of his manuscripts and hold it.'' Even the researchers have to use microfilm to see it.  Q. What can the general public see that belonged to Fitzgerald if they visit the library?  A.  Through the end of September, in the Firestone Library Exhibition Gallery, we are displaying the recently conserved original autograph [hand-written] manuscript of ''The Great Gatsby.''  Q. You have so many collections in your library. How do the Fitzgerald papers fit in?  A. Fitzgerald is a special case. He's an icon. That's why the papers are a national treasure. When you consider in the American mind what is the greatest American novel, it's ''The Great Gatsby.''</p>
        <p>MARGO NASH</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
