<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 7-23-00: Counter Culture; Promotion of the Fittest</title>
    <meta content="WLN110512" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6D6113BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 7-23-00: Counter Culture; Promotion of the Fittest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Sullivan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Sullivan article rejects the arguments against genetic testing by employers and health insurers, who presumably would discriminate against people on the basis of their DNA; says that while the point of laws against racial bias is to outlaw irrational discrimination based on irrelevant characteristics, barring genetic discrimination would be outlawing rational bias based on relevant information; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When you first think about it, it's a no-brainer. When the final stages of mapping the human genome were hyped last month, both President Bill Clinton and Prime Minister Tony Blair called for a swift, extensive ban on using genetic information to discriminate in employment or insurance. Clinton had already signed an executive order back in February, banning such discrimination for federal employees. True to form, both politicians had polling data to support them. A 1998 survey of 1,000 randomly selected Americans found that 63 percent of them balked at any genetic testing if an employer or health insurer could have access to the data. So a ban on genetic discrimination not only secures privacy and fairness; it also protects good research by reassuring study volunteers that the information they provide is in completely safe hands.</p>
        <p>What's not to like? Well, quite a lot, actually. Like most notions that command almost universal assent, the proposed ban on genetic discrimination makes far less sense the more you think about it. A few brave souls, like the writer Michael Kinsley, have pointed this out, but even he admitted that he wasn't sure what conclusion to draw. So here goes: genetic discrimination, however troubling, is both rational and inevitable. And the sooner we get over our hand-wringing, the better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When you first think about it, it's a no-brainer. When the final stages of mapping the human genome were hyped last month, both President Bill Clinton and Prime Minister Tony Blair called for a swift, extensive ban on using genetic information to discriminate in employment or insurance. Clinton had already signed an executive order back in February, banning such discrimination for federal employees. True to form, both politicians had polling data to support them. A 1998 survey of 1,000 randomly selected Americans found that 63 percent of them balked at any genetic testing if an employer or health insurer could have access to the data. So a ban on genetic discrimination not only secures privacy and fairness; it also protects good research by reassuring study volunteers that the information they provide is in completely safe hands.</p>
        <p>What's not to like? Well, quite a lot, actually. Like most notions that command almost universal assent, the proposed ban on genetic discrimination makes far less sense the more you think about it. A few brave souls, like the writer Michael Kinsley, have pointed this out, but even he admitted that he wasn't sure what conclusion to draw. So here goes: genetic discrimination, however troubling, is both rational and inevitable. And the sooner we get over our hand-wringing, the better.</p>
        <p>Start with the analogy to racial discrimination. It's bogus. The point of laws against racial bias is to outlaw irrational discrimination based on irrelevant characteristics. The point of laws against genetic discrimination is to outlaw rational bias based on relevant information. The two principles aren't merely different; they're opposite. We perform individual, rational acts of discrimination all the time. In fact, it would be hard to function without them. Deciding not to put an art historian in charge of a nuclear power plant is not bias but common sense. Similarly, discriminating against a blind person when hiring a baseball umpire is certainly not a function of hostility to blind people in general and wouldn't even be illegal under the Americans with Disabilities Act. Sure, it's discrimination -- but it's rational discrimination and is not, and shouldn't be, illegal. So why should genetic discrimination?</p>
        <p>The best answer to this is that most genetic information is speculative. It doesn't tell you what a person is; it tells you what she may be. Right now, it could tell an employer that a job applicant might have a propensity for heart trouble in the future, or for Parkinson's disease. Within the foreseeable future, it might even reveal that a person's genetic spatial skills are particularly good or that her verbal fluency is genetically high. But it won't tell you what a person has actually made of her natural gifts or whether she might be lucky and avoid certain likely genetic fates. It might tell you that a person has the genes to make a fine pianist, but it won't tell you if he has practiced or even knows how to read music.</p>
        <p>Clinton's executive order rested on this distinction. It bans the use of genetic testing to determine if a person has a propensity for being bad at a certain job or for having a specific physical ailment in the future, but it allows such testing to see if a person has an actual existing condition that makes him less able to perform a certain task. So it's O.K. to test if a fighter pilot has a genetic condition that makes him liable now to have a sudden heart attack on the job; but it's not O.K. to test him to see if his genes suggest that he could develop Alzheimer's in preretirement years.</p>
        <p>I get the distinction. I just don't see the ethical difference between using genes to hazard future performance and using other means to do so. After all, we already use countless ways of discriminating rationally on the basis of the likelihood of future ability. What else is an SAT score, if not an attempt to predict future performance? Or a garden-variety letter of recommendation? What are these but predictors exactly analogous to genetic testing -- not destiny as such, but pretty reliable guides? The real question, then, is, Why should imprecise and often dangerous predictors (like SAT results) be morally acceptable but more precise methods (like genes) be morally repugnant? If anything, genetic testing for future capacities is less objectionable because it's more reliable.</p>
        <p>Most of our current worries stem, of course, from insurance. What's to prevent insurers, we fret, from demanding genetic tests to see if someone is more likely to have breast cancer or heart disease than another random person? The result could be the end of insurance pools as we know them. But it's worth noting one thing. Genetic testing is not a reversal of the principle behind insurance; it's just an elaboration of it. All insurance is about predicting the future based on imperfect knowledge of the present. The point of genetic testing is to give us a better idea of the present and future. Young single males, for example, have a harder time getting car insurance than married middle-age women. We accept this principle as a recognition of reality. But why is it less objectionable than testing individuals for a genetic predisposition to high blood pressure? At least that doesn't extrapolate from a general population to an individual.</p>
        <p>What's happening is that the veil of ignorance that once covered our inner lives is wearing increasingly thin. The change will thrill and dismay us, whatever our politics. It seems to me, to take one obvious consequence, that socialized medicine is now all but inevitable. It's inevitable not because it's inherently better than an insurance-based system. It almost certainly isn't. It's inevitable because the ignorance on which an insurance-based system necessarily rests is slowly disappearing. We'll either have to force insurers to ignore glaring, easily obtainable facts relevant to their business -- and see the numbers of private entrepreneurs prepared to enter the market gradually shrink -- or we'll have to make it illegal for individuals with great genetic results to use and market that information to insurers for cheaper coverage. Eventually, as the writer Clive Crook has argued, the private sector will either be so expensive it will be beyond most of our reach or so regulated it will look like a public system anyway. In the long run, only the government will be dumb enough or enlightened enough to mandate a national insurance pool that works.</p>
        <p>Simply ban all genetic testing of any kind? That would mean losing a historic chance to cure countless diseases and develop unique health strategies for individuals who will want them. Prevent employers and governments from testing? Sure, but what do you do when private individuals get their own tests done and then bring them to job interviews? How do you practically stop an employer from being influenced by that information in a free society? And if some employers are high-minded enough to keep their eyes shut in a fiercely competitive market, others will realize that ignorance is too costly a financial risk to bear.</p>
        <p>The twists won't end there. As the potential for rational discrimination grows, the space for old-fashioned bias may shrink. Men and women will increasingly be judged not by the color of their skin but by the content of their chromosomes. The irrational cruelty of bias will be replaced by the rational cruelty of fate. In retrospect, we may miss the evils we could do something about.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
