<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Band of Angels</title>
    <meta content="23DONALDT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donald, David Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dark Midnight When I Rise (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D91F38F930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Band of Angels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Herbert Donald</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donald, David Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Herbert Donald reviews book Dark Midnight When I Rise: The Story of the Jubilee Singers Who Introduced the World to the Music of Black America by Andrew Ward (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DARK MIDNIGHT WHEN I RISE</p>
        <p>The Story of the Jubilee Singers Who Introduced the World to the Music of Black America.</p>
        <p>By Andrew Ward.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 493 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DARK MIDNIGHT WHEN I RISE</p>
        <p>The Story of the Jubilee Singers Who Introduced the World to the Music of Black America.</p>
        <p>By Andrew Ward.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 493 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.</p>
        <p>IN the late 1860's, students in Nashville enrolled in the struggling school for former slaves that would become Fisk University discovered, buried on the school's grounds, heaps of chains and manacles from Porter's Slave Yard, which had occupied the site before the Civil War. They sold these rusted relics of their bondage as scrap iron and used the proceeds to buy Bibles and spellers. Thus, Andrew Ward writes, they transformed ''the instruments of their enslavement into the agencies of their liberation.''</p>
        <p>That alchemy was characteristic of the early days of the struggling university, which was always on the verge of bankruptcy. The best example of the magic that saved Fisk was the transformation of an untrained student chorus into a magnificent singing group that raised more than $150,000 -- more than $2.5 million in today's dollars -- and kept the university afloat.</p>
        <p>''Dark Midnight When I Rise'' details the history of the Fisk Jubilee Singers. Based on careful research in the Fisk University archives and in the papers of the American Missionary Association, which sponsored the college, the book tells how the little troupe of less than a dozen young black singers, accompanied by their amateur choirmaster, George Leonard White, braved racism, indifference and hostility to bring their songs, and their pleas for support of their university, to thousands in the North and in Europe.</p>
        <p>When the Jubilee Singers began their work, most Americans thought of black music in terms of blackfaced minstrel troupes, with their racist jokes about the antics of a primitive people. Initially audiences did not know how to respond to the deeply religious spirituals of the Fisk singers. But Henry Ward Beecher, the most popular preacher in the United States, featured them at his Plymouth Church in Brooklyn and urged members of his congregation to give them money: ''Folks can't live on air. Though they sing like nightingales, they need more to eat than nightingales do.'' The group caught on and soon had engagements in all the major Northern cities. In Washington, they sang before a huge audience that included ambassadors, justices of the Supreme Court, clergymen, members of the cabinet and the vice president, and the next day they gave a private concert for President Ulysses S. Grant. ''We have conquered,'' White exulted. Within months ''the Jubilees'' -- as they were called everywhere -- had raised enough money to pay off the debt under which their college had been laboring, and by the end of the year the group deposited $14,000 in a building fund for a magnificent new stone structure that would be called Jubilee Hall.</p>
        <p>Encouraged by their success, university officials soon sent the singers back on the road again, this time to raise $45,000 more to complete Jubilee Hall. After ''farewell concerts'' in Newark, New York, Brooklyn, Providence and Boston, they sailed in April 1873 for England. Sponsored by the Earl of Shaftesbury, the 11 singers gained entree to the great houses of England and Scotland. Prime Minister William E. Gladstone invited them to perform at Carlton House before the Prince and Princess of Wales and, as Gladstone said, ''all manner of notabilities.'' At Argyll Lodge they met Queen Victoria herself, whose blessing opened all doors to them. Within days they were overwhelmed by invitations to perform. At Charles Haddon Spurgeon's vast Metropolitan Tabernacle they sang before an audience of nearly 7,000, the largest crowd they had ever drawn. Their British tour raised</p>
        <p>David Herbert Donald's ''Lincoln at Home'' will be published in the fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Herbert Donald's ''Lincoln at Home'' will be published in the fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
