<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Mysterious Mr. Love' Staged at the Emelin</title>
    <meta content="23THEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brancato, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Brent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Ann</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mysterious Mr Love, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DD1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Mysterious Mr. Love' Staged at the Emelin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Karoline Leach play The Mysterious Mr Love, directed by Joe Brancato and starring Brent Harris and Ann Dowd, at Emelin Theater in Mamaroneck, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE'S a dapper man, a ladies man, a self-described con man with a heart of gold. And the greatest con in the world, he says, is love.</p>
        <p>His name is Mr. Love, George Love, and he always travels first class.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE'S a dapper man, a ladies man, a self-described con man with a heart of gold. And the greatest con in the world, he says, is love.</p>
        <p>His name is Mr. Love, George Love, and he always travels first class.</p>
        <p>She is self-effacing, very plain, the strictly steerage type no one notices. On her job, sewing hats, she is cast off, with the other women of drabness, to the back room ''where the customers can't see us.'' All she's good for, she says, is ''making hats and eating biscuits.''</p>
        <p>Her name is Adelaide Pinchin. She thinks that she is ''too fat to be seen'' and that she has an eating disorder; it's not just biscuits. In truth, Adelaide is not even overweight. But she's drab all right.</p>
        <p>For contrast, she always wears a gold pin, and you can bet Mr. Love notices that. Indeed, it is the little something too expensive, too new, too nice for that face that Mr. Love looks for in his plain, drab victims. It is a sign that they have ''a few quid stashed away.''</p>
        <p>Although Karoline Leach sets up her two-character play, ''The Mysterious Mr. Love,'' at the Emelin Theater here in stock narrative manner, a larger purpose evolves. The dramaturgy is pedestrian; the devices of the genre (melodramatic, romantic, psychological thriller and all that), transparent, the story, set in 1910, schematic.</p>
        <p>But in its turns and its reach, ''The Mysterious Mr. Love'' is oddly involving, and there is a real payoff that invites speculation. This is the sort of play one should talk about on the way home. Good talk, that is: considerations of honor and truth in an unwelcoming world.</p>
        <p>In the beginning, it all promises little. Adelaide tells the audience, ''He looked at me.'' George then says, ''She smiled.'' It's Adelaide's turn: ''He smiled back.'' No surprise; she falls for his guile, deceit and treachery, and it isn't long before she shows him just where the few quid is hid.</p>
        <p>During an attenuated, slow plot, which involves Adelaide's uninteresting father fixation, the interplay  between Love and Pinchin, both symbolically surnamed, is predictable and implausible. Still, the actors are plausibly what -- and later, who -- they are programmed to be.</p>
        <p>Luckily, the director, Joe Brancato, grasps nuance and contradiction in human behavior, and he knows how to get it out of actors. These two arrive at moving moments of contact.</p>
        <p>Brent Harris is sartorially in place, economizing on oily charm. He not only gives needless stage directions obediently well but he also lives up to the specifications the audience does not hear. He is ''assured, attractive,'' not only worthy of being a Mr. Love but a mysterious one as well. Ann Dowd's Adelaide is tentative and wounded, measurably enough to convey desperation, delusions, susceptibility and repression.</p>
        <p>The real test for the actors is in their subtle shifts. Not all the play's reversals are pat. Ms. Dowd travels to assertiveness; she's on to the cad. Mr. Harris exposes nerve endings. Possibilities emerge: salvation for Adelaide, redemption for George.</p>
        <p>''The Mysterious Mr. Love'' is a small play with big ideas, unashamedly wearing its flaws with an open heart. The audience is in for a ride; destination: surprise.</p>
        <p>And the audience for ''The Mysterious Mr. Love'' is to increase by virtue of an alliance between two professional theaters. After the run at the Emelin ends tonight, the play moves to Penguin Rep in Stony Point in Rockland County, where Mr. Brancato is artistic director. Such arrangements prolong the life of a production and enlighten audiences about what is going on in the New York metropolitan region. One hopes it will happen more frequently, especially since the Emelin, essentially a booking and presenting house, has had a hard time developing an artistic vision of theater and programming it consistently, not that various managements haven't tried.</p>
        <p>An artistic risk like ''Mr. Love'' -- an unfamiliar work, produced in London in 1997 -- is a test case, an important positive act for the Emelin and for theater in Westchester.</p>
        <p>''The Mysterious Mr. Love'' at the Emelin Theater, 153 Library Lane, Mamaroneck. Performances today at 2 and 7 p. m. Box office: (914)  698-3045. Moving to Penguin Repertory at the Barn Theater on Crickettown Road, Stony Point. Performances from Aug. 3 through 27. Box office: (845) 786-2873.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
