<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking Infants Onto the Plane</title>
    <meta content="23PRAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DD133BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking Infants Onto the Plane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Betsy Wade Practical Traveler column offers advice from experts on traveling by plane with newborn babies in light of recent report in British medical journal depicting perils to the very young; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DR. PHILIP FISCHER, a specialist in pediatric and adolescent medicine at the Mayo Clinic in Minnesota, believes there is no age at which an infant is automatically too young to travel by air. He and some of his colleagues  take issue with a report in a British medical journal depicting perils to the very young in flight.</p>
        <p>The issue arose last month when Edward Lister, owner of the Travel Medicine Clinic in Rancho Mirage, Calif., a nurse belonging to the International Society of Travel Medicine,  asked the members' e-mail forum if there was any reason not to let a family take a 3-week-old infant on a 2,000-mile air trip to visit relatives. Plentiful dialogue followed, with almost all the medical experts supporting Dr. Fischer, a leader in the field of children's travel, in his statement: ''I would personally not restrict air travel because of a child's age.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DR. PHILIP FISCHER, a specialist in pediatric and adolescent medicine at the Mayo Clinic in Minnesota, believes there is no age at which an infant is automatically too young to travel by air. He and some of his colleagues  take issue with a report in a British medical journal depicting perils to the very young in flight.</p>
        <p>The issue arose last month when Edward Lister, owner of the Travel Medicine Clinic in Rancho Mirage, Calif., a nurse belonging to the International Society of Travel Medicine,  asked the members' e-mail forum if there was any reason not to let a family take a 3-week-old infant on a 2,000-mile air trip to visit relatives. Plentiful dialogue followed, with almost all the medical experts supporting Dr. Fischer, a leader in the field of children's travel, in his statement: ''I would personally not restrict air travel because of a child's age.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fischer had one caveat. ''A 2,000-mile air trip probably involves a big transition and some physical challenges for a postpartum mother and for a family adjusting to a new baby,'' he said. ''I would hope the scheduled itinerary is appropriate for all involved.'' Dr. Sheila Mackell of Oakland, Calif., a pediatrician and  member of the society, said she likewise asked patients whether they were ready for such a journey.</p>
        <p>A Need to Hurry Home</p>
        <p>In the travel medicine dialogue, many experts pointed out reasons that parents often undertook long air journeys with newborns: the family may prefer to have the delivery someplace other than where they live, or, commonly these days, the family may have adopted a baby in another state, or another country, and want to hurry home and settle in.</p>
        <p>Dr. David R. Shlim, a specialist in high-mountain illness and traveler's diarrhea, who has a clinic in Jackson Hole, Wyo., said: ''Many women who live in a developing country will leave that country in the last month of pregnancy in order to deliver in a safer environment. Often they have to leave their spouses behind and even children who might be in school.</p>
        <p>''They are understandably anxious to get back to their life in Nepal, or India, or Africa, as soon as possible after delivery. It is this group that is most likely to want to travel with a newborn baby. We flew home to Nepal from Bangkok with our first child when he was 8 days old.''</p>
        <p>Gail Rosselot, a nurse practitioner and public health expert who directs a clinic in Briarcliff Manor, N.Y., and her husband took their adoptive daughter on an air trip when she was 9 days old. The couple flew to California to meet her when she was 2 days old, then flew to Houston and on to San Antonio to complete adoption formalities before returning to New York through Houston.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosselot said that on her trip, Continental Airlines asked her how old the baby was, but said that 9 days was old enough and let her board. Clients of her clinic now tell her they have received conflicting information from an airline on the phone and then at the boarding gate, and sometimes aboard, and have met varying rules when they took connecting flights from California to Texas and home to New York.</p>
        <p>'Yellow Book' Warning</p>
        <p>Among the sparse material published on the subject is a notation in Health Information for International Travel 1999-2000, the ''yellow book,'' published by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Under ''Air Travel During Pregnancy,'' there is this: ''Women traveling with infants should keep in mind that newborns under 6 weeks old should not fly because their alveoli are not completely functional.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Phyllis E. Kozarsky of the Emory University Travel Clinic in Atlanta, who helped write this guideline, said that the 6-week age limit represented a theoretical consensus ''since there are really no firm data to support or refute.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mackell in Oakland characterized as inconclusive a report published in the British Medical Journal in 1998 saying that infants who traveled by air were more likely to be victims of Sudden Infant Death Syndrome. She said that this study had raised wide concern in the travel-medicine community.</p>
        <p>She and Dr. Kozarsky both said, however, that when an infant was involved they usually asked ''is this trip necessary.'' Dr. Kozarsky said: ''Occasionally we see adoptive parents who will be traveling to pick up their babies from overseas or even within the country and wish to bring the child home as soon as possible, and thus the question arises. If there is no urgency, however, one might be a bit more conservative.''</p>
        <p>On the issue of transmitting infections, Dr. Mackell said that the air in planes was perfectly good but that the passenger sitting next to the baby might be carrying something, and long proximity could be a problem. One participant in the dialogue, Dr. Alison Clough of the Travel and Geographic Medicine Clinic in Tucson, Ariz., a family doctor, said that studies had shown airline air to be quite clean and she believed that most post-air-travel colds and flu she had seen were picked up in airports and restaurants.</p>
        <p>Age Rules Differ</p>
        <p>Of seven major domestic airlines, three are concerned with minimum passenger age. Continental will not accept a child who is under 7 days old, according to Julie Gardner, a spokeswoman. United, according to Chris Nardella, a spokeswoman, wants a doctor's letter saying a child under the age of 7 days is able to fly. If American Airlines is asked the question, according to John Hotard, a spokesman, it replies that it does not accept infants under 3 days of age. But he said: ''If someone arrives with a baby in a bassinet, our agent is not going to say, 'Excuse me, ma'am, may I inspect your baby?' ''</p>
        <p>Trans World Airlines, US Airways, Delta and Northwest Airlines report no restrictions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Karl Neumann of Queens, a travel-medicine expert who specializes in pediatrics, had a few suggestions for parents taking infants -- or young children -- on planes. First, he said, parents are sometimes told their children need copious liquids in flight, and this is not the case. ''It just gives them a stomachache,'' he said. However, he said, the swallowing involved in breast-feeding or taking a bottle will often relieve earache in ascent and descent.</p>
        <p>''Lap children,'' that is children under the age of 2, can travel free domestically, but the experts said these babies traveled most safely in a rear-facing child seat strapped into an airline seat. This means buying a ticket for the child.</p>
        <p>In April, Northwest instituted a ''special delivery'' fare for parents going overseas to adopt a child. In company with KLM, it has a reduced fare to 100 destinations the lines serve in Asia, Africa, Europe, India and the Middle East. Information may be found on the Northwest Web site at www.nwa.com. Enter ''adoption fare'' in the inquiry box. For special services: (800) 322-4162.</p>
        <p>British Airways created special adoption fares in April. These too provide a 65 percent discount on the full economy fare from 21 United States cities to any point on the line's main routes. The line does not have a minimum age for passengers, according to John W. Lampl, its spokesman. Information: (800) 247-9297.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
