<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater of the Absurd</title>
    <meta content="23ROCKWET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockwell, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alexander, Jane</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Command Performance (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D91F38F930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater of the Absurd</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Rockwell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rockwell, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Rockwell reviews book Command Performance: An Actress in the Theater of Politics by Jane Alexander; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Command Performance</p>
        <p>An Actress in the Theater of Politics.</p>
        <p>By Jane Alexander.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 335 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>PublicAffairs. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Command Performance</p>
        <p>An Actress in the Theater of Politics.</p>
        <p>By Jane Alexander.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 335 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>PublicAffairs. $25.</p>
        <p>Jane Alexander, the actress who was chairwoman of the National Endowment for the Arts from 1993 to 1997, has written a memoir of her term there, and an earnest, nave and dispiriting document it is. Not dispiriting because Alexander failed to fight a good fight; by her own lights, the simple fact that the endowment was not eliminated under her watch, just further crippled, constitutes a triumph. The true cause for despair is her picture of the blind and deaf philistinism of American politicians.</p>
        <p>Alexander, a warmhearted liberal from the 1960's, was tapped by the Clinton administration early on. The first working artist to assume the position, she was bright, personable, famous and well-groomed enough (or so it was hoped) to disarm her opponents. Beaming with idealism, an amusingly self-styled ''Jane of Art,'' she wooed her way to a triumphant Senate confirmation that nearly everyone, on all sides of the culture wars, applauded.</p>
        <p>At first, while she had her troubles with Republican and conservative Democratic opponents, she seemed to be making headway. After the Republican sweep of Congress in 1994, her job became a war of attrition. She won in that the agency survived, but her hair turned white and she chose to leave at the expiration of her first four-year term.</p>
        <p>The interest in ''Command Performance'' lies in its anecdotal descriptions of friends and foes: of Strom Thurmond and her hero, Teddy Kennedy, and Jesse Helms and Orrin Hatch and Nancy Kassebaum and a West Texas congressman named Charles Stenholm, leader of the 25 ''blue dog'' Democrats, described as moderate Westerners who were so inundated with hate mail from the Christian right, and so reflexively anti-gay, that they could not see the endowment as anything but a nest of homosexuals.</p>
        <p>For the salvation of her soul, or at least her conscience, Alexander gradually lets her anger break through her veil of well-mannered deference and tactical discretion. She admits to despising the crude, not to say nakedly hostile, disdain for the arts in our nation's capital. The charming but elusive President Clinton essentially ignored the issue, concerned about keeping the endowment out of the news and delegating arts matters to his wife. Alexander rightly complains that Newt Gingrich would not make an appointment to meet with her, but neither would Clinton, for months on end. Yet the President never entirely deserted her, because for him the endowment was as potent a symbol as it was for the right.</p>
        <p>Alexander's principal animus is toward the generally debased level of discourse in Congress and the Gingrich Republicans, stubbornly intent on subverting the best interests of their constituents and their own beloved local arts institutions in favor of ideological purity and party loyalty. Tom DeLay's ''brain could fit in an eggcup as far as I could tell.'' ''I was extremely angry with Congress. I felt contempt for many of the members and despair over the level to which our federal government had sunk.''</p>
        <p>Peter Hoekstra, a Republican representative from Michigan who chaired a key subcommittee, practiced ''harassment pure and simple,'' Alexander writes. ''His tactics were scurrilous and his aide Derrick Max was rude and underhanded.''</p>
        <p>''It is hard to know what a politician believes anymore because he is so beholden to the special interests of those who elected him,'' she adds. ''The system is so corrupt that it may not ever be fixed.'' No wonder she's happy to be back on stage.</p>
        <p>The title, subtitle and chapter headings of Alexander's memoir suggest that she never quite left. Other than a proper Massachusetts upbringing, what seems to have enabled her to maintain her ladylike equanimity was her ability to distance herself from her role, to see the chairmanship as another part in a play that unfortunately lacked the comforting grounding of a good script. But one could argue that such distancing limited her effectiveness as an infighter.</p>
        <p>She could enjoy her own modest initiatives and small victories. She traveled to all 50 states and enjoyed what she saw there. She treasured her few friendships on Capitol Hill. She rested content in her simple belief that art is good and the more people it reaches, the better. She assayed some controversial reorganizations of the agency, which she does not explain very well. And she did manage to sustain the endowment's very existence in the teeth of conservative hostility and in the absence of much overt support from Clinton.</p>
        <p>All of this is recounted in workaday prose flecked with odd errors: Mario Botta, not Robert Venturi, designed the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art; Americans abroad are not ''ex-patriots''; and it was Gertrude Stein who famously said of Oakland, not Dorothy Parker of Los Angeles, that ''there is no there there.''</p>
        <p>Politically, what is curious about the National Endowment for the Arts is how tiny its budget actually is compared with, say, a missile, yet how symbolically important it remains in a kind of backhanded tribute to the power of art. For the right, it is a fund-raising tool; apart from grisly photos of dead fetuses, nothing apparently scores more money than a lurid newsletter portraying the agency as a tool to spread artistic, moral and sexual subversion through the republic. And since the right places such weight on this issue, the center-left has to defend it, at least nominally.</p>
        <p>In the end, it is hard not to sympathize with Alexander's despair. One wonders what might have happened -- in the arts as in so many other areas of policy -- had the Clinton administration mounted a more vigorous, impassioned advocacy for its putative beliefs. To be sure, her own decision never to comment positively or negatively on any artwork contributed to this politic distancing. ''I rose weakly to the challenge,'' she writes of her first encounter with Strom Thurmond. A cynic would say the same for her entire tenure, but then one must remember the dire circumstances.</p>
        <p>The endowment, founded in 1965 with bipartisan support, seemingly cannot win now. The right hates it as a subversive symbol. Multiculturalists undercut its support of high art institutions. Neo-conservatives suggest that since federal financing is so low anyway (a reduction they advocated in the first place), one might as well eliminate it. And centrists, however sympathetic they may be about the supposed moral uplift and economic advantages of culture, let the right define the debate and do not believe enough in the arts themselves to make them a priority.</p>
        <p>The only hope an arts lover might feel is a faith in the ultimate common sense of the American people in the long run -- common sense, because even on pragmatic terms, the endowment is clearly a benefit to society, and most Americans know it. Even with its present meager budget, it is positively positioned in the tumult of the culture wars to make a comeback when political circumstances permit: still supportive of the big institutions and European traditions that define the high arts but properly cognizant of the diversity and vitality of immigrant, folk and regional arts as well.</p>
        <p>An arts lover can cling to faith for the long run, because one can cling to the hope that the economic buoyancy that has revitalized our cities and our education budgets may eventually percolate down into sophisticated arts education and a general refinement of the national aesthetic sensibility, wherein the arts are valued as such, not just as symbols or stimuli for urban renewal. ''Congress had no interest in the worthiness of the art itself,'' Alexander notes in passing, which might seem obvious and almost universal until one realizes what a sad comment it makes about our country. Only when the people and their politicians care about art will they start caring about its proper and legitimate support. And if eventually the endowment is reinvigorated and properly budgeted, at least Jane of Art can take some credit for helping it survive its darkest days.</p>
        <p>John Rockwell is the editor of the Arts &amp; Leisure section of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Rockwell is the editor of the Arts &amp; Leisure section of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
