<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gentlemen Callers</title>
    <meta content="23ESSKLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Essex, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leveridge, Brett</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Men My Mother Dated and Other Mostly Ture Tales (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0D91F38F930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gentlemen Callers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Essex</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Essex, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Essex reviews book Men My Mother Dated and Other Mostly True Tales by Brett Leveridge (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Men My Mother Dated</p>
        <p>And Other Mostly True Tales.</p>
        <p>By Brett Leveridge.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 187 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Villard. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Men My Mother Dated</p>
        <p>And Other Mostly True Tales.</p>
        <p>By Brett Leveridge.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 187 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Villard. $19.95.</p>
        <p>''A boy's best friend,'' Norman Bates once said, ''is his mother.'' Brett Leveridge, an occasional essayist for the public radio programs ''This American Life'' and ''All Things Considered,'' has taken a potentially Batesian relationship -- one son's encyclopedic obsession with his mother's premarital love life -- and turned it into an aw-shucks portrait of small-town romance.</p>
        <p>Leveridge's mother -- identified throughout this book simply as ''Mom'' -- came of age in Okemah, Okla., sometime during America's postwar idyll. Specific dates are not provided, but references to ice-cream socials and Young Singles Sunday-school classes help set the ''American Graffiti'' stage. ''Though not a classic beauty,'' Leveridge writes, his mother possessed ''a wholesome girl-next-door quality, a warm smile, a winning manner and an innovative, if not quite daring, sense of personal style.'' She was, we learn, ''never lacking in suitors.''</p>
        <p>This would appear to be so. Over 20 chapters that range from Mom's first date at the age of 14 to a sneaky wager that required her to juggle (successfully) five men in a single day, we meet such well-intentioned specimens as Nick Fogarty, Tommy Sewell, Robert (Slim) Matthews and more than a dozen other fellows who didn't turn out to be Leveridge's dad.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, we never really meet Mom. Leveridge is a Polaroid essayist; he favors snapshots (one chapter is a paragraph long) over deeply focused reminiscences. ''Men My Mother Dated'' also happens to be almost entirely devoid of dialogue. As Leveridge explains in his introduction, his book is conceived as ''one woman's recollections of dates that occurred many years ago filtered through the overactive imagination of her no-account son.'' Perhaps,</p>
        <p>but after he has reanimated so many charming moments, it might have been diverting to hear Mom actually speak.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the author makes up for any dramatic shortcomings with a natural gift for capturing the absurdity of pre-sexual-revolution courtship. Leveridge chronicles the inevitable senior prom, speed demons in hot rods and a first encounter with pizza. There's a funny brush with greatness involving Jack Kerouac and a marijuana cigarette, which occurred while Leveridge's mother was a waitress in Texas. Later, Mom rebels against Oklahoma's racism and holds hands with a ''male Negro'' named Sela Mohammed Brouley, a dignified exchange student from the Ivory Coast. Leveridge remains respectfully uninterested in salacious details (though we do read of one failed boyfriend with a taste for Judy Garland; he later moved to San Francisco and became a floral designer). At his best, Leveridge is droll and effortless. At his worst, the chapters have the cloying charm of a Pepperidge Farm commercial.</p>
        <p>Having weighed in with 86 pages of maternal courting, Leveridge leaves Mom behind and segues into the ''Other Mostly True Tales'' that make up the second half of his title. As an essayist, Leveridge has an interesting voice. He belongs to the school of bemused dyspeptics that has produced such disparate observers as Calvin Trillin and Andy Rooney. Here he unloads willy-nilly on fawning fathers, Tupperware and Thanksgiving, among other things. The link between breaking up and getting fired produces his finest aper--&gt;us: ''Federal legislation should be drafted that requires the jilter to offer the jilted extended romantic benefits.''</p>
        <p>But after 100 or so pages of self-involved musing, Leveridge begins to lapse into forced precocity, and you long for another cameo from Mom. Where, for instance, is the date with the guy who eventually became Dad? By the final essay -- a three-page riff on Hollywood's preoccupation with vomit -- the author runs the risk of sounding like a comic who laughs too loudly at his own jokes.</p>
        <p>Andrew Essex is an editor at the Internet magazine Salon.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew Essex is an editor at the Internet magazine Salon.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
