<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives; As Is the Daughter, So Is Her Mother</title>
    <meta content="23LIVEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="66" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patchett, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Jeanne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Julie and Romeo (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D6123BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives; As Is the Daughter, So Is Her Mother</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ann Patchett</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Patchett, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Patchett article on coping with her mother's success with her first novel, Julie and Romeo, who has made more of a splash than any of the literary novels she herself has written (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To all my kind friends and professional associates who have shown such tender concern for my psychological health recently, I want to say thank you, I'm fine, really. The truth is, I'm very happy for my mother. Not as in, ''No, really, I'm happy for her.'' I love my mother. Just because she's becoming a celebrity does nothing to lessen my feelings for her. It's not as if I'm too busy to give Entertainment Weekly a quick quote about what she was like before her novel came out.</p>
        <p>We are all familiar with the situation of the very famous writer who spawns a less famous writer. We wonder if those grown-up children would have been published at all without such dazzling last names. Sometimes we wonder if they wouldn't have had a perfectly nice literary career if they hadn't been crushed by the impossible weight of expectation. That isn't my story, although, God help me, I suppose it could become my story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To all my kind friends and professional associates who have shown such tender concern for my psychological health recently, I want to say thank you, I'm fine, really. The truth is, I'm very happy for my mother. Not as in, ''No, really, I'm happy for her.'' I love my mother. Just because she's becoming a celebrity does nothing to lessen my feelings for her. It's not as if I'm too busy to give Entertainment Weekly a quick quote about what she was like before her novel came out.</p>
        <p>We are all familiar with the situation of the very famous writer who spawns a less famous writer. We wonder if those grown-up children would have been published at all without such dazzling last names. Sometimes we wonder if they wouldn't have had a perfectly nice literary career if they hadn't been crushed by the impossible weight of expectation. That isn't my story, although, God help me, I suppose it could become my story.</p>
        <p>I have enjoyed a perfectly respectable career as a literary novelist. If you looked up ''midlist author'' in the dictionary, you might find a tiny black-and-white picture of me in the margin. When I became a writer, I wasn't entering the family business. My father is a retired police captain. My mother, Jeanne Ray, is a nurse. People tell me she's a very good nurse. We're tight, Mom and I, and I've been trying to talk her into following my footsteps for as long as I've been writing books. I knew she'd be a natural. She's smart and funny and has always had a way with a sentence. As she started thinking about retirement and money and what she was supposed to do with her life at 61, I suppose I upped the pressure. She had a little novel, ''Julie and Romeo,'' she'd been playing around with on the side. I told her, after I read Chapter 5, that now was the time.</p>
        <p>My friend Lucy says I'm taking it like a champ. ''To spend your whole life with a mother who's so good-looking and then have her blow you out of the water in your own profession.'' She sighed long-distance. ''Personally, I'd kill her. If she was my mother.''</p>
        <p>My mother's success is hardly her own fault. Wasn't I the one who did the pushing? Didn't I snatch up her manuscript like a foundling left on the doorstep and rush it to my agent, who rushed it off to half of New York? If I had wanted my mother to stay a nurse, I would have given her a kiss upon her forehead after reading her book and said, ''Oh, Mom, I think it's so sweet that you tried to write a novel.''</p>
        <p>And she would have thrown it in the fireplace.</p>
        <p>The ''Today'' show listed ''Julie and Romeo'' as one of its picks for summer reads. A producer from ''48 Hours'' has called. Mom has gone to the Random House warehouse to speak to the people who ship her book. My sister saw 50 copies in the Minneapolis-St. Paul airport the day it was published. This is something I never knew before: the creation of a best seller sounds like a locomotive coming straight toward your house in the middle of the night. My mother's book roars, whereas one of my novels makes a sound like a cricket being set down in the lawn. ''Who knows?'' the producer from ''48 Hours'' said. ''This could have a big impact on your sales as well.''</p>
        <p>Let's be honest here. My mother has written an extremely funny book about 60-year-olds finding true love and great sex in a florist's cooler. I just finished writing a novel about opera and Peru. If ''48 Hours'' calls me again, chances are pretty good it's going to be because they've misplaced Mom's phone number.</p>
        <p>And that's fine. We've never been that competitive. Not that I am completely inured to what people say. I did feel a small shooting pain in my chest when I was visiting someone in the hospital last week and all the nurses were talking about my mother the way inmates immortalize the one who makes the daring prison break. ''Did you ever want to be a writer like your mom?'' one of them asked me.</p>
        <p>I just smiled and nodded. Why should this woman have any idea what I do for a living? And it's not as if I had any proof with me; I don't normally carry copies of my novels in my purse. Several people have already sat me down to tell me that they've figured it all out: my talent is, in fact, genetic, a gift that came packaged in my genome from my mother and so I had better start being appreciative. The word in the fiction aisle of Barnes &amp; Noble these days is that she gave me both my life and a job.</p>
        <p>Not that my mother says this. She's still her regular self, and she gives me all the credit. I sit on her bed while she considers outfits and asks me what she should wear to readings. It reminds me of when I was packing for college, only then I was the one who was nervous, and she was bolstering me. ''They're going to be crazy for you,'' I say. ''Read Chapter 4.'' ''I like the flat shoes better.'' This is my mother, after all. What daughter wouldn't want to see her mother's novel on the best-seller list?</p>
        <p>Ann Patchett is the author of ''The Magician's Assistant.'' Her new novel, ''Bel Canto,'' will be published next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ann Patchett is the author of ''The Magician's Assistant.'' Her new novel, ''Bel Canto,'' will be published next year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
