<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dutch Moment of Genius in Its Full Glory</title>
    <meta content="23RIDI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rijksmuseum (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D7103BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dutch Moment of Genius in Its Full Glory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>AMSTERDAM</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding reviews Glory of the Golden Age, exhibit of Dutch 17th-century art on view at Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam, Netherlands; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TINY country that over a short period produces artists of the stature of Rembrandt, Vermeer, Frans Hals, Jan Steen, Jacob van Ruisdael and Pieter de Hooch has good reason to wax proud over its golden age of painting. Indeed, the Netherlands is doing so yet again with ''The Glory of the Golden Age,'' a ''best of'' exhibition of Dutch 17th-century art that is being held at the Rijksmuseum here through Sept. 17 to celebrate the museum's 200th anniversary.</p>
        <p>The Rijksmuseum is itself, of course, a monument to the golden age and, as such, has been able to provide around half of the items in the show (with Rembrandt's ''Night Watch'' the pivotal work in the exhibition, just as it is the iconic painting of the permanent collection). But for this occasion, to complement its own masterpieces, it has also borrowed essential works from other Dutch museums as well as from collections elsewhere in Europe and in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TINY country that over a short period produces artists of the stature of Rembrandt, Vermeer, Frans Hals, Jan Steen, Jacob van Ruisdael and Pieter de Hooch has good reason to wax proud over its golden age of painting. Indeed, the Netherlands is doing so yet again with ''The Glory of the Golden Age,'' a ''best of'' exhibition of Dutch 17th-century art that is being held at the Rijksmuseum here through Sept. 17 to celebrate the museum's 200th anniversary.</p>
        <p>The Rijksmuseum is itself, of course, a monument to the golden age and, as such, has been able to provide around half of the items in the show (with Rembrandt's ''Night Watch'' the pivotal work in the exhibition, just as it is the iconic painting of the permanent collection). But for this occasion, to complement its own masterpieces, it has also borrowed essential works from other Dutch museums as well as from collections elsewhere in Europe and in the United States.</p>
        <p>In the main part of the exhibition, some 200 paintings, sculptures and works of decorative art have been organized both chronologically and around themes, some obvious (''Sky and Water,''  ''Masters of Landscape,''  ''The Delft Light''), others more quirky (''Whims and Drolleries,''  ''Extravagantly Decked Out,''  ''Deceptively Realistic'').</p>
        <p>Until July 16, 96 drawings and prints were also presented in a dimly lighted gallery on a lower floor, but their fragility prevented their being displayed through September.</p>
        <p>The package is impressive: with such raw material, how could it be otherwise? But the show's organizers have also done their bit. By placing sculptures and decorative arts in the same area as paintings, they underline how different art forms were flourishing simultaneously. And with the thematic hanging, they demonstrate how many different schools of paintings were busy at the same time, from portraiture to landscapes, from still life to genre painting.</p>
        <p>Yet perhaps most crucially, the show offers a salutary reminder that, for all the renown of Rembrandt, Vermeer and their like today, it was not artists who created the golden age. Rather, it was a special moment in Dutch history, characterized by political enlightenment and economic prosperity, that generated a veritable boom in artistic creation.</p>
        <p>In other parts of Europe, art was still reflecting the power of kings and popes. In the Netherlands, it mirrored the emergence of a new kind of civil society, one largely run by and for its Protestant mercantile burghers.</p>
        <p>Even more remarkably, for more than 30 years until the Treaty of Westphalia in 1648, the Dutch Republic, as the United Provinces of the north became known, was fighting to consolidate its independence from Spain, which had inherited the Netherlands from the Holy Roman Empire. Yet even during this time, its fleet was establishing new colonies and opening new trading routes that turned Amsterdam into an opulent port city: its population jumped from 50,000 in 1600 to 200,000 in 1650. And with prosperity came a demand for fancier homes and art to put in them.</p>
        <p>Amsterdam, which drew Rembrandt from his native Leiden, was at the center of artistic activity, but it was not alone. Haarlem, Utrecht, Delft and Dordrecht, as well as Leiden, had important guilds of artists, in many cases working independently of one another. For example, in Utrecht, which remained largely Roman Catholic, a tradition of religious paintings was kept alive by painters who had studied Caravaggio in Rome. Elsewhere, paintings were everywhere except churches -- in town halls, guild houses and private homes.</p>
        <p>Thus, relieved of the need to paint royal portraits and biblical scenes, many artists became unconscious chroniclers of the social history of the era. Important burghers, with their black satin suits and frilly lace collars, were natural subjects, but so also were maritime battles and elegant cityscapes. Domestic interiors, in which the nouveaux riches took special pride, were presented with revolutionary realism, with the paintings on their walls duly reproduced. Indeed, with still lifes decorating every self-respecting home, it was an enviable time and place to be an artist.</p>
        <p>''Thousands of painters of varying talents were active during this century, producing several million paintings altogether,'' Jan Piet Filedt Kok writes in an introduction to this exhibition's catalog. ''The production of decorative art -- ceramics, glass, silver and furniture -- achieved new heights, too; only sculpture lagged behind at first.''</p>
        <p>''The Glory of the Golden Age'' starts by introducing the ''New Faces'' of Dutch portraiture through Thomas de Keyser's ''Syndics of the Amsterdam Goldsmiths' Guild'' (on loan from the Toledo Museum of Art in Ohio) and Hals's bucolic ''Marriage Portrait of Isaac Massa and Beatrix van der Laen.'' This leads to the ''Extravagantly Decked Out'' section, where carefully painted accessories, from leather gloves with gold thread, pearls and sequins to delicate lace headwear, are both examples and symbols of wealth.</p>
        <p>''Deceptively Realistic'' is of course dedicated to still lifes, with Ambrosius Bosschaert's ''Bouquet of Flowers in a Vase'' of 1618 reminiscent of the tulipomania that gripped the Netherlands in the early 17th century (until the speculative bubble burst in 1637).</p>
        <p>But the fascination with still lifes went far beyond flower arrangements: with just a handful of works, the exhibition illustrates the virtuosity of painters who took special pride in portraying, say, cheese or fish or feathers or oysters, in each case as a realistically as possible.</p>
        <p>SEEMINGLY EVERYDAY'' is particularly interesting since it mirrors the ambivalence that the Protestant Dutch felt about their own affluence (''The Embarrassment of Riches,'' as Simon Schama entitled his acclaimed book on the Dutch golden age). Painters evidently enjoyed showing people having a good time, but they justified this by suggesting they were warning of the perils of decadence. ''In Luxury Beware'' by Jan Steen, for instance, shows a party in full swing, while the bare-breasted women and drunken men in Nicolaus Knupfer's ''Brothel Scene'' could be portrayed in the Calvinist Netherlands only as an admonition against immorality.</p>
        <p>Subsequent sections -- there are 23 -- underscore how, at the same time as they kept one eye on the market, Dutch painters of the period were also interested in exploring new techniques. For instance, chiaroscuro -- the strong use of light and shadow -- was initially borrowed from Caravaggio, but the Delft painters took it further, creating a more natural sense of drama. Vermeer's mastery of this technique can be seen here in ''The Glass of Wine,'' on loan from the Gemaldegalerie in Berlin, and in the Rijksmuseum's own ''Kitchen Maid.''</p>
        <p>Yet for all the array of treasures proffered by the golden age, the exhibition cannot escape the dominating presence of Rembrandt and Hals. Three Rembrandts on loan to the Rijksmuseum -- ''The Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicholas Tulp'' from the Mauritshuis in The Hague, ''Flora'' from the Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg and ''The Wedding of Samson'' from the Gemaldegalerie in Dresden -- show the broad range of his techniques. Similarly, in the section called ''Militia Companies,'' paintings of citizens' military units by other artists point up the remarkable composition of Rembrandt's ''Night Watch.''</p>
        <p>The section dedicated to Rembrandt and Hals includes numerous portraits by both men, but their styles can best be contrasted in two large oils that hang side by side: Rembrandt's 1662 ''Syndics,'' owned by the Rijksmuseum, and Hals's 1664 ''Regents of the Old Men's Almshouse in Haarlem,'' on loan from the Frans Halsmuseum in Haarlem. While Rembrandt's painting of five burghers and a servant from the drapers' guild offers six detailed and well-lighted portraits, Hals's seven regents -- dressed in black against a black background, with only their faces, hands and white collars immediately visible -- reveal how he achieved his effect with a few hurried brush strokes.</p>
        <p>Scattered throughout the exhibition are stone and marble sculptures (mainly busts of worthy burghers), embroidered chairs, wooden cabinets, glass and silver goblets and a good selection of Delft pottery.</p>
        <p>Most unusual, perhaps, is an 11-foot-tall copper candelabrum made by Joost Gerritsz in 1640 and donated that same year by the Dutch East India Company to Japan's shogun as part of a successful campaign to curry favor with the Japanese ruler: from 1641 until early in the 19th century, the Dutch enjoyed a European monopoly of trade with Japan. The candelabrum, now permanently on display in a complex of tombs and temples at Nikko in Japan, returned to the Netherlands for the first time for this show.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
