<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Team Tennis Finds a Home in Hartford</title>
    <meta content="23TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hartford Foxforce</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Billie Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bailer, Darice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D6113BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Team Tennis Finds a Home in Hartford</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DARICE BAILER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bailer, Darice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Hartford FoxForce, new professional co-ed tennis team in Hartford, Conn, and member of Billie Jean King's DuPont world Team Tennis league; league championship is set for August 26 at National Tennis Center in Flushing Meadows, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BILLIE JEAN KING found Hartford delightful the first time she visited while playing in a professional tennis tournament more than 15 years ago. And, the 20-time Wimbledon champion of the 1960's and 70's did not forget the city.</p>
        <p>Last year, when King hunted for new franchises for her DuPont World Team Tennis, a co-ed professional league she co-founded back in 1974, her thoughts turned to the East. She knew Hartford could support a professional sports team. After all, the city had been the home of the National Hockey League Hartford Whalers before that team became the Carolina Hurricanes in 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BILLIE JEAN KING found Hartford delightful the first time she visited while playing in a professional tennis tournament more than 15 years ago. And, the 20-time Wimbledon champion of the 1960's and 70's did not forget the city.</p>
        <p>Last year, when King hunted for new franchises for her DuPont World Team Tennis, a co-ed professional league she co-founded back in 1974, her thoughts turned to the East. She knew Hartford could support a professional sports team. After all, the city had been the home of the National Hockey League Hartford Whalers before that team became the Carolina Hurricanes in 1997.</p>
        <p>''I thought this would be a nice place to have a team,'' King said.</p>
        <p>King turned to Pam Batalis, who was the general manager of the (1996-98) New England Blizzard, Hartford's American Basketball League team in the defunct women's league. Did she know who might be interested in a franchise?</p>
        <p>Yes, Batalis said: Lisa Wilson-Foley and her husband, Brian J. Foley. The Simsbury residents were community-minded business entrepreneurs. And, last November, the Foleys bought a franchise for $60,000. They named it the Hartford FoxForce.</p>
        <p>FoxForce played its first home match inside the Hartford Armory on July 12. FoxForce defeated the three-time defending league champion Sacramento Capitals, which is the oldest of the current nine teams.</p>
        <p>Teams play seven home and seven away matches from July 10-30. On Tuesday, at 6:30 p.m., the FoxForce will play host to the Idaho Sneakers. That match will be Kid's Night and Fan Appreciation Night. On Friday, , FoxForce will take on Martina Navratilova and the Schenectady County Electrics.</p>
        <p>The league championship is set for Aug. 26 at National Tennis Center in Flushing Meadows, N.Y., before the United States Open begins.</p>
        <p>Monica Seles, a nine-time Grand Slam champion, was originally planning to play four nights for the FoxForce this summer. But she changed her mind and played five.</p>
        <p>''I was enjoying myself and I said, 'Why not? Let's just do it.' I just really enjoyed our teammates,'' Seles said. ''We got along so well. The owners are such fun, and it's a pleasure to play for people like that. It's just such a fun atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>A new professional team is just what Hartford needs, said FoxForce Coach Paul Assaiante, who also coaches men's tennis and squash at Trinity College.</p>
        <p>''This is what we're looking for,'' Assaiante said. ''I'm a resident of  this town and I watched what we felt like when the Whalers left and I  watched what we felt like when the Patriots went away. This is exciting. This is a professional team.''</p>
        <p>King co-founded World Team Tennis with her former husband, Larry. The Kings created a new tennis format in which there were two men and two women playing three matches each (singles, doubles and mixed doubles).</p>
        <p>''A little girl who comes out to see a match sees the equality factor, that  women make equal contributions to what's going on,'' said King, who is also the 2000 Olympic women's coach for the United States. ''They're assimilating that, and that's a very important message for kids to receive.''</p>
        <p>And, at the end of the season, women earn the same prize money -- $7,000 for the men's and women's singles champions and $9,000 for the men's and women's doubles and mixed doubles teams. Plus, athletes who play at least 11 of 14 matches are eligible for a $15,000 male and female Most Valuable Player Award, and a $10,000 male and female Rookie of the Year Award.  (Even today, of the four Grand Slam tennis tournaments, only the United States Open pays female winners as much as the male winners.)</p>
        <p>The players are paid by the league and are drafted by the franchises.  ''There's a range of salaries,'' said Ilana S. Kloss, the executive director of Team Tennis. The minimum pay for the season is $4,000 for three weeks. Kloss said every player is paid differently according to their world ranking. But, Kloss said, ''We do not disclose salaries.''</p>
        <p>King was driven by more than a desire for equality in performance and salary.</p>
        <p>''Our philosophy at W.T.T. is taking tennis to the people,'' King said.</p>
        <p>Only one match runs at a time. Every player wears a T-shirt with his or her name on the back. That way fans could get to know all the  players, including the top-ranked world stars.</p>
        <p>The matches are played in smaller arenas, so that fans could see the pros close-up. Although the armory has 3,000 seats, watching tennis there is like watching a high school basketball game inside a large gym. In the box seats, fans sit behind a short white trellis fence, a car length away from the court. And, in the stands, they're less than a half-court back.</p>
        <p>King changed traditional tennis scoring to shorten matches so that kids and adults wouldn't get bored. Women's singles and doubles, men's singles and doubles, and mixed doubles are one set long and played in rapid succession. Game scoring is no-ad. The first team to win 4 points wins the game, and five games takes the set. Each game counts toward a team's total score.</p>
        <p>Unlike Grand Slam tournaments, fans can talk and kids can run around and cheer as the players play.</p>
        <p>''World Team Tennis embodies everything that Billie Jean King likes  and thinks tennis should be,'' said Lynne Liebhauser, FoxForce's general manager.</p>
        <p>The Foleys want children to attend, so their tickets are half-price.</p>
        <p>Tim Hughes, a 9-year-old Avon youngster watched the home opener. ''I want to be a pro,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I think that's how we all started,'' Seles said. ''We all had someone who inspired us. That's how future champions come about.''</p>
        <p>Including the 1999 United State Open champion, Serena Williams. King said Williams told her that she wanted to become a tennis star after watching King play for World Team Tennis in Los Angeles years ago.</p>
        <p>Williams now competes for the Delaware Smash, which King owns. And, the other Williams sister and current Wimbledon champion, Venus, is a St. Louis Ace.</p>
        <p>King said she has hopes that the league will have a total of 16 teams in the next three years.</p>
        <p>''We're bringing top of the world tennis to towns like Springfield, Mo.,  and Hartford,'' said Murphy Jensen, a FoxForce player. ''Hartford's had world class tennis, but towns like Springfield, Wilmington, Del., Wichita, Kan., they'll never get to see Monica Seles or Martina Navratilova. We're bringing tennis to smaller venues and smaller markets. Not everyone can go to the U.S. Open, the French Open or Wimbledon. But here they get to see world players.''</p>
        <p>Bethanie Mattek, 15, of Boca Raton, Fla., will compete in Ms. Seles's place for the duration of the season. Her teammates are James Blake, 20, and Liezel Horn, 23. Mr. Blake, a Fairfield resident, played for Harvard before turning professional. And, in 1999, he became the first African-American to reach the National Collegiate Athletic Association tennis singles final since Arthur Ashe did it in 1965. Ms. Horn, who is from Durban, South Africa and Houston, Tex., was a 1999 Wimbledon semifinalist in doubles with Katarina Srebotnik.</p>
        <p>Mattek was one of two junior women to play at Wimbledon this year.  Jensen, who is from Hollywood, Calif., won the men's doubles at the 1993 French Open with his brother Luke, who is a St. Louis Ace.</p>
        <p>The Phoenix Home Life Mutual Insurance Company of Hartford is FoxForce's official sponsor. Phoenix and the Foleys have made a three-year commitment to the team. During the summer season, FoxForce team players promote tennis among children at clinics at area clubs.</p>
        <p>It didn't take long after King met the Foleys that she made up her mind that she wanted them to become one of her owners. ''They had all the qualities that were important,'' King said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foley owns Apple Health Care Incorporated in Avon, which manages nursing homes and he also owns a restaurant in Newport, R.I. He was the previous owner of the Connecticut Pride, a professional team in the Continental Basketball Association. (Mr. Foley changed the team's name from Hellcats to Connecticut Pride because he didn't want his kids using  a swear word when saying the team name.) Ms. Wilson-Foley owns a  bowling center/mini-golf course and two other golf courses in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wilson-Foley liked the idea of running a business with her husband. ''We thought it would be a fun venture for all of us,'' she said. ''It's fan  friendly, kid friendly, and community-oriented. That's so part of my life.''</p>
        <p>The Foleys have seven children, ranging from 1 to 19. They know what it's like to be busy working  parents, trying to eke out a couple of enjoyable hours with the kids. ''We  don't have enough time nowadays, especially if we're working parents,'' Ms. Foley said. ''If we can go out at night and we can bring our kids, and they can have a good time, it's golden. That's what we're all looking for, isn't it?''</p>
        <p>For more information and tickets, call (877) 369-3672. Prices start at $14.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
