<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Familiar Response to Power Plant: Nimby</title>
    <meta content="23POWE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kings Park (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ppl Global</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toy, Vivian S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3DB1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Familiar Response to Power Plant: Nimby</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toy, Vivian S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Kings Park, Long Island, are battling PPL Global plan to build 600-megawatt power station, even as local and New York State power authorities warn of brownouts and blackouts unless new energy sources are found; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESIDENTS of Kings Park are fighting a plan to build a 600-megawatt power station there, even as local and state power authorities warn that Long Island desperately needs new energy sources to avoid brownouts and blackouts.</p>
        <p>PPL Global, a subsidiary of a Pennsylvania power company, wants to build a plant on a 21-acre site, a former sand and gravel mine. The plant would burn natural gas from the Iroquois pipeline, which lies underground adjacent to the site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESIDENTS of Kings Park are fighting a plan to build a 600-megawatt power station there, even as local and state power authorities warn that Long Island desperately needs new energy sources to avoid brownouts and blackouts.</p>
        <p>PPL Global, a subsidiary of a Pennsylvania power company, wants to build a plant on a 21-acre site, a former sand and gravel mine. The plant would burn natural gas from the Iroquois pipeline, which lies underground adjacent to the site.</p>
        <p>But just beyond the pipeline, about 1,000 feet away from the proposed plant, sits a residential neighborhood where homeowners have formed a civic group to fight the power plant.</p>
        <p>Company officials say the plant, which they hope to have running by June 2002, would help fill Long Island's ever-growing need for electricity and provide competition with the Long Island Power Authority that might bring rates down.</p>
        <p>But home owners fear the plant will generate smoke and dust from its 110-foot smokestack and noise from its 12 combustion turbines, and thus ruin property values.</p>
        <p>The company filed its first formal plans for the $300 million plant with the state Public Service Commission last week, but had introduced its proposal to local officials and residents over the last month.</p>
        <p>The debate perfectly illustrates the Island's power puzzle: electricity demand is expected to break records this summer, coming within 5 percent of total capacity, but residents insist they do not want new plants built anywhere near their backyards.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants a power plant,'' said Richard M. Kessel, chairman of the Long Island Power Authority. ''And it's a hard reality. But no matter how much we do with energy-efficiency programs, if we don't get several new power plants built in the next few years, the lights will go out.''</p>
        <p>He said a prolonged heat wave would push the Island's electricity use to 4,893 megawatts, dangerously close to the 5,140 megawatts currently available.</p>
        <p>At meetings with PPL Global officials and before the Smithtown Town Board, residents have railed against the proposal and said they did not feel their community should suffer to solve a problem that some are not convinced really exists.</p>
        <p>Allen Leon of Commack, who lives near the site and is president of the newly formed Town Line Association, would not discuss the residents' concerns at length because the group is still formulating its position.</p>
        <p>But he said residents generally were fearful that the plant would cause noise pollution, traffic congestion and environmental hazards, and damage the underground water table. He also said residents were afraid of ''possible emergencies like fires or explosions.''</p>
        <p>Officials from PPL Global said that they had plans to deal with all of these concerns and that their plant, which would only operate during peak daytime hours, would actually be environmentally friendlier than the current activities. Sand mining operations were shut down some years ago but the site is now used for breaking down and sifting road construction debris.</p>
        <p>''We look at this site and say it's perfect,'' said James S. Potter, PPL Global's director of business development. ''Existing noise levels are unbelievably high and it's essentially one big dustbowl. We're going to come in and significantly improve the site.''</p>
        <p>Underground lines would be used to bring gas to the plant and to connect to the surrounding area's power grid. The plant would employ only about 8 to 10 people at a time and would eliminate the current truck traffic at the site, which ranges from 20 to 200 trucks a week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Potter said the company would use about 15 of the 21 acres for the plant itself, which would essentially be a 50-foot-high brick box of a building with a 110-foot smokestack. The remaining six acres would be landscaped with a 20- to 25-foot-high berm, making the structure and its smokestack virtually invisible to local residents.</p>
        <p>Residents say, however, that even if they did not have to look at the plant, they would still be able to hear it, and they worry about air pollution.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Potter said that the plant would use approximately 570 gallons of water a minute to help control emissions, and stressed that the emissions rate would be significantly lower than that at any existing power plant on the Island.</p>
        <p>To make sure that the water needs would not drain local resources, PPL Global is negotiating with the Suffolk County Water Authority to help clean up a nearby well that has been closed because of high nitrate levels. Mr. Potter said the well would produce 1,100 gallons of water a minute, twice what the plant would need.</p>
        <p>He also said that concerns about the overall danger of having a power station so close were legitimate, but that the plant would have sophisticated gas-leak detection systems and devices to shut down automatically. ''Statistically, the plant is much safer than someone using natural gas in the house,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Frank DeRubeis, the director of planning for Smithtown, said he agreed with many of the residents' concerns.</p>
        <p>''If I had my choice for a location for a power plant, this would not be it, because it's too close to residences,'' he said, noting that there are other sites within the town's industrial zone that would be further away from homes. He added, however, that while the town will be consulted during the approval process, the state has ultimate control.</p>
        <p>Many other power companies are considering building plants on the Island, but so far there is only one other application before the Public Service Commission. That proposal, for a 580-megawatt plant in Yap hank, which was submitted in March, has also met with a great deal of community opposition.</p>
        <p>LIPA agreed last month to purchase all the power from a planned $120 million cable under the Sound that would transport 300 megawatts of electricity from New England. The cable is to be completed by May 2002.</p>
        <p>David C. Flanagan, a spokesman for the Public Service Commission, said there is no question that the Island needs more power plants.</p>
        <p>''Long Island, like New York City, is constrained by how much electrical power it can import,'' he said. ''So therefore you need plans for new plants for reliability purposes.''</p>
        <p>But environmentalists say the warnings that Long Island is on the verge of a major power breakdown are exaggerated.</p>
        <p>''We don't need the Kings Park plant, or one anywhere else on Long Island,'' said Gordian Raacke, executive director of the Citizens Advisory Panel, a LIPA watchdog. ''It doesn't make sense to invest in a new plant until we've exhausted the potential for energy savings and the use of other renewable resources.''</p>
        <p>He said a recent study by the Pace University Law School Energy Project had found that Long Island could easily save 465 megawatts of electrical capacity through the more aggressive use of efficiency programs, and produce about 200 megawatts with new technologies like solar energy and wind power.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
