<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Guilt Pangs Here: Day Care for the Dog</title>
    <meta content="23DOG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pleasantville (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scarsdale (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Rochelle (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canine Companions (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elissa's Pet Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Critter Sitters (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodara, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2DB113BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Guilt Pangs Here: Day Care for the Dog</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN HODARA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hodara, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dog day care centers in Westchester County, NY; focuses on Canine Companions in Pleasantville, Elissa's Pet Services in Scarsdale and Critter Sitters in New Rochelle; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BANDIT is picked up from his home at 8:30 in the morning and brought back at 5. He spends all day with his friends.  Sparky, Jasper and Teddy are his favorites. They run around together in the yard, or play inside, and if they get tired, they nap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BANDIT is picked up from his home at 8:30 in the morning and brought back at 5. He spends all day with his friends.  Sparky, Jasper and Teddy are his favorites. They run around together in the yard, or play inside, and if they get tired, they nap.</p>
        <p>Nothing unusual about these day-care activities, except for one thing: 3-year-old Bandit and his pals have four legs, not a toddler's usual two.</p>
        <p>Bandit spends three days a week in dog day care at Canine Companions in Pleasantville. For his owner, Dr. Miriam Rampel, a clinical psychologist, the program is the only way she could have a dog.</p>
        <p>''I'm a senior citizen,'' she explained. ''I'm physically handicapped, and I recently had open- heart surgery. On top of that, we live in a condo. I wanted a dog, but I knew I couldn't provide enough physical activity for it. Bandit is a happy, frisky little dog who needs a lot more room to run than our back deck has to offer.''</p>
        <p>This was not always the case. When Dr. Rampel adopted Bandit from a shelter, he was fearful of people and dogs alike. It was at Canine Companions that he learned to enjoy the company of  other dogs. ''Within a few weeks, he blossomed,'' Dr. Rampel said. ''It's not about obedience training. It's about socialization, exercise and mental stimulation.  Bandit loves it! I love it! It's an idea whose time has come.''</p>
        <p>The idea for Canine Companions came about a year ago to Lisa Vetrano Siegel, who was then working as a registered nurse. ''I was trying to socialize my dog,'' she said, ''so I started taking other dogs into my home for him to play with. Before long, I was having regular doggie play groups, and it took off from there.''</p>
        <p>This month, Canine Companions moved from Ms. Siegel's home into a new indoor-outdoor place complete with gym equipment, a dog swimming pool and six gated rooms where smaller groups can mingle.</p>
        <p>Describing her clientele, Ms. Siegel said:  ''Some are puppies who are being cratetrained and whose owners can't be home as often as they need to be. Some are dogs whose owners don't have time to exercise them properly. Some, though not many, are dogs who are physically handicapped and need special care.''</p>
        <p>Others, she said, have severe separation anxiety; if left alone, they will destroy property or mutilate themselves.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegel's new center can accommodate up to 30 dogs, and while she accepts any breed and size, she screens applicants carefully. ''Sometimes owners don't know if their dog is aggressive,'' Ms. Siegel said. ''We watch them and get to know them. We put the new dogs in with other nonaggressive dogs. Then we separate them into groups where we know they'll have a good time.''</p>
        <p>Dogs are having a similarly good time with Elissa Mosca, who has been running Elissa's Pet Services in Scarsdale for 14 months. ''When you have children,'' she said, ''you arrange play dates. You take them to the park. You do things with them so they will be well socialized. Dogs are no different -- they need to socialize.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mosca, who left the corporate world about a year and a half ago to become a dog walker, described one dog that now spends every day with her.</p>
        <p>''He suffered from such intense separation anxiety that he was going to be put to sleep,'' she said. ''For three years, his owners tried everything -- from special training to medications to behaviorists -- but nothing worked. It was only after spending time with us, with other dogs, that he started improving. He still can't be alone, and I still can't close a door on him, but he has gained weight; his medication has been cut in half, and he's a much better dog.''</p>
        <p>Other (less neurotic) dogs also enjoy the canine company at Elissa's Pet Services, which is in a storefront in a shopping plaza off Central Avenue, with a fenced-in outdoor play area. Although she has a town permit to operate her business and claims she is welcomed by the stores around her, she has been challenged by residents of a neighboring co-op and will go to court in October to defend her right to offer her services.</p>
        <p>''I've never had any trouble with the dogs,'' she said. ''When there are children in a community, there are day-care centers. There are schools. When there are pets in a community, the community should support services for those pets as well.''</p>
        <p>For those who prefer the comforts of home, New Rochelle-based Critter Sitters offers a variation on the dog day-care theme. The owner, Beth Siegel, who is no relation to Lisa Siegel, makes house calls to dogs that are home alone and in need of extra care, from feeding and exercise to  companionship.</p>
        <p>''Some older dogs do better in their own homes,'' she said. ''And puppies can't be with other dogs till they've had all their shots. I can reinforce training, toss a ball around, administer any necessary medications or just hang out. I have one dog who needs to run, so I see him two hours in the morning and two hours again in the afternoon.</p>
        <p>''Some of my clients work long hours,'' said Ms. Siegel, who was a veterinary technician before starting Critter Sitters five years ago. ''Others are on vacation and use me as an alternative to boarding. The dogs  don't have to be caged. They get plenty of attention, and it's less traumatic for them to stay at home.''</p>
        <p>Another alternative to traditional boarding is offered at both Canine Companions and Elissa's Pet Services and is the natural accompaniment to dog day care. It is called cageless boarding, with all the dogs together. ''The dogs get to socialize,'' Ms. Mosca said, ''and if they want some quiet time, they can go off by themselves.''</p>
        <p>Where the Leash Is Off</p>
        <p>How much is that doggie in the day care? Here is more information about the the businesses mentioned in the article.</p>
        <p>CANINE COMPANIONS -- 9 Hobby Street in Pleasanvtille. Telephone: (914) 773 2020; Hours: Monday to Friday, 7 a.m. to 7 p.m.; day care fees: $25 for one day; $23 a day for three or more days in one week; monthly rates available. Overnight boarding: $35 a night for the first seven nights, $33 a night after that.Dogs that weigh less than 10 pounds are charged $30 a night.</p>
        <p>ELISSA'S PET SERVICES -- 398 Central Avenue, Scarsdale. Telephone: (914) 722-6564; Hours: Monday to Friday, day care; Saturday, limited day care; Sunday, boarders only.Day care: $20 for one day for small dogs; $28 for one day for medium dogs; $30 for one day for large dogs. Overnight boarding: $25 a night.</p>
        <p>CRITTER SITTERS -- New Rochelle. Telephone: (914) 235-2143; Hours: Monday to Friday. For each hour: $23.</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
