<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23GUID$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DC1E3BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The New York Philharmonic comes to Heckscher State Park in East Islip to play its 23rd annual free concert for the Islip Arts Council. This time out -- at 8 p.m. Saturday -- the orchestra, under the baton of Andre Raphel Smith in his Philharmonic debut, will play Glinka's ''Russian and Ludmilla Overture,'' Corigliano's ''Elegy for Orchestra,'' Four Dance Episodes from Copland's ''Rodeo'' and Shostakovich's Symphony No. 5 in D minor (Op. 47) (631) 224-5420.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The New York Philharmonic comes to Heckscher State Park in East Islip to play its 23rd annual free concert for the Islip Arts Council. This time out -- at 8 p.m. Saturday -- the orchestra, under the baton of Andre Raphel Smith in his Philharmonic debut, will play Glinka's ''Russian and Ludmilla Overture,'' Corigliano's ''Elegy for Orchestra,'' Four Dance Episodes from Copland's ''Rodeo'' and Shostakovich's Symphony No. 5 in D minor (Op. 47) (631) 224-5420.</p>
        <p>Doubling Up</p>
        <p>With the Neville Brothers available, Friends of the Arts just couldn't resist booking the quartet for its Summer Festival. So the group appears at 8 p.m. today at Planting Fields Arboretum in Oyster Bay. Come Saturday, again at 8 p.m., and the Friends will have Patti LuPone, perform ''Matters of the Heart,'' her one-woman show (516) 922-0061.</p>
        <p>New York on Film</p>
        <p>For more than 50 years, from the late 19th century to World War II, the Byron Company, a photography studio, witnessed and documented life in New York City. Though they specialized in theatrical and ship photography, Joseph Byron, the founder, and his son, Percy, also focused on the entire city as it matured into a great metropolis. Eighty vintage prints from the nearly 22,000 Byron Company prints and negatives owned by the Museum of the City of New York have been put together for ''Gotham Comes of Age: New York Through the Lens of the Byron Company,'' a traveling exhibition, accompanied by a catalog with an introduction by E. L. Doctorow, that runs through Oct. 29 at the Museums at Stony Brook on Route 25A. Today at 2 p.m. there's ''Celluloid New York: A Century in Film,'' a video program by Peter Conolly-Smith that takes a look at early films about the city, starting with Edison's turn-of-the-century short subjects and continuing through the Jazz Age and the Depression (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>'Tallulah Tonight'</p>
        <p>Not content with having the stage dark for even one night, the Bay Street Theater in Sag Harbor has scheduled a series of ''Summer Monday'' specials. Tomorrow, at 8 p.m., Tovah Feldshuh takes front and center with ''Tallulah Tonight,'' her musical-theatrical celebration of the actress. A one-act, three-character play, the piece, based on Bankhead's life from her youth in Alabama to her days on Broadway and in Hollywood, was written by Ms. Feldshuh with Larry Amoros and Linda Selman. It is directed by William Wesbrooks, and features Bob Goldstone, the musical director, and Mark Desauinier in the cast. Next week, the series offers ''Fully Committed,'' Becky Mode's comedy about life in a four-star restaurant (631)  725-9500.</p>
        <p>For Good Causes</p>
        <p>The summer benefit circuit heats up this week with three events worthy of a look-see. Tomorrow golf dominates the giving scene as the Lightpath Long Island Classic, a stop on the Senior P.G.A. Tour, opens at the Meadow Brook Club in Jericho. Seventy-eight golfers, including the defending champion Bruce Fleisher, Lee Trevino, Chi Chi Rodriguez and Lanny Wadkins, will take to the 6,842-yard, par-72 course to vie for $1.5 million in prize money. The action, to benefit Schneider Children's Hospital, runs through next Sunday (516) 753-4357.</p>
        <p>The creative energies of East End artists have been put to work in two events on Saturday: In Southold at 3 p.m. at the American Legion Hall, the East End Hospice will gain from ''Chair'ity VI,'' an auction of original furniture created by North Fork artists and crafts workers. Viewing begins at 2 p.m. (631) 288-8400.</p>
        <p>On the South Fork, the Retreat, the domestic violence agency and shelter, holds it fifth annual ''Artists Against Abuse Plate Auction.'' Hand-painted ceramic plates by artists like Ross Bleckner, Louise Bourgeois, Donald Sultan and Jenny Holzer and celebrities like Roy Scheider, Rudy Guiliani and Rosie O'Donnell will be auctioned from 5 to 8:30 p.m. during a cocktail party featuring the Larry Rivers Band. At the Channing Daughters Winery in Bridgehampton (631) 329-4398.</p>
        <p>More Films</p>
        <p>One local film festival, the ''2000 Stony Brook Film Festival,'' closes Saturday, making way for another, the ''Huntington International Film Festival.'' In Stony Brook, at the Staller Center on the State University campus, things end with an awards reception following the Long Island premiere at 9:20 p.m. of Jean Philippe Toussaint's ''Ice Rink,'' starring Dolores Chaplin, Charlie Chaplin's granddaughter, in her debut performance. Ms. Chaplin will be there. During the rest of the week a full schedule of films will be shown, including ''Jingle Hell,'' the comedy shot on the Island by Long Islanders, at 9:15 p.m. on Wednesday (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>The programming in Huntington at the Cinema Arts Center begins on Friday with ''To Sleep With Anger'' at 2:10 p.m., the first film in ''A Tribute to Charles Burnett,'' which will feature a preview of his new film, ''The Annihilation of Fish,'' with James Earl Jones and Lynn Redgrave, at 7 p.m. Saturday with the filmmaker on hand. Other highlights include Bette Gordon, a writer-director, with ''Luminous Motion,'' her on-the-road tale of a drunken mother and a psychotic son, at 7 p.m. Friday, followed by the festival's opening reception; ''An Affair of Love,'' a Belgian-French drama about a pornographic affair, which makes its debut in New York on Aug. 11, but will be shown here at 9:15 p.m. Saturday, and ''Sour Apple Freeze Pop'' with Chaz Lipp, the filmmaker, present, at 9:15 p.m. Sunday. There will also be a filmmakers' panel at 2 p.m. on Saturday, and a ''Talk Back to Critics'' panel at 2 p.m. Sunday (631) 423-7610.</p>
        <p>Around the Parks</p>
        <p>The ''something-for-everyone'' summer parks concerts continue this week as the Duprees appear at 1 p.m. today at Bar Beach in Port Washington (516) 327-3110. Tomorrow, Jim Dawson offers folk rock at 8 p.m. at Levittown Memorial Park (516) 489-4849, while on Tuesday there's a choice between the Duprees, who reappear at 8 p.m. at Burns Park in Massapequa (516) 797-7900 and David Sear, the folk artist, at 7 p.m. at Clark Botanic Garden in Albertson (516) 327-3110. Wednesday sees Nipsey Russell at Woodbury Community Park at 8 p.m. (516) 797-7900 or Mary Mancini and Mario Tacca in ''A Romanitic Evening of Song'' at 8 p.m. at Rath Park in Franklin Square (516) 489-4849. On Thursday, Squeaky Clean plays rock and doo-wop at 8 p.m. at Bethpage Community Park (516) 797-7900. The Capris sing at 7 p.m. on Friday at Martin Park in New Hyde Park (516) 327-3110 and also on Friday, but at 8 p.m., the Del Vikings, with Norman Wright, play the Hicksville High School Field (516) 797-7900. Finally, Steve Mitchell brings ''A Touch of Elvis'' to Post Park in Massapequa at 8 p.m. (516) 797-7900.</p>
        <p>Country Reigns</p>
        <p>With seven concerts on the schedule, this is a good week for country music fans. Today, there are two to consider: the Mary Lamont Band appears at 6:30 p.m. in the Music under the Dome series at the Vanderbilt Planetarium in Centerport (631) 854-5550, and, in a free concert, Buddy Merriam and Back Roads play at 8:30 p.m. at Heckscher Park in Huntington (631) 271-8423. Tomorrow, South Bound performs at 7:30 p.m. at Davies Park in Manhasset (516) 327-3110, while Thursday brings East Bound Freight to the Village Green in Westhampton Beach at 7:30 p.m. (631) 288-0780.</p>
        <p>On tour again, on Friday Glen Campbell comes to the Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts at 7:30 p.m. (631) 286-1133. Finally, Saturday demands decisions. Will it be Hugh Prestwood and Friends appearing in the Wine Country Concert Series 2000 at 6:30 p.m. at the Hargrave Vineyard in Cutchogue (631) 727-0900, or Ramblin' Jack Elliott headlining the Folk Music Society of Huntington's free concert at 8:30 p.m. at Heckscher Park in Huntington (631) 271-8423?</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Al Roker, the NBC weatherman, is the latest ''Writer at Guild,'' appearing at 2 p.m. (631) 324-0806.</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- Napoleon Revels-Bey Rhythm Kings Ensemble celebrates ''The Moorish Influence in Music'' at 7 p.m. at the Freeport Recreation Center (516) 223-2522.</p>
        <p>FRIDAY -- In ''Legendary Romances,'' the Sound Symphony plays music about love and romance at 7:30 p.m. on the grounds of the East End Arts Council on East Main Street in Riverhead (631) 727-0900.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- For a summer musical change of pace, how about some tunes from Victorian America? The Proper Ladies will sing them at 2 p.m. in the parlor of the 19th-century Village House on Village Lane in Orient. The music follows the annual Croquet Tournament at 10 a.m. (631) 323-2480.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
