<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soothing, Rural Landscapes; Haiti, Vivid and Sweetly Seen</title>
    <meta content="23ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bruce Museum (Greenwich, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weir, J Alden</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Robert C (Mrs)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DC103BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soothing, Rural Landscapes; Haiti, Vivid and Sweetly Seen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews A Connecticut Place: Weir Farm, An American Painter's Rural Retreat, and Haitian art from collection of Mrs Robert C Graham on view at Bruce Museum, Greenwich, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE wide attention that Weir Farm commands is out of proportion to its 60 acres in Wilton and Ridgefield. One reason for its fame is that it is the only national park in Connecticut. Another is that it is a proven, time-honored stimulus to art. The farm has been a home to artists since it was bought by the American Impressionist J. Alden Weir in 1882.</p>
        <p>In nearby Greenwich, the Bruce Museum's major summer exhibition -- ''A Connecticut Place: Weir Farm, An American Painter's Rural Retreat'' -- turns out to be an eye-opener, for it establishes Weir in the first rank of American artists of the era. The more than 70 works in the show also include paintings by notable visitors to the farm, pertinent items from his collection and some portraits done by Weir. Although now known as a landscape painter in the Impressionist mode, Weir made his living and early reputation as a portrait painter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE wide attention that Weir Farm commands is out of proportion to its 60 acres in Wilton and Ridgefield. One reason for its fame is that it is the only national park in Connecticut. Another is that it is a proven, time-honored stimulus to art. The farm has been a home to artists since it was bought by the American Impressionist J. Alden Weir in 1882.</p>
        <p>In nearby Greenwich, the Bruce Museum's major summer exhibition -- ''A Connecticut Place: Weir Farm, An American Painter's Rural Retreat'' -- turns out to be an eye-opener, for it establishes Weir in the first rank of American artists of the era. The more than 70 works in the show also include paintings by notable visitors to the farm, pertinent items from his collection and some portraits done by Weir. Although now known as a landscape painter in the Impressionist mode, Weir made his living and early reputation as a portrait painter.</p>
        <p>Weir studied in Paris, something that was a requisite for artists, in the 1870's and his portraits betray some current influences. He sometimes made compositions of black and gray that bring Whistler to mind. He frequently painted his family, and visitors can follow a poignant story.</p>
        <p>In 1883 he married Anna Baker but she died from complications giving birth to their second daughter, Cora, in 1892. The following year Weir married Anna's sister, Ella.</p>
        <p>Knowing these facts makes the full-length ''Baby Cora'' a compelling work. Ella Weir, sitting on the floor and wearing a black dress, supports a standing Cora on her knee. The baby's raised arms are in an awkward child's pose, yet they and her shimmering white dress stand for triumph.</p>
        <p>Monet is the obvious influence on the landscapes that are at the heart of the exhibition. Weir often achieved an all-over pale or whitewashed look, and this is very reminiscent of Monet. But Weir had his own peculiar and very hilly terrain in front of him in Connecticut, and this geological fact made him into something like a proto-Abstractionist.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of a painting, starting at the bottom, might be an vacant expanse. The eye is made to climb the hill to some incident at the top -- a simple gate, or something more unexpected in an ostensibly formal painting: clothes hanging on the line in ''The Laundry, Branchville.'' (Branchville, the 19th-century hamlet's name, remains the nearby Metro-North station's name.)</p>
        <p>More can occur in a Weir landscape than the usual inventory of natural forms and mundane evidence of life, such as gates and laundry. The exhibition includes a cunning, portable wooden shed Weir built himself to use as an all-weather painting studio. Monet had one, too. A painting of the portable shed parked in a shady depression is made stronger by the presence of the actual shed. One can imagine the Weir daughters coveting it as a playhouse.</p>
        <p>Of course, unusual divisions of space are a staple of Asian art, and it is widely known that its formal lessons were well-learned in Europe and America in the late 19th century. It is enlightening to come upon a couple of Japanese prints by Hiroshige and Utamaro that Weir owned. They fortify a strong but perhaps overlooked influence in spite of the fact that the Japanese were strong on line, and Weir's Impressionism tended to blur line. Weir tried his hand at a Chinese brush painting, and a modest example from 1893 is included in the show. Works done at the farm by several of Weir's contemporaries, including his brother John Ferguson Weir, are interesting in their own right, but they also make Weir look even better by comparison. The venerated Childe Hassam made his green too green, for example. The presence of a work by a painter regarded as an eccentric visionary, Albert Pinkham Ryder, is especially salutary. There is little mystical about the landscape, though when a viewer knows it's by Ryder, it has a disquieting glow.</p>
        <p>Weir's property might have had added allure because it was sometimes called the Land of Nod. The biblical designation has come to mean sleep, and although Weir's paintings do not make one drowsy in the least, they are especially soothing. This is where the Bruce's other summer show jumps in as a counterweight.</p>
        <p>''A Cultural Kaleidoscope: Haitian Art from the Collection of Mrs. Robert C. Graham'' is nothing if not intensely colorful, almost dizzyingly so. Despite all the well-known strife that has beset Haiti over several decades, the art from that place is always sunny, and this is a large part of its appeal. There exists naive Haitian art, the kind that tourists buy, along with a sophisticated sort distinguished by a strong color sense. What's in the Graham collection seems to be either sophisticated naive art or naive sophisticated art; the amalgam is quite satisfying. J. B. Bottex stands out because he unhesitatingly tackles biblical subjects literally. Eve being taken out of Adam's side is almost adorably sweet. Another, Wilson Bigaud, is a notch above the rest in sophistication. His still life featuring a fish being prepared for cooking is remarkable for its soft color and aspiration to volume over the customary linear pattern.</p>
        <p>''A Connecticut Place'' is at the Bruce Museum in Greenwich through Sept. 17. ''A Cultural Kaleidoscope'' closes Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
