<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlighting Racism Brings Anxiety As Well as Success</title>
    <meta content="23JONE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilman, Rebecca</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Spinning Into Butter (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DF113BF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlighting Racism Brings Anxiety As Well as Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with playwright Rebecca Gilman, who cmments on upcoming opening of her racially charged play Spinning Into Butter, directed by Daniel Sullivan, at Lincoln Center Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVERAL days before the New York opening of her racially charged play, ''Spinning Into Butter,'' Rebecca Gilman was sitting in a Manhattan hotel room, preparing to fax some last-minute script changes to Lincoln Center Theater and trying not to become consumed by worry. ''Everyone is walking around the theater looking very nervous and it's hard not to get caught up in all that,'' she said in a brief telephone interview, an uncharacteristic edge to her gentle voice. ''People's expectations have gotten very high. I worry that they will walk into the theater thinking I have the answers to all the problems of racism.''</p>
        <p>There was a long pause before she spoke again. ''I don't, you know.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVERAL days before the New York opening of her racially charged play, ''Spinning Into Butter,'' Rebecca Gilman was sitting in a Manhattan hotel room, preparing to fax some last-minute script changes to Lincoln Center Theater and trying not to become consumed by worry. ''Everyone is walking around the theater looking very nervous and it's hard not to get caught up in all that,'' she said in a brief telephone interview, an uncharacteristic edge to her gentle voice. ''People's expectations have gotten very high. I worry that they will walk into the theater thinking I have the answers to all the problems of racism.''</p>
        <p>There was a long pause before she spoke again. ''I don't, you know.''</p>
        <p>For those who have followed Ms. Gilman's career from its abrupt beginnings at a tiny storefront theater in an unfashionable Chicago suburb, this nervous talk of high expectations and answers to large social issues seems incongruous.</p>
        <p>But then the 35-year-old Ms. Gilman's life -- and the stakes therein -- have suddenly changed. As recently as late 1997, this Alabama-born graduate of the University of Iowa's playwriting program was working as a temporary employee in a Chicago accounting firm and writing plays by night. There had been no major productions of her work and the only thing growing in her professional life was the stack of rejection letters from theaters across the country.</p>
        <p>Within the last two years, however, she has received numerous major awards and commissions, including the American Theater Critics Association's Osborne Award and the London Evening Standard Award for most promising playwright (Ms. Gilman was the first American dramatist to win). And then there are the recent offers of work from Hollywood studios.</p>
        <p>After the world premiere of ''Spinning Into Butter'' at the Goodman Theater here last season, Ms. Gilman found herself balancing bids from the Manhattan Theater Club, the Joseph Papp Public Theater and Lincoln Center Theater, all vying to be the first to present her work in New York.</p>
        <p>''Spinning Into Butter'' traces the reaction of the white administrators of a fictional New England college to the news that an African-American freshman has been receiving anonymous threatening letters. Desperate to keep it from the news media and self-serving in their attempts to deal with the problem on campus, the administrators display a lamentable lack of knowledge about the life of the student receiving the notes.</p>
        <p>Reaction to the piece in Chicago focused on a second-act monologue delivered by the central character, Sarah Daniels, the dean of students. Upset by events personal and professional, she snaps in front of a colleague and confesses her own racism in a 20-minute speech. Since the character has been empathetic and the racism is expressed using language and logic often favored by liberals, some audience members have typically found that it comes very close to their own unacknowledged perceptions. It was this monologue in particular that garnered the play unusual attention in the media.</p>
        <p>Despite the tacit wishes of the Goodman, which had hoped to see its production, directed by Les Waters, remounted with the original cast in New York, Ms. Gilman opted for Lincoln Center Theater, which sought a separate production. After its artistic director, Andre Bishop, had seen the Chicago version, he chose Daniel Sullivan as the director and gave Mr. Sullivan freedom to cast as he saw fit. At the director's request, Ms. Gilman has made ''substantial changes'' in the script for New York. ''I went back,'' she said, ''and tried to methodically think out the characters' emotional geography.''</p>
        <p>The play, which is being presented in association with Lincoln Center Festival 2000, opens on Wednesday at the Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater with Hope Davis in the lead role. The other cast members are Daniel Jenkins, Henry Strozier, Brenda Wehle, Matt DeCaro (who was in the original production), Jai Rodriguez and Steven Pasquale.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the reaction to Mr. Sullivan's production, ''Spinning Into Butter'' is already scheduled at so many regional theaters that it will be among the most produced new American plays in the 2000-01 season. And it will bring in some healthy royalty checks for its hitherto impoverished author. ''I guess it would be good to have some success,'' Ms. Gilman said in a conversation in Chicago several weeks ago. ''But I have never thought of that as being important to me.''</p>
        <p>It may be time to start. ''Boy Gets Girl,'' Ms. Gilman's most recent play, about a young professional woman whose blind date turns into a devastating encounter with a stalker, will be produced next year at the Manhattan Theater Club with the original Chicago cast. And in its first season in its new home in downtown Chicago, the Goodman will present the third premiere of a Gilman play in as many years. Scheduled to open in May 2001 and dealing with an obviously commercial topic, ''The Great Baseball Strike of 1994'' is billed as a darkly comic political look at the issues behind the labor dispute that threatened the future health of the sport.</p>
        <p>No other local playwright has had such support and exposure from the Goodman since David Mamet enjoyed similar patronage in the 1970's and 80's. ''We put up a lot of new playwrights on the Goodman's stages,'' said Robert Falls, the theater's artistic director. ''But there have been many times in the past when I have put an author out there whom I believed in, only to find myself the lone supporter. What has been rather pleasant is that our audience has responded so warmly to Rebecca. They bought tickets in droves to 'Boy Gets Girl' and 'Spinning Into Butter.' In my time, no new plays at the Goodman have ever been as successful.''</p>
        <p>The play that caught the Goodman's interest was Ms. Gilman's 1997 drama, ''The Glory of Living.'' A tale of child abuse and serial murder, it is based on a case in Ms. Gilman's native Alabama. It involved a 15-year-old who found herself married to an older man whose sexual proclivities included the kidnapping and subsequent murder of vagrant teenagers. Since his young wife was persuaded to do much of the procuring, she subsequently became the youngest woman ever sentenced to death in the state. In Ms. Gilman's hands, the events are a relentless indictment of what the playwright described at the time as ''America's inability to let children be children.''</p>
        <p>First presented in a memorably intense production at the tiny Circle Theater in Forest Park, Ill., and later produced at the Royal Court Theater in London, the drama attracted the attention of the new-play office at the Goodman, which has commissioned most of Ms. Gilman's later efforts, including ''Spinning Into Butter.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilman's body of work, with its disparate styles and subject matter, does not permit easy categorization. ''Spinning Into Butter'' deals with racial objectification. ''Boy Gets Girl'' is about troubled relationships between the sexes. And a lengthy but moving 1999 play called ''The Crime of the Century'' chronicles the lives -- and deaths -- of the young nurses who were killed by Richard Speck, a notorious Chicago murderer of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>MOST of Ms. Gilman's plays, despite their dark thread of humor, are shot through with explicit scenes and images of violence, examples of interpersonal exploitation gone awry, and explorations of the consequences of failed communication.</p>
        <p>''The subject matter is bold but her approach is traditional storytelling,'' said Mr. Sullivan, the director, about Ms. Gilman's plays. ''Audiences are hungry for that now. There has been a steady theatrical diet of disjunctive abstractions and various ruminations of one kind or another. We've had so many thematically based plays, so many character-driven pieces. There's a hunger for plays that are stronger in narrative.''</p>
        <p>While a number of critics have agreed, others have had problems. In his mixed review of the Chicago version of ''Spinning Into Butter'' in The New York Times, Peter Marks ascribed ''admirable idealism'' to the play, but also found the author's earnestness trying. ''It's as if the playwright had been forced to comply with the Equal Time Rule,'' Mr. Marks wrote. ''She is as eager as a 'Nightline' producer to book all the representative points of view.''</p>
        <p>Given her nervous laugh and slight stature, the modest Ms. Gilman would seem to have little in common with the archetypal television producer. She also seems an unlikely author of violent works. Reluctant to offend her benefactors, she appears ill at ease at having to referee demands for her time and attention. In person, she is a mixture of reticence and candor. Over the last three years, in a number of interviews in various settings, her style has never changed. Her demeanor suggests a lack of comfort with talking about her work and a sense that she believes her thoughts cannot have much importance. And yet she usually surprises her questioner by her ability to stand outside -- and then comment upon -- herself.</p>
        <p>There are some clues in her biography. Ms. Gilman's Jewish father came from Boston and her Southern Baptist mother from southern Alabama (her parents met at the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa), and the family lived in Trussville, near Birmingham. Ms. Gilman was the youngest of four children. Asked whether her childhood was a happy one, she said both ''yes'' and ''not really'' in the same breath.</p>
        <p>''My dad was about the only Jew in Trussville,'' Ms. Gilman said. ''It always felt like we didn't quite fit in. Nobody was overtly mean or anything, but people tended to judge us without knowing about us. They made a lot of assumptions.''</p>
        <p>During her two years at Middlebury College in Vermont (the model for the school in ''Spinning Into Butter''), Ms. Gilman said she struggled with the same sense of dislocation she included in the play. ''I didn't come from Tobacco Road,'' she said. ''But I never felt comfortable where almost everyone was from New England and liked to ski. There was just a big cultural difference between me and everyone else.''</p>
        <p>So she went back to Birmingham, where she had a boyfriend, and eventually graduated from Birmingham Southern College. After graduate work at the University of Virginia, she got into the Iowa playwriting program, married and then quickly divorced. She now lives in Chicago with her partner, Charles Harmon, an English professor at Loyola University.</p>
        <p>Her own experiences, Ms. Gilman said, have sparked her interest in writing about objectification -- both from the point of view of those doing the objectifying and those suffering from it. Her new play about baseball (she is a lifelong fan of the sport) elaborates on these ideas by focusing on what happens when athletes lose their individuality and become hyped commodities.</p>
        <p>''The play is based on the strike, but I am taking some fictional liberties,'' Ms. Gilman said. ''Baseball players can become objects to people just as easily as anyone else.''</p>
        <p>THEATER Chris Jones writes about touring and Midwestern theater for Variety.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Chris Jones writes about touring and Midwestern theater for Variety.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
