<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fading Jewish Haven</title>
    <meta content="23WOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEYANA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Woodbine (Nj)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Woodbine Brotherhood Synagogue (Woodbine, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DE163AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fading Jewish Haven</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WOODBINE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article traces history of once thriving Jewish community of Woodbine, NJ, whose last vestige of its original late-19th-century Jewish agricultural community, Woodbine Brotherhood Synagogue, is about to be sold; Woodbine is now largely black and Hispanic; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Uniglicht remembers gliding down the streets of this small town in the wooded interior of Cape May County as if it were yesterday.</p>
        <p>''You'd go down Washington Avenue, that was the main street, and you would pass Collier's Department Store and Singers Barber Shop and Grossman's grocery,'' said Mr. Uniglicht of his childhood in the 1950's and 60's. ''Down Adams Avenue, there was Siegel's kosher butcher. Outside the town center were Franklin's children's clothing factor and the Rabinowitz Hat Factory and Bradstone's, where rubber for sneakers was manufactured.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Uniglicht remembers gliding down the streets of this small town in the wooded interior of Cape May County as if it were yesterday.</p>
        <p>''You'd go down Washington Avenue, that was the main street, and you would pass Collier's Department Store and Singers Barber Shop and Grossman's grocery,'' said Mr. Uniglicht of his childhood in the 1950's and 60's. ''Down Adams Avenue, there was Siegel's kosher butcher. Outside the town center were Franklin's children's clothing factor and the Rabinowitz Hat Factory and Bradstone's, where rubber for sneakers was manufactured.</p>
        <p>''It was a Jewish community, a wonderful close-knit community,'' he went on. ''I can't think there was a better way to grow up.''</p>
        <p>None of those shops and factories are left in Woodbine, which is largely black and Hispanic today. Now, the last vestige of Woodbine's origins as a late-19th-century Jewish agricultural community may also fade into history. The Woodbine Brotherhood Synagogue on Washington Avenue in the center of the borough -- on the National Register of Historic Places -- is under an agreement of sale. Another synagogue, Tefares Israel, was razed in the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Uniglicht, who is chairman of the synagogue's board of trustees, said it was decided to have the building -- the same one where his grandparents were wed in 1906 -- put up for sale while still well maintained.</p>
        <p>While there have been no weekly services there since the 1970's, the synagogue has remained opened for High Holy Days services every fall, with nostalgic visitors and vacationers at the shore a few miles away joining the shrinking population of Jews here for the traditional prayers.</p>
        <p>That is far from the thriving Jewish community that used to inhabit Woodbine. In 1891, a local judge sold 5,300 acres of Dennis Township to the Baron Maurice De Hirsch Fund for $37,500. Baron De Hirsch, a Frenchman, believed that the Jewish community in America would thrive if it got out of the cities and back to its agricultural roots.</p>
        <p>''He recruited his people from New York and Philadelphia and Chicago, Eastern European Jews who were already here,'' said Joseph Brandes, a professor emeritus of history at William Paterson University, who wrote ''Immigrants to Freedom: Jewish Communities in Rural New Jersey since 1882'' (University of Pennsylvania Press). ''He also thought it should be a balanced community, and so the farmers wouldn't loaf in the winter, he encouraged factories.''</p>
        <p>While there were other De Hirsch communities in Southern New Jersey -- Brotmanville, Rosenhayn, Alliance, Norma and Carmel near Vineland -- none of them were as prominent as Woodbine, which was the only one that was not just a place name, but also an incorporated borough.</p>
        <p>''A writer in 1907 called Woodbine the first self-governed Jewish community since the fall of Jerusalem,'' said Dr. Brandes. ''It became a prototype for the New Deal balanced communities like Roosevelt near Trenton, with the hope of having agriculture and industry combine.''</p>
        <p>But in fact, agriculture was not all that was happening in Woodbine.</p>
        <p>''It was sandy soil and had to be cleared of dense forest,'' said Rachel Rodgers, the executive director of the Cape May County division of culture and heritage. ''It was full of mosquitoes and scrub bushes, horrible conditions for agriculture. So the factories did a lot better.''</p>
        <p>The De Hirsch Fund established an agricultural high school here, which taught the physical sciences and had a roll of graduates who eschewed the land and became doctors and scientists. Gregory Pincus, an early developer of the birth-control pill, attended the De Hirsch school, as did Selman A. Waksman, who developed streptomycin, one of the first cures for tuberculosis. The school has long since become the Woodbine Developmental Center for the handicapped.</p>
        <p>For decades, the Jewish community thrived here.</p>
        <p>''People came here happily,'' said Mr. Uniglicht, who today is an administrator at the Woodbine center. ''It was far better than being in the dirty city.''</p>
        <p>Sitting in William Eisenberg's Haddonfield law office is the loving cup his grandfather, also named William, was awarded by Woodbine's citizens in 1922 after serving as the town's mayor.</p>
        <p>''My grandfather was a mason and helped to build the synagogue,'' said Mr. Eisenberg, whose family moved to Collingswood before he was born. ''My father and most of the family is buried in the cemetery there. So it's nostalgic for me. But things started to dissipate even before World War II.''</p>
        <p>The Depression did not help the factories here, though most managed to stay afloat during those times. And as children went off to war and to college, they could not imagine returning. In the late 1940's there was one more surge of interest: Legend has it that residents here smuggled weapons out of Millville Airport to the Hagannah resistance movement before Israel was formed in 1948.</p>
        <p>''But then the suburban Jewish exodus started, too,'' said Dr. Brandes. ''Jews naturally wanted to be in communities with other Jews and, primarily, moved to the places around New York and Philadelphia.''</p>
        <p>The places Mr. Uniglicht revered -- Singer's and Collier's and the Rabinowitz Hat Factory -- were all closed by the 1970's. The hordes that came from all over South Jersey to eat deli at Siegel's found other places to go. Even Mr. Uniglicht, though he works in Woodbine, moved to Vineland years ago.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Uniglicht, the decision to hold the last services at the synagogue was not a hard one. ''There isn't a Jewish community here,'' he said. ''We had a nice reunion on the 100th anniversary of the synagogue in 1993. It has been nice to have services here, but Jews also have to focus on the future.''</p>
        <p>Scott Novick, who lives in Cape May Court House a few miles away, has bid for the building and has a tentative closing date in the fall. Mr. Novick has told residents that he intends to keep it functioning as a synagogue, though he has not elaborated.</p>
        <p>The Borough of Woodbine and the State Police had considered buying the building and converting it to office space, but balked when consultants put the buying price and the cost of renovation at about $500,000.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Eisenberg put it, ''Those people in the graveyard who escaped oppression in Europe would have haunted the place if people in shiny boots and revolvers were in there anyway.''</p>
        <p>JERSEYANA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
