<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Quieter Immigration Debate</title>
    <meta content="23SUN1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DE153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Quieter Immigration Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial finds a few years of prosperity, tight labor market and growing activism by immigrant groups have forced end to anti-immigrant political rhetoric that was common theme in 1996 election campaigns</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The politics of immigration, though less prominent than in 1996 when anti-immigrant policies were ascendant in Congress, remain an important element in this year's presidential campaigns. Over the last decade, for example, California has registered one million new voters, most of them Hispanic. Next year it is expected to become the first big state where ethnic and racial minorities are the majority, a shift driven largely by new immigrants from Latin America and Asia.</p>
        <p>So it is no surprise that Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore are making overtures to immigrant communities that may provide the swing vote in California, Texas, Florida and New York. But they are doing so in an atmosphere far calmer than in the mid-1990's, when immigrant-bashing was in vogue and Gov. Pete Wilson of California pushed successfully for Proposition 187, which prohibited illegal immigrants from attending public schools and getting social services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The politics of immigration, though less prominent than in 1996 when anti-immigrant policies were ascendant in Congress, remain an important element in this year's presidential campaigns. Over the last decade, for example, California has registered one million new voters, most of them Hispanic. Next year it is expected to become the first big state where ethnic and racial minorities are the majority, a shift driven largely by new immigrants from Latin America and Asia.</p>
        <p>So it is no surprise that Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore are making overtures to immigrant communities that may provide the swing vote in California, Texas, Florida and New York. But they are doing so in an atmosphere far calmer than in the mid-1990's, when immigrant-bashing was in vogue and Gov. Pete Wilson of California pushed successfully for Proposition 187, which prohibited illegal immigrants from attending public schools and getting social services.</p>
        <p>A few years of prosperity, a tight labor market and growing activism by immigrant groups have forced a change in the political rhetoric. Increased enforcement, including a recent doubling of the size of the border patrol, has also tempered fears about an unlimited flow of illegal immigration. But there is still a need to examine whether current policies adequately meet the demand for skilled workers and humanitarian goals like family reunification.</p>
        <p>Much of the debate in the 1990's focused unproductively on the size of legal immigration. Whether the number of people allowed in is cut by 100,000 or increased by 100,000 is not the most crucial question in a nation of 270 million. More important is whether and how the roughly 800,000 legal immigrants who come annually can join the economic mainstream once they arrive. Some immigration experts would welcome more skilled workers who can enrich the economy through their talents and tax revenues. Others would reduce the low-skilled immigrants whose presence helps drive down wages of low-skilled native workers. Cutting the total number of unskilled immigrants would probably mean reducing family-based immigration quotas, a change that would trouble Hispanic and Asian Americans.</p>
        <p>A more politically viable approach may be to increase visas for skilled workers without cutting family quotas. Ultimately, reducing the impact on low-skilled native workers means improving their education and skills, a priority that should be met regardless of immigration policy.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there are several important changes needed in existing laws that deny basic legal protections to immigrants. In 1996, Congress made it harder for asylum seekers to enter the United States. Congress also stripped the courts of their power to review arbitrary decisions by immigration officers and mandated the deportation of legal immigrants for even minor criminal offenses committed decades ago. Immigrants whose countries refuse to take them back are now locked up indefinitely in federal detention.</p>
        <p>So far, the candidates have focused mostly on useful proposals to reform the Immigration and Naturalization Service. Mr. Gore also supports legislation to grant permanent residency to some 500,000 immigrants who have been in legal limbo since the mid-1980's. But if Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are concerned about fairness, they should be pushing hard to repeal cruel laws that deny immigrants due process of law, impose hardships on thousands of immigrant families and make America less hospitable to asylum seekers fleeing persecution.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
