<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barriers Come Tumbling Down, to Joy and Consternation</title>
    <meta content="23BARR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CLINTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Streets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7D8173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barriers Come Tumbling Down, to Joy and Consternation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Transportation Department, after consultations with police, decides to remove pedestrian barriers erected on Eighth Avenue between 45th and 46th Streets as part of plan to curb growing pedestrian and vehicular traffic in congested areas of city; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Department of Transportation installed pedestrian barricades on Eighth Avenue between 45th and 46th Streets last March, city officials said they would be permanent. But about two weeks ago, the barriers came down.</p>
        <p>''After consulting with members of the community and N.Y.P.D., it was decided that we would remove the pedestrian barriers,'' said Mark Patterson, a department spokesman.  He declined to discuss why the barriers were removed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Department of Transportation installed pedestrian barricades on Eighth Avenue between 45th and 46th Streets last March, city officials said they would be permanent. But about two weeks ago, the barriers came down.</p>
        <p>''After consulting with members of the community and N.Y.P.D., it was decided that we would remove the pedestrian barriers,'' said Mark Patterson, a department spokesman.  He declined to discuss why the barriers were removed.</p>
        <p>The barricades were erected as part of a city plan to curb growing pedestrian and vehicular traffic along congested areas citywide. In addition to the barricades, the transportation department relocated a bus stop two blocks north, installed traffic lights and put a midblock crosswalk on Eighth Avenue. Those actions resulted in a public outcry by residents who said the impediments would do more harm than good.</p>
        <p>''Certainly it didn't stop people from walking in the street,'' said State Senator Thomas K. Duane, who wrote letters to the mayor opposing the barricades. ''It really didn't seem to make any difference to traffic. The only thing it did was inconvenience pedestrians who live in the neighborhood, work in the neighborhood or were visiting.''</p>
        <p>When Community Board 4 heard about plans for the barricades this year, members complained they would endanger elderly and handicapped tenants who live nearby by fencing them off from the streets. They also feared accidents if delivery trucks pulled into crosswalks to unload. But mostly, board members said, they felt ignored.</p>
        <p>''We were not consulted in their being up, and we were not consulted upon their removal,'' said Walter Mankoff, co-chairman of the board's transportation planning committee. ''We certainly thought it was inappropriate in this particular location, and I'm pleased that they were taken down.''</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: CLINTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
