<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Installing a Floor-Mounted Toilet: A Tight Seal Is Important</title>
    <meta content="LICLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DB173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Installing a Floor-Mounted Toilet: A Tight Seal Is Important</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INSTALLING a floor-mounted toilet -- as opposed to the type mounted on a wall -- is not difficult, but it has to be done carefully and methodically or else the toilet will leak.</p>
        <p>Before buying a new toilet, remove the old one and measure the ''rough-in'' dimension. This is the distance from the wall behind the toilet to the two closet bolts projecting up from the floor flange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INSTALLING a floor-mounted toilet -- as opposed to the type mounted on a wall -- is not difficult, but it has to be done carefully and methodically or else the toilet will leak.</p>
        <p>Before buying a new toilet, remove the old one and measure the ''rough-in'' dimension. This is the distance from the wall behind the toilet to the two closet bolts projecting up from the floor flange.</p>
        <p>The rough-in is the amount of space that you need to fit the new toilet in. Some toilets need a 12-inch rough-in, while others require a 13-inch rough-in. The new toilet can have a shorter rough-in -- this will provide extra space behind it -- but it cannot have a longer rough-in. So it is better to have some extra space than too little.</p>
        <p>The most common type of floor-mounted toilet comes in two pieces, the bowl and the tank. This is sometimes called a close-coupled toilet.</p>
        <p>The other type of toilet has the bowl and tank joined in one piece.</p>
        <p>The installation procedure for both types is the same, but it is harder to install a one-piece toilet simply because the unit is heavier than the close-coupled model.</p>
        <p>It is essential that an installed toilet remains fixed and immobile. A toilet that tilts or pitches, even slightly, when someone uses it indicates that the joists and supporting floor are weak. These should be braced before installing the new unit.</p>
        <p>When you purchase a new toilet and get it home, remove the wrapping and look carefully at all parts to make sure there are no cracks or defects.</p>
        <p>Possible defects include a deformed inlet (the opening between the bowl and tank), a warped horn (the outlet piece that projects from the base of the toilet) or a misshapen base.</p>
        <p>Also make sure that all the hardware as well as the tank mechanism is included. Keep the carton, wrapping material and all paperwork in case you have to return a defective unit.</p>
        <p>When you remove the old toilet, the flange will still be screwed to the floor with two closet bolts projecting upward through slots in the flange. You can use these, provided they are in good condition. If the bolts are rusted or corroded, they should be replaced. You will have to buy new closet bolts, as they are not part of the hardware kit that comes with the new toilet.</p>
        <p>You will also have to buy a wax gasket. The gasket forms the seal around the toilet horn and prevents leaks. Plumbers differ on whether it is better to place the gasket onto the horn and then push the toilet in place on the floor flange, or to position the gasket on the flange and lower the toilet onto it. Either method will work, provided you maneuver the toilet carefully onto the flange to avoid damaging or distorting the soft wax gasket. Turn the bowl upright and lower it slowly onto the closet bolts.</p>
        <p>Some books suggest that you press down hard with your full weight to seat the bowl and shape the gasket to make a watertight seal. If you try this, be very careful to apply even pressure to the toilet rim. If you lean too hard on one side, you will distort the wax gasket and it will eventually leak. Also be careful of applying too much pressure; this could also distort the gasket.</p>
        <p>A better way to seat the bowl is by tightening the nuts on the closet bolts. Start on one side and give the nut five or six turns then move to other side and do the same. Repeat this alternate tightening routine until the bowl is snug to the floor. Do not overtighten these nuts or you could crack the bowl.</p>
        <p>The next step is to mount the tank onto the bowl.</p>
        <p>The installation procedure for the tank is straightforward; detailed instructions should be included with the toilet hardware.</p>
        <p>Invert the tank so the large opening, the flush-valve outlet, mates with the inlet opening on rear of the toilet rim. Push the two tank bolts through the bottom the tank and bowl rim. Align the tank so it is parallel with the rear wall, then tighten the bolts. Hook up the supply tube to the inlet opening under the tank and turn on the water.</p>
        <p>The last step is to draw a bead of caulk around the base of the toilet and the finish floor.</p>
        <p>It is a good idea, however, to wait a week before doing this. This will allow time for you to inspect the toilet base for any leaks that may occur around the wax seal. With the caulk bead in place, these leaks may be blocked and run under the floor where they will remain undetected until the water damages the space below.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
