<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Parsley on Its Own as the Main Ingredient</title>
    <meta content="CNFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DB173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Parsley on Its Own as the Main Ingredient</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PARSLEY rarely plays a leading role in a dish. Most often it serves as a useless piece of decoration. ''It takes up little space in the literature of food, probably because it is so ubiquitous that it has become commonplace,'' Waverly Root wrote in ''Food.'' ''Its presence is so much taken for granted that nobody remarks on it.''</p>
        <p>There are two main kinds, the curly leaf variety, which is used as a garnish, and flat-leaf Italian parsley, which has a stronger flavor and can hold its own as a central ingredient.  It makes a refreshing side salad, tossed with olive oil and lemon juice and seasoned with coarse sea salt. It is also delicious chopped and mixed with capers, anchovies and lemon as a dressing for grilled vegetables.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PARSLEY rarely plays a leading role in a dish. Most often it serves as a useless piece of decoration. ''It takes up little space in the literature of food, probably because it is so ubiquitous that it has become commonplace,'' Waverly Root wrote in ''Food.'' ''Its presence is so much taken for granted that nobody remarks on it.''</p>
        <p>There are two main kinds, the curly leaf variety, which is used as a garnish, and flat-leaf Italian parsley, which has a stronger flavor and can hold its own as a central ingredient.  It makes a refreshing side salad, tossed with olive oil and lemon juice and seasoned with coarse sea salt. It is also delicious chopped and mixed with capers, anchovies and lemon as a dressing for grilled vegetables.</p>
        <p>At the River Cafe in London, parsley is served on spaghetti with pancetta and Parmesan cheese. The recipe below is adapted from ''River Cafe Green'' by Ruth Rogers and Rose Gray, which has just been published by Random House in Britain. It is good either as a first course or a main dish, perfect for summer.</p>
        <p>Curly parsley may be maligned for its lack of flavor, but it's wonderful deep-fried. Served this way, it turns into a garnish you actually want to eat, not push to the side of your plate.</p>
        <p>Spaghetti With Parsley, Pancetta and Parmesan  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons unsalted butter  3 medium onions, chopped</p>
        <p>1/2 pound pancetta, sliced and cut in  1/4-inch pieces, plus 6 thin slices  2 cloves garlic  Coarse sea salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  2 dried red chilies, crumbled  1 cup chopped Italian flat-leaf parsley  Olive oil  1 pound spaghetti  Freshly grated Parmesan.</p>
        <p>1. Melt the butter in a heavy saucepan. Add the onion and cook over medium heat for 15 to 20 minutes, then add the chopped pancetta and garlic. Turn heat down low, stir and continue cooking for 10 minutes more. Season generously with salt, pepper and chilies. The mixture should be quite dark. Add the parsley, stir and turn off the heat.</p>
        <p>2. Heat a small frying pan. Brush it with olive oil and fry the slices of pancetta until they are crisp. Drain.</p>
        <p>3. Cook the spaghetti in six quarts of boiling water until al dente. Drain, keeping back two to three tablespoons of cooking water. Toss the spaghetti with the parsley mixture, adding a little pasta water to help the sauce coat the strands. Serve each portion topped with a slice of pancetta and grated Parmesan.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Parsley Salad  Total time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>1 large bunch Italian parsley (about 4 cups, loosely packed)</p>
        <p>1/2 to  3/4 cup extra-virgin olive oil  Lemon juice to taste  Coarse sea salt and freshly ground pepper  1 pint cherry tomatoes, cut in half.</p>
        <p>1. Pick the parsley leaves off their stalks, rinse and spin them dry. Put them in a salad bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Combine the olive oil and lemon juice and season to taste with salt and pepper. Just before serving, toss the parsley in the dressing. Divide it among four plates and garnish with cherry tomatoes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Grilled Summer Vegetables With Parsley Dressing  Total time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>4 Japanese eggplant  4 zucchini  2 red peppers  Coarse sea salt  1 cup extra-virgin olive oil  2 tablespoons capers  2 anchovies, preferably salt packed  1 shallot, minced  1 cup Italian parsley, chopped  1 lemon  Freshly ground pepper.</p>
        <p>1. Cut the eggplant and zucchini in horizontal slices and sprinkle them with salt. Put the slices in a colander and leave them for 30 minutes to drain off the bitter juices. Cut the peppers in quarters and press them flat on a plate.</p>
        <p>2. Preheat grill. Wipe the eggplant and zucchini dry with paper towels and brush them lightly with a little of the olive oil. Grill them on both sides and put them on a serving dish. Grill the peppers and put them in a paper bag for a few minutes, then peel off the skin. Slice the peppers and put them on top of the vegetables.</p>
        <p>3. Meanwhile, soak the capers in water to cover for five minutes.  Drain, rinse and chop. Chop the anchovies. Combine them in a bowl with the capers, the shallot, parsley  and lemon juice. Add the remaining olive oil and mix well. Season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>4. Pour the mixture over the vegetables and serve at room temperature.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
