<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping Their Eyes On High-Tech Fortunes</title>
    <meta content="MB003847" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS: DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFDF153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping Their Eyes On High-Tech Fortunes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Survey of 150 people who work in high-tech industry, have household income of at least $300,000 and net worth of at least $3 million finds only 54 are age 55 or older, by 89 percent said they had a will, and 75 percent had a complete estate plan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans who have grown rich in high-technology industries are highly likely to have made plans to preserve their wealth and to pass it along to their heirs, the United States Trust Company found in an annual survey.</p>
        <p>This year's survey was limited to people who work in high-tech, have an annual household income of at least $300,000 and a net worth of at least $3 million -- levels that put them in the top 1 percent of all Americans in both categories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans who have grown rich in high-technology industries are highly likely to have made plans to preserve their wealth and to pass it along to their heirs, the United States Trust Company found in an annual survey.</p>
        <p>This year's survey was limited to people who work in high-tech, have an annual household income of at least $300,000 and a net worth of at least $3 million -- levels that put them in the top 1 percent of all Americans in both categories.</p>
        <p>Just 54 of the 150 participants were 55 or older. But 89 percent of the total said they had a will, while 75 percent had a complete estate plan, which may include trusts; 72 percent had set aside money for the education of their children or grandchildren; and 70 percent had a written financial and tax plan. The participants had worked an average of 22 years in high-tech; their average age was 48.</p>
        <p>Over all, the group was quite generous to charities, donating an average of 6 percent of income. Americans in general give about 2 percent of their income to charity each year, with nearly half of that going to religious organizations, according to research by the National Center for Charitable Statistics.</p>
        <p>Among the high-tech wealthy, the most common recipients of gifts were human services charities; 69 percent of the respondents reported such donations. Close behind were educational and religious organizations.</p>
        <p>The survey also showed that some people paid a fairly high price in amassing their fortunes. All 134 respondents who had children said that building wealth had come at some expense in their relationship with them; 29 percent said the toll was substantial. Of the married respondents, 27 percent said their work took a significant toll on their relationship with their spouses. And 22 percent of all those surveyed said there was a significant adverse effect on their health.</p>
        <p>DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS: DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
