<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>July 16-22; Making Margin Calls in a Tightening Race</title>
    <meta content="23BOXA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4D6143AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>July 16-22; Making Margin Calls in a Tightening Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the album of Campaign 2000 cliches, get ready to paste in, ''Too close to call.''</p>
        <p>It's a term that Americans are likely to hear frequently this year, as strategists and journalists weigh in with state-by-state analyses of the treacherous electoral map that confronts Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the album of Campaign 2000 cliches, get ready to paste in, ''Too close to call.''</p>
        <p>It's a term that Americans are likely to hear frequently this year, as strategists and journalists weigh in with state-by-state analyses of the treacherous electoral map that confronts Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>The early conventional wisdom? It's too close to call.</p>
        <p>Swing states in the presidential race like New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Ohio, Illinois, Michigan, Missouri and Washington are all rated as tossups or moving only marginally toward Mr. Bush, who is strongest in the South and Rocky Mountain states, or toward Mr. Gore, whose support is heaviest on the East and West coasts. Factor in the participation of third-party contenders like Patrick J. Buchanan and Ralph Nader, and it's hard to conclude anything except: it's too close to call.</p>
        <p>The tightness of the race has, if anything, intensified the guessing game of who the candidates will choose as their running mates. With the Republican convention set to begin in Philadelphia in eight days, most of the attention is on Mr. Bush's choice, which the governor said he will make imminently.</p>
        <p>A leading contender is Richard B. Cheney, the former defense secretary in the Bush administration. Other names mentioned frequently include the Republican governors of two big industrial states, Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania and George E. Pataki of New York, as well as Senator Chuck Hagel of Nebraska, Gov. Frank Keating of Oklahoma and former Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole.</p>
        <p>And then, of course, there is the name with star power, Senator John McCain of Arizona, who was reported to be softening in his opposition to accepting the vice presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Gore was making his case for the presidency in Mr. Bush's own backyard, traveling to Texas to criticize his rival's reign as governor, which got some Texans' dander up. ''Texas isn't nearly as backward and third world as the Gore campaign would make us out,'' said Michael Levy, the publisher of Texas Monthly magazine. Proud of its homegrown candidate, Texas is probably not too close to call.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
