<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; Real Elections Can Be Dangerous to Dictators</title>
    <meta content="23SUN3$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Democracy (Theory and Philosophy)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7D6143AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; Real Elections Can Be Dangerous to Dictators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tina Rosenberg Editorial Observer column muses on dictators and elections</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Communist general secretaries to Latin American generalissimos, dictators have long confirmed their rule with what they called ''elections.'' Occasionally, however, autocrats hold somewhat free elections -- and to their great embarrassment, they sometimes lose. Augusto Pinochet in Chile, Ferdinand Marcos in the Philippines, the Sandinistas in Nicaragua and the Communists in Poland in 1989 were all voted out of office. Now another undemocratic group, Mexico's Institutional Revolutionary Party, has lost an election.</p>
        <p>In some cases, this unexpected respect for the people's will came from those within ruling parties -- like  President Ernesto Zedillo in Mexico -- who sincerely wanted to modernize and democratize their nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From Communist general secretaries to Latin American generalissimos, dictators have long confirmed their rule with what they called ''elections.'' Occasionally, however, autocrats hold somewhat free elections -- and to their great embarrassment, they sometimes lose. Augusto Pinochet in Chile, Ferdinand Marcos in the Philippines, the Sandinistas in Nicaragua and the Communists in Poland in 1989 were all voted out of office. Now another undemocratic group, Mexico's Institutional Revolutionary Party, has lost an election.</p>
        <p>In some cases, this unexpected respect for the people's will came from those within ruling parties -- like  President Ernesto Zedillo in Mexico -- who sincerely wanted to modernize and democratize their nations.</p>
        <p>But others, including many in Mexico's PRI, had no intention of relinquishing power. They wanted the internal legitimacy, diplomatic recognition, foreign aid or increased trade that comes with winning elections, and they were certain they would win because the very habits of authoritarianism allowed them to delude themselves about their own popularity. They forced people to march in their rallies and shout their slogans, and then they believed what they saw and heard.</p>
        <p>In Mexico, for example, the PRI pressured newspaper and television news editors not to report on pre-election polls that showed the party's candidate, Francisco Labastida, trailing Vicente Fox. Perhaps that is one reason Mr. Labastida told a television interviewer after the election that he never dreamed he would lose until he saw the exit polls.</p>
        <p>The election of the first non-Communist government in the East bloc in 1989 illustrates how dictators imprison themselves with their own repression. The Polish Communists convinced themselves they could beat Solidarity in a real election.</p>
        <p>Poland was in economic collapse. Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski decided to legalize the banned Solidarity movement, give it a share of power and use it to rally support for price hikes and plant closures.</p>
        <p>He thought the party could contain Solidarity in part because regional party officials, who were his main source of information, dutifully reported that the average Pole rejected Solidarity. General Jaruzelski was sure he could persuade Poles not to blame the party for their poverty. He fervently believed that more and better speeches produced more and better Communists. The head of the Communist labor unions was sure he could win a televised debate with an uneducated electrician named Lech Walesa.</p>
        <p>They erred. In elections the next year, Solidarity won 99 of 100 seats in the Senate, and all the 161 seats it was allowed to contest in the lower house -- familiar numbers in East bloc elections, now with a new twist.</p>
        <p>Autocratic systems isolate the men at the top. When General Pinochet held a plebiscite in 1988, he and his acolytes could not conceive of losing. They lived in luxury apartments or bucolic estates. But they could not see that the boom they enjoyed was not shared. The poor, whose consumption levels had dropped steadily, were invisible -- in part because bus fares were so high people could not leave the slums to beg.</p>
        <p>Hijacking a vote count -- or worse, annulling an election gone awry -- is costly for dictators interested in legitimacy. It is very visible, and by the time a dictatorship is defeated, democratic forces have usually acquired a momentum that is hard to stop. Autocrats prefer subtler forms of manipulation -- bribing voters, intimidating the opposition, blocking  voter registration and monopolizing television. They design rules to allow them to keep power even if they lose. Robert Mugabe in Zimbabwe controls the appointment of 30 members of Parliament. In Cambodia, Hun Sen's electoral rules in 1998 allowed him to convert minority popular support into a parliamentary majority.</p>
        <p>Until the world can organize a conspiracy of pollsters who will assure autocrats that they are so beloved that they can afford to call off the thugs and give the opposition equal television time, it must take manipulation of the campaign climate and election rules as seriously as election-day fraud. No election with these flaws should be declared ''free and fair,'' as a United Nations-sponsored group termed Hun Sen's 1998 victory.</p>
        <p>Recently, monitors from the Organization of American States pulled out of Peru before the electoral runoff because the campaign had been so orchestrated. Nevertheless, the O.A.S. accepted Alberto Fujimori's re-election. A spotlight on campaign abuses will help only if outsiders are serious about defending democracy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
