<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Billboards Go Digital, Who's In Control?</title>
    <meta content="23BILL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lexus Division of Toyota Motor Sales Usa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7D9173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Billboards Go Digital, Who's In Control?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Lexus car ad, projecting continuous loop of razor-sharp animated graphics onto loft building in lower Manhattan's NoHo Historic District, brings criticism; it is not yet clear which city agency has jurisdiction over this new form of advertising; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Large billboards once required the touch of artisans to paint every detail. More recently, they were mechanically printed onto vinyl canvases and hung wherever a nail could be secured. Now advertisers can erect billboards just by turning on a switch.</p>
        <p>Using technology created for digital film projectors, advertisers in recent weeks have blanketed facades in Manhattan with commercials selling cars, clothing and electronic gadgets. Over the Fourth of July weekend, Lexus, the car maker, projected a continuous loop of animated graphics onto 439 Lafayette Street, a loft building inside the NoHo Historic District. From afar, it looked as if a 50-foot-tall television set had been affixed to the wall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Large billboards once required the touch of artisans to paint every detail. More recently, they were mechanically printed onto vinyl canvases and hung wherever a nail could be secured. Now advertisers can erect billboards just by turning on a switch.</p>
        <p>Using technology created for digital film projectors, advertisers in recent weeks have blanketed facades in Manhattan with commercials selling cars, clothing and electronic gadgets. Over the Fourth of July weekend, Lexus, the car maker, projected a continuous loop of animated graphics onto 439 Lafayette Street, a loft building inside the NoHo Historic District. From afar, it looked as if a 50-foot-tall television set had been affixed to the wall.</p>
        <p>The new ads have alarmed some advocacy groups that say the projection technique invites advertisers to penetrate untapped spaces while allowing them to skirt regulations that apply to traditional billboards.</p>
        <p>''This has the potential to further degrade cityscapes,'' said Kent Barwick, president of the Municipal Art Society. ''With this technology, it's not even necessary to touch the building. You just plug it in and turn it on.''</p>
        <p>While traditional signs require building permits, it is not clear which city agency has jurisdiction over these ephemeral billboards. Michael Hamer, a freelance producer hired to coordinate several projections, said he spent several months being bounced around various city agencies while trying to obtain approval for his work.</p>
        <p>''It's so new that nobody knows how to handle it,'' he said. ''We didn't build anything or block off any streets, so we were able to circumvent the city agencies.''</p>
        <p>Paul Wein, a spokesman for the Department of Buildings, agreed, saying the existing regulations were ''virtually unenforceable'' against these kinds of billboards.</p>
        <p>For the Lexus billboard, Mr. Hamer simply signed a $15,000 contract with the building owners to rent their wall for four nights. ''It's comparable to the monthly rate for permanent signage,'' he said. For a West Village billboard, he parked his equipment truck on the street and fed the meter while the projector ran.</p>
        <p>Although projected billboards are arguably as old as drive-in movies, the new device uses a silicon chip embedded with millions of tiny mirrors. When a video signal is sent, the chip produces a razor sharp image that is reflected and magnified.</p>
        <p>Marc Herring, president and chief executive of the Herring Media Group, the agency that created the Lexus commercial, called the projector a realization of ''the futuristic 'Blade Runner' mythology where buildings come to life with messages.''</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
