<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Joe Eszterhas; The Id That Had Polyps</title>
    <meta content="23NITE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eszterhas, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Rhapsody (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D9173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Joe Eszterhas; The Id That Had Polyps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Post-theater scene described after screenwriter Joe Eszterhas joins actors in reading from his book American Rhapsody at Douglas Fairbanks Theater in New York City; photo (Pulse column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEORGE W. was getting into full stride and pulling some pretty decent laughs. Bill Clinton was making some comic headway explaining the cosmic unfairness of the whole Monica thing. (''A little reward. Just a little reward. A piece of angel food cake to recharge my batteries.'') Monica told all, once again, to Linda Tripp. And Joe Eszterhas, sitting front row center at the Douglas Fairbanks Theater on Monday night, listening to the words of his ''American Rhapsody'' wash over him, expertly delivered by seven actors, looked like a happy man.</p>
        <p>Or maybe not. Mr. Eszterhas's normal facial expression is clenched. Even in repose, if that's the word, it looks furious. His attire -- baggy black pants and a short-sleeved black shirt open almost to the navel -- seemed designed to dissipate the heat of a temperament permanently on the boil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEORGE W. was getting into full stride and pulling some pretty decent laughs. Bill Clinton was making some comic headway explaining the cosmic unfairness of the whole Monica thing. (''A little reward. Just a little reward. A piece of angel food cake to recharge my batteries.'') Monica told all, once again, to Linda Tripp. And Joe Eszterhas, sitting front row center at the Douglas Fairbanks Theater on Monday night, listening to the words of his ''American Rhapsody'' wash over him, expertly delivered by seven actors, looked like a happy man.</p>
        <p>Or maybe not. Mr. Eszterhas's normal facial expression is clenched. Even in repose, if that's the word, it looks furious. His attire -- baggy black pants and a short-sleeved black shirt open almost to the navel -- seemed designed to dissipate the heat of a temperament permanently on the boil.</p>
        <p>Tina Brown, the editor of Talk magazine, tried to take the measure of her star guest in her opening remarks to the audience she had summoned. She settled on the notion that to understand Mr. Eszterhas -- onetime Rolling Stone reporter and the author of screenplays like ''Flashdance,'' ''Basic Instinct'' and, always and forever, ''Showgirls'' -- one must understand that he is an idealist. ''He is not a jaded ex-hippie  or a tired celebrity,'' she said, as Mr. Eszterhas sat there, looking like a jaded ex-hippie and tired celebrity. ''You can think of him as the id of American culture.''</p>
        <p>The id had drawn a fun crowd. Talk, the magazine famous for still believing that something called synergy exists, excels at putting together events at which e-commerce tycoons talk earnestly with hip-hop producers. ''American Rhapsody,'' Mr. Eszterhas's personal channeling of the Clinton years, a blend of reporting, transcribing and fantasizing, seems tailor-made for Talk. It's Hollywood and Washington, politics and celebrities, and this night, it was New York, too.</p>
        <p>Drinking post-performance Champagne, the crowd milled in front of the theater. There was Carolyne Roehm, gliding past Pete Peterson, who bumped up against George Stephanopoulos, who did not seem to be rushing over to chitchat with Peggy Noonan. Mr. Stephanopoulos surely  would have something fascinating to say about ''American Rhapsody,'' in which the presidential penis becomes a character named Willard. But whatever Mr. Stephanopoulos was thinking, he was not about to share it with a reporter.</p>
        <p>Sonny Mehta, the editor in chief of Knopf, which published ''American Rhapsody,'' talked earnestly with Ed Victor, the agent for the book. Mr. Victor, aglow in a tan linen suit and shocking black and white spectator shoes, described the manuscript vividly. It poured forth from Mr. Eszterhas like lava from Mount St. Helen's. ''It blew me away,'' Mr. Victor said. Erica Jong, George Plimpton, James Atlas, Joni Evans and Harry Evans were there, giving a literary gloss to the affair. Suddenly the doors to the theater opened, and Mr. Eszterhas emerged, puffing madly on a cigarette and hugging his very pregnant wife, Naomi.</p>
        <p>After breaking free from photographers and scribling scribes, Mr. Eszterhas retreated to a corner of the theater lobby and reviewed the evening. ''George Bush just exploded on stage,'' he said admiringly. His own performance, limited to a brief reading, he dismissed with a wave of his cigarette. ''I've done very few readings,'' he said. ''It's a problem for me, because I have bad polyps on my sinuses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eszterhas wrote the book, he said, during a period of seclusion brought on by disgust at living a too-public life. Now, the book was starting the cycle all over again. And on top of that, polyps. ''Faulkner once referred to the writer's puny and inexhaustible voice,'' he said. ''It's getting puny already. Now we'll see how inexhaustible it is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
