<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Drives On With Grand Slam in Sight</title>
    <meta content="23GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D9153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Drives On With Grand Slam in Sight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ST. ANDREWS, Scotland, July 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tiger Woods leads after third round of British Open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Tiger Woods stood on the precipice of golf history. David Duval hoped to stand in the way.</p>
        <p>No matter what happens during Sunday's final round of the British Open, it will be memorable. Woods, 24, who ended today's third round holding a six-stroke lead, could become the youngest player to win the career Grand Slam. But Duval, the world's No. 2-ranked player, will be paired with Woods in the final group -- a showdown between No. 1 and No. 2 that will be their first pairing together in a major championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Tiger Woods stood on the precipice of golf history. David Duval hoped to stand in the way.</p>
        <p>No matter what happens during Sunday's final round of the British Open, it will be memorable. Woods, 24, who ended today's third round holding a six-stroke lead, could become the youngest player to win the career Grand Slam. But Duval, the world's No. 2-ranked player, will be paired with Woods in the final group -- a showdown between No. 1 and No. 2 that will be their first pairing together in a major championship.</p>
        <p>Cameras will click. Fans will roar. Emotions will run high. But only one player will hoist the precious claret jug, symbolic of winning the game's oldest major championship, on the Old Course at St. Andrews, recognized worldwide as the home of golf.</p>
        <p>Who could ask for more? Heading into the final round, Woods will not need to ask for strokes. Shooting a third-round 67, his third consecutive round in the 60's, Woods was 16 under par for the tournament (67-66-67--200) six strokes ahead of both Duval (10 under par, 70-70-66) and Thomas Bjorn of Denmark (69-69-68). Darren Clarke, Loren Roberts and David Toms were tied for fourth place at nine under par, but anyone further behind could probably kiss their chances of winning goodbye.</p>
        <p>Realistically, even Duval and Bjorn are long shots to catch Woods, who has won 18 of 20 professional tournaments that he has led after three rounds. And if Woods wins, he will complete the career Grand Slam, adding the British Open to his three other major championships -- the Masters (1997), the PGA Championship (1999) and this year's United States Open, which Woods won by a record 15 strokes. Only four other players have won all four modern majors -- Gene Sarazen, Ben Hogan, Jack Nicklaus, and Gary Player.</p>
        <p>Woods also has a chance to break the British Open record to par, 18 under, set by Nick Faldo at St. Andrews in 1990. Will Woods feel pressure Sunday? You bet. But does he think he can handle it?</p>
        <p>''The bigger the lead, the more pressure you feel,'' said Woods, who had a 10-stroke lead after three rounds of this year's United States Open, and who held a nine-stroke lead after three rounds of the 1997 Masters. ''I know the public has wanted to see No. 1 and No. 2 against each other in the final round of a major championship, and now they will see it. If you don't end up winning, you're not going to feel too good about yourself. But I've had big leads before, and I've been able to succeed. We will see tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>That is what Duval hoped to do, and he put himself in contention despite playing the entire tournament with a sore back. And Duval did not hide his excitement about teeing off against Woods.</p>
        <p>Asked the advantage of being in the last twosome against Woods, Duval said: ''You get to look him in the eye. If I can swing the golf club like I have the last few days and putt like I have, I can show him I've got a little game going right now, too. Absolutely, it would mean more to beat him. I want you to know that when you're at your best, I can beat you. That may sound cocky, but it's simply wanting to compete at the highest level. I'm going to be trying to win my first major championship, and he's going to be going for the career Grand Slam. So there's going to be some pressure on both parties. But yes, I'm excited. How could I not be?''</p>
        <p>Throughout his news conference, Duval stood to relieve the pain in his back, which he injured shortly after the United States Open. Duval is not sure how he sustained the injury, but he was in less pain today than at any time during the tournament. And it showed in his game, as Duval birdied four of his first nine holes to roar into contention, then secured his spot in the last group with a birdie at No. 18.</p>
        <p>Duval's tee shot at the par-4 18th was well right and nearly sailed out of bounds. But it kicked left after hitting the ground and it stayed in play, allowing him to hit a nice pitch shot from 75 feet that set up an 8-foot putt that he converted for birdie.</p>
        <p>Yet, Woods never relinquished the lead, and he doubled the three-stroke lead he began the day with. A crucial stretch came when Woods reached No. 8 at 11 under par, holding just a one-stroke lead over Steve Flesch, and a two-stroke lead over Duval, Ernie Els and Toms.</p>
        <p>Like a motorist stepping on the accelerator, Woods pulled away, making five birdies on his next seven holes. At the par-3, 175-yard No. 8, Woods hit a gorgeous 6-iron tee shot that landed 18 inches for the cup, then he tapped in for birdie. At the par-4 No. 9, Woods birdied again, hitting a 9-iron approach shot to 15 feet, then making the putt.</p>
        <p>At the par-4, 314-yard No. 12, Woods drove just short of the green, hit a splendid chip to 3 feet, then made the putt. At No. 13, he made a 20-foot putt for birdie, then at the par-5, 581-yard No. 14, he reached the green in two shots, then two-putted from 40 feet for birdie.</p>
        <p>Woods's streak of bogey-free holes at major championships ended at 63, when he three-putted for bogey at No. 2, and he also three-putted for bogey at No. 17. But Woods regained his six-stroke lead on the final hole, when he made a 10-foot putt for birdie and pumped his fist, knowing he had put himself in excellent position to win.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Els most likely lost his chance to win with a crucial double-bogey at No. 12, hitting his tee shot into the gorse. Els ended the day tied at eight under par with Flesch, who double-bogeyed No. 13, Tom Lehman, and Dennis Paulson.</p>
        <p>But all the pursuers would need help from Woods to win. Even if Woods shot par on Sunday, Duval and Bjorn would needed 66's just to tie.</p>
        <p>''He's not invincible, but he's playing great,'' Clarke said of Woods. ''He is going to be very, very difficult to beat.''</p>
        <p>So Woods had a six-stroke lead to sleep on, a showdown with Duval to look forward to, and perhaps a victory speech to deliver. Woods hoped to seize the moment. And after three rounds of superb and strategic golf, he appeared on the verge of seizing a special victory.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
