<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Public Health Meets Public Relations in the Battle of the Bugs</title>
    <meta content="23TOWN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bergen County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rockland County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D8153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Public Health Meets Public Relations in the Battle of the Bugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>PLEASANTVILLE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on contrasting policies regarding spraying of mosquitoes in Rockland County, NY, and Bergen County, NJ; Rockland has active spraying program in response to concerns about West Nile virus, but across border in Bergen County, while there is increased surveillance for virus, there are no plans for widespread spraying; public is of two minds about spraying, with some people demanding spraying and others demanding no spraying (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WEST NILE II, the summer sequel, was ready to air. Television cameras recorded the trucks waiting to roll from Westchester County's fire training center, and a demonstration run of a pesticide truck had been held in time for the late news.</p>
        <p>Then, with midnight approaching on Thursday, the driver of a beige pickup stopped on a dark road here and pushed a button. With that, the spraying was under way. The pump on the back of the pickup hummed, the truck's yellow lights flashed  and a plume of pesticides began settling on Pleasantville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WEST NILE II, the summer sequel, was ready to air. Television cameras recorded the trucks waiting to roll from Westchester County's fire training center, and a demonstration run of a pesticide truck had been held in time for the late news.</p>
        <p>Then, with midnight approaching on Thursday, the driver of a beige pickup stopped on a dark road here and pushed a button. With that, the spraying was under way. The pump on the back of the pickup hummed, the truck's yellow lights flashed  and a plume of pesticides began settling on Pleasantville.</p>
        <p>As a police car led the pesticide truck through sleepy streets, people reacted like unwitting extras in a science fiction movie. Drivers rolled up their windows and scooted away. A few residents clicked on their outside lights as the fog machine rolled by. Luis Rodriguez, who was outside on Vanderbilt Avenue, was urged into his truck by the police as the sprayer approached. He played his part beautifully, sitting in his truck bug-eyed as the sweet-scented haze melted away, muttering through a cracked window, ''It's a strange thing.''</p>
        <p>A half-year after navigating Y2K, we are in the grip of another threat that combines the specter of disaster with what may eventually be seen as overwrought drama. It's another group grope, not for a computer bug this time, but for a familiar insect once kept in check with a spritz of Off! and a slap. Uncertainty has bred an atmosphere of concern in some counties and crisis in others, in response to much the same threat.</p>
        <p>''It's a moving target in the night,'' said C. Scott Vanderhoef, the Rockland County executive. He ordered pesticide spraying along all 470 miles of roads in the town of Clarkstown on the recommendation of state and federal health officials, but he wonders how dangerous the virus really is. ''There's been no one who's been able to tell this county executive how big a threat this is to humans,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I got two calls this morning, both angry,'' Mr. Vanderhoef said. ''One lived in an area where there is spraying. She said, 'How dare you do this?' The other one was asking, 'Why aren't you spraying us? Are you waiting for a child to die?' ''</p>
        <p>Just across Rockland's border with Bergen County, N.J., the West Nile scare feels vastly different.</p>
        <p>Birds infected with the virus have been found in both counties. But Peter Pluchino, Bergen's 30-year veteran mosquito control officer, plans no widespread spraying. ''We wouldn't want to spray a residential area or spray into the air where there are no mosquitoes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mosquitoes have been such a scourge in New Jersey that the little buggers have not only been called the state bird, but also, a mosquito-control apparatus has been in place since 1914. The focus is on killing mosquito larvae year round -- a practice the rest of the New York region adopted after last year's West Nile outbreak -- rather than spraying adult mosquitoes, which New York City and surrounding counties are now doing.</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY has increased its surveillance for West Nile virus, but Mr. Pluchino said, ''The majority of the population really isn't at risk, as far as I know.'' Still, many people think that they are. These days, he said, ''any flying insect is a mosquito to most people.'' He added, ''People see a dragonfly on the screen and trap it in Tupperware until we get there.'' In Westchester, the state of readiness is palpable. Officials there decided to spray along 1,500 miles of roads -- or half the distance to California, if stretched end to end -- after finding the virus in two dead birds and a cluster of mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Joshua Lipsman, the county health commissioner, acknowledges that the virus isn't comparable to a public health threat like tobacco. But like a crime wave, it is potentially deadly and looms large in the public consciousness. He noted that last year there were 7 deaths, including one in New Rochelle, out of 62 known cases of serious illness, although a follow-up study estimated that hundreds more were infected with the virus but showed little or no effect.</p>
        <p>''It's new,'' he said. ''It's foreign. It's particularly unpredictable as to who could be hit next. And it's potentially deadly.'' Therefore, he said, it made sense to spray the pesticide, which he called ''fairly nontoxic.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said, attacking West Nile is a balancing act between minimizing fear and minimizing disease. With the public wary of pesticides, he said that spraying from trucks was preferable to the spraying from airplanes that took place in some areas last year. ''People's image of aerial spraying is like radiation fallout.''</p>
        <p>With uncertainty everywhere, it is not always clear where public health ends and public relations begins. When the Town Board of Lewisboro, citing environmental concerns, informed Westchester officials that Lewisboro did not want to be sprayed, the town supervisor, Thomas D. Herzog, said he was reminded that the county was in a health emergency. ''I think the powers that be don't want to have the accusations come back that they were negligent in protecting the public health,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
