<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hall Opens Its Doors to a Star Once Shunned</title>
    <meta content="Y23TUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baseball Hall of Fame (Cooperstown, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stearns, Norman (Turkey)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DA143AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hall Opens Its Doors to a Star Once Shunned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Norman (Turkey) Stearns, player in baseball's Negro National League; Stearns will be inducted into Baseball Hall of Fame this year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last spring, an off-Broadway theater presented ''Cobb,'' an intriguing play about a well-documented baseball icon from the early 20th century. Three actors portrayed Ty Cobb at different periods of his life. Meeting moments after the death of the Georgia Peach, the three Cobbs debated his athletic greatness, his racism and his fiery temperament.</p>
        <p>Drifting and chatting among them was an actor playing the role of Oscar Charleston, ''the Black Ty Cobb,'' who, like Cobb, is a member of the Baseball Hall of Fame in Cooperstown, N.Y. Charleston, the play suggested, might have been Cobb's equal but could not play against him in the major leagues because of racial restrictions that stood until 1947. The ghostly characters represented an element of American history that still haunts both the national pastime and the entire culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last spring, an off-Broadway theater presented ''Cobb,'' an intriguing play about a well-documented baseball icon from the early 20th century. Three actors portrayed Ty Cobb at different periods of his life. Meeting moments after the death of the Georgia Peach, the three Cobbs debated his athletic greatness, his racism and his fiery temperament.</p>
        <p>Drifting and chatting among them was an actor playing the role of Oscar Charleston, ''the Black Ty Cobb,'' who, like Cobb, is a member of the Baseball Hall of Fame in Cooperstown, N.Y. Charleston, the play suggested, might have been Cobb's equal but could not play against him in the major leagues because of racial restrictions that stood until 1947. The ghostly characters represented an element of American history that still haunts both the national pastime and the entire culture.</p>
        <p>That play came to mind last week because of what will take place at Cooperstown today. The annual Hall of Fame induction ceremonies will include Norman (Turkey) Stearnes, an outfielder from the Negro leagues who would be 99 years old if he were still alive. Stearnes had something in common with both Cobb and Charleston.</p>
        <p>Like Cobb, Stearnes played center field for a Detroit team in the early 1920's. Cobb was then the veteran star of the Detroit Tigers in the American League and Stearnes was the young star of the Detroit Stars of the Negro National League. When I interviewed Stearnes in 1979, two months before he died, I asked, ''Who was the best baseball player you ever saw?''</p>
        <p>Without hesitation, Stearnes said, ''Oscar Charleston,'' adding quickly that ''Joe DiMaggio was one of the best in the white league.'' He never played against Cobb, Stearnes told me, but he barnstormed against Babe Ruth's 1927 Yankees. He told me other things, too.</p>
        <p>''I sit in the bleachers, I know a lot of boys, and I have fun out there with them,'' he said, referring to his senior years as a fan in Tiger Stadium's center-field seats. ''We talk. We discuss things without fighting.'' Of baseball, in general, Stearnes said: ''It's a good game. It's the best game known. People like it. You go to see it, you'll enjoy it.''</p>
        <p>I have those quotes and others on an audio cassette from a Negro leagues reunion in Greenup, Ky., in 1979. Although better-known players attended, I worked for a Detroit newspaper then and Stearnes was our local angle. When I played that tape again last week, I also heard the voice of Stearnes's daughter, Joyce Thompson, who was with her ailing father during the interview. At the time, her father had cancer. He spoke in a thick accent of his native Nashville. He was hard of hearing, having worked in the roar of the foundry at the Ford Rouge plant for 27 years, so she helped keep the conversation going.</p>
        <p>Also on the tape, I heard the voice of Ray Dandridge, another Negro leagues star and Hall of Famer, who stopped by the table for Stearnes's autograph. During the conversation, Joyce voiced a poignant plea for her father. ''I wish he could get in the Hall of Fame,'' she said. ''At one point, there was talk about it. They never, ever follow through on it.''</p>
        <p>I had not talked with Joyce for more than 20 years, since her father's funeral. Last week seemed like a good time to call. ''I haven't cried in a long time,'' a joyful Joyce said from suburban Detroit, where she teaches deaf children. ''But I was talking to my daughter and I just started crying.'' Her daughter, a high school senior, is a basketball player, an athlete just like her grandfather.</p>
        <p>''I wish she could have known him,'' Joyce said. ''I wish he could have been here for his induction. People say, 'Better late than never.' Yeah, I guess. Better late than never.''</p>
        <p>Stearnes is the 17th Negro leagues player to be inducted. Also entering today will be Sparky Anderson, the former manager of the Detroit Tigers and Cincinnati Reds; Tony Perez, the first baseman on Anderson's Big Red Machine; Carlton Fisk, the catcher with Boston and Chicago; and Bid McPhee, an infielder for the Reds in the 19th century. I covered Anderson in Detroit and I like him, but Stearnes interests me the most. At that reunion in 1979, Stearnes kept his distance from most other Negro leaguers, who remembered his individualistic ways when he was a home run-hitting All-Star. Ray Sheppard, one of his Detroit teammates, said Stearnes ''was a peculiar guy.''</p>
        <p>''He was a loner,'' Sheppard said. ''He didn't run with anybody or fool around or drink. You couldn't use his bat or glove. Sometimes he didn't want a locker by you.''</p>
        <p>William (Judy) Johnson, a Hall of Famer from the Negro leagues, told me that Stearnes was very particular about his bat. ''If he made out, he'd sit there holding it and talking. 'I hit that good,' he'd say,' '' Johnson said. ''I believe sometimes he carried that bat to bed with him.''</p>
        <p>Others said Stearnes carried the bat to center field during pregame practice so that no one would borrow it. Highly paid at $600 a month, Stearnes watched for holes in the outfield fence and chased children back through them when they snuck into the ballpark without paying.</p>
        <p>His career ran from 1923 through 1942, and he also played for the Chicago American Giants and the Kansas City Monarchs, among other teams. Stearnes said he got his nickname as a boy because he had a pot belly and ran with his arms flapping. As a man, he was tall and lean with big, strong hands.</p>
        <p>His left-handed batting stance, others recalled, was odd, with his back foot in the bucket and his front foot raised. Statistics of Negro leagues players are incomplete, but it is believed that Stearnes led the Negro National League in home runs six times.</p>
        <p>Satchel Paige once called Stearnes ''one of the greatest hitters . . . as good as anybody.'' Cool Papa Bell once said of Stearnes, ''If they don't put him in the Hall of Fame, they shouldn't put anyone in.''</p>
        <p>And now he is in, with Paige, Bell, Cobb, Charleston, Ruth and DiMaggio. My knowledge of Stearnes is the shallow and fleeting kind of a journalist, but the memories of him are vivid and fond. In Detroit, we visited home plate at Tiger Stadium, the first time he had ever stepped on that field. We took a photograph in his batting stance, wearing a dress suit and hat. I sat next to him on the flight home from Kentucky. His daughter thought it was the first time he had traveled in the air, but Stearnes said he had flown previously with Paige and a team long before.</p>
        <p>A man born before the Wright brothers first flew at Kitty Hawk, Stearnes told me he preferred the peaceful rhythms of train travel and he recited station stops on the line to Los Angeles. For a while, with the jet engines humming, he closed his eyes and sang, in a low and melodic voice, about ''Old-Time Religion'' and ''My Country, 'Tis of Thee.''</p>
        <p>Another song, I don't know the title, included the lyrics ''long ago, long ago'' and ''everything's got to go.'' At one point, Stearnes stopped singing, opened his eyes, looked out the window and said suddenly: ''Lord, we're above the clouds. What man can do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
