<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bullpen and New Look Fail To End Cone's Skid</title>
    <meta content="Y23YAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0DF123AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bullpen and New Look Fail To End Cone's Skid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tampa Bay Devil Rays defeat New York Yankees, 12-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In desperate search of his second victory of the year, David Cone has experimented with every kind of adjustment, from tempo to grip to stance. Yesterday he rolled his newest concoction out of the lab: an Orlando Hernandez clone.</p>
        <p>Cone hiked his navy socks up high and adopted the El Duque high leg kick, hoping to change his luck, break his string of futility and recover his dignity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In desperate search of his second victory of the year, David Cone has experimented with every kind of adjustment, from tempo to grip to stance. Yesterday he rolled his newest concoction out of the lab: an Orlando Hernandez clone.</p>
        <p>Cone hiked his navy socks up high and adopted the El Duque high leg kick, hoping to change his luck, break his string of futility and recover his dignity.</p>
        <p>''I was looking for something different,'' he said with resignation. ''It was a semi-tribute to my idol.''</p>
        <p>Cone struck out the first two batters of the game, but he gave up a home run to the third, Greg Vaughn, and it was as if nothing had changed. Even so, he recovered and pitched effectively. He even retired nine straight batters, in the third, fourth and fifth innings. He gave up three runs and six hits, struck out five, and left after spotting the Tampa Bay Devil Rays a 3-2 lead.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' bullpen proceeded to unravel. Jeff Nelson and Jason Grimsley allowed five of the nine remaining runs, and the offense, no matter how much it was pressing to win for Cone, could not provide enough support to erase his loss.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay pounded the Yankees, 12-4, and Cone got the loss. His record dropped to 1-9 -- he hasn't won since April 28 -- and the Yankees have not won in his last 11 starts, a dismal franchise record that is destroying his pride.</p>
        <p>Even though he was much improved from his last outing, when he gave up six runs in five innings, Cone took no comfort in yesterday. ''It's not good enough,'' he said. ''I lost.''</p>
        <p>He paused. ''Again.''</p>
        <p>No matter the tinkering, he has not found his answer. ''It's a ball of confusion for me right now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he was not alone yesterday. ''Cone definitely pitched better than the end result,'' said Grimsley, who gave up Jose Canseco's double and back-to-back walks on eight straight pitches to begin the Devil Rays' seven-run eighth inning. ''We had a chance to win the ballgame and I didn't do my job. I didn't throw strikes.''</p>
        <p>Nor did Nelson, who came on in the seventh and allowed the Devil Rays to widen their lead to 5-2 by giving up two runs on two walks and a single. The Yankees had a chance to tie in the seventh inning, when Derek Jeter and Paul O'Neill each had run-scoring singles. With runners on first and third, Bernie Williams struck out on a contested at-bat.</p>
        <p>On a 2-1 pitch by the Tampa Bay left-handed reliever Mark Guthrie, Williams seemed to question Umpire Terry Craft's strike call, as did Manager Joe Torre. When Williams struck out, ending the inning, he turned to Craft and asked if he had fouled off the pitch. Guthrie walked off the field, seemingly telling Williams to keep quiet, and Williams mouthed that he was not addressing him. Lee Mazzilli, the Yankees' first-base coach, rushed to restrain Williams.</p>
        <p>Darrell Einertson relieved Grimsley in the eighth. He gave up two quick hits, and then Jeter's error on a force-out throw loaded the bases. After Vaughn fouled out, Fred McGriff knocked a single into center field. Williams ran slowly to the ball, assuming it would be a two-run single, but that allowed another run to cross. Bubba Trammell ended the scoring with a single that put the Devil Rays ahead, 12-4.</p>
        <p>Cone did not see the score, only his mistakes. ''It's a broken record,'' he said. ''We're not winning on days I pitch, regardless of what my personal numbers are.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have won just 5 of Cone's 18 starts this season.</p>
        <p>Yet, Torre was encouraged. ''I thought he was a lot better,'' Torre said. ''He pitched out of jams and his fastball had life. It was disappointing we let it get away.''</p>
        <p>The day began auspiciously for Cone. After his first two strikeouts though, he threw a 3-1 fastball to Vaughn, who belted it for a 1-0 lead.  ''That was a microcosm of my season,'' Cone said.</p>
        <p>It was the fourth straight game in which Cone had given up a home run, and his ninth allowed in the last three games.</p>
        <p>In the second inning, Cone gave up a leadoff walk to Canseco. After striking out Steve Cox, he gave up a ground-rule double to John Flaherty.  Miguel Cairo then fisted a singled past the left side of the infield to give Tampa Bay a 2-0 lead.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees inched back into the game. David Justice, playing left field again, singled in the second inning to extend his hitting streak to 10 games. Tino Martinez followed with another single and, after designated hitter Jorge Posada popped up to second base, Chris Turner, who has turned into Cone's personal catcher, helped his pitcher with a run-scoring single.</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch tied the game at 2-2 when he led off the third inning by cranking a 2-0 pitch from Tampa Bay starter Ryan Rupe (2-4) for his fifth home run of the season.</p>
        <p>Nothing is enough for Cone right now. ''I've got no quit,'' Cone said. ''I'm going to fight to the bitter end.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees made room for GLENALLEN HILL by designating outfielder FELIX JOSE for assignment. Hill came to the ballpark a half-hour before the game and joined the team on the bench in the second inning. . . . DENNY NEAGLE will try to record his 100th career pitching victory today as the series with the Devil Rays concludes at Yankee Stadium. . . . On a rehabilitation assignment, RAMIRO MENDOZA will throw 50 pitches tomorrow in a rookie league game in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
