<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Karen Kringel, Jeffrey Hoeh</title>
    <meta content="23KRIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRINGEL, MARY KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOEH, JEFFREY DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Karen Kringel, Jeffrey Hoeh</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mary Karen Kringel and Jeffrey David Hoeh were married yesterday at the Lehman Camp on Washington Island in Wisconsin. Judge Frederick P. Kessler, of the Milwaukee County Circuit Court, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, who is known as Karen, will keep her name. She is a first vice president of the Sentinel Real Estate Corporation in New York, and is also the company's creative director, overseeing its graphic design department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mary Karen Kringel and Jeffrey David Hoeh were married yesterday at the Lehman Camp on Washington Island in Wisconsin. Judge Frederick P. Kessler, of the Milwaukee County Circuit Court, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, who is known as Karen, will keep her name. She is a first vice president of the Sentinel Real Estate Corporation in New York, and is also the company's creative director, overseeing its graphic design department.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kringel, 33, is a daughter of Mary and Jerome H. Kringel of Shorewood, Wis. Her father is a partner in Michael, Best &amp; Friedrich, a Milwaukee law firm.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, also 33, is a lawyer with NBC in New York, where he advises its news department and television stations. He is also the content lawyer for ''Late Night With Conan O'Brien.'' He graduated from the Boston University School of Law. His mother, Sandra U. Hoeh of Milwaukee, is the assistant chancellor for university relations at the University of Wisconsin campus there. His father, David C. Hoeh (pronounced hoe), is an urban planning consultant in Louisville, Ky., where he lives with the bridegroom's stepmother, M. Brigid Sullivan.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom met when they were 13. ''He was the first boy I ever had a crush on,'' recalled Ms. Kringel, who said their dating lasted all of two weeks. ''It ended when my family went up to Washington Island for the summer, and I always wondered what happened to Jeff.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoeh said, ''The interest was always there.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kringel added, ''But we were busy doing our own thing.''</p>
        <p>Over the next 18 years, they kept bumping into each other, first as freshmen at the University of Wisconsin at Madison (where both graduated), once on a shuttle flight between Boston and New York, and once on the Upper West Side, where both were living.</p>
        <p>During that interval, he also married -- and divorced. In December 1997, they had a chance encounter at a West Village restaurant. They promised each other that they would get together but didn't until the following spring, when she called him to get his law firm involved in a fund-raiser for Sanctuary for Families, a New York organization that helps victims of domestic violence.</p>
        <p>Although the bride still thinks the meeting that followed was little more than a chance for two old friends to catch up, it quickly evolved into more than that. What began with drinks at the Royalton Hotel continued at a party held by a friend of the bride's, and then a nightcap, ending with a cab ride, which Mr. Hoeh thinks may have involved a good-night kiss. Ms. Kringel says it did not, but they agree that they talked about the possibility of his joining her on a business trip to Miami. They took the trip and have been together ever since.</p>
        <p>''You come to New York, and there are all these strangers who you meet in bars or through friends, but there's no history there,'' Ms. Kringel said. In their case, she said, ''you feel like it's fate that brought us together.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
