<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smitten by the Subway</title>
    <meta content="23FEAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models and Replicas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coppola, Philip Ashforth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kronenberg, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nisbett, Derek</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5DF143AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smitten by the Subway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York City subway buffs Philip Ashforth Coppola, who is devoting rest of his life to writing and publishing exhaustive, multivolume history of design and decoration of all 496 stations that ever existed in New York City subway system, Paul Kronenberg, who has mock-up of motorman's cab in his Brooklyn apartment, Derek Nisbett, who collects model subway cars, and David Pirmann, who runs subway Web site; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you have set foot on a subway platform during the last 20 years, there is a decent chance he has been standing there next to you, a small, smiling man in no hurry to catch a train.</p>
        <p>He was probably carrying a green satchel with a tiny American flag stitched on the flap. From this satchel, he probably produced a pair of junk store binoculars or a cheap camera and pointed them in the direction of a rust-stained wall that seemed to warrant neither close inspection nor documentation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you have set foot on a subway platform during the last 20 years, there is a decent chance he has been standing there next to you, a small, smiling man in no hurry to catch a train.</p>
        <p>He was probably carrying a green satchel with a tiny American flag stitched on the flap. From this satchel, he probably produced a pair of junk store binoculars or a cheap camera and pointed them in the direction of a rust-stained wall that seemed to warrant neither close inspection nor documentation.</p>
        <p>You probably did not notice him. He tends to fade into the tilework. And Philip Ashforth Coppola likes it that way. But once, on Aug. 29, 1978, he pinned a plastic envelope to his shirt, slipped a name tag inside and summoned up the courage to conduct his own private poll at four Midtown subway stations. He ''collared whoever looked like a likely candidate,'' as he later wrote, and with all the burning intensity of the Ancient Mariner, he asked a question:</p>
        <p>''Are you aware of the subway art?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coppola was talking about what he loved most in the world, the rivers of subterranean design -- in mosaic, faience, terra cotta, tile and steel -- that a grander generation of public builders had bequeathed the humble and hurried subway rider.</p>
        <p>The question was met mostly with blank stares that summer morning. But it mattered dearly to Mr. Coppola for a couple of reasons. One was that so many of his beloved treasures were either crumbling or being blithely buried in subway renovations.</p>
        <p>Another reason happened to be that Mr. Coppola, then on the verge of turning 30, a sometime dishwasher, a sometime printing press operator with little training in design and none in writing, had just decided to devote the rest of his life to writing and publishing at his own expense an exhaustive, multivolume, painstakingly detailed history of the design and decoration of every one of the stations -- 496, by his count -- that ever existed in the New York City subway system.</p>
        <p>In the pantheon of the New York City subway buff, a loose fraternity of urban transit fans who tend to begin in romanticism and veer into outright obsession, you could think of Mr. Coppola as the emperor of the obsessives.</p>
        <p>He does not, like one buff in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn, have a mock-up of a motorman's cab in his extra bedroom, supplemented with recorded sounds from the subway to make sitting in the cab more realistic.</p>
        <p>He also does not, like another buff in Fort Greene, Brooklyn, save money by driving a used Toyota Camry so he can buy expensive handmade model trains and turn his apartment into a miniature subway system.</p>
        <p>He certainly does not, like one veteran subway buff who tends to turn up at every Transit Authority function, sport a huge tattoo of a subway car on his bicep.</p>
        <p>But during almost a quarter of a century, what Mr. Coppola has done takes him beyond the bounds of even the most devoted railroad hobbyist. He has spent nearly every spare minute -- weekends, vacations, long nights too many to count -- haunting subway stations, libraries, archives, museums and microfilm readers in search of even the tiniest shards of fact for his masterwork.</p>
        <p>The danger, of course, was that he could have ended up another Joe Gould, the Greenwich Village eccentric who claimed to have written a nine-million-word opus called ''The Oral History of Our Time,'' largely drawn from overheard conversations and, in the end, largely existing in Mr. Gould's imagination.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Coppola, who is single and lives in Maplewood, N.J., was not just a dreamer. In 1984, after almost six years of hovering over his sketch pad and his I.B.M.  Selectric II, he self-published the first heavy volume of ''Silver Connections: A Fresh Perspective on the New York Area Subway Systems.'' Another volume appeared in 1990 and a third in 1994. The fourth and most recent, a thick digression that covers the design of the Manhattan and Hudson Railroad, the predecessor of the PATH train, came out last December. And after revising Volume I (''Simply far too much purple prose in that one,'' he says. ''Do not read too deeply into it.'') he plans to begin No. 5, which he hopes will appear in 2004 and will take the subway saga all the way up to 1915.</p>
        <p>Stacked on top of one another, the volumes, published in small batches, measure nine inches high. Not counting the mind-boggling bibliographies and indexes, they add up to more than 1,900 pages, several hundred thousand words and more than 1,000 of Mr. Coppola's hand drawings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coppola is now 52 years old.</p>
        <p>He has 404 more subway stations to go.</p>
        <p>''I always thought nine was a good round number, nine volumes,'' he says. ''Now I am not so sure.''</p>
        <p>He hopes his readers will like all of them, of course. But you get the sneaking sense from Mr. Coppola that his most devoted reader will always be Philip Ashforth Coppola. And this is perfectly fine with him.</p>
        <p>''Now if you're not the sort to be terribly concerned about whence there came the New York subway, nor how it came about,'' he writes in the introduction to Volume I, ''then I still suggest you keep this book on your bedside table, in case you can't sleep some night; I especially recommend my thoughts upon the extensions to the upper Broadway stations, found in my review of the 137th Street IRT station (pp. 338-341).''</p>
        <p>''A paragraph or two should send you off splendidly.''</p>
        <p>To outsiders, the world of the true subway buff, or rail fan, as many like to be called,  has never been easy to understand.</p>
        <p>Nearly every New Yorker has felt the fascination on some level. The subway -- ground was broken for it 100 years ago, in March 1900 -- has always represented a lot more than just a way to get around the city.</p>
        <p>It has represented, as much as the Statue of Liberty or the Empire State Building, the grandiose spirit of the city itself. (It remains the only subway system in the world that runs regular express trains. It is one of the few that run 24 hours a day.)</p>
        <p>The subway is also one of the best ways for New Yorkers to travel back into their own memories, to the old neighborhood, to the transit gloria of Ebbets Field and the Polo Grounds, to that rite of passage when they were finally grown up enough to ride by themselves. New Yorkers have made love in the subway. They have given birth in the subway. They have been married in the subway. They have missed their weddings stuck in the subway.</p>
        <p>And there are those buffs who remain simple romantics, drawn to the subject by a mix of nostalgia and municipal pride. These are the buffs we all know, the ones who have memorized the map, the ones who argue about the merits of the IRT over the BMT in an age when most commuters have no clue what the letters ever meant (Interborough Rapid Transit, now the numbered lines, and Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit, now part of the lettered lines).</p>
        <p>They are buffs like Stan Fischler, who has written four books on New York subways and trolleys and whose favorite subway facts are the personal ones, like how the old BMT ''standard'' cars had a jump seat that folded down so that a 5-year-old Stan Fischler could stand on it and poke his head all the way out the front window. Or how the old trains on the Brighton Line used to clack out a rhythm as they passed the Beverly Road curve that sounded exactly like the drumbeat in Benny Goodman's ''China Boy.''</p>
        <p>''When I first found out it was a nickel,'' said Mr. Fischler, a hockey analyst for the MSG Network, ''I said to myself, 'Oh my God, I'd pay five bucks for something like this, easy.' For a kid, it was paradise.''</p>
        <p>But the New York City subway system also tends to take its buffs to levels of fascination where most people would find the air growing thin.</p>
        <p>In many ways, they are no different from any other hardcore buffs: Trekkies; Civil War re-enactors; J. F. K. assassination buffs who come to blows over the role of the man with the umbrella in Dealey Plaza.</p>
        <p>But while the lure of those subjects is somewhat apparent, it is not as easy to figure out what motivates the dedicated rail fan.</p>
        <p>One of the telltale signs is that he -- and it is nearly always a he; most rail fans are male, middle-aged and single; the married ones call their wives ''rail widows'' -- can sit for hours watching slides of subway trains that look almost identical to the untrained eye. But the pictures of trains delight buffs the way pinned monarchs delight lepidopterists.</p>
        <p>At a meeting in June of the New York chapter of the Electric Railroaders' Association, a club formed in the early 1950's, about 200 people filled an auditorium at the College of Insurance in Lower Manhattan, where Harold Pinsker, a popular amateur train photographer, presented what the program called ''a mix of his best slides from the 1980's.''</p>
        <p>Such slides are known as roster shots. To the outsider, one thing becomes apparent about them immediately: there are no people in them. The aim of the perfect train shot is to show trains and only trains, with no passengers to block the view or scenery to distract the eye. (An Internet guide counsels: ''The main idea is to portray the locomotive in a very realistic and straightforward manner. Leave your artistic ambitions at home.'')</p>
        <p>The genuine rail fan also devotes as much of his vacation as possible to riding on and taking slides of subways around the world.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Pinsker's slides flashed on the screen that night, Charlie Akins, the longtime president of the rail club, whispered about his coming vacation to Budapest, where he would spend a week checking out Hungarian subways with a group of fans from around the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Akins, 54, a manager for the Social Security Administration, has also vacationed on subways in Hong Kong, London, Paris, Montreal and every American city that has one. (A rail-fan vacation guide warns about taking nonfans on such trips: ''If you want to be accompanied trackside by a spouse, child or buddy who doesn't like trains in an attempt to enlighten them as to the mystique of the rails, then by all means do so. But be forewarned, you do so at your own peril.'')</p>
        <p>Truth be told, even people who consider themselves steeped in the subway probably could not handle it.</p>
        <p>''Let's put it this way,'' Gene Russianoff said. ''Transit advocates are from Mars and transit buffs are from Venus. They're really two completely different types of people,'' Mr. Russianoff, a lawyer for the Straphangers Campaign, has been a subway advocate and a New York City subway expert for 20 years. ''I just can't sit there and hear about which cars are married pairs and which used a certain kind of lug nut.''</p>
        <p>Over the years, that kind of ardor has given rise to a list of less-than-flattering nicknames for rail fans. The most widely used term is foamer, which may have been first used by Amtrak employees to refer to rail fans who grew so excited when looking at trains they seemed to foam at the mouth. Another theory about the term was that it was adapted from the acronym Fomite, which stood for ''fanatically obnoxious mentally incompetent train enthusiast.''</p>
        <p>Other terms include glazer (eyes glaze over at sight of trains); gerf (glassy-eyed rail fan); and flim (foamer living with mother.)</p>
        <p>Even in England, with a long and distinguished history of train buffery, the term trainspotter has come to be a synonym for nerd or loser.</p>
        <p>In New York, Transit Authority employees privately use a much stronger term: fern, in which the ''r'' and the ''n'' stand for ''rail nut'' and the ''f'' does not stand for foamer.</p>
        <p>Many Transit Authority officials hold so dim a view of rail fans, in fact, that they do not like to comment publicly about them for fear that it will only encourage the more unstable among them, some of whom, officials complain, trespass or endanger themselves to get pictures of trains.</p>
        <p>Then there are the rail fans, nearly always loners, who love trains so much that they feel compelled to take them.</p>
        <p>Darius McCollum, probably the best  known, began at 15, persuading a motorman to let him drive an E train. Over the years, he frequently impersonated Transit Authority employees, commandeered buses and,  just this February, sneaked into a control tower at 57th Street and tripped the emergency brakes on an N train.</p>
        <p>''There are people who are interested in subways, and then there are people who are crazy,'' one transit official said. ''They tend to show up at any event where we're rolling out new equipment or making any changes in the system. You always know who it's going to be. And they don't look like regular human beings.''</p>
        <p>Rail fans become furious when the term subway buff is used in newspapers to describe someone who decides to steal a train. And the buffs cannot quite figure out why they seem to be lumped together, in the minds of transit officials and the public, with the criminally insane.</p>
        <p>''Guys who do that are not rail fans,'' said David Pirmann, a buff who created and has maintained a vast Internet compendium of New York subway history, lore and facts  (www.nycsubway.org). ''Guys who do that are crackpots and vandals, and they should be locked up for a long time.''</p>
        <p>Buffs also point out that if it were not for buffs, many of whom are or have been New York Transit employees, many pieces of history now in the authority's Transit Museum in downtown Brooklyn probably would have ended up in junkyards. In his book, ''The Subway'' (H&amp;M Productions II), Mr. Fischler relates the story of Frank Turdik, a transit employee who in the mid-1960's took several vintage cars about to be scrapped and hid them in an unused tunnel. The cars were preserved and are still around today, rolled out by the Transit Museum for special events.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people ask me how I can be so  into this,'' said Mr. Pirmann, 29, a systems management consultant in Manhattan. ''And I say: 'Look, it's a hobby. I mean, my parents collect little glass shoes. They must have 700 of them. This is what I do. You might think it's crazy, but I think it's cool.''</p>
        <p>There have been subway buffs ever since there has been a subway. But when the Transit Authority began to scrap many of the first subway cars after World War II, the obsession picked up speed.</p>
        <p>No one really knows how many buffs are out there now. The Electric Railroaders' Association has about 650 members in the city. Mr. Akins, the president, says a striking change over the years has been the growth in the number of members who are transit employees, apparently more bold now to admit that it is their passion as well as their job. The next largest club in the city, the New York Railroad Enthusiasts, whose interests extend to steam and diesel trains, has about 150 members.</p>
        <p>But there are probably thousands of subway buffs who will always remain uncounted, scattered throughout the city, the country and the world, because they prefer to nurture their fascination mostly in solitude.</p>
        <p>One is Derek Nisbett, an intensive case manager for the state's Office of Mental Health. Mr. Nisbett, 44, is the man who has bought more than 100 scale-model brass and plastic subway cars, costing about $500 each, and has been slowly turning his Fort Greene studio apartment into a miniature subway system. The crown jewel will be a set of elevated tracks that will circle his bed. ''I collect only subway trains,'' he said. ''Everybody who knows me knows that.''</p>
        <p>Another is Paul Kronenberg, 56, a math tutor in Sheepshead Bay. He is the man who has built the eerily realistic mock-up of a motorman's cab from an old IND train in his extra bedroom. The idea came to him when he was working near a Coney Island subway scrap yard in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>''Originally I just wanted the controller from a cab,'' Mr. Kronenberg said. ''Then I bought a brake stand, a door, a windshield, the brake boxes, the motorman's seat, a pressure gauge.'' He built the walls out of particle board and painted them the exact color of the old trains by mixing Sears paint with pigment.</p>
        <p>''Someone I knew saw it, and he said, 'When you drop dead and the authorities come in here and see this thing, you're going to make the newspapers,' '' he said. ''And I just kind of freaked out when he said that. But most people who know me don't think it's all that strange. They know I don't take it all that seriously.''</p>
        <p>Michael Vincze is perhaps the most isolated subway buff of all. He is incarcerated in South Woods State Prison in Bridgeton, N.J., where he avidly collects subway books and dreams about the Polo Grounds shuttle of his youth.</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to Mr. Coppola, who counts Mr. Vincze among his devoted readers. The prisoner has bought all four volumes of ''Silver Connections,'' and, like many of Mr. Coppola's fans from New York to Texas to Minnesota to Maryland, he has kept up a correspondence with the author for a decade, even while being transferred from prison to prison.</p>
        <p>''I really don't know much about him,''  Mr. Coppola said. ''I've never asked him why he's in prison. From what I can tell he has a fine mind and a nice personality. He knows a lot about the story of the subways.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coppola wants desperately to tell him the rest of the story, if only he can find time to tell it, between his job as a printing press operator and the care of his 90-year-old mother, Mary, with whom he has lived since his father, Joseph, died in 1974.</p>
        <p>The other day, wandering around the empty, cathedral-like Chambers Street station on the J line, one of his favorites, he was asked to explain why he loves the New York City subway enough to devote his life to it.</p>
        <p>After all, he never dreamed of growing up to be a motorman. He has spent nearly all his life in Maplewood, nowhere near a subway station. His father, who worked on Wall Street, hated the subway, avoided it whenever possible.</p>
        <p>''Why did I pick the subways?'' he says. ''Oh Lordy, that's a good one. I guess I felt like it needed a little public relations work, that's all. I thought it needed a voice. And then I just got hooked.''</p>
        <p>Or as his handwritten inscription in Volume III says, quoting from the Book of  Luke, ''For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.''</p>
        <p>TRACK FACTS  Are You Buff Enough?</p>
        <p>1. What is the longest subway trip you can take without changing trains?  2. What is the lowest subway station?  3. What happened on Malbone Street, in Brooklyn, on Nov. 1, 1918?  4. What was the name of the city's only private subway car?  5. Who owned the car?  6. Why can't you drive an A train through a No. 4 train tunnel?  Answers on Page 10. (pg. 9)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
