<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intricacies of I.M.S. Racing Not for Everyone</title>
    <meta content="23BOAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Measurement System</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7DB153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intricacies of I.M.S. Racing Not for Everyone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <dateline>NEWPORT, R.I., July 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses handicap racing in fleets under International Measurement System</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the past nine days, the steep green lawn overlooking Brenton Cove here at Harbour Court, the New York Yacht Club's Newport headquarters, has been host to scores of sailors competing in the club's second biennial Race Week.</p>
        <p>The front end of the split-format series of races was dedicated to handicap racing in fleets sailing under the International Measurement System and the Performance Handicap Racing Fleet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the past nine days, the steep green lawn overlooking Brenton Cove here at Harbour Court, the New York Yacht Club's Newport headquarters, has been host to scores of sailors competing in the club's second biennial Race Week.</p>
        <p>The front end of the split-format series of races was dedicated to handicap racing in fleets sailing under the International Measurement System and the Performance Handicap Racing Fleet.</p>
        <p>The latter half of the regatta, which was presented by Rolex and concluded today, featured dedicated one-design racing for 90 boats in 7 classes including J/35's, J/44's, Mumm 30's and New York 40's, all of which were using the event to stage their North American championships.</p>
        <p>In the 51-boat performance handicap division, Avalanche, a J/105 skippered by Craig Albrecht, took the honors for the week's best performance. The 34-boat I.M.S. field, which was contesting this year's Offshore World Championship, was split into cruiser-racer and racer divisions. The cruiser-racer title was won by the Farr 42 Mascalzone Latino, skippered by Vincenzo Onorato. The 42-year-old Italian shipping magnate also made shoreside news when it was reported that he was seriously contemplating an America's Cup challenge.</p>
        <p>But to find some sailors who have already racked up some cup miles, one only had to go as far as Craig Speck's Nelson/Marek 43, Vim 3, the winner of the I.M.S. racer class. The designer Bruce Nelson was aboard, as were the helmsman Terry Hutchinson and the crewman Moose McClintock. All three sailors played prominent roles in the San Francisco-based America One challenge in the last Cup.</p>
        <p>''I've known Terry for many years and Bruce was instrumental in all the changes we've made to the boat,'' Speck said.</p>
        <p>Like the old International Offshore Rule that preceded it, the I.M.S. rule -- which was established internationally in 1984 -- is no stranger to controversy, especially in the United States. ''Nobody's on the fence about it,'' said Ken Read, who called tactics on George David's Idler, a Nelson/ Marek 50, which finished second to Vim 3. ''People either love it or hate it.''</p>
        <p>Those who find the current state of I.M.S. racing less than satisfactory point to high costs, complex scoring configurations and a certain design fickleness that, in some cases, appears to fly in the face of nautical common sense. To obtain a more favorable rating, for instance, it sometimes pays to modify the boat in such a way that, in certain conditions, it becomes slower, not faster.</p>
        <p>''In general, in sailboat racing everyone's always trying to find ways to make their boat go faster,'' said Read, who will drive the New York Yacht Club's entry -- Dennis Conner's Stars &amp; Stripes -- in the next America's Cup. ''But a lot of times in I.M.S. that's not exactly the game you want to play.''</p>
        <p>Though the average sailor may scratch his head over such logic, in the I.M.S. Worlds the rule provided close racing, not an easy matter when the idea is to equitably rate -- and thus provide a level playing field for -- a fleet of boats ranging from 40 to 80 feet.</p>
        <p>''When the corrected times were sorted out, the gap between second and seventh place was frequently within 60 seconds,'' said the naval architect David Pedrick, who heads a committee that helps administer the rule.</p>
        <p>''I.M.S. is a purely objective means of handicapping yachts, based on physical measurements,'' Pedrick added. ''It's not for everyone, but I think it will continue to serve the more serious, aggressive racers.''</p>
        <p>And for some sailors, the challenge lies in the rule's intricacies. ''You've got to use a lot of technical know-how,'' Read said. ''Idler's owner, George David, is in the business of developing new technologies, so he loves tweaking a keel, or moving a mast back in a boat, and calculating what that's going to do to the rudder surface, and how to go from there. He enjoys the rule because of what it allows him to do and what it allows him to think of.''</p>
        <p>In the racer fleet here during the Worlds, Vim 3 got off to a quick start with three straight victories in the opening, around-the-buoys races, the first pair of which were sailed in Rhode Island Sound in brisk winds and big seas. ''We got rolling early in the regatta,'' Speck said. ''That really set the tone.''</p>
        <p>But Idler pulled back into contention with a third-place showing in the 128-mile distance race, which was counted more heavily in the standings. It set up what appeared would be a winner-take-all finale last Wednesday, but when racing was canceled because of a lack of breeze, Vim 3 was crowned the champion.</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
