<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protesters Warm Up; Mayor Upset; Los Angeles Ready for Democrats</title>
    <meta content="23ANGE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riordan, Richard J (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD9153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protesters Warm Up; Mayor Upset; Los Angeles Ready for Democrats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, July 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scores of would-be protesters at upcoming Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles bivouack in Malibu mountains at training camp to get pointers on protesting; Mayor Richard J Riordan has published stern warning against violent protest and nonviolent civil disobedience; police department has been thwarted in its plan to keep demonstrators fenced far away from entrance to convention; federal judge has called plan unconstitutionally restrictive; no one knows just what mischief loosely connected confederation of protesters with wide variety of issues might wreak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scores of would-be protesters have bivouacked in the Malibu mountains at a training camp featuring vegetarian cooking and classes in climbing skyscrapers. The mayor has published a stern warning against violent protest and nonviolent civil disobedience, with tough talk about rubber bullets and pepper spray, stiff fines and jail. And a federal judge has ruled that the police department's initial plan to keep demonstrators fenced far away from the entrance to the Democratic National Convention was unconstitutionally restrictive.</p>
        <p>Welcome to Los Angeles where, as usual, worlds collide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scores of would-be protesters have bivouacked in the Malibu mountains at a training camp featuring vegetarian cooking and classes in climbing skyscrapers. The mayor has published a stern warning against violent protest and nonviolent civil disobedience, with tough talk about rubber bullets and pepper spray, stiff fines and jail. And a federal judge has ruled that the police department's initial plan to keep demonstrators fenced far away from the entrance to the Democratic National Convention was unconstitutionally restrictive.</p>
        <p>Welcome to Los Angeles where, as usual, worlds collide.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, when civic leaders fought to get their first national political convention since the Democrats nominated John F. Kennedy here in 1960, they promised it would be a chance to celebrate the city's comeback from the plagues of the early 1990's with a four-day, internationally televised fiesta of the first order. But since then, practically nothing has gone as planned and the convention, Aug. 14 to 17, is shaping up as the biggest test in years for this sprawling, congested, divided city's mettle and its perpetually searching sense of itself.</p>
        <p>The City Council, all but 3 of whose 15 members are Democrats, has sought to block using city money to pay expected convention cost overruns, largely out of enmity for the convention's chief booster,  Mayor Richard J. Riordan, a Republican whom many of them loathe. The billionaire businessmen who promised to sponsor the convention have fallen to feuding in public. And no one knows just what mischief a loosely connected confederation of protesters whose concerns range from economic globalization to capital punishment, abortion, environmental justice, homophobia, housing and campaign finance might wreak.</p>
        <p>''The way to understand it, as one law enforcement official who I will not name told me, is like managing a week of peaceful, unlawful activity in order to keep it peaceful,'' said State Senator Tom Hayden of Santa Monica, the ''Chicago 7'' alumnus who says he finds in the protesters echoes of his 1960's radical roots. ''That's the challenge. The lawlessness is in the eye of the beholder, because it will be mostly misdemeanors, like blocking traffic and crossing against the light. I think it can be managed.''</p>
        <p>City officials, mindful of the recent protests in Seattle and Washington, have been less sanguine, and they went to federal court to fight an effort by the local chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union to overturn the security zone around the convention site at the downtown Staples Center as impermissibly broad. This week, in a sharp rebuke, Judge Gary Feess ruled that the city's plan to seal off a 186-acre site around the convention, and keep protesters penned in a parking lot out of earshot and direct sight of the convention delegates, was unconstitutional. The judge also ruled that the city's permit application process for parades and use of public parks for protests, which requires a 40-day advance application, was unconstitutionally restrictive and vague.</p>
        <p>Judge Feess said the security zone ''burdens speech more than is necessary,'' but he suggested that some relatively minor modifications to the northeast corner of the zone, near the arena entrance, could satisfy his concerns. The city, the police, the Secret Service and convention planners were scrambling to come up with an acceptable alternative, to be presented to the Civil Liberties Union over the weekend and reviewed on Monday, though they warned it would require more officers.</p>
        <p>Meantime, Mr. Riordan surprised many of his top aides and appalled convention planners 10 days ago with a sharply worded op-ed article in The Los Angeles Times that even some of the mayor's strongest supporters called a miscalculation likely to inflame the situation and rile potential demonstrators. Mr. Riordan denounced an umbrella organizing group of protesters called D2KLA as anarchists bent on violent disruption and property destruction, when in fact the group's Web site pledges nonviolence.</p>
        <p>''Don't stick your head up and make yourself a target,'' said one convention planner, speaking on the condition of anonymity. ''And don't get your facts wrong.''</p>
        <p>Protest groups were particularly incensed that Mr. Riordan not only vowed not to tolerate violence or vandalism but also said that ''we cannot tolerate nonviolent civil disobedience, such as the blocking of access to roads or buildings,'' time-honored protest tactics.</p>
        <p>''He is making a concerted effort to criminalize people of conscience, particularly the peaceful activists,'' said John Sellers, director of the Ruckus Society, a group based in Berkeley that co-sponsored the five-day training camp for 200 demonstrators in the Santa Monica Mountains this week. ''He's making every effort to marginalize us, vilify us before we even get into town, and therefore to make it easier for us to be dismissed and brutalized in the streets of Los Angeles and to scare more everyday folks away from being out in the streets with us with their concerns.''</p>
        <p>While protesters at past conventions have been confined mainly to designated areas, such areas have usually been directly across from the convention arena, and most big city police departments, including New York's, typically try to negotiate a certain amount of permitted civil disobedience (like blocking part of a street) in exchange for avoiding greater unplanned disruptions.</p>
        <p>But the Los Angeles Police Department  has a reputation for comparative high-handedness, and several local politicians said it should have been clear from the start that the plan for keeping protesters across the street from the Staples compound, behind a 14-foot fence, with their view to the arena blocked by a parking lot full of temporary trailers and television equipment, would never pass muster. At the same time, the Los Angeles department is comparatively small, about one-third the size of New York's. Los Angeles has just 9,346 officers (including supervisors) while the convention is expected to draw 5,000 delegates, nearly 15,000 journalists and an unknown number of demonstrators.</p>
        <p>A police spokesman, Lt. Horace Frank, said the department was confident that its planning for convention security, in progress for more than a year, would be up to the task. The department has canceled all vacations and regular days off for officers and civilian employees alike, and has worked out cooperation agreements with the county sheriff's department, in which its deputies will handle transportation security for delegates, and be available to process the arrests of protesters in the event of mass arrests. He said state officials had also assured the department of additional help if needed.</p>
        <p>''It's been a massive endeavor, Herculean to say the least,'' Lieutenant Frank said. ''But it's one that we feel very good about and very confident of. We recognize that the majority of protesters are legitimate groups who are going to be behaving in a legal and lawful manner, but we also know that there are those groups who are going to inject themselves and try to do harm, and we're prepared.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden acknowledged that 50 to 200  protesters might actually be from anarchist groups bent on destroying property to make a point, and based on the experience at the World Trade Organization meeting in Seattle last year, city officials' biggest fear is that such groups might blend in with more peaceful ones and cause trouble when it is least expected.</p>
        <p>The Secret Service was worried enough about the difficulties in securing Pershing Square in downtown Los Angeles that it moved Vice President Al Gore from the Biltmore Hotel there to Century City, several miles away from the convention site. And the federal court hearing on the security zone was so crowded with demonstrators this week that even some news organizations could not get in to cover it.</p>
        <p>For their part, Democratic Party officials and aides to Mr. Gore are having to walk a delicate line between making sure their typically fractious party is not seen as trying to stifle peaceful protests, while exercising diplomacy with a police department and local establishment whose help they need to have a successful convention.</p>
        <p>''We feel the real action of the convention is going to be in the hall, and we're real excited about it,'' said Peter Ragone, speaking for the party's convention committee. ''We recognize the possibility of demonstrations and protests and we're confident that the joint security team has the plans in place to deal with potential situations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden, who visited the protesters' training camp to lend moral support, said the biggest potential problem remained the city's unavoidable traffic and sprawl.</p>
        <p>''On a normal day here, we're congested,'' he said. ''For God's sake, the Indiana Pacers couldn't get from Santa Monica to the Staples Center in time for the first game of the playoffs. In my view, if the convention is shut down, it'll be simply because L.A. itself is this great, congested colossus and it grinds to a halt.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
