<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reed Gets His Chance And Beats Maddux</title>
    <meta content="23METS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DE123AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reed Gets His Chance And Beats Maddux</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Atlanta Braves, 4-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was the game Rick Reed wanted nine months ago. Reed was the Mets' scheduled starter for the seventh game of the National League Championship Series here last October, and the Mets seemed poised to give him the chance to pitch them into the World Series. But the Atlanta Braves won Game 6, and Reed never got his chance.</p>
        <p>''I thought about that all winter -- what if?'' Reed said. ''But that was last year.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was the game Rick Reed wanted nine months ago. Reed was the Mets' scheduled starter for the seventh game of the National League Championship Series here last October, and the Mets seemed poised to give him the chance to pitch them into the World Series. But the Atlanta Braves won Game 6, and Reed never got his chance.</p>
        <p>''I thought about that all winter -- what if?'' Reed said. ''But that was last year.''</p>
        <p>This year, the Mets are in a similar position. They still trail the Atlanta Braves, and with the Cincinnati Reds' Barry Larkin apparently leaning toward rejecting a trade to New York, the Mets are still searching for the right mix of players to bring them a pennant. ''It's not the best team that wins,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said, ''but the team that plays the best.''</p>
        <p>The Mets played the best today, and Reed had everything to do with it. He threw seven shutout innings, allowing only one runner past first base and leading the Mets to a 4-0 victory that cut the Braves' lead in the National League East to five games.</p>
        <p>The Mets won for just the second time in their last 17 games at Turner Field.</p>
        <p>At his best, Reed pitches like Greg Maddux, the Braves ace who opposed him. His stuff is not overwhelming, but he can throw it with uncanny precision and is very tough when he does.</p>
        <p>''His ball doesn't move as much as Maddux's,'' said Braves right fielder Brian Jordan, who grounded into two double plays today, ''but as far as control of the game, yes -- he knows what to do and he goes out there and does it.''</p>
        <p>The right-handers had nearly identical numbers today. Maddux threw 88 pitches, including 60 strikes, in eight innings; Reed threw 87 pitches, including 57 strikes, in seven innings. Maddux permitted five hits, Reed just four. Both pitchers issued one walk.</p>
        <p>But Reed (5-2) won because he kept the Braves from hurting him when it mattered. The Braves batted seven times with a runner on base but came away with no hits. Instead of aiming his pitches when he threw inside to left-handers, Reed said he ''let 'er fly.'' Instead of trying to blow hitters away, he stuck with his game plan.</p>
        <p>Reed paid close attention as Maddux set down the Mets in order in the first. He liked what he saw and did his best imitation. ''Every time I get a chance to watch him pitch, I'm glued to the TV, or if it's live, I'm glued to him,'' Reed said. ''I just admire the way he goes about his business. I try to do that, too.</p>
        <p>''The biggest thing -- and I tried to copy this today -- is that he doesn't go out there and throw every pitch 100 percent. That's just the way he goes about it. He keeps you off-balance. You're looking for a fastball, and he throws you a change-up. Or you might be looking for a fastball and get a fastball, but he takes a little bit off.''</p>
        <p>The Mets battered Maddux at Shea Stadium on July 1, scoring seven runs in two innings in Maddux's shortest start in four years. The four-time Cy Young Award winner was better today, making the Mets put the ball in play; his only walk was intentional.</p>
        <p>Todd Zeile had opened the fifth inning with a double, and Jay Payton singled him to third. After a ground out advanced Payton to second and Melvin Mora intentionally walked, Reed came up and lofted a fly to center, deep enough to score Zeile and give the Mets a 2-0 lead. Derek Bell, who had a .175 career average off Maddux in 57 at-bats, homered to lead off the sixth inning to increase the Mets' lead to 3-0.</p>
        <p>That was more than enough support for Reed, who outdid the master and won for just the second time in 12 starts. ''All those great things that his opponent does,'' Valentine said, ''and he matched them pitch for pitch.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Second baseman EDGARDO ALFONZO missed his second game in a row Saturday with a sore right hip, and though the condition has improved, he did not take any practice swings. Alfonzo was unsure if he would be able to play on Sunday. . . . Braves catcher PAUL BAKO said BOBBY VALENTINE was arguing with the umpires over Bako's positioning in the catcher's box, an issue that has been an ongoing problem for the Braves this year. . . . Outfielder DEREK BELL, a potential free agent, on the Mets' bid for BARRY LARKIN: ''That's awesome. Me and him have the same agent. That'd be cool -- maybe they could sign us both.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
