<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Salty Sliver of Island Life; In the City of Change, a Pocket of the Bronx Is Content to Stick to Its Small-Town Ways</title>
    <meta content="23ISLA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">City Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleinfield, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD6153AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Salty Sliver of Island Life; In the City of Change, a Pocket of the Bronx Is Content to Stick to Its Small-Town Ways</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kleinfield, N R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>a salty sliver of island life</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jacqueline Kyle Kall was doing what she does best, talking. Here she was coming into Artie's restaurant for lunch. Everyone seemed tickled to see her. She ate here a lot. The waitress plunked down her usual drink, a double martini, known as Jackie's Martini.</p>
        <p>She lived and sold real estate on City Island in the Bronx, a place that seems endowed with confirmed stasis. She was 75, with a doctorate in conversation, able to pontificate at length on the mannerisms of the snug island or most anything else. She could do an hour on Artie's menu alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jacqueline Kyle Kall was doing what she does best, talking. Here she was coming into Artie's restaurant for lunch. Everyone seemed tickled to see her. She ate here a lot. The waitress plunked down her usual drink, a double martini, known as Jackie's Martini.</p>
        <p>She lived and sold real estate on City Island in the Bronx, a place that seems endowed with confirmed stasis. She was 75, with a doctorate in conversation, able to pontificate at length on the mannerisms of the snug island or most anything else. She could do an hour on Artie's menu alone.</p>
        <p>She spoke of how City Islanders stayed put, how houses did not turn over much. Some were passed from generation to generation. A few dozen hit the market each year. She picked up the thought: ''On my street, nothing has sold in 35 years. I sold a house on Horton Street that had not been sold in 80 years. When I see the pallbearers go by my office, I know I have a house. Or like Lil Hansen. She had a stroke and went into the nursing home. I got a house.''</p>
        <p>Neighborhoods in New York are forever changing, refuting one image and embracing a fresh one, but there are pockets of immutability, places that seem to insist on staying as they are. City Island in the Bronx is one of those places. People come and go, new housing sprouts up, businesses change hands, but the tenor and intonation of the place have persisted for decades.</p>
        <p>''I call it a cross between Mayberry and Cape Cod,'' said Robert Carmody, 43, who has a real estate business and would like to see more development than others would. ''If you walked down the street 30 years ago, you'd see Mr. Smith. If you walk down now you'll see his son.''</p>
        <p>It is just a wisp of an island -- one and a quarter miles long and about a quarter of a mile wide, encircled by Long Island Sound and Eastchester Bay. Around 5,000 people live on it, mostly in modest clapboard houses. There is one main strip, City Island Avenue, clotted with seafood restaurants. The only place to stay overnight is a bed-and-breakfast called Le Refuge. There are no public beaches. There is no movie theater.</p>
        <p>Talk occasionally circulates about how City Island could become a grand tourist destination, with hotels and resorts, more condos, the whole bit. Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx borough president, is among those who hanker for some augmentation, while keeping the island's flavor. But the prospect of further development sends prickles down many spines. Last year, when the Parks and Recreation Department proposed a water park for nearby Orchard Beach, the residents said, ''Think again.'' The park went away. Some people are a bit miffed at Peter La Scala, who sold a plot of land opposite his yacht brokerage business not long ago, and now 20 houses are going up on it. Residents relish inactivity.</p>
        <p>City Islanders have their own idiom to classify people. Anyone born on the island is known as a clam digger. Residents born elsewhere are mussel suckers. Even the obituaries published in the island's monthly paper, The Island Current, will sometimes identify people as clam diggers, thus bestowing on them a stature that extends beyond their other mortal achievements. People neither born on the island nor living there are known as off-islanders, as in, ''I'm having an off-islander over for cocktails next Thursday.''</p>
        <p>Edward Sadler is a classic clam digger. He was born 84 years ago in the same upstairs bedroom he now sleeps in. His grandfather built the house and passed it on to his parents, who passed it on to him. He is a small, bent man, his face runnelled with lines. A retired fireboat pilot, he keeps busy adjusting compasses on boats. ''I do the big yachts and the Coast Guard vessels,'' he said. ''The way you do it, you take sun sights with a piece of equipment called a Polaris. It's the only perfect way of doing it.''</p>
        <p>Viewed across its lengthy history, City Island has actually witnessed a good deal of change. Originally the home of the Siwanoy Indians, it became an English settlement in 1685. Norwegians and Germans settled there, and the place evolved into a prominent shipbuilding and yachting center. During the world wars, battle craft were built in its boatyards. When fiberglass replaced wood as boat-building material starting in the 1960's, the boatyards got out of building boats. What remains are marinas, yacht clubs, and marine supply and repair shops.</p>
        <p>Decades ago, the island was emphatically rural. Herb Hild, 71, a clam digger who owns a business that makes canvas covers and cushions for boats and now lives on an island in nearby Rye, N.Y., remembers how empty the place was when he was a child. He marched to school to the distinctive ring of the caulking hammers at the boatyards.</p>
        <p>Back then, a game prevailed among the children. You would fetch a chestnut from the chestnut tree on Pilot Street, drill a hole in it and then loop a string through it so you could fasten it to your belt. When you encountered someone else with a chestnut, you would challenge him. If you could break the rival chestnut with yours, you put a knot in your string. Someone with five or six knots in his string was a fearsome presence.</p>
        <p>For many years, mainly working-class people have occupied the island, with a lot of police officers and firefighters. But houses have been turning over at enlarging prices, and the island has gotten more diverse (except racially; it is almost entirely white). A good many doctors and other medical personnel from the Bronx hospitals now live there.</p>
        <p>Malcolm Campbell, 40, the publisher of Spin magazine, arrived from Manhattan with his family five years ago. He rambled off his neighbors: a detective, a carpet salesman, an installer for a phone company. One of the best things about living on the island, he said, is that his off-island friends are easily lured to parties. They have never seen City Island and hunger for a peek.</p>
        <p>Mark Whitcombe, an artist, was painting a sailboat in his small cottage on Ditmars Street that he shares with his wife, Elizabeth. He has lived on the island for 45 of his 57 years. The couple do not own a car. They ride bicycles. In recent years, several artists have flocked to the island, pleasing Mr. Whitcombe.</p>
        <p>Like any small town, the island boasts its share of gothic tales, Mr. Whitcombe said. A man named Beau Barton used to live down the block. So the story goes, he had his hopes pinned on receiving a French honor in eighth grade. When he did not get it, he was shattered. He rebuffed society. He lived with his sister, who ran a bookstore, and he rarely showed himself outside.</p>
        <p>His sister died, and he made do on his own. He was known to take the bus at 4 in the morning to stores off the island to fetch groceries, the better to stay invisible. He had no heat in his house. One cold winter day about 10 years ago, he was found frozen to death.</p>
        <p>Residents moan when they hear about new condos going up, and they get worked up over traffic congestion. On the weekends, City Island Avenue shudders with cars of off-islanders heading for the restaurants. Residents avoid leaving the island for fear of how long it would take to return. Alice Collins, a clam digger now living in Florida, was visiting the other week. She had a plane to catch on a Sunday. ''I couldn't expect anyone here to drive me to the airport,'' she said. ''So I have to get a limousine, an off-islander.''</p>
        <p>Even things on-islanders dislike don't seem to change. Across the bay in Pelham Bay Park is Rodman's Neck, a police firing range and the place where the bomb squad detonates confiscated bombs and fireworks. Almost every day, residents and business owners facing the range hear the rat-a-tat-tat of gunfire as officers practice. Less frequently, but more noticeably, the bomb squad sets off a bomb. The island shakes.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Scala, whose yacht brokerage business is close to the range, says the pictures on his office wall fall off. He dug out a photo. It seemed to show the rising cloud from a small atomic bomb. ''That's fireworks being set off there,'' he said. At home, he kept a Hummel collection on a shelf in his living room. A few years ago, a particularly thunderous bomb was detonated. Down went the Hummels. Up went his blood pressure.</p>
        <p>A noise-deadening barrier is soon to be built on the range, but Mr. La Scala, like other residents, is dubious that it will solve the problem.</p>
        <p>The Boat Livery is on Bridge Street, on the water. It's a dark, scruffy place. In the late afternoon, nearly a dozen people were grouped around the bar, getting their $1 beers. It was hot and humid, and they were telling fish stories and otherwise gossiping.</p>
        <p>Trader John, as he is known, runs the place. His full name is John Persteins. He's 58, and he moved to the island with his parents when he was 2 months old, missing the honor of being a clam digger by those 60 days. He also has a used-boat equipment shop. The Boat Livery is strictly a beer and wine bar. As Trader John put it, ''There's enough problems with beer and wine.''</p>
        <p>Fishermen rent skiffs from Trader John, buy bait from him and fish. Then they return, quaff some drinks and tell about what got away. The alcohol tends to enlarge the dimensions of the escaped fish.</p>
        <p>''Most people know what they're doing,'' Trader John said. ''But we've had people fall asleep, forget to put out the anchor and end up 15 feet on the beach.''</p>
        <p>Pete Lewis, who works for Trader John, told about how the fish in the area enjoy the fried chicken and French fries that diners at the restaurants like to throw off the piers. ''I've caught 12-, 13-pound striped bass with French fries and chicken in them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A customer chimed in: ''I caught a 13-pound striped bass with a chicken bone as bait. I ate the chicken and put the bone on the line.''</p>
        <p>A buffalo head hangs behind the bar. When a newcomer stops in for a drink, one of the regulars will say, ''Go outside to see the other end.'' When the duped rookie steps outside, everyone has a good laugh.</p>
        <p>''There's a whole bear standing over there,'' Trader John pointed out. ''People sometimes dance with it. But when you start to talk to the buffalo, that's when you're turned off. You've had enough.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
