<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poland Finds Itself the Border Cop of West Europe</title>
    <meta content="Y28POL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boundaries and Territorial Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Poland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belarus</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belarus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belarus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6DB1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1241" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poland Finds Itself the Border Cop of West Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>NIEZNANY BOR, Poland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Poland's frontier with Belarus will soon become European Union's future eastern border with wild, untameable and unformed east, and burden of blocking illegal trade and immigration across it will fall on Poland, which is being asked by union to erect new, post-Communist barrier near Nieznany Bor as price of membership; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is the border where Europe ends.</p>
        <p>In this little spot named ''the unknown forest,'' near Bialowieza, is Poland's frontier with Belarus, which will soon become the European Union's border with the wild, untamable, unreformed east.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is the border where Europe ends.</p>
        <p>In this little spot named ''the unknown forest,'' near Bialowieza, is Poland's frontier with Belarus, which will soon become the European Union's border with the wild, untamable, unreformed east.</p>
        <p>Today you can walk into Belarus, at least for 100 yards or so. Then you hit the border fences, with their electronic sensors and a raked area to capture footprints, designed by the Soviet Union to keep out even its allies the Poles.</p>
        <p>But Belarus is beginning to take down this cold war barrier, even as the European Union is urging the Poles to put up a new, post-Communist one as part of the price of membership. Europe -- Germany and Austria most vocally -- want the Poles to build what some are calling the ''Belgian Curtain,'' after the country where the European Union has its headquarters.</p>
        <p>Whether the Poles like it or not, much of the burden of blocking illegal trade and immigration into the European Union will fall on them. That will do real damage to the active cross-border trade that helps keep this poorest part of Poland alive.</p>
        <p>Heavily agricultural, with little industry, this area east and southeast of Bialystok has an average income only about 65 percent of the national average, and a lot of hidden unemployment on the farm.</p>
        <p>Until the Russian ruble collapsed in 1998, there was an enormous amount of cross-border trade, with easterners bringing cheap vodka to sell here, buying Polish and European products to sell at home, then returning with more overvalued rubles with which to buy. Now the ''suitcase trade'' is recovering along with the ruble, just as Europe is pressing Poland to lock down the border.</p>
        <p>Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz, Poland's prime minister until the end of 1997, represents this area in Parliament, and he urges a soft border regime that would allow families and small traders to continue to cross with as little hindrance as possible.</p>
        <p>''The worst would be to apply European standards to this border and then have terra incognita on the other side of the wall,'' he said, making a political argument, too, about the spread of ideas and freedom, as a small eagle circled overhead.</p>
        <p>''We need to improve conditions on the other side,'' he said. ''Of course we have to control pathological aspects like crime and illegal immigration, but not to stifle trade. But why should we build a wall with our neighbors? We must rearrange Schengen not to build too strong a border here.''</p>
        <p>The 1995 Schengen agreement allows people and goods to move freely within the European Union without border checks, making it vital to control the external borders.</p>
        <p>''As the new outlying frontier of the European Union, Poland will be in a very uncomfortable position,'' said Krzysztof Bledowski, chief economist for the brokers Wood &amp; Company. ''It will have both the good and the bad.''</p>
        <p>Poland will be a magnet and clearinghouse for trade, he said, but also for more crime and smuggling along the long land border of people, drugs and goods.</p>
        <p>In the Bialowieza Forest, a national park here, is some of the last remaining primeval forest in Europe, 12,350 acres with lindens, maples, oak, spruce and ash -- strictly regulated now, full of fox and lynx, bison and roe deer. Nearby, Mr. Cimoszewicz has secured a hunting cabin, which he is refurbishing, combining politicking with pleasure.</p>
        <p>But already, says the chief forester, Jerzy Lugowoj, tunnels have been discovered under the Belarussian border fences, and at least some illegal immigrants, including Afghans and Vietnamese, have been captured.</p>
        <p>Poland's economy is growing at nearly 6 percent a year, while Ukraine and Belarus have been stumbling backward. The average wage in Ukraine is about $50 a month and in Poland nearly $400, so the attraction of any kind of job in Poland, even temporary, is vivid.</p>
        <p>Witold M. Orlowski, of the Independent Center for Economic Studies, specializes in the border question. The difference in income levels between Poland and its eastern neighbors is now much bigger than the difference between Poland and eastern Germany, which is about 2.5 to 1.</p>
        <p>So Poland must satisfy its future European partners about its ability to stop the smuggling of goods and people into the ''Europe without borders'' while it is also trying to make life better for those in Belarus and Ukraine to the east, to reduce the growing economic divide.</p>
        <p>''Everything depends on what the River Bug will be in the future,'' Mr. Orlowski said. ''Will it be the Rio Grande or the St. Lawrence Seaway?'' -- in other words, will Poland's relationship with the east be more like that of the United States with Mexico or with Canada?</p>
        <p>This border is actually relatively new, formalized in Yalta after the end of World War II, when Stalin got what he wanted in Eastern Europe -- including a chunk of Poland.</p>
        <p>The former unity of the area is obvious in the architecture and the skyline. There are many Russian Orthodox churches, including a huge modern cathedral in nearby Hajnowka, the Church of the Holy Trinity, consecrated in 1992 after nearly 20 years of construction.</p>
        <p>This is where Roman Catholic Poland meets Eastern Orthodoxy. Hajnowka has almost twice as many Russian Orthodox as Roman Catholics, and in outlying areas, the percentage who are Orthodox is even higher. The border divides families, and as many as 500,000 ethnic Poles live on the other side of the border, and 300,000 Belarussians on this side.</p>
        <p>But while Poland feels it has an eastern vocation, arguing within the European Union and NATO for better relations and special ties with Belarus and Ukraine, Mr. Cimoszewicz says, the Europeans are not particularly interested.</p>
        <p>Western Europeans are reconciled to a larger European Union that swallows large Poland and other countries of Central and Eastern Europe, a European Union ambassador said. ''But if you want to kill support in the E.U. for expansion and enlargement, just talk of Turkey, Ukraine and Belarus,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What worries the Western Europeans as much as illegal immigration is the smuggling of shoddy goods and unclean food, he said, and Europe is pushing for big improvements in the Polish customs service, too.</p>
        <p>The Poles will finally do what is necessary and apply full visa regulations to Russians, Ukrainians and Belarussians as the European Union is demanding, the ambassador said, as the Czechs have already done.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orlowski says that despite the sometimes cogent arguments of people like Mr. Cimoszewicz, Poland has no choice. With 70 percent of its trade now with the European Union and only 10 percent with the countries of the former Soviet Union, he said, Poland's future lies with Europe and the West, not with the East.</p>
        <p>''The Europeans are drawing the borderline of Europe for the next 50 years and don't care about Ukraine, Belarus and Russia,'' he said. ''We think it's wrong, but what can we do? We don't really have an option.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
