<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joyous Mix Of Mexican And Rock Traditions</title>
    <meta content="28WATC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cafe Tacuba (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DD1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joyous Mix Of Mexican And Rock Traditions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews the band Cafe Tacuba performing at the club Exit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At this point it's time to consider the band Cafe Tacuba, from Mexico City, outside of its limiting subcategory of Spanish-language rock, and start wondering if it isn't just one of the best rock bands in the Americas.</p>
        <p>This quartet looks to the future of rock songwriting -- occasionally reminding you of a grandly ambitious band like Radiohead -- while drawing on traditional and sometimes rural song forms from Mexico. Though these musicians are after breadth and try to create a different concept with each song, this semimusicological pursuit centers them, and prevents them from being merely a pastiche band. Their recent live performances have been so carefully designed, with such a seriousness of purpose and such an apprehension of joy -- not just art-rock profundity or forgettable youth-culture kicks but somewhere shrewdly in between -- that the band seems invincible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At this point it's time to consider the band Cafe Tacuba, from Mexico City, outside of its limiting subcategory of Spanish-language rock, and start wondering if it isn't just one of the best rock bands in the Americas.</p>
        <p>This quartet looks to the future of rock songwriting -- occasionally reminding you of a grandly ambitious band like Radiohead -- while drawing on traditional and sometimes rural song forms from Mexico. Though these musicians are after breadth and try to create a different concept with each song, this semimusicological pursuit centers them, and prevents them from being merely a pastiche band. Their recent live performances have been so carefully designed, with such a seriousness of purpose and such an apprehension of joy -- not just art-rock profundity or forgettable youth-culture kicks but somewhere shrewdly in between -- that the band seems invincible.</p>
        <p>Cafe Tacuba isn't above its audience: in its headlining slot on the Watcha tour on Wednesday, which played at the club Exit, the fans roiled and moshed right through the fast rock or ska or punk-ranchera songs.</p>
        <p>They were given license to be unruly by the singer Ruben Albarran's voice, which, in songs like ''Ingrata,'' turned serrated and flip. The crowd spent much of the time exploding. But intermittently, gearing down, the band presented a song like ''Dos Ninos'' that sounded as if it had thought about making rock from scratch: experimental, tender and slightly chilly, clearly composed on the piano.</p>
        <p>Lacking a drummer, Cafe Tacuba sometimes used robotic drum-machine rhythms in its hourlong set, lampooning the rhythmic one-dimensionality of traditional Mexican norteno music. But at the same time it was celebrating them: the crowd raised Mexican flags at these moments and applauded wildly for Alejandro Flores, a guest violinist who sawed through ballads and an old-fashioned son jarocho number, while the other band members played traditional Mexican guitars to make the fast-strummed music.</p>
        <p>Playing without a drummer isn't a liability for these musicians: it gives them license -- via their imaginative keyboardist and electronic-drum programmer, Emmanuel del Real -- to make themselves over in every song. They're professionals, and though the crowd stuck with them to the delayed end at 2:15 a.m., they, were struggling with an unfortunate situation, as were the other bands on the bill.</p>
        <p>It's hard to know how to make sense of such a badly produced event. The Watcha tour is overseen by the people who put on Warped, the annual summer bonanza of punk, rap and metal. Those multiband concerts run like clockwork, but Watcha is at the mercy of a different promoter in each town, and it got unlucky in New York. At Exit, the sound system couldn't have been much worse.</p>
        <p>The club had a ganglia of speakers throughout its two floors, but hardly any  were used. The music sounded as if it were being heaved at the crowd through a loud home stereo; vocals and guitar were lost in the acoustics.</p>
        <p>During the six-hour show, changing sets between bands took longer than expected. There was no air-conditioning in the club. Exit, as it happened, was the third announced site for the concert, a change which happened just days before the event. And the first three bands on the tour -- the flashy 80's-style rock bands Autotonic and Enanitos Verdes, and the punk band Animal -- had fans from South American radio hits, but in music and stage presence they were so far inferior to the second half of the concert that it took stamina to get through the night.</p>
        <p>Aterciopelados, from Colombia, suffered most from the sound; despite the strong stage presence of its singer, Andrea Echeverri, its music was the most delicate on the bill, striking a balance between electronics and alternative rock, mixing in traditional vallenato and cumbia rhythms.</p>
        <p>Molotov, from Mexico, suffered the least: massively popular through Latin America, it is the Sherman tank of rock en espanol, with two guitarists, two bassists and a steel-toed rock-hip-hop style that got over on volume. It had wild, aggressive humor: Tito Fuentes, its guitarist and leader, sang a rap version of Queen's operatic ''Bohemian Rhapsody'' (''Rap Soda y Bohemia''), making the song's main character flee to Mexico after committing murder; and closed with ''Puto,'' a screamed attack on cowards.</p>
        <p>This is the second year of Watcha and the first time the tour has come through New York. Though the concert drew a nearly sold-out house through advertisements in Spanish-language media, it has a long way to go before it attains the goal of so many involved in rock en espanol: a multilingual audience that doesn't care what language a song is sung in. A tolerable night out would be a good first step toward that goal.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
