<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>VoiceStream Seeks to Buy Wireless Player</title>
    <meta content="28WIRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Voicestream Wireless Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Powertel Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DC1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>VoiceStream Seeks to Buy Wireless Player</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew; Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>VoiceStream Wireless, US wireless carrier, reportedly agrees to buy Powertel, wireless operator in Southeast, for as much as $5.8 billion; acquisition gives VoiceStream coverage in 24 of nation's top 25 markets, filling a crucial gap in its network and its goal of offering seamless access across the entire nation; deal includes a payout if Deutsche Telekom's acquisition of VoiceStream is complete (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VoiceStream Wireless, the United States wireless carrier that is being acquired by Deutsche Telekom, is expected to announce today that it has agreed to buy Powertel, a wireless operator in the Southeast for as much as $5.8 billion, according to executives close to the deal.</p>
        <p>The acquisition of Powertel fills a crucial gap in VoiceStream's network and its goal of offering seamless access across the entire nation. The deal gives VoiceStream coverage in 24 of the nation's top 25 markets, adding cities like Atlanta, Memphis, Jacksonville, Fla., and Nashville, among others. VoiceStream's network previously covered 22 of the top 25 markets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VoiceStream Wireless, the United States wireless carrier that is being acquired by Deutsche Telekom, is expected to announce today that it has agreed to buy Powertel, a wireless operator in the Southeast for as much as $5.8 billion, according to executives close to the deal.</p>
        <p>The acquisition of Powertel fills a crucial gap in VoiceStream's network and its goal of offering seamless access across the entire nation. The deal gives VoiceStream coverage in 24 of the nation's top 25 markets, adding cities like Atlanta, Memphis, Jacksonville, Fla., and Nashville, among others. VoiceStream's network previously covered 22 of the top 25 markets.</p>
        <p>If anything, the deal illustrates how consolidation in the telecommunications industry, and in wireless communications in particular, is picking up speed. Usage of wireless services is also increasing, with carriers adding an estimated 30,000 new subscribers each day.</p>
        <p>While Powertel only has about 720,000 customers and is not one of the top 10 wireless companies in the United States, its network uses the same technical standard -- global system for mobile communications -- that VoiceStream uses and is compatible with Deutsche Telekom's network and most others in Europe and Asia.</p>
        <p>According to executives close to the deal, shareholders of Powertel, which is based in West Point, Ga., will receive about $85 for each of their shares. If Deutsche Telekom's acquisition of VoiceStream does not materialize, that represents no premium to Powertel's stock, which rose $4.69, to $86.63, on Friday.</p>
        <p>VoiceStream will assume about $1.2 billion in Powertel's debt.</p>
        <p>The complex deal also involves a collar, which is a method to determine stock prices in which a specific price range is agreed upon instead of the establishment of an exact cost per share. If VoiceStream's shares increase beyond $130.77 shareholders of Powertel will receive 0.65 shares of VoiceStream for each of their shares. If VoiceStream shares fall below $113.33, Powertel shareholders will receive 0.75 VoiceStream shares for each Powertel share.</p>
        <p>The deal also includes a payout if Deutsche Telekom's acquisition of VoiceStream is completed. If the deal receives regulatory approval, shareholders of Powertel will receive $105.36 a share in Deutsche Telekom stock, representing 2.6353 Deutsche Telekom shares for every one share of Powertel. In this instance, there is no collar.</p>
        <p>Generally speaking, the transaction guarantees Powertel shareholders that they will receive about the same amount of money for the shares regardless of how VoiceStream shares fluctuate.</p>
        <p>Executives close to the VoiceStream-Powertel deal hope that both transactions will be completed in six to nine months. Some analysts have questioned whether Deutsche Telekom is paying too much for VoiceStream, which is based in Bellevue, Wash., but others have suggested the acquisition of Powertel could make the VoiceStream deal more palatable to Deutsche Telekom shareholders.</p>
        <p>''Powertel is a critical enabler in VoiceStream's need for nationwide coverage,'' said Andrew Cole, a wireless communications consultant with Renaissance Strategy Worldwide. ''Now Deutsche Telekom is at least buying a car with the brakes included.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it is not clear yet whether Deutsche Telekom's plan to buy VoiceStream for more than $50 billion will be approved in Washington after resistance to the transaction emerged in Congress on concern over the acquisition of a United States telecommunications company by a large foreign concern.</p>
        <p>''It was shrewd for Deutsche Telekom to expand in the U.S. by buying a minor player in the wireless industry but now it seems that strategy is changing,'' said Jeffrey Kagan, an independent telecommunications analyst based in Atlanta. ''The bigger the deal appears, the more resistance the Germans could get from regulators.''</p>
        <p>John Stanton, VoiceStream's chief executive, sees things differently. ''Just because this deal scales us up in the Southeast isn't that meaningful when it comes to the regulatory issues,'' Mr. Stanton said in a telephone interview. ''I would say passionately that there are still no national security or technical reasons why the Deutsche Telekom deal should not be approved.''</p>
        <p>Since the deal was announced in July, VoiceStream's shares have declined 8 percent, to $118.19 from $128.50, while Deutsche Telekom has fallen more than 10 percent, to $40.31 from $45.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
