<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Island Breeze Revives a Dream; At Long Last, a Bahamian Band Has a Hit on Its Hands</title>
    <meta content="28BAHA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000901T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baha Men (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Universal Music Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Polygram Nv</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mercury Records</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">S-Curve (Record Label)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Steve (Record Producer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DD1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Island Breeze Revives a Dream; At Long Last, a Bahamian Band Has a Hit on Its Hands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baha Men's single, Who Let the Dogs Out, is the big hit of the summer, and the album far outsells group's six previous albums combined; group has been together in various incarnations for more than two decades, and it had been dropped from two major labels in US, most recently from Mercury Records as a casualty in merger between Universal Music and Polygram; album is first and only release of S-Curve, independent label begun by Steve Greenberg; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he was 7, Isaiah Taylor began having dreams that he compares to the visions God sent Joseph in the Bible. And his own vision was of leading a group of musicians from his home in the Bahamas to worldwide success.</p>
        <p>Last year, however, Mr. Taylor's dream could not have been further from reality. He was 50 and his group, the Baha Men, had been together in various incarnations for more than two decades, merging pop and funk with traditional Bahamian junkanoo music. The band had been dropped from two major labels in the United States, most recently from Mercury Records as a casualty in the merger between Universal Music and Polygram. And there was a further blow when its lead singer, Nehemiah Hield, left the group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he was 7, Isaiah Taylor began having dreams that he compares to the visions God sent Joseph in the Bible. And his own vision was of leading a group of musicians from his home in the Bahamas to worldwide success.</p>
        <p>Last year, however, Mr. Taylor's dream could not have been further from reality. He was 50 and his group, the Baha Men, had been together in various incarnations for more than two decades, merging pop and funk with traditional Bahamian junkanoo music. The band had been dropped from two major labels in the United States, most recently from Mercury Records as a casualty in the merger between Universal Music and Polygram. And there was a further blow when its lead singer, Nehemiah Hield, left the group.</p>
        <p>At a time when pop music is ruled by the fresh-faced teenage dreams of Britney Spears and the Backstreet Boys, it did not seem likely that an aging Bahamian band without a major label deal would have a grain of a chance.</p>
        <p>But the world of pop music is strange, and no one knows why some bands get second, third and fourth chances, while others do not get even one. As much as music executives like to think they have the market sewn up, popular music follows no one's rules but its own. And this summer Mr. Taylor's childhood dream became a reality.</p>
        <p>The Baha Men's single, ''Who Let the Dogs Out,'' released and distributed independently, is turning into the summer anthem of 2000, say radio programmers like Ed Lambert of KISS-FM in Dallas.</p>
        <p>The Baha Men may be the first casualty of the Universal merger to come back with a hit through an independent label. And the tale of the making of that hit is one that crosses borders and spans generations, changing the fortunes of a Trinidadian soca singer, a Bahamian junkanoo band and a record executive who would not give up.</p>
        <p>With its signature guttural barking and breezy island rapping, the song can be heard blasting everywhere from passing convertibles to Mets games. As is usually the case with such instant hits, some find the song irresistible, others find it obnoxious, and many find it both. One day last week viewers of Nickelodeon chose it as their video of the day over 'N Sync's ''It's Gonna Be Me.'' Other days on Nickelodeon the Baha Men have beat out Britney Spears, the Backstreet Boys, Aaron Carter and other teenage idols. Since its release in late July the band's album has been on fire. In its first week it was not even on the pop charts; by last week, it had climbed to No. 59 from 103 and is likely to rise.</p>
        <p>''It's the great Cinderella story,'' said Steve Greenberg, who put out the new Baha Men album as the first and only release so far on his own independent label, S-Curve. Mr. Greenberg had signed the group to two different record companies -- Atlantic and Mercury -- in the last decade with no success.</p>
        <p>''The song's been floating around for two years, the band has been floating around in some version for 30 years, and the label's 12 weeks old,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''It's the most unlikely hit ever. I couldn't even get arrested with this band on a major label.''</p>
        <p>If the band's story offers any lesson, it is that there is no such thing as a final chapter in a pop music career. Whether it is Santana reaping his greatest success 30 years after his prime, the rap producer Dr. Dre engineering his own comeback years after hip-hop advanced without him, or the Baha Men becoming a teeny-bopper sensation long after having been written off by the music business, the sweetest prizes in popular music sometimes go to those who stay in the game.</p>
        <p>''It goes way back, man,'' Mr. Taylor said of his band's success. ''God gave me the dream, and I actually had visions of doing all these things as a kid. When I sat down with my band and told them this, some of them probably thought I was crazy. But now they all see it coming to pass.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said that as a child he had no interest in music and would skip music classes in school. But he could not escape his destiny, he said, and he formed the Baha Men in the early 1980's as High Voltage, a collective of local junkanoo, rhythm-and-blues and disco musicians who had already been playing for years. Mr. Greenberg first heard High Voltage in 1991. He was working as a talent scout at Big Beat/Atlantic records when a Bahamian songwriter gave him a High Voltage cassette.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg changed the band's name to the Baha Men and released two of its albums on Big Beat. When Mr. Greenberg left the label for Mercury during an executive power struggle, Big Beat dropped the Baha Men. At Mercury, where he signed successful bands like Hanson, Mr. Greenberg stuck with the Baha Men as a pet project. He released two more of the band's records, the last of which sold fewer than 700 copies, which is not only a failure in the music business but an embarrassment as well.</p>
        <p>''It became a standing joke in the industry that every time I came to a new label, the first band I'd sign would be the Baha Men,'' Mr. Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>At the same time in Trinidad a soca star named Anslem Douglas was writing a song for the 1998 carnival. At previous carnivals, Mr. Douglas said, there were songs in which men made coarse references to women. Mr. Davis decided to create a way for women to respond and wrote a song around a local street cry, ''Who let the dogs out!''</p>
        <p>''They're always calling guys 'dogs' anyway,'' Mr. Douglas said. ''This was a way to legitimize it.''</p>
        <p>The flirtatious, suggestive song begins with a party setting in which the men start making passes at the women, who bark in response, ''Get back, you flea-infested mongrel.''</p>
        <p>The song became a hit in the Caribbean and eventually found its way onto Mr. Greenberg's desk when a musician stopped by his office at Mercury with a version he had recorded himself. ''That version was horrible,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''But the song stayed in my head for two years.''</p>
        <p>After the sale of Polygram's music holdings to Seagram, which owns Universal, Mr. Greenberg left his job to write a novel, and the Baha Men were dropped from the label. But Mr. Greenberg could not get the song out of his head. He wrote in his diary last December: ''I'm going to record that song, 'Who Let the Dogs Out,' with the Baha Men, and we're going to have a worldwide hit. I'm sure of it.''</p>
        <p>Around the same time, Mr. Taylor lost Mr. Hield, who quit to pursue solo projects and tour as a backup vocalist with Lenny Kravitz, who is part-Bahamian. The band held open auditions in Nassau and ended up not with one replacement singer but three.</p>
        <p>One was Mr. Hield's nephew, Omerit Hield. ''I was working as a teller at a bank,'' he said. ''Being in the Baha Men was something I always wanted to do, but I never thought I'd have a chance. When I went to the audition, there were at least 75 people there.'' He got the job.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Taylor almost turned down the song that would catapult the band to success. ''This is going to sound crazy,'' Mr. Taylor said. ''But when Steve Greenberg said 'Who Let the Dogs Out' would be a good song to cover, I said, 'I don't want to do that song.' ''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Taylor's mind the song was too popular in the Caribbean and too specific to the region for audiences in other countries to understand. But he finally relented. After recording the song using a number of different singers, backing tracks and studios, the band finally got it right by recording in the home of its producer, Michael Mangini.</p>
        <p>The barking sounds, Mr. Hield said, came naturally. ''If you go to Nassau, you'll see dogs running around in the streets. So we listened to them, and it was easy to imitate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg started his S-Curve label and made distribution and promotion deals with the independent companies Red and Artemis, owned by his former boss at Mercury, Danny Goldberg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg played the song for a friend, Winston Simone, who runs a music publishing company, Desmone Music, with, among others, the songwriter Desmond Child. ''I said, 'Oh my god, this is a smash!' when I heard it,'' Mr. Simone said.</p>
        <p>He tracked down the writer, Mr. Douglas, at his aunt's house and bought his entire catalog of songs, secured him a publishing deal and helped place ''Who Let the Dogs Out'' on the ''Rugrats in Paris'' soundtrack.</p>
        <p>''He probably stands to be a millionaire if things keep going this way,'' Mr. Simone said of Mr. Douglas. ''In the middle of the night sometimes I worry, 'What's he going to do with his money?' He's going to have a big hit, and I want to make sure he's always going to be O.K.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Douglas said not to worry. ''It's every writer's dream to be published,'' he said excitedly. ''It takes the financial strain off, the mental strain off. Finally, my ship has come in.''</p>
        <p>The Trinidadian newspapers are already pinning their crossover hopes for regional soca music on Mr. Douglas's lapels, with one newspaper declaring that ''the future of soca is cash register success on the Billboard charts, and Anslem's foot is in the door.'' Mr. Douglas, however, is looking forward to new challenges. He said he was awestruck when Mr. Simone suggested that he work on a song with Mr. Child for the new Ricky Martin album.</p>
        <p>''I've always been up there with the soca stars like Super Blue, but now I'm seeing my career take a whole new turn,'' Mr. Douglas said.</p>
        <p>Life has changed for the Baha Men, too. Mr. Hield summed up the last month most succinctly: ''I've never barked so much in my life.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 1, 2000, Friday  A picture caption on Monday with an article about the recording success of the Baha Men, a Bahamian band, misstated the surname of a band member. He is Marvin Prosper, not Prospect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 1, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Monday with an article about the recording success of the Baha Men, a Bahamian band, misstated the surname of a band member. He is Marvin Prosper, not Prospect.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
