<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Compressed Data; Carlson Revives Stamp Redemption Online</title>
    <meta content="28GOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Premiums, Coupons and Trading Stamps</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlson Cos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DE1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Compressed Data; Carlson Revives Stamp Redemption Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carlson Companies begins offering redeemable Gold Points to customers at 24k.com, which will serve both as a shopping portal and an online redemption catalog (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Carlson Companies could be called the grandfather of customer loyalty programs, dating to 1938, when the company first started giving out Gold Bond Trading Stamps.</p>
        <p>Now Curtis C. Nelson, grandson of the founder and Carlson's chief operating officer, wants to take it back to its roots -- this time, online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Carlson Companies could be called the grandfather of customer loyalty programs, dating to 1938, when the company first started giving out Gold Bond Trading Stamps.</p>
        <p>Now Curtis C. Nelson, grandson of the founder and Carlson's chief operating officer, wants to take it back to its roots -- this time, online.</p>
        <p>Carlson, Minneapolis-based owner of the TGIF restaurant chain, Radisson Hotels, Thomas Cook Travel and a long list of other businesses, is beginning to offer redeemable Gold Points to customers on a new site, 24k.com.</p>
        <p>Among other things, the site will be the online hub of the company's rewards program, both as a shopping portal and an online redemption catalog.</p>
        <p>Much like S &amp; H Green Stamps, Gold Bond Trading Stamps were doled out by the thousands the last half century, typically as a way for supermarkets, gas stations and shops to differentiate themselves in competitive markets.</p>
        <p>Consumers redeemed their stamps for a range of consumer items like toasters and hair dryers -- that is, until they began shopping at discount warehouses and the practice fell by the wayside.</p>
        <p>The online customer loyalty business is already fairly crowded, what with S &amp; H and others already doling out electronic trading stamps.</p>
        <p>But today's online loyalty programs are an entirely different beast from their predecessors. Among other things, they take advantage of Internet data collection that allows merchants to pitch specific products to customers based on their past shopping behavior. And these days, customers can redeem their stamps for much more than toasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson says that Carlson has a leg up on other redemption programs because of the variety of brands it owns. And where it does not have its own brand, he says, the company will join forces with other companies to fill the void. Already, 24k.com either owns or has a partnership with 1,500 sites that offer Gold Points.</p>
        <p>''Our objective,'' Mr. Nelson said, ''is to touch the customer 365 days a year, across all facets of their life.''</p>
        <p>LAURIE J. FLYNN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
