<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lisdoonvarna Journal; In Ireland's Pubs, a Startling Trend</title>
    <meta content="Y28IRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DB1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lisdoonvarna Journal; In Ireland's Pubs, a Startling Trend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>LISDOONVARNA, Ireland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Guinness stout remains best-selling alcoholic beverage in Ireland, but its consumption in rural areas such as Lisdoonvarna has declined by nearly 4 percent over last year; new wealth from nation's economic boom has allowed citizens to broadened tastes, with many opting for more fashionable drinking experience; sales of heavier and darker stout have been surpassed by those of lighter lagers as international brands compete for suddenly abundant pocket money of average Irish consumer; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the doorway of his family's pub, Peter Curtin has witnessed dramatic changes in Irish life. He remembers when one man's trip to the United States was considered so unusual that he was sent to the local schools to share what he had seen. He remembers when farmers would come in for a pint of Guinness while clutching the reins of horses poking their noses into the pub.</p>
        <p>What makes this remarkable is that Mr. Curtin is only 46. So much of Ireland has changed in recent years that he avoids general statements, for fear that another cultural upheaval will occur before he completes the sentence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the doorway of his family's pub, Peter Curtin has witnessed dramatic changes in Irish life. He remembers when one man's trip to the United States was considered so unusual that he was sent to the local schools to share what he had seen. He remembers when farmers would come in for a pint of Guinness while clutching the reins of horses poking their noses into the pub.</p>
        <p>What makes this remarkable is that Mr. Curtin is only 46. So much of Ireland has changed in recent years that he avoids general statements, for fear that another cultural upheaval will occur before he completes the sentence.</p>
        <p>But today this much is true: trips to the States are routine, customers at the bar could have a BMW parked where the horses used to stand -- and he is probably drinking something other than a Guinness, the midnight-black stout consumed by his father and his father before him.</p>
        <p>''It's too individual a taste,'' Mr. Curtin, who now manages that same pub, said with a hint of admiration. ''Plus, it doesn't have the perception as a drink for younger people.''</p>
        <p>Something seismic is happening in Ireland -- apart from the diminishing influence of the Roman Catholic Church, apart from an economy so ferocious that a tiger has replaced the tamer metaphor of a bull.</p>
        <p>In short, people here are not drinking Guinness stout as much as they used to. Signs once proclaiming that ''Guinness is good for you'' might now read, ''Guinness is no longer a given.''</p>
        <p>Last month Diageo, the international food and beverage giant that owns Guinness along with Pillsbury and Burger King, Smirnoff and Johnnie Walker, announced that worldwide sales for the stout were booming, particularly in the United States.</p>
        <p>But it also provided another, more intriguing statistic: while Guinness stout remains the best-selling alcoholic beverage in Ireland, over the last year its consumption here has declined by nearly 4 percent.</p>
        <p>This is not a blip. Pat Barry, the director of corporate affairs for a subsidiary called Guinness Ireland, said that in the last five years the sale and consumption of lagers here, the light, cold and transparent brews, have surpassed those of heavier, darker stout for the first time in -- well, for the first time ever.</p>
        <p>Nor is this just a routine shift in consumer tastes -- this is not Tayto's chips, it's ''the black stuff,'' something so psychically connected to Ireland that in Dublin after donating blood you are given the choice between a free cup of tea or a half-pint of Guinness.</p>
        <p>''Guinness is synonymous with Ireland and with Irish heritage,'' said Philip Hawkins, an analyst for Merrill Lynch in London. ''But as prosperity comes to Ireland at a rapid pace, youngsters have more money in their pockets than ever before and are looking for a more fashionable drinking experience in the fashionable clubs in Dublin.</p>
        <p>''And that means you don't walk around with a pint of Guinness in your hand.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barry agreed: ''The challenge for us is to ensure that Guinness continues to be relevant to a wide range of consumers and to make it more relevant to the newer consumer.''</p>
        <p>Having relevance in Ireland has never been an issue for Guinness. Part of the national story includes how Arthur Guinness began to brew ales and porter at St. James's Gate in Dublin in 1759; how the brewery introduced a stronger porter called ''extra stout'' in the 1820's; how the prospering company built housing for the poor and developed St. Stephen's Green as a gift to Dublin. When the company adopted the patriotic symbol of a harp, it seemed more fitting than impertinent.</p>
        <p>Of course, as the Irish writer Brendan Behan once observed, Guinness has been good to the Irish, but so too have the Irish been good to Guinness. Generations of men drank its stout as they talked rebellion or shared gossip in pubs, long the community centers of this country. The drink took on its own lore: how you ate a Guinness as much as drank it; how it contained restorative vitamins; how even a pregnant woman might benefit from its wonders.</p>
        <p>The famous ''Guinness is good for you'' slogan is no longer used here -- the beverage is, after all, alcohol. But the company still trumpets the phrase in a few countries, Mr. Barry said, where the stout is perceived by some to be ''a source of power and strength and virility.''</p>
        <p>In a country with more than 10,000 pubs and hotel bars, any failure in the exacting delivery of a pint -- from the cleanliness of the tap lines to the temperature of the beverage -- traditionally could ruin a pub's reputation.</p>
        <p>Christopher Curtin, a sociologist at the National University of Ireland, Galway -- and Peter Curtin's older brother -- has spent years studying rural communities like Lisdoonvarna, which is known for its spa water and for an annual September festival at which bachelor farmers once sought potential brides. His research has focused in part on pub life -- a life he knows well, having been born above the family pub, the Roadside Tavern.</p>
        <p>In that culture, Christopher Curtin recalled: ''To be a drinker was to be drinking Guinness. And if you were to ask what single drink would you have to have above any other, it would be Guinness.''</p>
        <p>But that culture is in transformation. There is an architectural shift away from the small, bevel-glassed windows, so perfect in thwarting the curious from peering in. The ''holy hour'' law -- which forced pubs to close on Sunday afternoons to encourage families to eat, and not drink, their Sunday dinners -- was recently set aside. Finally, there is the diminishing influence of Guinness.</p>
        <p>When the Curtins were children, their family's pub offered Guinness on tap, whiskey in the bottle, and gin for the nonconformist. Now it offers an assortment of tapped and bottled lagers, from Heineken to Budweiser, as well as ales, ciders, wine and a new line of ready-to-drink concoctions made of vodka, rum and other spirits.</p>
        <p>In a way, the choices at the Roadside Tavern reflect how far Ireland has come from being an island unto itself, a parochial place where Guinness profited from its captive audience.</p>
        <p>The international market is now competing for the suddenly abundant pocket money of the average Irish consumer. More people are returning from intercontinental vacations with broadened tastes. And the universal emphasis on slim figures, beamed daily over satellite television, bedevils the Guinness marketing executives who have tried for years to convey the difficult message that its heavy product is not particularly fattening.</p>
        <p>Guinness anticipated the changing tastes, and has spent millions of dollars on technology to cool the stout -- traditionally served at room temperature -- and to make it available in specially designed cans. But the younger drinkers are proving ever more elusive, acknowledged Mr. Barry. ''Our interest at this stage is to encourage the newer drinker to come on board at an earlier age,'' he said. ''And we're doing that through a variety of promotions.''</p>
        <p>One such promotion includes photographs of attractive young people with the advice to ''Live life to the power of Guinness'' -- a phrase that, at least in Lisdoonvarna, has Peter Curtin asking, ''What the heck does that mean?''</p>
        <p>The Guinness tap is far from running dry. The company continues to reap large profits in countries like Italy and Spain, to which it routinely sends architects to help recreate authentic Irish pubs. It still owns the brewing and marketing rights here for Budweiser and Carlsberg beer and distributes various other brands of ales and lagers.</p>
        <p>And while the company continues to streamline its operations -- it recently announced the closing of one brewery and layoffs at a packaging plant and another brewery -- Mr. Barry dismisses rumors that its parent company, Diageo, will either sell it or move its operations out of the country. Guinness, he said, will stay -- sponsoring the Rose of Tralee festivals, providing free lunches to the elderly of Dublin, remaining a part of the Irish psyche.</p>
        <p>Still, something has been lost. Forty years ago, who in Lisdoonvarna could have imagined that the Curtin lad named Peter -- the one who watched over their horses while they had a pint of Guinness -- would someday propose building a microbrewery next to his family's pub? A microbrewery that he promises would make its own brand of stout.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
