<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some New Math on MSNBC's Billboards</title>
    <meta content="28BRIA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000830T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msnbc (Cable Channel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">News With Brian Williams (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DE1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some New Math on MSNBC's Billboards</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some competitors of MSNBC questions the viewership claimed for The News With Brian Williams on two billboards in New York; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last few months, the cable network MSNBC has placed two billboards on the West Side Highway in Manhattan that promote its main nighttime news program in this way: ''THE NEWS WITH BRIAN WILLIAMS Find Out Why 42 Million People are Watching.''</p>
        <p>The sign features a photograph of Mr. Williams, who is considered to be among the heirs apparent to the NBC news anchor Tom Brokaw, looking confident and authoritative. It tells viewers they can tune in weeknights at 9 p.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last few months, the cable network MSNBC has placed two billboards on the West Side Highway in Manhattan that promote its main nighttime news program in this way: ''THE NEWS WITH BRIAN WILLIAMS Find Out Why 42 Million People are Watching.''</p>
        <p>The sign features a photograph of Mr. Williams, who is considered to be among the heirs apparent to the NBC news anchor Tom Brokaw, looking confident and authoritative. It tells viewers they can tune in weeknights at 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>But the billboard has struck executives at some of MSNBC's competitors as not only odd, but also a bit annoying because of the large ratings figure the sign boasts.</p>
        <p>In the second quarter of this year -- the most recent full quarter for which cable ratings are available -- the 9 p.m. showing of ''The News With Brian Williams'' was actually watched by an average 203,000 people, according to Nielsen figures. It was in fourth place in its time period among the cable news networks behind CNN's ''Larry King Live,'' with 936,000 people watching each night; CNBC's ''Rivera Live,'' with 374,000; and the Fox News Channel's ''Hannity &amp; Colmes,'' with about 308,000.</p>
        <p>So, how can MSNBC say the program is being watched by 42 million people when its nightly audience is about one-20,500th of that?</p>
        <p>Thanks to some statistical ingenuity and vague language, the MSNBC number is basically correct, according to MSNBC executives.</p>
        <p>Here is the calculus: Mr. Williams's program, which runs Monday through Friday, is repeated four times a night after its initial 9 p.m. showing -- twice on MSNBC and twice on CNBC, NBC's financial network. MSNBC executives said they arrived at the figure by taking the total number of people who watched at least one minute of the program in any of its runs in April.</p>
        <p>In other words, if while clicking through the channels in April, a viewer happened to pause for 60 seconds on Mr. Williams's program, she became one of the 42 million.</p>
        <p>That sort of method is not all that different from one used to determine audiences for Web sites. But it is quite different from that usually used to measure television audiences, in which statisticians track the number of people watching a particular program from minute to minute and then produce an average viewership number.</p>
        <p>Executives at MSNBC said they thought their method for the billboard would better represent the real audience for Mr. Williams in the course of a night since, they contend, many of his his viewers tune in briefly for information and then head elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people tune in to Brian Williams to get their news,'' said Robin Garfield, MSNBC's vice president for research. ''That's the statement we want to make: we are the news broadcast of record in cable.''</p>
        <p>JIM RUTENBERG</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK  Correction:  August 30, 2000, Wednesday  A report in the Media Talk column in Business Day on Monday about an MSNBC billboard promoting ''The News With Brian Williams'' misstated a comparison between the average audience for the program's 9 p.m. showing and what MSNBC says was its cumulative audience during April. The average nightly audience of 203,000 is one-206th of the cumulative audience of 42 million, which includes the number of different viewers tuned in to at least one minute of any of its showings, including four repeats a night. It is not one-20,500th.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 30, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Media Talk column in Business Day on Monday about an MSNBC billboard promoting ''The News With Brian Williams'' misstated a comparison between the average audience for the program's 9 p.m. showing and what MSNBC says was its cumulative audience during April. The average nightly audience of 203,000 is one-206th of the cumulative audience of 42 million, which includes the number of different viewers tuned in to at least one minute of any of its showings, including four repeats a night. It is not one-20,500th.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
