<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Political Pulse-Taker Is Back, Without Missing a Beat</title>
    <meta content="Y28LIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/28/national/28LIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Stan Greenberg</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Stanley B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DC1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Political Pulse-Taker Is Back, Without Missing a Beat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Stan Greenberg, Pres Clinton's pollster throughout his long march to White House, who has signed on with Gore campaign (Public Lives); photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STAN GREENBERG, who was President Clinton's pollster throughout his long march to the White House, is back in the fray of presidential politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg, a former Yale political science professor and a longtime interpreter of the political yearnings of the white middle class, quietly signed on with Vice President Al Gore's campaign five weeks ago. His action represented a certain closure: he had left Mr. Clinton after the debacle of 1994, when the Democrats lost the House and the Senate and Mr. Clinton shook up his political team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STAN GREENBERG, who was President Clinton's pollster throughout his long march to the White House, is back in the fray of presidential politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg, a former Yale political science professor and a longtime interpreter of the political yearnings of the white middle class, quietly signed on with Vice President Al Gore's campaign five weeks ago. His action represented a certain closure: he had left Mr. Clinton after the debacle of 1994, when the Democrats lost the House and the Senate and Mr. Clinton shook up his political team.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to make a change, given the '94 losses, and he made the change,'' Mr. Greenberg said, with the careful equanimity of a man who landed well and wants you to know it. ''It worked out fine. I'm very happy. My only question is why I'm so foolish to come back and do this,'' he added with a short laugh.</p>
        <p>Since he left Mr. Clinton, Mr. Greenberg has worked on campaigns around the world, developing a kind of specialty in helping center-left parties return to power. He worked on Tony Blair's 1997 campaign for prime minister of Britain, which broke 18 years of Conservative Party rule; Gerhard Schroder's 1998 campaign for chancellor of Germany; and Ehud Barak's campaign last year for prime minister of Israel.</p>
        <p>''Each battle has its uniqueness,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''But each of these parties has struggles in the postindustrial period and they're all trying to learn from each other.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg, 55, does not really want to talk about the strategy of the Gore campaign, which has taken a markedly populist turn in recent weeks (a turn that escalated with Mr. Greenberg's arrival, although the Gore campaign dismisses the connection).</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg dismisses the idea that there is a clear tension between that economic populism and the ''new Democrat'' philosophy championed by Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore in 1992, which was willing to break with liberal orthodoxy on issues like trade and welfare reform.</p>
        <p>''Al Gore's a new Democrat, he's always been a new Democrat, his message derives from who he is and what he's been saying in his political life,'' Mr. Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>But the pollster contends that Mr. Gore's candidacy comes at a new stage in American politics. Mr. Clinton's challenge was to deal with the Democratic Party's past, to persuade disaffected voters that the Democrats were not ''a big-spending party that's culturally elitist,'' Mr. Greenberg said. Mr. Gore's challenge is to build on that credibility and show that Democrats ''can manage the future,'' modernizing institutions like Medicare and the public school system wisely and carefully, using the surplus for great national needs.</p>
        <p>In that context, Mr. Greenberg asserts, the huge tax cut proposal of Gov. George W. Bush represents a failure of vision. It would mean ''that we're going to take the surplus and give it to individuals, now, to spend it, now, with no sense of what it would mean for the future.'' He added that Senator John McCain ''understood this moment much better than Bush does.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg has spent much of his professional life trying to synthesize the various themes of the Democratic Party and reconnect it to the middle-class and working-class voters it lost in the 70's and 80's. Mr. Greenberg, whose mother was a bookkeeper and father a ''self-taught environmental engineer,'' grew up in Washington, a product of public schools and the middle-class neighborhoods he studies so intensely today.</p>
        <p>He received his doctorate from Harvard, with a dissertation titled, ''The Politics of Poor Neighborhoods,'' and eventually joined the Yale faculty. One of his early academic passions was South Africa -- he worked on Nelson Mandela's campaign in 1994 -- but he inexorably moved into American politics in the early 1980's. After the Democrats' landslide defeat in 1984, the United Auto Workers and the Michigan Democratic Party hired him to study Macomb County, Mich., and determine why what was once the most Democratic suburb in America gave Ronald Reagan 67 percent of its vote in 1984.</p>
        <p>HE determined that middle-class voters felt the Democratic Party had abandoned them, was using their hard-earned tax dollars on giveaway programs that did not benefit them and was out of touch with their values. Mr. Clinton, whose thinking was headed in the same direction, hooked up with Mr. Greenberg in the late 1980's, and they soon began a campaign that revolved around ''the forgotten middle class,'' or ''the people who work hard and play by the rules.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg says he continues to have good relations with Mr. Clinton, despite their break after 1994. Dick Morris, who rose to power on the Clinton team after Mr. Greenberg left, related this comment about Mr. Greenberg: ''I'll quote President Clinton to you: 'He never told me what to do. He would always tell me on the one hand, on the other hand, but never tell me what to do.' '' Mr. Greenberg said he had no comment on that.</p>
        <p>Married to Representative Rosa DeLauro, Democrat of Connecticut, Mr. Greenberg has homes in New Haven and on Capitol Hill. He has three children by his previous marriage; one is a political scientist at Harvard, Anna Greenberg, with whom he recently co-wrote an essay on the Democrats' need to promote ''family-centered values.'' He continued national polling throughout the 90's for the Democratic National Committee and others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg said he did not worry that his opponents would think he had gone global, and lost touch with the nuances of American politics.</p>
        <p>''I'll leave it to them to figure out what I bring to the table,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he dismissed the notion that the Bush team in Austin, clannish and focused, was the dangerous equivalent of the winning Clinton team of 1992. ''They may have too tight a team and maybe too mechanical a vision of how to get him elected president,'' Mr. Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>It's an unusual moment in American politics, he contends -- one he clearly did not want to miss.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
