<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; Political Tongue Twisters</title>
    <meta content="28HERB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EED81131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; Political Tongue Twisters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column on Gov George W Bush's linguistic gaffes and malapropisms offers language-mangling quotes from several other politicians (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reporters covering George W. Bush's presidential campaign are having a field day with his so-called Bushisms. It's understandable. They're irresistible.</p>
        <p>''We must all hear the universal call to like your neighbor just like you like to be liked yourself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And then there was his message to struggling workers: ''I know how hard it is to put food on your family.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reporters covering George W. Bush's presidential campaign are having a field day with his so-called Bushisms. It's understandable. They're irresistible.</p>
        <p>''We must all hear the universal call to like your neighbor just like you like to be liked yourself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And then there was his message to struggling workers: ''I know how hard it is to put food on your family.''</p>
        <p>Yogi Berra, move over. Let the governor of Texas hit some malaprop-ups.</p>
        <p>Back in February, Mr. Bush said of John McCain, ''He can't take the high horse and then claim the low road.''</p>
        <p>You want economic insight? ''We ought to make the pie higher,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>These comments should not be dismissed as mere gaffes. We owe it to the governor to take him somewhat seriously. Consider the following question, which he posed in New Hampshire: ''Will the highways on the Internet become more few?''</p>
        <p>Whew!</p>
        <p>The danger if Mr. Bush keeps this up is that we will start to think of him as some kind of champ in the fine art of malaprophesizing. That would be a mistake. Consider, for starters, that the term Bushism initially referred to that great malapropartist George Herbert Walker Bush, the 41st president of the United States and father of the current contender.</p>
        <p>President Bush once said, ''We're enjoying sluggish times, and not enjoying them very much.'' He said, ''It's no exaggeration to say the undecideds could go one way or another.'' He said, in a reference to Dan Quayle: ''My running mate took the lead, was the author of the Job Training Partnership Act. Now, because of a lot of smoke and frenzying of bluefish out there, going after a drop of blood in the water, nobody knows that.''</p>
        <p>So, as you see, this ability of the younger Mr. Bush to get entangled in the obscurer thickets of the language is not that unusual. The plain truth is that politicians have always been brilliant at finding new ways to insert their feet into mouths that inevitably are running too much. Which is why you have books with titles like ''Political Babble: The 1,000 Dumbest Things Ever Said by Politicians.'' And, ''The 267 Stupidest Things Democrats Ever Said.'' (There's one for Republicans, too.)</p>
        <p>Edmund G. (Pat) Brown, commenting on an earthquake when he was governor of California, said: ''This is the worst disaster in California since I was elected.''</p>
        <p>Senator Christopher Dodd of Connecticut nicely bungled an appearance on behalf of a Democratic Senate candidate in South Carolina by saying: ''We've got a strong candidate. I'm trying to think of his name.''</p>
        <p>Did I mention Dan Quayle? He may be the champ. ''Republicans,'' he said, ''understand the importance of bondage between parent and child.''</p>
        <p>The former vice president was a master at mangling the language. He once said: ''I believe we are on an irreversible trend toward more freedom and democracy. But that could change.''</p>
        <p>His most famous foul-up, now enshrined in Bartlett's Familiar Quotations, was a reference to the motto of the United Negro College Fund, ''A mind is a terrible thing to waste.''</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Quayle: ''What a waste it is to lose one's mind, or not to have a mind is being very wasteful. How true that is.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard J. Daley of Chicago was terrific at this sort of thing. These were some of his best: ''I resent your insinuendoes.'' ''The police are not here to create disorder. They're here to preserve disorder.'' ''We shall reach greater and greater platitudes of achievement.''</p>
        <p>And then, of course, there was Ronald Reagan. Entire books have been written about his flubs. I loved the time when, annoyed by something Ed Asner had said, Mr. Reagan snapped, ''What does an actor know about politics?''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Bush should take heart. He's not the only one out there hacking away at the language. He might say on ''Meet the Press,'' ''Laura and I really don't realize how bright our children is sometimes until we get an objective analysis.'' Or, on the  ''Today'' show: ''I don't have to accept their tenants. I was trying to convince those college students to accept my tenants.''</p>
        <p>But he is not alone. As Mayor Daley happily pointed out, ''No man is an Ireland.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
