<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alford's Release Finishes 2-Year Development Project</title>
    <meta content="Y28GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alford, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DA1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alford's Release Finishes 2-Year Development Project</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants release receiver Brian Alford after two frustrating seasons; cut 15 other players; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the tense minutes between the second and third rounds of the 1998 National Football League draft, Giants officials hurriedly worked the telephones, trying to figure out a way to move up at least a few spots so they could select the highest rated speed receiver still on their draft board.</p>
        <p>That player was Brian Alford of Purdue University, and the Giants coaches were especially relieved when a trade was made and Alford was safely in the fold -- even if they had to forfeit their fourth-round pick in the deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the tense minutes between the second and third rounds of the 1998 National Football League draft, Giants officials hurriedly worked the telephones, trying to figure out a way to move up at least a few spots so they could select the highest rated speed receiver still on their draft board.</p>
        <p>That player was Brian Alford of Purdue University, and the Giants coaches were especially relieved when a trade was made and Alford was safely in the fold -- even if they had to forfeit their fourth-round pick in the deal.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Giants released Alford after two frustrating seasons, in which Alford played just six games and caught just two passes.</p>
        <p>''The selecting of players is not an exact science,'' Giants Coach Jim Fassel said yesterday of Alford. ''Along the way, you're going to get a guy who didn't pan out for you. We saw the speed and wanted to feel like we could develop the other things.''</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. draft has a history full of choices who have not worked out, as Fassel suggested. A handful of first-round picks are released every year, including this season. Even so, the drafting of Alford is a failed two-year experiment -- and there are always reminders of who else might have been taken.</p>
        <p>Drafted one pick after Alford, with the 71st pick over all, was wide receiver E. G. Green, a selection made by the Indianapolis Colts. The former Florida State receiver had 36 receptions for the Colts in the last two seasons. One round and 34 choices after Alford, the Atlanta Falcons selected wide receiver Tim Dwight of Iowa. Dwight has been a talented kick returner, and as a receiver, he has 8 career touchdown receptions and 28 other catches. Four picks after Alford, Atlanta also took wide receiver Jammi German. He didn't play much his rookie year, but last season had 3 touchdowns on 12 receptions.</p>
        <p>But yesterday the Giants were, understandably, living in the present.</p>
        <p>''Our only true mistake,'' Fassel said, ''would be to keep a player because you drafted him when a guy beat him out for the job.''</p>
        <p>In Alford's case this summer, Thabiti Davis, a free agent signed this spring from Wake Forest, beat him out as the team's fifth receiver. The rookie Ron Dixon, this year's third-round pick, also vaulted ahead of Alford early in training camp. Davis led all Giants receivers with 11 receptions and had 4 special-teams tackles in the preseason that just concluded.</p>
        <p>Alford, with a slight frame and a playing style that was hardly physical, gave the Giants little help on special teams. In the preseason, he had 3 catches for 35 yards.</p>
        <p>''Brian made some improvement,'' Fassel said. ''But he was still inconsistent. And the fifth receiver has to be somebody who can help on special teams.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the Giants' frustration with Alford could best be illustrated by a sequence from New York's game with St. Louis in December. A deep sideline pass was added to the game plan specifically for Alford. The play nearly clicked, with Alford just missing a fingertip catch deep in St. Louis territory. Later, however, as the coaches watched the videotape of the game, they saw that Alford had not run the pass route precisely the way it was designed. To them, if Alford had been exactly where he should have been -- instead of almost where he should have been -- the play would have resulted in a touchdown.</p>
        <p>The 25-year-old Alford was by far the most prominent name among the 16 players cut by the Giants yesterday. Linebacker O. J. Childress, a late-round draft choice last year, was also released, along with defensive ends Jomo Cousins and Frank Ferrara; tackles Chris Bober, Rome Douglas and Pita Elisara; fullback Michael Jones; safeties Tinker Keck, Tawambi Settles and Greg Williams; guards Scott Kiernan and Mark Nori; wide receiver Kevin Prentiss; and tight end Adam Young.</p>
        <p>Kick returner Bashir Levingston was put on a non-football injury list, which allows him to return to the Giants' roster in six weeks.</p>
        <p>In announcing the cuts, Fassel said that the rookie Cornelius Griffin, the team's second-round pick, who was expected to see considerable time as a third defensive tackle, would begin working full time as a defensive end because the Giants have no experienced backup at the position. Fassel said that Reggie Stephens, formerly a cornerback, would begin working at safety.</p>
        <p>Fassel also acknowledged that as other teams pare their rosters, the Giants could still add and cut more players.</p>
        <p>''More likely than not,'' Fassel said, ''the roster will be changed again.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
