<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Racing's Real Allure Is Romance</title>
    <meta content="Y28TRAV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travers Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">King's Bishop (Horse Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DA1131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Racing's Real Allure Is Romance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Drape</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Drape column on victory by Unshaded in Travers and of More Than Ready in King's Bishop, which preceded Travers at Saratoga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This time of year, with the glory of the Triple Crown faded and the stars of the spring series on the sidelines, there is a tendency to size up the 3-year-olds and hang the tag of ordinary around their necks. That's too bad.</p>
        <p>As the afternoon of the 131st Travers proved here Saturday, there's no such thing as an ordinary horse -- especially for the people most intimately involved with them. Ask Nick Zito, the colorful and competitive New York trainer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This time of year, with the glory of the Triple Crown faded and the stars of the spring series on the sidelines, there is a tendency to size up the 3-year-olds and hang the tag of ordinary around their necks. That's too bad.</p>
        <p>As the afternoon of the 131st Travers proved here Saturday, there's no such thing as an ordinary horse -- especially for the people most intimately involved with them. Ask Nick Zito, the colorful and competitive New York trainer.</p>
        <p>Hoarse and heartbroken after his Albert the Great was run down by Unshaded 20 yards from the wire, keeping Zito a neck from his first Travers victory, Zito composed himself and distilled the magic of horse racing. He explained how he had won the Kentucky Derby with Albert the Great's father, Go for Gin, and how Carl Nafzger, Unshaded's trainer, had won the Derby with Unshaded's father, Unbridled.</p>
        <p>''It's funny, racing is such a beautiful sport,'' Zito said with an appreciative smile. ''Here he is 10 years later, winning the Travers with his son. So it's a remarkable business we're in and there's a lot of romance.''</p>
        <p>Or ask Jim and Terry Scatuorchio, the owners of More Than Ready, the victor in the Grade I King's Bishop here, which preceded the Travers.</p>
        <p>Last year at this time, the small, black colt was being mentioned in the same breath as Affirmed and Easy Goer after topping a perfect five-for-five start with a nearly 10-length victory here at the Sanford Stakes. When a fever disrupted his training, two tough losses followed in the fall and the colt was sent to Kentucky for a complete physical. While veterinarians found nothing wrong, More Than Ready was laid up and forgotten.</p>
        <p>But the Scatuorchios and the trainer Todd Pletcher believed he was far from an ordinary horse and aimed him for the Triple Crown. In January, he was a dead-heat winner in his return race, the Hutcheson Stakes in Florida.</p>
        <p>Then he ran valiantly the next five races against the best 3-year-olds in the nation. But each time, he never quite got to the finish line first. In the Louisiana Derby, Mighty passed him in the final jumps; in the Blue Grass Stakes, High Yield nosed him after a breathtaking stretch duel; in the Kentucky Derby, he took the lead in the stretch but couldn't hold on and finished fourth, six lengths behind Fusaichi Pegasus.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one days ago, More Than Ready was poised to win his first Grade I race, a coveted designation worth millions when it comes time to sell a colt for stallion duties. He was among the top choices in the Haskell Invitational at New Jersey's Monmouth Park, the track where Jim and Terry Scatuorchio had their first date.</p>
        <p>This time, disaster hit the day before the race when the colt's regular rider, John Velazquez, broke his collarbone in a spill at Saratoga. With Richard Migliore on him for the first time, More Than Ready got in traffic trouble and finished fourth, three lengths from the winner.</p>
        <p>So More Than Ready was taken off the Travers trail and was entered in the seven-furlong King's Bishop. It was a Grade I race at a sprint distance he excelled at. Before the Haskell, Jim Scatuorchio had already signed a stallion deal for More Than Ready's post-racing career.</p>
        <p>A victory would secure a great deal of bonus money. But for the Scatuorchios, for Eddie Rosen, the pedigree consultant who helped pick out More Than Ready, for the dozens of family members and friends who had followed the colt across the country the past year, winning the King's Bishop was also about seeing a hard-working horse finally get the respect he deserved.</p>
        <p>''This has been an experience of a lifetime,'' Jim Scatuorchio said. ''He's brought a lot of joy into a lot of people's life, and you never know if you'll get an opportunity like that again.''</p>
        <p>So when More Than Ready went from last to first to capture the race, the winner's circle was crowded, exuberant and tearful with the colt's ardent followers. Even Pletcher, who is as reserved and measured as Zito is emotional, couldn't help but be touched.</p>
        <p>''I think sometimes this game isn't very sophisticated when you think here's a horse who has proven himself in Grade I company over and over again, but hasn't won,'' said Pletcher, who is leading the trainer standing here. ''If ever there was a horse deserving of a Grade I race, it's him.''</p>
        <p>At the end of the year, votes will be counted among writers and racing secretaries, and one 3-year-old will be named champion. It will probably be the Derby winner Fusaichi Pegasus. But don't tell Nafzger, Zito, Pletcher or the Scatuorchios that their horses are ordinary. They won't believe you.</p>
        <p>ON HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
