<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transportation Bond Act Awaits Details, a Campaign and a Vote</title>
    <meta content="28BOND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/28/nyregion/28BOND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver, Sheldon (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D91131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transportation Bond Act Awaits Details, a Campaign and a Vote</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Yorkers will vote in Nov on record $3.8 billion transportation bond act, but Gov George E Pataki and legislative leaders have yet to reach accord on how money would be spent; Comptroller H Carl McCall warns delay makes measure harder to sell to voters; Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, major act sponsor, sees contractors and unions launching campaign for measure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It just may be the quietest $3.8 billion in New York political history. In November, voters will be asked to decide the largest bond act in state history, to pay for transportation projects. But so far, there has been barely any campaign for it, and none against it.</p>
        <p>Just as unsettling for people inclined to support the measure is that it is now more than two months after the deadline set by Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders for producing their agreement on how the money would be spent. The lack of such an agreement makes it hard for anyone to know what it is they may be campaigning for or against.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It just may be the quietest $3.8 billion in New York political history. In November, voters will be asked to decide the largest bond act in state history, to pay for transportation projects. But so far, there has been barely any campaign for it, and none against it.</p>
        <p>Just as unsettling for people inclined to support the measure is that it is now more than two months after the deadline set by Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders for producing their agreement on how the money would be spent. The lack of such an agreement makes it hard for anyone to know what it is they may be campaigning for or against.</p>
        <p>All of this could bode ill for a borrowing measure that has been billed as a necessary step for building the first stages of a Second Avenue subway line and other projects in the ambitious capital building program for the New York metropolitan region's mass transit network. New York voters have turned down bond acts more often than they have approved them, and the ones that have passed, like the 1996 environmental bond act championed by the governor, have been supported by broad-based coalitions that raised large amounts of money for television advertising -- exactly the kind of thing that has been nowhere in sight this time around.</p>
        <p>''To get bond issues passed, you really have to do a job in terms of selling it to the public,'' State Comptroller H. Carl McCall said. ''This is reducing the amount of time you can go out and educate the public about what it's all about.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall described himself as being inclined to support the measure, and said he was asked daily ''by reporters, the financial community, by union leaders, environmentalists'' what he thinks of it. But he added that he ''can't render an opinion until I see the specifics.''</p>
        <p>A major sponsor of the measure, Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, said he was not concerned about the late start. In fact, Mr. Silver, who heads the state's most potent Democratic machinery, said he had no plans to organize a campaign for it or to raise money for such a campaign.</p>
        <p>''I think that in the last two months, the local officials, the contractors, the unions, who are all interested in making it happen, will get the message out,'' he said. ''I would expect to see an across-the-board campaign.''</p>
        <p>The bond act is a crucial piece of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's $17.1 billion, five-year capital plan for upgrading the region's rail and bus system, including the first work in a generation on a Second Avenue line, and the start of work on a connection between the Long Island Rail Road and Grand Central Terminal. Of the $3.8 billion the state would borrow under the bond act, $1.6 billion would go to the authority and the rest would go to other transit agencies across the state and to pay for highways and bridges.</p>
        <p>The financing for the authority's capital plan has been widely derided as shaky at best, and the promised state money from the bond act is one of the firmer pieces. Without that $1.6 billion, state officials and analysts outside government say, the authority would have to reopen the plan, which was approved this year, and either find a way to replace the money or eliminate projects.</p>
        <p>''What happens then, it would take a pretty good crystal ball to predict,'' said Albert Appleton, senior fellow at the Regional Plan Association, which supports the bond act.</p>
        <p>Gene Russianoff, staff lawyer with the Straphangers Campaign, a transit advocacy group, said: ''We're very torn about this, because we want the projects, but we think the financing of the plan is a disaster, and so the projects might not happen. So is it better to campaign for the one piece of it that looks pretty solid, the state money, or campaign against it and hope the whole thing blows up and forces them to start over?''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I would guess that they aren't helping their chances by waiting this long.''</p>
        <p>The wait has been mostly for a document, called a memorandum of understanding, signed by the governor and the leaders of the Assembly and the Senate, providing details of how the $3.8 billion would be spent. The lawmakers agreed to the bond act in May as part of the deal they reached on the state budget, and set a deadline of mid-June for producing the memorandum. Ten weeks after the deadline, it has yet to surface.</p>
        <p>''I would expect to get it wrapped up this month,'' said Michael McKeon, the governor's press secretary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver predicted a deal by ''the week of Labor Day or the week after that.''</p>
        <p>State officials in both parties said the main holdup has simply been distraction, since politicians have been paying more attention to their parties' national conventions and to the Senate race between Rick A. Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>The memorandum, while highly detailed, is not especially fraught with controversy. The money is going into a series of larger pots, like the authority's $17.1 billion program, so that, assuming the money from other sources materializes, it hardly matters whether the money from a particular project comes from Source A or Source B.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver learned an important lesson in 1997, from the defeat of a $2.4 billion bond act for school construction and repair that he had promoted. In that case, there was no memorandum saying with any precision how it would be spent, and opponents exploited that weakness, saying that state officials could not be trusted to spend the money well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's role is also crucial. He stumped hard for the 1996 environmental bond act, raising money for it and appearing in television advertisements promoting it, but he did nothing to promote the 1997 school construction act. In fact, he made it clear that he had agreed to place it on the ballot only to meet one of Mr. Silver's demands in closing a budget deal.</p>
        <p>Similarly, this year, the transportation bond act was demanded by the Assembly and Senate as part of a budget agreement. Although the governor agreed to put it on the ballot, the agreement came at a time when he was making a considerable show of wanting to rein in state debt, and he has openly voiced reservations about the act and has said he is not sure whether he would support its passage.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the governor would campaign for the bond act, Mr. McKeon said he wanted to see the final form of the memoradum first.  ''There are obviously some infrastructure needs that the governor wants to see addressed, but he wants to see that it's done in a smart way,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
