<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lieberman Seeks Greater Role for Religion in Public Life</title>
    <meta content="Y28LIE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/28/national/28lieb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arab-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2D91131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lieberman Seeks Greater Role for Religion in Public Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Aug. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic vice presidential candidate Sen Joseph I Lieberman campaigns in Detroit, where he visits city's largest African-American church; declares belief in God is basis of morality and of nation and calls for greater role role for religion in American public life; also meets with 30 prominent Arab-Americans after rally in Detroit suburb; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Declaring that belief in God is the basis of morality and of the nation, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman called today for a greater role for religion in American public life.</p>
        <p>''As a people we need to reaffirm our faith and renew the dedication of our nation and ourselves to God and God's purpose,'' Mr. Lieberman, the Connecticut senator and Democratic vice-presidential nominee, told the congregation of Fellowship Chapel, one of this city's largest African-American churches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Declaring that belief in God is the basis of morality and of the nation, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman called today for a greater role for religion in American public life.</p>
        <p>''As a people we need to reaffirm our faith and renew the dedication of our nation and ourselves to God and God's purpose,'' Mr. Lieberman, the Connecticut senator and Democratic vice-presidential nominee, told the congregation of Fellowship Chapel, one of this city's largest African-American churches.</p>
        <p>''John Adams, second president of the United States, wrote that our Constitution was made only for a moral and religious people,'' he said. ''George Washington warned us never to indulge the supposition 'that morality can be maintained without religion.' ''</p>
        <p>The candidates have been more overt about their religious faith this year than in any other presidential campaign in memory. Gov. George W. Bush has said that his favorite political philosopher is Jesus, ''because he changed my heart.'' Vice President Al Gore, a professed born-again Christian, has said that when faced with tough decisions, he asks himself, ''What would Jesus do?''</p>
        <p>Yet the comments today by Mr. Lieberman, the first Jew nominated for national office by a major party, were striking for a moderate Democrat. His words, if spoken by a conservative Christian, would probably be received with alarm by many factions in Mr. Lieberman's own party -- including many Jews -- who are wary of the political activism of the religious right.</p>
        <p>Unlike many conservative Christian politicians, Mr. Lieberman has not taken positions like advocating prayer in schools or saying that religious groups should take over much of the burden of social services now shouldered by government -- a position taken by Mr. Bush, the Republican presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lieberman, who refers at every campaign stop to his Jewish faith and the role of religion in Mr. Gore's life, went further today than he previously had in this campaign in asserting a role for religion in politics and public discourse.</p>
        <p>His themes -- and even his phrases -- were remarkably similar to those commonly voiced by conservative Republicans.</p>
        <p>''Let us reach out together to those who may neither believe nor observe and reassure them that we share with them the core values of America, that our faith is not inconsistent with their freedom, and that our mission is not one of intolerance but one of love,'' Mr. Lieberman said.</p>
        <p>But he bluntly made the case for allowing faith into politics. ''I want to talk to you this morning about another barrier that may fall, as well, as a result of my nomination,'' he said. ''I hope it will enable people, all people who are moved, to feel more free to talk about their faith and about their religion. And I hope that it will reinforce the belief that I feel as strongly as anything else, that there must be a place for faith in America's public life.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''we know that the Constitution wisely separates church from state, but remember: the Constitution guarantees freedom of religion, not freedom from religion.''</p>
        <p>Without biblical traditions from the Ten Commandments to ''the compassion and love and inspiration of Jesus of Nazareth,'' he said, ''it could never have been written, and wouldn't have been written, in our Declaration of Independence, 'We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal.' ''</p>
        <p>From the day Mr. Gore chose Mr. Lieberman, the first Democratic senator to publicly berate President Clinton over his extramarital affair, as his running mate, the Gore campaign has made it plain that it sees his religion and rectitude as an antidote to Republican efforts to use Mr. Clinton's ethical lapses as a campaign issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman has often tied his talk of faith to his criticism of vulgarity in popular culture. That link, which he reiterated today, allies him, both in fact and in the public mind, with Tipper Gore's longstanding campaign against violent and sexually explicit lyrics in popular music. Mr. Gore took up the call at the Democratic National Convention, speaking against what he said was ''a culture with too much meanness and not enough meaning.''</p>
        <p>The stop at Fellowship Chapel was the first in a string of events intended, in part, to appeal to traditionally Democratic constituencies that have viewed Mr. Lieberman warily as perhaps too conservative for their tastes. This afternoon, after a rally in Southfield, a Detroit suburb, he held a private meeting with 30 prominent Arab-Americans, including leaders of several Arab-American groups, at the Southfield Civic Center. On Monday, he is scheduled to address a convention of the Communications Workers of America, one of the country's largest labor unions, in Anaheim, Calif.</p>
        <p>At the church this morning, the Rev. Wendell Anthony, president of the Detroit branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, gave an impassioned defense of the senator's bona fides as a defender of black people's interests. He told of the summer Mr. Lieberman spent campaigning for voting rights for blacks in Mississippi in 1963, when he was a student at Yale, and of his attendance at the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s ''I have a dream'' speech that year in Washington. He read a letter from Mr. Lieberman, explaining his views on civil rights, that was published in The Yale Daily News.</p>
        <p>''We have to deal with why he went to Mississippi, because he got involved in our struggle,'' Mr. Anthony said. ''It does mean something. I ain't read about no Bushes in Mississippi. I ain't seen no Cheneys on no freedom marches.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, too, spoke of his work in Mississippi, and told of meeting Dr. King and Rosa Parks. He also effusively praised Representative John Conyers Jr., who was in the congregation.</p>
        <p>At the afternoon rally, Mr. Lieberman focused on the Democrats' plans to set money aside to protect Medicare and Social Security, and to provide prescription drug coverage under Medicare, while accusing Mr. Bush of ignoring those issues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
