<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="28MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3D61131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BRONX: GAS STATION EXPLOSION AVERTED  The driver of a gasoline truck received the scare of his life yesterday when a frustrated robber threw a lighted match at him as he was filling an underground tank at a Bronx gas station, the police said. They said the man who threw the match was angry because the driver, Roman Galvan, had refused to surrender money to him and an accomplice. The match caused a flash of fire at the Gaseteria station at 3804 Boston Road, but Mr. Galvan put out the flame with an extinguisher, the police said. Both would-be robbers escaped. Mr. Galvan was not injured.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BRONX: GAS STATION EXPLOSION AVERTED  The driver of a gasoline truck received the scare of his life yesterday when a frustrated robber threw a lighted match at him as he was filling an underground tank at a Bronx gas station, the police said. They said the man who threw the match was angry because the driver, Roman Galvan, had refused to surrender money to him and an accomplice. The match caused a flash of fire at the Gaseteria station at 3804 Boston Road, but Mr. Galvan put out the flame with an extinguisher, the police said. Both would-be robbers escaped. Mr. Galvan was not injured.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>WHITE PLAINS: ECSTASY ARRESTS  Three Connecticut men are accused of supplying the drug Ecstasy to students at Byram Hills High School in Armonk. District Attorney Jeanine F. Pirro said the men were sources for a drug ring at the Westchester County school, where seven students were arrested in June. The police arrested two of the men in Rye Brook Friday night and one in Greenwich early Saturday. They are Brian Richard Frazier, 24, and Chung Hoang, 21, both of Greenwich; and Marc Mantia Jr., 20, of North Haven. Officers said they seized 1,600 Ecstasy tablets and more than 150 small bottles of the drug ketamine.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: STABBING IN MIDTOWN  A 29-year-old Brooklyn man was stabbed five times in front of his wife and another couple while walking in Midtown early yesterday morning, the police said. The authorities said two couples were walking together on 10th Avenue near 55th Street at 12:15 a.m. when a group of 10 men jeered at them. One man threw a liquid, perhaps a drink, into the face of the wife of Yung Cze, the police said. Mr. Cze scuffled with the men and was stabbed by one of them. Mr. Cze was in stable condition yesterday, the police said. There were no arrests.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CITY WORKER KNIFED  A Parks Department employee was stabbed in the arm by a homeless man yesterday after trying to roust the man from a men's room in Central Park. The police said the employee, Terry Richards, was not seriously injured in the noontime attack. The homeless man, William Gillum, was charged with assault and weapons possession and was to appear in court today.</p>
        <p>C.J. Chivers (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: PUBLIC ACT LEADS TO SHOOTING  A 23-year-old man shot another man in the leg early yesterday in an argument that began when he told the man to stop urinating against a building, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The 23-year-old, Franciscus Torrvellas, was walking with his mother about 1 a.m. in Bedford-Stuyvesant when they came upon Troy Watkins, 53, relieving himself, said Kevin Davitt, a spokesman for the Brooklyn district attorney's office. Mr. Torrvellas took offense and words were exchanged, and Mr. Torrvellas fired at Mr. Watkins, hitting him in the thigh, Mr. Davitt said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torrvellas struggled when he was arrested, and an officer was taken to the hospital with a hand injury, Mr. Davitt said. Mr. Torrvellas was charged with assault. Mr. Watkins was treated at a hospital and released.</p>
        <p>Andy Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: WOMAN DIES IN SHOOTING  A second woman died Sunday of injuries sustained in a shooting Saturday night, officials said. Latasha Logan, 20, of Hartford, died at 11:20 a.m. at St. Francis Hospital, officials said. She had been shot in the head. Desire Privette, 19, of Hartford, died earlier in the shooting, Her aunt, Caroline Privette, 39, was shot in the head and body and was in serious condition yesterday at St. Francis. The motive for the shooting is unknown.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: HAY FEVER ALERT  Hay fever sufferers in New Jersey may face an especially tough fall after a rainy, cool summer, unless even more rain arrives in the days ahead. Above-average rainfall, particularly this month, combined with record cool weather last month to help pollen-producing plants thrive in New Jersey. Also, relatively few sunny days this summer have kept ragweed, molds and other allergy triggers from drying out and burning up. ''Everything's growing like crazy,'' said Dr. Catherine Monteleone, an allergist at the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey. She said dry, windy days this fall could release that pollen.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>HEARING FOR HIRSCHFELD  A hearing in State Supreme Court in Manhattan is scheduled today in the grand larceny case against Abe Hirschfeld, the real-estate developer who was convicted in June of trying to hire a hit man to kill a former business partner.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY OPEN-SPACE LAW  Gov. Christine Todd Whitman is scheduled to go to a farm in Lawrence, N.J., to sign legislation designed to preserve open space.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
