<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winning Washington's Ear, With a Checkbook and a Tale</title>
    <meta content="28CHAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/28/nyregion/28CHAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUYING ENTREE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golden, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7D71131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="4330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winning Washington's Ear, With a Checkbook and a Tale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN and DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Golden, Tim; Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, Buying Entree, on influence peddling by David Chang, Asian businessman with questionable background who ingratiated himself with politicians by giving generously to senators and congressmen and who pleaded guilty in June to channeling more than $53,000 in illegal contributions to New Jersey Democratic Sen Robert G Torricelli; Chang is at center of widening federal inquiry into possibility that Torricelli's 1996 campaign staff may have been complicit in Chang's illegal donations; has reportedly given prosecutors information suggesting Torricelli's aides accounted improperly for some of his contributions; Torricelli and other politicians now cast him as unscrupulous con man, and themselves as his unwitting victims; portrait of Chang--drawn from interviews, court records and lawsuits pending against him--shows man of glaring and sometimes comical contradictions whose credibility is likely to be central issue in any new case that is brought; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At his small suite of offices in Fort Lee, N.J., David Chang was a tycoon without much to do.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang, 56, often rode to work in a Rolls-Royce and strode through the door in a long mink coat, a cigarette dangling from his lips. But although his holding company boasted of big, global deals in everything from oil exploration to telecommunications, almost none of those ventures ever got off the ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At his small suite of offices in Fort Lee, N.J., David Chang was a tycoon without much to do.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang, 56, often rode to work in a Rolls-Royce and strode through the door in a long mink coat, a cigarette dangling from his lips. But although his holding company boasted of big, global deals in everything from oil exploration to telecommunications, almost none of those ventures ever got off the ground.</p>
        <p>''I never really saw anybody there do anything,'' said Clark R. Wilcox, a former banking executive who was hired to help run the firm in 1997, only to quit soon after and successfully sue his former employer for breach of contract.</p>
        <p>In Washington, however, Mr. Chang cut a very different figure. There, he attended state dinners at the White House and visited informally with the president. He hired Mr. Clinton's chief fund-raiser as a consultant and cultivated senators and congressmen from both parties. The chairman of his company, a retired Navy admiral, had been chief of staff to George Bush when he was vice president.</p>
        <p>The secret of Mr. Chang's popularity among American politicians was of course no secret: he and his employees gave generously to favored candidates and their parties -- more than 100 contributions that totaled $325,000. Mr. Chang also pledged at least $1 million toward the presidential library that Mr. Clinton hopes to build in Little Rock, Ark.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang's activities finally caught the attention of federal campaign-finance investigators, who learned he was spending more on politicians than he was reporting in taxable income. In June, he pleaded guilty to channeling more than $53,000 in illegal contributions to one of the Democratic Party's most important fund-raisers, Senator Robert G. Torricelli of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Chang is at the center of a widening federal inquiry into the possibility that Mr. Torricelli's 1996 campaign staff may have been complicit in Mr. Chang's illegal donations -- something the senator strongly denies. Lawyers familiar with the case say Mr. Chang has given prosecutors information suggesting that Mr. Torricelli's aides accounted improperly for some of his contributions, and at least two dozen Federal Bureau of Investigation agents have been added to the inquiry in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli and other politicians now cast him as an unscrupulous con man, and themselves as his unwitting victims. Through his Washington lawyer, Mr. Chang declined to comment at all. But Mr. Chang's credibility is likely to be a central issue in any new case that is brought.</p>
        <p>A portrait of Mr. Chang -- drawn from interviews, court records and a thick file of lawsuits by and against him -- shows a man of glaring, sometimes comical contradictions: one who claims to have been educated at England's best schools but who speaks broken English; whose closest business contacts included Communist officials from North Korea and a former Republican congressman from New Jersey; who rallied American politicians to help him buy a billion-dollar South Korean insurance company but never had even a small fraction of the money he needed.</p>
        <p>''How can a guy like Chang get hooked up with all these people?'' asked Mr. Wilcox, his former employee. ''As a citizen, quite frankly, it makes me very angry.''</p>
        <p>As a businessman, many of his former employees say, Mr. Chang generated all sorts of ambitious schemes but almost no apparent profit. Though he has owned large homes, expensive cars and the 235-room Fort Lee Hilton hotel, just over the George Washington Bridge from Manhattan, it is unclear where he has gotten his money, large chunks of which have arrived in wire transfers from abroad, court records show.</p>
        <p>And while Mr. Chang's generosity won him many attentive friends in Washington, it did not buy him all the political favors he sought. His most important request, that the Clinton administration help him win repayment of tens of millions of dollars he said he was owed by North Korea for grain shipments, made almost no progress at all.</p>
        <p>''Did anything go wrong?'' said a spokesman for Mr. Clinton, Jake Seiwert. ''His proposals were neither accepted nor acted upon. What he wanted to do didn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Still, the story of Mr. Chang's education in money politics is a remarkable chapter in the saga of Washington influence bought and sold. In a world of fund-raiser business executives, deal-savvy senators and retired officials who increasingly exploit their connections abroad, Mr. Chang was a magnet for the powerful -- even after he was publicly identified as having given illegal donations to two different election campaigns.</p>
        <p>Basic Contradictions</p>
        <p>Just who David Chang is has been difficult to ascertain.</p>
        <p>At a bail hearing earlier this year, prosecutors noted that Mr. Chang had used at least two passports and three Social Security numbers, listed two different birthplaces and three different birth dates, and was married to two women at the same time -- not including a reputed girlfriend who has also been listed as his wife.</p>
        <p>''David Chang is a chronic liar,'' one of his many former lawyers, Michael S. Kimm, asserted in a recent lawsuit that, like several others by other people, claims that Mr. Chang failed to pay him what he owed.</p>
        <p>Even on the basic facts of his background, Mr. Chang has at least contradicted himself repeatedly. In one set of court papers, he said he was born in Beijing in 1943 and emigrated to South Korea soon after the Communist takeover of China six years later. In an interview last year with a South Korean newspaper, he said he was born in Korea and left his homeland in 1963, when he hopped a freighter and sailed to America. In New Jersey, Mr. Chang told his employees that he spent the 70's and 80's working as a high-flying oil trader in London and the Middle East. Through his Washington lawyer, David Schertler, Mr. Chang said he had worked abroad for his own oil company, Nikko Petroleum, and moved its operations to New York in 1976.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang's profile began to rise in the United States around 1990, when he became an American citizen. By then, he was calling his firm Nikko Enterprises Inc. and had moved it into offices in Fort Lee, just across the river from Manhattan.</p>
        <p>He portrayed himself as a man of discreet but powerful patrons. He told associates that he had named his firm for its sponsorship by the Nikko Securities Company, Japan's third-largest brokerage, and that he had a rich young wife back in Japan, the daughter of a Nikko executive.</p>
        <p>But not only did Nikko Securities have nothing to do with Mr. Chang, it also apparently persuaded him to stop using its name, prompting him to reincorporate his company in 1994 as Bright &amp; Bright. Soon enough, though, he found new sources of respectability in the United States.</p>
        <p>Among the first and most important of Mr. Chang's Washington contacts was Daniel J. Murphy, a high-profile lobbyist with a gleaming government resume. A retired four-star admiral, Mr. Murphy had commanded the Navy's Sixth Fleet, had served as chief of staff to George Bush when he was vice president, and had been a deputy director of the Central Intelligence Agency, and a deputy undersecretary of defense.</p>
        <p>After resigning from Vice President Bush's staff in 1985, Mr. Murphy went to work as a lobbyist, first for Gray &amp; Company, a firm closely tied to the Reagan administration, and then on his own. He quickly built a reputation for putting business ahead of politics, representing the Marxist government of Angola, trying to drum up business in Gen. Manuel Noriega's Panama, and maintaining a friendship with Tongsun Park, the former South Korean lobbyist and intelligence agent, long after Mr. Park's ties to American congressmen touched off a political scandal involving United States officials in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy, who declined to say anything about his relationsip with Mr. Chang, began working for him as a consultant and lobbyist by at least 1990, according to Mr. Schertler, Mr. Chang's lawyer. Mr. Murphy soon became a business partner as well, helping Mr. Chang open some of the more important doors in Washington.</p>
        <p>''He was at the White House once a month, when I was there,'' said one former assistant who worked for Mr. Chang during the latter half of the Bush administration. Mr. Bush's spokesman said the former president did not recall ever meeting Mr. Chang, and there are no records that he ever made a private visit to the White House.</p>
        <p>Creating a Niche</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang used his contacts to carve out an unusual business niche, trying to supply goods and services to countries hostile to the United States. Besides shipping wheat to North Korea, his former employees said, he tried to send ambulances and other equipment to Iraq. He also bought American real estate and Asian stocks, tried to sell repackaged cigarettes in Russia and beer snacks in South Korea, and explored building a fleet of mini-blimps for advertising. Almost none of his start-ups, however, seem to have even gotten off the ground.</p>
        <p>It is unclear what Mr. Chang was using for capital. For his grain deal with North Korea, he received at least $60 million from South Korea's Shinhan Bank, and from L.G. International, the New Jersey subsidiary of one of South Korea's biggest conglomerates.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. Chang obtained one of the first Commerce Department licenses authorizing the sale of food to North Korea, which was then subject to American trade sanctions. By 1994, court records show, he had shipped the government there some 560,000 tons of wheat, with a value of $110 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chang accused the North Korean government of failing to pay him $71 million on the deal and reneging on a $1.2-billion contract for further shipments. He made the accusations in a libel suit filed against a Korean-language newspaper based in Queens, which published an article accusing him of giving free rooms at the Fort Lee Hilton to visiting North Korean officials. The paper stood by its story; Mr. Chang dropped his suit three years later.</p>
        <p>Whatever misgivings Mr. Chang had about doing business with the North Koreans apparently eased. By 1998, he had been back in North Korea on a contract to provide logistical support for a United States Army team that sought to recover the remains of American soldiers missing there since the Korean War.</p>
        <p>New Alliances</p>
        <p>With Mr. Bush out of the White House and South Korean financiers pressing him for repayment on the grain deal, Mr. Chang began to cultivate the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Until then, he had been a relatively modest and mainly Republican donor. In 1992, for instance, he gave $25,000 to Republicans and $1,000 to Mr. Torricelli, then his local congressman. But by the 1995-96 election cycle, the balance of his generosity shifted to Democrats, and Mr. Torricelli became his most-favored politician.</p>
        <p>When pressed, a spokesman for Mr. Torricelli said his campaign fund-raisers merely found Mr. Chang's name -- along with hundreds of others -- on a list of New Jersey donors provided by the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''He was not one of the senator's inner circle of fund-raisers,'' the senator's chief of staff, Eric B. Shuffler, said. ''Not in any way, shape or form anything close to that.''</p>
        <p>But many of Mr. Torricelli's friends and former aides tell of a much closer relationship. ''All of a sudden,'' one former aide recalled, ''he became a player.''</p>
        <p>Over the next few years, Mr. Chang and his aides gave $8,000 to Mr. Torricelli, and Mr. Chang was named to the finance committee for Mr. Torricelli's 1996 campaign. Mr. Chang gave Mr. Torricelli use of his corporate jet during his 1996 Senate campaign, and investigators are now examining whether the campaign fully reimbursed Mr. Chang for the 19 flights. Mr. Chang gave $30,000 more to the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, of which Mr. Torricelli was named vice chairman and then chairman, and $5,000 to a legal-defense fund set up on Mr. Torricelli's behalf for a House ethics inquiry involving Mr. Torricelli, who was ultimately cleared.</p>
        <p>As his relationship with the White House grew, Mr. Chang and his companies gave $100,000 to the Democratic National Committee and $70,000 to the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. Over the same period, Mr. Chang, his aides and his companies gave only about $44,000 to the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Between late 1995 and 1996, Mr. Chang also arranged for an additional $53,700 in illegal contributions to Mr. Torricelli's campaign, funneling the money through friends, business associates and even the former chairman of the Bergen County Republican Party, Berek Don. Mr. Don has pleaded guilty to campaign finance violations and is cooperating with prosecutors.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Torricelli, who declined to answer questions himself, said the senator's office did almost nothing for Mr. Chang.</p>
        <p>''I know it looks strange, but this is not a guy who we did anything for,'' Mr. Shuffler said. ''No one on our staff, in our Washington office, ever spoke to Chang or met him.''</p>
        <p>Again, however, several other politicians and current and former Torricelli aides remember the relationship differently.</p>
        <p>''He was seen as someone who Torricelli was actively engaged with,'' one former aide said. ''This was a guy who was important to Bob.''</p>
        <p>In December 1997, Mr. Torricelli went to South Korea just days before a presidential election there. The American embassy, concerned that Mr. Torricelli might be seen as meddling in the campaign, balked at setting up political meetings for him. Mr. Chang swept into the void.</p>
        <p>In a one-page statement issued in response to written questions, Mr. Torricelli's office denied that Mr. Chang was present on the trip, made any of the arrangements for it, or communicated about it with any members of the senator's staff.</p>
        <p>But two people with detailed knowledge of the trip said Mr. Chang did stay in the same hotel as Mr. Torricelli, while Mr. Chang's aide, Christopher Kim, helped set up meetings for the senator with the two opposition candidates, Kim Dae Jung, who won the vote, and Rhee In Je. In a brief interview, Mr. Kim also acknowledged that Mr. Chang sent him to Seoul to help with the arrangements and to act as the senator's guide as he met with Korean officials and candidates.</p>
        <p>The week of Mr. Torricelli's visit, one of Mr. Chang's companies also made a $30,000 donation to the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee.</p>
        <p>Seeking Payback</p>
        <p>Despite all that support, a spokesman for Mr. Torricelli said he never helped Mr. Chang with the matter of his greatest concern -- persuading the administration to transfer frozen North Korean assets to him, or to pressure the North Korea to repay the debt. But other politicians were apparently more forthcoming.</p>
        <p>As recently as last fall, a handful of legislators, from the relatively liberal Senator Frank R. Lautenberg of New Jersey to conservative Republicans like Senator Craig Thomas of Wyoming, wrote to the administration on Mr. Chang's behalf, urging it not to ease the sanctions on North Korea without pressing for the repayment of debts to American companies like Bright &amp; Bright.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Lautenberg said they wrote a pro forma letter for him because he was a New Jersey resident. An aide to Mr. Thomas said the Wyoming senator supported Mr. Chang's appeal after being lobbied on his behalf by one of his business partners, James A. Courter, the former Republican congressman from New Jersey.</p>
        <p>According to two politicians close to Mr. Clinton, Mr. Chang was introduced to the president by Mr. Torricelli at a fund-raising event for the senator. Under questioning by the head of the Justice Department's campaign-financing task force, Robert J. Conrad Jr., Mr. Clinton said that Mr. Torricelli might have made the introduction, but that he could not remember.</p>
        <p>When South Korea's president visited Washington in June 1998, Mr. Chang and his then 30-year-old assistant, Audrey Yu, were among the guests at a state dinner. Barely a month later, on July 14, Mr. Clinton invited Mr. Chang over again, this time to watch a movie in the White House screening room. When Mr. Clinton traveled to Seoul that November, Mr. Chang and others said, he was invited to the president's hotel room for conversation and pizza. Days before Christmas, Mr. Chang was invited to the White House again, for a holiday dinner.</p>
        <p>Early the following spring, Mr. Chang was invited to the White House to watch the N.C.A.A. basketball final with Mr. Clinton. And when the Chinese prime minister, Zhu Rongji, visited that April, Mr. Chang and Ms. Yu were invited to another state dinner.</p>
        <p>Over the year that he was so assiduously wined, dined and entertained by Mr. Clinton and other administration officials, Mr. Chang and his companies donated more than $150,000 to the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Terry McAuliffe, the president's friend and chief fund-raiser, said, Mr. Chang ''was treated no differently from any other supporter.'' White House officials suggested that while senior National Security Council officials were dispatched twice in 1998 to meet with Mr. Chang and listened to his thoughts on the Middle East, North Korea and Iraq, mostly they just humored him.</p>
        <p>Yet even as Mr. Chang became a more prized Democratic donor, his legal troubles were in fairly plain sight.</p>
        <p>His role in making $12,000 in illegal campaign contributions to the 1992 campaign of former Representative Jay Kim, a Korean-American Republican from California, had come to light in news articles by August 1997. (Mr. Chang was not charged, after agreeing to cooperate with federal prosecutors.) His involvement in illegal contributions to the 1996 Torricelli campaign surfaced clearly in May 1999, when Mr. Don, the former Bergen County chairman, pleaded guilty to funneling Mr. Chang's money through employees at his law firm.</p>
        <p>Nor was there much evidence that Mr. Chang was flourishing in business.</p>
        <p>Between 1996 and 1998, while he donated more than $270,000 to various political causes, Mr. Chang reported only $183,000 in income. Over a one-year period starting in the fall of 1998, he also lost nearly $300,000 gambling in Atlantic City, federal prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seiwert, the White house spokesman, said a presidential visitor and donor like Mr. Chang should typically have been vetted by the Democratic National Committee, the Secret Service and White House researchers. He said administration officials were ''still checking'' to determine how that vetting might have been done in his case.</p>
        <p>In mid-1998, Mr. Chang hired Mr. McAuliffe to help him try to buy a bank in South Korea. Mr. McAuliffe said that before signing a yearlong consulting contract with Mr. Chang, he checked with several people, including Mr. Courter, the former congressman who was listed on company documents as the president of the new trading company that Mr. Chang established in late 1997, Panacom Inc.</p>
        <p>A person familiar with the contract said  Mr. Torricelli provided an enthusiastic reference, telling Mr. McAuliffe, ''He's a legitimate person, a legitimate businessman, his wife's family owns Nikko Securities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli's aides deny that he or any staff member ever vouched for Mr. Chang.</p>
        <p>The Biggest Deal</p>
        <p>Mr. McAuliffe said he never discussed Mr. Chang's business deals with President Clinton, and ended his consulting arrangement after only about six months. Roughly six months after that, however, he agreed to work for Mr. Chang again, this time as an investment banker when Panacom sought to buy the troubled Korea Life Insurance Company, South Korea's third-largest insurance company.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAuliffe said he went back after learning that Mr. Murphy was acting as Panacom's chairman, and after Mr. Courter assured him that Mr. Chang had enough money to buy the company. He said one of Mr. Chang's lawyers also gave him a Korean newspaper clipping indicating that former President Bush had already met with Korean officials on Panacom's behalf, something that one of Mr. Chang's former lawyers, Michael Critchley, also asserted during a hearing in federal court.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Bush, Gian-Carlo A. Peressutti, said this was untrue. The former president, he said, had been in Korea on behalf of another American firm, the Carlyle Group, which is headed by former Republican adminstration officials.</p>
        <p>The Korea Life deal would have been by far Mr. Chang's biggest yet, one that three of the world's largest multinational insurance companies had already bid on and lost by the summer of 1999, when Mr. Murphy and Mr. Chang stepped into the void.</p>
        <p>''It was a bit of a surprise, because no one had ever heard of them,'' recalled Lee Jong-Koo, a senior Finance Ministry official who attended the meeting. ''Chang and Admiral Murphy asked questions about K.L.I. and they indicated that they could raise abundant funds to acquire the company from various sources, especially New Jersey pension funds.''</p>
        <p>In an interview at his office in Seoul, Mr. Lee said Korean officials repeatedly sought further evidence from Mr. Chang that Panacom could assemble the roughly $1.5 billion they were seeking for the company. Instead, they heard about Mr. Chang's politician friends. ''I remember David Chang said he knew Senator Torricelli and other politicians,'' Mr. Lee said. ''He also said that he knew President Clinton and that he had eaten pizza with the president.''</p>
        <p>Within weeks, the Korean prime minister, Kim Jong Pil, began to receive letters from politicians in Washington and New Jersey. Representative Gregory W. Meeks, a New York City Democrat, wrote to ''highly recommend Panacom for this acquisition because of their strong record in investment, trade and finance for many years.'' Representative Carolyn Maloney, another New York City Democrat, who received $2,000 from Mr. Chang and his assistant in 1998, wrote a similar letter. Senator Torricelli and a New Jersey state finance official, also wrote letters, Korean officials said.</p>
        <p>The two representatives said through spokesmen that they did so because they believed Panacom was a legitimate business with operations in New York. Aides to one lawmaker said they also checked first with Mr. Torricelli's staff, which vouched strongly for Mr. Chang. A spokesman for Mr. Torricelli denied this had happened.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli agreed to provide The New York Times with a copy of the letter he wrote to the Korean government on Panacom's behalf. After several weeks, however, his aides said the letter could not be found.</p>
        <p>Deepening Troubles</p>
        <p>As Mr. Chang's push for the insurance deal continued last summer, Korean officials became openly suspicious that he was acting as a front man for the former owner of the insurance company, who had been jailed on corruption charges but was trying to win it back.</p>
        <p>''I knew this guy Chang was lying to me,'' Mr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McAuliffe flew to Seoul in late August to help move the deal ahead. But he said that after only two discussions with Panacom lawyers, he turned around and flew home, refusing to meet with Korean officials.</p>
        <p>The Korea Life deal finally fell through last fall, as Mr. Chang's legal troubles were deepening in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>With the pressure from federal prosecutors growing, the lawyer then leading Mr. Chang's defense, Mr. Critchley, did something that stunned many of the lawyers following the case. After Mr. Chang's arrest on campaign-finance, conspiracy and obstruction of justice charges, Mr. Critchley announced in court that Mr. Chang had ''no information about any criminal wrongdoing'' by any public officials, mentioning President Clinton, Senator Torricelli and Mr. McAuliffe by name. With that, Mr. Critchley, who is active in Democratic Party politics in New Jersey, seemed to foreclose the possibility that Mr. Chang would ever cooperate with the government.</p>
        <p>Less than six months later, however, as Mr. Chang prepared to go to trial with a new lawyer, he indicated to prosecutors that he might have that kind of information and agreed to cooperate with the authorities. He became the sixth person to plead guilty to making illegal contributions to Mr. Torricelli's campaign.</p>
        <p>BUYING ENTREE Calvin Sims contributed to this report.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Calvin Sims contributed to this report.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
