<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Republican Blazes a Trail In the Campaign For Lazio's Seat</title>
    <meta content="28JOHN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/28/nyregion/28john.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORK PRIMARY -- Second Congressional District" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Joan B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walsh, Robert T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Richard N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4D61131F93BA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Republican Blazes a Trail In the Campaign For Lazio's Seat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>BAY SHORE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan B Johnson, Islip town clerk, comments on being first black Republican woman to seek House seat in either Nassau or Suffolk County, NY; will face Robert T Walsh in Republican primary and Richard N Thompson in Conservative primary for seat being vacated by Senate candidate Rick A Lazio; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was, she says, divine inspiration that cast her into a race that could make her the first black Republican woman ever to serve in Congress.</p>
        <p>''I really think I am on a path that someone higher than me is preparing me for,'' says Joan B. Johnson, 66, the elected town clerk of Islip, who has mounted a campaign to win the Suffolk County seat that Representative Rick A. Lazio is giving up for his Senate candidacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was, she says, divine inspiration that cast her into a race that could make her the first black Republican woman ever to serve in Congress.</p>
        <p>''I really think I am on a path that someone higher than me is preparing me for,'' says Joan B. Johnson, 66, the elected town clerk of Islip, who has mounted a campaign to win the Suffolk County seat that Representative Rick A. Lazio is giving up for his Senate candidacy.</p>
        <p>There was, of course, some earthly machination as well. Two of Suffolk County's most powerful Republicans, the party leaders of the county organization and the town of Islip, the largest community, threw their support behind Mrs. Johnson, a blunt-spoken former social worker. She may lack the polish of a political pro, party leaders reasoned, but she is a proven vote getter whose moderate stances to the left of Mr. Lazio -- and perhaps her race and sex -- will attract  Democrats' votes in the Second Congressional District, where Republicans hold only a slight edge in voter registration.</p>
        <p>And now Mrs. Johnson, one of a few black Republican women running in the country but the one political analysts say has the best shot, finds herself in the semi-comfortable position of blazing a trail, maybe two, lined with obstacles. She must win a primary on Sept. 12, and confront the possibility that, as she and her supporters concede,  some people may not vote for her, simply because of her race and sex.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people really thought they were going to get this nod, mainly because here on Long Island you tend to have a cookie-cutter type profile of what a congressperson should look like,'' Mrs. Johnson said, alluding to the Island's penchant for sending young, white male lawyers to Washington. ''And it didn't look like me. It's never female. And in that respect, that's the historic piece of this. I would be the first Republican woman in either Nassau or Suffolk Counties to ever run for Congress.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Johnson, who grew up in Florida when segregation was legal and has lived in Islip for 38 years, said the racial aspect of her potential achievement never occurred to her until a reporter for a political journal raised the issue, shortly after she entered the campaign in June.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Oh, my God.' First time I heard it. Never even thought about it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Johnson, who teaches Bible study on Saturdays and dispenses marriage licenses and other bureaucratic documents during the week, now weathers the gale of a high-stakes Congressional race, one symbolically and tactically important for Republicans. Their five-seat hold on the House is on the line, and they are loath to surrender any seat, much less that of Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>And so Mrs. Johnson, town clerk since 1991, is surrounded by a staff she hardly knows, with a state party operative as her campaign manager and a Washington consultant, Tony Marsh, as campaign strategist. Her eyes bulge at her fund-raising goal, $1.5 million, 88 times the most she ever raised for a town clerk campaign and a far cry from what she has now, about $130,000.</p>
        <p>The open seat has brought out a bevy of contenders to a contest that Congressional Quarterly, a leading political journal, rates a tossup between the eventual Democratic and Republican nominees.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Johnson has received the endorsement of the Republican and the Conservative Party organizations, but faces a primary on both lines. Her Republican challenger is Robert T. Walsh, a retired banker from Deer Park who represents a Russian humanitarian organization at the United Nations. Mr. Walsh also plans to run on the Right to Life line, as he did in 1994 when he ran for governor. (Mrs. Johnson favors abortion rights with no restrictions, unlike Mr. Lazio, who opposes both public financing for abortions and late-term procedures.) Richard N. Thompson of West Islip is challenging her on the Conservative line.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh, calling Mrs. Johnson's positions on abortion and gun control out of step with the district's electorate, said, ''I think she is an extraordinarily weak candidate and has little chance to beat the Democrats running.'' He said his years as a banking executive and as a goodwill ambassador at the United Nations stood above her qualifications ''or lack thereof'' as town clerk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, a lawyer from West Islip who was a pitcher for the Cleveland Indians and Montreal Expos in the 1980's, said he viewed Mrs. Johnson as too far to the left on a number of issues. ''I don't think she was the best candidate chosen by the Republicans,'' he said. ''I didn't think she was a voice for conservative values, so I felt compelled to run.''</p>
        <p>The opponent the primary winners will face is still undetermined. Democrats are headed for a three-way primary, with the victor almost guaranteed strong backing by the national party in an effort both to embarrass Mr. Lazio by grabbing his seat and to help win back the House. They are seeking to reclaim a seat held by a Democrat, Thomas Downey, for 20 years before Mr. Lazio defeated him in 1992.</p>
        <p>But among the biggest question marks looming is how voters will take to Mrs. Johnson's race and sex, in a district that has never sent a woman to Congress and whose population of 580,000 is about 79 percent white, 9 percent black, 9 percent Hispanic and 2 percent Asian.</p>
        <p>Republicans have portrayed her candidacy as groundbreaking and emblematic of the diversity and inclusiveness they seek. National party officials gave her a brief but valuable daytime speaking role at the Republican National Convention this month. The National Republican Congressional Committee, which conducted a poll in early June that placed Mrs. Johnson near the top of the potential candidates in name recognition, is expected to send a hefty sum to her campaign this fall.</p>
        <p>That said, even some of Mrs. Johnson's supporters openly wonder whether people will choose not to vote for her principally because of her race. ''I'd like to say that won't happen, but realistically it might,'' said State Senator Carl L. Marcellino of Syosset, who said he was hopeful that ''people in the district will look beyond that.''</p>
        <p>Some Republicans privately worry about Mrs. Johnson's age and lack of political or legislative experience and rue the decision of Peter McGowan, the powerful Islip town supervisor, to skip the race even though he topped the list of six or seven contenders for the party's backing. Mrs. Johnson, who was not on the initial list, is most often described as kindly, but lacking the fierce ambition that could make waves in a local party striving for stability after scandals and a succession of leaders.</p>
        <p>She scoffs at those who question her experience, saying the administrative tasks of the town clerk's office and service on numerous community organization boards adequately prepare anyone for Congress. She cites the case of Representative Carolyn McCarthy, a Long Island Democrat, who won office in 1996 with no political experience by running on a gun control platform rooted in the death of her husband in the Long Island Rail Road shooting in 1993.</p>
        <p>As for strategy, Mrs. Johnson hammers an antitax message but also has firmly hitched her fortune to Mr. Lazio, a popular figure in the district. In remarks at a recent ''meet the candidates'' picnic, Mrs. Johnson scarcely mentioned herself for all her praise of Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Black Republicans have always tilted at political windmills, said David Bositis, senior political analyst for the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies, a Washington-based organization that studies African-American affairs. There is only one black Republican now in Congress, J. C. Watts of Oklahoma, and there have been only five this century, Mr. Bositis said.</p>
        <p>''Face it, there is a lot of history between African-Americans and the G.O.P.,'' said Mr. Bositis, citing as an example the party's advocacy during the 1960's and 70's of ''states' rights' and other positions that blacks have seen as racially tinged appeals to white Southerners. ''At least in the recent past, most of it is negative. No amount of image making in the short term is going to change that around.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Johnson grows impatient with talk about one party being for one race or another, a form of ''racial profiling,'' she says with a laugh. If Democrats are perceived as more likely champions of racial advancement, people need to go further back in history, she says with mounting bitterness, rattling off names of Southern Democrats with reputations for intolerance. ''I'll tell you who the people were in power when my people were hanging from ropes in trees. They were Democrats.''</p>
        <p>Her views are generally liberal. She is for not only abortion rights, but also affirmative action, and -- as the godmother of a 17-year-old murder victim -- gun control, including registration. She supports the death penalty, for the most heinous crimes like serial killings, but she says her positions are not rigid and shifted uncomfortably as she discussed the topic. ''These issues don't come easy to me,'' she says. ''All life is precious.''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Johnson says she feels philosophically closer to Republicans because of her goals to lower taxes and shrink government.</p>
        <p>More than anything, however, Mrs. Johnson senses victory in her web of community connections, from her work at Head Start to children's clubs to the town clerk's office.</p>
        <p>''See that robe?'' she says, motioning to a black gown hanging in the campaign office here on East Main Street that once was where she got her nails done. ''I've married 2,500 couples. That's 5,000 people who personally know me because I've put them together.'' She added: ''I go to the Eagle Scout awards, and I was a member of the Boy Scouts Council, and I was a vice president of the Girl Scouts Council, so I do a lot of things locally. My weekends are always filled with community things, the Fire Department, the whatever, the church events.''</p>
        <p>Theresa Sanders, president of the Urban League of Long Island, a nonpartisan group, said: ''She always has been an unsung hero in our community. What Joan Johnson does represent is we've always had progressive, articulate, dedicated African-Americans in our community, and Joan Johnson is no stranger to us.''</p>
        <p>New York Primary</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining individual primary contests in Congressional and local districts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
