<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2DD1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-8</p>
        <p>Basic Error Behind Missile Defense Test Failure  A crucial test in the Pentagon's program to defend American territory from missile attacks collapsed in failure because the high-speed interceptor that was supposed to destroy a dummy warhead in space never separated from its booster rocket, the Pentagon said.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-8</p>
        <p>Basic Error Behind Missile Defense Test Failure  A crucial test in the Pentagon's program to defend American territory from missile attacks collapsed in failure because the high-speed interceptor that was supposed to destroy a dummy warhead in space never separated from its booster rocket, the Pentagon said.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>H.I.V. Education in South Africa  Erotic and hard-hitting phrases are part of a down-to-earth campaign aimed at reducing by one-half the rate of infection from H.I.V., the AIDS virus, in South Africa in five years. The campaign is gathering pace as South Africa hosts the 13th International Conference on AIDS, opening today.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Putin Offers State of Union  President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia assembled both houses of Parliament and a national television audience to present a glum assessment of the state of the nation. It was notable for his emphatic and, at some points, seemingly emotional commitment to building a democracy.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>U.S. Envoy Visits China  A visiting American official to China praised the country for becoming ''a major participant'' in nonproliferation efforts in Asia and around the world but said two days of talks did not allay concerns about recent Chinese help for Pakistan's ballistic missile program.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Gay Pride Parade in Rome  Defying the Vatican and right-wing political groups, tens of thousands of demonstrators marched peacefully in a gay pride parade through central Rome.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>10-22</p>
        <p>Judges Named by Bush Are Viewed as Moderate  Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has appointed justices who have been a moderating influence on the state's Supreme Court, which is often regarded as among the most conservative and pro-business in the country. The appointments might offer some insight into what Mr. Bush would do in Washington.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore is seeking to tie Gov. George W. Bush tightly to the Republican-led Congress and blame him for the legislative stalemate on major issues.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Debate Over the Perfect Lawn  The Scotts Company is developing genetically engineered grass that would require less mowing, or thrive in the winter, or glow in the dark. Some fear that the plants will fundamentally alter the environment.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A Deadly Lesson  The founder of a group that contended alcoholics could drink in moderation has pleaded guilty to vehicular homicide after a binge drinking episode. She is awaiting sentencing, and she has changed her views.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Lutheran-Episcopal Alliance  Church leaders say an alliance between the Episcopal Church and the nation's largest Lutheran denomination could lead to other sharing.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Snapping Up Harry Potter  Children and parents across the country made treks to bookstores that opened just after midnight to capitalize on the demand for ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire.''</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Female Bishops in Running  The African Methodist Episcopal Church might soon elect a female bishop, the first in its history.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>23-30</p>
        <p>City's Housing Shortage Worst in Decades  New Yorkers are suffering in the grip of the worst housing shortage in decades, with soaring prices to match. That verdict is virtually unanimous among business and real estate executives, academics, community leaders, planners, politicians and advocates for the poor. But while nearly everyone agrees New York has a housing problem, there is no consensus on what, if anything, to do about it.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Police Baffled by Incident  A day after two off-duty police officers shot and killed an unarmed man in an unusual rush-hour confrontation on a Queens highway, the authorities said that they could not explain why he had leapt from a car into fast-moving traffic and then attacked the officers. The investigation into the shooting focuses on whether the two police officers were justified in firing their weapons at the man.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Charles Alan Wright  An authority on constitutional law and the federal courts who represented President Richard M. Nixon at a crucial moment in the Watergate scandal, he was 72.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Barbara T. Christian  A professor of African-American studies who was a pioneer of contemporary American literary feminism, she was 56.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>30  Weather</p>
        <p>27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
