<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hats Off to the Flag and, Of Course, George Cohan</title>
    <meta content="09THEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gateway Playhouse (Bellport, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohan, George M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Yankee Doodle Dandy (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6D71139F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hats Off to the Flag and, Of Course, George Cohan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>BELLPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews musical Yankee Doodle Dandy, featuring songs of George M Cohan and directed by David Armstrong, at Gateway Playhouse in Bellport, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PANORAMA of musical comedy images unfurls like a grand old flag symbolizing America's indigenous theater form. There's Tevye and here's Dolly, in eternal visual testament to Jerome Robbins and Gower Champion. What do those gyrating dancers giving their bowler hats a workover signify if not ''Steam Heat''? After Bob Fosse, can Michael Bennett be far behind? A whole chorus line would be nice, but it only takes a few bespangled gypsies extending top hats along with high kicks to spark a singular sensation.</p>
        <p>It's not an elementary best-of-Broadway quiz, but the best of ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'' at Gateway Playhouse here. And that doesn't come until the finale when those instantly identifiable characters crisscross. By then, it is dazzlingly clear that the visual language of American musical theater is as powerful and as lingering as its sounds and stories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PANORAMA of musical comedy images unfurls like a grand old flag symbolizing America's indigenous theater form. There's Tevye and here's Dolly, in eternal visual testament to Jerome Robbins and Gower Champion. What do those gyrating dancers giving their bowler hats a workover signify if not ''Steam Heat''? After Bob Fosse, can Michael Bennett be far behind? A whole chorus line would be nice, but it only takes a few bespangled gypsies extending top hats along with high kicks to spark a singular sensation.</p>
        <p>It's not an elementary best-of-Broadway quiz, but the best of ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'' at Gateway Playhouse here. And that doesn't come until the finale when those instantly identifiable characters crisscross. By then, it is dazzlingly clear that the visual language of American musical theater is as powerful and as lingering as its sounds and stories.</p>
        <p>But the show's creators are spotlighting the importance and the influence of George M. Cohan.</p>
        <p>In a burst of ego and braggadocio, Cohan surged from vaudeville to Broadway at the turn of the century. He brought along the rest of the Four Cohans: his father, Jerry; his mother, Nellie, and his sister, Josie. And he took over the Great White Way, as star, songwriter, director and eventually playwright. Critics deplored his simplistic jingoism. Audiences adored it. He was dubbed ''The Man Who Owns Broadway,'' which happened to be the title of one of his shows.</p>
        <p>How many of his shows are still known? When ''Little Johnny Jones,'' Cohan's breakthrough hit of 1904, was resuscitated on Broadway as a showcase for Donny Osmond, it opened -- and closed -- on March 21, 1982. That production was imported from Goodspeed Opera House in East Haddam, Conn., where the 1968 Broadway musical ''George M!'' is now being produced.</p>
        <p>''George M!'' -- a star vehicle for Joel Grey in the title role and Broadway debut for 20-year-old Bernadette Peters as Josie -- is rarely revived. More a Cohan songfest (''Give My Regards to Broadway,'' ''You're A Grand Old Flag,'' ''Over There'') than an interesting narrative or structured musical, the show was Gateway's choice for this season.</p>
        <p>But David Armstrong, who has directed musicals here and written his own, ''pitched the idea'' for his newly conceived show about Cohan, said Paul Allan, the theater's producer. Mr. Allan took the leap, knowing it was at least hasty to expect a new musical, even one with old songs, to coalesce in three and a half months. Some of the theater's best known flops took a decade.</p>
        <p>With no previews, ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'' opened on June 28 for three weeks. Actors Equity rules and the demands of the theater itself, where another full production -- ''South Pacific'' -- begins July 19, mean that changes requiring rehearsals, and even rehearsals of existing material, are out of the question.</p>
        <p>What to do? Mr. Allan's risk could pay off in time. Before the parade of legendary moving pictures passes by in the finale, a bare-bones book, with lots of names dropped (Ziegfeld, Jolson), a few new songs with dreadful lyrics, all by Albert Evans, attempt to tell the tale of an unfulfilled man who, besides fame and fortune, had it all, marriage (marriages), family, friends, and, well, just messed it all up. It is traditionally hard to care about theater legends, or for that matter the celebrated of any stripe, who whine: ''What was it all for?'' That's because anyone in the audience can provide the answer.</p>
        <p>Putting the neurotic, obsessed life, as opposed to the popular work, on the stage, is all too often an unsolvable obstacle. It's the persona and the talent that counts, not the tantrums, ''the fists, the fights, the egos,'' to paraphrase a Sondheim lyric. And not the dysfunctional elements. Which is why attempts to make a musical of Al Jolson's life have been failing for decades, while the old-fashioned sanitized, Hollywoodized bio-musicals succeeded in their time. No one wants to know that Jolson was a cad, and Cohan was, evidently, no better. And besides, he won financing and contracts for ''Little Johnny Jones,'' before he even wrote it. And then it was a smash. Poor thing.</p>
        <p>At Gateway, the musical numbers, staged by Jamie Rocco, range from derivative without that Champion touch (think ''42nd Street'') to inspired (the finale). In the end, the indelible post-Cohan images follow replays of the old-fangled ones that are performed throughout. A statement about the evolution of musical theater is potently made, and not even musical comedy buffs may think of Cohan in such terms. It is an idea to develop in a show that somehow needs to lead up to just what Cohan contributed to an art form that many people insist is dying. For he was out of fashion. Cole Porter was in.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, as an all-singing, all-dancing potential work-in-progress, ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'' has its moments. But not when it talks. Whatever your time limits -- the first act is way too long -- don't bolt before the 11 o'clock number.</p>
        <p>''Yankee Doodle Dandy,'' Gateway Playhouse, 215 South Country Road, Bellport, N.Y. Box office (631) 286-1133. Performances through Saturday.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
