<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Elbow Room For Plovers and Terns</title>
    <meta content="09PLOV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plover (Bird)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terns (Birds)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fish and Wildlife Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marcazzo, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D61139F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Elbow Room For Plovers and Terns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REGINA MARCAZZO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marcazzo, Regina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on program aimed at protecting nesting plovers, put at about 250 pairs, and least terns, estimated at 2,750 pairs, along Long Island beaches; both bird species are protected by federal and state governments and many agencies handle protection programs developed by US Fish and Wildlife Service; supporters and opponents of program comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Valerie Stillman-Tidwell learned that a piping plover had nested on her property, she was thrilled. ''I feel like their mother,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stillman-Tidwell, who owns a home on Dune Road in Westhampton Beach, each year gives the Nature Conservancy permission to go on her property and set up fencing to protect birds. The pair of plovers, who have three eggs, tried two other times to nest this year but failed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Valerie Stillman-Tidwell learned that a piping plover had nested on her property, she was thrilled. ''I feel like their mother,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stillman-Tidwell, who owns a home on Dune Road in Westhampton Beach, each year gives the Nature Conservancy permission to go on her property and set up fencing to protect birds. The pair of plovers, who have three eggs, tried two other times to nest this year but failed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stillman-Tidwell also has to deal with more disruptive least terns, but she doesn't mind.</p>
        <p>''The least terns are more aggressive,'' said Joseph Jannsen, director of the Coastal Species Recovery Program at the Nature Conservancy, which has seven people overseeing 16 Island nesting sites. ''People are not as likely to want to protect them. All we can do is try to educate them.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone has Ms. Stillman-Tidwell's welcoming attitude. Some bumper stickers read, ''Piping plover tastes like chicken'' and ''Piping plover makes good traction.''</p>
        <p>The plovers and the terns are protected by both the federal and state governments. They started disappearing from the Island in the late 1800's, when they were hunted for sport and for their feathers. They were protected from hunting in 1918 and the population recovered to peak in the 1940's. Development and recreational use of the beaches has since caused a decline in population. They have been protected since 1983.</p>
        <p>About 250 nesting pairs of plovers make the Island their home, as do about 2,750 pairs of least terns.</p>
        <p>Many different agencies handle the protection programs, which were developed by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</p>
        <p>The operation does not have universal support. ''You don't want to see something become extinct,'' said John Lund, president of the Davis Park Association. But he adds: ''We have thousands of people. There's no way in the world you're going to educate so many people. It's a royal pain in the neck.''</p>
        <p>Ed Bianchi, a board member of the Water Island Association, had terns nesting in front of his house, but he does approve of the protection programs. Meetings with various agencies and community organizations mean everyone knows exactly what to do. ''They have us involved in the decision making,'' Mr. Bianchi said.</p>
        <p>When nests are found where vehicles are needed to carry supplies, for example, a person must walk in front of each vehicle to check for plovers.</p>
        <p>Members of the Long Island Beach Buggy Association also understand that the birds must be saved but feel the protection program could be less confining. ''It affects us in a big way: we cannot ride the open beach anymore,'' said Thomas Kehlenbeck, a former president of the association.</p>
        <p>Every bird counts. Sammy's Beach in East Hampton is being closed through August because a plover chick was killed and found in a tire track, and Democrat Point in Babylon has been closed to vehicles.</p>
        <p>''It puts a cramp on surf fishing,'' said Tony Mendola, treasurer of the beach buggy association and resident of Towd Point in Southampton. ''It's a major inconvenience for us. I don't really know that we're helping them that much,'' he said, noting an increase in natural predators like red fox since the program began.</p>
        <p>Piping plover pairs have increased substantially since 1983 but the numbers have leveled out over the past five years, according to Dan Rosenblatt, the regional coordinator of the endangered species program for the state Department of Environmental Conservation. The goal is to reach about 575 pairs, and ''we're basically half way there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The availability of habitat is a big problem because breeding birds -- unlike some vacationing humans -- do not share space with other pairs. The birds tend to come back to the areas where they nested previously.</p>
        <p>In East Hampton there has been an increase in piping plover nests this year, with five pairs nesting at Sammy's Beach. Last year there was only one pair; for the three years before that, there were none.</p>
        <p>Southampton Town has also seen improvements, with the number of fledged plovers rising to 41 last year, from 29 in 1998.</p>
        <p>''It's a very, very challenging management program,'' said Scott Strough, president of Southampton's board of trustees. But ''we understand that we have to keep these beaches open.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
