<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Middle Passage to Martin's Dream</title>
    <meta content="09VALE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amistad (Schooner)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models and Replicas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2DE1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Middle Passage to Martin's Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes musical events scheduled for two-day festival in New Haven, Conn, as city welcomes replica of schooner Amistad to its home port; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the 19th-century reproduction schooner Amistad pulls into its homeport of New Haven next weekend for a two-day festival honoring the struggle for freedom of its enslaved passengers, music of African Americans will be played throughout the city.</p>
        <p>From West African drumming at the wharf, to the New Haven Symphony's concert on the green of music by African American composers, to the New Haven-homegrown Soul Tempo (who have toured with Elton John), the festival offers a lesson not only in American history but also in the African-American music tradition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the 19th-century reproduction schooner Amistad pulls into its homeport of New Haven next weekend for a two-day festival honoring the struggle for freedom of its enslaved passengers, music of African Americans will be played throughout the city.</p>
        <p>From West African drumming at the wharf, to the New Haven Symphony's concert on the green of music by African American composers, to the New Haven-homegrown Soul Tempo (who have toured with Elton John), the festival offers a lesson not only in American history but also in the African-American music tradition.</p>
        <p>Kay George Roberts wields the baton for the free symphony concert entitled ''Hearing Amistad,'' an idea she said came to her two years ago when she read about the Amistad. Ms. Roberts, the first African-American woman to earn a doctor of musical arts degree in conducting from the Yale School of Music, has most recently led the Cleveland Orchestra and the Dallas Symphony. Ms. Roberts is on the faculty of the University of Massachussetts at Lowell, and spoke by telephone from Cambridge about how the Amistad and its story inspired the concert.</p>
        <p>''A year ago I was in the Mystic area'' Ms. Roberts said, ''and I went to see how the ship was coming along. I got a personal tour. I was tremendously moved by the history there.</p>
        <p>''But there was a personal connection as well,'' she added. ''The American Missionary Association, which in 1840 helped the Amistad captives secure their freedom, helped establish educational institutions. One of those schools was Fiske University in Nashville, Tenn., where I grew up.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberts, who is 49 years old, said her father founded the psychology department at Fiske, and she earned her bachelor of arts in music there before coming to Yale.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberts said she is committed to conducting classical music written by African-American composers. ''This goes back all the way to the 1700's in America,'' she said, adding that these composers worked in the European classical style.</p>
        <p>Modern-day composers have written works specifically about the Amistad ordeal, including an opera, and Ms. Roberts has designed a program of contemporary pieces that chronicle the African-American experience from the mid-1800's to the present.</p>
        <p>Adolphus Hailstork wrote ''Celebration!'' for the Bicentennial celebration in 1976, and it incorporates the musical traditions of Europe and Africa, in a Spanish 7/8 tempo.</p>
        <p>''African Portraits,'' by Hannibal Lokumbe, is a music drama that evokes the experience of the African captives through the Middle Passage to slavery. ''The music captures the sounds of waves smashing against the creaking wooden ship,'' Ms. Roberts noted.</p>
        <p>The Underground Railroad is portrayed in Wendell Logan's ''Runagate, Runagate.'' ''It's a captivating drama about the escape from slavery to freedom in the North,'' Ms. Roberts said.</p>
        <p>The spiritual ''Great Day'' will be sung by the the Heritage Chorale of New Haven.</p>
        <p>''Dance for Martin's Dream,'' by Michael Abels, incorporates musical styles of blue grass, funk, salsa, early American ballet and beat-box. Ms. Roberts draws a parallel between the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and the captive Cinque, who led the revolt on the Amistad.</p>
        <p>The concert will conclude with the spiritual ''I'm So Glad I'm Free,'' for gospel choir and orchestra.</p>
        <p>The celebration on the green continues when New Haven's own quartet, Soul Tempo, takes the stage. ''We've been together all of our lives,'' said Jerry Brunson, a member of the group and its spokesman. ''We used to hang out in the streets,'' he said, ''and we'd sing a cappella in the park on summer nights until the neighbors told us to go home.'' More than likely now the neighbors would clamor for encores. Influenced by the smooth harmonies of the Persuasions, Temptations, Earth, Wind and  Fire and Blue Magic, the four members of the group went to school together, then to college in Bridgeport, then out into the world to make a go of it.</p>
        <p>Soul Tempo's big break came when Penny Marshall in her role as movie producer summoned them for an audition. ''When we got the movie 'The Preacher's Wife,' that really put our name out there,'' said Mr. Brunson.</p>
        <p>''Next thing you know, we're in New York on the West Side with Penny, Denzel and Whitney,'' he said, referring to Ms. Marshall and the movie's stars, Denzel Washington and Whitney Houston.</p>
        <p>Soul Tempo -- whose other members are Tony Burnett, Kevin Mitchell and Philip Mitchell -- tours all over the world, and will be leaving soon for Britain.</p>
        <p>But the date in New Haven is one of the most important. ''Being a part of Amistad is history for the group. We're really looking forward to it,'' said Mr. Brunson. ''We have a lot of gigs, I made sure I put this one down on the calendar. This is our town. We want to let the people know they have a group here thats making some noise.''</p>
        <p>The group will be doing several cuts from their latest CD, ''I Can't Wait'' (Music Avenue Records), and will have a band. Songs from artists who inspired them will be sprinkled throughout the set as well, and the whole show is choreographed.</p>
        <p>The Tony Award-winning actress and singer Melba Moore will then take the stage, singing a special concert in honor of Amistad.</p>
        <p>The Amistad Homeport Arrival Celebration will be held Saturday and next Sunday. The festivities begin at Long Wharf Park at 10:30 a.m. and feature African drumming and dancing, a festival of tall ships, exhibits, theater performances, a food court and Freedom Trail tours. The concert, which begins at 6 p.m. on Saturday on the New Haven green, includes performances by the New Haven Symphony conducted by Kay George Roberts, the group Soul Tempo and Melba Moore. The festival continues on the green on Sunday with an interfaith service at 2 p.m. and a concert by the United States Coast Guard Band at 4 p.m. At 7 p.m., at the Long Wharf Theater, the festival's final event will be ''Waiting for Justice: The Trials of the Amistad.'' The reading is free and will be followed by a discussion. All festival events are free and open to the public.</p>
        <p>The number to call for further information is Amistad America in New Haven at (203) 499-3894 or one can visit the event's Web site at www.amistadamerica.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
