<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Banishing the Dickensian Factor</title>
    <meta content="09GREE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweatshops</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fair Labor Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D61738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Banishing the Dickensian Factor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anti-sweatshop movement is finally beginning to prod manufacturers to take steps that may lead to improvement of working conditions around the world; manufacturing giants have for first time joined Fair Labor Assn, which has adopted code of conduct and called for large-scale overseas monitoring that is set to begin this fall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN this era when the consumer is king, many Americans are displaying noblesse oblige toward the millions of foreign workers who make the goods that flood store shelves. High school students have demonstrated at Disney's Mickey-filled emporiums over the company's use of low-wage factories in China and Haiti. Nuns concerned about child labor have distributed leaflets outside Gap stores. At Duke and Georgetown, students have staged sit-ins to protest conditions at factories producing apparel carrying their college logos. And everyone seems to beat up on Nike.</p>
        <p>For years, these anti-sweatshop protests accomplished next to nothing. Many manufacturers responded by simply saying they did not control the overseas factories that they contracted with. Some embarrassed designers adopted codes of conduct, which were often ignored abroad. Before monitors visited, factory owners hid their under-aged workers and ordered employees to say they worked 40-hour weeks, not the more typical 75 hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN this era when the consumer is king, many Americans are displaying noblesse oblige toward the millions of foreign workers who make the goods that flood store shelves. High school students have demonstrated at Disney's Mickey-filled emporiums over the company's use of low-wage factories in China and Haiti. Nuns concerned about child labor have distributed leaflets outside Gap stores. At Duke and Georgetown, students have staged sit-ins to protest conditions at factories producing apparel carrying their college logos. And everyone seems to beat up on Nike.</p>
        <p>For years, these anti-sweatshop protests accomplished next to nothing. Many manufacturers responded by simply saying they did not control the overseas factories that they contracted with. Some embarrassed designers adopted codes of conduct, which were often ignored abroad. Before monitors visited, factory owners hid their under-aged workers and ordered employees to say they worked 40-hour weeks, not the more typical 75 hours.</p>
        <p>But as the anti-sweatshop movement continues to grow -- and grow louder -- manufacturers have recently taken steps that just might improve working conditions around the world. Companies see that many consumers want to know that their clothing was not made under Dickensian conditions. So for the first time, industry giants have joined an ambitious effort, the Fair Labor Association, that has adopted a code and called for large-scale overseas monitoring that begins this fall.</p>
        <p>Nike, Reebok, Liz Claiborne, Philips Van Heusen and other manufacturers have joined the association, a White House-backed program that promises to inspect hundreds of factories yearly. Currently only a factory or two is monitored each month. The association's leaders say this latest effort, well financed and international, should make a difference. Monitors, ranging from accounting firms to union-friendly Jesuit advocates, will visit factories to check that there is no child labor, that managers do not sexually harass workers and that no one works more than 60 hours a week.</p>
        <p>The days of companies adopting a see-no-evil stance are over, said Sam Brown, executive director of the association, which includes several consumer and human rights groups. ''This effort says for the first time, 'You must know, you have to know about conditions in every single factory, and you have to bear responsibility,'  '' Mr. Brown said.</p>
        <p>The association's plans call for monitoring 30 percent of its members' 4,000 factories over the next three years, with 5 to 10 percent of each company's factories being monitored each subsequent year. Some critics say the percentage is too small to uncover every problem, but association members say monitoring, and requiring that complaints about conditions be investigated, will greatly help.</p>
        <p>Many critics say the association and other monitoring efforts will do little to improve the lives of third-world workers. They fear that corporations may hide the monitors' findings from the public, and that the accounting firms doing the monitoring will not dig hard enough to find problems.</p>
        <p>''I think the Fair Labor Association is just window-dressing,'' said Charles Kernaghan, director of the National Labor Committee, a labor rights group. ''You don't have full disclosure of what's found, and it doesn't require that factories pay a living wage. And it allows companies to produce in China, a country that prohibits independent trade unions.''</p>
        <p>Other monitoring efforts have sprouted because some groups think the association is too lenient toward manufacturers while others believe it is too harsh. Social Accountability International, an offshoot of the nonprofit Council on Economic Priorities, has persuaded Toys ''R'' Us, Avon Products and Eddie Bauer to push their manufacturers to comply with minimum labor standards developed by a group of companies, unions and nongovernment organizations. Students from 56 universities including Brown and Cornell recently formed the Workers Rights Consortium to work with nongovernment organizations overseas to review conditions at factories making T-shirts and other apparel carrying college logos. And the industry's main trade group, the American Apparel Manufacturers Association, has also adopted a code of conduct. Stung by criticisms, Nike, the Gap and others have hired their own monitors, and many critics say these companies have improved labor practices.</p>
        <p>''None of the programs have achieved critical mass yet,'' said Elliot Schrage, a Columbia University Business School professor who advises companies on how to improve factory conditions, ''but the principle that the conditions under which products are made is a legitimate concern for consumers is now well established.''</p>
        <p>The word sweatshop has long been used to describe factories with low wages and deplorable conditions, but whether a particular factory is a sweatshop is often in the eye of the beholder. An American or European may quickly conclude that a Chinese or Vietnamese factory paying workers $2 a day is a sweatshop. But the young women working there often say they earn far more than at other local factories or in the farm villages they left behind.</p>
        <p>''The question is to make sure these young people, mostly women a long way from home, are not abused,'' Mr. Brown said. ''Even if the situation is better than where they were, that doesn't mean there shouldn't be minimal standards of decency on how you treat people.''</p>
        <p>THE nation's largest apparel union, the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees, argues that free trade has encouraged American companies to move factories to countries with the lowest wages and worst conditions. Hoping to slow this exodus and help foreign workers, the union wants the World Trade Organization to allow trade sanctions against countries that perpetuate sweatshops by not enforcing their laws on minimum wage and overtime. But the W.T.O. has rejected such proposals.</p>
        <p>Monitoring, Mr. Brown said, is the best alternative for improving factory conditions. ''It is the way to think about how you make free trade into fair trade,'' he said. ''It's a way to ensure that the goods are produced under conditions that don't shock the conscience.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
