<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Lions and Bulls And Squares (Oh My!)</title>
    <meta content="09ESSA$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT: ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logotypes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFD81638F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Lions and Bulls And Squares (Oh My!)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patrick McGeehan essay on mutual fund logos, most of which leave him cold; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF your investing style could be a geometric figure, what kind would it be?</p>
        <p>Perhaps a polyhedron, like the pyramid with the shining upper chamber that serves as the logotype for Fidelity Investments? Or the concentric triangles that symbolize Alliance Capital Management? Or maybe the stylistic circle that representsthe Invesco funds?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF your investing style could be a geometric figure, what kind would it be?</p>
        <p>Perhaps a polyhedron, like the pyramid with the shining upper chamber that serves as the logotype for Fidelity Investments? Or the concentric triangles that symbolize Alliance Capital Management? Or maybe the stylistic circle that representsthe Invesco funds?</p>
        <p>If you are like me, all these fund family crests leave you cold. Granted, illustrating something so fuzzy as an investment philosophy is no easy feat but can't we do any better than a bunch of polygons, sailing vessels and oak trees?</p>
        <p>No wonder studies show that the most memorable icon of the mutual fund industry is the lion that belongs to the Dreyfus Corporation, a unit of Mellon Financial. As Merrill Lynch has proved, when it comes to building a strong public image, you can't beat a magnificent hairy beast. Investors are likely to keep identifying Dreyfus with its mascot long after they have forgotten the $2.95 million the company recently agreed to pay to settle accusations that it failed to adequately disclose the risks of its Aggressive Growth fund and that the fund's early performance was inflated by one its former managers, Michael L. Schonberg. (Neither Dreyfus nor Mr. Schonberg admitted wrongdoing.)</p>
        <p>It comes as no surprise that people have trouble remembering that Fidelity's logo resembles the pyramid on the back of a dollar bill -- without that eerie eye -- or that the Franklin fund family logo, a portrait of Benjamin Franklin, looks as if it might come from the front of an old $100 note. If you are going to use cash to represent the promise to shareholders, why not go with a big pile, maybe in a wheelbarrow? But on second thought, that image might be mistaken for the managers carting off commissions of 5 percent plus assorted annual fees.</p>
        <p>And, please, no more boats. What is it with money men and all things nautical? You can't walk through the headquarters of a major financial institution in the Northeast without feeling as if you have stumbled into the offices of the Dutch East India Company of the 17th century. The walls are lined with paintings and sketches of schooners and ketches. I've noticed that the money managers have learned to keep the pictures of their own yachts out of sight of the paying customers.</p>
        <p>The State Street and Pioneer fund families, which share the home port of Boston, each use a variation on a sailing ship as a logo. The Vanguard Group has taken the seafaring theme to such an extreme that you might never guess that the company is based as far inland as Valley Forge, Pa. The index-fund giant is so hooked on sailing that one ad in a glossy magazine reads, ''While many fund companies are learning the ropes of indexing, consider who built the rigging.'' (Rigging is a word you probably will not see in a Dreyfus ad anytime soon.)</p>
        <p>The new symbol for the Scudder funds is distinctive: a racing shell with four rowers pulling their oars in unison. It conveys sleekness, fitness and teamwork and certainly resonates better with baby boomers than Scudder's previous icon -- an old, bearded sea captain, bedecked in foul-weather gear. He always gave me a sudden craving for frozen fish sticks.</p>
        <p>The old salt sailed off into the sunset last year after Scudder merged with the Kemper fund family, yet Kemper has kept its more mysterious symbol, a sheaf of wheat. You can't get much more old-economy than a farming metaphor.</p>
        <p>A bull may be a perfect symbol for a Wall Street firm, but none of Merrill's competitors has tried to rustle it lately. For the most part their mascots are avuncular bankers promising to earn your trust. But some of Merrill's rivals, who of course manage their own funds, have landed some memorable slogans, like ''We make money the old-fashioned way, we earn it'' and ''We measure success one investor at a time.''</p>
        <p>The closest analog from a fund company comes from Massachusetts Financial Services, which flatly declares: ''We invented the mutual fund.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to distinguish among Fidelity's ''Invest responsibly'' theme, the Aim fund family's ''Invest with discipline'' and T. Rowe Price's ''Invest with confidence.'' But they are durable. Is there any slogan that says ''out of step with the times'' more clearly than Kemper's ''long-term investing in a short-term world''?</p>
        <p>Then there's the mythology thing. Janus, the Denver company that has become synonymous with making concentrated bets on fast-growing technology companies, has clearly studied Nike's playbook, not Vanguard's. The evidence: Nike was named for a Greek goddess, Janus for a Roman god. Nike's rallying cry was ''Just do it''; Janus says ''Get there.''</p>
        <p>Janus's logo is one of the more recognizable in the industry. There may already be thousands of investors who know that two-faced god symbolizes doorways and beginnings, but there probably are more who think he was the god of beating the market. Of course, more than a few old-school investors would argue that Bacchus would be a more appropriate icon for a company that so thoroughly reveled at the technology-stock feast of the last several years.</p>
        <p>Aside from Dreyfus and Merrill, surprisingly few fund companies have turned to the tried-and-true use of animals as symbols. One is T. Rowe Price, whose mascot is a ram that represents surefootedness.</p>
        <p>But another is a newcomer, and its choice of a logo may be spot-on. Thomas Marsico already was something of a maverick before he bolted from Janus's stable of managers a few years ago to start his own firm focused on investing in fast-growing companies. The symbol he chose looks a lot like a wild horse; that is appropriate, because his funds have taken shareholders on a exhilarating ride. The flagship Marsico Focus fund returned more than 50 percent in 1998 and again in 1999, though it was down about 9 percent this year through June 30.</p>
        <p>For established fund firms that want to project a more sober image, inventive marketing has proved a major challenge. Consider what Fidelity, arguably the most successful fund company since somebody came up with the idea of putting stocks in baskets, has done to promote itself in recent years. To hammer home its ''Invest responsibly'' mantra, it hired Don Rickles and Lily Tomlin, two people who made their fortunes by sticking their tongues out at strangers.</p>
        <p>The truth for the people who run Fidelity is that they have the single most valuable promotional resource in the industry on the board of directors. His name is Peter Lynch and, although he has not managed a Fidelity fund in many years, he is generally accepted as one of the greatest living investors.</p>
        <p>At 56, he will probably be around for a long time, but Fidelity executives should be planning how they will continue using Mr. Lynch's Midas-like reputation after he is gone.  They might consider replacing the current logo, which conjures up images of some sort of cult or a secret society, with a sketch of Mr. Lynch's brain and a simple, direct slogan, like ''We didn't invent the mutual fund but we have dibs on Peter Lynch's gene pool.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT: ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
