<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Sides Share Subdued View of Mideast Summit Talks</title>
    <meta content="09MIDE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDD1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Sides Share Subdued View of Mideast Summit Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>TEL AVIV, July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Even though residents of Israel, West Bank and Gaza are prisoners of dreary pursuit for peace, only Jewish settlers are treating Camp David summit as pivotal event; only in sttlements has daily life been altered to plan for what many see as most significant battle of political lives; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Today, as on every Friday, a group of Israeli men who were classmates at Balfour Elementary School in the early days of the state gathered at Cafe Lenzner on bustling Sheinkin Street for an informal salon.</p>
        <p>They drank iced tea, smoked cigarettes, watched girls and engaged in their familiar routine of banter and political debate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Today, as on every Friday, a group of Israeli men who were classmates at Balfour Elementary School in the early days of the state gathered at Cafe Lenzner on bustling Sheinkin Street for an informal salon.</p>
        <p>They drank iced tea, smoked cigarettes, watched girls and engaged in their familiar routine of banter and political debate.</p>
        <p>These men and the friends who joined them have lived Israel's history and prehistory, fought its various wars, established its businesses, served in its government, emigrated and re-immigrated. There is a lawyer, an architect, an economist, a factory owner who survived the Holocaust on Schindler's list.</p>
        <p>Outsiders might assume that today's debate would be intense, that these men would be obsessed by the Camp David summit meeting that begins on Tuesday with the momentous aim of trying to resolve the Israeli-Palestinian conflict that has overshadowed their country's existence. But outsiders would be wrong.</p>
        <p>''We have had so many moments of truth,'' said Danny Simon, 54, a businessman who considers himself a leftist. ''We are not naive. We would never attach too much importance in advance to any one event. Do we feel on the edge of something historic? We are not holding our breath. We can only hope that the process keeps inching forward.''</p>
        <p>The Israeli-Palestinian conflict is the backdrop to life here, even on Sheinkin Street, the epicenter of Israeli secularism. Young adults with spiked hair, nose rings and bare midriffs affect a willful distance from the battles and animosities that defined their parents' lives, and they do not live elbow-to-elbow with the conflict like Jerusalemites or settlers.</p>
        <p>But everyone in Israel, the West Bank and Gaza is a prisoner of what President Clinton, announcing the summit meeting, called the ''abject dreariness of the pursuit.'' Everyone knows that deadlines are always broken and that two steps forward are always followed by one step back.</p>
        <p>In a day of interviews throughout Israel and the West Bank, only the Jewish settlers were treating the  summit meeting as a potentially pivotal event. Only in the settlements -- where children stopped cars to plaster them with stickers that said, ''Peace, yes! Suckers, no!'' -- has daily life been altered to plan for what many see as the most significant political battle of their lives.</p>
        <p>''Why should we give the Arabs anything?'' said one settler, Yishai Cacotai, 14. ''We give them land, they give us buses that go boom boom.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, people refused to be distracted by what they saw as the latest stop on the local train to a lessened conflict, if not peace. In Ramallah in the West Bank, behind the opaque glass of a rare women-only cafe called Privacy, two young Palestinian sisters sat smoking a fruit-flavored water pipe -- an unusual activity for women here. They waved away talk of Camp David.</p>
        <p>''I follow it closely,'' said Samar Alkour, the cafe owner, who is 35. ''But I don't go into discussions. Let me tell you about this peace process: the big men are cooking, and the little people are eating. We will take what we are served because we will have no other choice.''</p>
        <p>At the nearby Cafe Brazil, a men-only cafe with thick sawdust on the floor, one group of men playing cards seemed like the Palestinian equivalent of the Israeli salon in Tel Aviv, a circle of longtime companions who finished one another's sentences.</p>
        <p>Muhammad Faidi, a hotel owner, laid down an ace of spades, snorted and said, ''Arafat will go and return without achievements.'' He was referring to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. ''It's all nonsense,'' he muttered, and no one disagreed.</p>
        <p>Down the street, at the Sanabel Bakery, Khaled Rabieh, 27, stacked sugary elephant ears pastries. He said that he considered the peace effort to be ''a show'' and that Camp David would be one of the ''last scenes before the curtain comes down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabieh's family originally came from a town next to Jaffa, where, as far as they are concerned, they still own 250 acres of agricultural land, which he said he routinely visits, parks beside and stares at with frustrated longing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabieh, like most refugees, believes that if a peace agreement is  achieved it will be at the refugees' expense. He said that if the Israelis obtain what they want -- separation from the Palestinians -- he will not even be able to visit his land. He said he looked ahead to Sept. 13, the deadline by which Mr. Arafat has pledged to declare a Palestinian state, as a day more bitter than sweet.</p>
        <p>''It will be a day when we laugh at ourselves,'' he said. ''It will be a day when we get a state without power, without sovereignty. ''</p>
        <p>A world away, in the nearby settlement of Bet Horon, Avi Weissman, who immigrated 30 years ago from Pelham Parkway in the Bronx, spoke with equally deep-seated suspicion of the Palestinians' ultimate intentions. ''The whole process of what's called peace,'' he said, ''it amounts to giving the Arabs a part of our homeland that they can use as a military base for taking the rest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weissman wearily unloaded groceries from his car and trudged up to his hilltop home of 23 years.</p>
        <p>''I'm very, very worried and very, very upset,'' Mr. Weissman said. ''With the mood of this government, and the mood of the Israeli people, you can't feel safe. In my wildest dreams, I can't think that the Arabs will ever be willing to live in peace with us. And yet we go to Camp David? Why? Because we have lost our motivation, we have gotten soft. They are willing to spill their blood, to be martyrs, but we don't want to lose a single soldier.''</p>
        <p>At Cafe Lenzner, it was hard to separate the serious conversation from the fast-flying repartee.</p>
        <p>''You want to know the history of this country?'' said Lutek Harel, the Holocaust survivor, who owns an airplane-parts manufacturing business. ''We had nothing. What we have now, we took it all. If we want to talk about peace, we have to talk about the people who were here when we arrived. We have no choice but to live as two people on one land.''</p>
        <p>Moti Lenzner, the resident right-winger who is also Mr. Harel's lawyer, hooted. ''I will give back your factory in Jaffa, then! It belongs to these Arabs you so love.''</p>
        <p>''Give it back!'' Mr. Harel said. ''I could use a rest. Maybe I'll go to Camp David. That sounds like a nice break.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simon, the businessman, said  the left was afraid that the situation would disintegrate before it improved. ''Even if something comes out of Camp David,'' he said, ''things will slip backward. They always do. It will take a lot of aggravation, a lot of deaths, a lot of riots, a lot of smoke to get to the end.''</p>
        <p>Working hard to get a word in, Yoram Fogel, an architect, was interrupted by the table's running commentary on the girls walking by. ''People forget how much progress we have made,'' he said. ''Slowly, slowly, we accept peace. It's a revolution in the life of Israel. It doesn't matter if Camp David succeeds or fails. It's a process.''</p>
        <p>Dan Shilo, 55, an economist, suggested that a partial agreement could be reached, one that left aside the thornier issues of Jerusalem and the refugees. But Mr. Simon did not think that would be a good idea. ''Then it will just take more pain, more casualties and in the end we will be in the same place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lenzner shot back: ''What's the matter with pain and suffering? Did you forget you are Jewish?''</p>
        <p>And in the routine dynamic of the salon, Mr. Lenzner was left with the last word. It is his cafe after all, and he was buying the drinks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
