<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>KEY MISSILE PARTS ARE LEFT UNTESTED AS BOOSTER FAILS</title>
    <meta content="09MISS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DE1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>KEY MISSILE PARTS ARE LEFT UNTESTED AS BOOSTER FAILS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Crucial test in Pentagon's complex, $60 billion antimissile defensive system fails after high-speed interceptor 'kill vehicle' designed to destroy dummy warhead fails to separate from booster rocket; failure will make it politically and diplomatically more difficult for Pres Clinton to move ahead with plan administration contends is crucial to defend against attack, but which opponents say is technically unsound, militarily unnecessary and waste of money; reinforces calls in Congress to leave decision to next president; failure was in well-developed technology, used successfully in rockets that have launched satellites and missiles for decades; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A crucial test in the Pentagon's program to defend the United States from missile attacks collapsed in failure because the high-speed interceptor that was supposed to destroy a dummy warhead in space never separated from its booster rocket, the Pentagon said today.</p>
        <p>The failure was a setback in the Pentagon's quest to demonstrate the workability of a complex $60 billion defensive system in time for President Clinton to decide whether to proceed with its initial deployment  before he leaves office. The unexpected malfunctioning of the booster meant that the experiment produced few meaningful lessons about the weapon's capabilities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A crucial test in the Pentagon's program to defend the United States from missile attacks collapsed in failure because the high-speed interceptor that was supposed to destroy a dummy warhead in space never separated from its booster rocket, the Pentagon said today.</p>
        <p>The failure was a setback in the Pentagon's quest to demonstrate the workability of a complex $60 billion defensive system in time for President Clinton to decide whether to proceed with its initial deployment  before he leaves office. The unexpected malfunctioning of the booster meant that the experiment produced few meaningful lessons about the weapon's capabilities.</p>
        <p>Today's dramatic miss will make it politically and diplomatically more difficult for Mr. Clinton to move ahead with a plan that the administration contends is crucial to defend against attack from countries like North Korea but that opponents say is technically unsound, militarily unnecessary and a waste of money. And it reinforces calls in Congress to leave the decision to the next president.</p>
        <p>Officials said the component that failed appeared not to be one of the sophisticated elements that the Pentagon was hoping to demonstrate: the targeting radar, homing sensors and communications links. Instead, it was a failure in a well-developed technology that has been used successfully in rockets that have launched satellites and missiles for decades.</p>
        <p>The failure underscored the frailty of any such complex weapon system, even in the carefully controlled world of test shots. And in a separate failure, the target of the interceptor also malfunctioned when a Mylar polyester balloon that accompanied the simulated warhead as a decoy never inflated.</p>
        <p>Lt. Gen. Ronald T. Kadish, director of the Pentagon's Ballistic Missile Defense Organization, appeared humbled by the chain of events.</p>
        <p>''What it tells me is we have more engineering work to do,'' he said at an early morning news conference.</p>
        <p>''And as we've said all along, this is a very difficult, challenging job,'' he added. ''This is rocket science, so there's a lot of things that can happen in this process.''</p>
        <p>The ability of a 54-inch, 130-pound ''kill vehicle'' to shed the rocket that propelled it had been viewed as a given. When the separation failed to occur, the important part of the $100 million test -- homing in for the collision in space -- was never even attempted, apparently because the interceptor's on-board sensors were designed to turn on only after the separation.</p>
        <p>Asked where the successful separation of the kill vehicle from its booster had ranked on his list of concerns, General Kadish gave a direct answer. ''It wasn't even on my list,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Without its sensors working, the kill vehicle streaked blindly into space, and few of the critical technologies of the missile exercise were actually tested.</p>
        <p>Although General Kadish expressed confidence that the research program could continue, the failure complicates the political decision about proceeding with deployment.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we should draw conclusions from any one test that are irrevocable,'' he said. ''No one test tells you everything you need to know. We have a body of tests even before this one that tells us an awful lot. And we have increasing confidence as a result of that.''</p>
        <p>Even though today's test was only the third in a series of 19 intercept tests planned by the Pentagon, it was supposed to have been the defining one that would have let Defense Secretary William S. Cohen recommend that Mr. Clinton proceed with a limited missile defense.</p>
        <p>But both General Kadish and Dr. Jacques Gansler, an under secretary of defense, acknowledged that the president and Mr. Cohen might decide to seek more data before they can judge whether to move forward with a defensive shield.</p>
        <p>''We need more flight tests,'' Dr. Gansler said.</p>
        <p>''We need more flight tests,'' General Kadish echoed.</p>
        <p>The next test will take place in October or November, Dr. Gansler said. But he noted that if construction is to begin on a radar system on Shemya Island in the Aleutians in the spring, a decision should be made before then.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon calculates that construction must begin next spring if a limited missile defense is to be completed by 2005, when intelligence estimates have said North Korea could field a long-range missile.</p>
        <p>Today's failure could enable Mr. Clinton to delay making a decision at least until after the presidential election. The president has said he will decide in several weeks whether to go along with the Pentagon timetable.</p>
        <p>P. J. Crowley, a spokesman for the National Security Council, said, ''The failure of the intercept will have to be fully evaluated by the Pentagon first, but it obviously will be an important factor that the president will take into account when analyzing the technical feasibility of national missile defense.''</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic contender for the presidency, today declined to say how he thought the administration should respond to the failed test. ''I'll wait until we receive a report from the military and from Secretary Cohen,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>His Republican competitor, Gov. George W. Bush, who has called for a more ambitious plan that could be deployed in space, said he would press forward with a vigorous missile defense plan.</p>
        <p>''While last night's test is a disappointment, I remain confident that given the right leadership, America can develop an effective missile defense system,'' Mr. Bush said in a prepared statement.</p>
        <p>Both Russia and China adamantly oppose the missile defense because they consider it a threat to their nuclear deterrents. Even the United States' European allies are distressed that the country would take such a serious unilateral move.</p>
        <p>Building a missile defense would require a change in the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty, which Russia has refused to accept.</p>
        <p>In October, the Pentagon hailed its first test as a complete success, but later acknowledged that the kill vehicle initially had drifted off course and picked out the large bright decoy balloon instead of the simulated warhead. In a second, more complicated test in January, the kill vehicle missed the target warhead by 300 to 400 feet.</p>
        <p>This morning's test was delayed two hours by technical problems. Later, the gleaming white reconfigured Minuteman carrying the dummy warhead thundered aloft over the Pacific Ocean from Vandenberg Air Force Base, 125 miles north of Los Angeles, at 12:19 a.m. Eastern Time.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one minutes later, the rocket containing the kill vehicle lifted off from Kwajalein Atoll, about 4,300 miles away in the Marshall Islands. The kill vehicle was supposed to separate from the second-stage rocket booster 2 minutes and 37 seconds into flight, then move into the path of the mock warhead for a spectacular, blinding collision at 16,000 miles an hour over the Pacific.</p>
        <p>But television monitors showed no bright white flash indicating a collision. About 30 minutes later, officials  told reporters that the kill vehicle had sailed by its target.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
