<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Wrong Passions</title>
    <meta content="09BERMANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berman, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shapiro, James</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oberammergau (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DC1F30F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Wrong Passions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Berman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berman, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Berman reviews book Oberammergau: The Troubling Story of the World's Most Famous Passion Play by James Shapiro; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oberammergau</p>
        <p>The Troubling Story of</p>
        <p>the World's Most Famous</p>
        <p>Passion Play.</p>
        <p>By James Shapiro.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 238 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oberammergau</p>
        <p>The Troubling Story of</p>
        <p>the World's Most Famous</p>
        <p>Passion Play.</p>
        <p>By James Shapiro.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 238 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $24.</p>
        <p>What can account for the long, strange tradition of hating the Jews? James Shapiro is a wonderfully knowledgeable professor of literature at Columbia, and in an earlier book called ''Shakespeare and the Jews'' he cited an explanation from 1656. It was a psychological theory, proposed by a Dutch rabbi named Menasseh ben Israel. People who hate the Jews notice something about themselves, and then project it onto the Jews. That was the rabbi's idea. He cited the very weird accusation of ritual child murder.</p>
        <p>In ancient times ritual child murder was imputed to the Christians by their pagan enemies. But in the Middle Ages Christians took to imputing that same crime to the Jews. The Christians convinced themselves that Jews needed the blood of Christian babies in order to bake a properly sinister matzoh, or Passover bread. And with that belief in mind, Christian mobs used to assemble during Holy Week and, enraged by their own fantasies, go rampaging through the ghettos, murdering Jews. And so (to push the rabbi's insight one more step), it was the Christians who ended up performing what could be described as ritual murders -- killings conducted in the name of religion, on dates selected from the sacred calendar.</p>
        <p>Psychological inversions about Jews go back a long way in the history of Christianity. The historical Jesus was a Jew who was killed by the gentiles -- that is, by the Romans. But in the Christian interpretation the historical Jesus was nicely transformed into a Christian who was killed by the Jews. And those same inversions have managed to reappear in modern times in all kinds of versions. It is the commonest thing in the world even today to hear the Jews being accused of greed and money-grubbing. Yet as the Swiss banking scandal and a dozen revelations from the art museums and countries around the globe keep on demonstrating, it is the Jews who have been systematically robbed, on a giant scale, and by the finest of banks and governments, too.</p>
        <p>I could go on. The theme has the misfortune of being inexhaustible. Menasseh ben Israel turns out to have discovered a persistent truth of Western civilization. But how did those many strange psychological inversions from long ago manage to survive the end of the Middle Ages and wend their way into the modern age? That is James Shapiro's great topic. In his book on Shakespeare he showed how a series of legends from the Middle Ages and the early modern era succeeded in creeping into ''The Merchant of Venice'' and other works of art in England, which then turned out to be masterpieces of world civilization, therefore immortal. And in his new book, ''Oberammergau: The Troubling Story of the World's Most Famous Passion Play,'' he shows a very similar phenomenon, the preservation of ancient fantasies by means of art, this time in a German setting.</p>
        <p>Oberammergau is a quaint Catholic village in Bavaria that began putting on a passion play in 1634, or possibly earlier, and has performed the play every 10 years from that time on. Half the village takes part in the production, in one way or another, and the mass participation long ago created an impression that Oberammergau must be a sort of Christian Shangri-La, as Shapiro puts it -- a timeless place where the villagers ''were believed to be somehow in touch with a primitive Christian spirituality.'' By the 1930's, hundreds of thousands of people were making the trek into the Bavarian hills to see the amazing spectacle. Yet what was Oberammergau's play, in its traditional form? It was an extended expression of loathing for the Jewish people. It was an extravaganza of spiritualized hatred, in which the performers and audiences could feel themselves borne away on clouds of innocence and love.</p>
        <p>Shapiro captures the experience by quoting an unusually astute Scottish visitor from 1860, who described the play in these words: ''The Jewish race appeared hateful in your eyes, as you watched them gathering round the cross, looking upon the man they had crucified, and railing at him, and taunting him with his powerlessness and his pain. Then for the first time you seemed to understand the significance of those ungovernable explosions that in the history of the Middle Ages one reads of, when sudden outbursts of hatred against the Hebrew race have taken place, and have been followed by cruelties and barbarities unrivaled in history.''</p>
        <p>In later years, after the cruelties and barbarities of the Middle Ages had been rivaled and even outrivaled, a delicate but crucially important question arose on the topic of Christianity and its relation to modern barbarism. Did the Nazi crimes draw on Christian tradition? Or did Nazism draw instead, as the Roman Catholic Church has argued, on pagan ideas that were distinctly anti-Christian? Whatever the larger answer might be, Shapiro's investigation shows that in the little village of Oberammergau it was not so easy to tell Nazi paganism from Christian tradition.</p>
        <p>The village may have been famously pious, but some important Nazis set up headquarters there, even so -- for instance, the man who designed and built the crematoriums at Auschwitz. Hitler himself was famously fond of the play, which he saw twice. And the villagers returned his affection, even if, in later years, they have steadily pleaded innocent on questions of Nazi guilt. In the 1950 and 1960 productions of the play, the village assigned the role of Jesus to someone who had been convicted, after the war, of having been a Nazi. In the 1970 production the ex-Nazi went on to become the artistic director.</p>
        <p>Still, eventually the village did begin to notice that not everyone was in love with its play. The American Jewish organizations began making a fuss over the play in 1966, and they pushed some of the Jewish intellectuals into mounting a protest, and the point was made. The American Jewish organizations kept at it, too, and are at it even now. But the real pressure on the village, as Shapiro explains, came from the highest ranks of the Catholic Church. It was because in 1965, during the Second Vatican Council, the church officially abandoned its ancient doctrines about the collective guilt of the Jewish people and the eternal divine curse upon Jewish blood. In one fateful stroke, because of the new theological interpretations, the play fell outside of correct doctrine. And the good Catholics of Oberammergau suddenly had to rethink.</p>
        <p>The villagers have been caught up in one fight after another ever since then, in their effort to fend off the American Jews and the Catholic hierarchs. Reforming the play is not so easily done, though. Some of the most hair-raising anti-Semitic lines can be removed from the script, and the play's Jews can be relieved of their customary horns, and Jesus can be portrayed as a Hebrew-speaking Jew, which is how he appears in this year's radical new production. But the demonic nature of the Jews lies at the heart of the drama. The triumph of virtuous Christianity over satanic Judaism supplies the cathartic emotion at the end. Not much can be done about that.</p>
        <p>Shapiro's book is mostly a journalistic account of the recent efforts to reform the play, and of how frustrating those efforts have been. Shapiro himself can't seem to make up his mind about the results. He feels a respect and even an affection for the new artistic director and the script director, both of them Oberammergau natives, who have worked quite a few changes into the play. In the course of observing their efforts, Shapiro even allowed himself to be drafted into becoming the Hebrew coach to the two actors who, in rotating roles, play Jesus in the new production. But, for all his sympathy with the modern reformers, Shapiro sometimes throws up his hands in despair at Oberammergau and its play. He never does describe or summarize the play at any length, which is an odd failing in a book like his and makes it difficult for his readers to arrive at any judgment of their own.</p>
        <p>The value of Shapiro's book, though, lies in seeing the issues arranged in neat patterns across the page, and analyzed and discussed, even without a final judgment. Shapiro takes the position that plays like the one at Oberammergau and like ''The Merchant of Venice'' should never be censored. They should be produced, if only to shine a light on some dark themes. This idea conforms perfectly, I would say, with Menasseh ben Israel's psychological theory from 1656. There is no point in trying to pretend that ancient anti-Semitic fantasies have entirely disappeared from modern life. The only thing to do is to try to be lucid about those fantasies, to bring them into the open air and let people see them for what they are.</p>
        <p>Quite a few writers have been trying to do exactly that lately -- to be lucid and informative about some of the less obvious aspects of Richard Wagner's operas, T. S. Eliot's poems, Christian theology, Louis Farrakhan's idiosyncratic Muslim theology, Marxist political theory and several other lively zones of modern culture. But Shapiro's contribution seems to me especially valuable. He knows how to keep his cool, which is a useful talent for anyone who wants to talk about these several issues of religion and bigotry. But most of all, he is able to bring into his discussion a solid familiarity with the folklore of the medieval and postmedieval age -- a bygone era that, as he carefully demonstrates, is not exactly bygone.</p>
        <p>Paul Berman is the editor of ''Blacks and Jews'' and the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Berman is the editor of ''Blacks and Jews'' and the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
