<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unusual Choice for the Role of Studio Superhero</title>
    <meta content="09WEIN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">X-Men (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D91039F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unusual Choice for the Role of Studio Superhero</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with 34-year-old director Bryan Singer, whose latest project is science fiction drama X-Men, expected to be summer extravaganza; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN his jeans and V-neck sweater, Bryan Singer walked into the commissary at 20th Century Fox at lunchtime this spring resembling a youthful and eager production assistant. And he was treated that way. He was escorted to a small table right beside the kitchen's swinging doors. He removed his sunglasses and rubbed his eyes. Around him, studio executives in more comfortable accommodations seemed oblivious to the filmmaker -- ironic since the studio's fortunes this summer have, to a degree, been placed firmly in the hands of a director whose career has centered so far on low-budget and independent-style films like ''The Usual Suspects'' and the less successful ''Apt Pupil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer's film, ''X-Men,'' which is based on characters from the best-selling comic book series created by Stan Lee, is neither low-budget nor indie style. Far from it. The science fiction drama, opening Friday, is one of the bigger extravaganzas of the summer, a film that the studio is banking on after recent big-budget disappointments like ''Fight Club,''  ''Anna and the King'' and ''The Beach.'' If successful, ''X-Men'' could also turn into a franchise for Fox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN his jeans and V-neck sweater, Bryan Singer walked into the commissary at 20th Century Fox at lunchtime this spring resembling a youthful and eager production assistant. And he was treated that way. He was escorted to a small table right beside the kitchen's swinging doors. He removed his sunglasses and rubbed his eyes. Around him, studio executives in more comfortable accommodations seemed oblivious to the filmmaker -- ironic since the studio's fortunes this summer have, to a degree, been placed firmly in the hands of a director whose career has centered so far on low-budget and independent-style films like ''The Usual Suspects'' and the less successful ''Apt Pupil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer's film, ''X-Men,'' which is based on characters from the best-selling comic book series created by Stan Lee, is neither low-budget nor indie style. Far from it. The science fiction drama, opening Friday, is one of the bigger extravaganzas of the summer, a film that the studio is banking on after recent big-budget disappointments like ''Fight Club,''  ''Anna and the King'' and ''The Beach.'' If successful, ''X-Men'' could also turn into a franchise for Fox.</p>
        <p>At the time, though, Mr. Singer, who seemed alternately confident and insecure, was not dwelling on how dependent those nearby studio executives were on his talents to shape a successful franchise. He didn't have the time. He was spending almost seven days a week editing the futuristic film which, after his initial reservations, now consumed and fascinated him. (And not only because of its 470 visual-effect shots, but also because of its subject matter.) ''It's actually about prejudice,'' said the 34-year-old filmmaker.</p>
        <p>The movie is based on Marvel Comics' extraordinarily popular saga about outcast -- or mutant -- superheroes who protect a world that loathes them for being different. The characters themselves are outsiders and misfits with supernatural powers: the allegory about bigotry is not too subtle.</p>
        <p>Adapted by Mr. Singer's boyhood friend from New Jersey, Christopher McQuarrie, who also wrote ''The Usual Suspects,'' and Ed Solomon (''Men in Black''), the movie's cast includes Sir Ian McKellen, Patrick Stewart, Halle Berry, Famke Janssen, Bruce Davison and Anna Paquin.</p>
        <p>Bill Mechanic, chairman and chief executive of Fox Filmed Entertainment (who resigned last month), said that partly because the movie's stars are not high priced (neither is its director, for that matter) and partly because it was made on a tight budget, mostly in Toronto, its cost had been whittled down to $75 million, which is relatively inexpensive for such a project. (Its marketing costs, though, could add at least $30 million to the budget.)</p>
        <p>Why did Fox select Mr. Singer? Mr. Mechanic said: ''We didn't want to make a silly comic book film. Stars and cars and big bangs. We didn't want an action director. These are anti-hero heroes, they're outsiders. We wanted someone young and fresh and someone who would take the material seriously. This movie was going to be about the characters in it, not the effects. We wanted someone on the edge and someone who's a bit on the outside. The characters in Bryan's movies are very much like that. We wanted it to reflect an outsider's sensibility. And if you look at all those things, Bryan's like a fastball down the middle. He's exactly what we were looking for.''</p>
        <p>The potential negatives of working with an untested director in the big-budget league were obvious. Fox surrounded Mr. Singer with an accomplished and experienced creative team on the set. But Mr. Mechanic said candidly that working with a newer director is often easier than dealing with a veteran: ''A lot of guys who do big-budget movies just want to know, 'How do I make it bigger, bigger, bigger?' Which is what we didn't want at all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer said he was unfamiliar with the comic book, and was reluctant at first to get involved in the project. But one of his producing partners, Tom DeSanto, was an ''X-Men'' fan since childhood and urged him to meet Mr. Lee, who created ''X-Men'' in 1963 (and was a big fan of ''The Usual Suspects''). Mr. Singer also met with executives at Marvel Comics and Fox.</p>
        <p>I  started to explore structural ideas, story ideas,'' Mr. Singer said. ''I started to realize that there was something quite serious about this. It's basically about reluctant superheroes sworn to defend the world that hates and fears them.''</p>
        <p>At an early stage, as Mr. Singer seriously considered the project, he was invited to an acting showcase by a friend in Los Angeles. It was the same day that Mr. Singer had met executives at Marvel Comics. As he sat in the first row of the small theater, Mr. Singer said he suddenly realized how he could open the film with a series of sequences that would introduce the cast of characters, born different from everyone else, who discover their supernatural powers at puberty.</p>
        <p>''I needed to see the opening sequences that would establish that universe,'' he said. ''I needed to set the stage in my own mind so I could move forward. It was such a tremendous undertaking. I needed to visualize the opening. I had a kind of epiphany that night.''</p>
        <p>The next morning Mr. Singer told Fox he wanted to proceed with the project.</p>
        <p>Sir Ian, who had previously worked for Mr. Singer as a Nazi in ''Apt Pupil,'' plays Magneto, one of the key roles in ''X-Men.'' Magneto is a powerful mutant who had rejected society, believing that the outsiders and humans can never coexist and that mutants are the heirs to the world's future.</p>
        <p>The actor said that Mr. Singer's enthusiasm and even unpredictability as a director made him popular among actors. ''I don't always know with Bryan what he's been getting at, where he's precisely going, until I've seen the dailies or the complete film,'' Sir Ian said. ''He always has a vision of what he wants, but it's rather a private thing. More than any director I know of, you're on a roller coaster with Bryan. You're racing along but you don't quite know where you're going. With other directors you're following a map. Not with Bryan. He works in the moment. He eschews planning and rehearsals. This might be very alarming for some actors. Not for me.''</p>
        <p>Sir Ian, by now a friend of Mr. Singer's, said with a laugh that he's constantly amused by and impressed with Mr. Singer, who, at times, has the air of a naif. ''Actors alarm him,'' Sir Ian said. ''He's baffled by acting. I told him he ought to direct a play, and he said, 'But I don't know anything about acting.' And I said, 'Yes, exactly.'</p>
        <p>''He always speaks with huge enthusiasm about the actors he's worked with and the performances he's seen. He's recently discovered the talents of Bette Davis. He said to me the other day -- and this is where his youth can be alarming -- he said, 'Have you ever seen a movie called ''All About Eve''?' I said, 'Yes, I have heard of it.' ''</p>
        <p>Actually, Mr. Singer became a director because of Steven Spielberg. As a child, Mr. Singer grew up in Princeton Junction, N.J. His father, Norbert Singer, is a businessman and his mother, Grace, is an environmental activist and former state environmental official. By age 11, young Bryan was working with 35-millimeter cameras and had his own dark room, and by his early teens was making 8-millimeter films.</p>
        <p>At the age of 16, while at a friend's house, Mr. Singer saw a television profile of Mr. Spielberg. ''He was this Jewish kid like me, he lived in New Jersey for awhile, he had a drawer full of 8-millimeter movies too when he was young,'' he said. ''And I thought, I make all these films for fun and I take all these photographs and why don't I do this for a living, just like Steven Spielberg?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer laughed. ''I remember walking home to my house in the middle of the night feeling like, wow, if nothing else I've decided what I want to do with my life,'' he said. ''Even if I weren't successful I knew I would always make films.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer attended the School of Visual Arts in Manhattan for two years, and then transferred to the University of Southern California. During that time he made a movie, ''Lion's Den,'' with a New Jersey friend, Ethan Hawke. The film, which was shown in a workshop at the Director's Guild in Los Angeles, proved fortunate for Mr. Singer.</p>
        <p>A representative of a Japanese media company, Tokuma, was at the screening. The company had decided to select six young directors around the world and bankroll them with $250,000 each to make a film. Mr. Singer, together with Mr. McQuarrie and Michael Felt Dugan, wrote an offbeat story about a stranger who starts his own cable television call-in show designed to unmask secrets in a town. Mr. Singer got the money, made the film, titled ''Public Access,'' and it shared the Grand Jury Prize at the Sundance Film Festival in 1992 with ''Ruby in Paradise.''</p>
        <p>His next film, ''The Usual Suspects'' (1995), about five men who meet in a criminal line-up, was so stylish and highly praised that Mr. Singer was promptly placed in the pantheon of hip, young and sought-after Hollywood directors. The film won two Academy Awards, including a best-supporting-actor Oscar for Kevin Spacey.</p>
        <p>MR. SINGER was then heavily in demand. He passed up opportunities to earn millions of dollars directing some high-profile films with big stars, including ''The Devil's Own,'' with Brad Pitt and Harrison Ford. He wanted to direct ''The Truman Show,'' but the movie went to Peter Weir. Mr. Singer chose to direct a dark and wicked drama, ''Apt Pupil,'' based on a Stephen King novella, about an average schoolboy (Brad Renfro) who discovers that a notorious Nazi (Sir Ian) is hiding in his town and slowly turns into a monster himself. The film earned mixed reviews and failed at the box office.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to try to use the influence I had to make this difficult and cold movie,'' Mr. Singer said. ''I don't regret it at all. How can I? It has a base of fans. I have disappointment. Plenty of disappointment. You want things to be successful.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer lives alone in a large unfurnished house in Los Angeles, and seems ambivalent about it. ''I have always lived in a rent-a-room in someone's house for $850 a month, I've always lived like a college student,'' he said. ''But then I buy a house as an investment. It's a beautiful, awesome house and I refinished it, I did all these cool things except furnishing it. I keep putting it off. It's been completely empty for two years except for a bed, my television with a VCR and DVD and a fish tank. When I have friends over we have pizza on the floor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Singer is unsure of his next project. The outcome of ''The X-Men'' will most certainly affect his career. He's been working on the movie for nearly four years. ''You have to anticipate failure with every film you do,'' he said. ''But whatever happens, I know I care deeply about each movie I do, I know I bring a certain visual style and control over the medium, and I know I'm careful with the dollars. I feel confident weathering the successes, and I feel confident weathering the failures. I do my very best. Give it my all. That's all I can possibly do.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
