<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey. Harry Potter. Perfect Together?</title>
    <meta content="09COLU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Craver, Desiree</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galant, Debra</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DB1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey. Harry Potter. Perfect Together?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA GALANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Galant, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debra Galant Jersey column on stir created by upcoming pubication of fourth in series of Harry Potter books, Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire; 15-year-old Desiree Craver of Elmer, NJ, managed to buy and read book five full days before sale date; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I found out that Barnes &amp; Noble's national warehouse is in Jamesburg -- or as it is more popularly known, Exit 8A -- and that every single new Harry Potter book the superchain was delivering would actually go through there, I called up the South Brunswick police to see if they had been put on alert. The station officer, Bob Chibbaro, didn't know a thing about it, or even who Harry Potter was.</p>
        <p>That was refreshing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I found out that Barnes &amp; Noble's national warehouse is in Jamesburg -- or as it is more popularly known, Exit 8A -- and that every single new Harry Potter book the superchain was delivering would actually go through there, I called up the South Brunswick police to see if they had been put on alert. The station officer, Bob Chibbaro, didn't know a thing about it, or even who Harry Potter was.</p>
        <p>That was refreshing.</p>
        <p>By now, of course, graduates of Evelyn Wood speed-reading classes will already know that at the end of ''Goblet of Fire,'' the fourth Harry Potter book, our hero . . . Just kidding. I'm not going to spoil the book for anyone. I don't know any more about it than your average third-grader.</p>
        <p>But 15-year-olds are something else. Desiree Craver of Elmer, who just turned 15, finished the book last Monday -- five full days before it  went on sale -- because a Wal-Mart store in Millville accidentally displayed the book.</p>
        <p>The cunning young Desiree discovered the Holy Grail last weekend when she was shoppping with her mother, who bought Desiree the book for her birthday on July 3.</p>
        <p>I don't have to tell you about all the hoopla surrounding the book or that Harry Potter, a fearless little wizard, is the biggest news out of Britain since the Beatles and Christine Keeler.</p>
        <p>Months ago, bookstores decided to stay open past midnight on Friday to sell the book exactly as the clock struck 12. (They all signed affidavits promising that they would not so much as peek at the book before then.)</p>
        <p>So last Wednesday -- after it was disclosed in The Bridgeton Evening News that Desiree had accomplished what no one in the literary world could -- NBC offered to send a limousine to interview her.</p>
        <p>But Katie Couric would have to wait. Desiree, dripping wet after a shower, talked to me on telephone -- her parents wisely deciding that somebody from New York (as they yelled up to the bathroom) merited an instant response from their damp daughter.</p>
        <p>Forget Desiree; this may be my closest brush with celebrity, at least when it comes to this particular media circus. And believe me, I've been trying, if only to impress my 8-year-old son, a huge Harry Potter fan. For weeks, he dragged me into every bookstore we passed, hoping for more information about the new Harry Potter.</p>
        <p>When I went to the Barnes &amp; Noble at Clifton Commons to interview the store manager there about the party they were planning, my son  couldn't help blurting out his own suggestions. Will there be moving and talking portraits? he interrupted. Will there be a Scabbers costume? Will Fred and George be setting off dung bombs? Filibuster fireworks? Stink pellets?</p>
        <p>And, finally, Can I have the first copy?</p>
        <p>Deprive him a chance to be part of the big Harry Potter extravaganza exactly as he clock struck midnight? Like Cinderella, he would find a way to get there anyway.</p>
        <p>Besides, how could I deny my own flesh and blood the opportunity to tell his grandchildren that he had been there for this generation's  equivalent of Woodstock?</p>
        <p>The question was, could the book -- or even a midnight extravaganza to celebrate the book -- possibly live up to the anticipation?</p>
        <p>But then, why should it?</p>
        <p>In this celebrity-saturated age, why should children be different from anybody else? Even with a million affidavits signed by booksellers promising the utmost secrecy, who doesn't want to be two steps ahead of the crowd.</p>
        <p>And who cares about the event in question after it actually happens? (Y2K comes to mind.)</p>
        <p>So when my husband came home from a big licensing show at the Javits Convention Center last month with four tins of Bertie Botts Every Flavor Beans (a Harry Potter delicacy that won't be available until November), and my son was able to take one into the school, it was as if he knew ahead of time how the Microsoft antitrust case would turn out. Who cares if we could have sold them for $36 on eBay?</p>
        <p>And when my husband came home last week with news that he might get to read a few pages of the book a day or two ahead of time -- because he does a radio show with Newsweek, which bought the excerpt -- you might have thought that he had spotted Elvis.</p>
        <p>But then, Desiree stumbled onto Judge Crater and Jimmy Hoffa rolled into one.</p>
        <p>''I'm probably the coolest kid to all the little kids,'' she said. Alas, her celebrity wattage is probably dimmed somewhat, she said, because most of her friends consider themselves too old for Harry Potter.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Desiree does sound old beyond her years.</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
