<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 07-09-00: The Ethicist; Conjugal Miss</title>
    <meta content="WLN091917" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDF1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 07-09-00: The Ethicist; Conjugal Miss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen The Ethicist question-and-answer column on ethics of seeking divorce that could lead to deportation of immigrant spouse; also responds to question about ethics of disregarding poor in marketing e-technology (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years ago I met a 45-year-old woman in China and arranged for her to come to New York. We were married within two weeks. Since that time she has refused to disrobe in front of me or to have sexual intercourse. We do not sleep in the same room. She refuses to visit a Chinese-speaking woman therapist. If I divorce her, she may lose her immigration status and be forced to return to China. Would it be unethical to divorce her? -- R.S. Flushing, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A whirlwind courtship, a quick trip to the altar, a romance gone sour -- you know the old saying: marry in haste, repent in China. But if yours is a real situation, that is a harsh fate to impose on a woman with whom you've lived for three years and for whom you seem to have some feeling. You are right to seek a solution to your intimate problems that does not involve a deportation hearing. In fact, your first step should be to get some legal advice so neither of you ends up on the wrong side of the immigration laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years ago I met a 45-year-old woman in China and arranged for her to come to New York. We were married within two weeks. Since that time she has refused to disrobe in front of me or to have sexual intercourse. We do not sleep in the same room. She refuses to visit a Chinese-speaking woman therapist. If I divorce her, she may lose her immigration status and be forced to return to China. Would it be unethical to divorce her? -- R.S. Flushing, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A whirlwind courtship, a quick trip to the altar, a romance gone sour -- you know the old saying: marry in haste, repent in China. But if yours is a real situation, that is a harsh fate to impose on a woman with whom you've lived for three years and for whom you seem to have some feeling. You are right to seek a solution to your intimate problems that does not involve a deportation hearing. In fact, your first step should be to get some legal advice so neither of you ends up on the wrong side of the immigration laws.</p>
        <p>Even if divorce would not lead to deportation, you should make every effort to improve your marriage.</p>
        <p>If she married you simply to get to the United States or if you married a mail-order bride, the origins of your union are less significant than what you've made of it. And it is not just your wife who should talk to a therapist; resolving this conflict is something you must undertake together.</p>
        <p>If these efforts fail, you might consider an accommodation that allows you to seek sexual satisfaction elsewhere while the two of you stay married -- without putting her on a plane to China, that is. Her eagerness to remain in America does not trump your desire for marital happiness and a fulfilling erotic life, but you should seek a solution that does not provide for one person's tranquillity at the expense of the other's.</p>
        <p>It is possible that your wife will neither disrobe nor have sexual intercourse because love is absent or because of her sexual orientation. There is also an odder possibility to consider, a scenario treated with great sensitivity in ''M. Butterfly.''</p>
        <p>At a sales meeting on e-technology, a presenter said that to be successful, we should disregard those with minimal income in favor of those with substantial income. How does one deal with this social injustice? -- J.L.M., Omaha</p>
        <p>I assume the presenter was encouraging you to disregard the poor in your marketing efforts, not to run them over with your Lexus should anyone making less than $15,000 a year fail to get out of your way quickly enough. There is, on the face of it, nothing unethical about devotion to goods or services that only a few can afford -- hence the existence of Tiffany, the Four Seasons and Patricia Duff. Indeed, most of the world's people are unable to afford pretty much everything on sale in American department stores. But it is also true that fortunes have been made by producing things many people can enjoy -- paperback books, ballpoint pens, fresh peaches. Thus, while catering to the rich is an option, it is not the only option. The best way to respond to what you see as social injustice is to have the courage of your convictions and find a different job, one that allows you to live your values.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
