<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Farewell, My Cross-Dressing Lovely</title>
    <meta content="09LEHPHT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehman, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shames, Laurence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Naked Detective, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFDC1F30F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Farewell, My Cross-Dressing Lovely</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Lehman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lehman, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Lehman reviews book The Naked Detective by Laurence Shames (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Naked Detective</p>
        <p>By Laurence Shames.</p>
        <p>225 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Villard. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Naked Detective</p>
        <p>By Laurence Shames.</p>
        <p>225 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Villard. $22.95.</p>
        <p>THE title of this diverting sendup of murder mysteries refers to Pete Amsterdam, a middle-aged tennis-playing oenophile enjoying early retirement in Key West. On his accountant's advice Amsterdam has set himself up as a detective strictly as a tax dodge. A self-described ''bourgeois cream puff,'' he hasn't had the inconvenience of a client in the more than two years since.</p>
        <p>One afternoon he is naked in his hot tub when a tall woman -- a blonde, of course; it's always a blonde, right?'' -- barges right in, bearing the expected newspaper clipping (Apparent Suicide in Key West Harbor). When Amsterdam, running out of ways to say no, asks the blonde who she is, she whips off her wig and ersatz breasts and lowers her voice three-quarters of an octave. End of chapter.</p>
        <p>Amsterdam's cross-dressing client is Kenny Lukens, the apparent suicide of the headline, and that's another generic convention that Laurence Shames meticulously observes: in the precincts of literary crime, no one is who he seems to be. Lukens had to disappear, he explains, because he used to tend bar until he got caught with his hand in the gangster owner's till. He will turn into a corpse for real, we suspect, as the rest of the plot falls into place.</p>
        <p>The gangster dies of an apoplectic fit in his hospital bed. There's a second murder. There are sidebars about Key West ''conchs'' (as the denizens are called) on their bicycles, Jet Skis, trawlers and floating casinos. A crowd of variously unsavory characters is in pursuit of a buried bank deposit pouch. What does it contain?</p>
        <p>On the romantic front, the dead gangster's nymphomaniac daughter has designs on our hero. So does a sexy yoga instructor named Maggie. Whom will he choose? ''I got goose bumps because I was weirding myself out, big time,'' Amsterdam muses in a burst of paranoia about Maggie. Had he nearly gone to bed with ''a murderess''? More shtick: Maggie seems about as fatale as Liza Minnelli in ''Cabaret.''</p>
        <p>The charm of this literary exercise comes with the self-conscious indulging of a fantasy -- the fantasy of every granola-eating good citizen over 40 -- that we can have the thrill of adventure and risk and danger in our lives and that we would acquit ourselves well in conflict with gamblers, goons and crooked cops.</p>
        <p>''The Naked Detective'' is a lighthearted, sardonic homage to the detective novel as a form. Not every mystery fan will approve. The by-the-book plot</p>
        <p>is as thin as a blackmailer's alibi. Shames, who has written seven previous Key West novels (including ''Mangrove Squeeze'' and ''Tropical Depression''), has a breezily engaging manner, though he does better at aping the genre than at exemplifying it.</p>
        <p>Pete Amsterdam stands in relation to his life as Steve Martin does to the 1940's movies quoted in ''Dead Men Don't Wear Plaid.'' ''I may not know diddle about being a detective, but I have a certain rudimentary grasp of the detective story,'' Amsterdam remarks, summing up the book's rationale. ''Doesn't everybody? We all grow up with it. It's like the 32-bar jazz tune. We get it without analysis because it's heritage.''</p>
        <p>David Lehman's books include ''The Perfect Murder: A Study in Detection'' and ''The Daily Mirror: A Journal in Poetry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Lehman's books include ''The Perfect Murder: A Study in Detection'' and ''The Daily Mirror: A Journal in Poetry.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
