<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Entire Community Showed That They Cared</title>
    <meta content="09NEGR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR THE RECORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Negron, Hector</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DD1E39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Entire Community Showed That They Cared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Sleepy Hollow high school graduate and wrestling champion Hector Negron, who was helped by school community and coaches after his mother died in traffic accident; he is headed to Lycoming College in Williamsport, Pa, where he plans to continue wrestling; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Hector Negron received his diploma from Sleepy Hollow High School 10 days ago, he did the same thing at the ceremony he had done after his many wrestling triumphs.</p>
        <p>He glanced skyward for just an instant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Hector Negron received his diploma from Sleepy Hollow High School 10 days ago, he did the same thing at the ceremony he had done after his many wrestling triumphs.</p>
        <p>He glanced skyward for just an instant.</p>
        <p>''I could see my mom's smiling face,'' he said. ''It made me feel so much better.''</p>
        <p>Hector's success is far more than the story of a talented and dedicated athlete. It is the story of a family and an entire sporting community banding together after a tragedy.</p>
        <p>Hector, already a sectional wrestling champion as a freshman, was returning from a sophomore meet in Binghamton, sleeping in the family car with his younger brother, Jose, 8, and his sister Jenesia. Their mother, Evelyn, was driving through the rain and mist on Route 17.</p>
        <p>There was a head-on collision. Mrs. Negron, 40, was killed instantly. Hector woke up in the hospital with a jaw broken in three places and broken ribs. And a broken spirit.</p>
        <p>''To walk in, seeing him like he was,'' said the Sleepy Hollow wrestling coach, Brian Tompkins, ''it was . . . ''</p>
        <p>The sentence goes unfinished.</p>
        <p>''His father, Hector Sr., was there, and his older brother, Juan,'' Tompkins continued. ''The first thing Hector said was, 'Where's mommy?'</p>
        <p>''To see him come all the way back, as a wrestler and as a person, well, he's just a great kid.''</p>
        <p>The high school community rallied around the Negron family. His father, his older brother and his sister were there for Hector. All, especially Hector, were there for Jose. And Tompkins and the entire Sleepy Hollow program lent support and understanding.</p>
        <p>''It was sort of hard just even accepting it,'' Hector said. ''If it wasn't for the love of my family, friends and coaches -- and people we never even knew who showed they cared, I don't know where I'd be.</p>
        <p>''I almost felt as if it was wrestling's fault,'' Hector continued. ''Coach Tompkins and my father and my older brother talked to me. They told me mom would be proud if I kept on wrestling. That's why I look up at her after each match.''</p>
        <p>Besides looking up, he has looked after Jose. It is Hector who gets him up and off to school each morning. It is Hector who then takes him to wrestling practice where Juan, an assistant coach, also watches the young athlete.</p>
        <p>''I knew it would be hard for him,'' Hector said. ''Just 8 and not going to have a mom there for him. I wanted to give him so much more support.'' He had already given him a love of wrestling.</p>
        <p>''He'll be better than I am,'' Hector, who started the sport at 8 by tagging along with Juan, said of his younger brother. ''He's won every tournament we took him to. I think he'll be two times better than I will. He started when he was 5.''</p>
        <p>Hector's career almost ended before it began.</p>
        <p>''I was 8, and Juan took me to an Ossining kids wrestling tournament,'' he said. ''All I'd ever done was fool around in the living room -- mom used to yell when she heard things break.</p>
        <p>''I lost my first match in 15 seconds! I was really down. I didn't want to wrestle any more for about two weeks. Then I got competitive. I wanted to be better.</p>
        <p>''Within a couple of months I won my first tournament.''</p>
        <p>He has done little but win since, while moving up from the 101-pound division to his current 128 pounds.</p>
        <p>Tompkins said: ''He lost two sectional title matches, his sophomore and junior year, both by one point. What makes him the best? His ability to keep going in tight matches. He's able to go into the gas tank for that little extra easier than other kids.''</p>
        <p>For Hector, wrestling is a year-round sport. He is headed to Lycoming College in Williamsport, Pa., where he will continue wrestling. He feels the sport helped get him there.</p>
        <p>''It disciplines you, and you need discipline to do well in class,'' he said. ''I think wrestling made me the person I am today.''</p>
        <p>FOR THE RECORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
