<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Buzz: The Redskins Are a Lock</title>
    <meta content="09FOOT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7D61438F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Buzz: The Redskins Are a Lock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Freeman column on growing belief that off-season spending spree to acquire top players puts Washington Redskins in position to win Super Bowl; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The whispers are beginning to build toward a bold crescendo. From top National Football League executives to frequent-flyer-mile-earning scouts to assistant trainers, there is a unanimous belief that the season need not even be played, because the Washington Redskins, after one of the liveliest off-season spending binges in league history, have already won the Super Bowl. Pencil them in, it is said.</p>
        <p>But some of the talk has a dual purpose. Like those sunburned ''Survivor'' castaways who smile at each other and then plot to steal coconuts, some of Washington's rivals are pumping up the Redskins in the hope that they can make Washington a target by praising the team to death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The whispers are beginning to build toward a bold crescendo. From top National Football League executives to frequent-flyer-mile-earning scouts to assistant trainers, there is a unanimous belief that the season need not even be played, because the Washington Redskins, after one of the liveliest off-season spending binges in league history, have already won the Super Bowl. Pencil them in, it is said.</p>
        <p>But some of the talk has a dual purpose. Like those sunburned ''Survivor'' castaways who smile at each other and then plot to steal coconuts, some of Washington's rivals are pumping up the Redskins in the hope that they can make Washington a target by praising the team to death.</p>
        <p>It is impossible, though, not to shuttle the Redskins to the top of the line of championship contenders. In what was a busy N.F.L. off-season -- with a murder trial for one of the league's stars and the retirement of a half-dozen great coaches and players -- Washington's stockpiling of Pro Bowl players ranks as the most interesting development.</p>
        <p>With the beginning of training camps only days away -- I know, it seems as if last season just ended -- Washington's moves loom large over the N.F.L. landscape.</p>
        <p>The Redskins are hardly the first team to hire high-priced free agents; the San Francisco 49ers and the Dallas Cowboys have done it for years. But no team has revamped on such a grand scale in such a short time.</p>
        <p>The Redskins' owner, Daniel Snyder, spent $17 million in signing bonuses alone during the off-season for defensive end Bruce Smith, cornerback Deion Sanders, safety Mark Carrier and quarterback Jeff George, all 30-somethings in the latter part of their careers.</p>
        <p>Snyder emptying his checking account was one of many trends in the months following the St. Louis Rams' unlikely Super Bowl victory in January. They include:</p>
        <p>*Coaches moving on. Jimmy Johnson, Bill Parcells, Dick Vermeil and Mike Ditka all left the coaching sideline. Bobby Beathard retired from the front office.</p>
        <p>*Players following. Dan Marino and Steve Young, both first-ballot Hall of Famers, retired and instantly changed the face of the league. Denver will be forced to rely on the shaky Brian Griese, while Miami must decide if Damon Huard or Jay Fiedler will replace Marino.</p>
        <p>*Keyshawn Johnson leaving New York. Often brash, occasionally selfish and always a great player, the former Jets wide receiver signed a free-agent contract with Tampa Bay. The Buccaneers, along with the Redskins and the Rams, are championship contenders from the National Conference. Each team has at least one big-time pass catcher.</p>
        <p>*The estate tax disappearing. Yes, the estate tax became a huge issue this off-season. On June 9, the United States House of Representatives voted, 279 to 139, to phase out the federal estate tax, the tax on rich people's assets when they die. The estates of many owners of N.F.L. teams, including Wellington Mara of the Giants, Buffalo's Ralph Wilson and Oakland's Al Davis, would very likely be forced to sell their teams, under the current law, to pay the hefty tax after an owner's death. But if the Senate were to pass a bill similar to the one approved by the House, and if both bodies were to override a threatened veto by President Clinton, the federal tax burden would be erased and families of N.F.L. owners would not have to go through a painful sale process.</p>
        <p>*The Tennessee Titans' consolidating. The team did the right thing by giving Coach Jeff Fisher a new long-term contract. One of the best backs in the league, Eddie George, is close to signing a six-year extension. Now Tennessee is trying to add depth by talking Reggie White out of retirement.</p>
        <p>*Is Atlanta in trouble? Running back Jamal Anderson is still having problems with his surgically repaired right knee, which tends to swell after long workouts. Not time to panic -- yet -- but the Falcons signed Ron Rivers, a career backup, just in case. If Anderson continues to have problems, the Falcons would again be mopping up the N.F.C. West.</p>
        <p>*Players behaving badly. Murder charges against Baltimore Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis were dropped, after he agreed to plead guilty to lying to the police. Rae Carruth, the former Carolina Panthers wide receiver, will stand trial next year for plotting to kill his pregnant girlfriend. Oakland Raiders kicker Sebastian Janikowski was arrested June 21 on a charge of possession of GHB, a drug that has been linked to date rapes.</p>
        <p>Several teams, frustrated that some players continue to show up on the police blotter, are beginning to insert protective clauses in contracts in case players end up in trouble. Some of these additions call for the withholding of bonuses if a player is found guilty of a serious crime.</p>
        <p>As for the Giants, people close to Coach Jim Fassel say he is more motivated than ever to get the team back into the playoffs and beyond. There is no nicer person in the N.F.L. than Fassel, but he was given only a one-year contract extension; if he does not win this year, he could be dismissed.</p>
        <p>The Jets, meanwhile, are still a team that has still not picked up a solid wide receiver in free agency to replace Johnson, but the team might in the coming weeks. Meanwhile, Coach Al Groh will have Parcells hovering over the team.</p>
        <p>The only thing the Redskins may mop up is Champagne after the Super Bowl. The team should be outstanding. If not, look for Snyder to fire everyone, and start over.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
