<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out Spots, Cats and Bad Lines</title>
    <meta content="09MCKI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Superstitions</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grammer, Kelsey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Macbeth (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D71738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out Spots, Cats and Bad Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Short run of Broadway production of Shakespeare's Macbeth starring Kelsey Grammer appears to support long-standing superstition that play is cursed; long list of other Broadway superstitions noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHORT of dinner theater or being cast in a musical about tooth decay, there are few terrors that hold more sway over theater folk than the curse of ''Macbeth.'' Legend has it that the hex dates from the first production in 1606, when the actor playing Lady Macbeth died backstage, cursing the play.</p>
        <p>Since then, various productions of ''Macbeth'' have been waylaid by death and disaster. Over the years, the myth has gained such authority that many actors are loath to utter even the name of the play, preferring instead to call it ''the Scottish play,'' or occasionally ''the Scottish play about the guy who wants to be king so bad he knocks off some other dudes and then watches his wife go totally bonkers.'' Others refer to it merely as ''the Scottish play I've never read.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHORT of dinner theater or being cast in a musical about tooth decay, there are few terrors that hold more sway over theater folk than the curse of ''Macbeth.'' Legend has it that the hex dates from the first production in 1606, when the actor playing Lady Macbeth died backstage, cursing the play.</p>
        <p>Since then, various productions of ''Macbeth'' have been waylaid by death and disaster. Over the years, the myth has gained such authority that many actors are loath to utter even the name of the play, preferring instead to call it ''the Scottish play,'' or occasionally ''the Scottish play about the guy who wants to be king so bad he knocks off some other dudes and then watches his wife go totally bonkers.'' Others refer to it merely as ''the Scottish play I've never read.''</p>
        <p>Recently, the hex claimed yet another victim when the Broadway production of ''Macbeth'' starring Kelsey Grammer of the hit show ''Frasier'' folded after only 13 performances. That gave it the shortest run since the 1998 comedy ''More to Love,'' a four-performance wonder that featured an actress in the role of an electrical fuse. Just a day after Mr. Grammer's reviews came out, the jinx struck the British actor Antony Sher, who was starring in a production of the play in New Haven. He walked offstage at the end of Act I but did not return. A throat infection kept him out for several days.</p>
        <p>Of course the ''Macbeth'' curse is hardly the only superstition hanging over the black-magic-laden world of the theater, a profession in which open incantations of blood lust (''Break a leg!'') are routine.</p>
        <p>The list of taboos is long: never whistle in the dressing room, never open an umbrella onstage and never, never be cast as an electrical fuse. So treacherous are these potential psychic land mines that, in the name of public service, the following is a brief rundown of some current and ancient omens plaguing the stage:</p>
        <p>Cats -- According to ''A Brief Dictionary of American Superstitions,'' by Vergilius Ferm (Philosophical Library, 1959), it bodes ill if a cat walks across a stage during rehearsal. The exception, of course, is if you invested in the musical ''Cats,'' Broadway's longest-running musical. In which case, bring on the kitties.</p>
        <p>Chorus girls -- If a chorus girl dances on spilled powder before a performance, it can inspire good fortune. Or a bout of wheezing.</p>
        <p>Costumes -- It is considered very bad luck to change costumes if your first performance was a success. It is considered very bad taste to never change it.</p>
        <p>Curtains -- According to Mr. Ferm, yellow curtains are said to bring bad luck to a new play. No reason is given, except for the obvious garishness, of course.</p>
        <p>Death -- A death in the audience is considered bad luck for the production. It's particularly unfortunate for the poor theatergoer.</p>
        <p>Disney -- Considered very good luck for investors; produced ''The Lion King,'' a sellout for nearly three years; ''Aida,'' Broadway's second-highest-grossing musical; and ''Beauty and the Beast,'' which is in its seventh year on Broadway. You do the math.</p>
        <p>Flowers -- Artificial flowers are preferred over the real thing in the theater, except by actresses, who have divorced men for less.</p>
        <p>The Gypsy Robe -- One of Broadway's oldest traditions: a chorus member from the last musical to open passes along a robe to the most recently opened musical. Each cast embroiders a memento on it before the robe goes to the next production. When all the space is used up, a new one is begun and the old robe is retired to the Museum of the City of New York; the chorus members, meanwhile, retire to Florida.</p>
        <p>Horror Movies -- ''Carrie: The Musical'' (1988) is widely considered one of the greatest flops in Broadway history. The play was a stunning display of both bad taste -- a big dance number centered around a pig slaughter -- and money ($7 million, all lost). Its director was Terry Hands, whose most recent credit was ''Macbeth,'' with Mr. Grammer.</p>
        <p>Knitting -- Engaging in this handicraft onstage is taboo, especially during any big dance scene.</p>
        <p>Peepholes -- Once considered acceptable on Broadway, where actors could sneak peeks at the audience. Accidentally banned in 1998 as part of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's anti-sex campaign.</p>
        <p>Sales -- According to the superstitions of theater managers, if the first purchaser of tickets is young, the run will be short. If the buyer is elderly, it means a long run. By this logic, and the demographics of Broadway today, every show on Broadway would be a hit.</p>
        <p>Talent Agents -- Having an agent is considered good luck. Not having one is considered bad luck. Lately, being Mr. Grammer's agent is considered particularly bad luck.</p>
        <p>Television Stars -- See above.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
