<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Measure for Measure' Staged at Boscobel</title>
    <meta content="09THEA$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rucker, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Measure For Measure (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DE1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Measure for Measure' Staged at Boscobel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>GARRISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Measure for Measure, directed by Mark Rucker, first of two plays in Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival's 14th season in Garrison, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE entrance of the players, from the distant waters through the garden paths and across the immense verdant landscape, is by now an essential rite of summer here. Perhaps they have sprung, magically, fully costumed and all dry, from the Hudson. It happens, however, that the grand procession signals the beginning of summer revelry in these parts. Under the big tent, all the grass is a stage. The Boscobel estate is out back; the mountains and lights over the river provide the omnipresent backdrop.</p>
        <p>The first of this season's two plays in the Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival's 14th season is ''Measure for Measure,'' a poisonous comedy of deceit for a noble purpose. Vincentio, the duke, is good, a benevolent imposter. Angelo, his ''outward- sainted'' lord deputy, is bad. A case study in sexual repression acted out through cruelty and censorship, Angelo is enslaved by his own passion for the chaste Isabella, who is on her way to a nunnery. Anyone who perceives Isabella, the pure, as sanctimonious and sexy has a point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE entrance of the players, from the distant waters through the garden paths and across the immense verdant landscape, is by now an essential rite of summer here. Perhaps they have sprung, magically, fully costumed and all dry, from the Hudson. It happens, however, that the grand procession signals the beginning of summer revelry in these parts. Under the big tent, all the grass is a stage. The Boscobel estate is out back; the mountains and lights over the river provide the omnipresent backdrop.</p>
        <p>The first of this season's two plays in the Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival's 14th season is ''Measure for Measure,'' a poisonous comedy of deceit for a noble purpose. Vincentio, the duke, is good, a benevolent imposter. Angelo, his ''outward- sainted'' lord deputy, is bad. A case study in sexual repression acted out through cruelty and censorship, Angelo is enslaved by his own passion for the chaste Isabella, who is on her way to a nunnery. Anyone who perceives Isabella, the pure, as sanctimonious and sexy has a point.</p>
        <p>''Liberty plucks justice by the nose'' and mercy ultimately tempers it. Hypocrisy is humanized. Shakespeare found harmony in opposites.  Compromise passes for compassion, and all ends well enough, but not happily.</p>
        <p>The director Mark Rucker has called ''Measure for Measure'' ''a morality play without a moral.''  When he staged it with acting students in the graduate program at the Yale School of Drama last year, it  was, no surprise, widely perceived as a reflection of contemporary scandals and betrayals, sexual and political.</p>
        <p>And, yes, it is a comedy, but one with a first act of ''high rancidity'' in Harold Bloom's words. In ''Shakespeare: The Invention of the Human'' (Riverhead Books, 1998), Mr. Bloom termed the play ''Shakespeare's farewell to comedy.''</p>
        <p>Before that farewell, farce was not forgotten. Antic humor of the wild and crazy kind permeates an otherwise dark, exceedingly complex tale. The Hudson Valley staging abounds in master clowning by Chris Edwards (Pompey, Mistress Overdone's pimp), Carl Palmer and Steve Ross as Elbow and Froth, both fools, smoking joints. In a funny, audience-winning performance, Mr. Edwards appears to have traveled to 17th-century Vienna by way of Runyonland with stopovers in Mafioso hangouts, if only to inform his turn as the friendly hangman.</p>
        <p>But then, nothing about Terence O'Brien's staging suggests Vienna anyway; it's only in the script, and everyone is used to Shakespeare set anywhere and placed in any time.</p>
        <p>Given the company's signature style of rampant eclecticism and merry pranks in mixed periods, it must be reinforced that the text always comes first. All the rest is adornment for the sake of accessibility and sheer fun. Yet, Mr. O'Brien's ''Measure'' is mostly unadorned in that savage first act, which is pure in language and free of fuss.</p>
        <p>That the voice of Eartha Kitt (''Santa Baby'') accompanies a  sheerly insane conga line in a second-act opener that almost brings down the tent does not mean intentions have strayed. Bo Bell's sound design mixes the liturgical with the symphonic, with the purely classical providing apt scoring for Kurt Rhoads' necessary duplicities as the real Duke and the disguised Friar.  Dukedom becomes Mr. Rhoads, a royal Shakespearean actor whose performances, season after season,  provide reason upon reason to take this festival seriously. His Friar is tenderly, rationally merciful.</p>
        <p>Nance Williamson, who is married to Mr. Rhoads and is to play the shrew to his tamer in this season's next staging, is Mistress Overdone. In true repertory spirit, a minor, often throwaway role is made major by Ms. Williamson.</p>
        <p>Given its exploration of the soul's dark corners, ''Measure for Measure'' has been branded as an unpleasant comedy and, for a long time, an unpopular one. It is easy to say that an obviously renewed interest in a once rarely produced ''problem play'' attests to our own moral ambiguities. Which makes it extraordinarily contemporary and as enveloping as Hudson Valley's wraparound scenery.</p>
        <p>And don't forget the comedy. Mr. O'Brien's troupe doesn't miss a beat.</p>
        <p>''Measure for Measure'' at Hudson Valley Shakespeare Festival at Boscobel Restoration in Garrison. Performances through July 30. Box office: (845) 265-9575.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
