<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baseball May See .400 Hitter For the First Time Since '41</title>
    <meta content="09BASE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DF1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baseball May See .400 Hitter For the First Time Since '41</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baseball Notebook article focuses on possibility of .400 hitter this season, who would be first since 1941; notes 11 players are currently batting .350 or higher; tables; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the years have passed -- it's 59 since the last one -- the likelihood of a .400 hitter has dwindled. Some players have threatened, Larry Walker hitting .379 last season, Tony Gwynn .394 in the strike-shortened 1994 season; going back a few more years, George Brett .390 and Rod Carew .388. But the first digit in each case was still a 3.</p>
        <p>Now arises a development that regenerates the prospect of having someone attain that lonesome plateau, which hasn't been breached since Ted Williams hit .406 in 1941. Entering yesterday's schedule, 11 players, 6 in the National League, 5 in the American, were hitting .350 or higher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the years have passed -- it's 59 since the last one -- the likelihood of a .400 hitter has dwindled. Some players have threatened, Larry Walker hitting .379 last season, Tony Gwynn .394 in the strike-shortened 1994 season; going back a few more years, George Brett .390 and Rod Carew .388. But the first digit in each case was still a 3.</p>
        <p>Now arises a development that regenerates the prospect of having someone attain that lonesome plateau, which hasn't been breached since Ted Williams hit .406 in 1941. Entering yesterday's schedule, 11 players, 6 in the National League, 5 in the American, were hitting .350 or higher.</p>
        <p>Only twice in the past 10 seasons, Elias Sports Bureau research shows, have as many as seven players reached the All-Star Game break at .350 or higher. In the first three seasons of the 90's, a total of two players achieved that status at this time of the season, and only two years ago, no National Leaguers and only two American League players batted .350 or better before the break. Bernie Williams was the leading hitter then, his average .353.</p>
        <p>Nomar Garciaparra of Boston was this season's leading hitter before play yesterday, batting .386. Todd Helton of Colorado, who for much of the early part of the season was over .400, was next at .385. The Montreal Expos had two players in the .370's, Jose Vidro and Vladimir Guerrero. Vidro was one of three second basemen in the group, Luis Castillo of Florida and Jeff Kent of San Francisco being the others. And there were two catchers, Ivan Rodriguez of Texas and Mike Piazza of the Mets, who were also the top vote-getters in their respective leagues in the All-Star Game balloting.</p>
        <p>The hitters and their high averages have generally been overlooked with the focus on the increase in home runs. But the same factors that are said to be involved in home run inflation appear to fuel the higher batting averages, too.</p>
        <p>''Not only is the ball juiced, but it's fatter than it used to be,'' Sandy Alderson, baseball's chief of baseball operations, said jokingly. Then Alderson, who after recent tests blessed the balls as no different from last year's, ticked off the real reasons he and others see as being behind the increase in high hitters.</p>
        <p>''You can talk about the smaller strike zone,'' he said, ''stronger players, lighter bats leading to better bat control, dilution of pitching, smaller ballparks, smaller not only in the sense that something is going over the wall more frequently but also off the wall more frequently, less foul territory.''</p>
        <p>Syd Thrift, head of baseball operations for the Baltimore Orioles and a longtime student of hitters, said he believed much of the hitting improvement stemmed from preparation.</p>
        <p>''The hitters have prepared themselves more effectively to be better hitters with the aid of technology and technique training by hitting coaches plus their own abilities,'' Thrift said. ''All those top hitters use the whole field. They are much more proficient hitters. They don't try to pull the ball. The hitters show a lot of discipline. They wait longer, they get good pitches, they take pitchers deep into the count.''</p>
        <p>The pitchers have to accept their share of the change, Thrift added. ''I think the pitching, because of expansion, is inferior,'' he said. ''I think there are pitchers in the major leagues right now who are 3, 4, 5 starters on some teams who would not be in the major leagues when you go back in previous times.''</p>
        <p>The Orioles executive also cited improved ballpark lighting as allowing hitters to see the ball better. But he didn't omit the ball itself from his list of reasons for higher averages.</p>
        <p>''I'm not certain the baseball is not different,'' he said, despite the test results. ''The surface seems to be different. It seems to be tighter and harder from a feel standpoint. How much of a factor that is I have no way of knowing.''</p>
        <p>However the factors are figured, Thrift said it ''certainly appears'' that hitters could be headed for .400.</p>
        <p>Alderson said prediction of a .400 hitter is ''speculation maybe for a statistician,'' but he added, ''That's a possibility,'' citing Helton as an example of a possible .400 hitter. Alluding to the Rockies' hitter-friendly home at Coors Field, Alderson said: ''Not only does the ball carry well, but a line drive hitter with an expansive area can do very well there. I think it's certainly a possibility. As averages creep up from .300 to .350, who's to say we won't see someone take that extra step.''</p>
        <p>That New Voice</p>
        <p>Maybe that's the voice John Hart was talking about.</p>
        <p>When the Cleveland Indians fired Mike Hargrove as their manager last October after he led them to five division championships and two World Series but no World Series championships, Hart, the general manager, said the team needed ''a new voice coming from the clubhouse'' and named Charlie Manuel, the Indians' batting coach, as the new manager.</p>
        <p>Last Sunday, with the Indians 10 1/2 games out of the position in the standings to which they had become accustomed, Manuel spoke. He announced to the players that their Ping-Pong table was being removed from the clubhouse, as were two cushy couches. And one more thing, he said: no more card games in the clubhouse, either.</p>
        <p>Manuel said ''these things'' distracted from the goal of winning.</p>
        <p>The Indians, who hadn't been so far from first place since the 1993 season ended, won all of their division championships under Hargrove with the Ping-Pong table.</p>
        <p>Midseason Tumbles</p>
        <p>Despite winning only 18 games and losing 28 in an eight-week span, the Yankees did not tumble out of the American League East race. Some other teams were not so fortunate.</p>
        <p>*Cleveland. The Indians, from May 23 through July 1, won 18 and lost 22, plummeting from half a game behind the Chicago White Sox (28-11) to 11 back.</p>
        <p>*Texas. The Rangers, beginning June 6, lost nine games in a row and through July 2 had a 7-16 record. In that four-week period, they plunged from one percentage point behind Seattle (18-7) to 10 games back.</p>
        <p>*Cincinnati. The Reds were half a game ahead of St. Louis on the morning of June 5. In the next month the Reds lost 19 of 28 games and fell 10 games behind the Cardinals (19-8).</p>
        <p>A Carpenter's Story</p>
        <p>The Yankees tried Jake Westbrook, Ben Ford and Ed Yarnall. The Arizona Diamondbacks tried Geraldo Guzman. The four players are among any number of pitchers who have been summoned in desperation from the minor leagues this season as teams have tried to plug holes in their starting rotations.</p>
        <p>In the Yankees' case, their trio of rookies have started a total of five games, and they have lost four. They won the fifth, against Baltimore last Thursday, because their hitters somehow overcame the seven-run deficit Yarnall helped create. In their five starts, Westbrook, Ford and Yarnall gave up 29 hits and 11 walks in 132/3  innings, allowing 24 earned runs for a 15.80 earned run average.</p>
        <p>Then there was the Diamondbacks' initial experience with Guzman. Deciding to demote Omar Daal and his 2-9 record (for a first-place team) to the bullpen, the Diamondbacks promoted Guzman from Tucson of the Pacific Coast League for their game Thursday night in Houston. He answered their call with a 2-1 victory in which he permitted one run and four hits in eight innings.</p>
        <p>The 27-year-old Guzman is no ordinary rookie.</p>
        <p>Originally signed by the Montreal Expos, Guzman pitched for their team in the Dominican Republic in 1990 and 1991. Plagued by shoulder problems, he quit the game and became a carpenter, a trade he worked for the next seven years. Last year he decided he wanted to play again, and Junior Noboa, the Diamondbacks' Latin America scouting coordinator, helped place him with a team in Taiwan.</p>
        <p>When he returned home after the season, he was working out at the Diamondbacks' academy in the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>''We saw him throw and we signed him,'' Sandy Johnson, the team's assistant general manager, said. ''He pitched in the winter league and he kept pitching better and better. Rather than taking a chance on losing him in the draft the way he was throwing, we put him on the 40-man roster.''</p>
        <p>Guzman looked no less impressive in spring training this year, Johnson said. But the Diamondbacks didn't want to rush him. They initially made him a middle reliever for El Paso of the Class AA Texas League, then moved him up to closer. ''Then we put him in the rotation and he handled that well,'' Johnson related. ''He kept getting better and better.''</p>
        <p>On to Tucson, where he reeled off a 4-1 record with a 1.42 earned run average and 23 hits, 10 walks and 44 strikeouts in 38 innings. When the Diamondbacks needed another starter, he was the obvious choice. He made it more obvious with his performance against the Astros.</p>
        <p>Even more obvious than that is the discovery that teams have been going about it all wrong in trying to develop pitchers. They have done it by having their young prospects pitch. Instead, they should just give the kids a hammer and tell them to swing it for a few years, then come back and pitch.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
