<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West Nile Virus Detected in Birds in 3 New York Counties</title>
    <meta content="09NILE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crows (Bird)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rockland County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DA1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West Nile Virus Detected in Birds in 3 New York Counties</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State health officials announce four more dead crows, two on Long Island and one each in Westchester and Rockland Counties, test positive for West Nile Virus, bringing total number of confirmed cases in New York to eight; there are no plans to spray pesticides to try to eliminate mosquitoes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four more dead crows, two on Long Island and one each in Westchester and Rockland Counties, have tested positive for the West Nile virus, state health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The test results, released by the state to local health departments on Friday, bring to eight the number of confirmed cases of West Nile virus in birds in New York State, with another case confirmed in New Jersey last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four more dead crows, two on Long Island and one each in Westchester and Rockland Counties, have tested positive for the West Nile virus, state health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The test results, released by the state to local health departments on Friday, bring to eight the number of confirmed cases of West Nile virus in birds in New York State, with another case confirmed in New Jersey last month.</p>
        <p>And Westchester County officials said yesterday that they suspected the virus had caused the death of another bird but that they were awaiting further test results.</p>
        <p>West Nile is a mosquito-borne virus that killed 7 people and infected 62 others in the New York area last year. As part of a regional program aimed at detecting the virus, which can cause encephalitis in humans and can be fatal, state officials have been testing dead birds and mosquitoes and taking blood samples from live chickens, which carry the virus but do not get sick from it.</p>
        <p>Kristine A. Smith, a spokeswoman for the New York State Department of Health, said the findings were not surprising, given that hundreds of birds across the state were infected last year, even in places, like Rockland County, where there were no human cases reported.</p>
        <p>''We don't think that people need to be alarmed,'' she said. ''We don't think they need to avoid outdoor activities. But they should be aware that the infection has surfaced in birds.''</p>
        <p>Since the winter, when city health officials found evidence of the virus in hibernating mosquitoes in Fort Totten, Queens, the virus has been detected only in birds.</p>
        <p>There have been no confirmed cases in New York City, where the outbreak began, in northern Queens, late last summer.</p>
        <p>The two Long Island cases in dead crows, both in Suffolk County, were the first cases this year on Long Island. Those test results were first reported yesterday by Newsday.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, a red-tailed hawk that was found dead in February tested positive for the virus, but officials determined that the bird had been infected during last year's outbreak. The dead crow, which was found in New Rochelle, was the first confirmed case during mosquito season, officials said.</p>
        <p>In Rockland County, the crow that tested positive for the virus last week brought to five the number of birds in that county found to have died from the virus since local health departments began sending dead birds to a lab in Albany for testing earlier this year, state health officials said.</p>
        <p>Millie Svatek, a spokeswoman for the Suffolk County Health Department, said yesterday that officials had not determined whether the dead birds, found in West Babylon and Lindenhurst, had been recently infected with the virus or had picked it up during last year's outbreak.</p>
        <p>However, experts say crows tend to die quickly after contracting West Nile infections, making it likely the birds caught the virus this year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Svatek said the county had no immediate plans to spray mosquito pesticides in the area.</p>
        <p>Westchester county also had no plans to begin spraying, Ms. Tolchin said. But officials there and in other counties said they would continue aggressive mosquito-prevention measures, including dumping chemicals that kill mosquito eggs into catch basins and other bodies of water. Rockland County health officials could not be reached for comment on their plans yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
