<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Duly Notes Absence of Dayne</title>
    <meta content="09NFLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dayne, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DA1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Duly Notes Absence of Dayne</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Football Notebook article focuses on New York Giants first-round draft pick Ron Dayne, who has irritated National Football League by missing mandatory league-sponsored rookie symposium; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ron Dayne, the Giants' first-round draft pick, has managed to get his National Football League career off to a rocky start. He has committed two no-no's. First, he missed the league-sponsored rookie symposium this month that is arguably the best program in sports aimed at teaching life skills to its new players. That leads to Dayne's second mistake: by skipping the mandatory symposium, he has irritated the league.</p>
        <p>Getting on the N.F.L.'s bad side at such an early stage is not a great career move. Besides, Dayne missed perhaps the most inspiring symposium since the program began four years ago. Quarterback Kerry Collins, a Giants teammate, spoke of how alcoholism almost ruined his life. Dayne missed Ray Lewis, the Baltimore Ravens linebacker against whom murder charges were dropped, who warned rookies to be careful of the friends they choose. And he missed St. Louis Rams linebacker Leonard Little, who talked about how one night of drunken driving on his birthday cost a woman her life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ron Dayne, the Giants' first-round draft pick, has managed to get his National Football League career off to a rocky start. He has committed two no-no's. First, he missed the league-sponsored rookie symposium this month that is arguably the best program in sports aimed at teaching life skills to its new players. That leads to Dayne's second mistake: by skipping the mandatory symposium, he has irritated the league.</p>
        <p>Getting on the N.F.L.'s bad side at such an early stage is not a great career move. Besides, Dayne missed perhaps the most inspiring symposium since the program began four years ago. Quarterback Kerry Collins, a Giants teammate, spoke of how alcoholism almost ruined his life. Dayne missed Ray Lewis, the Baltimore Ravens linebacker against whom murder charges were dropped, who warned rookies to be careful of the friends they choose. And he missed St. Louis Rams linebacker Leonard Little, who talked about how one night of drunken driving on his birthday cost a woman her life.</p>
        <p>The league is disappointed in Dayne, the former Wisconsin running back, because it had hoped that as a Heisman Trophy winner he would set a better example. Dayne was the only rookie out of more than 250 invitees to miss the entire symposium.</p>
        <p>After the event, Dayne presented a note to league officials from a doctor in Wisconsin stating he did not attend because he had an earache. The N.F.L. is not buying it, and unless Dayne presents a better excuse, he may face a $10,000 fine. Several years ago, the San Diego Chargers rookie quarterback Ryan Leaf skipped the bulk of the symposium without a legitimate excuse and was fined $10,000.</p>
        <p>Dayne could not be reached for comment about his absence. His agent did not return a phone call.</p>
        <p>The league stresses to the rookies soon after they are drafted that attendance at the program is mandatory, and that it could be the most important group of meetings they will attend in their careers.</p>
        <p>At Wisconsin, Dayne was known for being a solid citizen off the field. He is definitely not a troublemaker, quite the opposite. But Dayne's absence, assuming his reason for not attending was a simple ear infection, should not be minimized.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. is constantly being criticized, especially by the news media, for not doing enough to stop the cycle of violence involving its players. The symposium is a proactive step by the league, a road map that, if followed, should keep players out of trouble.</p>
        <p>So, when arguably the most high profile rookie from the last draft class skips the session it is understandable if the N.F.L. becomes bothered. Because in the highly unlikely event that Dayne runs into trouble, the league will be blamed. But it was Dayne who did not take advantage of a valuable resource.</p>
        <p>This year's symposium is especially important to the league because of the rash of recent legal problems for its players. Harold Henderson, chairman of the N.F.L.'s Management Council, decided to put the troubles to good use. He invited players who had been arrested and charged with various criminal acts to give advice to the rookies on how not to fall into the same traps.</p>
        <p>People in attendance said one of the best speakers was Collins, the Giants' starting quarterback and former No. 1 draft pick of Carolina. Collins told the rookies that his battles with alcohol almost cost him his career. Collins, with the players riveted to his every word, said alcoholism led to his making the infamous racial remark to a black former Panthers teammate, which Collins says he made in jest. After that incident, which made national headlines, Collins said he was never able to gain the respect of his Carolina teammates again. The Panthers eventually cut their ties with Collins.</p>
        <p>Collins explained that the Giants gave him a second chance, and he plans to make the most of the opportunity. The rookies appreciated Collins's brutal honesty and gave him, and other members of the panel, a rousing ovation.</p>
        <p>The symposium brings real players to talk about real problems and offers real solutions. The idea is to head off any potential problems, especially since, according to Henderson, statistics show that four rookies will be arrested this year. That number will increase to 12 in players' second year.</p>
        <p>The symposium features skits by professional actors, panel discussions and video presentations. There are sessions regarding finance, dealing with the news media, gambling, labor relations and insurance. The rookies are told the league will do free background checks on potential investments, so the players are protected from unscrupulous financiers. The league says that last year alone players were cheated out of $16 million because of fraudulent schemes.</p>
        <p>''I think this year was probably the best symposium ever,'' Henderson said.</p>
        <p>Top Official to Retire</p>
        <p>Jerry Seeman announced yesterday that this season will be his last after 10 years as the N.F.L.'s head of officiating. In many ways, Seeman, who spent 16 years officiating games, became one of the most important, and recognizable, personalities in the sport. The league has not yet found a replacement.</p>
        <p>Titans Wooing Reggie White</p>
        <p>The Tennessee Titans recently received permission to try to pry the Hall of Fame sack artist Reggie White out of retirement. White, friends maintain, is in fabulous shape, and the Titans have a solid chance of getting him because White and Coach Jeff Fisher are close. Fisher was the defensive coordinator when White and Fisher were with the Philadelphia Eagles.</p>
        <p>But make no mistake about it: White is planning to explore his options. Other teams are interested in him, and White will have his choice of several teams.</p>
        <p>White may still have plenty left to give on the field. It was just two years ago that he led the N.F.C. with 16 sacks. But White is still not completely sure about whether he should play again, his friends say.</p>
        <p>Even though the Titans, who are expected to sign running back Eddie George to a lucrative contract extension in the coming weeks, may not have a ton of cash to give White, they probably have the best chance of snagging him. They envision White as a tutor to the young phenomenon Jevon Kearse.</p>
        <p>Deferred Riches</p>
        <p>What if your employer took a significant portion of your salary, put it in a money market-type trust fund, and said you would receive it only after your term of employment expired, and only if you were a good citizen, and only if you did not withhold your services in any way?</p>
        <p>That is basically the type of deal Miami cornerback Sam Madison agreed to recently. The question is -- will other teams follow in presenting such demands in contract offers?</p>
        <p>Madison, one of the best cover corners in the game, signed a seven-year, $54 million deal. He agreed to put $5 million of his $11 million bonus in a trust that will earn interest. The catch is that the Dolphins can get back the prorated portion of the $5 million if Madison defaults on the contract.</p>
        <p>Basically, if Madison does not hold out, or retire, or get suspended for an entire season because of off-field problems, then he will get the money back at the end of the contract, with interest, which could be as much as $20 million, his agent, Gene Burrough, said.</p>
        <p>If Madison is injured, or dies, the trust stays intact.</p>
        <p>It is a novel idea. The team is happy because it is protected, somewhat, from a player holding out or being lost for a season because of a drug suspension or an arrest. The player, in turn, is practically guaranteed to have money when his career is over.</p>
        <p>The only concern, and it is something the players association will definitely address, is that the team has a massive amount of control over a player's finances. The union may not fight these types of contracts, but it will definitely make some noise.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
