<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books in Brief: Fiction</title>
    <meta content="RV131347" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frucht, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trollope, Joanna</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Marrying the Mistress (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D91F30F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books in Brief: Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Abby Frucht</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frucht, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abby Frucht reviews book Marrying the Mistress by Joanna Trollope (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marrying the Mistress  By Joanna Trollope.  Viking, $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marrying the Mistress  By Joanna Trollope.  Viking, $23.95.</p>
        <p>With its sharp eye, light tone and sly, witty pace, Joanna Trollope's ninth novel delivers all the ingredients of romantic comedy, yet ends with a subtle, dark twist. When a respectable judge named Guy Stockdale decides to leave his 40-year marriage to take up with his longtime mistress, his grown sons warily prepare to weather the consequences. Simon, his mother's favorite, takes her side, and Alan, Simon's gay brother, assumes his usual posture of good-natured temperance. But neither Guy's mistress, Merrion, nor Laura, his left-behind wife, are conventional types, and neither plays her expected role in this incisive drama. Merrion is smarter and nicer than even Alan expects her to be, and the manipulative, spoiled Laura behaves more horridly than even Simon's resentful wife, Carrie, could have imagined. Everyone's shifts in allegiance and emotion, evoked in family huddles and emergency telephone calls, provide convincing entertainment, but Trollope brings genuine depth to the picture by following Jack, Guy's teenage grandson, into and out of his first love affair, allowing the story of Jack's thrilled sexual awakening and its betrayal to unfold alongside the less innocent adult counterpart. Meanwhile, interference from Merrion's mother proves more significant than she intended it to be. These interwoven tales have unanticipated and highly satisfying conclusions, and this best-selling British author's American readers will be tickled along the way by Guy's observation, ''If we were Americans, we could tell each other we loved each other.''</p>
        <p>Abby Frucht</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
