<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Westchester; In White Plains, New Town Houses With a Twist</title>
    <meta content="09WCZO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sheltering the Homeless is Our Responsibility</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D61139F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Westchester; In White Plains, New Town Houses With a Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY McALEER VIZARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unusual 14-unit low- and moderate-income housing development on two White Plains, NY, sites is set to open; each town house in $2.5 million Sheltering the Homeless Is Our Responsibility development has two-bedroom rental apartment that must be rented by owner to homeless family; map; photo (In the Region/Westchester) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LONG-AWAITED ribbon-cutting ceremony was held on June 28 for an unusual 14-unit low-  and moderate-income housing development in a leafy suburban neighborhood not far from this city's downtown, capping an almost eight-year effort. The first residents -- including city employees and several formerly homeless families -- at the $2.5 million development, on two sites about five blocks apart, are expected to begin moving in later this month.</p>
        <p>At the larger of the two sites, 233 West Post Road, at Quinby Avenue, the finishing touches are being applied to two peak-roofed buildings on a half acre. The two buildings contain a total of four town houses. Each town house was sold for from $77,000 to $81,000, depending on small differences in size and configuration. Each is a two-bedroom, one-bath unit, on two floors, with a loft. And each has an additional two-bedroom, one-bath rental apartment that must be rented by the owner to a homeless family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LONG-AWAITED ribbon-cutting ceremony was held on June 28 for an unusual 14-unit low-  and moderate-income housing development in a leafy suburban neighborhood not far from this city's downtown, capping an almost eight-year effort. The first residents -- including city employees and several formerly homeless families -- at the $2.5 million development, on two sites about five blocks apart, are expected to begin moving in later this month.</p>
        <p>At the larger of the two sites, 233 West Post Road, at Quinby Avenue, the finishing touches are being applied to two peak-roofed buildings on a half acre. The two buildings contain a total of four town houses. Each town house was sold for from $77,000 to $81,000, depending on small differences in size and configuration. Each is a two-bedroom, one-bath unit, on two floors, with a loft. And each has an additional two-bedroom, one-bath rental apartment that must be rented by the owner to a homeless family.</p>
        <p>The ribbon-cutting took place at the other site, 19 Osborne Street, at Winthrop Avenue, which has a similar arrangement, similar design and similar rules -- but there are three town houses and accompanying apartments in one building.</p>
        <p>''There were 70 applicants for the seven town houses,'' said Richard Adelmann, president of Sheltering the Homeless Is Our Responsibility, a nonprofit group also known as SHORE that is developing the project.</p>
        <p>The group held a lottery last summer to whittle down the applicant list. ''We selected 10,'' Mr. Adelmann said, ''then looked over their financials, and several dropped out. Then we selected another 10, until we got the number that we needed.''</p>
        <p>To qualify, buyers had to earn no more than $47,150 -- 80 percent of Westchester County's median household income of $58,937. They also had to qualify for conventionally financed mortgages. Priority was given to city employees and residents. Some of the homeless families were selected from the county's shelters.</p>
        <p>''The renters are obliged to pay 30 percent of their income in rent, with a maximum possible rent of around $400,'' Mr. Adelmann said, adding that income includes housing allowances from social-service agencies. ''This works out to everyone's benefit. The homeless family gets the chance to get back on their feet in a nice new home in a nice neighborhood. And the town-house owner gets help with monthly expenses.''</p>
        <p>''Many of the renters would also qualify for federal Section 8 rent subsidies,'' Mr. Adelmann added, ''which are much less than the county now pays to keep them in shelters, which can be upward of $100 a day.''</p>
        <p>Sheryl Harris, a White Plains traffic-enforcement officer, bought one of the town houses on West Post Road, after having lived for many years in public housing with her four children. ''This is the first time that I've ever owned something myself,'' Ms. Harris said.</p>
        <p>She expects to move into her new two-bedroom town house at the end of the month. ''After the apartments we've been living in,'' Ms. Harris said, ''this is plenty of space.''</p>
        <p>At first, Morelda Ford, who bought a town house on Osborne Street, said she was frightened by the prospect of having to rent an apartment in her home to a homeless family. ''Then I tried to put myself in their place, and knew that I would want someone to give me a chance,'' Ms. Ford said. ''Being homeless could happen to anyone. When there was a fire in my building, I was homeless for a night.''</p>
        <p>Each owner was allowed to choose among three families selected by the developer. Ms. Ford said that the tenant she selected is a single mother with two children who has been living in a homeless shelter in Ossining.</p>
        <p>''I'm a single mother too, so I felt comfortable with her,'' Ms. Ford said. ''We'll be living together in a way, but we also have separate entrances, so we can each maintain our privacy.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ford, a mental-health worker at New York Hospital in White Plains, said that the project came along at a propitious time. ''The building where I'm living now was just sold,'' she said. ''And they were going to double or maybe triple my rent. I feel really lucky to have found a way to own something of my own.'' Before being able to buy her town house, Ms. Ford said, she had to fill out many forms. ''I had to produce rent stubs for the past year, pay stubs, W-2's,'' she said. ''There were times I felt like canceling. Now I'm glad I didn't.''</p>
        <p>The project received $1.8 million in federal and state housing grants, $550,000 from charitable organizations, and a $195,000 construction loan from the city of White Plains, which also provided the Osborne Street building site.</p>
        <p>The almost eight-year gestation period for the project was longer than anticipated, Mr. Adelmann said. ''There have been seemingly endless city requests for construction changes,'' he said, ''and endless red tape that thwarted the development's progress.''</p>
        <p>Susan Hable, the city's deputy planning commissioner, said: ''White Plains's building codes are stringent, and I know that they added to their costs, but then we very rarely have any fires either. So in the end, I think it's worth it.''</p>
        <p>At first, SHORE had hoped to build a rental project, ''because that's where there's the greatest need,'' said Rosemarie Noonan, executive director of the Housing Action Council, a nonprofit organization that advises on low-  and moderate-income housing projects.</p>
        <p>''During the approvals process, the city asked that we include ownership units as well,'' Ms. Noonan said. ''I can understand the city's position because when people own something they tend to take better care of it. Most projects of this kind take about three to five years minimum. But having all these delays is not at all unusual.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hable said that the city's greatest concern was for the West Post Road site. ''Since it's such a busy road, we didn't want a lot of density there,'' she said. The site is adjacent to a condominium project, and a residence for the elderly is across the street.</p>
        <p>Because the city owned the Osborne site nearby, Ms. Hable said, ''we offered to include it in the project in order to spread out the units and for them to be able to include ownership units as well.'' Because of the city ownership, applicants for housing at that site had to be city residents, she said.</p>
        <p>T HE combination of buyers and renters in a single project has been tried in other places and really seems to work well,'' Ms. Hable said. ''But with the high costs of construction now, especially here in the Northeast, these low-density projects are very costly, and most developers won't do them.''</p>
        <p>She added, however, that the city is committed to finding other innovative ways to provide low-cost housing without disrupting neighborhoods. One of the latest methods is to encourage developers who are building market-rate rentals downtown to set aside a portion of their units for lower income tenants, Ms. Hable said.</p>
        <p>''One developer who plans to build 500 market-rate rentals near the Metro-North train station has agreed to set aside 30 of the 500 that are more affordable,'' Ms. Hable said. ''Another who plans to build 99 apartments will set aside seven.''</p>
        <p>The site with the 500 rentals is a proposed $140 million hotel-apartment complex at Main and Bank Streets to be developed by the Robert Martin Company of Elmsford, N.Y., and two other developers. The other proposal is for a site on Church Street to be put up by Pappas Enterprises, which is based in Boston.</p>
        <p>''In this way,'' Ms. Hable said, ''we hope that we can keep increasing our stock of  more affordable units in those neighborhoods that need them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
