<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style; Social Security</title>
    <meta content="09STYLET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spindler, Amy M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DC1139F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style; Social Security</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amy M. Spindler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spindler, Amy M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amy M Spindler article on fashion designers' new enchantment with young New York socialites, who have replaced movie starlets as their muses; photos of fashions for Park Avenue Princesses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would be impossible to deconstruct fashion designers' enchantment with the latest minted icon, the Park Avenue Princess, without dwelling for a moment on the utter disenchantment with the last iconic figure championed: the movie starlet.</p>
        <p>No sooner had designers canonized the indie goddesses (and Oscar nominees) Gwyneth Paltrow, Julianne Moore, Chlo Sevigny and Kristin Scott Thomas than those icons began shilling away in fashion ads. How can a starlet be your muse when she's selling someone else's clutch? Icons are by definition untouchable; how can a star be untouchable and bought?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would be impossible to deconstruct fashion designers' enchantment with the latest minted icon, the Park Avenue Princess, without dwelling for a moment on the utter disenchantment with the last iconic figure championed: the movie starlet.</p>
        <p>No sooner had designers canonized the indie goddesses (and Oscar nominees) Gwyneth Paltrow, Julianne Moore, Chlo Sevigny and Kristin Scott Thomas than those icons began shilling away in fashion ads. How can a starlet be your muse when she's selling someone else's clutch? Icons are by definition untouchable; how can a star be untouchable and bought?</p>
        <p>Then, a new kind of bribery began to emerge: designers paying celebrity stylists outright to get the stars into their clothes. Celebrities-cum-handbag peddlers began looking less like muses and more like hired help. There are, after all, only so many products a celebrity can push before her endorsement loses its clout.</p>
        <p>What a waste of celebrity, the most powerful currency in existence today. Imagine -- to borrow a word from John Lennon -- if that currency were being used to stop racism, or cancer, or wars, or even the worship of false idols, instead of using it to sell handbags, wristwatches, and cheap T-shirts. (Not to mention magazines on the newsstand.)</p>
        <p>Time and again, those designers who declared Park Avenue women to be their inspiration cited grim West Coast style as their reason for expunging starlets from their dreamscape. And the big selling point for the Park Avenue Princess is that, unlike her West Coast counterpart, she picks out her own clothes.</p>
        <p>''I think at a certain point it's sort of, oh, my God, I can't look at another person who went to a stylist and did themselves up,'' says Michael Kors, who championed Park Avenue as fashion's new ground zero in his New York collection. ''There's a backlash even in L.A,'' he continues. ''Now even a starlet wants to look like she lives the life, even if she just landed in her cash.'' He calls it the 50's meets the 80's -- because the new Park Avenue Princesses are groomed and dressed like kept wives, but they work for a living.</p>
        <p>Some of the Princesses have let it be known that they feel that the visions they've inspired on the runway are caricatures at best. But fashion relies on more stereotypes than a stand-up comic in the Catskills. The gold lame coats, the pieced geometric furs, the exploded herringbones with fur collars -- it's a fantasy of Park Avenue life, the same way that satin gowns and diamonds are a fantasy of a starlet's regular evening out.</p>
        <p>''What's going on in fashion is a lot more than who's wearing what down the red carpet,'' says Josh Patner, of Tuleh's design team, over a retro lunch of vodka gimlets. ''These Park Avenue women are wearing fashion every day. It's the way they present themselves for life.'' In other words, it's not the biggest night of the year in New York when someone pretty with a little money and talent puts on an evening gown and has her hair done. ''It's New York glamour as opposed to Hollywood glamour. It's the resurgence of New York as a fashion center and the resurgence of New York women as style makers. They live the life. It's not some stylist's fantasy.''</p>
        <p>There is something about actually being paid to wear clothes that sends a shiver down a New York client's back. Isn't that, after all, what models are for? But an astonishing number of Academy Award contenders -- one presumes serious actors being considered for the greatest honor their peers bestow -- are far from fearful at being mistaken for nothing but a pretty face. Remember when former models like Jessica Lange worked so hard to distance themselves from such a vacuous profession? The new generation is embracing the vacuum. And then offering to sell it!</p>
        <p>The Academy Awards are starting to look like the opening of a trade fair in Las Vegas, thanks in no small part to the efforts of the so-called celebrity stylists, manipulating greedy girls who refuse to just pay for their gowns. Here they are, young stars whose only asset is their image, and they're jeopardizing it all for the price of a dress. And then using it to sell a handbag! Paltrow has a contract to shill, something that a star who took home an Oscar used to slink away to Japan to do.</p>
        <p>Such cheap behavior, needless to say, would not get publicized on Park Avenue. Except if Dominick Dunne happens to be around to do the chronicling.</p>
        <p>In fact, in Dunne's ''An Inconvenient Woman'' (1990), when a well-bred East Coast socialite finds herself entertaining in Los Angeles, she makes a point never to ask the movie crowd around. Among other reasons, her distaste for ''movie people'' is that they don't talk about ''things'' -- they only talk about ''what's going on on the set, which is so boring, don't you think?''</p>
        <p>A big part of East Coast chic has always been the ability to hold forth on a variety of topics, aided by the fact that unlike Los Angeles, New York is more than a one-industry town, and one of the biggest industries is fashion. Patrick McCarthy, the social arbiter and editorial director of W, told Brill's Content in March: ''The movie industry has nothing on the fashion industry. The movie business is dull, dull, dull.''</p>
        <p>Only a few years ago, when a designer was asked for his inspiration, he would drum up a litany of West Coast women living and dead. These days the only star designers can stomach seems to be Sarah Jessica Parker, and she's as much a Manhattanite as Jerry Seinfeld, which is why she's one of the only actresses on television ever to carry a Louis Vuitton bag. Is it any wonder that the Metropolitan Museum of Art's next Costume Institute show will feature the consummate East Coast icon, Jacqueline Onassis?</p>
        <p>Since the media world is Manhattan-centric, and no one is more so than the editors of major fashion magazines, the rise of the Park Avenue Princess as a glossy page darling is as conniving as it is contrived. But no doubt it's refreshing to deal with women who buy the clothes they like, have their own jewels (so they don't try to make off with the borrowed ones on the set) and don't arrive with a publicist in tow.</p>
        <p>But lacking a publicist hasn't led to a lack of overexposure. One old society dame intones of the younger set: ''I know nothing about them. All I know is I see their pictures in the paper.'' Long pause. ''Too often.''</p>
        <p>It seems like only yesterday we were saying that about the movie stars they were supposed to replace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
