<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Credit Comes At a Price; The Criticism Is Free</title>
    <meta content="09VIEW$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DC1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Credit Comes At a Price; The Criticism Is Free</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard W Stevenson Economic View column notes central banks in US, Europe and Japan face difficult decisions about whether to raise interest rates; predicts strategies they pursue over remainder of year could have big impact in global economic outlook; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS is a tale of three central banks. All face tough choices about whether to raise interest rates, and the strategies they pursue over the remainder of this year could have a big effect on the global economic outlook.</p>
        <p>* After pushing its benchmark lending rate down to just a notch above zero in an effort to resuscitate the Japanese economy, the Bank of Japan is hinting that it will soon tighten monetary policy, even though many analysts think that deflation is still a greater risk than inflation, and that the financial system needs more money and credit, not less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS is a tale of three central banks. All face tough choices about whether to raise interest rates, and the strategies they pursue over the remainder of this year could have a big effect on the global economic outlook.</p>
        <p>* After pushing its benchmark lending rate down to just a notch above zero in an effort to resuscitate the Japanese economy, the Bank of Japan is hinting that it will soon tighten monetary policy, even though many analysts think that deflation is still a greater risk than inflation, and that the financial system needs more money and credit, not less.</p>
        <p>* With an economic upswing under way across Europe, the European Central Bank is likely to continue raising rates this year. But the 11 nations sharing a common monetary policy are running at different economic speeds and are not, at the moment, good candidates for a one-size-fits-all interest rate prescription.</p>
        <p>* In the United States, six interest rate increases over the last year are beginning to have their intended effect, as illustrated by Friday's report from the Labor Department showing a slowdown in the rate of job creation. But there is considerable uncertainty and debate within the Federal Reserve about how much more tightening, if any, will be necessary to squelch inflation pressures without putting the long expansion at risk.</p>
        <p>Of the three major central banks, the Bank of Japan faces the most dire situation and the most second-guessing.</p>
        <p>Masaru Hayami, the central bank's governor, has signaled that he would like to bring to an end what he considers an emergency period of exceptionally low interest rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayami's rationale seems to be twofold: that higher rates would force Japanese industry to stop relying on cheap money for survival and get on with the painful business of restructuring itself, and that moving rates up now, when the economy is showing tentative signs of life, would give the Bank of Japan the ability to cut them again if the economy goes back into a swoon.</p>
        <p>But his approach is viewed skeptically even in his own government's finance ministry. And many economists say Japan's problems are not linked so much to interest rates -- the cost of money -- but rather to a lack of available money and credit at any price.</p>
        <p>According to Carl B. Weinberg, chief economist at High Frequency Economics, a consulting firm in Valhalla, N.Y., bank credit in Japan contracted 4.7 percent in the 12 months ended in May, reflecting the dead weight of bad loans held by lenders and the continued decline in the value of assets that borrowers can use as collateral.</p>
        <p>Rather than raising rates, he and other critics say, the Bank of Japan would do better to grease the wheels of the financial system, perhaps by buying bad loans from banks, to spur new lending and get the economy humming again.</p>
        <p>In Europe, the head of the new central bank, Wim Duisenberg, is facing the first big test of his institution's ability to weather the economic and political strains inherent in establishing a transnational institution to perform a function that has always been closely linked to national sovereignty.</p>
        <p>In one group of European countries, including Ireland, Spain and Finland, inflation is creeping up, putting pressure on the central bank to raise rates. But in another group, including Germany and France, the economic and political heavyweights at the European Union's core, inflation is low and unemployment remains stubbornly high, a combination that argues for stable or even lower rates.</p>
        <p>''This development raises the prospect that, over the next year, monetary policy will be trapped between the tightening needs of overheating countries and resistance to higher real rates from low-inflation ones,'' economists at Salomon Smith Barney said in a recent report.</p>
        <p>THE question in the United States is whether the slowdown in growth is enough to keep inflation under wraps.</p>
        <p>At the Fed's meeting in May, staff economists presented a forecast showing that growth would slow this year to around 3.5 percent, from a 5.5 percent rate in the first quarter. But the same forecast projected that core price inflation -- which excludes volatile food and energy prices -- would ''rise noticeably'' this year.</p>
        <p>So both inflation hawks and doves at the Fed have plenty of ammunition as they debate whether to raise rates again. It may be some consolation to Alan Greenspan as he tries to sort it all out that his fellow central bankers around the world are not having it any easier.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
