<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sense of What Brings Us Together</title>
    <meta content="09WINT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Podeswa, Jeremy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frieberg, Camelia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkam, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Volter, Philippe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bussieres, Pascale</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winters, Laura</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Five Senses, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DA1039F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sense of What Brings Us Together</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA WINTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winters, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Winters article on Canadian director Jeremy Podeswa, who recalls meeting between producer Camelia Frieberg and horticulturalist Larry Burkam, who eventually married; event served as inspiration for his new feature film, The Five Senses, starring Philippe Volter and Pascale Bussieres; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the fall of 1994, the Canadian director Jeremy Podeswa and his producer Camelia Frieberg were heading down the West Coast to promote Mr. Podeswa's first film, ''Eclipse.'' They stopped to see a woman whom Ms. Frieberg had met when she was a teenager on vacation; the two women had agreed, as a lark, to meet again in 20 years' time.</p>
        <p>During the visit, they met the horticulturalist Larry Burkam, who was working on the woman's property, and they all ended up having dinner. ''And you could just see the lightning bolts over the table,'' Mr. Podeswa recalled recently. ''When we got back to the hotel that night, I looked at Camelia and said, 'You know, I have the funniest feeling that you're going to marry that guy.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the fall of 1994, the Canadian director Jeremy Podeswa and his producer Camelia Frieberg were heading down the West Coast to promote Mr. Podeswa's first film, ''Eclipse.'' They stopped to see a woman whom Ms. Frieberg had met when she was a teenager on vacation; the two women had agreed, as a lark, to meet again in 20 years' time.</p>
        <p>During the visit, they met the horticulturalist Larry Burkam, who was working on the woman's property, and they all ended up having dinner. ''And you could just see the lightning bolts over the table,'' Mr. Podeswa recalled recently. ''When we got back to the hotel that night, I looked at Camelia and said, 'You know, I have the funniest feeling that you're going to marry that guy.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Frieberg did, indeed, marry Mr. Burkam, and this random encounter -- like something out of an Eric Rohmer film -- became one of the inspirations for Mr. Podeswa's second feature, ''The Five Senses,'' which opens on Friday and which traces the tangled relations among a group of people in Toronto.</p>
        <p>''What I witnessed with Camelia got me going on the idea of destiny and what brings people together,'' Mr. Podeswa said when he was in New York recently. ''We tend to lead our lives in a very intellectual way -- but, in fact, our lives are irrational and there are things we can't explain. I wanted to make a film about people who are coming to understand those kinds of things.''</p>
        <p>The 38-year-old Mr. Podeswa, who is warm and bitingly articulate, has seen his own share of life's eccentricities. He struggled for years in Canada to find financing for his feature films while he worked as a journalist, a film publicist and an assistant film editor. Though Mr. Podeswa is relatively unknown in this country, his profile in Canada and abroad has changed dramatically with ''The Five Senses'': the film was a hit at both the Cannes and Toronto International Film Festivals, was sold in more than 40 countries and earned Mr. Podeswa the Genie Award (Canada's version of the Academy Award) for best director last January.</p>
        <p>Diane Ackerman's 1990 book, ''A Natural History of the Senses,'' was the direct impetus for the film. ''I loved Ackerman's enthusiasm for how the senses enhance our lives,'' Mr. Podeswa said. ''We tend to take our senses for granted, just as we can take other people for granted. So I began to write about these characters who are surrounded by a wealth of possibilities, and yet they all feel that there is something missing.''</p>
        <p>Each of Mr. Podeswa's five main characters in ''The Five Senses'' is linked thematically to a particular sense. For hearing, there's an eye doctor (Philippe Volter) who is going deaf; for taste, there's a cake-maker (Mary-Louise Parker) whose gorgeous but bland cakes only hint at her deeper emotional blockage. Smell is represented by a bisexual housecleaner (Daniel MacIvor) who is convinced that love has its own distinct scent. Touch is symbolized by a massage therapist (Gabrielle Rose), who can soothe strangers but who is unable to reach her teenage daughter (Nadia Litz), a budding voyeur who, in turn, represents sight.</p>
        <p>The disappearance of a little girl draws together these interlocking stories. Her mother's (Molly Parker) desperate search for the child galvanizes the other characters and throws into relief their prickly, fervent attempts to connect with other people.</p>
        <p>But the film also has a light touch in scenes such as the one where Mr. MacIvor's and Mary-Louise Parker's characters avidly gossip in a car. Their mutual list of romantic no-no's includes ''never fall in love with someone who's too good looking'' and ''never fall in love with someone who lives more than a bus ride away.''</p>
        <p>MR. PODESWA has always been interested in the quest for intimacy, whether it be through romance, friendship or family. Though his films are not directly autobiographical, he calls each one ''a snapshot of my psyche at a particular time.''</p>
        <p>He is one of the generation of Canadian filmmakers that includes Atom Egoyan, Patricia Rozema and Don McKellar, among others. ''Jeremy was an inspiration to me in the 1980's because of a supremely assured short film he did called 'David Roche Talks to You about Love,' '' said Mr. Egoyan, on the telephone from Toronto.</p>
        <p>He continued: ''But Jeremy had a long apprenticeship. He went to the American Film Institute, which I think gave him a different outlook. As Canadians, we're very aware of making our films in contrast to a dominant American cinema.'' He laughed. ''Jeremy was one of the few who spent time in the belly of the beast, so to speak, and then came back.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Podeswa spent a year in Los Angeles after graduating in 1984 from Ryerson Polytechnical Institute in Toronto. ''It really demystified the studio system for me,'' he said. ''But I also discovered that there were films I wanted to make that I didn't think could be made in that system. Canadian filmmakers tend to use film as a form of personal expression, to say something that is personal and idiosyncratic.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Podeswa's strongest signature as a director is his insistence on pluralism, whether it be the range of languages spoken by his characters or the variety of sexual relationships he depicts. ''Eclipse,'' Mr. Podeswa's first feature (1995), was inspired by Arthur Schnitzler's play ''La Ronde'' and featured a gallery of lonely, questing characters who go from partner to partner. ''The Five Senses'' also portrays both gay and heterosexual relationships without judgment or stereotype.</p>
        <p>''It's very important for me to deal with sexuality in a non-hierarchical way,'' Mr. Podeswa said. ''I always resented, when I was younger, seeing films where the only gay character would be the best friend, or the kooky neighbor. I wanted to move those stories into the center and give them equal weight with the other stories.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Podeswa's producer, Ms. Frieberg, describes him as ''interested in the diversity of experience, be it sexual or ethnic.'' But his goal is not polemics, but, rather, universality -- to show how love and longing cut a swath through everyone's life.</p>
        <p>Several factors have shaped Mr. Podeswa's outlook -- ''being gay, being Jewish and a first-generation Canadian,'' he said. ''My parents are both immigrants and my father is a Holocaust survivor. This background makes you very aware of what it feels like to be an outsider. But I think it's also made me sensitive to other people's issues as well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Podeswa's father, who is from Poland, survived concentration camps and emigrated to Toronto after the war, where he met Mr. Podeswa's mother, who had come there from England. Both Mr. Podeswa's father and his brother are painters, and he himself grew up, he says, addicted to movies.</p>
        <p>After attending the American Film Institute, he moved back to Toronto determined to start making films. But a musical feature that he was planning fell through, and it took him considerable time to finance ''Eclipse,'' and then, in turn, ''The Five Senses.''</p>
        <p>WHEN asked why it took so long, Mr. Podeswa said, '' 'Eclipse' was a multi-character tale with an unconventional story. And 'The Five Senses' was even more ambitious. But feature film funding has also really dried up in Canada. The government film funding agencies have quite limited resources now, so they can't really support that many movies a year.''</p>
        <p>What got Mr. Podeswa through was what he calls his ''monomaniacal'' nature: ''I'm like a dog with a bone,'' he said. ''I wouldn't let go.'' But his persistence seems to have paid off. He now has a first-look deal with Alliance Atlantis, an independent distribution and production company and one of the principal backers of ''The Five Senses,'' and he is set to adapt and direct Anne Michaels's acclaimed novel, ''Fugitive Pieces,'' about the legacy of the Holocaust, for the Toronto-based Serendipity Point Films. He is also adapting Catherine Bush's first novel, ''Minus Time,'' about the relationship between a young girl and her astronaut mother, for the screen.</p>
        <p>Hollywood is not out of the question, either, though his approach would no doubt be novel there. ''I remember at one point during the shoot, we disagreed about something and he stopped and said, 'Let's talk about this,' '' Mary-Louise Parker recalled. ''There wasn't that feeling which happens so often of 'just get the shot and move on.' ''</p>
        <p>Emotional truth is Mr. Podeswa's priority. For him, ''The Five Senses'' is his most affirmative film. ''I had done a film about people who were unfulfilled and afraid,'' he said, ''and I wanted to show people who were at the next stage, trying to engage with life.'' At the same time, he deplores what he calls ''the tyranny of happy endings.''</p>
        <p>''Hollywood-style endings can sometimes make an audience feel really bitter,'' he said with a laugh, ''because they start to think, 'Why can't my life be more like that?' I'd like, instead, for people to see themselves in my work. It's about the reality -- rather than the fantasy -- of how we live now.''</p>
        <p>FILM Laura Winters, a writer based in New York, writes about the arts here and abroad.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Winters, a writer based in New York, writes about the arts here and abroad.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
