<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Madrid, There's No Such Thing As Too Much Ham</title>
    <meta content="09FRUG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ham</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madrid (Spain)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mclane, Daisann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain/Madrid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D61239F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Madrid, There's No Such Thing As Too Much Ham</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAISANN McLANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mclane, Daisann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daisann McLane Frugal Traveler column on return trip to Madrid, Spain, to enjoy local salt-cured ham called jamon serrano; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY first stop in Madrid, minutes after hopping off the bus from the airport, was the museum. No, not the Prado, but the Museum of Ham. The Museo del Jamon is the largest of several chains of delicatessen-lunch spots scattered throughout Madrid (the competing chains are called the Ham Palace, the House of Ham and Mr. Ham). The decor of these emporiums is straightforward: Formica counters, glass cases filled with cheese, chorizo and salchichones (spicy salamis) and, overhead, close to a thousand salty cured carcasses suspended from the ceiling by the hoof, like chandeliers.</p>
        <p>Madrilenos eat their ham, sliced into the thinnest of slivers on a plate, or curled between small loaves of dry, crusty bread, for breakfast, lunch, dinner and in between. I discovered the deliciousness of jamon serrano on my first trip to Madrid 12 years ago. Made from a special breed of white mountain pig and air-cured for nine months according to centuries-old traditions, the ham is like a mouthful of Spain itself. Long after I'd returned from Madrid -- when it finally became legal to import jamon serrano to the United States -- the salty, intensely rich meat was enough to send me back to the Gran Via, the Plaza de Toros, the Prado. It was a reverie I couldn't afford to indulge in very often, for the ham that hangs from every deli rafter in Madrid and costs $2 a plate sits on a high shelf at the Manhattan purveyor Dean &amp; Deluca, priced at a hefty $15 a pound.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY first stop in Madrid, minutes after hopping off the bus from the airport, was the museum. No, not the Prado, but the Museum of Ham. The Museo del Jamon is the largest of several chains of delicatessen-lunch spots scattered throughout Madrid (the competing chains are called the Ham Palace, the House of Ham and Mr. Ham). The decor of these emporiums is straightforward: Formica counters, glass cases filled with cheese, chorizo and salchichones (spicy salamis) and, overhead, close to a thousand salty cured carcasses suspended from the ceiling by the hoof, like chandeliers.</p>
        <p>Madrilenos eat their ham, sliced into the thinnest of slivers on a plate, or curled between small loaves of dry, crusty bread, for breakfast, lunch, dinner and in between. I discovered the deliciousness of jamon serrano on my first trip to Madrid 12 years ago. Made from a special breed of white mountain pig and air-cured for nine months according to centuries-old traditions, the ham is like a mouthful of Spain itself. Long after I'd returned from Madrid -- when it finally became legal to import jamon serrano to the United States -- the salty, intensely rich meat was enough to send me back to the Gran Via, the Plaza de Toros, the Prado. It was a reverie I couldn't afford to indulge in very often, for the ham that hangs from every deli rafter in Madrid and costs $2 a plate sits on a high shelf at the Manhattan purveyor Dean &amp; Deluca, priced at a hefty $15 a pound.</p>
        <p>I'm not so ham-crazy that I'd cross the Atlantic just for a taste. But jamon was certainly on my mind when I stumbled across a special discount fare to Madrid on Iberia Airlines' Web site last April.</p>
        <p>Spring is when air fares to Europe start their warm-weather climb into the stratosphere, but here was a round-trip ticket to Madrid from Kennedy Airport in New York for $421, including tax. I called the Iberia Airlines office in the United States and secured reservations for late April to mid-May, and bought an additional round-trip ticket to the Canary Islands. (The package came to $575.) I'd spend my first six days in Madrid, and I could already taste them.</p>
        <p>At 11 a.m. my room at the Hotel Paris ($55 a night), which I'd booked over the phone before my departure, wasn't ready. And so I dropped my bags there and headed, fresh from a full flight and running on no sleep, into the Museo del Jamon around the corner. The large room was redolent of the  cured meat, mingled with beer and cheese, and the long, undulating counter was elbow-to-elbow with the early lunch crowd. There weren't any tables, and I really needed to sit down. And so I walked back out to the street and noticed a less frenetic spot across the street, La Taurina, that had a counter and tables.</p>
        <p>La Taurina's motto, emblazoned on its menu, was ''Ambiente Taurino'' -- bullfight atmosphere. They weren't kidding. The place was like a Hard Rock Cafe of bullfighting. Around the room hung about 30 huge stuffed bull heads, real ones. Glass cases displayed the pink capes and trajes de luces (sequined suits) of famous matadors. Behind the bar, several tiled murals portrayed bullfighters in action. The remaining wall space featured vintage photographs of dramatic moments in the ring.</p>
        <p>I seated myself under several images of bulls charging unfortunate toreros, and savored my first $2 plate of ham.</p>
        <p>Memories of the fun I had on my earlier trip to Madrid came flooding back -- they involved ham-snacking, wine-drinking, tapas-grazing, and, most of all, enjoying the bonhomie of Madrilenos snacking alongside me at the various bars I frequented past the midnight hour. To really enjoy Madrid takes a bit of digging and patience; it isn't a city of obvious charms like Paris or London. Madrid was born of political expediency. In order to bind the diverse regions of Spain into a nation, in 1561, King Felipe II created a capital in the middle of the Iberian peninsula, on a desolate plateau whose most significant advantage was that it was roughly equidistant from every other part of the realm.</p>
        <p>As a result, Madrid lacks the box-office punch of many world capitals. It has no ancient cathedrals, no harbor, no impressive medieval architecture or staggeringly beautiful skyscrapers. It's also low on the scenic scale, without waterways, mountains or beaches. But Madrid's role as Spain's center makes it a powerhouse attraction in other ways -- the arts, for instance. In Madrid it's possible to see in a single day many of the greatest Spanish paintings.. Before the trip I had made a quick sweep through the listings on the Web site of the first-rate Madrid newspaper, El Pais, and come up with more than a dozen performances, events, films, concerts and exhibits I wanted to see -- at prices about half to two-thirds what events like these would cost in New York. Perhaps if Madrid looked more like a picture postcard it would not be one of the most affordable large cities in Europe. The room without bath that costs $80 a night in London will set you back only about $28 in Madrid. For my $55, at the Hotel Paris in the center of the city, the Puerta del Sol, I had a large bathroom with shower and bidet, a double bed, and even a little balcony. Every morning, I walked down a grand red-carpeted staircase to the breakfast room where a light buffet of bread, croissants and coffee was served gratis (although I usually skipped it and ducked around the corner to La Taurina, for morning ham).</p>
        <p>Madrid, like all of Spain, has  a well-organized lodging network  of small, usually family-run, guest houses called hostals. So numerous are the hostals with their little blue ''H'' signs in central Madrid that I didn't think twice about booking only two nights at the Hotel Paris in advance. I figured I'd arrive, settle in, and then look for someplace even cheaper to move into. What I didn't factor into my calculation was that my arrival coincided with the beginning of a Spanish long-weekend holiday, the First of May. Early on my second morning I started the rounds of the hostals in the old section of Madrid, near the best tapas bars and restaurants. To my astonishment, every door I knocked upon was answered by a proprietor with the single word: ''Completo'' -- full up.</p>
        <p>I'd anticipated spending an hour finding a new place -- instead, I was knocking on doors until past lunchtime. Finally, as I started to panic, I got lucky at the Hostal Rifer, on the fourth floor of a building overlooking the calle Mayor near the Puerta del Sol. The room smelled a bit damp (the shower and sink were next to the double bed), and the toilet was down the hall, but it was clean enough, cheap enough ($26) and, best of all, right next door to another branch of the Museo del Jamon. I booked it for three nights, and gave the landlady a deposit to hold it until the next day, when I moved in.</p>
        <p>There's a traveler's grail that one follows in Madrid, and its first stop is the Prado. It was more crowded than it was when I visited last time (there's an X-ray check on both bags and people at the entrance that slows things to a crawl during busy times), but the Velazquez paintings that form the heart of the collection seemed even more staggering than on my first viewing. I unwound from the Prado with a walk through the adjacent botanical gardens, where tulips were in bloom, then paid a visit to Picasso's ''Guernica,'' and the rest of the modern Spanish painting collection at the Museo Reina Sofia.</p>
        <p>ON Sunday I strolled from the Rifer to the Plaza Mayor, and then followed the crowds down to the neighborhood called Lavapies, where the Rastro flea market is held. The crowd of browsers got so thick it hardly moved, and so I ducked into a subway -- Madrid has an excellent one, and a 10-pass ticket is only around $10 -- and emerged on the Gran Via, Madrid's Broadway. At the Teatro Coliseo I bought one of the hottest tickets in town for around $15, a center seat for the new dance extravaganza performed and choreographed by Joaquin Cortes, a classically trained flamenco dancer.</p>
        <p>The dancer, who affects a logo and attitude similar to those of the rock star Prince, made his first appearance onstage cross-dressed as a female flamenco dancer in a ruffled skirt with a 30-foot train. That was the tamest point of an amazing two hours of music and dance that managed to quote every Spanish cultural icon, from flamenco to gypsies to bullfighting, before switching gears and ending with a Cuban rumba.</p>
        <p>Cortes put me in the mood for a Madrid Night on the Town. I headed straight for the Calle Echegaray, a narrow street not far from the Prado that's lined with little bars and restaurants. I was thrilled to find that the sherry bar where I learned to tell the difference between a fino and a manzanilla 12 years ago was still there. Nothing seemed to have altered inside the dark, narrow bar of La Venencia. Even the dust on the barrels appeared intact.</p>
        <p>The bartender handed me a fino and a small dish of perfectly fresh green olives, and marked my bill, as is the custom there, in chalk on the bar. Almost immediately, Raul, a fellow to my left, began chatting to me about the relative pluses and mi nuses of manzanilla and amontillado sherry. Raul, as it turned out, had strong opinions about sherry, wine, ham and Spanish cheese. Not surprisingly, he was a Madrid native. He expounded at length to me, and to his companions, Ricardo and Jose, who were visiting from Argentina.</p>
        <p>I mentioned Spanish ham, and Raul got excited. Had I tasted jamon iberico? I wasn't sure. ''It's the ham with the black hoof,'' he said. ''It is the best of Spain. You must try it!'' Immediately, he paid for all of our sherries and led us down the block to a tapas bar, La Trucha.</p>
        <p>At the jam-packed La Trucha, the four of us squeezed up to the counter and savored slice upon slice of a ham that was saltier, drier and funkier than the serrano I knew. It went smashingly well with the glass of velvety red wine from the Ribera del Duero region that Raul had ordered. Under the influence of wine and ham, Jose opened up, whispering to me that this was a special occasion -- Raul and Ricardo were on their first date. They'd met on the Internet, but never before in person. He himself was along, he joked, ''in case Raul turned out to be a serial killer.'' And I'd gotten swept along in the general drama, which was becoming more like a Pedro Almodovar movie every minute, as Raul gestured expansively and ordered more delicacies, like codfish liver spread on toast points.</p>
        <p>A Madrileno, and a gentleman, he would not let me pay for anything.</p>
        <p>We moved on to another bar, and then another. I was wobbling on  the cobblestones. The problem with roller-coaster Madrid nights like this is figuring out how to end them. To leave is to invite sadness, break  the party mood, lose the sparkling moment when strangers become friends. The words of farewell on such occasions are crucial. And fortunately the right ones popped into my head the instant I needed them. ''I'll always remember this night, Raul. And I will never forget this ham.''</p>
        <p>The bottom line: tapas and ham</p>
        <p>I spent $62 a day on food, lodging, local transport and activities during my six days in Madrid in April and May. The peseta was falling when I was there. I got an exchange rate of about 183 to the dollar.</p>
        <p>Hotels</p>
        <p>The Hotel Paris, Alcala 2, (34) 91-521-6491, fax (34) 91-531-0188), a grand fin de siecle building a bit threadbare at the edges, is centrally situated and near a subway stop. My room, clean and a decent size, had a tiny balcony, good light, a double bed and a big bathroom with lots of hot water, a shower and a bidet. The price of $55 a night included a Continental breakfast.</p>
        <p>The Hostal Rifer (Calle Mayor 5, fourth floor, (34) 91-532-3197) had some drawbacks. There was no toilet in the large room with double bed (the bathroom was down the hall). The shower, which was in the bedroom, wasn't fully enclosed, and dampness lingered for hours every time I showered. Hot water was spotty, and noise drifted up from the lively street below. The price per night was $26; no breakfast is served.</p>
        <p>The more upscale Hostal Don Diego, Velazquez 45, (34) 91-435-0760, is in the Salamanca district, Madrid's version of the Upper East Side. Because I was the last guest to check in that day I was given a huge triple room with separate bathroom and an enormous tub for the price of a single -- $54. The Don Diego is quietly classy, and well placed for shopping trips, but the tapas bars are too far away to reach on foot at night.</p>
        <p>Food</p>
        <p>Jamon serrano at El Museo del Jamon, was around $2 a plate. The Museo has branches all over Madrid, but the one I visited is at Carretera San Jeronimo 6.</p>
        <p>Across the street from El Museo, La Taurina, San Jeronimo 5, serves ham, beer, cheese, coffee, and wine. A plate of ham was around $2.50.</p>
        <p>La Venencia, Calle Echegaray 7, (34) 91-429-7313, serves sherry -- fino, manzanilla, amontillado and oloroso -- from large wooden casks, along with fresh olives, smoked trout and cheese plates. A glass of sherry is around $1, and the plates range from $1.50 to $4.</p>
        <p>El Lacon, one of a cluster of tapas bars and restaurants on Calle Manuel Fernandez y Gonzalez (they're at number 8) has an excellent selection of Spanish wines to go with their specialties like mushrooms sauteed in garlic sauce, and caldo gallego (a hearty bean soup). A dinner of soup, two tapas and two glasses of wine cost around $10.</p>
        <p>La Trucha, Manuel Fernandez y Gonzalez 3, down the street from El Lacon, is a Madrid institution -- always crowded and filled with local characters. There, I ate unusual tapas like higado de bacalao -- a pate made from codfish liver -- and I sampled the rich jamon iberico, which is cured for more than two years. Two glasses of wine and a large plate of ham and cheese was around $10.</p>
        <p>One night I sat down to a proper restaurant meal at El Inti de Oro, (34) 91-429-6703, Ventura de la Vega 12, a Peruvian restaurant. My chicken tamale baked in cornmeal and my merluza (cod) in shrimp sauce came to $14 with wine.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>There's a discounted pass available that allows entry into three of Madrid's most popular museums, the Reina Sofia, the Prado and the Thyssen-Bornemisza. It's available at the admission desks of all three and costs $7, a saving of about $5 over single admissions. The Prado is closed on Monday, the Reina Sofia is closed on Tuesday, and admission to both is free after 2:30 p.m. Saturday, and all day Sunday. But lines to enter the museums were especially long at these times.</p>
        <p>DAISANN McLANE</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
