<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With AT&amp;T at the Brink, Pressures Rise at the Top</title>
    <meta content="09ATTT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, C Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DB1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With AT&amp;T at the Brink, Pressures Rise at the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T chairman C Michael Armstrong is on defensive for first time since he took charge of company in 1997; investor response to company's disappointing performance and scaled-back growth forecast has been swift and harsh; Armstrong's bid to transform company by offering combined television, Internet-access and telephone service over cable television lines has yet to pay off; photos, graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was the evening of Monday, May 1, and C. Michael Armstrong, the chairman of AT&amp;T, needed help.</p>
        <p>Huddled in a conference room at the company's headquarters in Basking Ridge, N.J., with key members of his executive team, Mr. Armstrong said he turned for advice to two Wall Street analysts, later identified by people close to the meeting as Frank J. Governali of Goldman, Sachs and Jack Grubman of Salomon Smith Barney. Mr. Armstrong asked the two just how he should tell investors that some of AT&amp;T's core businesses had stumbled. At least as important, Mr. Armstrong also wanted their assessment of how AT&amp;T's shares, one of the nation's most widely held stocks, would react to the bad news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was the evening of Monday, May 1, and C. Michael Armstrong, the chairman of AT&amp;T, needed help.</p>
        <p>Huddled in a conference room at the company's headquarters in Basking Ridge, N.J., with key members of his executive team, Mr. Armstrong said he turned for advice to two Wall Street analysts, later identified by people close to the meeting as Frank J. Governali of Goldman, Sachs and Jack Grubman of Salomon Smith Barney. Mr. Armstrong asked the two just how he should tell investors that some of AT&amp;T's core businesses had stumbled. At least as important, Mr. Armstrong also wanted their assessment of how AT&amp;T's shares, one of the nation's most widely held stocks, would react to the bad news.</p>
        <p>''The analysts came in and they said, 'Well, look, what you have to do is just put this on the table, tell it like you're going to tell it,' '' Mr. Armstrong recounted in an interview late last month. '' 'You're being forthright, you're talking about something in the future.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Governali and Mr. Grubman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>''Their bottom line,'' Mr. Armstrong added, ''was, 'You'll probably take a four- to seven- point hit and then bounce back, for a three- to five-point problem.' That's what their judgment was to me.''</p>
        <p>It did not work out that way.</p>
        <p>The next morning, AT&amp;T dropped its bomb on the company's investors. AT&amp;T said its operations would grow more slowly and earn less this year than the company had previously led the market to expect. AT&amp;T added that its core consumer long-distance unit would shrink faster than expected. Worst of all, the company said that its unit that sells communications services to business customers, which had been one of its bastions of strength, would miss its previous growth target because it had dropped the ball with some of AT&amp;T's biggest accounts.</p>
        <p>The reaction was swift and harsh. The company's shares, which had closed that Monday at $49, skidded $7.0625, shaving more than $25 billion from AT&amp;T's market value. And the shares did not bounce back. They continued to slide the next day. And the day after that. And the day after that.</p>
        <p>The pain continues. AT&amp;T's shares, which traded above $60 as recently as late March, closed on Friday at $33.25.</p>
        <p>But it is not just AT&amp;T's shares that are feeling the burn. For the first time since he took over as chairman in the fall of 1997, Mr. Armstrong himself is on the defensive. His bet-the-company vision to transform AT&amp;T by delivering a package of interactive digital television, high-speed cyberspace access and local telephone service over cable television lines is still largely just that, a vision.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the core long-distance operations that he was counting on to avoid trouble while the company focused on the cable strategy have found it instead. Even AT&amp;T's vaunted offering of a new stock meant to track its fast-growing wireless operation has been a disappointment. Mediocre would be a charitable description of its performance, at least for investors who bought it at the offering price of $29.50 a share. On Friday, the stock closed at $25.4375.</p>
        <p>With the Bell local phone giants finally moving in force into the $80 billion long-distance market, the outlook in AT&amp;T's core consumer business is not likely to improve anytime soon. With the company's market value at about $125 billion -- versus, say, the $96 billion that AT&amp;T spent to acquire the Tele-Communications Inc. and MediaOne cable television operations over the last two years -- a recurring theme in financial circles this summer has been that the company would be an attractive target for an unsolicited takeover and breakup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong does not appear to be in any danger of losing his job. Strategically, he appears to have done as fine a job as anyone could have expected, given the unenviable hand he was dealt. To survive, AT&amp;T had to transform itself from a lumbering, backward-looking long-distance behemoth into something new;  Mr. Armstrong's bold moves, especially in the cable arena, appear poised to do that.</p>
        <p>But tactically, he has not yet proved that he can execute on the broad range of small, unglamorous, nitty-gritty chores that are required to turn his visionary strategy into a concrete success. Time is running out, investors are losing patience, and AT&amp;T is on the edge.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, it's a little irrational, but I think people are just fed up,'' said one Wall Street analyst, on condition of anonymity. ''I know one fund manager who said: 'Don't talk to me about this stock; I'm dumping it. Call me in a year if things turn around.' ''</p>
        <p>A Shrinking Business</p>
        <p>In a year, it should be fairly clear whether Mr. Armstrong will deserve to be placed in the pantheon of great executives or instead be remembered as the man who valiantly tried to turn AT&amp;T from decades of inertia and failed.</p>
        <p>It was fear of that inertia's power that made the May 2 disclosures so damaging. The actual numbers were far from devastating -- a percentage-point change in outlook here, maybe two points over there. But it has been so long since AT&amp;T truly impressed investors with its performance -- years, for sure -- that the May warning raised fears that beneath Mr. Armstrong's beaming visage at the helm, this was still the same old sclerotic AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>About Mr. Armstrong himself, the warning raised an even more pointed concern: if he cannot mind the shop in AT&amp;T's core businesses, how can he be expected to succeed in the new ones?</p>
        <p>So how does Mr. Armstrong himself think he is doing?</p>
        <p>''I think that we're making some really sound progress,'' he said, with the unwavering, barrel-chested confidence that has become his trademark. ''I think a lot of the progress is masked by financials as a result of the declining voice business.''</p>
        <p>What the financials may have masked is AT&amp;T's belief that it will be delivering local phone service over cable lines to at least 400,000 households by year-end. And even in states where the company does not own cable systems, AT&amp;T is making inroads in local phone markets. In New York State, for instance, where Bell Atlantic has made a strong move in the long-distance arena, AT&amp;T has counterattacked by signing up more than 475,000 local phone users.</p>
        <p>In addition to phone service, the other parts of AT&amp;T's cable service are also developing. While interactive television is not yet a reality in the market, the company has about 300,000 cable modem users and expects that figure to top 700,000 by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''What gives me confidence to respond to that question rather than go look at the price of the stock and get depressed is that the investments and the strategy are working,'' Mr. Armstrong said. ''I see it, and the people who take the time to look at our company know it. But the overhang of the decline in voice and, in a large part, the consumer business is very depressing.</p>
        <p>''Depressing to the value,'' he added.</p>
        <p>What may also be depressing, or perhaps liberating, is the fact that a big part of AT&amp;T's troubles -- those in the $20 billion consumer long-distance business -- are for most practical purposes out of Mr. Armstrong's control.</p>
        <p>Since agreeing to break itself up under pressure from the government in 1984, AT&amp;T has seen its share of the long-distance market shrink each year. But what has also begun to shrivel in recent years is the overall revenue of AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance unit.</p>
        <p>After battling head-to-head with MCI (which has since been acquired by WorldCom) and with Sprint for long-distance customers during most of the 1990's, AT&amp;T has largely given up that fight under Mr. Armstrong. The incessant marketing in the last decade -- the television commercials, the print advertising and, most important, the free long-distance ''checks'' -- meant to persuade consumers to switch long-distance carriers -- helped prop up revenue in the long-distance unit, but at a cost to profitability.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Armstrong, AT&amp;T has essentially put its consumer long-distance unit on life support, allowing it to get smaller but milking it for billions in cash flow.</p>
        <p>In one sense, that is nothing but a concession to the inevitable. Just about anyone with a few million dollars can start a long-distance phone carrier by buying access to the big companies' networks at wholesale and selling long-distance minutes at a profit, as do small companies like Talk.com and Telecare. Many of the upstarts initially zero in on AT&amp;T. And it is only going to get worse as, with the Federal Communications Commission's blessing, the Bell companies move into long-distance. By the end of this month, Bell Atlantic, which changed its name last week to Verizon Communications, will have probably signed up one million long-distance customers in New York State alone. Tomorrow, SBC Communications, which does business as Southwestern Bell, is set to jump into the consumer long-distance business in Texas.</p>
        <p>''It's a systemic declining industry, long distance,'' Mr. Armstrong said. ''That is irreversible. And not just for AT&amp;T, but for the long-distance industry.''</p>
        <p>That is one reason that AT&amp;T recently tried to raise some of the prices in its basic calling plan. But that effort met with an outcry from some Washington regulators and consumer advocates, who said that AT&amp;T was reneging on a pledge to  reduce those rates. The criticism forced AT&amp;T to revise its plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong often points out that if AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance business were set aside, the remainder of the company would have shown a 12 percent growth rate in the first quarter of 2000. In the Internet world, that would impress no one, but 12 percent growth would be a home run for AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>Of course, AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance business has not been set aside, at least not yet. But Mr. Armstrong's real problem resides in the continued weakness in that unit, which makes it harder for him to convince investors of his success in other areas. The company must find gargantuan amounts of new business just to show modest growth.</p>
        <p>In May, AT&amp;T said it expected the consumer unit to decline by 6 to 8 percent this year, raising its earlier estimate of 3 to 5 percent. If that unit, which generated about $22 billion in revenue last year, shrinks by 7 percent, that amounts to about $1.5 billion in vanished sales. So AT&amp;T needs to find that much new revenue this year just to stay even.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T booked $62.4 billion in overall revenue last year, while earning $3.4 billion. If the company wanted to achieve, say, 10 percent growth -- it is instead hoping for 7 to 8 percent --  the company would have to find a whopping $7.8 billion in new revenue (think Paine Webber) this year alone.</p>
        <p>If the consumer unit declined an additional 7 percent next year, and the company again wanted to show 10 percent growth over all, it would have to find an additional $8.3 billion in new revenue (think Conseco) in 2001.</p>
        <p>In other words, the decline of the consumer long-distance business puts a lot of pressure on AT&amp;T's other operations. And that is one reason that AT&amp;T is considering ways to quarantine the consumer unit's financial results from those of the rest of the company, perhaps by selling a new stock to track the consumer operation. The idea seems to appeal to Mr. Armstrong, and it appears that a decision on such a move could come within months, if not weeks.</p>
        <p>''I've tried to tell everybody that a business has to reach three conditions and then I would consider a segmentation of it,'' he said. ''Is it operationally prepared for public investment? Will it create a currency that would serve a purpose? And will there be some value creation as a result of doing it?</p>
        <p>''Well, it's 115 years old, so I think it kind of qualifies that it kind of operationally knows what it's doing,'' Mr. Armstrong said, in answering the three questions. ''The creation of the currency is more obscure, because it has declining revenue. On the other hand, the currency would obviously have a value greater than it now has. And then third, would it create shareholder value? In this case, it would maybe permit that if there was some segmentation for the rest of AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>''So I would say that those three conditions would apply to the consumer business and that's kind of where it is,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Painful Stumbles</p>
        <p>As Mr. Armstrong says, the problems in his company's long-distance unit are systemic and not likely to change. The missteps in AT&amp;T's unit that sells services to business customers, however, are purely of the company's making.</p>
        <p>Put bluntly, the business-services unit tripped on its own shoelaces. While AT&amp;T was reorganizing the unit to transfer some big corporate customers to the Concert international venture that the company formed in 1998 with British Telecommunications, some of those customers got lost in the shuffle. AT&amp;T's sales force appeared to get lazy in selling new data services to those customers, opening the door for competitors like WorldCom and Sprint. As a result, AT&amp;T said growth in the business-services unit would be about 8 percent this year, rather than the 9 to 11 percent it had predicted earlier.</p>
        <p>Again, the numbers did not scream failure. But again, they gave some investors the impression of a ship adrift. And AT&amp;T is not going to be able to fix the problem right away.</p>
        <p>''Where the problem happened, I'm accountable, but I don't operate quite at that level,'' Mr. Armstrong said. ''The relationships, the administrative support, the skill coverage in those accounts was not carefully managed and we lost the kind of proposing, anticipating and customer-relationship role. And we've got to redo that. And you don't do that in weeks or months. It's going to take quarters.''</p>
        <p>There are two ways to view this sort of lapse. The first is that it is in some way more comforting than the sort of overarching issues afflicting AT&amp;T's consumer business, because it can be fixed.</p>
        <p>The other is that it is in fact even more disquieting, because there were no fundamental underlying reasons for the problem to have ever emerged. Moreover, the problems in the business-services operation were a direct result of the sort of organizational change that is fundamental to Mr. Armstrong's overall plan.</p>
        <p>There is no more important quality for the chief executive of a public company than credibility -- credibility that goals can and will be achieved and credibility that the company will be forthright in its dealings with the outside world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong's credibility is intact. But the manner and timing of the May 2 announcement left a bad taste for many investors and analysts.</p>
        <p>Just three business days before AT&amp;T delivered its bad news, the new stock meant to track the company's wireless business, whose offering brought AT&amp;T a $10.6 billion windfall, began trading.</p>
        <p>In the days and weeks leading up to the offering, AT&amp;T executives led by John D. Zeglis, AT&amp;T's president, had crisscrossed the country touting  the new wireless shares to investors. And in the course of those discussions, it does not appear that Mr. Zeglis gave even a hint of the problems that AT&amp;T was about to announce, leading some investors to worry that perhaps they had been manipulated.</p>
        <p>''Some people said: 'Hey, I just met with Zeglis. What's that about?' '' said one communications analyst, on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Had AT&amp;T delayed the announcement of the bad news to avoid tainting the wireless offering, whose ticker symbol is AWE? What would that say about AT&amp;T's communications in the future?</p>
        <p>''We didn't think it was relevant to the AWE offering,'' Mr. Armstrong said. ''What I was focused on was how can I maintain the most credibility by giving shareholders the most lead time to the bad news that I was coming with.''</p>
        <p>If he could do it again, would he handle the disclosure differently?</p>
        <p>''Oh, do I think that the perfect thing would have let a couple weeks go in between the two? Sure, yeah, I'd wait. But I don't think withholding information is a good idea. And that's what drove me to do it.''</p>
        <p>The Toughest of Times</p>
        <p>It was the early 1980's, and I.B.M. had recently introduced a new device called the personal computer. Critics harped that only I.B.M.'s arrogance would let it believe that people would pay to put a such a powerful machine on their desks.</p>
        <p>It was the early 1990's, and Hughes Electronics had faded along with the cold war. Instead of retrenching, Hughes went against the grain and invested in new civilian satellite systems.</p>
        <p>These are the stories Mr. Armstrong recounts as he tries to put this difficult moment in perspective. After all, he oversaw I.B.M.'s PC group in the early 80's, and he was running Hughes in the 90's.</p>
        <p>''I'm going through the toughest time, just like I did back in '83 and '84 with the personal computer,'' he said. ''The same tough time that we went through back in 1992 and '93 with the commercialization-of-space strategy. This is more visible. I've never enjoyed so many critics and authors and helpers from the outside as to what I should have done and what I could do.''</p>
        <p>He does not quite sound beleaguered. The strut, the confidence, are still there. But the force of personality is not quite as overwhelming as it was a couple of years ago.</p>
        <p>Rightly or not, AT&amp;T will always labor under especially intense scrutiny from investors. As AT&amp;T has tried to remake itself, its struggles have at times seemed the same as those of any other old, powerful, slightly dotty organization pushing to become something lean and new. But AT&amp;T has muddled for so long now that only a big surprise -- a big, good surprise -- will suffice to get investors excited again.</p>
        <p>''The street has gotten very emotional about this stock,'' said Daniel P. Reingold, chief telecommunications analyst for Credit Suisse First Boston. ''It seems that every fear in the world has found its way into this stock and it has led to a very over-sold condition. It's going to take good news on revenue or structural shock treatment, like some spinoffs or additional tracking stocks, to unlock the hidden value. But patient investors could be rewarded very handsomely.''</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Armstrong probably would not describe himself as patient, nor would investors be pleased if he did. But he does have perspective.</p>
        <p>''This has been as tough a challenge as I bargained for,'' he said. ''This is the toughest of times, when people view their success in terms of the stock price. Transformation doesn't come easy. It comes from hard work and ramping up new products and services with new people and new technology, and we're doing that.</p>
        <p>''I don't mind if people wonder if it can be done, this transformation,'' he added. ''But I do mind if people wonder if it can be done when it's being done. And it's being done here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
