<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Baby's Quilt to Sew Up the Generations</title>
    <meta content="09COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quilts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Webb, Marilyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DF1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Baby's Quilt to Sew Up the Generations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia Lee Coping column on welcome quilt made by Manhattan writer and novice quilter Marilyn Webb for her first grandson; quilt is made of decorated fabric squares contributed by members of extended family, including half-siblings, stepparents and stepsiblings; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stepgrandparents on the mother's side sent a photo of themselves in Pisa, Italy. Cousin Barbara sent a paraphrased quotation from ''The Little Prince'' that said, ''What is essential is invisible to the eye.'' From a maternal great-great-grandmother came a piece of her apron, on which was inscribed a cookie recipe.</p>
        <p>Each contribution was attached to a fabric square and each is part of a quilt that Marilyn Webb, a writer who lives on the Upper West Side, is making for her first grandchild. The boy will be born to her daughter Jennifer Kiefer and her son-in-law Jason Kiefer in Manhattan Beach, Calif.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stepgrandparents on the mother's side sent a photo of themselves in Pisa, Italy. Cousin Barbara sent a paraphrased quotation from ''The Little Prince'' that said, ''What is essential is invisible to the eye.'' From a maternal great-great-grandmother came a piece of her apron, on which was inscribed a cookie recipe.</p>
        <p>Each contribution was attached to a fabric square and each is part of a quilt that Marilyn Webb, a writer who lives on the Upper West Side, is making for her first grandchild. The boy will be born to her daughter Jennifer Kiefer and her son-in-law Jason Kiefer in Manhattan Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>The people behind the 40 squares represent the modern version of an extended family tree that includes half-siblings, stepparents and stepsiblings as well as the usual branches.</p>
        <p>The quilt, with a blue border of little dogs, is draped over a couch in Ms. Webb's dining room, an old-fashioned gift for a new kind of family. It is a family story literally stitched together at a time when so many families drift apart, connecting mostly by e-mail and telephone through marriages, remarriages, births and deaths.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty amazing,'' Ms. Kiefer said of the quilt. ''It's the one thing I've ever had combining the both of us, which is what the baby is.''</p>
        <p>For each square, ''There are a zillion little stories I learned,'' Ms. Kiefer said. ''There are so many older people you don't think about as someone's baby or little daughter. It reminds you of your ever-changing existence.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Webb was inspired to create an heirloom quilt for her grandson after joining a women's group that made a friendship quilt for her cousin, Barbara Bobrow. The women came together to meditate and to support each other after Ms. Bobrow was diagnosed two years ago with breast cancer, which later spread to her liver.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bobrow's 60-square healing quilt was made after the women began meeting Monday mornings at the home of a friend in Woodbridge, Conn. Each square in the quilt, which Ms. Bobrow takes with her to chemotherapy, came from her friend's treasures. There were pieces of curtains, baby blankets, wedding gowns, napkins.</p>
        <p>''It created a model for how a community can come together to support each other,'' said Ms. Webb, the former editor of Psychology Today magazine and the author of ''The Good Death: The New American Search to Reshape the End of Life'' (Bantam 1997). ''When I learned my daughter was pregnant, I thought: 'This child is very lucky. It has a huge network. Why not use a woman's art form to teach him about his family tree?'</p>
        <p>''In the ways that families were large before, they are large now in different ways,'' Ms. Webb said. ''People divorce and remarry and have children.''</p>
        <p>Both Ms. Webb and her former husband, her daughter's father, remarried. Ms. Webb has three stepchildren and one child who was born to her. Her daughter's husband is also a child of divorce, with half-siblings and stepsiblings on each side.</p>
        <p>In January, Ms. Webb sent a letter to dozens of family members that read, in part: ''Following a women's tradition that apparently dates back to the 1800's, if not way before, I'd like to make this new baby a welcome quilt in which he/she can be wrapped in the very fabric of our families' lives. A true family quilt and maybe a new family tradition.''</p>
        <p>In addition to a seven-inch square, the letter also asked family members to write a letter introducing themselves to the new child and telling him (they later found out it would be a boy) what was special about the fabric and design they were contributing.</p>
        <p>And so the pieces of lives came by mail from all the country. Scraps of tablecloths, shirts, baby blankets, bibs. Some of the pieces came from people connected to the baby by blood, some from people linked by marriage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Webb used books to teach herself to make a quilt and turned her dining room into a sewing room.</p>
        <p>She laughed at the idea of herself, a typically busy New Yorker, doing something as rooted in the past as quilting. Her daughter remembers Ms. Webb as a single mother who answered the question, ''What's for dinner?'' by picking out a menu.</p>
        <p>''Quilting has a long and political history,'' Ms. Webb said. ''It was an art form that women used to communicate ideas and keep in touch.''</p>
        <p>She believes quilting is an idea for these times, as many people seek ways to have more family time and preserve family history.</p>
        <p>''A friend of mine came over and said, 'You made an heirloom,' '' Ms. Webb said. ''Tears came to my eyes.''</p>
        <p>The quilt, she said, will give the new baby ''a living record of something he can pass down to his family.''</p>
        <p>''All these people may not be here when he's grown,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''We lose track of where we came from. We lose track of the fabrics we wore, the cookie recipes, the fabric that covered the sofa in our parents' living room.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
