<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Believable Family</title>
    <meta content="09BERNET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berne, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bender, Karen E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Like Normal People (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DC1F30F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Believable Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Suzanne Berne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berne, Suzanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suzanne Berne reviews book Like Normal People by Karen E Bender (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE NORMAL PEOPLE</p>
        <p>By Karen E. Bender.</p>
        <p>269 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE NORMAL PEOPLE</p>
        <p>By Karen E. Bender.</p>
        <p>269 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $23.</p>
        <p>Most parents will tell you they hope their children will be ''normal,'' meaning they hope their children will behave and look pretty much like everybody else. But what children really represent for their parents is unspoiled ambition. At the beginning at least, as Karen E. Bender notes in her poignant first novel, ''Like Normal People,'' children could be anyone: they are ''mysteriously joined with all the people'' they could become. So what happens when a child -- that repository of extravagant hopes -- turns out to be not only different but less than normal?</p>
        <p>This is exactly the situation that besets the Rose family, whose story begins in the mid-1920's with the courtship of Ella and Lou, a kindly, optimistic, working-class pair who move from Boston to Los Angeles in search of the good life. Lou opens a shoe store, which predictably flourishes, and Ella gives birth to a baby girl, whom she names after a movie star. But gradually it appears that something is not right with Marlene. At 3, she is declared to be ''mildly mentally retarded.'' Ella, who dreamed of her daughter becoming ''a glamorous actress'' or ''fluent in French'' or a cook ''proficient in preparing the fine foods of several European countries,'' finds herself with a little girl who cannot drink from a cup, who has ''the smile of a baby seal,'' who will most likely need to be looked after all of her life.</p>
        <p>Soon along comes another baby, Vivien, destined to be as graceful, intelligent and confident as Lena is awkward and tentative. We follow the Roses into the early 1970's and Ella's widowhood, by which time Vivien has become a dance instructor and a parent herself. Lena lives in a group home. Alternating between Ella's past and present, and between her point of view and that of Shelley, Vivien's 12-year-old daughter, ''Like Normal People'' probes the secret of how family members persist in caring for one another while contending with enormous disappointments.</p>
        <p>Bender's portrait of the tension caused for the Roses by the disparity between Lena and Vivien is particularly vivid. In her quest to help Lena lead a ''normal'' life, for example, Ella enrolls her in a charm school, where Lena practices applying lipstick and walking with a book balanced on her head. She learns to answer a telephone request for a dinner date. ''Her manners became impeccable, authoritarian.'' Ella and Lou allow themselves to hope that Lena might marry; Ella even consults a matchmaker, who says helpfully: ''So she's a little slow. We're all a little slow.'' At last, Lena falls in love with a mentally retarded man named Bob. Ella and Lou accompany the newlyweds on their honeymoon and -- finally, out of desperation -- find them a place to live on their own. Even the most cynical reader hopes everyone will manage to prosper, but that isn't what happens.</p>
        <p>It's here that Bender's novel glides away from its television-movie counterparts, and also where the other half of its story comes in. Ella's granddaughter, Shelley, begins visiting Lena and Bob by herself. Like many adolescents, Shelley doesn't consider herself normal, so being with her aunt and uncle is a relief. They tend to wander just as aimlessly as she does. Together they play a game Shelley learned at school called Dare, in which one person challenges the others to perform some minor feat -- swiping patio chairs, for example, or crouching on a fire escape. The game becomes a metaphor for what these three may venture in their larger lives -- dare to fall in love, dare to marry and have children, dare to hope that those children will accomplish great things. In fact, all these normal ambitions require great courage, once you consider everything that could go wrong.</p>
        <p>And the game of Dare eventually does go terribly wrong for Lena, Bob and Shelley. In the aftermath, Shelley is forbidden to visit, but, guilt-stricken and forlorn, she manages to hoodwink her grandmother and steal away with Lena. They dare each other to hop on a bus and, without consulting anyone, head off for a long, precarious day at the beach, during which both are forced, in different ways, to grapple with maturity.</p>
        <p>Much of the novel's appeal stems from Bender's descriptive skill, particularly when she evokes the bright torpor of Los Angeles, with its endless parking lots, its hills ''furred and golden with chaparral,'' its palm trees leaning ''like lonely giraffes into the wind.'' She's also adept at capturing wistfulness. Lena's bedroom before her marriage featured stuffed animals, but it ''was not a child's room; it lacked that hope of transformation.'' Parents at the charm school flank their children ''like generals guarding dictators of small, important lands.'' At the beach, Lena and Shelley are mesmerized by a group of body builders, who ''stood in their trunks of fire red and lemon yellow and lime green, and their bodies swelled up around them like weird, hopeful dreams.'' This is marvelous writing: energetic, precise, sympathetically alive to the strangeness of ordinary life.</p>
        <p>Such virtuosic moments make the clumsy ones seem more egregious, however, and there are a surprising number for an otherwise accomplished book. So many things ''shimmer,'' or are ''delicate,'' ''dainty,'' ''fragile'' or ''radiant,'' that these words lose their associative charge. Bender also occasionally indulges in pop psychologizing. ''While Lena struggled to create light in herself,'' one passage intones, ''Vivien was willing her own light to grow dim.'' More puzzling, we never find out how Lou dies, although Ella's mourning is a significant part of the book. Nor can we believe that sensitive Shelley entirely forgets about her parents and grandmother until the very end of her renegade day with Lena.</p>
        <p>And yet, despite these weaknesses, Bender succeeds in winning us over because she has populated her novel with a believable cast of characters whose kindnesses and sacrifices exemplify what, in lucky circumstances, can make a family the ultimate place of refuge. Early in their courtship, Ella and Lou go out to dinner; when Ella discovers that the meat she has ordered is tough, Lou comes to the rescue. ''It was wonderful,'' we are told, ''the way he'd cut the brisket for her. It was, somehow, the gesture she had been waiting for her whole life.'' Whether it's something as mundane as cutting tough brisket or as noble as cherishing grand ambitions for a disabled child, the Rose family perseveres with practical gallantry and without a speck of sanctimony. They are admirable people indeed. Whether they are ''normal'' is perhaps a matter for each reader to decide.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Berne is the author of a novel, ''A Crime in the Neighborhood.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Suzanne Berne is the author of a novel, ''A Crime in the Neighborhood.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
