<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weathering an Austrian Political Squall</title>
    <meta content="09CROY$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Croyden, Margaret</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEED81039F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weathering an Austrian Political Squall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGARET CROYDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Croyden, Margaret</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on boycott of international artists that threatened, but did not stop, most recent Vienna Festival, which dates to 1951; artists responded positively to open letter from program directors condemning right-wing Austrian populist party, refusing, for most part, to abandon festival, which went on as planned; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Vienna Festival, which has been bringing innovative performances to attentive Austrian audiences since 1951, this spring presented among its many offerings a Verdi ''Macbeth'' with a chorus line of lascivious-looking witches doing kicks and bumps, a von Hofmannsthal ''Elektra'' in a spectacular set of iron bars and scaffolds and a site-specific play in which actors from 10 countries dramatized the life of Balkan refugees in hotel ''rooms'' created in an empty factory building.</p>
        <p>But it's possible that the most intense drama of this year's festival was the one that occurred off-stage, before it began. With diplomatic sanctions imposed by the European Union and an international outcry greeting the inclusion of Jorg Haider's extreme right-wing, anti-immigrant Austrian Freedom Party in the national government's ruling coalition, it appeared in February that the festival, which is subsidized by the city of Vienna, would be in jeopardy. Fearing a boycott by the international array of artists who had agreed to participate, the festival's three program directors issued an open letter strongly condemning ''the integration of a right-wing populist party and its inhuman xenophobic ideology'' into the Austrian government and rejecting ''xenophobia, racism, intolerance and discrimination.'' It cited the festival's program, planned and announced before the government had come into power, as ''a declaration of openness and plurality.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Vienna Festival, which has been bringing innovative performances to attentive Austrian audiences since 1951, this spring presented among its many offerings a Verdi ''Macbeth'' with a chorus line of lascivious-looking witches doing kicks and bumps, a von Hofmannsthal ''Elektra'' in a spectacular set of iron bars and scaffolds and a site-specific play in which actors from 10 countries dramatized the life of Balkan refugees in hotel ''rooms'' created in an empty factory building.</p>
        <p>But it's possible that the most intense drama of this year's festival was the one that occurred off-stage, before it began. With diplomatic sanctions imposed by the European Union and an international outcry greeting the inclusion of Jorg Haider's extreme right-wing, anti-immigrant Austrian Freedom Party in the national government's ruling coalition, it appeared in February that the festival, which is subsidized by the city of Vienna, would be in jeopardy. Fearing a boycott by the international array of artists who had agreed to participate, the festival's three program directors issued an open letter strongly condemning ''the integration of a right-wing populist party and its inhuman xenophobic ideology'' into the Austrian government and rejecting ''xenophobia, racism, intolerance and discrimination.'' It cited the festival's program, planned and announced before the government had come into power, as ''a declaration of openness and plurality.''</p>
        <p>Although acknowledging that ''the vehement international reactions have been helpful as a warning'' of threats to democracy in Austria, the letter went on to say that ''we do not consider a boycott an effective solution -- the best resistance is through cooperative creative expression, not through isolation.'' And it called on artists to continue to come to Vienna: ''It is through their presence and work that we will achieve more than we will with treatises and boycott statements.''</p>
        <p>The artists responded to the gesture, and for the most part refused to abandon the festival, which went on as planned. And several prominent figures used the occasion to assert their political views. Zubin Mehta, who conducted a public concert on opening night, said that as an Indian he was proud to be in Vienna playing the music of Robert Stolz, Arnold Schoenberg and Gustav Mahler -- all composers whose music had been banned by the Nazis. Other musicians said they were performing for the 70 percent of Austrians who had not voted for Mr. Haider. The actors Klaus Maria Brandauer and Michel Piccoli appeared at a rally in support of the festival's position. A protest march supported by leading Austrian writers and intellectuals attracted some 150,000 people.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH officially the festival is run by the triumvirate of program directors, the major force is the 52-year-old, Paris-based theater director Luc Bondy, born in Switzerland to Jewish parents of Austrian-Hungarian descent. Having directed opera, theater and film all over Europe, and with his strong ties to Viennese culture, he is a commanding figure at the festival, to which he has devoted himself for the last three years. He will be on the job again next season and has already commissioned important artists to write about xenophobia, the festival's theme for 2001. (New Yorkers will have their first chance to see his work when he directs Janacek's ''Jenufa'' at the Metropolitan Opera during the 2002-03 season.) In addition to his supervisory functions at the festival, this year he staged two of its highlights, Chekhov's ''Sea Gull'' and Verdi's ''Macbeth.'' And he became deeply involved in the politics, appearing at meetings, making speeches and giving press conferences, where he took a forceful, even controversial stand on the Haider question. In fact, a Haider representative attacked Mr. Bondy on television, telling him to make art and shut up.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bondy would not keep quiet. A nonstop talker with a simple manner that belies a keen sophistication, Mr. Bondy characterizes the Haider supporters as yuppies and technocrats ''fed up with the socialists who were entrenched for three decades and had not come through on their promises.'' Emphasizing the 70 percent of Austrians who did not vote for Mr. Haider, he took issue with Israel's recall of its ambassador: ''As a 100 percent Austrian-Hungarian Jew, I think it is not the right position. I expect to be in Israel and I hope to discuss it with them. The correct position is to stay here and fight to show who I am.'' And he says the sanctions voted by the European Union could turn out to be double-edged: ''They tend to encourage nationalism and defensiveness. Austrians feel they are being persecuted. On the other hand, it may force Austrians to examine their past.''</p>
        <p>Vienna's councillor for cultural affairs, Peter Marboe, who is responsible to the city for the management of the Vienna Festival, believes that the sanctions have caused a backlash among Austrians who would normally distance themselves from Mr. Haider. ''The E.U. did not think of the consequences,'' Mr. Marboe said. ''They have done this because they are afraid of their own right-wing movements. Maybe it was symbolic. Maybe it was meant as a warning. If so, it succeeded in many ways.''</p>
        <p>But many Austrian Jews have taken a somewhat ambiguous stance. Disturbed by the rise of Mr. Haider and mindful of Austria's embrace of Hitler during the Nazi period, Ariel Muzicant, a leading figure in the small Jewish community that has re-formed since World War II, condemns the government's inclusion of Mr. Haider's party. But he also believes that Israel must rethink its position: ''The main problem is for the Austrians to understand the situation and for politicians to campaign for Austria to come to terms with its past,'' he said. Austrians, he continued, have yet to grasp the significance of the fact that they are the first Europeans since 1945 to accept a racist extremist in the national government.</p>
        <p>Dorian Rabinovici, a well-known writer who organized the first large anti-Haider protests, believes that Mr. Haider, who has made pro-Nazi remarks, could be a harbinger of worse to come. ''Europeans wonder how they can be sure that what happened in the past will not happen again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The rise of Mr. Haider has exacerbated Austria's lingering reputation for anti-Semitism. Mr. Bondy, who as a Jew is highly sensitive to the issue, thinks Europe's negative image of contemporary Austria is erroneous: ''People who come to my plays are of a different generation. They are not like this. You cannot stigmatize a whole people and put them in a corner for eternity and not give them a chance. The intellectual community, the artists, are against Haider, and every Thursday there is a demonstration against him. Look, I am an artist and my job is to make art. But the day that Haider becomes a majority in Vienna, that day will be the last day for me here. I would leave immediately and go to Paris.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bondy's choices in Vienna reflected the festival's traditionally humanistic, international ethos. His own productions, which played to capacity audiences, exemplify this sensibility. '' 'Macbeth' is about people who cannot love,'' he says. ''It is about cruelty and violence. 'Sea Gull' is about show business, about vanity, narcissism, self-involvement. It is a play about illusion. 'The Sea Gull' can be placed anywhere and is not specifically Russian.''</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Mr. Bondy disregarded time, place, class and the lifestyle of the Russian gentry in his ''Sea Gull.'' The famous actress Arkadina and her family are run-of-the-mill middle-class folk. In his interpretation, their ostensible glamour is but a shallow pretense born of self-involvement and vanity. And with her flaming red hair and unflattering modern clothes, Arkadina suggests bad taste as well as a touch of vulgarity. The seduction scene between her and the writer Trigorin caught the farcical elements in the play. An original piece of staging, it ended with the couple rolling on the floor, Arkadina's hands around her lover's neck in a wrestler's grip. Even the summer house in which the play is set is plain, almost shabby. In a gesture to the modern age, a refrigerator stands in full view against the wall. Only a battered piano and a fur piece spread on a divan recall old Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bondy's version of the Verdi ''Macbeth'' was also directed with a blend of the contemporary and the old. (''This mixture,'' he said, ''is my approach -- historical reconstruction is for me a kind of science fiction.'') The witches, dressed in grotesque minis, were lined up like Rockettes in an image as witty as it was shocking. The setting, a huge background of simple red brick around a black pit, created a menacing, nightmare atmosphere. In one brilliant, ghastly scene, the pit is filled with Macbeth's victims, lying on top of one another, conjuring up the Holocaust. Into the pit comes Macduff, embracing his dead son and surrounded by a chorus of plainly dressed mourners; it was the most moving part of this Scottish Opera production, in which the theatrical elements overshadowed the singing.</p>
        <p>Another impressive and quite different theater piece was Sophocles' ''Elektra,'' in Hugo von Hofmannsthal's adaptation, directed by the renowned German actress Edith Clever, who also played Clytemnestra. Ms. Clever was the centerpiece of the production. Making her entrance in a long, voluminous, old-fashioned fur coat, this classical actor of charismatic intensity dominated the stage, conveying grandeur with every facial expression and hand movement, filling the enormous, high-ceilinged space with her characterization of the doomed queen.</p>
        <p>Among several productions from Eastern Europe and Russia was the striking, avant-garde ''Hotel Europa.'' This clever multimedia piece was created and performed by a young international company of actors and directors led by Goran Stefanovski of Macedonia. The audience was escorted into numerous small ''hotel'' rooms in a refurbished factory to witness dramas from 10 different countries -- about love, loneliness, hopelessness, aggression, isolation. Somber, bitter, even morbid, the playlets had little or no dialogue  (when actors did speak, they used their native languages). These innovative and moving mood pieces, with their sometimes mysterious plots and intense and powerful acting, were a tribute to the festival's ideals of diversity and experimentation.</p>
        <p>The Vienna Festival, organized after World War II to reaffirm the city's place as a cultural metropolis, seems to have survived its political perils with its soul intact. And if audiences were deterred or upset by its vocal anti-Haider stance, it was not evident from the still, steady concentration they brought to the events -- or from their warm responses afterward.</p>
        <p>THEATER Margaret Croyden's most recent book is a memoir, ''In the Shadow of the Flame: Three Journeys'' (Continuum). She is a regular contributor to nytheatre-wire.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Margaret Croyden's most recent book is a memoir, ''In the Shadow of the Flame: Three Journeys'' (Continuum). She is a regular contributor to nytheatre-wire.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
