<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ready or Not, Here They Come; Tall Ships Go to New London, but Can the City Really Cope?</title>
    <meta content="09SAIL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opsail 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New London (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parsekian, Penny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Mystic and the Southeastern Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EEDE1E39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ready or Not, Here They Come; Tall Ships Go to New London, but Can the City Really Cope?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, Robert A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming four-day layover of 40 sailing ships in New London, Conn, as part of Operation Sail 2000; Main Street Program manager Penny Parsekian and other town officials describe preparations for event; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER three years of planning, New London officials said the city is as prepared as possible for the arrival of more than 40 sailing ships that will visit this week as part of Operation Sail. But with as many as  1 million visitors expected during the ships' four-day layover, roughly 40 times the small city's normal population, everybody is bracing for the crush.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time that OpSail has come into a town this size, so nobody knows quite what to expect,'' said Penny E. Parsekian, manager of New London's Main Street Program. ''How does it work when a million people descend on a town of 25,000? I guess we're going to find out.''</p>
        <p>New London is the seventh stop of Operation Sail, which started in San Juan, then proceeded to Miami, Norfolk, Baltimore, Philadelphia and New York. Despite a dispute with Boston, which is holding a competing tall ships event, ships from as far away as Argentina, New Zealand and the Ukraine will arrive in New London this week to take part, although at least four of them have also committed to Boston and will leave before the Saturday fireworks show.</p>
        <p>The festival will begin Wednesday with the parade of ships coming up the river, led by the United States Coast Guard's tall ship, the barque Eagle. The New London stop is the ship's homecoming -- it is normally berthed at the Coast Guard Academy just north of the downtown. The festival itself runs through the late-Saturday-night fireworks display, at four main venues, each with its own tall ships.</p>
        <p>So New London is expecting a crowd, but some officials wonder how the city, despite all its planning, will be able to cope with it. Parking, for example, is one problem. There just aren't enough spaces in New London for such a crowd, so organizers have had to look away from the city. OpSail Connecticut, which is supervising the event, has arranged for 30,000 parking spaces, almost all of them outside of the city, some more than 10 miles away. There will be 28 message signs and traffic officers at 55 key intersections directing people to the lots. Visitors will then be bused into the city, which has arranged for more than 400 shuttle buses.</p>
        <p>''We've spent a ton of money with some of the best minds in the transportation business, coming up with a plan that should be able to accommodate the numbers,'' said Fred Franchi, director of operations for OpSail Connecticut. ''But of course, if everyone comes in all at the same time, it's going to be a mess.''</p>
        <p>William C. Gavitt, New London's deputy chief of police, said the latest estimates were more encouraging than what he heard three years ago when Operation Sail announced it would come to the city.</p>
        <p>''In the beginning they were telling us to expect 3 million people,'' Mr. Gavitt said. ''Now, the thinking is 500,000 to 1 million over four days, which is a lot more manageable.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gavitt said, he has asked that his force be augmented by as many as 30 police officers from seven other eastern Connecticut towns, under a mutual aid agreement that is part of the local Law Enforcement Council.</p>
        <p>''Norfolk, Va., had 590 cops and a separate sheriff's department to handle OpSail there,'' Mr. Gavitt said. ''We don't even have 90. We're looking at 12-hour minimum shifts, especially for our uniformed people.''</p>
        <p>While the crowds are expected to provide a big boost to businesses that rely on walk-ins, businesses that rely on customer appointments, such as hair salons and doctors' offices, are worried that their clients might have a tough time getting through.</p>
        <p>''We don't do much business with tourists, and I figure with the crowds and all the traffic, it won't pay to open up,'' said Jerome F. Silverstein, who operates a real estate appraisal business downtown. And, he said, shutting down will give him time to see more of the festival.</p>
        <p>Others don't have much choice. A large part of the festival will take place on Adm. Harold Edson Shear State Pier, where Logistec Connecticut Inc. operates a freight business that moves almost 200 million board feet of lumber a year off railroad cars and cargo ships onto trucks for distribution around the Northeast. Max Krebs, the terminal manager, said he had to try to remain open, though he had moved as much of his inventory as possible to make way for the event.</p>
        <p>''I've got customers out there who want their material and they couldn't care less whether OpSail is going on or not,'' Mr. Krebs said. ''If the trucks come in, we will be here in the stevedore business. The question is, will they be able to get here?''</p>
        <p>The overcrowding is expected to extend out into the water, with 4,000 to 6,000 recreational boats expected over the four days.</p>
        <p>''The marinas are filling up quickly, but there are a lot of places out in the river for anyone who wants to just anchor for the day,'' said Lt. Cmdr. Steven M. Sheridan of the Coast Guard. ''Fireworks night, Saturday, is the big concern. We usually have 800 boats during a usual year, and we figure we may have three or four times that this year. That's a night when the harbor could get full.''</p>
        <p>Commander Sheridan said the Coast Guard has the authority to close the harbor to additional traffic, but he hopes to avoid that by putting as many as 50 law enforcement boats on the Thames River, including boats from the Coast Guard Auxiliary, local police, and State Department of Environmental Protection officers, to enforce safety rules, in particular speed limits and laws against boating while intoxicated.</p>
        <p>''We want everybody to have a good time,'' Commander Sheridan said. ''We're not going to be out there to harass people, but we are aware of the potential for problems and we're going to do what's necessary to prevent them.''</p>
        <p>City Manager Richard M. Brown said he was confident that it would all come together. ''We deal with large crowds every July at Sailfest and the fireworks, so I know we can do this,'' Mr. Brown said. ''We've spread it out over a large area and we've done a lot of planning, so I don't expect any problems.''</p>
        <p>Operation Sail, the officially sanctioned tall ships circuit in this country, was founded by President John F. Kennedy in 1961 and has organized flotillas of tall ships on several major occasions, most recently in 1992, the 300th anniversary of Christopher Columbus's arrival in the New World.</p>
        <p>In this week's event, ''New London and Beyond'' at City Pier will feature displays by 10 local museums and cultural groups, as well as Eagle and the Brazilian ship Cisne Branco. City Pier, adjacent to Union Station, the transportation hub of the city, anchors one end of a new 2,000-foot-long, 28-foot-wide waterfront boardwalk that links it to the new Amistad and Redwood piers, on the water side of the historic Customs House, where 14 smaller vessels will be berthed.</p>
        <p>''Festival America'' will be at Fort Trumbull, the Revolutionary War-era fort, where the State Department of Environmental Protection is completing a $20 million makeover. In addition to five tall ships -- Simon Bolivar from Venezuela, Guayas from Ecuador, Juan Sebastian de Elcano of Spain, Sagres II of Portugal, and the Rose from nearby Bridgeport -- there will be demonstrations by various Coast Guard and Navy units.</p>
        <p>The Chilean ship Esmerelda and 18 smaller craft will tie up at ''Celebrate Connecticut'' at State Pier, where two stages have been erected for live entertainment, and a variety of the state's tourist attractions will have displays.</p>
        <p>The fourth site will be across the river. ''Groton Experience'' will feature two major ships, Soren Larsen of New Zealand and Gazela of Philadelphia, as well as some smaller ships and a floating concert stage for the American Wind Symphony, which will perform during the parade of sail.</p>
        <p>Warren Edward ''Ted'' Colburn, the vessel liaison official for Operation Sail, has been coordinating with nine different navies and dozens of other ship operators in an effort to make sure there is pier space for everyone when they arrive that will show the craft to their best advantage. And there was a scramble to make sure everyone had electrical hookups, sewage pumpouts, and garbage pickup.</p>
        <p>''We're using just about every inch of space available to us,'' Mr. Colburn said. ''But it's amazing how many piers there are, once you start adding them all up. New London really is a port city.''</p>
        <p>Visitors will be able to buy a wrist band for $3 that will allow them use of all land transportation at the festival all day, or for another $4 buy a pass on the water shuttles that will ferry people between sites.</p>
        <p>Nancy Tyler, a spokeswoman for OpSail, said she was convinced the crowds would be manageable because so many committees have worked out so many details. The estimate is that the crowds will consume a mile of sausages, 200,000 cans of soda and 350,000 bottles of water daily. Five hundred portable toilets have been placed around the area.</p>
        <p>''I never thought about how many Portolets it would take to handle a crowd like this, but we have people who do that kind of calculation for all kinds of events,'' Ms. Tyler said. ''We're expecting people to come here with their sunscreen and their hats and have a good time, because everything else will be here. People will come and go over the four days, and they're going to be spread over all the different sites, so the crowds will be manageable.''</p>
        <p>The festival has acquired 350 radios and 150 cell phones for use by its staff during the events, ''So if any problem do develop, there should be someone right there who can communicate directly with the police and emergency services command center,'' Ms. Tyler said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Parsekian, the manager of the New London Main Street Program, said her organization got involved about a year ago to extend the festival atmosphere from the waterfront deep into downtown. It will operate three hospitality centers, a food court, and a nonprofit marketplace where community organizations can sell raffle tickets or do promotions. It has hired bagpipers, mimes, puppeteers and jugglers to wander the streets, and there have been two major cleaning efforts where volunteers picked up trash and spruced up the most visible buildings.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep people entertained while they're going to be standing in line for the buses, and we want to lure people downtown,'' Ms. Parsekian said. ''We don't want this festival to happen to us, we want to take advantage of it. No one is going to leave New London unhappy -- we want to make sure they have a reason to come back.''</p>
        <p>A number of projects that have been low priority in the past became a very high priority because of the tall ship festival. State officials were amazed at how quickly Fort Trumbull was renovated. A dilapidated former Coast Guard pier in the downtown has been completely overhauled, and a new waterfront park came together in a matter of months.</p>
        <p>''It really became a much larger project than anyone ever envisioned,'' said Mr. Brown, the New London city manager. ''But it was work that needed to be done to make the waterfront more attractive. We look at the waterfront to be a very active part of our downtown from now on, and to bring a lot of people to New London.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER three years of planning, New London officials said the city is as prepared as possible for the arrival of more than 40 sailing ships that will visit this week as part of Operation Sail. But with as many as  1 million visitors expected during the ships' four-day layover, roughly 40 times the small city's normal population, everybody is bracing for the crush.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time that OpSail has come into a town this size, so nobody knows quite what to expect,'' said Penny E. Parsekian, manager of New London's Main Street Program. ''How does it work when a million people descend on a town of 25,000? I guess we're going to find out.''</p>
        <p>New London is the seventh stop of Operation Sail, which started in San Juan, then proceeded to Miami, Norfolk, Baltimore, Philadelphia and New York. Despite a dispute with Boston, which is holding a competing tall ships event, ships from as far away as Argentina, New Zealand and the Ukraine will arrive in New London this week to take part, although at least four of them have also committed to Boston and will leave before the Saturday fireworks show.</p>
        <p>The festival will begin Wednesday with the parade of ships coming up the river, led by the United States Coast Guard's tall ship, the barque Eagle. The New London stop is the ship's homecoming -- it is normally berthed at the Coast Guard Academy just north of the downtown. The festival itself runs through the late-Saturday-night fireworks display, at four main venues, each with its own tall ships.</p>
        <p>So New London is expecting a crowd, but some officials wonder how the city, despite all its planning, will be able to cope with it. Parking, for example, is one problem. There just aren't enough spaces in New London for such a crowd, so organizers have had to look away from the city. OpSail Connecticut, which is supervising the event, has arranged for 30,000 parking spaces, almost all of them outside of the city, some more than 10 miles away. There will be 28 message signs and traffic officers at 55 key intersections directing people to the lots. Visitors will then be bused into the city, which has arranged for more than 400 shuttle buses.</p>
        <p>''We've spent a ton of money with some of the best minds in the transportation business, coming up with a plan that should be able to accommodate the numbers,'' said Fred Franchi, director of operations for OpSail Connecticut. ''But of course, if everyone comes in all at the same time, it's going to be a mess.''</p>
        <p>William C. Gavitt, New London's deputy chief of police, said the latest estimates were more encouraging than what he heard three years ago when Operation Sail announced it would come to the city.</p>
        <p>''In the beginning they were telling us to expect 3 million people,'' Mr. Gavitt said. ''Now, the thinking is 500,000 to 1 million over four days, which is a lot more manageable.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gavitt said, he has asked that his force be augmented by as many as 30 police officers from seven other eastern Connecticut towns, under a mutual aid agreement that is part of the local Law Enforcement Council.</p>
        <p>''Norfolk, Va., had 590 cops and a separate sheriff's department to handle OpSail there,'' Mr. Gavitt said. ''We don't even have 90. We're looking at 12-hour minimum shifts, especially for our uniformed people.''</p>
        <p>While the crowds are expected to provide a big boost to businesses that rely on walk-ins, businesses that rely on customer appointments, such as hair salons and doctors' offices, are worried that their clients might have a tough time getting through.</p>
        <p>''We don't do much business with tourists, and I figure with the crowds and all the traffic, it won't pay to open up,'' said Jerome F. Silverstein, who operates a real estate appraisal business downtown. And, he said, shutting down will give him time to see more of the festival.</p>
        <p>Others don't have much choice. A large part of the festival will take place on Adm. Harold Edson Shear State Pier, where Logistec Connecticut Inc. operates a freight business that moves almost 200 million board feet of lumber a year off railroad cars and cargo ships onto trucks for distribution around the Northeast. Max Krebs, the terminal manager, said he had to try to remain open, though he had moved as much of his inventory as possible to make way for the event.</p>
        <p>''I've got customers out there who want their material and they couldn't care less whether OpSail is going on or not,'' Mr. Krebs said. ''If the trucks come in, we will be here in the stevedore business. The question is, will they be able to get here?''</p>
        <p>The overcrowding is expected to extend out into the water, with 4,000 to 6,000 recreational boats expected over the four days.</p>
        <p>''The marinas are filling up quickly, but there are a lot of places out in the river for anyone who wants to just anchor for the day,'' said Lt. Cmdr. Steven M. Sheridan of the Coast Guard. ''Fireworks night, Saturday, is the big concern. We usually have 800 boats during a usual year, and we figure we may have three or four times that this year. That's a night when the harbor could get full.''</p>
        <p>Commander Sheridan said the Coast Guard has the authority to close the harbor to additional traffic, but he hopes to avoid that by putting as many as 50 law enforcement boats on the Thames River, including boats from the Coast Guard Auxiliary, local police, and State Department of Environmental Protection officers, to enforce safety rules, in particular speed limits and laws against boating while intoxicated.</p>
        <p>''We want everybody to have a good time,'' Commander Sheridan said. ''We're not going to be out there to harass people, but we are aware of the potential for problems and we're going to do what's necessary to prevent them.''</p>
        <p>City Manager Richard M. Brown said he was confident that it would all come together. ''We deal with large crowds every July at Sailfest and the fireworks, so I know we can do this,'' Mr. Brown said. ''We've spread it out over a large area and we've done a lot of planning, so I don't expect any problems.''</p>
        <p>Operation Sail, the officially sanctioned tall ships circuit in this country, was founded by President John F. Kennedy in 1961 and has organized flotillas of tall ships on several major occasions, most recently in 1992, the 300th anniversary of Christopher Columbus's arrival in the New World.</p>
        <p>In this week's event, ''New London and Beyond'' at City Pier will feature displays by 10 local museums and cultural groups, as well as Eagle and the Brazilian ship Cisne Branco. City Pier, adjacent to Union Station, the transportation hub of the city, anchors one end of a new 2,000-foot-long, 28-foot-wide waterfront boardwalk that links it to the new Amistad and Redwood piers, on the water side of the historic Customs House, where 14 smaller vessels will be berthed.</p>
        <p>''Festival America'' will be at Fort Trumbull, the Revolutionary War-era fort, where the State Department of Environmental Protection is completing a $20 million makeover. In addition to five tall ships -- Simon Bolivar from Venezuela, Guayas from Ecuador, Juan Sebastian de Elcano of Spain, Sagres II of Portugal, and the Rose from nearby Bridgeport -- there will be demonstrations by various Coast Guard and Navy units.</p>
        <p>The Chilean ship Esmerelda and 18 smaller craft will tie up at ''Celebrate Connecticut'' at State Pier, where two stages have been erected for live entertainment, and a variety of the state's tourist attractions will have displays.</p>
        <p>The fourth site will be across the river. ''Groton Experience'' will feature two major ships, Soren Larsen of New Zealand and Gazela of Philadelphia, as well as some smaller ships and a floating concert stage for the American Wind Symphony, which will perform during the parade of sail.</p>
        <p>Warren Edward ''Ted'' Colburn, the vessel liaison official for Operation Sail, has been coordinating with nine different navies and dozens of other ship operators in an effort to make sure there is pier space for everyone when they arrive that will show the craft to their best advantage. And there was a scramble to make sure everyone had electrical hookups, sewage pumpouts, and garbage pickup.</p>
        <p>''We're using just about every inch of space available to us,'' Mr. Colburn said. ''But it's amazing how many piers there are, once you start adding them all up. New London really is a port city.''</p>
        <p>Visitors will be able to buy a wrist band for $3 that will allow them use of all land transportation at the festival all day, or for another $4 buy a pass on the water shuttles that will ferry people between sites.</p>
        <p>Nancy Tyler, a spokeswoman for OpSail, said she was convinced the crowds would be manageable because so many committees have worked out so many details. The estimate is that the crowds will consume a mile of sausages, 200,000 cans of soda and 350,000 bottles of water daily. Five hundred portable toilets have been placed around the area.</p>
        <p>''I never thought about how many Portolets it would take to handle a crowd like this, but we have people who do that kind of calculation for all kinds of events,'' Ms. Tyler said. ''We're expecting people to come here with their sunscreen and their hats and have a good time, because everything else will be here. People will come and go over the four days, and they're going to be spread over all the different sites, so the crowds will be manageable.''</p>
        <p>The festival has acquired 350 radios and 150 cell phones for use by its staff during the events, ''So if any problem do develop, there should be someone right there who can communicate directly with the police and emergency services command center,'' Ms. Tyler said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Parsekian, the manager of the New London Main Street Program, said her organization got involved about a year ago to extend the festival atmosphere from the waterfront deep into downtown. It will operate three hospitality centers, a food court, and a nonprofit marketplace where community organizations can sell raffle tickets or do promotions. It has hired bagpipers, mimes, puppeteers and jugglers to wander the streets, and there have been two major cleaning efforts where volunteers picked up trash and spruced up the most visible buildings.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep people entertained while they're going to be standing in line for the buses, and we want to lure people downtown,'' Ms. Parsekian said. ''We don't want this festival to happen to us, we want to take advantage of it. No one is going to leave New London unhappy -- we want to make sure they have a reason to come back.''</p>
        <p>A number of projects that have been low priority in the past became a very high priority because of the tall ship festival. State officials were amazed at how quickly Fort Trumbull was renovated. A dilapidated former Coast Guard pier in the downtown has been completely overhauled, and a new waterfront park came together in a matter of months.</p>
        <p>''It really became a much larger project than anyone ever envisioned,'' said Mr. Brown, the New London city manager. ''But it was work that needed to be done to make the waterfront more attractive. We look at the waterfront to be a very active part of our downtown from now on, and to bring a lot of people to New London.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
