<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scam Artiste</title>
    <meta content="09KAPLANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Alice</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spurling, Hilary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">La Grande Therese (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDC1F30F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scam Artiste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alice Kaplan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaplan, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Kaplan reviews book La Grande Therese: The Greatest Scandal of the Century by Hilary Spurling; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LA GRANDE THERESE</p>
        <p>The Greatest Scandal of the Century.</p>
        <p>By Hilary Spurling.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 132 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LA GRANDE THERESE</p>
        <p>The Greatest Scandal of the Century.</p>
        <p>By Hilary Spurling.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 132 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $20.</p>
        <p>In 1902, the French police were looking for an escaped con artist named Therese Humbert. Since Henri Matisse was connected to Therese through his wife's family, the police raided Matisse's studio and put his in-laws under strict surveillance. In researching her 1998 biography of Matisse, Hilary Spurling became fascinated by the woman who nearly destroyed the artist's family. ''I had to fight so hard to relegate Therese to a minor role,'' she explains. ''I felt I owed her a book of her own.'' The result is ''La Grande Therese: The Greatest Scandal of the Century,'' which recasts the Humbert material from Spurling's ''Unknown Matisse'' into an enticing historical fable.</p>
        <p>The fable of Therese Humbert begins with a childhood in rags in the Toulouse region of France and peaks in a 20-year career as one of the great hostesses of belle epoque Paris. Her steppingstone to success was marriage to her first cousin Frederic Humbert, son of the French politician Gustave Humbert. The weak and dreamy child of an ambitious man, Frederic would seem, on the surface, unlikely to be interested in a cousin from the poorest branch of his family. Therese wooed Frederic Humbert, as she would so many others, with made-up stories about a castle she had inherited from the supposed wealthy lover of her deceased mother. Frederic may have started as her dupe, but he became her accomplice. That make-believe castle was the collateral for a banker's loan, which then allowed the Humberts to invest in a real castle. And so it went, with bigger lies, bigger loans and increasing social status for the Humbert family, whose patriarch, Gustave, had by now become France's minister of justice.</p>
        <p>Humbert's scams were simple variations on the old adage ''The check is in the mail,'' and on an even older one, ''There's a sucker born every minute.'' She always told her backers that an inheritance was on the way, often in the form of real estate, and they complied by advancing her vast sums. There were many small frauds, but over the years she perfected one triumphant master narrative, the Crawford story. Spurling unravels it with admirable clarity. In her elaborate Parisian apartments on the Avenue de la Grande Armee, Therese kept a strongbox. It was supposed to contain four documents. The first was the final will and testament of an American millionaire, Robert Henry Crawford, naming Therese as sole beneficiary. A second, competing will left everything to Therese's youngest sister and Crawford's two American nephews. Therese insisted there was a third document in which the two Crawford boys agreed to give their uncle's fortune to Therese while the dispute over the competing wills was being resolved. The fourth fictional document was a deed. In it, the Crawford boys agreed to waive their claim to their uncle's vast fortune in return for a payoff of six million francs and the promise that one of them be allowed to wed Therese's youngest sister.</p>
        <p>As Therese pitched it to her financiers, if they lent her the six million francs to pay off the Crawford nephews, she would inherit a hundred million francs and pay them back with handsome interest. Over the years, the con and its variants reached such a degree of theatrical perfection that there were actual court dates where sincere lawyers represented the Crawford and the Humbert sides of the case. The Crawford brothers -- impersonated by Therese's brothers, speaking French with bad American accents -- even appeared at a dinner party. The scheme finally broke down when, in response to a lawsuit by an angry lender, a judge asked the obvious question: What was the Crawford brothers' permanent address? ''1302 Broadway,'' was Therese's reply, showing a rudimentary knowledge of New York geography -- only there were no Crawfords at that address. Nor, after Therese and her entourage fled Paris, were there any wills or deeds in the legendary strongbox.</p>
        <p>Therese Humbert had simply embroidered her own version of a commonplace French myth, that of the American uncle, ''l'oncle d'Amerique'' -- the fellow who had gone off to the land where the streets are paved with gold, capable of saving the folks back home from ruin if not elevating them to riches that matched his.</p>
        <p>Therese's story ends with a stunning lack of drama. There was a much-publicized trial, during which the French press printed lists of the distinguished men and women who had been taken for their fortunes, including the exiled Empress Eugenie and the son of the president of the French Republic. Therese and her husband spent five years in prison at hard labor, then disappeared from history.</p>
        <p>How did she succeed? Therese Humbert's career defies literary cliche. She wasn't particularly beautiful, and sex never entered into her manipulations. Her main physical attribute was a charming lisp -- she said ze instead of je -- which seems to have driven bankers, jewelers and couturiers wild with the desire to do business with her. She had a weakness for hideous hats piled high with artificial fruits and feathers. She also offered the highest interest rates in Paris: 64 percent, in one case, so that when the lender sued her, she sued back -- for usury.</p>
        <p>Much of Therese's life is right out of Zola's ''Nana'' -- if you can imagine ''Nana'' without the sex. There are faithful retainers, lavishly decorated apartments, mounting debts and endless creditors. In a typical scene, when a bailiff comes calling for a lender's payment, Therese throws a string of pearls angrily to the floor, breaking the string and sending her staff on their knees to collect the jewels. The clock strikes 5 and she announces coolly that the bailiff's writ has expired, and sends him home.</p>
        <p>What interests Spurling most is the quality of Therese Humbert's verbal performance. ''She lied as a bird sings,'' explained one of her contemporaries, and Spurling concludes, ''If she had chosen books, instead of real life, as the medium for her romantic fictions about missing deeds, locked coffers, surprise legacies and long-lost parents, she would have been a 19th-century best seller.'' A pity, then, that Therese Humbert didn't turn her talents to writing novels in the era that saw the birth of France's most charming literary thief, Arsene Lupin, and yielded any number of women writers who thrived on adventure -- Colette and Myriam Harry, to name just two. Writing, however, would not have brought the financial gratification, the power or even the danger that her real-life schemes did. In the uglier part of the story revealed by Spurling, Therese's brother Romain served as hit man for her confidence game. The result was murder in a few cases and numerous suicides, as lenders who had lost all their money ended their lives in despair.</p>
        <p>By meticulously combing the press accounts from Toulouse and Paris, Spurling has found the facts of the case. She has also derived a remarkable sense of the main characters in this complicated drama -- Therese, Frederic, Romain and their extended family. There are a few shortcomings, all connected to the decision to tell the story in 132 pages. Spurling can't adequately support her most ambitious claim: that the Humbert affair nearly toppled the Third Republic and was contained only by stringent damage control on the part of government officials implicated in the scandal. In addition to the newspaper sources and a very good 1984 book by Benjamin F. Martin that she drew on, materials housed in the French National Archives, which include a parliamentary investigation of the Humbert scandal and are available on request, would have helped.</p>
        <p>Although her book is filled with delightful cartoons and illustrations, readers will regret that Spurling didn't flesh out more of the social history of the era, especially when it comes to the scandalmongering newspaper world in which Therese Humbert could become a star -- a world of episodic true-crime stories, grandiose political scandals and detective fictions.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, brevity has its virtues when dealing with a liar like Therese Humbert. Spurling is able to convey the speed and mystery of Humbert's rise and fall, giving us the sense of a fairy tale. We're left, like her victims, seduced and astounded.</p>
        <p>Alice Kaplan's most recent book is ''The Collaborator: The Trial and Execution of Robert Brasillach.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alice Kaplan's most recent book is ''The Collaborator: The Trial and Execution of Robert Brasillach.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
