<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia</title>
    <meta content="PHILLY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000723T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DE1339F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MANSNERUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column describes upcoming events, sights, lodging and restaurants in Philadelphia, Pa; photos; chart; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Philadelphia has done everything it could think of for the 45,000 visitors expected at the Republican National Convention: its landmark architecture is polished, its streetscapes groomed, its hotels gleaming with restored marble and brass and stocked with concierges. But the convention is brief (July 31 through Aug. 3) and the summer is long, making for many more weeks of prime tourism in the nation's original convention city.</p>
        <p>When you're inviting the whole country, it's good to have a city full of walking opportunities. While the convention site, the First Union Center, is in deep South Philadelphia, the restaurants, shopping and historic sites are clustered in mercifully compact Center City, a 15-minute subway or cab ride away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Philadelphia has done everything it could think of for the 45,000 visitors expected at the Republican National Convention: its landmark architecture is polished, its streetscapes groomed, its hotels gleaming with restored marble and brass and stocked with concierges. But the convention is brief (July 31 through Aug. 3) and the summer is long, making for many more weeks of prime tourism in the nation's original convention city.</p>
        <p>When you're inviting the whole country, it's good to have a city full of walking opportunities. While the convention site, the First Union Center, is in deep South Philadelphia, the restaurants, shopping and historic sites are clustered in mercifully compact Center City, a 15-minute subway or cab ride away.</p>
        <p>There, in the two-mile stretch between rivers, the spines of skyscrapers give way quickly to narrow, leafy residential streets that make life easy for walkers, if not for traffic. A tourist could spend a day just inspecting the courtyards and mews, especially plentiful in the old neighborhoods east of Broad Street.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia in summer is still the hot, placid city where street life means corner taverns with open doors and row-house stoops occupied by supervising grandparents. But with the dizzying revival of Center City, another public life -- the kind involving theater tickets and cell phones -- brings people out.</p>
        <p>High summer is also the time to set sandals to the streets around Independence Hall and see where the delegates to the First and Second Continental Congresses sweltered. Or to explore the cool halls of museums that have given their all to this summer's exhibitions. Or to visit the rivers: the Delaware, with its night life on the piers, and the more sedate Schuylkill, where the grassy banks invite picnics and jogging.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The city will greet the convention on its eve, July 30, with a parade of 59 lighted boats at 9 p.m. and fireworks along the Delaware. Penn's Landing and the New Jersey State Aquarium in Camden are prime viewing spots. Information: (800) 770-5883.</p>
        <p>You don't have to be a G.O.P. delegate to get into PoliticalFest, described as a world's fair of politics. It will have historical and interactive (want to read from a teleprompter?) exhibits at the Pennsylvania Convention Center, 12th and Arch Streets, July 26 through Aug. 3. Admission: $10 and $5 for students, ages 4 to 11 and 65 and older; (215) 686-0350.</p>
        <p>And at the Atwater Kent Museum, 15 South Seventh Street, the exhibit ''Vote: Campaign Choices/Presidential Voices'' is showing two centuries of campaign memorabilia until Nov. 26. Admission to the Atwater Kent, Philadelphia's history museum, is $3, $2 for ages 55 and older and $1.50 for children 3 to 12. Information: (215) 922-3031.</p>
        <p>The African American Museum in Philadelphia, 701 Arch Street, (215) 574-0380, is celebrating the blues all summer. In addition to a photography exhibition, through Sept. 3, the museum plans outdoor lunch concerts on Wednesdays in July and August, with hip-hop, zydeco and classical music represented, too. A second exhibit, through Sept. 17, celebrates Paul Robeson. Admission: $6, $4 for students, those aged 55 and older and the handicapped.</p>
        <p>''Andy Warhol: Social Observer'' is at the museum of the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Broad and Cherry Streets, (215) 972-7600, through Sept. 21. The show, including paintings of Presidents Reagan and Nixon, Chairman Mao and Lenin, is the first major exhibition of Warhol's work since 1988. Admission is $8, $7 for students and ages 60 and up, and $5 for ages 5 to 18.</p>
        <p>On the streets or in the galleries,  plastic cups of wine in hand, people gather in Old City, just northeast of the Liberty Bell, on First Fridays. This month, an extra Friday, July 28, will accommodate convention visitors at the sprawling open house. About 40 art galleries, on Second and Third Streets, will open from 5 till 9 p.m. For information, call (215) 625-9200 or (800) 555-5191.</p>
        <p>It's not Wrigley Field, but Veterans Stadium does have real baseball, and it's next to the First Union Center. No matter what they say about Philadelphia fans, the Vet is a friendly place. The Phillies are home July 25 to July 30 (Chicago and Los Angeles), Aug. 7 to Aug. 16 (San Diego, Houston and Arizona) and Aug. 25 to Aug. 30 (San Francisco and Colorado). Tickets, $7 to $22.50; information, (215) 463-1000.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>In a city that never runs out of material, the Foundation for Architecture leads walking tours of about two hours five days a week -- Saturday and Sunday at 2 p.m., and Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday evenings at 6. A dozen offerings during the convention include ''20th Century Unlimited,'' around Center Square, and ''Littlest Streets,'' along the old, once-bohemian residential alleys of Washington Square West. Adults $7, students $6; (215) 569-3187.</p>
        <p>A different thread of history is on view at the hulking Eastern State Penitentiary, 22nd Street and Fairmount Avenue. Eastern State, one of the nation's first penitentiaries, opened in 1829 and was home to Al Capone and Willie Sutton. The gothic stone monster was only recently rescued from decades of decay and opened for tours of Capone's specially furnished cell and other exhibits on Wednesdays through Sundays from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. in summer. The fee is $7, $5 for students and ages 55 and up, and $3 for under 17. Information, (215) 236-3300.</p>
        <p>Walkers naturally seek out Society Hill, the core of Philadelphia's original civic life and of its downtown revival 30 years ago. It's a genteel quarter, red brick from the sidewalks up, encompassing Independence National Historic Park and dotted with courtyards and churchyards, with many Georgian and Federal buildings. But at its southern edge, South Street booms at night with bars and quirky shops.</p>
        <p>Across Society Hill's northern boundary, Market Street, is Old City, which 20 years ago was a disused quarter of small, abandoned garment factories with a few luncheonettes and a string of restaurant-supply stores. The area is now packed with galleries, coffeehouses, restaurants and clubs.</p>
        <p>Runners can always put on shorts and head up the Benjamin Franklin Parkway from Center City to the Philadelphia Museum of Art. A jogging and bike path continues another four miles along the Schuylkill, where the sights -- bridges, scullers, masses of willows -- are pretty much as Thomas Eakins painted them more than 100 years ago.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Philadelphia is booked for convention week, but the building binge has ensured a tourists' market for most other weeks of the summer and fall. To find out about hotel packages, including tickets to cultural events,  call a visitors' information number: (888) 467-4452.</p>
        <p>The Sheraton Society Hill, Second and Walnut Streets, has a quiet, established niche in the historic district. Like its surroundings, the low-rise red-brick hotel is Colonial (except for the swimming pool) and sedate. The 365 traditional rooms  and suites range from $155 to $270 for a double. Reservations, (215) 238-6000, fax (215) 238-6652.</p>
        <p>A block from the convention center, Loews, 1200 Market Street, (215) 627-1200, fax (215) 231-7305, is an Art Deco creation in an old bank building (check out the vault doors). The 583 rooms are pure 1930's luxe. A standard double is $175 to $240.</p>
        <p>Just off Rittenhouse Square, the Sofitel, a part of the French hotel chain, recently opened at 120 South 17th Street, on a pleasingly unreconstructed block of tiny shops. The hotel, by contrast, is all modern and smooth, its 306 rooms furnished in gleaming woods and geometric prints. Doubles, $189; (215) 569-8300, fax (215) 569-1492.</p>
        <p>Budget: The Hawthorn Suites, 1100 Vine Street, (215) 829-8300, fax (215) 829-8104, is crisp and new, if a bit spare. Each of the 294 suites, at $149 to $159 (sometimes less on weekends), has refrigerator, microwave and wet bar, making life easier for families. At the northern edge of Center City, the hotel towers over the convention center and Chinatown.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The Park Hyatt Philadelphia at the Bellevue, Broad and Walnut Streets, is rich in detail and history, a match for the Academy of Music on the next corner of the theater district. With just 172 rooms, including suites, it has a ballroom, a conservatory, a rooftop rose garden and such amenities as a day spa. Doubles start at $275; (215) 893-1234, fax (215) 732-8518.</p>
        <p>Rittenhouse Bed and Breakfast, 1715 Rittenhouse Square, (215) 545-1755, fax (215) 545-1750, is as elegant as the neighboring square, formal from its facade to its nightly shoeshine service. Some of the 10 individually decorated rooms, all with baths, have fireplaces and whirlpools. Rates are $220 to $340 and include full breakfast.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>An anchor of Center City's restaurant row, Susanna Foo, 1512 Walnut Street, (215) 545-2666, has done Asian fusion elegantly for years. Under silk lanterns, diners can make their way from Chinese soups and delicate dumplings to emphatically French desserts (apricot tart with almond ice cream, for one). Dinner for two people with wine, about $125.</p>
        <p>Fishmarket, 122 South 18th Street, (215) 569-9080, offers seafood in a town house with just enough painted wood to feel like a crab house. In fact, for the summer, the Fishmarket is making a big production of crabs. Take a stool at the glistening raw bar at happy hour and enjoy oysters for $1 each. Dinner for two, with a bottle of wine, about $120. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>Le Bar Lyonnais, 1523 Walnut Street, (215) 567-1000, is the downstairs wing of Le Bec-Fin, the French restaurant that has been on national best-of lists for years. The bar offers many lighter Bec-Fin standards like the galette de crabe and vichyssoise au caviar at considerably lower prices. The atmosphere is rich, dark and close -- it seats about 30. No reservations. Dinner for two with drinks, about $100. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>On the other side of Rittenhouse Square, Audrey Claire, (215) 731-1222, opens its wide windows at the corner of 20th and Spruce Streets to a neighborhood of brownstones and small shops. The fare is Mediterranean -- Audrey Claire is known for its grilled flatbreads -- and simple. Outdoor tables available. No reservations on Friday and Saturday. Bring your own wine. Dinner for two, about $60. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Effie's, at 1127 Pine Street on Antique Row, (215) 592-8333, is a tiny Greek restaurant in a row house with a tiny, inviting garden. Effie's has fresh fish every day, usually served whole, brushed with lemon and olive oil and grilled. Bring your own wine. Dinner for two, under $40.</p>
        <p>For those who cannot leave town without a cheesesteak, the pure South Philadelphia version is available at Pat's King of Steaks, (215) 468-1546, or Geno's, (215) 389-0659, competing cholesterol palaces at the intersection of Passyunk, South Ninth and Wharton Streets.</p>
        <p>And for South Philly pizza, try Marra's, 1734 East Passyunk Avenue, (215) 463-9249, now in its third generation. Wear a tank top and bring $5 to $10 a person (that includes the beer).</p>
        <p>A note about Pennsylvania dining: Most restaurants have liquor licenses, but if you must bring your own, plan. Wine and liquor are sold only in state stores, which are sparse, poorly stocked and expensive. They are also not open late or on Sunday.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN LAURA MANSNERUS, a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The Times, lives in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 23, 2000, Sunday  A chart on July 9 with the What Doing column, about Philadelphia, misstated the fare for a ride downtown from the airport. It is $20, not $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 23, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A chart on July 9 with the What Doing column, about Philadelphia, misstated the fare for a ride downtown from the airport. It is $20, not $22.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">LAURA MANSNERUS, a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The Times, lives in Philadelphia.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
