<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; With One Pitch, A Day Goes Sour</title>
    <meta content="09ARAT$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piazza, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DA1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; With One Pitch, A Day Goes Sour</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column on New York Yankees pitcher Roger Clemens's pitch that hit New York Mets star Mike Piazza in head, souring good cheer of crosstown doubleheader (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE good cheer of an original New York event on a crisp summer day disappeared just as the sun was sinking last night in the Bronx. The day-night doubleheader turned sour, in the manner of the most timeless of baseball episodes of dishonor, with a brushback fastball that wreaked far more havoc than its desired effect.</p>
        <p>No one can prove that Roger Clemens was trying to hit Mets catcher Mike Piazza in the second inning last night at Yankee Stadium. Clemens said he was pitching inside, the way he always has. Mets Manager Bobby Valentine spit out his cynicism, making himself clear that Clemens headhunted Lenny Harris and Derek Bell before drilling Piazza because the Mets and Piazza, in particular, had in the past handed Clemens ''his lunch.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE good cheer of an original New York event on a crisp summer day disappeared just as the sun was sinking last night in the Bronx. The day-night doubleheader turned sour, in the manner of the most timeless of baseball episodes of dishonor, with a brushback fastball that wreaked far more havoc than its desired effect.</p>
        <p>No one can prove that Roger Clemens was trying to hit Mets catcher Mike Piazza in the second inning last night at Yankee Stadium. Clemens said he was pitching inside, the way he always has. Mets Manager Bobby Valentine spit out his cynicism, making himself clear that Clemens headhunted Lenny Harris and Derek Bell before drilling Piazza because the Mets and Piazza, in particular, had in the past handed Clemens ''his lunch.''</p>
        <p>Piazza hit a grand slam off Clemens in June in Yankee Stadium, and with a rout the Mets furthered the notion that Clemens in pinstripes would never be the Clemens who will one day grace the Hall of Fame. Because Piazza and the Mets had roughed him up last season as well, it was time last night for Clemens to make a statement, take a stand.</p>
        <p>The only debatable issue was how far he decided to go. Pitching is a subtle art, a fine line, and it's never easy to know when it has been crossed. Yet Clemens threw his two-seam fastball, which has always had spectacular movement, and he threw high and inside and to the Mets' franchise player. It tailed in on Piazza, bypassing his raised hands on the barrel of his bat and crashing off the top of his helmet.</p>
        <p>''A brushback is here,'' Valentine said, holding his hands across the letters.</p>
        <p>''Belt high,'' Clemens said when asked what he was aiming for.</p>
        <p>Piazza was down, on his back, his eyes closing slowly as if were on the verge of losing consciousness. The long day of baseball wasn't festive anymore. It wasn't about subway riders commuting between Queens and the Bronx anymore. It wasn't about Doc Gooden coming out of oblivion and giving the Yankees five gutsy innings in their 4-2 afternoon victory at Shea Stadium. It wasn't about a couple of obstruction plays that strangely involved both Chuck Knoblauch and Todd Zeile, or Clemens's strong pitching as the Yankees won again, 4-2, to sweep the day.</p>
        <p>It was about Piazza being out of the game, off to a hospital with a slight concussion, the Mets holding their breath that it was nothing worse.</p>
        <p>It was all about intention and interpretation now, about what the Mets were supposed to make of a pitcher who throws in the mid-90's, even at the advanced age of 37, firing one hard and high and tailing in. It was about the Mets' starter, Glendon Rusch, retaliating by hitting Tino Martinez to lead off the home half of the inning.</p>
        <p>So the challenge was made, and accepted, and if Mike Hampton happens to lose control of a fastball when Derek Jeter is in the batter's box tonight in the series finale, well, as Valentine charged, what Clemens did was ''terrible.''</p>
        <p>''I hope someday he'll pitch in a National League park when we're playing against him,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The Mets and Bobby Valentine were already in a rotten mood, after losing two close games and getting no breaks. First Yankees right fielder Paul O'Neill robbed Derek Bell of a game-tying home run Friday night in a 2-1 Yankee victory. Then Lee Mazzilli, the Yankees' first-base coach, talked the young umpire Robb Cook into an obstruction call against Zeile, the Mets' first baseman, when Knoblauch rounded first and headed for second after singling to lead off yesterday's first game. Valentine was ejected for arguing the call. The Yankees scored two runs on the way to a two-run victory.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had begun the day in first place, a week after they were all but written off as has-beens who had better get Sammy Sosa. They won the first three games of the series with the Mets in the way they have always won: pitching, defense, timely hits and Mariano Rivera.</p>
        <p>It was bad enough for the Mets to lose a couple of games at home when nothing went right. It was bad enough to have Gooden, of all people, rushed up from Tampa, George Steinbrenner's idea of a good subway story. They weren't thrilled at having their weekend series broken up with the makeup of a June rainout at Yankee Stadium. They got their police escort crosstown, the way the Yankees did, but they were already down, 0-2, and suddenly Piazza was down, nearly out, on his back.</p>
        <p>''I've gotten mad at Roger Clemens,'' said Yankee Manager Joe Torre, scrambling back on defense. ''He hit a couple of my guys, Derek Jeter in spring training. That's the way he pitches, up and in.''</p>
        <p>It was too late in a long day of losing for Valentine. He wasn't buying it. He wasn't saying it was over.</p>
        <p>''I'd be mad, too, if I were him,'' Torre finally said.</p>
        <p>One day. Two boroughs. Two teams. Maybe the players didn't like having to hit and run, but it was for the fans, who filled both parks and jammed into the No. 7 train into Manhattan and then rerouted uptown. But then Clemens threw his fastball that tailed, and Piazza went down, and it didn't feel like a great baseball day in New York City anymore. All good will was derailed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
