<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gravediggers' Gallows (What Else?) Humor</title>
    <meta content="09BAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hollywood (Nyc Bar)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDF1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gravediggers' Gallows (What Else?) Humor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bending Elbows column describes scene at Hollywood bar on Main Street and 58th Avenue in Flushing, Queens, where local gravediggers congregate after work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A. Berg was buried last week. His remains were laid to rest in a hole dug 2 feet wide, 8 feet long and 4 feet deep, in accordance with Jewish law.</p>
        <p>His was the seventh funeral of the day at Mount Hebron Cemetery in Flushing, Queens. His grave was dug precisely, by hand, and a mourner admired its craftsmanship and square corners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A. Berg was buried last week. His remains were laid to rest in a hole dug 2 feet wide, 8 feet long and 4 feet deep, in accordance with Jewish law.</p>
        <p>His was the seventh funeral of the day at Mount Hebron Cemetery in Flushing, Queens. His grave was dug precisely, by hand, and a mourner admired its craftsmanship and square corners.</p>
        <p>''Say, that's a very nice grave,'' the mourner said to the burial gang.</p>
        <p>''Thank you very much, sir,'' said Armando Malave, a 28-year-old gravedigger standing at a respectful distance, his shovel against his shoulder like a military cadet, his voice low and rueful. ''I'm sorry for your loss.''</p>
        <p>''Well, back to the grind,'' the mourner said as he brushed some imaginary dust from his palms. Then he put his hand around a woman's waist, and they turned and walked away.</p>
        <p>The gravediggers scrambled toward the hole as though it was last call at an all-you-can-eat buffet. The day was hot and humid and it made no sense to be working in the sun longer than necessary .</p>
        <p>''Come on, Willy, hurry it up,'' Mr. Malave said to William Taylor, a man in his 50's with more than 30 years on the job.</p>
        <p>''It don't matter,'' Mr. Taylor said, going as leisurely as you please. ''He's already dead. He ain't going nowhere.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor lost his shovel speed after he was stabbed by a replacement worker who crossed a picket line two years ago during a strike over wages and benefits. The strike was settled after seven months, but Mr. Taylor has never been the same. He doesn't go out for drinks anymore, for one.</p>
        <p>Some of the other men do. The gravedigger's credo: After a long day of putting cold ones in the ground, you look forward to putting a few cold ones down.</p>
        <p>''It's gallows humor, I know,'' says Johnnie, the foreman. ''But you've got to have it if you're in a business like this.''</p>
        <p>When their work is done, Mr. Malave and Sammy Acevedo head to Hollywood,  at Main Street and 58th Avenue in Flushing. It is one of those cheerless cracker-box-type bars that blanket the city. It has too many television sets and looks as though it was decorated by a beer distributor.</p>
        <p>When death is your occupation, death is your conversation, and the gravediggers make for grim fellowship over burgers and chicken wings and beer.</p>
        <p>''The babies, those are the hardest,'' said Mr. Acevedo, 35, a big man who has three children. ''You have to get in the hole with the casket, it's so small. It's like you're staring down at your own kids. That's when I go home and give my kids a kiss.''</p>
        <p>Equally disheartening are the cheap particleboard coffins. ''They come straight from the nursing home. No rabbi comes, no family, and you're wondering how this person must have lived,'' Mr. Malave said.</p>
        <p>He rubbed at the calluses on his hands, souvenirs from more than a thousand burials.</p>
        <p>''New York can be the saddest place on Earth,'' he said.</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
