<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Duel of New Dynasties May Lift TV Ratings</title>
    <meta content="09NBAA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Grant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duncan, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgrady, Tracy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DB1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Duel of New Dynasties May Lift TV Ratings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basketball Notebook article focuses on possibility that free agents Grant Hill, Tim Duncan and Tracy McGrady may join Orlando Magic, creating powerhouse to rival Los Angeles Lakers and boost basketball's television ratings and waning fan appeal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scenario from heaven may be unfolding for the National Basketball Association. With television ratings down and its buzz having given way to a hum, what is potentially a new millennium version of the engaging 1980's rivalry between the Los Angeles Lakers and the Boston Celtics appears to be taking form.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 1, the Orlando Magic could announce that the free agents Grant Hill, Tim Duncan and Tracy McGrady will join the team for the next six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scenario from heaven may be unfolding for the National Basketball Association. With television ratings down and its buzz having given way to a hum, what is potentially a new millennium version of the engaging 1980's rivalry between the Los Angeles Lakers and the Boston Celtics appears to be taking form.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 1, the Orlando Magic could announce that the free agents Grant Hill, Tim Duncan and Tracy McGrady will join the team for the next six years.</p>
        <p>No contracts have been signed, but Hill has told his former club, the Detroit Pistons, that he intends to go to Orlando; McGrady, who grew up in Auburndale, Fla., has said repeatedly that he wants to play for the Magic; and Duncan is currently fighting between his loyalty to the San Antonio Spurs and his desire to team with Hill.</p>
        <p>Every Eastern Conference club not coached by Doc Rivers is hoping that the league's best power forward stays loyal because if those three, or even just Duncan and Hill, combine forces in Orlando, the East is theirs. Patrick Ewing's already dim chances of winning a title would die instantly. Pat Riley would not even have the best team in his state, let alone division or conference. And Indiana's retro Conseco Fieldhouse would be as old as the design of its bleacher seating the next time it saw an N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>''Without question, Orlando would be the best team in the East,'' said a coach from an Eastern Conference playoff team who requested anonymity. ''It would be them, the Lakers and Portland.''</p>
        <p>And while Portland could potentially crash the Lakers' and Magic's annual finals party, their chances of doing so lessen with each game since the legs of Scottie Pippen, Steve Smith and Arvydas Sabonis are getting heavier, not fresher. What you would very likely have is Shaquille O'Neal, Kobe Bryant and whoever versus Duncan, Hill and McGrady each June, just like the old days when it was Magic Johnson, Kareem Abdul-Jabbar and James Worthy versus Larry Bird, Robert Parish and Kevin McHale.</p>
        <p>Even though that might frustrate some of the league's coaches, it might also bump up the ratings and fan appeal that have been waning since Michael Jordan's retirement two years ago.</p>
        <p>''Something like that would be good, especially when you look at what's happening to the league,'' said Wayne Embry, the former general manager and president of the Cleveland Cavaliers.</p>
        <p>Dynasties have been good for the N.B.A., as fans seem to like familiarity in their champions. Magic and Bird rescued the league from the public perception of insignificance and drug abuse by helping their teams dominate their conferences. Magic's Lakers won eight conference championships and five league titles in the 1980's while Bird's Celtics won five Eastern titles and three N.B.A. crowns.</p>
        <p>A Los Angeles-Orlando run would not have the unspoken, though intense, racial undertones that Los Angeles-Boston had, but there would be contrasting social themes to enhance the drama. Shaq and Kobe are hip-hop -- brash, stylish and intimidating in their play -- while Duncan and Hill are classical: smooth, staid and quietly outstanding. As the followings for the Lakers and Celtics sometimes broke down along racial lines, the followings for the Lakers and the Magic would perhaps at times flow along cultural ones. And, of course, there is the story line of O'Neal bolting Orlando for Los Angeles as a free agent in 1996.</p>
        <p>More important, O'Neal, Bryant, Duncan and Hill are the league's best players at their positions, and they would often be matched against each other. Also, all four are excellent role models off the court.</p>
        <p>Of course, this could all be irrelevant if Duncan stays in San Antonio.</p>
        <p>Hill and McGrady alone do not make the Magic the cream of the East. In fact, several league executives believe it would be foolish of Hill to go to Orlando without Duncan. For that reason, a popular thought around the league is that Hill already knows that Duncan is going to Florida. After all, they do share the same counsel in Lon Babby.</p>
        <p>San Antonio is hoping such speculation is untrue.</p>
        <p>''Tim's enjoyed it here, and we've obviously enjoyed him,'' said Gregg Popovich, the Spurs' coach and general manager, who along with Duncan helped bring San Antonio its first championship two years ago. ''We've had great success and we still have the same championship team in the healing process, so to speak. I think it's a great situation for Tim and we hope that's what he decides to do.''</p>
        <p>Only oral agreements have been made, so if Duncan chooses to stay in San Antonio, there is nothing to stop Hill from changing his mind and going to the Spurs or any of the other teams, including the Knicks, that tried to court him last week.</p>
        <p>The more likely scenario, however, has Duncan and Hill going to Orlando, where they would each receive six-year, $67.5 million contracts.</p>
        <p>Obtaining McGrady, who has already said that ''it won't be fair for Eastern Conference opponents if all three players go to the Magic,'' will be more complicated.</p>
        <p>Because Orlando does not have enough money to pay all three players the maximum immediately, Toronto will either have to agree to a sign-and-trade deal with the Magic or McGrady will have to accept playing for $5 million or $6 million next season instead of $9 million. If that is the case, Orlando will most likely give him an out clause after four years that would allow him to receive the maximum amount of money available.</p>
        <p>If all of this comes together, the Magic would not only be envied; it would also be admired. After losing O'Neal and Penny Hardaway, the young building blocks of what looked like a championship team, within the last four years, its general manager, John Gabriel, has repositioned the Magic to be a powerhouse.</p>
        <p>''Orlando has done a lot of impressive things,'' Embry said. ''Losing Shaq and Penny could have devastated their franchise. But they took a negative and turned it into a positive. If all of this happens, they've done a heck of a job.''</p>
        <p>And perhaps a heck of a service to the league and its fans.</p>
        <p>Knicks in a Bind</p>
        <p>After being spurned by Grant Hill, the Knicks are faced with the fact that they have no comparable Plan B that will be anywhere near as effective. One member of the organization scoffed when asked if it could somehow obtain another superstar, such as Seattle's Gary Payton.</p>
        <p>''There's no way,'' the Knicks official said. ''That's all just speculation and stuff people write about, but it can't happen.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks cannot even bring Portland power forward Brian Grant to New York. Uninterested in the Knicks' offer of Marcus Camby and Chris Childs, the Blazers would demand Latrell Sprewell or Allan Houston and a front-court player. And the Knicks believe that parting with either of their star swingmen for Grant would be ludicrous.</p>
        <p>Kurt Thomas's agent, Jerry Hicks, has proposed a six-year deal worth $29.9 million, the maximum amount Thomas can be paid by the Knicks. It is a reasonable offer, and the Knicks are mulling it over.</p>
        <p>Danny Fortson, the Boston Celtics free agent who is dying to play for the Knicks, was in an uproar on Thursday after hearing a false rumor that the Knicks had made a sign-and-trade deal for the Los Angeles Clippers' Maurice Taylor. Fortson, who is said to be proudly carrying around the Knicks jersey the club sent to him, has reportedly been offered a seven-year, $31 million deal from the Celtics.</p>
        <p>While the Knicks like Fortson -- he is one of the best offensive rebounders in the league -- they are contemplating whether they want to pay him that kind of money. He had a great season in Denver two years ago, averaging 11 points and 11.6 rebounds, but his numbers may be skewed because they came on a losing team. Last season, he averaged less than 16 minutes for the struggling Celtics. Some around the league believe that at 6-7 he is an undersized center or a slow, immobile power forward.</p>
        <p>A Bargaining Chip</p>
        <p>The players union will hold its annual meeting July 23-28 in the Bahamas. More than 70 players are expected to attend, plus more than 100 retired players from the Ex-N.B.A. Players Association. The players will vote to fill the six vice president slots on their nine-member board, but the hot topic of conversation could be the union's purchase of the Continental Basketball Association from Isiah Thomas.</p>
        <p>The union has signed a letter of intent to buy the C.B.A., with its impetus for the purchase being bargaining power if another work stoppage takes place when the current collective bargaining agreement ends in either 2004 or 2005 (the owners have an option for a seventh year). Owning the C.B.A. would give the union the infrastructure necessary to put its players to work in the event of a lockout.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
