<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>My Night at Andre's</title>
    <meta content="09DINE$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andre's Restaurant (Newton, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EEDA1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>My Night at Andre's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>NEWTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catherine Jones reviews Andre's Restaurant in Newton, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDRE'S Restaurant is all about paying attention, whether it be on the part of the owners, the staff or the customers. Yes, the customers.  Andre's clientele -- most often from northwestern New Jersey -- want to taste new things and trust in Andre deWaal's choices and his preparations. These diners may not be accustomed to hangar steak or sweetbreads. They may dislike foie gras. But if Mr. deWaal is offering these items on his menu, which changes twice a month, then they will try it.</p>
        <p>Which leads to the second factor: the staff. Tracey deWaal, Andre's wife, always knew that she wanted to run her own business and thus studied business administration at Montclair State. She runs the front of the house with a contagious grace and warmth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDRE'S Restaurant is all about paying attention, whether it be on the part of the owners, the staff or the customers. Yes, the customers.  Andre's clientele -- most often from northwestern New Jersey -- want to taste new things and trust in Andre deWaal's choices and his preparations. These diners may not be accustomed to hangar steak or sweetbreads. They may dislike foie gras. But if Mr. deWaal is offering these items on his menu, which changes twice a month, then they will try it.</p>
        <p>Which leads to the second factor: the staff. Tracey deWaal, Andre's wife, always knew that she wanted to run her own business and thus studied business administration at Montclair State. She runs the front of the house with a contagious grace and warmth.</p>
        <p>She purposely placed her wedding photos near the front door and (there are some in the bathroom, too) so her customers understand immediately that she is a co-owner with more than just a fleeting interest in their evening.</p>
        <p>And then there is Andre deWaal, who has been paying attention to food as long as he can remember. He graduated from the Culinary Institute of America in 1988, and started on the line at Park 111 in Ridgewood.  He followed the owner, Brooks Nicklas, to Rosemary and Sage in Riverdale, which Mr. Nicklas and his wife, Wendy Farber, run as a team. It is clear that Mr. deWaal paid close attention to that partnership, along with the seasonal nature of their menu, during his training there.</p>
        <p>His menu is simple yet wonderful, his food elegant yet not threatening.  His urbane menu, with a small but growing emphasis on locally grown organic ingredients, may challenge his mostly rural clientele. But he is always solicitous. If a customer attends one of the restaurant's theme nights and has certain dietary constraints, Mr. deWaal will happily look out for them (he recently created an all-scallop menu for a diner partaking of his summer crab fest; he's made pretzel- and Tostito-crusted chicken fingers for children, and he even adapted one group's meal to the special wine they had selected).  Clearly Mr. deWaal aims both to enlighten and to please, and his food reveals that earnestness along with his unmistakable sense of style.</p>
        <p>I'm going to skip ahead to dessert, as the fresh blueberry lemon tart encompasses everything the restaurant is about. The afternoon I tried it, it was baked fresh the afternoon. The tart was served warm, and tasted like a cobbler, a pie and a muffin all at once. Fresh lemon verbena, plucked from Mr. deWaal's neighbor's garden, infused both the splash of lightly caramelized sugar syrup and the puff of whipped cream alongside.</p>
        <p>Each element was simple yet ethereal -- I could not decide whether to savor the tart, the cream or the syrup alone or whether to dive in and spoon a bite containing all three delights.</p>
        <p>My predicament with the tart was not new; similar ones had occurred repeatedly throughout the meal.  Take the Perona Farms smoked salmon bacon with eggplant caviar, warm blini and chive sour cream.  The salmon hinted at molasses, the garlicky eggplant caviar easily outshone the real thing, and tender blini and cream might have been the best I've ever eaten. And there was the spicy beef and noodle salad, served with peanuts and garlic shoots. Was it better to alternate between the peanuty soba noodles and the tiny strips of sirloin or mix them together into one riotous mouthful? The penne pasta with toasted almonds, blue cheese, basil and cherry tomato was similarly enthralling. This combination was new to me, served atop perfectly al dente pasta dressed in veal stock and cream. And Mr. deWaal's crab cakes with homemade tartar sauce over slivers of red potato disappeared before I could even come up with a plan of attack.</p>
        <p>Two appetizer specials had also caught my eye. Warm, crispy sweetbreads were paired with stir-fried vegetables covered in a chilled sweet and sour sauce, providing a contrast in color, flavor and most of all temperature. A duck sampler of smoked duck breast, duck liver mousse and foie gras was so decadent that I forgot for a moment that there was more to come. Andre's portions are manageable -- further evidence that the deWaals are paying attention, as  they recommend ordering a five-course meal that includes a salad and soup too.</p>
        <p>Entrees are well balanced, hearty and expertly seasoned. Pan-roasted mahi-mahi lay over roasted vegetables in a lobster broth; seared tuna steak surrounded mango salsa and creamy coconut rice; medallions of pan-roasted lamb loin rested on Yukon gold potatoes and roasted shallots. One favorites was sauteed sea scallops tucked into white corn grits and creamed spinach, and another was a breast of chicken floating on a mound of mashed potatoes over a pool of milky white goat cheese cream. These were creative comfort food, presented beautifully and executed masterfully.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's long, narrow space initially reminded the deWaals of an alley, and rather than try to hide that fact, the pair chose instead to run with it. They painted one stucco wall green and covered it with French posters; another they painted yellow and filled with old wooden window frames. The tin ceiling suggests a black night, while the walls in the entrance area evoke a lazy blue sky. A flecked carpet mimics a cobblestone street. This all does not come off as a movie-set version of a French town, but it reinforces the feeling of the buildings captured in the photos of the de Waals' honeymoon in Provence.</p>
        <p>It is apt that the deWaals chose rural yet up-and-coming Newton as the setting for their restaurant. Mr. deWaal affectionately refers to it as ''the little town that could.'' With Andre's Restaurant securely in place, I think it can.</p>
        <p>Andre's Restaurant  182 Spring Street, Newton  (973) 300-4192</p>
        <p>EXCELLENT</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- European alley cafe replicated indoors.  SERVICE -- Homey yet upscale.  SMOKING -- Not permitted.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Menu changes twice monthly. Present menu includes  smoked salmon bacon; crab cakes; spicy beef and noodle salad; penne pasta; sweetbreads; duck sampler; mahi-mahi; tuna steak; lamb loin; sea scallops and chicken in goat cheese; creme brulee; bullseye cheesecake and blueberry lemon tart.  PRICE RANGE -- soup and appetizers: $5 to $8.50; main courses: $19 to $23.50; desserts: $6; five-course meal, $37 to $44.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major accepted.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended (only 11 tables).  HOURS -- Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 5 to 9 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5 to 10 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- All on one level.  RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
