<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Seven-Year Lesson in Investing: Expect the Unexpected, and More</title>
    <meta content="09RETI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Korben, Eric M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Sheldon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brill, Jack A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinnel, Russel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evensky, Harold R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DE1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Seven-Year Lesson in Investing: Expect the Unexpected, and More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Assessment of second-quarter and seven-year results of hypothetical mutual fund portfolios managed by Eric M Korben, Sheldon Jacobs, Jack A Brill, Russell Kinnel and Harold R Evensky; managers each began with $50,000 on July 17, 1993; exercise concludes with results from second quarter of 2000; tables; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a way, it has been a seven-year cold shower for the idea that an ordinary investor can do any better than the market, even with expert advice.</p>
        <p>Because saving for retirement had become a crucial issue for Americans, The New York Times in 1993 asked five mutual-fund experts how they would invest a hypothetical nest egg of $50,000 for someone who planned to retire in 20 years or more. Each quarter since then, the five portfolios have been reviewed and fine-tuned and their performances compared in these pages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a way, it has been a seven-year cold shower for the idea that an ordinary investor can do any better than the market, even with expert advice.</p>
        <p>Because saving for retirement had become a crucial issue for Americans, The New York Times in 1993 asked five mutual-fund experts how they would invest a hypothetical nest egg of $50,000 for someone who planned to retire in 20 years or more. Each quarter since then, the five portfolios have been reviewed and fine-tuned and their performances compared in these pages.</p>
        <p>With results from the second quarter of 2000, the exercise concludes, and the participants discuss what they, and investors, have learned along the way.</p>
        <p>Three of the five participants tripled their money in the seven years ended June 30. The portfolio overseen by Eric M. Kobren, president of the Kobren Insight Group and editor of Fidelity Insight in Wellesley Mass., did the best over all, with a cumulative gain of 210.19 percent.</p>
        <p>Close behind were the portfolio managed by Sheldon Jacobs, editor of the No-Load Fund Investor, in Irvington, N.Y., at 204.42 percent, and the portfolio of ''socially responsible'' funds assembled by Jack A. Brill, vice president of Natural Investment Services in San Diego, with a cumulative gain of 200.10 percent. .</p>
        <p>In fourth place was a portfolio tended most recently by Russel Kinnel, editor of Morningstar Fund Investor in Chicago, at 146.97 percent. The fifth entry, managed by Harold R. Evensky, an investment adviser in Coral Gables, Fla., finished at 123.63 percent, according to Lipper Inc.</p>
        <p>None of the portfolios, however, managed to outperform the market over the seven-year period. In retrospect, simply investing the whole stake in the Vanguard 500 Index fund and letting it ride would have done better, yielding a gain of 277.51 percent.</p>
        <p>But overall performance was intended to be just one dimension of the exercise. Investors also had a chance to explore the thinking behind mutual fund management as the managers discussed strategies, styles and selections each quarter.</p>
        <p>The object lessons were limited by the unexpected way the economy and the stock market have moved over the last seven years -- almost exclusively straight up. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index returned an annual average of 20.625 percent over the period; by contrast, stocks returned an annual average of 12.1 percent in the 65 years from 1926 to 1990, according to Ibbotson Associates in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Big growth stocks dominated the stock market for much of the last seven years, lifting the performance of large-capitalization index funds and dragging down the returns of actively managed mutual funds, which tend to own smaller stocks. According to Morningstar Inc., just 21.4 percent of 990 actively managed domestic diversified equity funds in its database outperformed the S.&amp; P. 500 over the period.</p>
        <p>And the stock market has become more volatile in the 1990's, jumping or slumping abruptly -- as a whole or sector by sector -- in hard-to-predict ways. Fast-moving markets stumped the experts several times along the way.</p>
        <p>Even so, stocks -- and funds that hold them -- are still the best way to meet long-term financial goals like retirement, the experts said, because they have always outperformed other investments over time.</p>
        <p>''This exercise shows what a prudent, diversified mutual fund portfolio can return, given time and compounding,'' Mr. Kobren said. ''It isn't necessary to dart in and out of the market, take foolish risks in the hopes of scoring a home run or get overly complicated by owning dozens of funds.''</p>
        <p>ALL five participating managers continue to recommend diversified fund portfolios, even though diversification was a far from optimal strategy during much of the last seven years. Carefully balancing big stocks with smaller ones, or American issues with international issues, turned out to be counterproductive because of the relentless market leadership of the big-growth stocks.</p>
        <p>But there is no way of knowing if the same will be true in the future. ''I still thoroughly believe in diversification for my own portfolio and for my clients,'' Mr. Kobren said, ''because you can never know with certainty which sectors of the market will yield the biggest returns in the future.''</p>
        <p>Sticking to a diversified portfolio while market favorites come and go can be trying, the experts conceded. ''Long-term investing is my mantra and my faith,'' Mr. Evensky said, ''but I will admit that sometimes, long-term seems interminable.''</p>
        <p>The exercise also reaffirmed the power of the financial markets to confound expectations, said John Rekenthaler, now director of research at Morningstar, who started the portfolio that was later managed by Susan Dzuibinski and then Mr. Kinnel. He stuffed his initial portfolio with funds holding small stocks, value issues and overseas holdings; they had been superior performers over the long term but had slumped around the time the exercise began, and Mr. Rekenthaler thought they looked ripe for a rebound. As it turned out, though, none caught up with the large caps. ''Expect to be surprised,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rekenthaler said his own results occasionally caught him off guard. ''I remembered my good picks,'' he said, ''and then forgot the fact that I had a big stake in emerging-markets funds as the whole sector tanked.'' The lesson: Track your investment results carefully, so you can learn from your decisions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brill's success ratifies an investing approach that seemed unorthodox and untried in 1993. ''Socially responsible investing works,'' he said. ''We have competitive returns because our screening identifies high-quality, well-managed companies.'' He added, ''I never tried to outsmart the market or get in on hot sectors.''</p>
        <p>When he started, he said, there were only about 15 comprehensively screened social-investing funds, plus an additional 25 funds without the social label that qualified based on the types of stocks they held. Those 40 choices have grown to more than 150 today, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evensky recommends diversifying within asset classes. In that vein, he used to include in client portfolios three funds run by managers who choose large-cap growth stocks. In his hypothetical portfolio for this exercise, though, he felt he had room for only one, and chose the Yacktman Fund, whose subsequent performance was disappointing. These days, he prefers index funds for large-cap growth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evensky said he learned another lesson the hard way: not to make a big bet on a new fund idea. At the outset he allocated some of his portfolio to the Barr Rosenberg Market Neutral fund, which aims to neutralize market volatility through a mix of long and short sales. The idea fell flat; Mr. Evensky said the fund's managers told him its undoing was a run of extraordinary behavior by the stock market that no one could have anticipated. Now, Mr. Evensky said, he advises waiting for a few years until a new concept has proved itself in different market environments.</p>
        <p>Realigning a portfolio periodically is wise, all five experts said, because strong performance in one area could lead to an ill-advised concentration of assets. The five hypothetical portfolios could be rebalanced quarterly, and generally were; once a year is probably often enough for most long-term investors.</p>
        <p>Finally, don't be too quick to sell, Mr. Evensky said. After he researches a fund and buys its shares, he will stick with it through two years of bad times if performance seems likely to improve. But he dumps funds immediately when managers change their stripes, say by adding big overseas positions or by switching style from growth to value-oriented.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
