<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Front Seat Now, Forgetting the Back-Seat Misery of Youth</title>
    <meta content="09TOWN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7DD1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Front Seat Now, Forgetting the Back-Seat Misery of Youth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>DARIEN, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Purdy Our Towns column discusses family driving vacations and ways parents keep children amused on long trips (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Lisa Del Papa's childhood, vacations meant long hours of enforced intimacy in the family car. ''We did one to Cape Cod at that age when you can't stand being with your parents and I couldn't stand Cape Cod,'' she said. ''I wrote to my best friend every night that I hated vacation.''</p>
        <p>So there she was this week, at age 34, of free will and sound mind, idling with her husband and a 13-month-old daughter at the Connecticut Turnpike rest area here, ready to get back in their car, packed with luggage and toys. ''Now we have Ellen and we're going to Cape Cod,'' she said cheerily, holding her daughter. ''I hear it's beautiful.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Lisa Del Papa's childhood, vacations meant long hours of enforced intimacy in the family car. ''We did one to Cape Cod at that age when you can't stand being with your parents and I couldn't stand Cape Cod,'' she said. ''I wrote to my best friend every night that I hated vacation.''</p>
        <p>So there she was this week, at age 34, of free will and sound mind, idling with her husband and a 13-month-old daughter at the Connecticut Turnpike rest area here, ready to get back in their car, packed with luggage and toys. ''Now we have Ellen and we're going to Cape Cod,'' she said cheerily, holding her daughter. ''I hear it's beautiful.''</p>
        <p>More proof that those who forget the lessons of family car vacations are doomed to repeat them.</p>
        <p>Nationwide amnesia has struck again as close relatives climb into close quarters and drive away from everything back home, except one another. It's that special moment, or many moments, or several days (a seeming eternity, really) when, as one man said, pointing to his laminated-looking children in the back of the family van, ''they're bored and we're driving.''</p>
        <p>The petroleum industry, in a humanitarian move, tried to spare Americans the car trip this summer by charging more for a gallon of gas than the going rate for a cup of coffee. But still, we blithely tank up on latte and unleaded, and head for the open road.</p>
        <p>After all, as only genome mappers can explain, we're wired to drive.</p>
        <p>''The first hour was O.K.,'' Ms. Del Papa reported on the second morning of a planned three-day trip from Princeton to Cape Cod. ''We've been listening to a Mickey Mouse tape. I've been singing politically incorrect songs like 'Ten Little Indians.' '' Ms. Del Papa said that as her husband, Jan-Olaf, drove, she tried to toss toys to her daughter faster than Ellen was dropping them. It was cherished quality time with her, but when Ms. Del Papa was asked to imagine her future, say six hours hence, she said, ''We're going to have whiskey in the car.''</p>
        <p>Whiskey, and other alcoholic beverages, remain legally incorrect in the car (in fact, one mother said she and her children passed the miles singing ''Ninety-Nine Bottles of Ginger Ale on the Wall''). But recent upgrades in family car vacations include E-ZPass, Gameboys and sibling-rivalry-resistant triple-row seating.</p>
        <p>The TV helps,'' said Joy Borbidge, traveling home from North Carolina to New Hampshire with her husband, two teen-age daughters and a 10-year-old son. ''Everybody has their own personal CD player.'' Joy and her husband, Brad, had the Dead on the radio, and the kids had the Backstreet Boys and Christina Aguilera on their headphones.</p>
        <p>THERE was also a film festival under way in the family Windstar. ''We just left Philadelphia and the kids said it will take four movies to get home,'' Mrs. Borbidge said. ''They're watching 'Big Daddy' now. They already watched 'The First Wives Club.' The girls don't want to watch 'Star Wars.' You know how it is.'' It was a rec room on radials, and at one point Mr. Borbidge relinquished the wheel and jumped in the back to catch the screening of ''Dances With Wolves.''</p>
        <p>Everyone was anticipating 15-year-old Jenna's threat to take the wheel once they got into New Hampshire, where her learner's permit would allow her to drive. ''We're going to hide,'' said her 14-year-old sister, Jamy.</p>
        <p>Many adults manage a pioneer spirit about car trips. They assure you that if they leave early and traffic is moving and the back-seat wrestling doesn't necessitate emergency room visits, they can make it from the tip of Long Island to the Bering Strait by sundown. And their children don't need electronic toys, they're thrilled playing hangman and studying French infinitives.</p>
        <p>Of course, there's another side to this story. Joe and Sue Gallen were saying how well the trip from Reading, Pa., to Maine with their three boys was going. It was nothing like the rollicking adventure Mr. Gallen had growing up in a family of eight children who traveled the country in a motor home one summer, forgetting the oldest child at one stop and smashing the vehicle.</p>
        <p>But the Gallens were having fun, they said. The traffic was moving along, they were playing games with their boys, and the older one was even reading to the younger ones.</p>
        <p>To which a little voice squeaked from the back seat: ''And I'm sick of it.''</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
