<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY DIARY</title>
    <meta content="09DIAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDA1F39F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Judging by their Fourth of July parade, the citizens of Montclair don't think many truths are self-evident.</p>
        <p>How else explain why -- among the Scout troops, aged veterans, beat-up old (nostalgic) cars, tinny brass bands and waving local officials -- so many brandished placards and other props proclaiming such causes as fair labor practices (Children Against Sweat Shops), opposition to a defense scheme of the 80's (Peace Voters Against Star Wars, both of them), the eschewing of meat (one man with a sign that said ''Vegetarian''), keeping guns out of the hands of children (some of the Million Moms), keeping bullets out of bears (men and women, waving teddy bears in protest of a proposed two-day bear hunting season) and breast feeding (La Leche League, all the way from Morristown).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Judging by their Fourth of July parade, the citizens of Montclair don't think many truths are self-evident.</p>
        <p>How else explain why -- among the Scout troops, aged veterans, beat-up old (nostalgic) cars, tinny brass bands and waving local officials -- so many brandished placards and other props proclaiming such causes as fair labor practices (Children Against Sweat Shops), opposition to a defense scheme of the 80's (Peace Voters Against Star Wars, both of them), the eschewing of meat (one man with a sign that said ''Vegetarian''), keeping guns out of the hands of children (some of the Million Moms), keeping bullets out of bears (men and women, waving teddy bears in protest of a proposed two-day bear hunting season) and breast feeding (La Leche League, all the way from Morristown).</p>
        <p>In the spirit of fair debate, maybe there should have been equal-time paraders. Picture a contingent marching for child labor, and in an act multitasking, another in favor of having children shoot bears and then eat them. And how about Fathers for Formula?</p>
        <p>There would have been no further need for fireworks.</p>
        <p>(May the Fourth be with you.)</p>
        <p>THE SUBLIMINAL MESSAGE OF OPSAIL  Gray hulks in the harbor stand fast  As Eagle sails gracefully past  Where tall ships and warships unite,  Displaying our barque and our bite.</p>
        <p>Some residents of Weehawken -- the more hungry ones, or those with yellowing kitchen floors -- were less than enamored with last week's OpSail, featuring Bill and Hillary Clinton and a cast of millions.</p>
        <p>All day long on Tuesday, customers of the Pathmark on Park Avenue circled the parking lot looking for a space. Forget it. The day's gapers had gobbled up the spots.</p>
        <p>Ungenerously, of course, they saw it more as Photo OpSail than OpSail.</p>
        <p>Two little boys, splashing about the Glen Rock pool, were comparing their amphibious strengths.</p>
        <p>Boy one: ''I'm ruler of the land and king of the ocean. Plus, I can hold my breath for three whole minutes.''</p>
        <p>Boy two: ''I can touch the bottom of the pool with my nose, hold my breath for four minutes and I eat plankton.''</p>
        <p>Boy one: ''Really? Does that come with a Happy Meal toy?''</p>
        <p>DEIRDRE FLANAGAN WARD</p>
        <p>And to show how McDonald's has permeated (or perhaps exterminated) today's culture . . .</p>
        <p>Overheard outside a McDonald's in Rockaway Townsquare Mall:</p>
        <p>Small boy: ''Grandma, if you take me to McDonald's I'll give you a big hug.''</p>
        <p>Grandma: ''And if I don't take you, what will you do?''</p>
        <p>Small boy: ''Give you a big hug anyway.''</p>
        <p>Needless to say, they went to McDonald's.</p>
        <p>AUDREY CORN</p>
        <p>OLD RHYME,</p>
        <p>NEW RHYME</p>
        <p>Mother, may I go out to swim?</p>
        <p>Yes, my darling daughter,</p>
        <p>Hang your clothes on a hickory limb</p>
        <p>And bring your bottle of water.</p>
        <p>EDMUND CONTI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
