<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; A Victory That Was Much More</title>
    <meta content="Y09RHO$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davenport, Lindsay</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DB1538F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; A Victory That Was Much More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column on Venus Williams's victory over Lindsay Davenport in Wimbledon Tennis Tournament, first victory by black woman since 1958; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VENUS WILLIAMS is not the classic pioneer. Not understated, muted, conciliatory. Not grateful. Maybe it's a sign of the times, maybe a mark of personality or the protective armor of the two black women who came to this title round before her.</p>
        <p>But when Lindsay Davenport's forehand volley dribbled into the net yesterday, Williams reacted just like any winner. She leaped a mile high at Center Court. She was suddenly the winning pitcher in the last game of the World Series, the triumphant boxer whose opponent can't answer the bell, the ballerina.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VENUS WILLIAMS is not the classic pioneer. Not understated, muted, conciliatory. Not grateful. Maybe it's a sign of the times, maybe a mark of personality or the protective armor of the two black women who came to this title round before her.</p>
        <p>But when Lindsay Davenport's forehand volley dribbled into the net yesterday, Williams reacted just like any winner. She leaped a mile high at Center Court. She was suddenly the winning pitcher in the last game of the World Series, the triumphant boxer whose opponent can't answer the bell, the ballerina.</p>
        <p>Williams gathered herself, shook hands with Davenport, then rushed into the stands and hugged her sister Serena and her father, Richard. She was exuberant and all smiles. Later she would talk about the dress she bought for the Wimbledon champions ball in anticipation of this moment.</p>
        <p>''This was meant to be,'' she said. ''I worked hard all my life. I had a lot of sacrifices, I had a lot of injuries and I had a lot of tough losses, too. But I didn't let that get to me. I kept working hard and I kept believing, even at some points when I didn't have a reason to because I played so badly sometimes.''</p>
        <p>In one two-minute answer, the 20-year-old Williams defined the quality of faith that sustains the march of history.</p>
        <p>This women's final was not a classic match but a survivor's game. Neither player could consistently hold service, and each made unforced errors. There were moments of brilliance -- Davenport's precise placement, Williams's running down balls and hitting scorching winners. But there were more bumbles than blazing winners.</p>
        <p>Williams was serving in the second set, leading five games to four, but couldn't hold serve to close out the match. She had to wait to win in a tie breaker.</p>
        <p>''I just don't think I was calm,'' Williams said. ''I wanted to hit the ball before it could even get over the net.''</p>
        <p>But this was a match in which the quality of the moment was greater than the quality of the points. History held center stage, and the statistics were part of the daily routine: the first black woman to win Wimbledon since Althea Gibson won her second championship here in 1958; the first to play for the championship since Zina Garrison in 1990; the third African-American to win Wimbledon, joining Arthur Ashe and Gibson.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Williams said that Garrison had been the light who illuminated her hopes for a championship. Ignited hope that young African-American women could actually go to England and compete for a championship.</p>
        <p>''Maybe the first time that Wimbledon meant a lot to me was when Zina was doing so well in 1990,'' Williams said. ''When she beat Monica in the quarterfinal. And she beat Steffi in the semis. That meant a lot to us. We would be out there practicing on the courts in the afternoon when Zina won against Monica, against Steffi.''</p>
        <p>Garrison was in the friends box yesterday afternoon and had to keep herself from crying. ''In 1990 when I got to the finals, it was like, 'O.K., we're getting close' '' Garrison said. ''Ten years later, for it to actually happen, it's awesome. I called home and my friend said her phone was ringing off the hook.</p>
        <p>''I still get a lot of reaction for what I did in 1990. I think with African-Americans, we know this is a white sport. When something happens like this, everybody understands just how tough they had to be, how much stronger they had to be to get to that level.''</p>
        <p>When someone asked Williams if she had any idea how difficult the journey must have been for Gibson in 1958, Williams gave an answer that paid tribute to the past and shed light on a struggle that continues.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, it had to be hard because people were unable to see past color,'' she said. ''Still these days it's hardly any different because you have to realize it's only been 40 years. How can you change years and centuries of being biased in 40 years?</p>
        <p>''So, realistically, not too much has changed. But I really appreciate how hard it was. You realize not everyone wants you to win, not everyone's going to support you -- and that's O.K.''</p>
        <p>Venus Williams is very much her father's daughter. During a far-reaching discussion on Friday, Richard Williams had chosen to offer hard-edged snapshots of history in order to make a larger point about his two daughters' presence here.</p>
        <p>''Most black people want to do what white America does,'' Richard Williams said. ''That's why a lot of them are not successful. Lots of time most black people, if they have something good going for themselves, they'll move.</p>
        <p>''What we've learned is that we have to go back and look at our history. Many blacks don't know their history, so we do what we are told to do, like we did many, many years ago in the fields. Once you learn your history, you don't have to go and move out of the neighborhood you're in.''</p>
        <p>He also talked about how Americans have spent succeeding centuries reconstructing slavery and its impact on generations, discovering who and what they are and, by extension, what the United States is.</p>
        <p>Venus and Serena Williams are large pieces of that puzzle. They don't walk the thin line between embracing who they are and trying not to offend mainstream sensibilities.</p>
        <p>''We ain't walking a line,'' Richard Williams had said a day before the women's singles final. ''We are the line. We are the history. That's why you're here talking to me and everyone else is right now. Because when people see the history, they want to know, 'What's going on?'</p>
        <p>''When we first came up, they said, 'They're cocky; you can't talk to them. They're crazy. Something's wrong.' They didn't know whether we was a bulldog, a hound dog or what -- but they knew it was something. But as they kept talking to us, they learned that we knew our history; we don't need to walk no line.''</p>
        <p>Richard Williams continued: ''Any time a man walks a line, that means he needs something to follow.  We ain't following nothing. Now, if you want to follow behind us, great. You'll learn how to get to the top of the mountain.''</p>
        <p>Richard Williams was 16 years old in 1958 when Gibson won her second Wimbledon. He had no idea that it would take 42 years for another African-American woman to win the third, had no idea that the woman would be his daughter.</p>
        <p>But yesterday he waved off reporters who wanted his perspective on the match. He had talked enough this week.</p>
        <p>''I'm through,'' he said. ''This is Venus's day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
