<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="09PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1213567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DF1738F93AA35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HARLEM  A New 'Romeo and Juliet' In the Hip-Hop Nation</p>
        <p>Latino Montagues meet African-American Capulets in the second annual Classical Theater of Harlem Shakespeare Festival production of ''Romeo and Juliet.'' The classic love story is set in the ''hip-hop nation,'' and will be performed in modern dress outdoors at the Harlem School of Arts Courtyard Theater. The show opens Friday and runs through Aug. 6.</p>
        <p>This production of ''Romeo and Juliet'' seeks to give voice to concerns of the ethnically and culturally diverse young adults of Harlem. The production has created nearly 60 professional theater jobs in Harlem, and seeks to re-establish Harlem as a theatrical and cultural center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HARLEM  A New 'Romeo and Juliet' In the Hip-Hop Nation</p>
        <p>Latino Montagues meet African-American Capulets in the second annual Classical Theater of Harlem Shakespeare Festival production of ''Romeo and Juliet.'' The classic love story is set in the ''hip-hop nation,'' and will be performed in modern dress outdoors at the Harlem School of Arts Courtyard Theater. The show opens Friday and runs through Aug. 6.</p>
        <p>This production of ''Romeo and Juliet'' seeks to give voice to concerns of the ethnically and culturally diverse young adults of Harlem. The production has created nearly 60 professional theater jobs in Harlem, and seeks to re-establish Harlem as a theatrical and cultural center.</p>
        <p>''Romeo and Juliet;'' opens Friday 7:30 p.m., performances run through Aug. 6; Harlem School of Arts Courtyard Theater, 645 St. Nicholas Avenue, near 141st Street; $12; students and people over 65, $10; groups of 10 or more, $8; (212) 539-8828.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM MILE  Old TV and Current Music At the Jewish Museum</p>
        <p>Tuesday night is taken. the Summer Nights series at the Jewish Museum kicks off this week with Tuesday evening screenings of television treasures from the National Jewish Archive of Broadcasting, live music on the first floor, food on sale in Cafe Weissman (the museum's kosher restaurant) and access to the current exhibitions at the museum.</p>
        <p>Opening night (on Tuesday) will feature music by the Howard Fishman Quartet, specializing in New Orleans-style swing, jazz and blues. The screenings have the theme of Weddings, with episodes of ''The Golden Girls,'' ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show'' and other shows.</p>
        <p>Next week's event  features Chris Rael and Deep Singh, members of an East-West rock band who play Indian tabla music (Hindustani classical music played on a sitar and small hand drums), fused with rock. The theme of the screenings will be Bar and Bat Mitzvahs, including episodes of ''Diff'rent Strokes,'' ''The Dick Van Dyke Show'' and ''The Wonder Years,'' the cast of which is shown here.</p>
        <p>Summer Nights; this Tuesday and next Tuesday, July 18, 5 to 9 p.m.; The Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street; free, with a pay-what-you-wish donation; (212) 423-3200.</p>
        <p>FLUSHING  Burmese New Year Festival With Splashing Ceremony</p>
        <p>Mohinga (lemon grass seafood soup) and Kao Shwe (Asian vegetables with rice noodles) will be among the Burmese dishes offered at the sixth annual Rakhaing Thingyan-Burmese New Year Water Festival today. In addition to food, fashion, music and art, a major part of the Thingyan (which means renewal) Water Festival is getting wet. The New Year's tradition involves joyously splashing friends and family with water to cleanse away last year's troubles.</p>
        <p>The Thingyan Association invites participants to ''splash someone special.''</p>
        <p>Sixth annual Rakhaing Thingyan-Burmese New Year Water Festival 2000; today, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Queens Botanical Garden, 43-50 Main Street (near Daliah Street); free; (212) 580-1687.</p>
        <p>ALSO AROUND TOWN</p>
        <p>ASPHALT PLAYGROUNDS -- The Police Athletic League is closing off streets in 200 neighborhoods beginning tomorrow in order to give children safe places in which to play during the out-of-school warm- weather period; the program makes possible hopscotch, basketball, any number of games, arts and crafts, music as well as dance; free; for information: (212) 477-9450.</p>
        <p>RIVER MUSIC -- The first of two shows in the Sunset Series ''Music and Movement on the Hudson'' is Tuesday (the second show is scheduled for Aug. 17), with international performers; the programs include Moroccan music presented by Sout al-Ghorba, Jamaican reggae and ska by Floyd Lloyd; the master of ceremonies is Jack Silbert; Tuesday, 7 p.m.; Chelsea Piers, Pier 62 at 23rd Street; free; information: (212) 477-8161.</p>
        <p>GONE FISHING -- Children under 16 can participate in Macy's Fishing Frenzy. The workshops are called Meet the Fish, Water World and Fish for Fun. Poles are provided, and all fish that are caught are released; Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Prospect Park, near the Kate Wollman Rink; free; for information: (718) 965-8954.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
