<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music, Minus Those Pesky Composers</title>
    <meta content="06TOMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center Festival</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6D8113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music, Minus Those Pesky Composers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini article on multimedia display at Columbia University's Low Library, in conjunction with Lincoln Center Festival's Electronic Evolution series of six interactive sound and image installations, which offers glimpse into where music as a whole may be headed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Lincoln Center Festival's five-concert Electronic Evolution series last month surveyed the history of electronic music, starting with the 1920 invention of the theremin, the electronic instrument that looks like a radio transmitter and was once a staple of sci-fi movie soundtracks. These rewarding concerts showed where electronic music has come from.</p>
        <p>But a free preconcert event in the Low Library at Columbia University showed where electronic music, maybe music as a whole, could be going. It was a multimedia display of six interactive sound and image installations, and it was packed with mostly young adults. For this veteran concert goer, the glimpse into the interactive musical future was at once fascinating and disconcerting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Lincoln Center Festival's five-concert Electronic Evolution series last month surveyed the history of electronic music, starting with the 1920 invention of the theremin, the electronic instrument that looks like a radio transmitter and was once a staple of sci-fi movie soundtracks. These rewarding concerts showed where electronic music has come from.</p>
        <p>But a free preconcert event in the Low Library at Columbia University showed where electronic music, maybe music as a whole, could be going. It was a multimedia display of six interactive sound and image installations, and it was packed with mostly young adults. For this veteran concert goer, the glimpse into the interactive musical future was at once fascinating and disconcerting.</p>
        <p>The gizmos on display were not inventions of computer geeks who had drifted into music. All of the creators are composers pursuing advanced degrees who have gotten increasingly involved with computer software. Yet these interactive inventions may someday put composers out of business, at least those who cling to the quaint idea that composing means one person in private putting notes and sounds together for later public performance.</p>
        <p>Just compare that passive, laughably outmoded way of experiencing new music with the fun and challenge of ''Soundscape Navigator,'' an experimental installation by R. Luke DuBois and Mark McNamara. It allows you to navigate through a virtual-reality space, a kind of room where wildly varied sounds with corresponding images, like amazing sonograms, appear, collide and vanish on wall-size panels. Moving around the ''room'' with a hand-held lever changes the way the sounds are ''spatialized,'' to quote the composers, though perhaps ''designers'' would be a more apt billing.</p>
        <p>In a way ''Soundscape Navigator'' turns Messiaen's conviction that harmonies have colors into glaring, fast-paced reality. Instead of just hearing sounds, ''it's as if you are driving around in them,'' said Douglas Irving Repetto, the producer of the exhibit and the creator of ''BeatyBeatyBeaty and the Infinite Grid,'' a software-based instrument that allows the user to improvise highly complex music. Or so I was told. Try as I did to follow the explanations of ''gains,''  ''frequency curves'' and ''multitrack graphical interface,'' I had no idea what the instrument really does, though it's surely ingenious.</p>
        <p>''Tinkering With Speech,'' an installation by Timothy Polashek, was easy to use and attracted lots of partakers. It enables you to collaborate in the creation of a text-sound work by speaking into a microphone and watching the computer-generated results. The sounds of the words are fragmented in every way imaginable: syllables get shifted around, vowels are substituted for one another, parts of words are combined into new words, some as nonsensical as anything in Gertrude Stein.</p>
        <p>Jason Freeman's ''Locust Tree in Flower,'' the title taken from a William Carlos Williams poem, is essentially a four-minute ''composition,'' an aural and visual representation of the poem. Listening through earphones, the ''audience member,'' to use Mr. Freeman's term, is asked to speak selected syllables and words from the short poem into a microphone. The software responds by mixing, looping and otherwise altering the speech sounds and corresponding images.</p>
        <p>The biggest hit was ''Interactions,'' by David Birchfield. The user -- again, just one at a time -- begins by typing into a computer an Internet address of his or her choice. This generates a burst of images on two adjoining screens. Concurrently, the installation presents the user with two sets of sounds triggered by the imagery, one in each cup of the earphones. The user indicates a preference by tapping one of two small drums with a mallet. This causes the rejected sound source to alter its content more in line with the chosen one. But when the sneaky rejected source gets too similar, the previously chosen one changes drastically. So in a sense the two sides are constantly fighting for the fickle user's favor.</p>
        <p>Watching people thwacking the drums with glints in their eyes, you could sense the seductive allure of ''Interactions.'' All concertgoers have had the experience of sitting impatiently through pieces they didn't much like, thinking: ''What's the music doing now?''  ''Why can't it repeat that pretty good thing it did before?''  ''I wish the pace would pick up.''  ''What a bore!''  ''Ah, I like that; it's sort of neat.'' With this installation, the listener finally has the power to change the piece immediately, to cater to his or her own taste, mood and attention span.</p>
        <p>Give listeners this degree of choice, and they are likely to use it. Of course, advanced interactive technology, we are told, will not eliminate the need for composers but simply expand available sound resources and create a role for newly engaged audiences. I would say to the composer-computer whizzes who are inventing this stuff, ''Be careful what you wish for.'' I will not soon forget the giddy sense of empowerment that every user of ''Interactions'' projected while I stood by, sort of nervous. I mean, who will care what critics think when music becomes an interactive endeavor?</p>
        <p>For those of us who persist in thinking of a musical composition as a creative statement of a trained and artistic individual, there was one reassuring thing: though the users of these interactive installations worked alone, having witnesses watching and listening on extra earphones seemed a large part of the enjoyment. So composers as we known them may disappear someday. Yet perhaps the concert, or at least a new kind of collective listening experience, will continue.</p>
        <p>In any event, the new technology is astounding. But sometimes I'm glad I'm not younger than I am.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
