<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haskell Offers Next Test For a Healthy Dixie Union</title>
    <meta content="06HASK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Haskell Invitational</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DD133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haskell Offers Next Test For a Healthy Dixie Union</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <dateline>OCEANPORT, N.J., Aug. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dixie Union, after series of disappointing finishes, will run in Haskell Invitational at Monmouth Park (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disappointment of Dixie Union's fifth-place finish in the 1999 Breeders' Cup Juvenile was still with the trainer Richard Mandella when he made his way to the barn at Gulfstream Park the morning after the race. But even more bad news awaited Mandella: Dixie Union had just run the worst race of his career after having won the Hollywood Juvenile Championship, the Best Pal and the Norfolk, and had sustained a chipped knee that would need surgery.</p>
        <p>So instead of going back to California, he went straight to Kentucky for the operation, Mandella said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disappointment of Dixie Union's fifth-place finish in the 1999 Breeders' Cup Juvenile was still with the trainer Richard Mandella when he made his way to the barn at Gulfstream Park the morning after the race. But even more bad news awaited Mandella: Dixie Union had just run the worst race of his career after having won the Hollywood Juvenile Championship, the Best Pal and the Norfolk, and had sustained a chipped knee that would need surgery.</p>
        <p>So instead of going back to California, he went straight to Kentucky for the operation, Mandella said.</p>
        <p>Dixie Union made a swift recovery, and by early spring Mandella was debating whether to hustle him onto the Triple Crown trail. A streak of bad weather and bad racetracks made that decision for him. So instead of heading to the classics, Dixie Union made his first start as a 3-year-old the day after the Kentucky Derby, winning a six-and-one-half-furlong allowance at Hollywood Park in California.</p>
        <p>In his next two starts, Dixie Union finished second as the favorite in both the Lazaro Barrera Memorial at seven furlongs and the mile-and-a-sixteenth Affirmed Handicap, showing improvement each time. On Sunday, he faces eight others, including the Belmont winner Commendable, the favored More Than Ready and the Triple Crown veterans Captain Steve and Impeachment in the $1 million Haskell Invitational at Monmouth Park. It is a Grade I race.</p>
        <p>''He's had a couple of sprints and a route race,'' Mandella said. ''Right now, he's a very good sprinter we hope will get one and one-eighth miles. He's not quite back to where he was, but I am optimistic.''</p>
        <p>Dixie Union was listed at 6-1 behind the 5-2 favorite More Than Ready, who ticked off five straight victories as a 2-year-old and has been consistent this year, if victorious only once. Captain Steve, winner of the Swaps in his last start, was made the 3-1 second choice,, while the entry of Commendable and Impeachment was 4-1.</p>
        <p>Also entered in the Haskell are Thistyranthasclass, the winner of four straight at Monmouth; Mercaldo; Kiss A Native; and the Ohio Derby winner, Milwaukee Brew, who has won four straight races.</p>
        <p>''There's a bunch of real nice horses in here,'' said Kevin Attard, who will saddle Milwaukee Brew for his father, Tino. ''If the track plays fair, it should be to our advantage.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
