<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Projecting Moderation as the True Moderates Sit on the Sidelines</title>
    <meta content="06TOWN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D8123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Projecting Moderation as the True Moderates Sit on the Sidelines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Our Towns column on meeting of National Black Republican Leadership Caucus at party's convention in Philadelphia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE meeting of the National Black Republican Leadership Caucus should have ranked high on the A-list of happenings at the new Party of Inclusion's convention. The featured politician was Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, a Miss Moderate from the political center, where Gov. George W. Bush of Texas supposedly wants to herd the Grand Old Elephants.</p>
        <p>Surely the joint would be jammed, upbeat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE meeting of the National Black Republican Leadership Caucus should have ranked high on the A-list of happenings at the new Party of Inclusion's convention. The featured politician was Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, a Miss Moderate from the political center, where Gov. George W. Bush of Texas supposedly wants to herd the Grand Old Elephants.</p>
        <p>Surely the joint would be jammed, upbeat.</p>
        <p>But fewer than 30 black Republicans -- and not many others -- gathered in the basement auditorium of the African-American Museum here on Tuesday to listen to Mrs. Whitman. The telegenic tax cutter and supporter of abortion rights tried hard to rally the room.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry she's not our vice-presidential candidate,'' said Doris Oliveira, a black delegate from Tuskegee, Ala. ''But we would have lost the South. They were going to walk out of the convention if Bush had chosen someone who supports a woman's right to choose. Our party's gotten so conservative.''</p>
        <p>Although Governor Bush lavishly embraced the rhetoric and style of moderate Northeastern Republicans, few of those moderates made it to center stage. At the convention four years ago the region's Republican governors were leading men and ladies, helping in the fruitless task of softening the harsh image of the party's nominee, Bob Dole.</p>
        <p>This year, the candidate softened himself. It has been widely noted that Mr. Bush kept the party's conservative elements out of the glare of the convention, but he kept moderates largely out of sight as well. His own language and tone did the job the moderates did for Mr. Dole.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman was a co-chairwoman  for Mr. Dole's convention, along with none other than Governor Bush. Gov. George E. Pataki of New York gave a speech nominating Jack Kemp as vice president, and Gov. John G. Rowland of Connecticut also spoke. Staten Island's Susan Molinari, then a rising Republican in the House of Representatives, gave the keynote address. This year, only Governor Pataki had a prominent role, but it was to read a scripted tribute to the three living Republican former presidents.</p>
        <p>The showcasing of moderate governors that year was a bit of a head fake. Mr. Dole had little intention of shaping the party in their image. Mr. Bush managed to hit moderate chords, even as he reassured many conservatives that he was their man, too.</p>
        <p>''Someone said to me today, Governor Bush sounded like a George Pataki last night with the moderate message he was pushing out,'' Daniel Stewart, the mayor of Plattsburgh, N.Y., and a convention delegate, said Friday.</p>
        <p>With the theme of ''Leave No Child Behind,'' and people of all races turning the convention stage into Mr. Bush's Neighborhood, and lines like ''We Shall Overcome'' in his speech, Mr. Bush left moderates feeling as if he had unleashed the party's inner Connecticut Yankee. It was easier for them to swallow conservative platform planks and his stands against gun control and abortion rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart, New York State's first openly gay mayor, disagrees with Mr. Bush on abortion and is upset with antigay language in the party's platform. But in Mr. Bush he hears the tenor of the Republican Party he knew growing up in New England and living in New York.</p>
        <p>He was buoyed by the appearance of the party's first openly gay convention speaker, even if he spoke about international trade. Sure, some Texas delegates held a silent prayer protest while he spoke, but other Texans applauded. And a New York delegate waving a gay pride flag on the convention floor drew a thumbs up sign from another delegate.</p>
        <p>''I just see it as progress,'' Mr. Stewart said, ''slow progress.''</p>
        <p>The pro-choice moderates expressed delight with the convention, even if most were sidelined. Unlike the 1996 convention, ''there aren't the hard edges,'' Mrs. Whitman said.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki, among the losers in the vice-presidential sweepstakes to the far more conservative Dick Cheney, said Mr. Bush replaced ''the angry face of our party'' symbolized by strident Congressional Republicans, with the ''positive, problem-solving wing of the party'' dominated by Republican governors.</p>
        <p>By prompting a blend of compassion and conservatism, said William Kristol, editor of the conservative Weekly Standard, ''Bush has balanced his own ticket.''</p>
        <p>Unless of course it's another head fake.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
