<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once a Chef, Now With His Own Place</title>
    <meta content="06DINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Riccardo's Seafood House (East Hampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5D61E3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once a Chef, Now With His Own Place</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Riccardo's Seafood House in East Hampton, Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S the American dream. Riccardo Traslavina fled Pinochet's Chile with the help of Amnesty International when he was 17. He landed in New York City and later went to the East End to labor in the kitchens of the restaurants there. With hard work and a lot of talent, he attained the position of sous chef at Nick &amp; Toni's in East Hampton and was picked to be the chef of their Honest Diner. He went on to be executive chef at 95 School Street in Bridgehampton and the Laundry in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>This summer he achieved the ultimate: a place of his own. At Riccardo's Seafood House, on Three Mile Harbor in East Hampton, he is turning out the kind of Hamptons' fare that made him popular, in addition to preparing a number of dishes from his native Chile and other Latin American countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S the American dream. Riccardo Traslavina fled Pinochet's Chile with the help of Amnesty International when he was 17. He landed in New York City and later went to the East End to labor in the kitchens of the restaurants there. With hard work and a lot of talent, he attained the position of sous chef at Nick &amp; Toni's in East Hampton and was picked to be the chef of their Honest Diner. He went on to be executive chef at 95 School Street in Bridgehampton and the Laundry in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>This summer he achieved the ultimate: a place of his own. At Riccardo's Seafood House, on Three Mile Harbor in East Hampton, he is turning out the kind of Hamptons' fare that made him popular, in addition to preparing a number of dishes from his native Chile and other Latin American countries.</p>
        <p>Where else can adventurous East Enders find curanto, camarao na moranga or humitas? The last, a corn puree accompaniment to beautifully grilled tuna, was such a hit at our table that we had our waitress rushing back to the kitchen to get the recipe. (Cut freshly cooked corn off the cob and puree it in a blender with oregano, parsley, oil and vinegar for a side dish with the sweet taste of summer. It's steamed in a corn husk at Riccardo's.)</p>
        <p>That hard working, can't-do-enough-for-you waitress was representative of the staff. This is a team that really clicks. Diners' needs are anticipated. The bringing of replacement silver and decrumbing of the table after every course are automatic. Runners delivering dishes know exactly where to place them.</p>
        <p>The restaurant says summer. The dining room is small and simple, with its white walls interrupted only by playful works by local artists and vintage signs announcing neighboring hamlets. The broad covered porch is where the action is. Here diners enjoy the lovely flower garden with its flaming torches and have good views of moored boats and spectacular sunsets over Three Mile Harbor.</p>
        <p>The food, though, steals the show from those sunsets. The menu changes nightly. Two appetizers to watch for are the lightly warmed arugula salad glossed with a lime vinaigrette and studded with rock shrimp, and a dish simply called grilled tuna salad: a stack of snappy yellow and green beans tossed with black olives and an oregano-mint vinaigrette is crowned with rare slices of herb-marinated tuna -- wonderful!</p>
        <p>Other good choices are the lobster-potato salad blessed with a generous amount of seafood, slices of blue potato and local corn; the imposing shrimp cocktail of four jumbos, and the frisee salad ringed with slices of chorizo and chunks of goat cheese. The gazpacho was a refreshing pick on a hot night, but the New England clam chowder, which also contained striped bass and corn, was thin and watery. Give a miss, too, to the fried calamari, which are tasty (lime-mustard batter) but too chewy.</p>
        <p>One evening we ordered a chunky guacamole with crisply fried flour tortilla triangles. It was listed with the side dishes and cost only $4. I thought it would make a super opener. Someone in the kitchen obviously had the same thought. When I returned a second time, it was found among the appetizers with a price tag of $8. It's still recommended, although it's not as much a bargain.</p>
        <p>Speaking of side dishes, order the French fries ($4); every entree comes with appropriate and interesting accompaniments, but those crisp, greaseless fries are still a treat.</p>
        <p>For the main event, give the South American dishes a try. Curanto translates to a light stew of monkfish, scallops, shrimp, smoked ham, chorizo and chicken over quinoa. It's tasty and satisfying. Also worthy is camarao na moranga, a baked acorn squash filled with lots of firm shrimp in a creamy cheese sauce with black beans and rice on the plate.</p>
        <p>More familiar and equally fine are the sweet steamed lobsters ($18 a pound); the crunchy, lightly breaded fish and chips; the crisp veal chop Milanese with arugula and a yellow and red tomato salad, and a juicy New York strip steak marinated in a chimichurri sauce.</p>
        <p>Portions are large, but save room for dessert. The drunk cake, oozing rum, was a hit, as were the rich chocolate chiffon cake, the silky flan and the banana tres leches. The last is a lush layering of sponge cake, whipped cream and sliced bananas. Only a Brazilian rice pudding, made not from rice but from Brazilian flour sweetened with coconut milk, failed to please. It had only the barest trace of sweetness. Maybe it's an acquired taste.</p>
        <p>Riccardo's Seafood House  313 Three Mile Harbor Road, East Hampton (631) 324-0000.</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Summery spot starring Latin-American seafood.  SERVICE -- Super.  SOUND LEVEL -- Average.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Warm arugula salad with shrimp, grilled tuna salad, lobster-potato salad, guacamole and chips, gazpacho, shrimp cocktail, frisee with chorizo and goat cheese, French fries, fish and chips, camarao na moranga, curanto, steamed lobster, grilled tuna, strip steak, chocolate chiffon cake, banana tres leches, flan, drunk cake.  WINE LIST -- A work in progress, with about 45 selections at $24 to $80; a bit heavy on big reds (cabernet, zinfandel, shiraz, rioja) for a seafood restaurant.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch and brunch, entrees $8 to $14. At dinner, appetizers $7 to $12; entrees $18 to $28; desserts $6.  CREDIT CARDS -- Visa and MasterCard.  HOURS -- Lunch, noon to 3 p.m. Wednesday to Friday; brunch, noon to 3 p.m. Saturday and Sunday. Dinner, 6 to 10 p.m. Monday to Thursday and Sunday, to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- No steps.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
