<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miami Is Back on Top, But Without the Bluster</title>
    <meta content="06MIAM$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Miami</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DD133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miami Is Back on Top, But Without the Bluster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Miami University, ranked fifth in preseason poll, hopes to regain dominance of late 1980's and early '90's; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Miami Hurricanes are back. Tell them that at your own risk.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to go back to old times,'' Dan Morgan, a senior middle linebacker, said, practically scowling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Miami Hurricanes are back. Tell them that at your own risk.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to go back to old times,'' Dan Morgan, a senior middle linebacker, said, practically scowling.</p>
        <p>They like to think they walk with a swagger that is different from the old Miami swagger. They have made it back near the top of the college football polls by struggling, which the old Miami teams never had to do during the run of four national titles during the late 1980's and early 90's.</p>
        <p>These Hurricanes have overcome the transgressions of the old Miami teams -- transgressions that cost the program 31 scholarships and too much time -- and this Miami team does not seem eager to heap new transgressions atop the old ones. All these Hurricanes want to do is to beat teams like Florida State and Virginia Tech for the first time in their careers.</p>
        <p>It is as if the Miami program has been recreated. Butch Davis, the straight-talking former Dallas Cowboys assistant, is entering his sixth season as the Hurricanes' head coach, and he has worked very hard to eliminate any resemblance to the renegade Miami teams that won national titles and had players who were were as good at taunting as playing.</p>
        <p>''Anybody can go out and talk a good game,'' the senior wide receiver Reggie Wayne said. ''We want to go out and play a good game, too.''</p>
        <p>That is not to say that the Hurricanes have completely abandoned trash-talking. This Miami team has a full complement of 85 players on scholarship and returns 14 starters. It finds itself in just about every preseason college football top 10, including the No. 5 spot in the Associated Press ranking that was released yesterday. The Hurricanes have amassed so much talent that the players simply do not want to mess up a good thing.</p>
        <p>''People see us in a very positive light right now,'' Davis said. ''Maybe this year, it's not based on the past. Maybe it's because we have enough athletes to put ourselves in that situation.''</p>
        <p>Right tackle Joaquin Gonzalez, a junior, said this is the first time in his collegiate career that the Hurricanes have felt some pressure to accomplish something big. Gonzalez said Davis told them to behave as if they had been there before, but the fact is, Miami has not had a team of national-championship caliber for several years.</p>
        <p>Miami lost 31 scholarships because of National Collegiate Athletic Association sanctions in 1995. The Hurricanes, down to 58 scholarship players, finished 5-6 in 1997, Davis's third year.</p>
        <p>''That was an eye-opener,'' said Gonzalez, then a redshirt freshman. ''We had been living off the Miami legend -- hiding behind that.''</p>
        <p>Davis figured the best way to deal with that facade was to get rid of it. He instituted rules, and lots of them. His players, figuring the old way did not work, bought into it.</p>
        <p>Two key players missed a mandatory study hall before Miami's 1998 game against U.C.L.A. -- Davis suspended them. He hired a new strength coach. He has supplemented the wide-open passing game that made Miami famous in favor of a no-nonsense running attack.</p>
        <p>With such an emphasis, Davis has accumulated almost too much backfield talent. The Hurricanes enter the season with four excellent running backs: Clinton Portis, James Jackson, Jarrett Payton (Walter Payton's son) and Najeh Davenport. Miami has so much talent in the backfield that Davis said, jokingly, ''We're going to run the wishbone.''</p>
        <p>Kenny Kelly, the quarterback who led the Hurricanes to a stunning victory over Ohio State in the 1999 season opener, has left the program to pursue a professional baseball career with the Tampa Bay Devil Rays. But Davis was prepared for that contingency, too.</p>
        <p>Kelly sustained knee and shoulder injuries late in the season, giving Miami a chance to groom Ken Dorsey, a 6-foot-5-inch sophomore. Dorsey completed nearly 62 percent of his passes and finished with a better quarterback efficiency rating than Kelly's.</p>
        <p>Dorsey started the last three games of the season, all lopsided victories for the Hurricanes.</p>
        <p>''It lessens some of the anxiety and some of the questions you have with a new quarterback,'' Davis said.</p>
        <p>''He's got a heart like a lion,'' Santana Moss, a senior wide receiver who could become a Heisman Trophy candidate, said of Dorsey. ''But he's a young dude, too. We'll have our arms around him like he's our little brother.''</p>
        <p>This is the way the Hurricanes got through the tough times. Many of them decided to come to Miami because they had been Hurricanes fans in the old days.</p>
        <p>Morgan, the linebacker, said, ''I wanted to be one of the people who brought the program back to prominence.''</p>
        <p>The players quickly figured the only way to do that was to listen to Davis, 48, who had been an assistant at Miami under Jimmy Johnson from 1984 to 1988. Davis wants them to play with emotion, but they knew showboating and taunting were out. Moss said they are expected to be men first on the field, then players.</p>
        <p>The 5-6 season showed them that they needed to work harder in the off-season. They were rewarded with a 9-3 season in 1998 in which they ruined the national championship hopes of U.C.L.A. in the final regular-season game. They whipped Ohio State in the 1999 season opener, then rebounded from tough losses to Penn State, East Carolina and Florida State by winning seven of their last eight games. The only loss in that stretch was to Virginia Tech, and they think they learned something from that.</p>
        <p>''I think it brought us together,'' the senior defensive back Al Blades said. ''Now we know what the cost is. I think we work as hard as any team in the nation.''</p>
        <p>Maybe the old Miami players felt that way, too, but those Hurricanes never made a point of publicizing their work ethic. Now Davis anchors his defense around a soft-spoken-yet-ferocious player like Morgan, whom Davis said ''is easy to hold up as a role model.''</p>
        <p>Even during the tougher times, Miami was able to sign most of the top high school players from South Florida and many from elsewhere in the state. But now Miami can sign national-caliber players from outside the state again.</p>
        <p>Davis can even be picky. He said he needs players with character.</p>
        <p>One freshman, D. J. Williams of De La Salle High in Concord, Calif., could start right away at weakside linebacker at Miami. Williams is the kind of player who might not have given Miami much consideration early in Davis's tenure.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they wanted to go through the perception that the program was going to take a dip,'' Davis said.</p>
        <p>Those who were around for the dip seem to be glad they stayed. Blades said any school is subject to lean times. In some ways, the tough times make the good times all that much more enjoyable, even if these Hurricanes do not want these good times to be like the old good times.</p>
        <p>''There definitely have been some growing pains,'' Gonzalez said, ''but you definitely have to go through some things to learn about them.''</p>
        <p>Wayne said, ''Talking, to me, is nothing if you lose.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
