<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Suit of High-Priced, High-Tech Armor to Fend Off Latter-Day Highwaymen</title>
    <meta content="06ARMO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mercedes-Benz</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D8143CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Suit of High-Priced, High-Tech Armor to Fend Off Latter-Day Highwaymen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on new Mercedes-Benz S500 Guard, first production model armored car that Mercedes has brought to United States; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE were speeding along in what the Mercedes-Benz executive at the wheel had promised would be a two-part demonstration of a new S-Class sedan -- 0-to-30 acceleration, followed by 30-to-0 braking. He did not tell us about the third part, involving three guys with .44 Magnums who surrounded the car as it screeched to a halt.</p>
        <p>In less time than it takes to say ''faster than a speeding bullet,'' they fired six shots at the back-seat window next to me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE were speeding along in what the Mercedes-Benz executive at the wheel had promised would be a two-part demonstration of a new S-Class sedan -- 0-to-30 acceleration, followed by 30-to-0 braking. He did not tell us about the third part, involving three guys with .44 Magnums who surrounded the car as it screeched to a halt.</p>
        <p>In less time than it takes to say ''faster than a speeding bullet,'' they fired six shots at the back-seat window next to me.</p>
        <p>As you have probably figured out, I survived, but not because I can deflect bullets like a superhero. The guns were loaded with soap pellets that left pinkish splotches on the window. But Mercedes says that if the ammunition had been real, the ultrathick glass and lightweight door armor would have kept me safe.</p>
        <p>I was riding in a production-model S500 Guard, the first armored car that Mercedes has brought to this country. It looks almost the same as a regular S-Class sedan, but has factory-installed equipment meant to turn an already solid car into a fortress on wheels. In addition to the body armor and the glass (which Mercedes says can withstand gunfire if no three shots are closer together than about 5 inches), the car comes with run-flat tires.</p>
        <p>The S500 Guard starts at $153,950, making it the high-priced entry among factory-built armored cars. BMW's 740iL and 750iL ''Protection'' models are $99,400 and $124,400.</p>
        <p>Both companies are hoping to capitalize on Americans' fear of highway violence. Mercedes expects to find 1,000 buyers a year; BMW projects far fewer sales.</p>
        <p>Worried drivers can have their old cars armored by companies that specialize in making body panels Superman-tough, but Mercedes and BMW are betting that some buyers would rather have factory equipment.</p>
        <p>''Retrofitting means you disassemble and reassemble the car,'' said Rob Allen, manager of special vehicles for Mercedes-Benz and the driver in the demonstration. ''Anytime you have to take a car apart to armor it, when you put it back together, it's not going to be the same.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen said the S500 Guard had 300 armored parts and weighed 800 pounds extra -- not that anyone is likely to notice. ''The security's as incognito as possible because you do not want to be reminded of your own vulnerability,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So nothing in the S500's ''occupant cell'' indicates that the car withstood 128 bullets in a test to see whether it met European security-industry standards for ''street violence where the victim is chosen randomly.''</p>
        <p>But there is more to the S500 Guard than a bullet-resistant body. The engine has been beefed up to handle the extra weight; after all, security experts say that one way to foil bad guys is to make a speedy getaway. The S500 Guard can go from 0 to 60 in 7.3 seconds (about a second longer than an ordinary S500).</p>
        <p>''No special-protection car is impregnable,'' Mr. Allen said. ''The reason you buy a car like this is to get out of trouble. You don't want to just stand there and take shots.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
