<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dot-Com's Smell of Success Is Just the Options Burning</title>
    <meta content="06VIEW$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Posh&amp;Sticks.Com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Timothy Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lauder, Ronald S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lauder, Leonard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6143CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dot-Com's Smell of Success Is Just the Options Burning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY JACK WARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ward, Timothy Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Timothy Jack Ward article describes demise of Posh&amp;Sticks, home-furnishings Internet business financed by group that included Ronald and Leonard Lauder; analyzes reasons for its failure; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OUR multimillion-dollar dot-com folded, and all I got was this lousy T-shirt. Everyone at Posh&amp;Sticks got one, the day our enigmatic -- let's face it, odd -- name was announced last January. Now, it is a bittersweet souvenir from the rush for the elusive e-commerce mother lode. Don't get me wrong: I loved the name and was proud to wear it on my chest. We gave this our best shot, but we are toast.</p>
        <p>The demise of Posh&amp;Sticks, a home-furnishings Internet business financed by a group that included Ronald and Leonard Lauder, was not as splashily public as the recent comeuppance of more deeply financed sites like Boo.com, which sold clothes until it declared bankruptcy, or iVillage, whose stock has pancaked. Our experience is not unique, but it is emblematic of the Great Web Wipeout of '00, when the capital for e-commerce suddenly dried up and the dot-com magic carpet ride ended ingloriously.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OUR multimillion-dollar dot-com folded, and all I got was this lousy T-shirt. Everyone at Posh&amp;Sticks got one, the day our enigmatic -- let's face it, odd -- name was announced last January. Now, it is a bittersweet souvenir from the rush for the elusive e-commerce mother lode. Don't get me wrong: I loved the name and was proud to wear it on my chest. We gave this our best shot, but we are toast.</p>
        <p>The demise of Posh&amp;Sticks, a home-furnishings Internet business financed by a group that included Ronald and Leonard Lauder, was not as splashily public as the recent comeuppance of more deeply financed sites like Boo.com, which sold clothes until it declared bankruptcy, or iVillage, whose stock has pancaked. Our experience is not unique, but it is emblematic of the Great Web Wipeout of '00, when the capital for e-commerce suddenly dried up and the dot-com magic carpet ride ended ingloriously.</p>
        <p>One day before the scheduled debut in mid-June of our high-style home furnishings site, we were told that our board had decided to pull the plug after spending between $14 million and $30 million (the accepted figures around the office). Since then, the business has wound down in a painful series of mass layoffs and liquidation sales. On Monday, we last stragglers packed and moved out of our offices on far West 26th Street, in what had once seemed the hippest dot-com building in town.</p>
        <p>Plug-pulling doesn't quite capture it. It was more like cutting the strings that tethered a magnificent kite, moments before its maiden flight. It seemed like a weird way to toss in the towel. But perhaps no weirder than the notion of selling furniture, lighting and accessories, sight unseen, via the Internet, which is what our business proposed.</p>
        <p>Just nine months earlier, I had been startled out of my normal life by a headhunter who had read a freelance article I wrote for this newspaper about buying furnishings on the Web. To research it I'd spent two months surfing the Web, and that was all it took to make me a kind of world expert in a brand-new sector of e-tailing then being promoted as the next great bonanza, a multibillion-dollar market. By January, I was creative director of the company, overseeing a team that was putting together the visual design of our Web site, along with the company's logo and even its gift wrap.</p>
        <p>When I arrived in November, our competition, sites like GoodHome .com, HomePortfolio.com and Furniture.com, were already well out of the gate. But the group of Israeli software developers who founded the company along with the Lauder brothers, who run the Estee Lauder Companies, promised that we would eclipse the competition with superior technology, which they were building. Our Web site would be chock-full of bells and whistles like streaming video interviews with famous designers and 3-D tools that would let customers take their sofas for a virtual spin before purchase.</p>
        <p>But our competitors already do this, some of us whispered. Our proprietary technology is superior, the software developers, who all seemed to have ties going back to their service as Israeli military officers, assured us.</p>
        <p>We studied our competitors' sites like entomologists. No detail was left unpinned, untweezed or unitemized. We recruited a staff of dozens to create images and text for our site that would rival the glossy shelter magazines we had formerly worked for. We sent columnists to Milan and Tokyo, photographers to shoots in lovely estates in Bedford and sleek lofts in Manhattan. We set up our own state-of-the-art digital photo studio in our offices in the Starrett-Lehigh Building.</p>
        <p>Starrett-Lehigh is a 19-story fill-the-block warehouse, stark and vast with 15-foot-tall lofts. Around every floor are multipane glass window walls. (Look closely, and you'll see them as a backdrop in many fashion magazines and catalogs.) The photographers who enjoyed this once-cheap-to-rent outpost (hence the ubiquitous J. Crew backdrop) were mostly chased out by the building management. The new tenants were style-oriented dot-comers like Screaming Media, Ibeauty and Martha Stewart Omnimedia, who made it the place to be in Silicon Alley.</p>
        <p>The awesome views jazzed my many late nights. I was surrounded by the glittering Hudson river-scape from the George Washington Bridge to the Statue of Liberty. One night I realized I could pick out most of my resume in the skyline: the statuesque Hachette Filipacchi offices at Broadway and West 50th Street, the Times Building tucked behind the Disney development on 42nd Street and the headquarters of Ian Schrager Hotels, aglow like a lighthouse in Hell's Kitchen every night till exactly 11.</p>
        <p>Our warrens of wobbly Ikea desks were almost always gritty to the touch from drywall dust that wafted in each night from a renovation project down the hall. Starrett-Lehigh folklore: the Marthas (as anyone associated with Martha Stewart was known) planned to drive golf carts through their vast offices. Martha herself would drive her Range Rover door to door from her new farm in Katonah and into the building by way of the truck-size freight elevators.</p>
        <p>I found that I could save time, and have fun, by riding my desk chair like a skateboard to get around in our 7,000 square feet of space. The young women down at Ibeauty rode those shiny chrome scooters to the bathrooms, which are a block away down the hall.</p>
        <p>The two halting elevators functioned like a vertical Main Street. As you stopped at a floor, you'd find the citizens to-ing and fro-ing, as if from central casting: hopped-up and pierced-out programmers, teams of 27-year-old venture capitalists dolled up in Prada, everyday-is-casual chief executives, impossibly tall and dour teenage girls on their first go-sees, lost Urbanfetch messengers packing Haagen-Dazs pints (the Breakfast of Champions after start-up all-nighters).</p>
        <p>Where did all that adrenalin in Starrett-Lehigh come from? It was all about the options. We were all thinking options, the stock option plans you just cannot get out of your mind, no matter how hard you try. The hard-knock lesson: options mean nothing if you crash and burn.</p>
        <p>What to call yourself is a big deal for dot-coms. You want something earthshaking, nothing off the rack. In four months our name changed three times, from C2Buy to Ibelli to Posh&amp;Sticks. This decision was overseen by first the entire staff, then by a blue ribbon panel that included branding experts and board members. The time, talent and invention devoted to the name could have launched a thousand ships. Or maybe one Web site.</p>
        <p>One night we had a book party in our photo studio for Marco Pasanella's ''Living in Style Without Losing Your Mind.'' The author rode his vintage Vespa in and parked it at the middle of the room. A Tuscan chef roasted a suckling pig, and Glenfiddich provided a steady stream of old Scotch. It was a wonderful feast, all lighted with votive candles that seemed to mirror the glittering Hudson below.</p>
        <p>But there was trouble on the wind. The Nasdaq had recently gone into its swoon. The date for our Web coming-out had been pushed back. That night, colleagues mused about feeling like the roast pig. I kept my game face. When I saw old friends from the shelter magazines at the party, I invited them to my desk for a sneak preview of our site on my monitor, to mostly rave reviews.</p>
        <p>But the ill omens were growing. Our visionary founding chief executive had been sacked without warning in December, a month after I was hired. Thereafter, our investor-technologists would surface in New York, jet-lagged after overnight flights from Israel; they would attend meetings and pick brains, but clearly they were the ones making the major decisions, not the replacement chief executive, Vivian Behrens, who had been recruited after 20 successful years with Estee Lauder.</p>
        <p>The ad budgets were cut to zero. We'll get the word out with P.R., the technologists said. The site will not work on an Apple, we were told, as if in an afterthought.</p>
        <p>I remember the day the long-awaited proprietary 3-D software the technology developers had promised arrived. It looked to us like off-the-shelf software and was packed in a box marked California Closets, 1996.</p>
        <p>Umpteen variations on our business plan were written. Teams of managers would return from investor pitch meetings empty-handed, only to grind out another draft of the plan.</p>
        <p>Today, no one will say how much money has just been flushed down the e-toilet. We do know that scores of thousands of dollars are owed to freelancers. Part of the pain of failure is knowing that my enthusiasm for the gold rush brought many of our creative people to the company.</p>
        <p>Whatever went wrong wasn't unique to Posh&amp;Sticks. The whole home-furnishings sector of the Web has been in free fall, as entrepreneurs face the cold reality of returned merchandise, the difficulty of ordering and warehousing inventory and the reluctance of manufacturers to undercut their longstanding retailers. Today, less than 1 percent of all furniture sales are made on the Web, and whatever growth is possible will come much more slowly than first anticipated.</p>
        <p>We should have listened to our hearts, or common sense, the instincts that tell you that building a brand from the ground up is a tough sell when your medium is a slow-mo, glitched-out home computer.</p>
        <p>In the final days, colleagues straggled into the office dressed either in shorts and flip-flops or in their interview best. It was a decent gesture from management that we were allowed a staging area for our job searches. Our Web master has joined the Marthas. Dale, a store designer, is with Calvin Klein. Anita, our talented style director, has returned to Elle Decor. When a member of my team lands safely at a next job, I give a little cheer and a silent thank-you.</p>
        <p>A pioneer ancestor of mine, Solomon Hockett, was part of a great wagon train adventure west on the Oregon Trail. His family's wagon was loaded improbably -- but perhaps no more so than a Web site stocked with sofas -- with fruit tree seedlings from the Midwest, which in time provided the orchards for an entire region.</p>
        <p>His exploits made for a great 1950's children's book, ''Tree Wagon,'' which my children have enjoyed growing up with, and we take a special delight in eating an Oregon apple or pear from the market.</p>
        <p>When I'm old, I'll be able to tell the story of being a pioneer, too, of the Great Gold Rush of 1999. I'll edit out the unsavory parts about money, greed and naivete. But I'll remember the elevators, the Hudson view and this silly T-shirt.</p>
        <p>VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
