<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Cares, as Long as It's Natural?</title>
    <meta content="06CONT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santa Fe Natural Tobacco Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DC153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Cares, as Long as It's Natural?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst column questions Santa Fe Natural Tobacco Co's 'natural' cigarettes and other pretend 'natural' products (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF there's a sure-fire way to sell something these days, it's to claim the thing is natural -- even if it's a cigarette.</p>
        <p>''Natural American Spirit Products,'' the Santa Fe Natural Tobacco Company Web  site says solemnly, ''were created based on our belief in the traditional Native American usage of tobacco -- in moderation, in its natural state. Our brand name was chosen as a symbol of respect for this tradition.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF there's a sure-fire way to sell something these days, it's to claim the thing is natural -- even if it's a cigarette.</p>
        <p>''Natural American Spirit Products,'' the Santa Fe Natural Tobacco Company Web  site says solemnly, ''were created based on our belief in the traditional Native American usage of tobacco -- in moderation, in its natural state. Our brand name was chosen as a symbol of respect for this tradition.''</p>
        <p>Above those words is a row of mannered photographs showing hipsters smoking what are presumably Natural American Spirit cigarettes. It's a seductive lineup; you can just see yourself puffing away, joining this gallery of quirky individualists.</p>
        <p>The Natural used to be Roy Hobbs, Bernard Malamud's mythic baseball player, but now it's an obsession that many of us seem to share about a life we have somehow lost. In the grip of something like lapsarian fever, people buy natural cigarettes presumably to be sure that when the cancer comes, it wasn't caused by any horrible chemical additives. They shop at health food stores and pay outrageous prices for herbal remedies to be consumed in blissful indifference to the absence of scientific support or  approval by the Food and Drug Administration. A new book, ''The Soul of the New Consumer'' by David Lewis and Darren Bridger, says the key to success in business is to give people authenticity, and, of course, suggests a few sophisticated techniques for accomplishing this.</p>
        <p>Natural? Authentic? Some fairyland of trees and grass that we can traverse in our sport utility vehicles? For women, a truly natural life probably means having a dozen babies and spending all the time in between breast-feeding. For men, I imagine, it's spearing mammoths and dying at 30 of gangrene in a broken leg.</p>
        <p>The truth is that people have never before lived so far from anything like ''the natural'' -- or worked harder to widen the distance. And a good thing, too. The sooner we stop pretending, the sooner businesses will stop fooling us with natural folderol. I myself lead as unnatural life as possible, and I'm proud of it. If you are reading these words, you shouldn't need reminding that primitive hunter-gatherer societies had a terrible time getting home delivery of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>At some level, of course, people know that they are pretending. They drive cars to natural childbirth classes. They buy natural European spring water bottled in plastic and shipped thousands of miles. They object in Internet discussion groups to genetically engineered products. Is it any wonder that businesses respond by marketing pretend ''natural'' products?</p>
        <p>Oh, to wake up one day in a world that knows the state of nature is no more hospitable than the state of North Korea. Then we'll all demand hard proof that herbal remedies are safe and effective, instead of simply assuming that being herbal makes them O.K. We'll recognize that some of the nastiest toxins we ingest are made by Mother Nature without capitalism's help. And we'll be open to more ''unnatural'' technologies that actually increase safety, like food irradiation.</p>
        <p>For now, though, if you're selling something, natural goes with traditional, as long as the second term is used the right way. Clever marketers like Restoration Hardware, for instance, know that people hanker for ''simpler times'' and stock the shelves accordingly.</p>
        <p>Among the group that David Brooks has christened Bobos (for bourgeois bohemians, from his book ''Bobos in Paradise''), the natural fetish extends even to children's toys. One mother I know believed for a while that children shouldn't play with stuff made of plastic, only wood. What difference does it make? Who knows?</p>
        <p>PERSONALLY, I'm hoping for more products like Gatorade. My favorite flavors are Riptide Rush, Alpine Snow and, in a truly marvelous aqua hue, Glacier Freeze. Not only do they taste great, but there is no pretense whatsoever of any naturalness about them.</p>
        <p>Mine remains an unfashionable opinion. I bought a tasty electric-blue sports drink once from a California sales clerk who scorned its artificiality.</p>
        <p>''But what's natural?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''From the earth,'' she replied disdainfully.</p>
        <p>Apparently she has never visited the Natural American Spirit Web site, which (at the government's behest) offers the perfect rejoinder: ''No additives in our tobacco does NOT mean a safer cigarette.''</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
