<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chance To Hear A Legend's Debut</title>
    <meta content="06GURE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Staditsche Oper Berlin</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurewitsch, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischer-Dieskau, Dietrich</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fricsay, Ferenc</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Don Carlos (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D7113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chance To Hear A Legend's Debut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW GUREWITSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurewitsch, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Gurewitsch reviews newly released CD set of German baritone Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau's debut operatic performance in Verdi's Don Carlos with Hungarian Ferenc Fricsay conducting Stadtische Oper Berlin; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO would have suspected, this late in the game, that there were any crucial gaps left to fill in the discography of the German baritone Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau? The very model of the serious postwar vocal artist, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau turned 75 in May. From the very dawn of his career, microphones seemed to spring up where'er he walked. For him as for legions of other performers ''legendary,'' honorable or merely retired from the scene, the opening of the archival floodgates in the CD era has brought an all but engulfing tidal wave of documentation, much of it previously impossible for any but the most resourceful, connected and determined fanatic to find.</p>
        <p>Yet here comes Myto Records of Milan, upstaging a flurry of new Fischer-Dieskau offerings on other labels with what is advertised as the premiere release of Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's first operatic appearance. The assignment is no novice's walk-on, either, but Rodrigo, freethinking confidant of royalty, a principal in Verdi's ''Don Carlos'' (001.H038; three CD's). Where on earth did Myto turn up the source tape? And how is it possible no one got there before?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO would have suspected, this late in the game, that there were any crucial gaps left to fill in the discography of the German baritone Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau? The very model of the serious postwar vocal artist, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau turned 75 in May. From the very dawn of his career, microphones seemed to spring up where'er he walked. For him as for legions of other performers ''legendary,'' honorable or merely retired from the scene, the opening of the archival floodgates in the CD era has brought an all but engulfing tidal wave of documentation, much of it previously impossible for any but the most resourceful, connected and determined fanatic to find.</p>
        <p>Yet here comes Myto Records of Milan, upstaging a flurry of new Fischer-Dieskau offerings on other labels with what is advertised as the premiere release of Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's first operatic appearance. The assignment is no novice's walk-on, either, but Rodrigo, freethinking confidant of royalty, a principal in Verdi's ''Don Carlos'' (001.H038; three CD's). Where on earth did Myto turn up the source tape? And how is it possible no one got there before?</p>
        <p>Quite apart from the interest Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's debut gives the evening in retrospect, this was an occasion. The company was the Stadtische Oper Berlin (now the Deutsche Oper). Its previous efforts to raise itself from the postwar ashes had failed ingloriously. With the premiere of a new ''Don Carlos'' on Nov. 18, 1948, Heinz Tietjen, who had run the operation to acclaim in the late 1920's, was back in charge. In the pit stood his discovery Ferenc Fricsay, a Hungarian conductor of remarkable gifts, then 34.</p>
        <p>Typically for Mr. Fischer-Dieskau, his debut in opera was early and auspicious. An ex-prisoner of war of the British in Italy, he made his first concert appearance, in the brief (though crucial) baritone solo of Brahms's ''German Requiem,'' in Freiburg in 1947.</p>
        <p>In January 1948, at 22, he was heard on Berlin radio in Schubert's agonized song cycle ''Winterreise.'' That broadcast has been on CD at least since the late 80's, evidence of his preternaturally precocious interpretive maturity. True, in later years he would develop a leaner sound, a broader palette of colors and greater variety and swiftness of utterance. (This ''Winterreise'' clocks in at a lugubrious 78-plus minutes, some seven minutes more than later readings of his.) By comparison with his subsequent work, this performance has a slightly presentational, old-fashioned cast. Still, no one familiar with the artist Mr. Fischer-Dieskau was to become could fail to recognize the timbre, musicianship or personality.</p>
        <p>With the Myto ''Don Carlos,'' sung in German, as was the local custom of the time, we are already in the presence of the ''modern'' Fischer-Dieskau. (Perhaps Fricsay's extremes of tempo, especially the fast ones, have something to do with it.) At his first appearance, an unexpected reunion with Don Carlos, to whom Rodrigo is devoted, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's taut rhythms and mercurial reactions bring not only his own character but also the whole dramatic predicament sharply to life. What he hears is dire. The young prince is in love with his stepmother. Mr. Fischer-Dieskau gives Rodrigo's thunderstruck exclamation in a smothered, almost asthmatic voice but quickly recovers to suggest, with lofty solemnity and a trace of Mephistophelean insinuation, that Carlos take up the cause of oppressed Flanders.</p>
        <p>THE famous duet that ensues goes painfully awry, and the tenor, Boris Greverus, must bear the blame. (Such from-the-heart, pitch-approximate bawling as is heard from him throughout the performance is quite exciting at a visceral level here and there but catastrophic where voices must blend, twisting Verdi into Ives.) When Rodrigo reappears, bearing a letter to the queen from her mother and a whispered message from the prince, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau is urbane, smooth and youthful, his precise diction charged with the sense of detailed motivation one hopes for in a spoken play. Once again, he is rhythmically scrupulous; a detractor might say pedantic.</p>
        <p>In his big paragraph of melody describing the prince's suffering, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau conveys tremendous compassion, emphasizing emotional detail rather than the allure of his own sound. Italians do not sing this way. And for many, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's vocal character has always been intrinsically incompatible with Verdi. ''Che fa, questo Discher-Fieskau?,'' Renata Tebaldi, the quintessential Italian soprano, is said to have asked when he showed up to sing Rodrigo on Georg Solti's recording in 1965: ''What is he doing, this Discher-Fieskau?'' No doubt she scrambled his name perfectly innocently. Why would she have known it? He was not of her world.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Fischer-Dieskau could reveal potentialities in Verdi Italians are apt to overlook. On Myto, face to face with Josef Greindl's King Philip -- a colder, harsher portrait than one might think possible, snarly and granitic, as withholding of voice as of tenderness -- Mr. Fischer-Dieskau starts out rather cool and stiff. As their wide-ranging dialogue proceeds, he grows mysterious, strangely tentative, before breaking out with wild horror at the evils he has seen abroad. Thanking the king for his favor, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau at first seems dazed, almost catatonic.</p>
        <p>Then, with a single word left to go (''Sire''), the light changes, and Rodrigo seems transfigured, off in his own radiant world. By the end of the opera, the character will have dealt double with the king, sacrificing himself for Carlos and the cause of liberty. Verdi gives the dying man an aria in which the beauty of the melody expresses the nobility of his ideals. In Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's performance, the arc toward transcendence already begins many scenes before.</p>
        <p>The Myto ''Don Carlos'' merits comment on other counts. Verdi's score is long, and it underwent significant revisions. Different editions solve the resulting problems in different ways, and the choices of Julius Kapp, the director of the Berlin production, are unusual, at times ingenious. Fricsay's highly individual sense of pace and texture serves the drama excellently, and the cast forms a remarkably coherent ensemble. As an acting singer, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau was very much among his kind. The practice of speaking in song -- and of speaking as clearly and expressively as actors at the playhouse -- is common to the entire cast. Myto provides no libretto, but if you understand German, you will not need one. (Supertitles? Was ist das?)</p>
        <p>But rather than dwell on these matters, let's turn to other noteworthy recent additions to Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's immense discography. Aribert Reimann's ''Lear,'' adapted from Shakespeare's tragedy, was composed -- slowly, and against powerful internal resistance -- at the singer's suggestion. Mr. Fischer-Dieskau made specific dramatic suggestions, too, but these were ignored. Nor was he consulted about the vocal writing. The score that resulted -- replete with 12-tone rows, quarter tones and other equally singer-friendly attributes -- received its premiere in Munich, conducted by Gerd Albrecht, in a production by Jean-Pierre Ponnelle. Long out of print on LP, Deutsche Grammophon's live recording of 1978 now returns to the catalog (463 480-2; two CD's).</p>
        <p>Verdi, as is well known, dreamed of setting ''Lear'' as an opera but gave up. He cannot have been thinking of anything like this. Though the vocal writing, notably for the three sopranos as Lear's daughters, is in spots jagged and stratospheric, the singers operate fundamentally within a domain of declamatory recitative unrelieved by melody. The instrumental writing -- particularly for percussion, strings (divided into as many as 48 parts) and solo flute -- creates a bleak yet mesmerizing soundscape within which the terrors of the action unfold.</p>
        <p>''A work charged with meaning that must be grasped in its totality and is far removed from the sensationalism so customary today,'' Mr. Fischer-Dieskau calls Mr. Reimann's ''Lear'' in an introductory note. ''Seldom -- perhaps only in Alban Berg's 'Wozzeck' -- has the loneliness of man been so convincingly portrayed as the consequence of his blindness to his fellow man.''</p>
        <p>At a poignant moment on the hard road to self-knowledge, Shakespeare's mad, outcast monarch calls himself ''a man more sinned against than sinning.'' Mr. Fischer-Dieskau has the courage to go beyond the partly justified self-pity, taking his character to the extremes. Whether the voice is writhing through little serpentine melismas or oscillating in anguished jungle cries, whether he is shouting or growling, cracking or letting the sound fade and flare like the last exhalations of a dying candle, he surrenders unconditionally to the truth of the moment. The extraordinary supporting cast is with him every step of the way.</p>
        <p>This journey into the heart of darkness, though one of the artist's supreme achievements, is surely not for all travelers. As a happier tribute for his 75th year, Deutsche Grammophon has issued the Fischer-Dieskau Edition. This boxed set of reissues (463 500-2) consists of 20 CD's, some also to be sold individually at a later date, plus a bonus disc of folk-song settings by Haydn, Beethoven and Weber, recorded in 1961 and 1970: a jewel, demonstrating how light and unaffected this obsessively detail-oriented interpreter could be.</p>
        <p>Exploring the treasure chest in full will take devotion. (The cover story of International Record Review in June consisted of nearly three pages of repertory listings from the set and just over two pages of commentary.) The selection represents most of the breadth of the artist's repertory, from Buxtehude, Bach and Handel to Debussy, Ravel and Ives by way of an extremely comprehensive canon of the German lied (not only Schubert, Schumann, Brahms, Wolf, Mahler and Strauss but also Liszt, Schoeck, Reger, Busoni and Pfitzner). A disc of opera arias recorded between 1949 and 1964 includes forays into Bizet (not only the ''Toreador Song'' from ''Carmen'' but also ''O Nadir, tendre ami'' from ''Les Pecheurs de Perles''), Rossini (''Sois immobile'' from ''Guillaume Tell,'' sung in Italian), Leoncavallo (the prologue to ''I Pagliacci'') and Puccini (the quartet from Act III of ''La Boheme'').</p>
        <p>Inevitably, complete operas are absent, and symphonic repertory is scarce. On these grounds alone, the Fischer-Dieskau Edition must be accounted only the tip of an iceberg. (A recent Web search for the artist turned up 163 record listings, a total that gives a very false impression. His great Schubert sets, recorded from 1966 to 1972 and originally issued as 29 LP's, include no fewer than 463 songs and appear in discographies as only three items.) Still, Deutsche Grammophon has struck a perfect balance: the Fischer-Dieskau whose portrait emerges from the new edition is the artist who defined an era.</p>
        <p>YET even now, there are addenda. Since 1992, when Mr. Fischer-Dieskau quietly discontinued his singing career, he has taken engagements reciting poetry and texts with music. Thus, in 1994, for Hyperion's Schubert Edition, he recorded the Wilhelm Muller poems omitted by Schubert in his setting of the cycle ''Die Schone Mullerin,'' adding a rare perspective to Ian Bostridge and Graham Johnson's febrile account of the songs. (That Mr. Bostridge's volatile, psychologically searching performance style is scarcely imaginable without Mr. Fischer-Dieskau's example makes the linkage all the more meaningful.)</p>
        <p>And last year, for ECM New Series, Mr. Fischer-Dieskau lent his voice to Peter Ruzicka's 21-minute ''Sich Verlierend'' (''Vanishing''). It is the final track on a CD of string quartets by Mr. Ruzicka, performed by the Arditti String Quartet. Between sharp gestures that hang in air like the strokes of a Chinese master calligrapher and pools of silence, the speaker is heard in snippets of text in several languages by a handful of mandarins of modern prose, Handke, Adorno and Celan among them.</p>
        <p>First, though, is Paul Valery, whose bit begins, ''Die Musik ist in mir'' (''The music is within me''): a pregnant beginning, spoken from the soul. And last is the oracular Proposition No. 7 with which Wittgenstein ends his ''Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus'': ''Wovon man nicht sprechen kann, daruber muss man schweigen'' (''Of things whereof one cannot speak, one must be silent''). Awkward as this sounds in translation, the original German has the elegance that arises where accuracy of thought and economy of expression intersect. If this is not the master's last recorded word, it deserves to be.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
