<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Empty Nests of Seven Mile Island: Where Did the Egrets Go?</title>
    <meta content="06MAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seven Mile Island (Nj)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wetlands Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Tedor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DE113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1250" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Empty Nests of Seven Mile Island: Where Did the Egrets Go?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DEMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wetlands Institute director Tedor Whitman answers questions on coastal habitat along New Jersey's barrier Seven Mile Island and this year's dearth of migrating shore birds; photo (On the Map column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The seven-mile-long barrier island that is home to Avalon and Stone Harbor also includes a large area of swampy marshland with tree cover where a variety of shore birds historically nested each season. This year the birds did not return there, and experts are unsure why they did come back, where they have gone or whether they will return. Tedor Whitman, director of education at the Wetlands Institute, a nonprofit organization founded to promote conservation, research and education about the local coastal habitat, talked recently about the birds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The seven-mile-long barrier island that is home to Avalon and Stone Harbor also includes a large area of swampy marshland with tree cover where a variety of shore birds historically nested each season. This year the birds did not return there, and experts are unsure why they did come back, where they have gone or whether they will return. Tedor Whitman, director of education at the Wetlands Institute, a nonprofit organization founded to promote conservation, research and education about the local coastal habitat, talked recently about the birds.</p>
        <p>Q. How many and what kind of birds have been seen in the area?</p>
        <p>A. For at least 20 years until the mid-1990's, the birds nested each spring like clockwork in the wetlands in Stone Harbor where the maritime forest had not been destroyed by development. There are more than 30 acres of wetlands in Stone Harbor and Avalon. You would have more than 1,000 nesting pairs in the trees and each would raise two to three chicks. There were snowy egrets, glossy ibis, black-crowned and yellow-crowned night herons, little blue herons, green herons and tri-colored herons. Then about five years ago for some unknown reason, they moved to a different section of the wetlands that is in Avalon.</p>
        <p>Q. What did the Wetlands Institute do while they were here?</p>
        <p>A. For the last few years the nests and birds have been visible from the roadway so we started having ''Thursday Evening with the Egrets'' each week from spring through fall. We would have someone from the Wetlands Institute show visitors the nests and talk to them about the birds.</p>
        <p>Q. What happened this year?</p>
        <p>A. We don't know, but the birds just did not show up. Last year there was a reduction in the nest count to about 700. This spring they just did not show up from their southern wintering grounds in late March or early April as they usually did, and they are not back in Stone Harbor. They could be in trees in some other area where they cannot be seen from a road. We just don't know. We don't think they are dead because we would probably know about a traumatic event capable of killing more than 2,000 birds. A lot of marshland is only accessible by small boat or has poison ivy and greenbriar so thick you can walk on it, so there is no way to get into to look for the birds.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did they come here in the first place?</p>
        <p>A. Because this is where the trees are. Everything else in this immediate area is developed. These birds like to be in groups. They are large and obvious, so if you are large and obvious, you might as well be in a big group. You can't hide.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did they leave?</p>
        <p>A. The birds do a lot of damage to the trees, so maybe the tree cover diminished to a point where they did not like it. Maybe they will be back when the canopy returns. Or maybe there was just too much human activity. Why they moved is a mystery Stone Harbor would have liked to have solved five years ago. The only ones who know the answer to that are the birds.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you still have ''Thursday Evenings with the Egrets''?</p>
        <p>A. We still do it because people are still curious about the birds. We also want to emphasize that this is still a bird sanctuary that is very important to migrating species that use this as a stop over in the spring and fall. This is literally an oasis in the midst of development along the East Coast where birds can stop to refuel for the rest of their flight north or south. This is a critical point to them and it is important that it is maintained as a sanctuary.</p>
        <p>KAREN DeMASTERS</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
