<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY DIARY</title>
    <meta content="06DIAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDD173CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Congress, in its election-year wisdom, decided that I could earn as much as I wanted and still collect my Social Security check.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Congress, in its election-year wisdom, decided that I could earn as much as I wanted and still collect my Social Security check.</p>
        <p>I figured it would be a good idea to start slowly, so I went to a temp agency. I was ushered into a small room and given directions on a proofreading test that stumped me for 10 minutes. Unfortunately, the entire exam was supposed to take 20.</p>
        <p>They told me they would call me. After wandering around for a while in a daze, I happened to see the young woman who interviewed me. With an amused look on her face, she began placing some papers in a machine that made a shredding sound.</p>
        <p>Martin Obolsky</p>
        <p>The scene is the town pool in Glen Rock at about 3 p.m., and private swim lessons are in full swing. One mother sitting poolside and observing the lessons -- in addition to the toned and tanned male instructor -- calls to another mother a few yards away.</p>
        <p>''Come sit by me, the view is quite nice,'' she calls.</p>
        <p>''I know,'' responds the other. ''I'm paying for that view.''</p>
        <p>Ah, the perks of private swim lessons.</p>
        <p>Deirdre Flanagan Ward</p>
        <p>NO FORD IN MY FUTURE</p>
        <p>That Ford makes more intimidating versions</p>
        <p>Of S.U.V. each year is evident:</p>
        <p>Explorer Expedition now Excursion</p>
        <p>Towering over my Expedient.</p>
        <p>Bob McKenty</p>
        <p>One car poem deserves another one -- in this case untitled:</p>
        <p>My shining new car is expensive and nifty.</p>
        <p>It cost what my house did in 1950.</p>
        <p>BARBARA ALPREN</p>
        <p>I recently put a new ''Welcome Friends'' mat on my front porch. That night, I heard someone at the door. When I investigated, I discovered a wild turkey beating his head against the storm door, his wife and chick waiting expectantly under my dining room window.</p>
        <p>Dorothy Ryan</p>
        <p>A different take on the endless, spendless days of summer.</p>
        <p>Cost of admission for one adult and four children to the Metropolitan Museum of Art: $10.</p>
        <p>Lunch at Ruby Foo's, including garage parking: $85.</p>
        <p>The opportunity to cross the bridge and expose my four sons to a day of culture rather than a day of chlorine: priceless.</p>
        <p>Deirdre Flanagan Ward</p>
        <p>The week of my daughter's high school graduation, she received a letter from a town near Princeton Junction, which is where we live, though we couldn't identify the name on the envelop.</p>
        <p>It was a letter from a little girl describing her family, among other things. We thought it was the school's idea to get her to be the big sister to a girl from the next town.</p>
        <p>It took a while for my daughter to realize the little girl was herself, and  it was an assignment from Madeline Crass's second-grade class. Ms. Crass had kept the letters and mailed them to her students upon their graduation.</p>
        <p>My daughter wrote her back that it was by far the best graduation gift she could have asked for.</p>
        <p>Joseph Sun</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
