<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Sweet Hotel</title>
    <meta content="06FEAT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pedersen, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEEDF153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Sweet Hotel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA PEDERSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pedersen, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on increasing number of people who are opting to live in apartment hotels in New York City, which are beginning to experience resurgence; traces history of such hotels, which began in late 1870's and appealed to single men and young families unable to afford servants and proliferated in 1920's, when they appealed to the wealthy; currently, they are favored by wealthy seeking food, housekeeping and other services they would rather not have to do themselves, young women seeking better security than what apartment buildings offer and those recently separated and divorcing; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE high school assignment seemed simple enough: draw or paint your dream house and don't hold back. And so my classmates up in the Buffalo suburb of Amherst, N.Y., dutifully submitted renderings of elaborate Southern plantations, festive pink and blue Caribbean bungalows and sprawling Spanish haciendas.</p>
        <p>I, on the other hand, turned in a sketch of the architecturally lackluster Marriott Hotel that had recently gone up two blocks from my house. My instructor asked if I'd mistakenly signed up for his art class instead of the mechanical drawing course down the hall. I explained that no, the Marriott Hotel was my dream home. It still is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE high school assignment seemed simple enough: draw or paint your dream house and don't hold back. And so my classmates up in the Buffalo suburb of Amherst, N.Y., dutifully submitted renderings of elaborate Southern plantations, festive pink and blue Caribbean bungalows and sprawling Spanish haciendas.</p>
        <p>I, on the other hand, turned in a sketch of the architecturally lackluster Marriott Hotel that had recently gone up two blocks from my house. My instructor asked if I'd mistakenly signed up for his art class instead of the mechanical drawing course down the hall. I explained that no, the Marriott Hotel was my dream home. It still is.</p>
        <p>As an only child living with my single, working mother in a house that needed constant upkeep, I knew all about the American Dream of home ownership:  mowing the lawn, trimming hedges, cleaning out gutters, pumping a flooded basement. It was for the birds.  Or at the very least, the neighbors.</p>
        <p>Well, now that I've put in 16 years as a Manhattan apartment dweller, I'm even more convinced there's nothing noble about do-it-yourself home maintenance.  Ask me today to draw my dream house and you'll get a brochure for the Phillips Club at Lincoln Square, a new and improved version of an old concept in urban living.</p>
        <p>Back then it was called an apartment hotel and offered long-term rentals with a full complement of hotel services. The Phillips Club, which opened four years ago at Broadway and 66th Street, is an extended-stay refuge for wealthy individuals who couldn't care less about tax breaks and real estate appreciation, just as long as they don't have to change sheets, mop floors, call the plumber, shop for furnishings, wait for the cable guy or schlep groceries from Zabar's.</p>
        <p>Of the 184 units, from studios to three bedrooms, 88  serve regular overnight guests. The remaining 96 are for people who either rent by the month ($6,000 to $17,000) or who, as club members, are given a deed to a fractional share of a residence, much like a time share.</p>
        <p>But everyone at the Phillips Club gets all the hotel amenities: round-the-clock housekeeping, concierge and valet service, an on-site library, a personal safe and even use of the nearby Reebok Sports Club. Eloise, eat your heart out.</p>
        <p>Generally out of fashion since the Great Depression, this style of living is now on the rise. A new Ritz-Carlton Hotel in Battery Park City will offer accommodations in the apartment-hotel vein, as will the St. Moritz. Citywide, the Marriott hotel chain has 600 apartments for executives that offer hotel-like services, and the number is growing.</p>
        <p>''Hotels offer a style of living that's very appealing to people and, given the strong economy, it's definitely making a comeback,'' said Gary Schweikert, general manager of the Plaza Hotel. Mr. Schweikert, himself a year-round resident of the Plaza, envisions a return to offering residential accommodations there in the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>One reason for the resurgence is the rising number of renovations in the city, as well as sales of residences before the occupants have found new digs. But there may be deeper causes.</p>
        <p>For one, the concept of what it means to be wealthy is evolving. For some, being rich no longer means owning the most toys, but  owning nothing at all, save for the casual Friday clothes on their backs. Even to the middle class, leasing a sports utility vehicle may be as credible a symbol of prosperity as plunking down cash to purchase it. Why buy and have all the grief of ownership if you can rent, hire or charter whatever estates, jets, old masters or yachts that your lifestyle requires?</p>
        <p>Faith Popcorn, the futurist, says hotel-style living is also particularly appealing to busy professionals. ''The hotel is the substitute wife,'' says Ms. Popcorn, the co-author  of ''Eveolution,'' a new book about marketing to modern women whose dual roles require juggling career and family. ''Women need wives these days, especially married women with children.''</p>
        <p>Frances Rochat may well agree. She and her banker husband, Andrew, and two small children moved into the Phillips Club six months ago. A registered dietitian who is attending New York University for a master's degree in nutrition, Ms. Rochat says she loves the arrangement because she doesn't have to do dishes and because the doormen help her carry things.</p>
        <p>THE earliest apartment hotels in New York City date to the late 1870's. They appealed mostly to single men and young families unable to afford servants. But then, in the 1920's, such accommodations became trendy for the well off and even the rich.</p>
        <p>''In town it is no longer quite in taste to build marble palaces, however much money one may have,'' wrote Arthur Pound, a social commentator of the time. ''Instead, one lives in a hotel.'' However, few wealthy New Yorkers were interested in a life without servants. The apartment hotel was the perfect answer.</p>
        <p>Like the current comeback, this rise in hotel living in Manhattan came during prosperous times. It was the Jazz Age, when money was easy, stocks were soaring and the city was in the midst of a postwar building boom. The cost of the hotel amenities and the lack of equity for the money did not seem to matter to many people.</p>
        <p>One of the first post-World War I hybrids was the Buckingham Apartment Hotel, built in 1924 at 101 West 57th Street. Now primarily a tourist hotel, its large staff provided top-notch hotel service. But the comforts didn't come cheap. ''A pen and a checkbook are the sole requisites of housekeeping or homemaking,'' wrote Martin Clary, a real estate publicity man, in 1926.</p>
        <p>The fanciest, and at 42 stories the tallest, was the Ritz Tower, which was opened the year after the Buckingham by Arthur Brisbane, a Hearst newspaperman-cum-investor. A Renaissance palazzo in travertine marble throughout, the building, at Park Avenue and 57th Street, supplied its well-heeled tenants with anything their wallets desired, including hot meals sent up in electrically heated dumbwaiters and served by butlers stationed on every floor. From 1940 to 1966, the structure housed Henri Soule's  Pavillon, one of New York's most luxurious restaurants.</p>
        <p>Comfort was what those residential hotels were all about. H. L. Mencken said the Algonquin, which offered residential living to him and Dorothy Parker, among other writers, was the most comfortable hotel in America. ''The distance from the front door to the elevator is only 40 feet,'' he wrote, ''an important consideration to a man whose friends all drink too much, and sometimes press the stuff on him.''</p>
        <p>One niche of the apartment-hotel business rested on the city's reputation for slightly different standards than the rest of the country. Years ago, everyone knew that a young woman of a certain social standing -- or with a minister father back in Duluth -- who headed off to live on her own in New York would take up lodging at places like the Barbizon, on East 63rd Street. The Barbizon, now an upscale boutique hotel, was a ''women's residence club'' from 1927 to 1981, home at various times to Grace Kelly, Joan Crawford, Liza Minnelli and Candice  Bergen. In these and similar spots, which have now virtually disappeared, housemothers reigned supreme on every floor, and only in the lounge and music room could a  young woman entertain a young man.</p>
        <p>''You didn't have to worry about men trying to come up to your room,'' said Judy Hauser, a Wilhelmina fashion model who arrived at the hotel in 1966 from a conservative family in Dearborn, Mich. ''Also, drugs were just coming onto the scene, and of course the Barbizon excluded all that.''</p>
        <p>By the late 1920's, apartment hotels were proliferating so greatly that they aroused the competitive ire of regular hoteliers. Soon the hotel owners marched on City Hall and petitioned Mayor Jimmy Walker to outlaw the hybrid poseurs, claiming they violated safety regulations and building codes.</p>
        <p>The hotel owners got their wish with the 1929 Multiple Dwelling Law. That state statute loosened many rules that applied to both regular apartments and regular hotels, allowing both to give the upstart apartment hotels a run for their money.</p>
        <p>But before the industry had a chance to absorb these changes, the stock market crashed. Aside from a few projects already on the drawing board, construction halted.</p>
        <p>By the start of the Depression, the city had as many as 150 apartment hotels, housing some 15,000 wealthy and middle-class families. After World War II, with the shine off the onetime fad, some of the buildings were converted to regular apartments. Many others, caught up in the postwar economic boom, were demolished to make way for office skyscrapers. And although some of the apartment hotels, like the Pierre, still cater to extended-stay guests, many others were changed into regular hotels. Among the more prominent to make the transition were the Gotham (now Peninsula), Barclay (now Inter-Continental), Drake (now Swissotel New York the Drake), Roosevelt and  Mayflower.</p>
        <p>The day of the apartment hotel had come and gone.</p>
        <p>The airplane speeded its demise. ''Hotel living in general declined as air travel became the norm for people of means,'' said Mr. Schweikert of the Plaza. ''When the Plaza opened in 1907, the wealthy traveled by steamship. They would be loaded down with steamer trunks and staff and think nothing of settling in for months at a time.''</p>
        <p>The Vanderbilts considered the Plaza their Manhattan pied-a-terre, as did Enrico Caruso and of course Kay Thompson, creator of ''Eloise.'' The F. Scott Fitzgeralds  were frequently in residence at the Plaza, and at least once made fully clothed guest appearances in the fountain in Grand Army Plaza out front. The couple so loved the hotel that Ernest Hemingway advised Fitzgerald to bequeath his liver to Princeton and his heart to the Plaza.</p>
        <p>Hotel living may have declined after those heady days, but it never went out of style for Herbert R. Weissberg, 87, the owner of the Gramercy Park Hotel. For the last  half century he's been happily ensconced in a suite at his 509-room hotel in the East 20's.</p>
        <p>The hotel, whose long-term rates start at $3,500 a month, remains one-quarter residential, and has been home to many other  permanent lodgers over the years. Joseph P. Kennedy, John F. Kennedy's father, had an apartment at the Gramercy. More recently, an ''extended stay'' by Paul Shaffer, David Letterman's bandleader, lasted for 12 years.</p>
        <p>IN the current comeback, three types of people seek hotel living, according to Marty Weissberg, son of the Gramercy owner. The first are those who aren't  willing to look in the Yellow Pages for a carpet cleaner, call Con Edison or wait for  telephones to be hooked up. The Gramercy  provides phone, fax, food and housekeeping,  and there is also a barbershop, a beauty  parlor and valet service on the premises.</p>
        <p>And it all goes on one bill. Marty Weissberg said that having to pay a long distance phone bill in addition to a local one was the last straw for many harried New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>The second type of guest is the young woman who doesn't want to be wandering the halls of an apartment building, the sort who might have stayed at the Barbizon years ago. ''The hotel has a security staff and room clerks who recognize you, and of course there's a wake-up service,'' Marty Weissberg said.</p>
        <p>The third kind of resident is recently separated or divorcing. ''They get brain dead,'' he said. ''There's so much going on with lawyers that they can't handle food and laundry.''</p>
        <p>Uptown, the Carlyle Hotel at Madison Avenue and 76th Street, the longtime New York abode of President Kennedy, has always offered residential living to those who can afford it. ''Residents are financially capable of having their own sizable apartments anywhere in the world,'' said James Sherwin, the manager. ''But then they would have to deal with security and staffing.''</p>
        <p>Long-term Carlyle dwellers either own their apartments and pay a monthly service charge or sign a three-year lease.</p>
        <p>With the renewed interest in hotel living, more companies are entering the field. Millennium Partners, the owner of the Phillips Club, is building a Ritz-Carlton Downtown in Battery Park City to expand on such accommodations. In addition to a 311-room hotel, the company will offer 122 condominiums with a separate lobby and access to all the hotel's amenities. The condominiums start at $500,000 for a one-bedroom. Forty have been sold, said Matthew Hall, a Millennium spokesman.</p>
        <p>''You can pick up the phone and order anything, and yet you only have to pay for extra services on an as-needed basis,'' Mr. Hall said. ''Wall Street workers with long hours and lots of travel don't want to screen maids and dog walkers.''</p>
        <p>Millennium Partners is also converting the elegant St. Moritz Hotel on Central Park South into a 300-room Ritz-Carlton. The top 12 floors will accommodate condominiums, whose owners will get all hotel amenities.</p>
        <p>Meantime, for the business market, Marriott has leased about 600 apartments so far in which it offers maid service, furnishings and the like. A Marriott competitor, Oakwood Corporate Housing, is also fattening  its stake in this niche. It has 300 such apartments in the city and plans to add 200 more.</p>
        <p>Some moderately priced hotels, like the Roger Williams, 28 East 31st Street, and the 30-30, formerly the Martha Washington, 30 East 30th Street, have recently done away with their residential accommodations. But this countertrend seems small compared to the revived interest in such arrangements.</p>
        <p>Fortunately for those lacking trust funds,  at least one moderately priced residential hotel has no plans to convert. The venerable Chelsea Hotel on West 23rd Street has been catering to long-term tenants since 1905. Still delightfully bohemian, it has a guest register that is living history, bearing the signatures of long-term tenants like Arthur Miller and long-gone literary lions like Thomas Wolfe, O. Henry, Mark Twain, Vladimir Nabokov, Tennessee Williams and William S. Burroughs. Arthur C. Clarke wrote ''2001: A Space Odyssey'' while in residence. Tour guides and necrophiliacs like to point out that the hotel is where Dylan Thomas stayed during his final visit to New York, when he drank himself to death, and where Sid Vicious fatally stabbed his girlfriend, Nancy Spungen.</p>
        <p>''It's funky,'' said Holly Solomon, who has an art gallery in the Chelsea and has lived in the hotel since February. ''If you're feeling bad, you walk through the lobby and someone says hello and then you feel better.''</p>
        <p>If you're not talented enough to leave art in lieu of payment, as have some former residents -- there's a gallery of their work in the lobby -- one-year contracts at the Chelsea start at $1,900 a month.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, my husband continues to buck this trend by agitating for the purchase of a weekend home outside the city.  While he's devouring the real estate ads,  I'm getting price quotations from the Hotel  Wales on Madison Avenue, complete with VCR and CD player in every room and conveniently located above Sarabeth's restaurant and bakery. For the nature lover in me, there's not one, but two potted topiaries out front. Because when you say country house to this city mouse, I say dry rot, dead tree removal and termite infestation.</p>
        <p>My husband (who has seen a gutter up close only once, and that was in the Leisure Time bowling alley in Port Authority) insists that we can call in professionals for such inconveniences. I say that in a hotel we can call professionals who will call those professionals. I want to get my wake-up call in my dream hotel and say: ''Honey, there's a leak in the ceiling. Call the concierge. And have them send up some Bloody Marys.''</p>
        <p>Laura Pedersen is a journalist whose books include ''Play Money'' (Crown), about her experiences as an options trader on the American Stock Exchange.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Pedersen is a journalist whose books include ''Play Money'' (Crown), about her experiences as an options trader on the American Stock Exchange.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
