<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Does Nothing To Erase the Doubts</title>
    <meta content="Y06CUR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DE133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Does Nothing To Erase the Doubts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Curry On Baseball column discusses New York Yankees pitcher David Cone's struggle this season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The vein in the right side of David Cone's neck was the first indication. It was bulging. It was bulging because Cone's eyes were moist and he was trying to prevent tears from flowing. Cone tried so hard to suppress the tears that his jaw tightened and the vein stuck out like a blue branch.</p>
        <p>This happened two or three times as Cone talked about another incredibly emotional day in his baseball life. Cone is desperately trying to prove to the Yankees that he can still be a competent pitcher, but he knows his opportunity is evaporating. So do the fans. So do Cone's teammates. So does Joe Torre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The vein in the right side of David Cone's neck was the first indication. It was bulging. It was bulging because Cone's eyes were moist and he was trying to prevent tears from flowing. Cone tried so hard to suppress the tears that his jaw tightened and the vein stuck out like a blue branch.</p>
        <p>This happened two or three times as Cone talked about another incredibly emotional day in his baseball life. Cone is desperately trying to prove to the Yankees that he can still be a competent pitcher, but he knows his opportunity is evaporating. So do the fans. So do Cone's teammates. So does Joe Torre.</p>
        <p>Cone pitched six draining innings that did not erase the doubts, even as the Yankees and 55,629 people at Yankee Stadium openly wished they would. That was why Cone had a crimson face, a weakened voice and glassy eyes after the Yankees fell to the Seattle Mariners, 6-5, yesterday. Cone did not get the loss because he left after an astounding 137 pitches, but his victory drought still stretched to 15 starts.</p>
        <p>''I came into this trying to have one good game and see what happens,'' Cone said. ''Because I know my situation is tenuous at best right now.''</p>
        <p>It was so perilous before the start that Torre would not guarantee Cone's next start. But after Cone allowed three runs on seven hits and five walks in a sluggish performance, Torre said that Cone had shown progress and that he would get another start. He did not mention two.</p>
        <p>Torre was so desperate to get Cone a victory, something Cone has not experienced since April 28, that Torre allowed the 37-year-old to throw the most pitches he has thrown since the fifth game of the 1995 division series. That was when Cone's forkball to Doug Strange bounced for his 147th fateful pitch.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was early August, not early October. It was a regular-season game, not a postseason game. But Torre ignored Cone's pitch count of 113 after five innings because the Yankees were losing, 3-2. If Cone could halt Seattle in the sixth and the Yankees could score two or more runs in the sixth, Cone would have been in line for the victory. So Torre, who insisted that he would not put Cone ahead of the team, let Cone amble out for the sixth. For Cone, this was do or die, and Torre treated it that way.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to get him the win,'' Torre conceded. Cone, his voice wavering, said, ''I appreciated that.''</p>
        <p>Overwhelming. Cone kept using that word to describe how he felt about the support he received when he first arrived at the Stadium. So many fans yelled ''Good luck'' that he could have been a groom before his wedding. But Cone was more like a man on trial, not knowing how this intense day was going to evolve. When it was over, a serene Cone talked about taking steps, about time running out and about being treated like royalty.</p>
        <p>''How many pitchers that are 1-10 get that type of ovation?'' Cone asked. ''Clearly, the fans know what's going on. They showed me a lot of respect today and I appreciate that.''</p>
        <p>Cone did not have an artistic outing. He used a more compact delivery in which he shortened the drop step of his left foot, lowered his hands and tried to be quicker to the plate.</p>
        <p>Despite the adjustments, there was a sequence from the second to the fourth innings in which Cone walked or went to three-ball counts on 8 of 10 batters.</p>
        <p>With a 2-0 lead, Cone walked Mark McLemore to lead off the third and he later scored. Cone jumped ahead of Alex Rodriguez with two quick strikes but could not get him to bite at breaking pitches and the count moved to 3-2. Jorge Posada set up for Cone to throw an outside fastball, it caught too much of the plate, and Rodriguez lined it over the right-field fence to make it, 3-2.</p>
        <p>''He gets to two strikes soon on guys, but then he's not able to put them away,'' Posada said. ''Some pitchers make mistakes and batters miss. When Coney makes a mistake, they're not missing them.''</p>
        <p>While Torre has said he trusts Cone as much as any other pitcher he has managed, there is limited space for loyalty in a pennant race, and the memories of 1996, 1998 and 1999 are only memories. Torre cannot let games disappear like extra baseballs and that is why Cone's leash could be reduced to one start.</p>
        <p>When Torre was asked a hypothetical question about ever telling Cone he was through, he talked about times that he was fired and how he preferred the news to be candid and direct. That is how Torre would tell Cone if he had to. ''David Cone would take it a lot better than I would give it,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>There have been many happy endings for Cone during a glorious career that includes 181 victories and four World Series rings. But there has now been a year of evidence against Cone's helping the Yankees. This time, it does not seem as if Cone's story will have a happy ending. The Yankees would love to wait for Cone, but they cannot wait much longer. Cone understands that.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I should be more blind,'' Cone said about sensing doom. ''Maybe I should be more confident. I feel like I'm so close to locking into a groove. It becomes frustrating. It's almost like I can reach out and touch it, but I can't seem to grab it. I can't seem to pitch the way I know I can.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
