<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thanks for Nothing but a Lesson in Life</title>
    <meta content="06COLU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abandonment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Popcorn Park Zoo (Forked River, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DE1F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thanks for Nothing but a Lesson in Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger Jersey column on dearth of reader reponse to his leaving five $20 bills around state and asking those who found them to send him notes telling how they used them; experiment's only response was from reader who wished he had found money so he could donate it to Popcorn Park Zoo in Forked River; Genzlinger describes trip to zoo for abandoned and abused animals; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'D like to begin by thanking New Jerseyans for being the languid, lifeless lunkheads that you are.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, you may recall, I left five $20 bills around the state and used this space to drop clues about where they were. I asked the people who found the money to send me notes telling how they used it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'D like to begin by thanking New Jerseyans for being the languid, lifeless lunkheads that you are.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, you may recall, I left five $20 bills around the state and used this space to drop clues about where they were. I asked the people who found the money to send me notes telling how they used it.</p>
        <p>Every day since, I've been going to the mailbox with dread. We journalists, as you may know, are a cynical, bitter lot, and I've been worried that I would open the mailbox and find a heartwarming, tear-inducing tale from someone who had picked up one of the twenties -- ''I used it to buy my aging mother some roses'' or, ''Your $20 went straight into the offering basket at church'' or, ''My arm aches from pumping $20 worth of quarters into the slots at the Taj.''</p>
        <p>I needn't have worried. My little experiment drew not a single response, heartwarming or otherwise. Not a single response. Apparently the most creative thing the five blobs who scarfed up my money could think of to do with it was stuff it into their wallets. So thank you, Garden State slugs, for not forcing me to get all misty-eyed with tales of charity and good will.</p>
        <p>I did, however, receive a note from someone who said that although he had not found one of my twenties, he wished he had so that he could donate it to the Popcorn Park Zoo in Forked River. He urged me to go visit the place and see for myself why it's worthy of a hard-earned double sawbuck.</p>
        <p>So I threw three children into the car and headed there, expecting just another zoo, finding instead an amazing monument to human compassion and stupidity. The zoo, which is run by the Associated Humane Societies, consists of animals that have been abused, injured, abandoned or otherwise dealt a bad hand. The variety of idiocy and cruelty that put them there is astounding.</p>
        <p>There's Jake the python, found outside a church in Matawan in 1987, apparently abandoned by the fool who tried to keep him as a pet. There's a bear from Iowa whose owner traded her for a car. There's a monkey that someone hosed down with scalding water. There's a goat that was found, bizarrely, on a rooftop in Newark; the sign on the pen speculates that the animal was about to become a religious sacrifice.</p>
        <p>John Bergmann, who oversees the zoo and the more conventional animal shelter next to it, says the misfit menagerie has about 250 animals, many from New Jersey but an increasing number from out of state as the zoo gets more widely known. There is plenty to be outraged about. At the top of the list is the continuing phenomenon of ''fad animals,'' as Mr. Bergmann calls them -- the exotic ''pets'' that, as their moronic owners discover after six months or a year, are not suitable pets at all.</p>
        <p>Walking around the zoo, you can trace the various fads of recent years. There's a pen full of Vietnamese potbellied pigs; a pond of caimen, an alligator-like beast that grows to five feet; a hutch with the current craze, iguanas. ''The problem isn't going away,'' Mr. Bergmann said. ''Every year you've got something else coming in.''</p>
        <p>Right now is prime season for exotic-pet abandonment. ''You've got kids heading off to college,'' he said, ''and they're trying to make arrangements for their iguana, their boa, their python, because mom and dad said, 'You can't leave it here.' ''</p>
        <p>If it seems as if the zoo is struggling against the tide, there are at least small victories -- a pet store, for instance, might be persuaded to stop selling iguanas. And there is the less tangible effect. ''Young people walk out of here with a better respect for wildlife, and they walk out of here with a lot more compassion than they came in with,'' Mr. Bergmann said.</p>
        <p>Certainly the two 13-year-olds in our outing were deeply moved; all they could talk about was signing up for the zoo's $2-a-month animal-sponsorship program. The cynical journalist in the car was more stoic. What, he wondered, is the rationale for saving one injured deer or traveling-zoo bear when elsewhere in the state we're lining up to shoot these same animals as pests?</p>
        <p>Then the journalist absent-mindedly popped in a cassette for the 3-year-old in the car, who has an unforgiving disability that will leave her dependent on other people throughout her life. The tape was magically queued up to an old Bill Staines song.</p>
        <p>''All God's critters got a place in the choir,'' the song goes. ''Some sing low, some sing higher. . . .'' The journalist hereby confesses that he succumbed to a wave of the sentimentality he had been dreading for weeks. Only for a moment, though. Just long enough to be glad that there are people who make it their business to help life's castoffs.</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
