<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="06PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD9143CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLINTON  Rescue Demonstrations Show Coast Guard Prowess</p>
        <p>A Coast Guard HH-65 Dolphin helicopter will send out a rescue swimmer to recover a mock victim in the water and perform basket hoists of another mock victim from the deck of a Coast Guard rescue boat. It isn't ''The Perfect Storm,'' however; it's United States Coast Guard appreciation weekend, which ends today at the Intrepid Sea Air Space Museum.</p>
        <p>The crew members from several Coast Guard cutters will be on hand to conduct tours, answer questions and give out information about recruiting and procedures. Hands-on demonstrations by the auxiliary (the civilian volunteer arm of the Coast Guard) will include knot tying, putting on rescue gear and heaving a ring buoy. For younger audiences, Coastie the Talking Cutter will interact with children while they ride along the pier in a motorized boat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLINTON  Rescue Demonstrations Show Coast Guard Prowess</p>
        <p>A Coast Guard HH-65 Dolphin helicopter will send out a rescue swimmer to recover a mock victim in the water and perform basket hoists of another mock victim from the deck of a Coast Guard rescue boat. It isn't ''The Perfect Storm,'' however; it's United States Coast Guard appreciation weekend, which ends today at the Intrepid Sea Air Space Museum.</p>
        <p>The crew members from several Coast Guard cutters will be on hand to conduct tours, answer questions and give out information about recruiting and procedures. Hands-on demonstrations by the auxiliary (the civilian volunteer arm of the Coast Guard) will include knot tying, putting on rescue gear and heaving a ring buoy. For younger audiences, Coastie the Talking Cutter will interact with children while they ride along the pier in a motorized boat.</p>
        <p>Coast Guard Appreciation Weekend, today 1 p.m. to 4 p.m.; Intrepid Sea Air Space Museum, Pier 86, West 46th Street (at 12th Avenue); free events (though there is a charge for museum admission); (212) 957-7055.</p>
        <p>EAST VILLAGE  A Twist on the British For 'Pinafore' in Yiddish</p>
        <p>''Think British, Sing Yiddish'' is the motto of ''Der Yiddisher Pinafore,'' a musical based on the Gilbert and Sullivan operetta ''H.M.S. Pinafore.'' ''Der Yiddisher Pinafore,'' presented by the Gilbert and Sullivan Yiddish Light Opera Company, takes the story of a poor young sailor's love for a rich captain's daughter and adds a Jewish twist: in this version, religion rather than class separates the lovers. The songs are in Yiddish while the dialogue is in English and the plot has been bent just a little.</p>
        <p>The production is directed by Georgia McGill and was adapted by Al Grand and Bob Tartell, who also produced the show and will perform in the role of Der Kapitan. (Mr. Tartell is shown here with Roz Gertz.) The company encourages Yiddish speakers and non-Yiddish speakers alike to attend.</p>
        <p>''Der Yiddisher Pinafore''; Aug. 12, 13, 19, 20, 26 and 27; Saturdays 8:30 p.m., Sundays 2 p.m. and 7 p.m.; the New 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street between First and Second Avenues; $30; (212) 532-8887.</p>
        <p>KINGSBRIDGE  'The Mill Girl' Recalls Memorable Labor Struggle</p>
        <p>Audiences of all ages can take something from ''The Mill Girl,'' a completely sung, original musical that is historically accurate with regard to the role young people played in the 19th-century fight for better pay and working conditions in the cotton mills of Lowell, Mass.</p>
        <p>The story takes place in the early 1840's, when textile workers were uniting to strike for a 10-hour work day. The story follows 11-year-old Callie, played by Alicia Sommer (upper right). The cast of 30 ranges in age from 7 to 60.</p>
        <p>The musical was composed by Judith C. Lane, who lives in Kingsbridge and was commissioned by the Children's Opera Company of Ossining for a world premiere in 1998. Now, in conjunction with the Amalgamated Housing Corporation of the Bronx, ''The Mill Girl'' makes its New York premiere.</p>
        <p>''The Mill Girl;'' Friday and Saturday 8 p.m., Sunday 3 p.m.; Vladeck Hall, 74 Van Cortlandt Park South; $6; children under 12 and people over 60, $3; (718) 796-9300.</p>
        <p>ALSO AROUND TOWN</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN AT DUSK -- Plymouth Church, the A. A. Low Mansion and the Brooklyn Historical Society are stops on the Big Onion walking tour ''Brooklyn Bridge to Brooklyn Heights at Twilight''; participants will cross the bridge, hear the story of its construction, and proceed to one of the city's first suburbs; Thursday, 6:30 p.m.; meet on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street; $12; students and people over 65, $10; (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>POPS OUTDOORS -- Snug Harbor will be the site of the finale of a series of outdoor concerts by the New York Pops; today, 5 p.m.; the Bandshell at Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, near Snug Harbor Road; free; more information is available from the New York Pops, (212) 765-7677, or Snug Harbor Cultural Center, (718) 448-2500.</p>
        <p>SNOW IN AUGUST -- The last day of the Riverside Church Family Arts Festival features a full-length musical from Canada, ''Aah-Pootee! That's Snow!'' (Aah-pootee is a word for snow among the Eskimos who refer to themselves as Inuit); today, 2 p.m.; Theater at the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue at 120th Street; $18; people over 65, $15; children $12; (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
