<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bellflower for Everyone and Everywhere</title>
    <meta content="06WGAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D6163CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bellflower for Everyone and Everywhere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elisabeth Ginsburg In the Garden column describes attributes of bellflower (Campanula) family; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY year, at the end of January, I come down with the gardener's version of Seasonal Affective Disorder. Last year I treated this affliction by buying a botanical print at an antiques show. The print is a graceful illustration of several members of the bellflower (Campanula) family, as rendered by Dorothea Loudon, more commonly known simply as Mrs. Loudon, a prominent 19th-century English illustrator. The print's colors and shapes are so alluring that I felt compelled to investigate and invest in various Campanulas.</p>
        <p>Bellflowers are members of the large Campanulaceae family. A reunion of the clan would be crowded with 300 species of annuals, biennials and perennials, but most members could be distinguished by their bell-shaped blossoms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY year, at the end of January, I come down with the gardener's version of Seasonal Affective Disorder. Last year I treated this affliction by buying a botanical print at an antiques show. The print is a graceful illustration of several members of the bellflower (Campanula) family, as rendered by Dorothea Loudon, more commonly known simply as Mrs. Loudon, a prominent 19th-century English illustrator. The print's colors and shapes are so alluring that I felt compelled to investigate and invest in various Campanulas.</p>
        <p>Bellflowers are members of the large Campanulaceae family. A reunion of the clan would be crowded with 300 species of annuals, biennials and perennials, but most members could be distinguished by their bell-shaped blossoms.</p>
        <p>Campanulas have been popular for ages, though they are not as celebrated as the members of some of the flashier genera. They are happiest in full sun, but will grow perfectly well in light shade.</p>
        <p>I raised my first Campanula when I was a novice gardener. The species was Campanula calycanthema Medium, known to its friends as Canterbury bells. I started mine from seed, and, having ignored the package description of their biennial nature, was disappointed when only a few plants bloomed the first year. By the second year, when I had completely forgotten about my Canterbury bells, I was stunned to find their two-foot stalks dominating the area where I had planted them. Most stood resolutely upright, though a few leaned crazily and might have benefited from staking.</p>
        <p>After the first year, the plants reseeded themselves without any help from me. The illustration on the seed package had shown equal numbers of purple, white and pink flowering stalks. Ninety percent of mine were purple, leading me to the conclusion that the genes for pink and white flowers must be recessive.</p>
        <p>The wonderful thing about bellflowers is that there are species for every situation. Suppose you are stumped for an edging plant. You can invest in the Blue Clips or White Clips varieties of Carpathian Harebell (Campanula carpatica), which are widely available, and grow to be only eight inches tall. Campanula portenschlagiana Resholdt's Variety is another low grower that would work equally well in the front of the border or in a rock garden.</p>
        <p>Just because you have a balcony or patio or porch garden does not mean that you can't get on the bellflower bandwagon. Campanula poscharskyana may be a mouthful to pronounce, but it trails wonderfully from a hanging basket.</p>
        <p>The Blue Gown variety has the added attraction of a starry white eye in the middle of each blossom. If you have one of the fashionable dry-laid stone walls, Blue Gown would surge over it magnificently. Campanula isophylla is another trailing type. A hanging basket of it can survive over winter in a cool greenhouse or a bright, underheated room.</p>
        <p>In the past I have had trouble growing delphiniums. My despair at this situation has led me to consider Chimney Bellflower (Campanula pyramidalis). The catalogs say that this cultivar can grow as tall as six  feet. ''Hortus,'' that indispensable reference work, allows that it will reach five feet, which is tall enough to assuage my delphinium grief.</p>
        <p>I believe I will get some of the white ones for my front yard beds, and perhaps a few blue ones for the back. Like most tall things, they have to be staked, but it's a small price to pay so the neighbors (at least those observing from a distance) think I have finally succeeded in outwitting the nefarious delphiniums.</p>
        <p>If some of your beds fry in the summer sun, consider the old favorite, Peachleaf Bellflower (Campanula persicifolia). I am especially attracted to Chettle Charm, an English hybrid that the catalog describes as ''creamy white suffused with blue at the margins.'' Like Peachleaf Bellflower, White Clustered Bellflower (Campanula glomerata) grows to be two to three feet tall, a moderate, middle-of-the-border height. Both species are also noted for their heat tolerance and nonwilting dispositions.</p>
        <p>Though hybridizers have obviously worked on campanulas, they have refrained from trying to make them into something else. There are, for example, no bellflowers that look like roses or spiders, and none in shades of orange, chartreuse or brown. Campanulas come in cooling colors and flower in the summer.</p>
        <p>With a little planning you can easily create a blue and white campanula garden that will bloom from June through August.</p>
        <p>Let everyone else deal with the black spot on their roses and the insatiable thirst of their hydrangeas. You and your bellflowers can enjoy the (partial) shade.</p>
        <p>THIS WEEK  From Seed To Big Bloom</p>
        <p>If you like starting plants from seed, Canterbury Bells can be planted either directly in the ground or in seed trays now. Be sure to water faithfully. They will establish themselves and form a rosette of leaves before the end of the current growing season, and flower next summer. Check for them on the seed racks at your local garden center.</p>
        <p>Peachleaf Bellflower is frequently available locally.</p>
        <p>But, if you meet with frustration in your corner of the world, you may have more luck with mail or Internet ordering. White Flower Farm (P.O. Box 50, Litchfield, Conn. 06759; 800-503-9624; www. whiteflowerfarm.com) and Bluestone Perennials (7211 Middle Ridge Road, Madison, Ohio 44057; 800-852-5243, www.bluestoneperennials .com) are excellent sources of a number of varieties.</p>
        <p>ELISABETH GINSBURG</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
