<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Works That Appear Soft but Are Posed in Stone</title>
    <meta content="06SEGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neuberger Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Segal, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4DD1F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Works That Appear Soft but Are Posed in Stone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with sculptor Barbara Segal, who is working on exhibit for Neuberger Museum of Art in Purchase of fabricated living room and one her family members chiseled from marble; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Victorian house was what you might expect of a sculptor with Barbara Segal's sensibilities: nooks and crannies, stained glass windows, the Hudson River and Palisades a stone's throw from the front porch. The house was quiet on a recent summer morning, with 11-year-old David away at camp, and Steve Mack, Ms. Segal's husband, at his job as a contractor.</p>
        <p>The artist herself, slightly breathless from deadline pressure, was working to finish a life-size stone portrait of David, which will be a focus of ''Staged in Stone,'' her coming exhibition at the Neuberger Museum of Art in Purchase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Victorian house was what you might expect of a sculptor with Barbara Segal's sensibilities: nooks and crannies, stained glass windows, the Hudson River and Palisades a stone's throw from the front porch. The house was quiet on a recent summer morning, with 11-year-old David away at camp, and Steve Mack, Ms. Segal's husband, at his job as a contractor.</p>
        <p>The artist herself, slightly breathless from deadline pressure, was working to finish a life-size stone portrait of David, which will be a focus of ''Staged in Stone,'' her coming exhibition at the Neuberger Museum of Art in Purchase.</p>
        <p>Known for her double entendre lingerie and clothing of chiseled marble, Ms. Segal has shifted gears for this show, which will be on view at the museum from next Sunday through Oct. 29. Visitors will walk into a fabricated living room, where the Segal-Mack family will be assembled in stone: the artist's father and husband smiling from a 5-by-7-foot slab of carved marble; her mother framed and glamorous in black and gray bas-relief; her son standing, in chiseled three dimensions, by a door.</p>
        <p>On this morning, however, David's portrait was still a work in progress in Ms. Segal's basement studio. The head awaited completion on one table, the hands rested on another, while the body stood beside a headless dummy. The dummy wore a denim shirt and khakis, which Ms. Segal was striving to represent in stone. She is known for this technique, which is her forte -- the ability to make what is hard and unyielding appear soft and fluid.</p>
        <p>''It looks much better with a head,'' she said, stepping back with chisel in hand to survey the sculpture. ''I'm really trying to get the movement of the fabric and folds on the body.'' David had grown three and a half inches since she began the work, and she wasn't happy with the head, especially around the mouth, nose and eyes. ''He's coming home next week, and he's going to sit here for two days,'' she said, so she could improve the likeness.</p>
        <p>Each portrait combines the fleeting with the enduring: Ms. Segal's love for her fast-growing son, who is posed like a welcoming angel at the door; her husband and father seated together as they never were in life, since her father died when she was 10; the impact of a beautiful mother on a young girl.</p>
        <p>Her mother's portrait, done from a photograph, resembles a dreamy-eyed Joan Crawford. ''She was a fashion model during World War II,'' Ms. Segal said. ''I always compared myself to her.''</p>
        <p>With that, the critically praised marble corsets and bustiers, on display in Ms. Segal's ''real'' living room, suddenly took on new meaning. Provocative and exquisitely carved, with sensuous folds and streaming garters, the lingerie suggested the voluptuous pleasures restricted to grown-ups. One bustier, carved from white marble with bronze lace running down the center, looked like a great flying bird (and is called ''Flight of Fancy''). Another, translucent with real lace and beads, gathered light in a window.  Ms. Segal said that as her own sense of self-confidence has grown, she has come to feel the ''power of female beauty.''</p>
        <p>''I think I'm a post-feminist,'' she said.  ''It's O.K. to like lingerie and be sexy when it's coming from a position of being a female and being powerful.''</p>
        <p>She would, however, rather discuss Renaissance carving techniques than psychology and comparisons to her mother. She became seriously interested in stone after studying sculpture in Paris and Italy. ''I was so awed by the beauty of the architecture,'' she said. ''I always wanted to get that feeling in my work -- that's why I started with the female, from a place of sensual arousal, beauty and passion.''</p>
        <p>Though her work has a contemporary edge, she identifies with artists of the past. ''I have conversations in my head with Bernini,'' she said, meaning Gianlorenzo Bernini. She calls herself a dinosaur -- no Web site for her -- yet her multi-colored marble bathrobe, shirt and smoking jacket convey a hip sense of humor.</p>
        <p>Such self-contradictions don't faze her.</p>
        <p>''Part of me is very kitsch, American, suburban,'' she said. ''That's mixed with a European sensibility'' that is influenced by ''the beautiful work of the Italian Baroque artists.''</p>
        <p>Around her house are other works in the same anachronistic spirit: an elegantly carved marble pinball machine, with nuclear missiles ready to fire. A coffee table covered with a trompe l'oeil decorated cloth, made entirely of carved marble (which will be in the Neuberger show). An apron resembling a wedding cake, suggesting the figure of a woman.</p>
        <p>Next, she said, she will do a series of stone portraits ''of interesting people in interesting poses in high relief in frames.''</p>
        <p>Nor has she finished making lingerie. ''I have a piece of orange alabaster downstairs,'' she said, conjuring up the possibilities. ''It's like an orange Popsicle.''</p>
        <p>Another idea is to cover female forms with molded rubber lace and then remove the forms, leaving the ghosts of women in free-standing lace. Pieces of rubber lace trail over two mannequins in her studio.</p>
        <p>Ms. Segal, who teaches at the School of Visual Arts in Manhattan and the Westchester Art Workshop in White Plains, said she has reached a point of technical expertise that will allow her to do whatever she wants.  ''I love to carve,'' she said, observing that her great-grandfather, who ran a furniture business, was a carver, too. ''I'm doing something from the past and hoping to retell the story -- the story that the material can tell.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
