<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: David W. Simpson; WM Growth Fund of the Northwest</title>
    <meta content="06INVO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WM Growth Fund of the Northwest</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DD153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: David W. Simpson; WM Growth Fund of the Northwest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes work of David W Simpson, manager of $721 million WM Growth Fund of the Northwest; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE other people who live in Seattle, David W. Simpson is never too far from Mount Rainier, the highest peak in the Northwest. But he is often closer than most. On weekends and during vacations, Mr. Simpson leads climbers over the Mount Rainier's glaciers and rocks; on weekdays, he drives past the mountain on his way to work managing the $721.1 million WM Growth Fund of the Northwest.</p>
        <p>The mountain is also the polestar of the portfolio, whose prospectus requires it to be at least 65 percent invested in companies with headquarters in Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Montana and Alaska. The remainder must be in companies doing business in that region. The geographic area may be small, but it has been fertile territory for investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE other people who live in Seattle, David W. Simpson is never too far from Mount Rainier, the highest peak in the Northwest. But he is often closer than most. On weekends and during vacations, Mr. Simpson leads climbers over the Mount Rainier's glaciers and rocks; on weekdays, he drives past the mountain on his way to work managing the $721.1 million WM Growth Fund of the Northwest.</p>
        <p>The mountain is also the polestar of the portfolio, whose prospectus requires it to be at least 65 percent invested in companies with headquarters in Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Montana and Alaska. The remainder must be in companies doing business in that region. The geographic area may be small, but it has been fertile territory for investors.</p>
        <p>''We're quite diversified in terms of industries, and we've become something of a hotbed of technology,'' Mr. Simpson said from his office overlooking Puget Sound. ''Many executives leave Microsoft with enormous amounts of wealth that they use to finance new businesses, seeding the region with start-ups.''</p>
        <p>The fund returned 26.8 percent a year, on average, for the three years through Thursday, versus 7.4 percent for its peers among small blend funds, according to Morningstar Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson, 41, can pluck almost any of the roughly 300 public companies in those five states. He can find long-term capital growth in start-ups  or choose behemoths like Starbucks, Microsoft and Nike. Small fry make up 60 percent of the portfolio; the balance is split between midsize and large-cap companies.</p>
        <p>His style could be called eclectic. The fund may hold basic materials companies in forestry and steel as well as red-hot technology concerns. Unprofitable biotech businesses rub shoulders with value plays. ''There's a perception that regional funds are dependent on the local economy,'' he said. ''But that's not true. What drives the companies we buy are national and global markets.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson works with three equity analysts to pick the fund's 70 or so holdings. He aims to keep shares at least three to five years; the turnover rate is 40 percent.</p>
        <p>He does not use computer screens to scout out purchases. ''I keep a hit list of new companies that I look at every day,'' he said, ''and I pay attention to the local news and investment analysts.''</p>
        <p>In particular, he wants companies to have relatively low debt and adequate working capital. Although working-capital needs vary by industry, as a rule of thumb he wants companies with current assets that exceed current liabilities, and the bigger the margin, the better. He also checks a company's ''quick ratio,'' which compares cash and accounts receivable to current liabilities; again, bigger is better.</p>
        <p>Generally, he wants a company to have a price-to-earnings multiple that is lower than its growth rate, although he will pay more for technology companies and less for consumer cyclicals.</p>
        <p>''I want to identify a competitive advantage and make sure that it is protected,'' he said. That advantage may be a brand name (Starbucks), a technology (Intel or Microsoft) or domination of a small market niche (Electro Scientific Industries).</p>
        <p>Solid management is vital. For big companies, he relies on Wall Street research to evaluate management's record. ''I'm more active talking to management of smaller companies,'' he said, ''because we can gather information that's not well understood on the Street.''</p>
        <p>What does he look for? ''I like them to be able to articulate business strategy in a sensible way,'' he said. ''And I prefer management that can answer my detailed questions on the spot, because it means they have their finger on the pulse of the business.''</p>
        <p>MR. SIMPSON recently added shares of Paccar Inc., a Bellevue, Wash., company that sells heavy-duty trucks. ''The stock was very inexpensive, because an industry downturn is under way domestically,'' he said. ''But the company is more global than perceived.''</p>
        <p>The company has some debt but low fixed costs because it assembles trucks from components rather than manufacturing them from scratch, he added. That has helped earnings during the downturn.</p>
        <p>He first bought shares in 1991 at $16.96 and recently added more in the low 40's. They closed on Friday at  $41.9375, or almost seven times Wall Street's earnings estimate of $6.27 a share for 2000.</p>
        <p>The fund also expanded its position in Monaco Coach, a manufacturer of recreational vehicles in Coburg, Ore. ''We're playing into a strong demographic trend,'' he said. ''Young retirees love these things, and the market should be very strong as baby boomers reach retirement age.''</p>
        <p>The company's stock price is down because of rising interest rates and fuel prices, he said, but the company is debt-free and management is adjusting production. He started buying in July 1999 and has paid an average of $12.94. The stock now trades at $15.8125, or more than six times the consensus 2000 earnings estimate of $2.48 a share.</p>
        <p>Another favorite is the Corixa Corporation, which he bought at the initial offering in 1997 at $13 a share. It closed on Friday at $38.875. Corixa, a biotechnology company in Seattle, is developing vaccines for cancer and autoimmune diseases. Its chairman and chief executive, Steven Gillis, was co-founder of Immunex, another biotechnology company in Seattle. Mr. Simpson said he had ''confidence in his grasp of the business and science of managing a biotech company.''</p>
        <p>Canadian regulators recently approved the company's melanoma vaccine, and approval by the Food and Drug Administration is expected by year-end, he said.</p>
        <p>Wall Street's consensus estimate is that the company will lose $1.62 a share this year. Nevertheless, Mr. Simpson is optimistic about the long-term prospects.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
