<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Taste for Frequent-Flier Miles</title>
    <meta content="BPSHEE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheehan, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D7133DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1254" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Taste for Frequent-Flier Miles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SHEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sheehan, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Sheehan travel essay describes some of the bargains she has gotten, and round-about ways she has traveled, while trying to take advantage of frequent-flyer bonus points; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I AM my mother's daughter: I love the idea of getting something for nothing. In the 1960's, mother went from bank to bank, bringing home a new appliance each time she opened a $25 savings account. By the 70's, we were both collecting the green stamps grocery stores handed us with our purchases and redeeming them for toys for my young girls.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, with the advent of frequent-flier miles, getting something for nothing took a major turn for the better. I earned ample mileage (and subsequent free trips around the country) simply by flying a lot in the course of researching magazine articles and books. Later, with the felicitous appearance of airline credit cards, I charged everything possible to these plastic rectangles and flew to Europe free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I AM my mother's daughter: I love the idea of getting something for nothing. In the 1960's, mother went from bank to bank, bringing home a new appliance each time she opened a $25 savings account. By the 70's, we were both collecting the green stamps grocery stores handed us with our purchases and redeeming them for toys for my young girls.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, with the advent of frequent-flier miles, getting something for nothing took a major turn for the better. I earned ample mileage (and subsequent free trips around the country) simply by flying a lot in the course of researching magazine articles and books. Later, with the felicitous appearance of airline credit cards, I charged everything possible to these plastic rectangles and flew to Europe free.</p>
        <p>Last August, when one card offered double mileage for all purchases for a year, I forsook the others and paid every supermarket and department store bill, as well as all newspaper subscriptions, burglar-alarm maintenance bills and charitable donations with my Delta Optima. A biography of my life appears in monthly installments on the credit card statements.</p>
        <p>I am also my mother's daughter in that I have spent most of my life chasing seven pounds up and down the scale. Last spring, while tossing a package of Healthy Choice macaroni and cheese into my shopping cart, I read on the box that I would receive 500 free miles for every 10 Healthy Choice products I bought before the end of the year. By Dec. 31, 1999, I had a collection of 110 proofs-of-purchase from 55 lunches of Colonial Chicken Pie and 55 dinners of Chicken and Vegetables Marsala. I had also lost 10 pounds from eating out of cardboard boxes.</p>
        <p>I mailed them to Healthy Choice, received certificates valid for 5,500 miles on a number of participating airlines, and sent them to TWA, where they brought my mileage to just over the 25,000 miles required for a free round-trip economy ticket in the United States.</p>
        <p>I paid my way to an assortment of cities  this year, saving the California interviews for a new book until last. I knew that TWA flew there from our home in Washington by way of its hub in St. Louis. In June I called  TWA and asked to fly to San Francisco on July 6. I was told I could go to Ontario.</p>
        <p>''Thanks, not going to Canada,'' I said to the person at TWA's 800 number.</p>
        <p>''Ontario, California,'' she said. ''It's an airport 46 miles from Los Angeles.''</p>
        <p>I kept telephoning but TWA steadfastly declined to put me on a flight to San Francisco, where I had four interviews in four days. I also had an interview in central Los Angeles on July 11. TWA would let we fly out to Ontario on July 6 and then home on July 12 from Orange County Airport, 36 miles from Los Angeles International Airport. After 57 phone calls, I persuaded a person at TWA's 800 number to let me fly home from LAX, although not at a convenient hour -- I would have a three-hour layover in St. Louis instead of the hour layover available to paying passengers. But the basic arrangement would work.</p>
        <p>I bought a United round-trip ticket with a flight from Ontario to San Francisco on July 7 and one from San Francisco to LAX three days later, for just over $100. Flying TWA to Ontario through St. Louis was fine, and a night at the Super 8 Motel in Ontario was more than fine. Some months earlier, I had discovered the charms of Super 8's -- firm beds, free Continental breakfasts and reasonable prices. In small towns like Le Mars, Iowa, there are no upscale hotel chains.</p>
        <p>I arrived at Ontario Airport at 9 a.m. on July 7 for my 10 a.m. United flight to San Francisco. An agent could be heard telling another passenger that the 10 a.m. flight had been canceled because of fog in San Francisco. ''My boyfriend says there's no fog in San Francisco,'' a woman waving a cell phone shouted to the agent.</p>
        <p>''Well, if there's no fog, then there are high clouds over San Francisco,'' the agent retorted.</p>
        <p>We were to be put on the 12:30 p.m. flight, but upon further questioning were told United would have no flight leaving Ontario for northern California until 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>I asked a skycap if any other airline flew to the San Francisco area. Southwest did, he said. I sprinted a quarter-mile with my luggage to the Southwest terminal, bought a $100 one-way ticket to Oakland, and was there by noon. I didn't see any fog or high clouds over either Oakland or San Francisco. I later learned that a slowdown by United pilots had been disrupting flight schedules.</p>
        <p>Three-hour layovers are regrettably frequent when planes experience mechanical problems or encounter bad weather. One sits and frets and doesn't dare leave the departure gate, even as projected delays escalate from 3 to 18 hours. This layover was different. I knew I would be in St. Louis from 4 to 7 p.m. on July 12 and decided to make the most or my time. I sent an e-mail message to my friend Pat, a knowledgeable St. Louis resident, with a string of questions.</p>
        <p>I started with airport facilities. Any manicurists? (I had recently had my nails done at Reagan National in Washington.) Any interesting stores, like the Body Shop or the Gap? (I had once done my Christmas shopping at Pittsburgh airport.) ''No manicure just yet, but by September you'll be able to get a back rub or foot massage,'' Pat answered. ''No particularly interesting stores come to mind.''</p>
        <p>WELL, then, might the Cardinals be playing a home game on July 12? I would have liked to see Mark McGwire at bat. ''No ball teams playing anywhere,'' Pat wrote. ''It's the day after the All-Star Game, part of a three-day break for every team.''</p>
        <p>I asked her about a few of the city's celebrated attractions -- the St. Louis Art Museum, the zoo, the Missouri Botanical Garden, the Scott Joplin House and the Arch. ''The last place I would go on a July afternoon would be the Arch, as there are HUGE lines all summer long to go up to the top in the trams,'' she wrote. ''Of course, you could hang out under the Arch without having to stand in line for the tram, but you still would encounter MANY sweaty people.''</p>
        <p>To anyone who has grown up in Manhattan, huge lines and sweaty people are part of one's heritage. I spent a little over half an hour getting to the Arch on the MetroLink light-rail system and a glorious something-for-nothing hour marveling at Eero Saarinen's Gateway Arch, a stunning memorial to Thomas Jefferson and others who expanded the country westward. I MetroLinked back to the airport, and flew home.</p>
        <p>When I returned, my husband reminded me of a long-ago Thanksgiving weekend he and my father had spent assembling a green-stamp made-in-Czechoslovakia bicycle for our older daughter.</p>
        <p>Our daughter, the former bicycle rider turned business executive, extolled the merits of taking and paying for nonstop coast-to-coast flights. I spotted a picture of an American Airlines jet on a box of All-Bran on the breakfast table. Kellogg's is now offering 500 free miles on American for mailing in five pictures of the plane on boxes of its cereals. I took out the scissors.</p>
        <p>SUSAN SHEEHAN is a staff writer for The New Yorker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SUSAN SHEEHAN is a staff writer for The New Yorker.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
