<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The One-Room Schoolhouse</title>
    <meta content="ROOMT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bloomfield (Montana)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borntrager, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gulliford, Andrew (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">America's Country Schools (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DD113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The One-Room Schoolhouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jodi Wilgoren</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <dateline>Bloomfield, Mont.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on one-room schoolhouse in Bloomfield, Montana, where Linda Borntrager teaches 13 pupils of various ages; photos; quaint rural schools have almost disappeared in America, but traditions of intimacy and multi-age learning provide education model for larger districts nationwide; Andrew Gulliford, author of book America's Country Schools, explains that country schools, which trained generations of Americans, are very good at ego and character development and at turning out well-rounded individuals (special section, Education Life) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCHOOL doesn't start until the Mullets arrive. Today, they are late, so we wait.</p>
        <p>Kenny Whitmer, age 7, is going 'round and 'round on the rickety pentagon that a local welder built out of $46 worth of pipes half a century ago. Julia Lindquist, a seventh-grade loner, is sitting by herself, contemplating the gaping sky and the wind pushing waves through the grassy field. The boys are shooting hoops, as usual. They let Monica Hostetler, 14, play to even out the teams -- first when there are only three of them, then again when there are five. In between, she hangs at the other end of the makeshift court, lobbing jumpers into the net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCHOOL doesn't start until the Mullets arrive. Today, they are late, so we wait.</p>
        <p>Kenny Whitmer, age 7, is going 'round and 'round on the rickety pentagon that a local welder built out of $46 worth of pipes half a century ago. Julia Lindquist, a seventh-grade loner, is sitting by herself, contemplating the gaping sky and the wind pushing waves through the grassy field. The boys are shooting hoops, as usual. They let Monica Hostetler, 14, play to even out the teams -- first when there are only three of them, then again when there are five. In between, she hangs at the other end of the makeshift court, lobbing jumpers into the net.</p>
        <p>It's 10, 12, maybe 15 minutes past 8 a.m. when the forest green 1998 Oldsmobile Regency pulls into the dirt driveway and the Mullets tumble out: Marshall, the eighth grader, Winston, a year younger, Merrilee, 11, and little Sterling, age 9. They live the farthest from the white clapboard schoolhouse, 11 miles down gravel roads across empty plains, so their lateness might be forgivable -- except that it holds up everybody else.</p>
        <p>As the Mullets pull backpacks, musical instruments and lunch boxes from the trunk, the boys on the blacktop hurry to land one more basket. Linda Borntrager, the teacher, stands on the steps, one hand on the hip of her faded jeans, the other clasping the old cow bell, ready to ring. It's time to raise the flag, say the Pledge of Allegiance, start another day at Bloomfield School.</p>
        <p>''If they're absent, we really have declined enrollment for the day,'' Mrs. Borntrager, 48, laughed about the Mullets. The family accounts for four of her 13 pupils, and two more are Mullet cousins. Children at Bloomfield ''just have to learn how to be flexible,'' she added. ''That's a good skill in life.''</p>
        <p>Bloomfield, which opened in 1908, is one of nearly 400 remaining public one-room schoolhouses in the nation, at once a nostalgic remnant of the past and a modern outlet for educational experimentation. Even as the number of tiny rural schools has plunged in recent years, the fundamental aspects of teaching inside them -- from multi-age classrooms and peer tutoring to interdisciplinary projects and keeping students with the same teacher for more than one year -- are being copied in large school systems across the country.</p>
        <p>Small classes and, especially, small schools, are increasingly seen as crucial to students' success in the early grades, leading many urban educators to create islands within large school buildings that attempt to foster the intimacy and individual attention of places like Bloomfield.</p>
        <p>And, with the Internet, long-held concerns about the narrow curriculum available in an isolated one-teacher school are fading. ''One-room schools really represent, I think, the best model for training American children for the first through the eighth grades,'' said Andrew Gulliford, director of the Center for Southwest Studies at Fort Lewis College in Durango, Colo., who is the nation's leading expert on one-room schools.</p>
        <p>''In terms of ego development, in terms of character, in terms of personality, in terms of the well-rounded individual fitting in with the group, country schools are very efficient -- they helped train generations of Americans,'' added Professor Gulliford, author of the definitive book on the subject, ''America's Country Schools'' (University of Colorado Press). ''In a one-room schoolhouse, every child counts -- they've always counted, whether it was 1890 or 1990. How can you say that in most modern educational systems today? It's just not true.''</p>
        <p>IT is 10:50 a.m. on a Tuesday, a couple of hours after I've arrived here amid the cattle ranches and wheat farms, and Mrs. Borntrager is deep into an eighth-grade math lesson on symmetry, using a mirror and a book of drawings to show how even complex shapes can sometimes be divided exactly in half.</p>
        <p>Kenny, meanwhile, is hunched over a first-grade reader. Sterling, the third grader, is copying contractions into his notebook. Brady Boese, 12, and Matthew Kanagy, 14, are suffering through a quiz on probability and percentages, while Brady's twin brother, Kirk, is pondering a work sheet titled ''Remembering Details,'' based on the novel, ''Where the Red Fern Grows.''</p>
        <p>Julia, a seventh grader, has her nose stuck in ''The Call of the Wild,'' legs outstretched, ankles crossed, and Winston, age 13, is methodically computing fractions and decimals. Daniel Whitmer, six years older than Kenny, is tackling problems from a math text, and Keith Hall, 13, is ''Drawing Conclusions'' -- at least according to the paper on his desk -- from Red Fern. Clayton Unruh has his seventh-grade spelling workbook open to a crossword puzzle. Merrilee, 11, is in the back of the room, using a computer to type sentences she made up from a list of new vocabulary words.</p>
        <p>It could be educational chaos, but all is quiet except for the ceiling fans spinning overhead and the teacher's low-voiced prompts to the two students at her half-moon table in the corner. Most of the children have pencils moving, pages turning. Julia or Keith or Daniel occasionally stare blankly out the large windows at the endless brown earth. And, every so often, one of the boys pops up from his desk, carrying a book or a paper over to Mrs. B. with a question.</p>
        <p>Eyes searching behind his wire-rims, Brady, 12, wants to know which number should be the numerator as he forms an algebraic equation to answer the question: 18 is 30 percent of what number?</p>
        <p>''It's a quiz, Brady, so you're going to have to figure it out on your own,'' the teacher says. ''One thing is to try both and then use your sense.''</p>
        <p>By 11, it's time for a different math ''class'' -- Julia and Keith, seventh graders who lag behind, and Merrilee, a fifth grader a bit advanced for her age, stand at the chalkboard adding and subtracting fractions. Four reading groups have already cycled through Mrs. B.'s station this morning. At 11:15, the children race outside for calisthenics, led by little Kenny, as much the school's mascot as he is one of its students. They fold their legs into a pretzel stretch, then run around the wheat field that lies beyond the school's large yard in a haphazard training regimen for the coming track meet with nearby one-room schools. Today, the twins will have to wait until after lunch for math.</p>
        <p>''We just do kind of a rotation,'' Mrs. Borntrager shrugged. ''I think my goal is to try to make sure everybody's doing constructive work almost all the time.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Borntrager, who is paid $26,000 a year -- twice what she made when she started at Bloomfield 17 years ago -- often has as many as 25 different lessons to prepare each day. This year, her 13 students are in six grades, but she sometimes subdivides the older students according to ability or interest. For example, ''The Red Badge of Courage'' and ''The Call of the Wild'' are novels of similar difficulty but appeal to different students.</p>
        <p>At Bloomfield, students spend most of the day working by themselves at their desks, old-fashioned wood-topped tables with attached chairs. Mrs. Borntrager relies heavily on textbooks and work sheets she has collected over the years; she rarely lectures to the group, instead running mini-classes in her corner, most lasting no more than 10 minutes. A teacher's aide often helps the younger boys with reading or art projects, or stands by a student's desk, administering a vocabulary test in the most nonthreatening way.</p>
        <p>''The kids who come out of Bloomfield have real good study stills,'' said Cindi Hostetler, Monica's mother, who teaches music and serves as a part-time aide at the school, earning the minimum wage. ''They know how to go back to their desks and go to work.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Borntrager does not assign homework, but students who fall behind must finish their work after school. At the high school in Richey, Mont., about 20 miles away, Bloomfield graduates often rise to the top of their classes. Last spring, alumni of the school won the top awards for freshmen, sophomores and juniors at the Eastern Montana Math Meet.</p>
        <p>Statewide, students from elementary schools with fewer than 40 students tend to outperform their peers on standardized tests in every subject. During the 1997-98 school year, in both fourth and eighth grades, more students from Montana's small schools were rated ''advanced'' or ''proficient'' -- and fewer were ''novice'' or ''near proficiency'' -- than their counterparts in reading, math, language arts, science and social studies.</p>
        <p>''What you're showing there is small class-size ratio and individual teacher contact with kids,'' said Lance Melton, executive director of the Montana School Boards Association.</p>
        <p>ONE of the advantages parents and educators see in one-room schools is the natural tailoring of the curriculum to children's needs.</p>
        <p>''Nobody gets left through the cracks,'' said Mrs. Hostetler, whose husband and two older children also graduated from Bloomfield. ''If you're a smart kid, they take you where you can go. If you're struggling, you get the individual attention.''</p>
        <p>That is what brought Keith Hall to Bloomfield last spring. Growing up in the Portland, Ore., suburbs, Keith, now 13, bounced among nine different schools, including one with 3,000 students. He was learning very little, but getting into plenty of trouble. ''They were just shoving him through,'' said Phyllis Mullet, his grandmother and guardian.</p>
        <p>Keith spent the summer of 1999 on Mrs. Mullet's farm here, hunting and fishing and tooling around on the four-wheeler. After another year of fighting at home and at school, he returned to Bloomfield two weeks before school let out in May, upping the school's enrollment by 8 percent.</p>
        <p>He reads at about a third-grade level, misspells even basic words like reason (reazer), other (outer) and touch (tuch). But Keith, one of two Bloomfield students who take Ritalin, is a sweet boy who stays after school to help Mrs. B. move furniture, a smart kid who is energized by tactile science projects like identifying bone fragments from owl pellets or building rockets out of soda bottles.</p>
        <p>''The other schools were junk,'' said Keith, whose dark-brown buzz cut is a remnant of his city brashness. ''This one, it's different.</p>
        <p>''At my old school, it would take them half the year just to know you. There was, like, 32 kids in my class, so it was kind of hard to ask the teachers questions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Here, they keep track and stuff. They tell you, 'do you have this reading or this done.' There, they never tell you.''</p>
        <p>IN 1917, there were 196,000 one-teacher public schools in the United States. At last count, in 1996, there were 380.</p>
        <p>Spread throughout 28 states, one-room schools are concentrated in Nebraska, which has 128, and Montana, which has 81. But while schools throughout the rural Midwest and Mountain States have been consolidating, California has seen a 22 percent growth in the number of one-room schools in the past five years, fueled in part by flexible work schedules and telecommuting policies that allow families to pursue frontier living again.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Amish and Mennonite communities, among others, have been opening private one-room schools, which total nearly 1,200; about a third of them are in Pennsylvania. Among the public schools, average enrollment in 1996 was 9.4 students, according to a study by researchers at Brigham Young University in Provo, Utah.</p>
        <p>Here in Dawson County, a 2,358 square-mile expanse of empty plains and badlands that was once called the gateway to Montana, there were 138 rural schools in 1919, according to a fading chronicle of their history. A ledger kept by the county superintendent shows that in 1955, the county had 47 teachers. That dwindled to 32 over the next decade, then to 21 in 1969. When Mrs. Borntrager arrived at Bloomfield in 1983, she was one of nine teachers in the county; today there are three.</p>
        <p>The attrition is mostly about economics, as fewer and fewer families find they can survive farming the arid land. There are now 53 stops on the 44-mile postal route around Bloomfield; once, there were two routes, with 80 families each.</p>
        <p>But Bloomfield, a one-gas-station outpost 247 miles from the Billings airport -- and 27 miles from the nearest McDonald's -- is also losing students to home-schooling, which is increasingly popular among the area's religious Mennonites, and to the schools in Richey, the nearest town, where students can play on basketball and volleyball teams. This fall, Marshall and Monica will start high school and the Boese twins and Clayton Unruh plan to enroll at Richey, leaving Mrs. Borntrager with just eight students. The next kindergartner on the horizon is Elizabeth Nissley, who will not enroll until the fall of 2001.</p>
        <p>''That's probably why I'll stop teaching,'' Mrs. Borntrager sighed one afternoon during the eight-mile drive from school to her modest house, a double-wide trailer with an addition her husband built. ''We're going to run out of kids.''</p>
        <p>Once, Bloomfield was packed with 40 students, and voters approved a special tax to create a second classroom. Now the two rooms are combined into a 35-foot by 60-foot space, filled not with children but with an upright piano, project tables for art and audio, three computers, and a library of 4,000 worn paperbacks running around the perimeter. In the basement, there is enough open space to hold gym class indoors.</p>
        <p>The first Bloomfield School burned in 1918. Another fire felled the new one a decade later. This third building got electricity in 1948 (after years of running a wire from a 32-volt battery at the store down the road) and indoor plumbing in 1950, although the outhouse, with separate wood-lidded toilets for boys and girls, still stands out back.</p>
        <p>''This, to me, doesn't look like a school,'' said Jeff Whitmer, 77, Kenny and Daniel's grandfather and the unofficial historian of Bloomfield. ''This, to me, is just like a big living room.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitmer, a 1936 Bloomfield graduate, built the merry-go-round in 1954 or 1955, after the ladies of Bloomfield discovered that $46 would not buy them much playground equipment. He rode on the giant stride, a kind of swing made of a metal pole with chains hanging off the top, when it was built in the 1930's. Back then they rode horses to school, or sleds in winter. It would take a while for the coal furnace to warm up, so the water bucket in the hallway would be frozen solid each morning. There were no janitors; the children cleaned the classroom themselves.</p>
        <p>''Our classroom had four rows of desks and a big bench at the front for the teacher,'' Mr. Whitmer said. ''The teacher would holler out, 'Fourth Grade Arithmetic!' and you'd march on down. You were told to shut up about twice, and then you were hit upside the head, or hit with a book.''</p>
        <p>Today's discipline is somewhat softer. Occasionally Mrs. Borntrager will look up from her corner and say ''Quiet, please, guys,'' or ''People, there's too much talking in here,'' but there are not a lot of rules.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Borntrager, who was born in Hebron, N.D., rode a horse four miles each way to Farmer's Valley, a one-room schoolhouse, through fifth grade. After attending the state university in Fargo, N.D., she worked as a waitress, then for the telephone company in Denver and in Arizona. After divorcing her first husband, she returned home to get an elementary education degree. When she fell in love with a farmer-rancher from these parts, the teacher's desk at Bloomfield was vacant.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if I'd like teaching in a big classroom, with all the other things that go with it,'' said Mrs. Borntrager, whose three children are among the 28 students who have been graduated from the school since she arrived. ''The teachers' lounge. The rigidity as far as the classroom timing.</p>
        <p>''I'm probably like the kids in a sense,'' she added. ''I like the ability to have that freedom.''</p>
        <p>In a community where the drivers of every passing car acknowledge each other with a half-wave, Mrs. Borntrager is surrounded by her successes -- and cannot walk away from students who are struggling.</p>
        <p>''I don't have to spend two weeks in the fall figuring out where these kids are, and I can be, in the back of my mind, planning during the summer,'' she said. ''We don't have to spend any time getting to know each other in the fall. We can get right on to it.''</p>
        <p>KENNY, his blond bangs almost hiding his ice-blue eyes, is paired with Monica, whose metal-filled mouth and experiments with eyeliner betray her entry into adolescence. They are planning their bottle rocket for the end-of-the-year launch.</p>
        <p>''What color do you want?'' the eighth grader asks.</p>
        <p>''You can pick this time,'' Kenny says generously, then suggests that each name a favorite color to combine in the decorations.</p>
        <p>Kenny picks yellow. Monica picks orange.</p>
        <p>''Yellow and orange?'' Kenny squeals. ''Those are my favorite colors!''</p>
        <p>Monica gets the construction paper. Kenny names the project The Rocketeer. She draws the lines, he tries the scissors.</p>
        <p>''We're going to make it actually shoot up in the air,'' she tells him confidently, then adds: ''I don't know exactly how.''</p>
        <p>Kenny concentrates, chews a lip.</p>
        <p>''I can't cut straight,'' he says.</p>
        <p>''It's a good thing I didn't draw straight, huh?'' she responds.</p>
        <p>''How'd you know I couldn't cut straight?'' Kenny asks.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know,'' Monica says. ''That's good. That's what gives it character.''</p>
        <p>The rocket project is a classic one-room schoolhouse lesson. For Kenny, it is practice with shapes. For Sterling, the third grader, it is real-life application of the concepts of aerodynamics, thrust and lift-off in his science text. The older students have researched the space shuttle on the Internet. There will be fraction work as the students decide how much water to put in the bottles. And, it's all about teamwork.</p>
        <p>The challenge of teaching at Bloomfield is finding things that are interesting to a boy of 7 and a girl of 14 -- and everyone in between. The peer tutoring, like pairing Monica and Kenny, often creates the most magical moments of learning. And while it can be lonely to be the only girl of a given age, the small, multi-age setting limits peer pressure; children have little choice but to get along.</p>
        <p>Before moving to Bloomfield, ''I got picked on a lot,'' said Julia, whose skull was malformed at birth and has required several surgeries, leaving a prominent scar on the top of her head.</p>
        <p>Julia, 13, draws beautiful pictures of horses and is writing her 11th book in a series about mining, but, ''for some reason, I kind of get along better with younger kids,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I like watching cartoons and playing with toys. Merrilee and Sterling and Kenny and I can really have conversations,'' she added. ''Probably when I get into high school, I'll stay by myself a lot.''</p>
        <p>In gym, Cori Schultz, the teacher's aide, tries to separate brothers and create games where the eighth graders won't mow down the first grader. Instead of traditional kickball, they put a garbage can at home plate, and kickers score points according to what base they reach before the fielders land the ball in the bucket (I played to even out the teams, and triumphed with a home run).</p>
        <p>After two days of designing and building the bottle rockets, with their ever-more elaborate noses and fins, it was time for the launch. We placed the homemade launcher around second base, and lined up. The eldest Mullet sat atop the swing set with a video camera, Matthew Kanagy stood ready to release the bottles, and Keith Hall primed the pump. The students scattered to see which rocket would fly highest and farthest, which would twirl and spin, and which would fall flat.</p>
        <p>Keith's masterpiece, its two-foot cardboard cylinder festooned with a picture of President Clinton, floundered; too heavy. The Mountain Dewzy, by Winston and Matthew, performed a spectacular loop-the-loop before sputtering out. Monica and Kenny's Rocketeer looked pretty but had an unremarkable ride. The strongest rocket was the unlikely, simple design by Julia and Sterling, who filled their bottle half full and used the maximum amount of air.</p>
        <p>Daniel's was the biggest disappointment. Its small orange wings and white cone head could not stand up to the stiff wind. He had planned to fill the bottle 5/8 full of water, but some spilled out. And Daniel only used four air pumps -- in retrospect, clearly not enough.</p>
        <p>He moped around the field alone awhile, ignoring the other rockets as they flew overhead. If only he could try again. He would use maximum air, less water. Design a stiff cardboard cone to cut through the wind. Waste less time on the useless paper fins. And, definitely, not go first, before the kinks are worked out of the launching system.</p>
        <p>''Did you say we're doing this again next year?'' Daniel asked the teacher, hopefully.</p>
        <p>''You want to do it next year?'' Mrs. Borntrager replied. Well, why not?</p>
        <p>Jodi Wilgoren is a national education correspondent for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jodi Wilgoren is a national education correspondent for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
