<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proposal to Ban Sale Of Diet Drug to Minors</title>
    <meta content="06DIET$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ephedrine (Chemical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DF173CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proposal to Ban Sale Of Diet Drug to Minors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester County (NY) Executive Andrew Spano proposes measure to prohibit sale of products containing herbal supplement called ephedrine, marketed as weight loss aid, to anyone under 18 and to warn consumers of their possible side effects (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is an herbal supplement called ephedrine and it is marketed as a sure-fire way to lose weight, build muscle or get high without using illegal drugs.</p>
        <p>But as products containing the substance come under increasing scrutiny by the federal Food and Drug Administration, County Executive Andrew J. Spano has proposed a law to prohibit the sale of ephedrine-containing items to anyone under 18 and to warn consumers about their possible side effects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is an herbal supplement called ephedrine and it is marketed as a sure-fire way to lose weight, build muscle or get high without using illegal drugs.</p>
        <p>But as products containing the substance come under increasing scrutiny by the federal Food and Drug Administration, County Executive Andrew J. Spano has proposed a law to prohibit the sale of ephedrine-containing items to anyone under 18 and to warn consumers about their possible side effects.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to wait for a death in Westchester to move on this,'' said Elaine M. Price, the county's director of consumer protection. ''Clearly, the evidence is compelling that the unregulated ephedrine products pose a public health risk.''</p>
        <p>Ephedrine comes from a plant known as ma huang, grown widely in Asia, and it can be found in more than 200 diet supplements, in often expensive pills and powders, in drinks and diet bars. Advocates say it decreases appetite, raises metabolism, improves concentration, burns fat and even enhances sexual performance.</p>
        <p>But because it is a central nervous system stimulant, similar to amphetamines, reactions can vary widely. Studies suggest that ephedrine can produce side effects that include anxiety, insomnia, hypertension, psychosis, kidney damage, dependency, heart attack, stroke and death.</p>
        <p>Roughly 70 deaths of people using products that were known to contain or may have contained ephedrine (some products were missing labels) are being studied by the Food and Drug Administration.</p>
        <p>A public hearing on the deaths and other reports will be held by the Food and Drug Administration in Washington on Tuesday and Wednesday. Over-the-counter drugs are subject to Food and Drug Administration regulation, but the agency's ability to regulate dietary supplements like ephedrine has been severely curtailed since the passage of the Dietary Supplement Health and Education Act in 1994.</p>
        <p>Florida banned the sales of herbal products that mimic the illegal drug ecstasy, which contained ephedrine, in 1996, a month and a half after a 20-year-old student from SUNY Albany, Peter Schlendorf, died of an overdose of Ultimate Xphoria on spring break.</p>
        <p>Douglas G. Aspros, chairman of the county Board of Health, said a ban on ephedrine products was considered in 1996, but that the board opted instead to launch a public education campaign.</p>
        <p>New York City is now considering legislation similar to Westchester's proposal, Mr. Spano said.</p>
        <p>In addition to barring sales of ephedrine-based products to minors, the local legislation would ban all sales of any products that suggest users will experience a rush or a high, Ms. Price said. The law would also require merchants to post signs warning of the side effects of ephedrine and to caution consumers to seek professional health advice before taking any supplements.</p>
        <p>June B. Hochberger, president of Mrs. Green's Natural Market, a chain of natural food stores, said she opposed that provision of the bill.</p>
        <p>''Why is there a necessity of warnings for ordinary, good-for-you supplements stuck into legislation banning the sale of ephedrine to minors?'' she said. ''We believe that is a little bit infringing on the freedoms and rights of ordinary consumers.''</p>
        <p>But Susan Tolchin, a spokeswoman for Mr. Spano, said the law is not meant to regulate vitamins. For vitamins, a warning would ask consumers to talk to a doctor before using such supplements. For anything with ephedrine, a warning about ''serious side effects'' would be required, she said.</p>
        <p>George S. Latimer, the chairman of the county's Board of Legislators, said the law appears to be a good idea but one that needs study in committees on health and legislation and possibly a public hearing.</p>
        <p>''If it can reduce a problem that is being experienced out on the streets then we will support it,'' Mr. Latimer, a Democrat, said. ''But we have to go through a process of analyzing the law in detail first.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
