<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Hudson River: Its History in Boats</title>
    <meta content="06ART.$19" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hudson River Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D61F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Hudson River: Its History in Boats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews exhibit tracing history of boats on Hudson River on view at Hudson River Museum in Yonkers, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE see boats as lenses,'' said Robert Panetta, a history professor at Marymount College in Tarrytown, in talking about the lavish, profusely documented exhibition ''Boats on the Hudson: Navigating Through History.'' He organized the exhibition with Ellen Keiter, curator of exhibitions, at the Hudson River Museum here. ''They're a way to look at the history of the river,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Eight different boats are examined in the show. On a walk through, the curators began with a dugout canoe -- or rather several different canoes on the way to completion.  There is even a tulip tree, whose wood the Indians used, as large as life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE see boats as lenses,'' said Robert Panetta, a history professor at Marymount College in Tarrytown, in talking about the lavish, profusely documented exhibition ''Boats on the Hudson: Navigating Through History.'' He organized the exhibition with Ellen Keiter, curator of exhibitions, at the Hudson River Museum here. ''They're a way to look at the history of the river,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Eight different boats are examined in the show. On a walk through, the curators began with a dugout canoe -- or rather several different canoes on the way to completion.  There is even a tulip tree, whose wood the Indians used, as large as life.</p>
        <p>''The several stages of the canoe were made by Jeff Kalin,'' Ms. Keiter said. ''He used authentic stone-scraping tools. He made almost everything in this section, including the paddles and traps. He calls himself a 'primitive technologist.'</p>
        <p>''The Indians would sink the boats during the winter,'' she said. ''This helped preserve them. This exhibition is full of the practical side of life in the river. In this way it is a complement to the Hudson River School, which saw the river in a romantic way.''</p>
        <p>But an outsize and rather romantic Hudson River School painting, ''The Landing of Henry Hudson,'' in which Indians go out in boats to greet the Half Moon, forms a bridge to the next ''lenses.''</p>
        <p>Sloops were single-mast sailboats used mainly to transport people and goods in the 18th and early 19th centuries. A quarter-scale model of a cargo dock on a sloop is the central feature of this section. ''It's not finished yet,'' Ms. Keiter said. ''We're going to get a mast.''.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panetta said: ''You have to understand how crowded with boats the river was. In 1832 there were 1,200 sloops sailing on the Hudson. It was rather chaotic at first, but as time went on, things became regularized according to schedules.''</p>
        <p>But it was the steamboat that really put America on a schedule. Robert Fulton's Claremont, reputed to be the first steamboat in 1807, is represented by a small model; the paddlewheel is minuscule compared with later ones. ''Fulton couldn't have been that confident; his ship was equipped with two masts and sails,'' Mr. Panetta said.</p>
        <p>The focus of the steamboat section is the Mary Powell, known as the Queen of the Hudson, which made day trips between Kingston and New York City, beginning in 1861 and continuing until 1917. The curators stress the Victorian-era's ornateness of this boat. It had every creature comfort, and a creature: there are photographs of Buster, a bull terrier. ''He was a religious dog,'' Ms. Keiter said. ''He would sit at the table with the passengers and bow his head in prayer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Panetta said, ''In all that time the Mary Powell had a perfect safety record.'' But accidents involving steamboats were common. The Henry Clay caught fire in 1852 trying to beat another steamer to Albany from New York City, and several dramatic lithographs illustrate that event.</p>
        <p>''The right word for the river is 'highway,' '' Mr. Panetta said. ''The river meant business. But just as today Westchester's roads go north and south -- it's almost impossible to get from east to west -- the Hudson was a north-south route until the advent of the ferry. The ferry functioned like a bridge until real bridges came along.'' There have always been ferries going from one side of the river to the other, but in the 19th century ferries and railroads teamed up to form a vast transportation network. Unlike today's highways, ''people could feel and smell nature.''</p>
        <p>Tugboats, workhorses of the river, continue to work with the railroads, pulling freight cars on barges. ''People wonder how such a small boat can pull those loads,'' Mr. Panetta said. ''They don't realize that a tugboat is just an engine on a deck.'' Fast disappearing on the lower Hudson are shad fisherman who have had their day in the sun. ''New York was a real fish culture,'' Mr. Panetta said. ''Servants used to complain about eating shad three times a day; they were called porcupines turned inside out for all the bones they have.''</p>
        <p>The shad fishing section may be a romantic exception to the exhibition's emphasis on business. While shad fishing was and is a business (there are shad fisherman who still work under the George Washington Bridge), the presence of a shad boat, the re-creation of a fisher's shanty and lore like the blooming flowers that mark each section of the short shad season steer viewers into a genuinely romantic environment.</p>
        <p>In a room by themselves are two boats existing purely for sport and pleasure: ice boats and sculls. A video projects large documents of an ice boat race. ''The quiet but powerful subtheme of this exhibition is speed,'' Mr. Panetta said while he was touring the steamboat section, but it's fully graspable here. ''An ice boat can go four times the speed of wind, and that must have seemed incredibly fast.''</p>
        <p>The rowing shell section includes many photographs of groups of men in the 19th century showing off their torsos built up by rowing. But there is also a simulated hands-on installation in which up to three viewers can learn to row, guided by a nine-minute videotape. Ms. Keiter said, ''We wanted an actual museum experience that wasn't for kids only.''</p>
        <p>''Boats on the Hudson'' is at the Hudson River Museum through Jan. 7. The information number is (914) 963-4550.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
