<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankee Paco Wins Hambletonian on Stamina</title>
    <meta content="06HAMB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hambletonian (Harness Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DD133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankee Paco Wins Hambletonian on Stamina</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.,Aug. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yankee Paco wins Hambletonian at Meadowlands Racetrack; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The favorite got locked in around the turn and the front-runner faded in the stretch in today's  $1 million 75th edition of the Hambletonian. That allowed Yankee Paco to take control in the stretch and capture the most prestigious event in harness racing this afternoon in ideal conditions at the Meadowlands Racetrack.</p>
        <p>Driven by Trevor Ritchie and trained by Doug McIntosh, Yankee Paco withstood pressure from Credit Winner for his sixth consecutive victory. A Canadian-bred chestnut, Yankee Paco finished three-quarters of a length ahead of Credit Winner, who edged Armbro Trick for second place. Yankee Paco covered the mile in 1:53 2/5 and paid $6.60 for a $2 bet to win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The favorite got locked in around the turn and the front-runner faded in the stretch in today's  $1 million 75th edition of the Hambletonian. That allowed Yankee Paco to take control in the stretch and capture the most prestigious event in harness racing this afternoon in ideal conditions at the Meadowlands Racetrack.</p>
        <p>Driven by Trevor Ritchie and trained by Doug McIntosh, Yankee Paco withstood pressure from Credit Winner for his sixth consecutive victory. A Canadian-bred chestnut, Yankee Paco finished three-quarters of a length ahead of Credit Winner, who edged Armbro Trick for second place. Yankee Paco covered the mile in 1:53 2/5 and paid $6.60 for a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>''I'm living a dream of when you were a kid,'' Ritchie said about his and McIntosh's first Hambletonian triumph.</p>
        <p>''This is just a special horse. He gets in a gear and keeps it. I was confident he'd be strong, but you never know until the wire.''</p>
        <p>Yankee Paco was in the middle of the field of 3-year-old trotters at the halfway point, but took control when Legendary Lover K, then the front-runner, faded on the rail in the stretch and Dreamaster, the favorite, was still locked. Dreamaster finished fifth and Legendary Lover K ended up sixth.</p>
        <p>Yankee Paco was purchased for $30,000 as a yearling in 1998 by the Ivey family, Dr. Tom of Cincinnati and his father, Harry, of Highland Park, Wis. With his victory today, Yankee Paco earned $1,551,047 for the season. His biggest victory before today was in the $840,100 Canadian Trotting Classic on June 24 at Woodbine near Toronto. ''He's a great athlete,'' McIntosh said of Yankee Paco, a son of Balanced Image. ''Sometimes trainers take too much credit for developing these things. This horse is just a natural. I think Balanced Image is the greatest trotting sire ever.''</p>
        <p>McIntosh said it was very unlikely that Yankee Paco would enter the Yonkers Trot, which means another year may go by without a Triple Crown winner for trotters since Super Bowl in 1972.</p>
        <p>John Campbell, who was seeking his sixth Hambletonian title as a driver, finished ninth after his horse, Pine Drop, broke twice. Berndt Hanover, with Mike Lachance driving, also had some misfortune. He pulled up and did not finish on a day of surprises before a crowd of 30,026, the largest here since 1994.</p>
        <p>There was a huge upset in the $500,000 Hambletonian Oaks, the Hambletonian equivalent for 3-year-old trotting fillies. Cologne Kosmos left as the 1-2 favorite but finished fifth in a race captured by Marita's Victory, who paid $48.60 on a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>Driven by Berndt Lindstedt and trained by Jan Johnson, Marita's Victory posted only her second victory in eight starts this season. She won by a nose over Aviano and covered the mile in 1:54, three seconds faster that her previous best time this season.</p>
        <p>''I saw the favorite coming,'' Lindstedt said about Cologne Kosmos, who lost for only the second time in eight starts this season. ''So I let her go and she finished strong. It was a dream of a trip. We trained her harder for this race and she deserved to win.''</p>
        <p>Bob Blanton, the driver of Cologne Kosmos, said after the race that his horse was injured but that it was not serious. ''She started popping her left hind at the top of the stretch, and I knew something was wrong.''</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>Moni Maker proved her class one more time by winning the $500,000 Nat Ray for her 19th victory in 32 starts the last two years. Driven by WALLY HENNESSEY, she covered the mile in 1:52 to increase her earnings the last two years to $2,246,000 and her career to $5,168,631. . . . The $350,000 United States Pacing Championship was captured by Space Shuttle, who covered the mile in 1:474 5 . Driven by RON PIERCE, Space Shuttle edged Western Ideal and paid $12.40 for a $2 bet to win. . . . The $343,500 Mistletoe Shalee for 3-year-old fillies was the first big event in the card of 15 races this afternoon. It was captured by Art's Virtue, who covered the mile in 1:50 3/5 and paid $5.80 for a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
