<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOLLOWING UP</title>
    <meta content="06FOLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spam (Canned Meat)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Patronage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hormel Food Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Henson, Jim, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Volberg, Deborah I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Muppet Treasure Island (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Following Up</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D9123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOLLOWING UP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Following Up column on outcome of Hormel Foods Corp suit against Jim Henson Productions over Muppet name Spa'am, which Hormel took to be insult to its famous old product Spam; photo; Federal courts found that Hormel has already proved it can withstand bad Spam jokes, and US Supreme Court declined to take up case; in second follow-up, Deborah I Volberg's suit over her dismissal by Pataki administration as lawyer in environmental conservation department has been dismissed without trial; Volberg drew up list of lawyers who could be fired because they owed jobs to previous political connections, and was fired for pointing out to her bosses that lower-ranked lawyers they wanted to dismiss instead included minority-group members (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Is a Wart Hog A Canned Pork Product?</p>
        <p>Not often in the course of American litigation have the words ''good-natured wart hog'' appeared. Ditto ''evil in porcine form'' and ''nasty pagan brute.'' But the battle of Hormel Foods Corporation v. Jim Henson Productions Inc. -- affectionately known as Spam v. Spa'am -- was not your average case.</p>
        <p>Still, it attracted little public attention as it wended its way through three federal courts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Is a Wart Hog A Canned Pork Product?</p>
        <p>Not often in the course of American litigation have the words ''good-natured wart hog'' appeared. Ditto ''evil in porcine form'' and ''nasty pagan brute.'' But the battle of Hormel Foods Corporation v. Jim Henson Productions Inc. -- affectionately known as Spam v. Spa'am -- was not your average case.</p>
        <p>Still, it attracted little public attention as it wended its way through three federal courts.</p>
        <p>Hormel, the maker of Spam, the canned luncheon meat, said it was worried about being confused with Spa'am, one of Miss Piggy's tribal guards in the ''Muppet Treasure Island'' movie. So worried that it sued for trademark infringement.</p>
        <p>The three-day trial in Federal District Court in Manhattan in 1995 revealed just how seriously one can take canned meat. Testifying for Hormel, Laura A. Peracchio, a consumer behavior expert, said ''Spa'am is unappealing and will lead to negative associations on the part of consumers because he has small eyes, protruding teeth, warts, a skull on his headdress, is generally untidy and speaks in a deep voice with poor grammar and diction.''</p>
        <p>Judge Kimba Wood, however, was more persuaded by Anne Devereaux Jordan, an expert in children's literature, who noted that kids like characters that are not classically handsome, like ''Pumbaa, the good-natured wart hog in another kids' movie, 'The Lion King.' '' While Hormel found Spa'am unhygienic, the judge found him merely sloppy.</p>
        <p>Hormel argued that Henson ''falsely personifies Spam as a nasty pagan brute,'' and expressed fear that sales of Spam would drop off if it were linked with, yes, ''evil in porcine form.''</p>
        <p>Judge Wood and the judges of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, who upheld her ruling, found that Hormel had already proved it could withstand  bad Spam jokes. ''In a recent newspaper column,'' the appeals court wrote, ''it was noted that 'In one little can, Spam contains the five major food groups: Snouts. Ears. Feet. Tails. Brains.' In view of the more or less humorous takeoffs such as these, one might think Hormel would welcome the association with a genuine source of pork.''</p>
        <p>Adding that Spam is eaten in 30 percent of American homes, the judges said, ''To the extent that Spam is popular and highly regarded by consumers, as Hormel claims, that popularity exists in spite of a media barrage of highly negative humor at Spam's expense.''</p>
        <p>For the people behind the Muppets, the dispute was a tempest in a pigpen.</p>
        <p>''He was a bit character in a background scene in a movie,'' said Peter Schube, general counsel for the Henson Company. The boar's name came up only once in the film, and Spa'am hasn't made a screen appearance since.</p>
        <p>Spam v. Spa'am never made it to the United States Supreme Court, which declined to review the appeals court decision.  That's too bad, really. The case would have been right at home in a city known for its pork barrel, hams -- and the occasional good-natured wart hog.</p>
        <p>A Political Dispute Ends Quietly</p>
        <p>When Deborah I. Volberg, formerly acting general counsel of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, was asked to come up with a list of lawyers who could be fired after the Pataki administration took office in 1995, she recommended some who had very likely been hired for their political connections. Her bosses wanted to dismiss others, who had been hired more recently and had no political clout. Ms. Volberg pointed out that  many of these lawyers were black, Asian or Hispanic.</p>
        <p>She was promptly fired herself. She sued, arguing that she lost her job over politics instead of performance.</p>
        <p>Her lawyer, Jonathan Lovett, said the case was eventually dismissed without a trial. Ms. Volberg, now in private practice in White Plains, would not comment on the case.</p>
        <p>TINA KELLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
