<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>John Who?</title>
    <meta content="06ORESKET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oreskes, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garment, Leonard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In Search of Deep Throat (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDF163DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>John Who?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Oreskes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oreskes, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Oreskes reviews book In Search of Deep Throat: The Greatest Political Mystery of Our Time by Leonard Garment; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Search of</p>
        <p>deep Throat</p>
        <p>The Greatest Political Mystery</p>
        <p>of Our Time.</p>
        <p>By Leonard Garment.</p>
        <p>280 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Search of</p>
        <p>deep Throat</p>
        <p>The Greatest Political Mystery</p>
        <p>of Our Time.</p>
        <p>By Leonard Garment.</p>
        <p>280 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $25.</p>
        <p>Washington is a city full of secrets. Most of them don't mean much or last long. A lot of them aren't even true. But knowing a secret and when to share it is, as Leonard Garment writes, ''the official and unofficial coin of the realm, the universal matter out of which individuals create their status, power and wealth.'' Which makes it all the more remarkable that for 27 years no one has spilled one of the great secrets of Watergate. Who was Deep Throat?</p>
        <p>There have been plenty of guesses, educated and not. But it seems that only four people know for sure. They are Deep Throat himself (we are told he is a man) and Bob Woodward, the then ambitious young Washington Post reporter (now middle-aged assistant managing editor and author) to whom Deep Throat imparted valuable inside perspective on the break-in at Democratic headquarters, the larger political intelligence operation of which it was a part and the White House effort to cover up both; Woodward in turn told his reporting colleague, Carl Bernstein (who says that during all the years they were married he never told Nora Ephron), and then his editor, Benjamin Bradlee, although not until Bradlee asked Woodward as they sat on a park bench after the resignation of Richard Nixon. There the secret kept all these years.</p>
        <p>The fact that we can still care is an interesting implicit point of Garment's new book. Watergate was a true scandal of substantial and lasting import. It is difficult to imagine some unresolved detail of, say, the Lewinsky matter (as we shall call it) that could hold our interest in this way for the next quarter-century. If you disagree, meet me on the park bench in Lafayette Square facing the White House on this date in 2025. I'll be the one holding a first edition of ''In Search of Deep Throat: The Greatest Political Mystery of Our Time.'' For I suspect it will still be worth reading then.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Garment gives us a valuable short summary of Watergate, reminding us of twists and context that have receded into that haze in which anything vaguely unsavory is now called a scandal and suffixed with ''-gate.'' This history lesson is quite timely.</p>
        <p>We have entered what I will call the post-post-Watergate era of American government (a free copy of Garment's book to the creator of a better name). In the past two years or so, much of the political change brought on by the Watergate scandal has been swept away by the tides of this new era. Rules designed to limit money in politics have collapsed, the independent counsel law has lapsed, and journalists, lionized among the heroes of Watergate, have been condemned as among the villains of the Lewinsky matter (as we shall call it).</p>
        <p>Garment argues that at least some of these failures happened because the post-Watergate changes were built on a bad understanding of what really happened in Watergate.</p>
        <p>For example, the special counsel law, which eventually brought us Kenneth Starr, was based on the premise that the Nixon Justice Department could not investigate the Nixon administration. The lesson of Watergate, Garment argues, was precisely the opposite. The Justice Department was conducting a vigorous investigation. When Nixon tried to block it he doomed his presidency. As for journalism, few areas of American society have been more influenced by the perceived lessons of Watergate, and not all for the better, Garment says.</p>
        <p>''Investigative reporters grew in numbers and skill,'' he writes. ''They gave us, predictably enough, ever more news about the failings of institutions and leaders. They directed sunlight to some places that surely needed it. They also fed an unjustified and dangerous disenchantment with public life.'' Here again, Garment rightly argues that a more careful reading of what actually happened in Watergate would be an important corrective to later excess. Deep Throat was not the source for the Watergate scandal. He didn't simply leak ready-to-publish allegations. He was one of many sources, valuable not for the information he provided but for the way he was able to deepen Woodward and Bernstein's understanding of the information they had garnered elsewhere. Between those two thoughts lies the line between good journalism and sloppy. Over all, the contribution Garment seeks to make is that a better understanding of what actually happened in Watergate might actually help lead to better government, politics and, yes, even journalism. His route to this understanding is his search for Deep Throat.</p>
        <p>Garment is fun to tag along with on his sleuthing through the offices, restaurants and even saunas of Washington. He candidly describes the very thing that most irritates people outside the Beltway about life inside the Beltway. ''I began gathering fresh information in the prototypical Washington ways,'' he writes, ''through talk in general and lunch and dinner in particular.''</p>
        <p>I have not rushed to tell you his conclusion about Deep Throat's identity because it seems almost secondary to the spirit of his search and his thinking about why Watergate and Deep Throat's role in it still matter. But here is his conclusion. Deep Throat, who met with Bob Woodward in a parking garage, was John Sears.</p>
        <p>If you had been told this at the time you almost surely would have replied, John who? Sears at the time of Watergate was a young man in his early 30's who had worked on Richard Nixon's campaigns but had ended up without the influence in the White House he had hoped for. After Watergate, he became one of the most prominent political strategists in the Republican Party, guiding Ronald Reagan's campaign for president in 1976 and then again in 1980 until Reagan fired him to resolve personality clashes between Sears and Reagan's more ideological compatriots. He had a reputation, and still does, as a brilliant political tactician, but also as someone thoughtful about the meaning and purposes of politics. After his dismissal from the Reagan campaign, Sears spent considerable time in the Republican political wilderness. He was almost named manager of Bob Dole's 1988 campaign, but was blocked by Dole allies in New Hampshire. In 1995 he began preparing Jack Kemp for a presidential campaign that never happened. ''His long banishment,'' Robert Novak wrote in 1996 of Sears, ''is attributable to his reputation for not being a team player.''</p>
        <p>Garment, by his own account, does not have the smoking gun that proves John Sears was Deep Throat. At the end of the book, Sears denies it and threatens to sue Garment. Garment assuages him and, of course, invites him to lunch.</p>
        <p>All Garment can do is give us a plausible case. He has convinced himself. Ben Bradlee once said that if all the clues about Deep Throat scattered through The Washington Post and through ''All the President's Men'' and ''The Final Days,'' Woodward and Bernstein's two books, were fed into a computer, along with available facts about all the key suspects (such as who was out of town on the dates of those garage meetings) the identity of Deep Throat could probably be established with considerable certainty. Garment adds one element that no computer could (yet) incorporate. He knew virtually all the potential suspects personally and can measure them not just against facts (Deep Throat was taller than Woodward) but also against their personalities as he knew them. Garment was Richard Nixon's last White House counsel, successor to the fallen John Dean. In the midst of Watergate, he says, he had no interest in the Deep Throat question. ''The pressures of reality had driven out any capacity I might otherwise have had for speculating about who and what had produced that reality.'' Despite Garment's efforts, Nixon's presidency collapsed. Garment went back to the practice of law (he is of counsel to the Washington firm Verner, Liipfert, Bernhard, McPherson &amp; Hand). His interest in Deep Throat did not emerge until 20 years later, when he began work on a memoir, ''Crazy Rhythm,'' which was published in 1997 and is by far the most emotionally perceptive of all the Watergate memoirs. With the memoir done, Garment embarked on his hunt for Deep Throat.</p>
        <p>One figure stands out as indispensable to Garment's search. That is Woodward himself. Woodward, of course, has declined to identify Deep Throat. But as Garment tells it he regularly dropped bread crumbs that kept the trail visible. He announced that Alexander Haig was not Deep Throat so the question would not hang over Haig's 1988 presidential campaign. He ''waved me off'' Patrick Gray of the F.B.I., Garment reports. He told John Dean during an author's tour that Deep Throat had been publicly identified but had denied being Deep Throat. Then Garment asked Woodward (over lunch, naturally) why Deep Throat had not simply come forward himself, since much of the country would now consider him a hero: ''Woodward answered that, in 1972 and early 1973, Deep Throat had been, if not wholly unknown, at least relatively anonymous. In the years since then, Deep Throat's 'public persona' -- Woodward's exact words -- had changed. His 'public persona' after Watergate was inconsistent with his actions during Watergate days.''</p>
        <p>From this Garment surmises that Deep Throat's post-Watergate clients, audience or constituency might not have approved of his role consorting with a reporter from The Washington Post. For a long time, this led him to believe that Deep Throat was Robert F. Bennett, who at the time ran a public relations company with strong ties to both the White House and the C.I.A. Bennett went on to become a senator from the conservative state of Utah. Over time, this theory collapsed, however. The facts didn't fit together. Deep Throat as portrayed by Woodward and Bernstein was a smoker and a drinker. Senator Bennett is a devout Mormon. Crushed and depressed by the failure of his Bennett theory, Garment has a eureka moment in 1999, while reading an article in a journalism review criticizing Woodward. He has accepted at face value most of Woodward's claims about Deep Throat, but he comes to realize, he writes, that Woodward might be literally honest but, shall we say, cagey in the impressions he leaves. This leads him to believe that Sears was both a source for Bernstein (which Sears confirms) and at the same time Deep Throat to Woodward. To Garment's eye Sears, who as a northeasterner (from Syracuse) was always somewhat suspect on the right, fit the portrait of someone little known at the time of Watergate whose later professional persona was at odds with the role played by Deep Throat: his career, one way or another, was still bound up with Republican politics.</p>
        <p>One small mystery at the end of this book is that Woodward, so visible throughout, just vanishes. There is no lunch at which he waves Garment off the Sears theory or nods knowingly but refuses to confirm or deny it. So I did what most readers will not be able to do. I called Woodward, who dismissed Garment's theory. ''He's got it wrong,'' Woodward said. ''Sears does not fit the description.'' When Deep Throat was described in ''All the President's Men'' as someone high in the executive branch, it was meant literally, Woodward said; Deep Throat was not, as Garment has it, someone who had close ties high in the executive branch.</p>
        <p>So all we are left with is the denials of Sears and Woodward, and Garment's conviction that he has solved the riddle. ''When I finally concluded that John Sears was Deep Throat, I realized that I had discovered not just the answer to one particular puzzle but something more general -- sobering and a little bit saddening -- about American politics of the past 25 years,'' Garment concludes.</p>
        <p>''My opinion is that Sears took the actions he did because of mixed motives, as is the case with all humans; but if there was a dominant political impulse moving him, it was a sense that the marriage of realism and idealism in our politics, a delicate union to begin with, was on the rocks. The political arena, he thought, was in danger of becoming just a war between the knife-wielders and the moralists. Sears was right, of course; he could not have known that the drama of which he was a part was about to drive the wedge between the two camps even deeper.''</p>
        <p>If John Sears, the thoughtful, even occasionally poetic believer in politics, was Deep Throat, let us hope he will leave us his own book on how he feels about the world he helped create.</p>
        <p>Michael Oreskes is the Washington bureau chief of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Oreskes is the Washington bureau chief of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
