<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; The Donors Rule, But in Name Only</title>
    <meta content="06VANN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Natta, Don Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DB153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; The Donors Rule, But in Name Only</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON VAN NATTA Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Natta, Don Jr</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on names that political parties to give to orgns of their top campaign donors; Republican Party gives big titles to big donors; photo of Gov George W Bush (S)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT began with Team 100, a name for a political club that was purposefully subtle and maybe even a bit coy. One had to imagine what the 100 stood for: Senators? Dollars? Nickels?</p>
        <p>Hardly. Team 100 was made up of the $100,000 contributors, the pinnacle of political generosity back in 1988 when George Bush invented the Republicans' first elite donor club for a handful of the party's most generous patrons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT began with Team 100, a name for a political club that was purposefully subtle and maybe even a bit coy. One had to imagine what the 100 stood for: Senators? Dollars? Nickels?</p>
        <p>Hardly. Team 100 was made up of the $100,000 contributors, the pinnacle of political generosity back in 1988 when George Bush invented the Republicans' first elite donor club for a handful of the party's most generous patrons.</p>
        <p>But in presidential politics, donation inflation is at least 50 percent, and last week the Republican convention was overrun by a stampede of 600 Team 100 members. Their suite at the Ritz-Carlton was jammed. Those who complained were offered an option: Take out those checkbooks and give the party $250,000, the entry fee to the Republican Regents, the party's newest and most exclusive donor club, whose suite at the Four Seasons had plenty of leg room.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Regents were given receptions with both George Bushes, a Saks Fifth Avenue fashion show and a party at Tiffany &amp; Co. ''There's something to do every minute,'' said Sam Fox, the top-giving Regent (nearly $600,000), who sounded worn out by the yacht rides and golf tournaments.</p>
        <p>The word regent is defined as one who governs a kingdom in the minority, absence or disability of the sovereign ruler. In this era of outrage over campaign finance excesses, it seems odd that the Republicans would choose a name that allows Americans to imagine a seat next to the throne for the party's $250,000-and-up sponsors -- a list that includes the Phillip Morris Companies, the National Rifle Association, AT&amp;T and Enron Corporation, the Houston energy and commodities conglomerate.</p>
        <p>The donor group was named by Mel Sembler, the Republican's gregarious finance chairman, who made a royal fortune building shopping centers. ''I just thought it had a nice ring to it,'' he said earlier this year. But a few fund-raisers have quietly complained that the name opens the party to criticism that it caters to a blue-blood elite.</p>
        <p>The Democrats were far more careful, calling their top donor club Leadership 2000 (for people who give or raise $350,000; there are 18 members). Other Republican club names also sound benign: the Eagles, the Majority Council.</p>
        <p>Yet the Regents is a runaway success. Mr. Sembler's goal was to sign up 100 members by Nov. 7, but there are already 139. Two-thirds are individuals who say they give not because they want something in return but because they believe in what the party stands for -- less government and lower taxes.</p>
        <p>What's next for the Republicans? A $500,000 club? A $1 million club? Perhaps, a few fund-raisers acknowledged last week. But they quickly promised that the name would give nothing away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
