<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Changing Face of Catholic Education</title>
    <meta content="CATH1T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DD113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="4111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Changing Face of Catholic Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Timothy Egan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on history of Roman Catholic schools in US, and changes taking place as lay teachers replace dwindling number of priests and nuns and students of many faiths enroll in inner cities, many taking advantage of voucher programs; photos; graphs (special section, Education Life) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY slouch into chairs, faces rumpled and downcast, a sluggish clot of high school juniors in Gonzaga Prep's 8 a.m. religion class. Members of a generation stuffed with Pokemon and Simpsons reruns, they are about to get their daily dose of Roman Catholic Church history, focusing today on the eighth century.</p>
        <p>The bell rings. The day begins with a quick prayer, followed by individual pleas on behalf of a hospitalized sibling and the track team. Shuffle, shuffle, cough, cough. And then class gets under way, run by the rarest kind of teacher in an American Catholic school at the dawn of the new century: a priest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY slouch into chairs, faces rumpled and downcast, a sluggish clot of high school juniors in Gonzaga Prep's 8 a.m. religion class. Members of a generation stuffed with Pokemon and Simpsons reruns, they are about to get their daily dose of Roman Catholic Church history, focusing today on the eighth century.</p>
        <p>The bell rings. The day begins with a quick prayer, followed by individual pleas on behalf of a hospitalized sibling and the track team. Shuffle, shuffle, cough, cough. And then class gets under way, run by the rarest kind of teacher in an American Catholic school at the dawn of the new century: a priest.</p>
        <p>I look around for familiar signs from my days at this very school 27 years ago. On the wall, I spot the two icons held up to us for veneration: the first Roman Catholic President, John F. Kennedy, and the crucifix.</p>
        <p>But in much bigger ways change is everywhere. The most startling thing is the presence of girls. Gonzaga was an all-boys institution until two years after I left. Young Catholic men would not be able to learn Latin or the history of the Peloponnesian War with the distraction of girls, the thinking went.</p>
        <p>The hack paddle -- nearly three feet of solid oak, an inch thick and perforated for maximum pain delivery -- is long gone. On several occasions, I was sent down to the office of a 240-pound, chain-smoking Irish-American priest who made me bend over and understand what a baseball feels like when it's hit by Mark McGwire. Gone, also, is Rockpile, the after-school cleanup detail for the discipline-challenged.</p>
        <p>''In 756, Pepin defeats the Lombards and gives control of central Italy to the pope,'' says the Rev. Tom Lamanna, a young Jesuit, who has never strayed far from his roots here in his hometown, Spokane, Wash. ''What this does is eat away at spiritual authority. Popes and bishops shouldn't be involved in this sort of stuff. ''</p>
        <p>There is no religion by rote for these 17-year-olds, no word-for-word rehash of doctrine. Father Lamanna, one of the few priests in the nation teaching at a Catholic school, is suggesting that conversion by sword was not such a great idea.</p>
        <p>A student raises her hand, and Father Lamanna's face brightens. ''Is this going to be on the quiz?'' the student asks. The important things never change.</p>
        <p>Nearly 10 years after many educators had written them off for dead, Roman Catholic schools in America are in the midst of an extraordinary revival. Enrollment is up across the nation. Hundreds of new schools have opened. And more than 40 percent of all Catholic elementary and secondary schools have waiting lists for admission.</p>
        <p>More remarkably, Catholic schools, once staffed primarily by nuns, priests and brothers from various religious orders, are nearly devoid of clerics -- reflecting the crash of vocations in the last 25 years as priests have become more urgently needed in the parishes. In the nation's Catholic schools, priests account for fewer than 1 percent of the 157,000 teachers. Ninety-three percent of the teachers are laity, while nuns make up 5.5 percent and brothers less than 1 percent.</p>
        <p>There are 10,000 fewer priests now than there were 25 years ago. And the ranks will continue to shrink: nearly one-fourth of the nation's 47,000 Catholic priests are over the age of 70.</p>
        <p>Schools that were once Dominican or Franciscan now speak of being in the Dominican or Franciscan ''tradition.'' Gone are the days when virtually every Catholic parish in the country supported a teaching staff of nuns or priests living year-round near the school grounds, laboring for compensation well below the poverty line.</p>
        <p>As the Roman collars and the black-and-white habits have disappeared from the halls, so too, has the overwhelmingly Catholic makeup of the typical student body. A record 13.4 percent of the 2.6 million students are non-Catholic -- more than four times the percentage of 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>And in many of the old industrial cities where immigration led to a flowering of Catholic schools in the 1880's, a majority of the students at some schools named for saints and holy days are not Catholic. In Lower Manhattan, for example, Buddhists make up a large segment of the students in two schools, Saint Patrick's Old Cathedral School and Transfiguration School. Throughout the Archdiocese of New York, 20 percent of the students are non-Catholic.</p>
        <p>The numbers of non-Catholics could dramatically increase if various voucher or tax credit proposals, which subsidize private school education, are enacted in some of the states now considering them and upheld by the courts. This fall, California will vote on a voucher program that Catholic educators in the state say could lead to waiting lists for nearly every Catholic school in the state.</p>
        <p>''With or without vouchers, the problem for us now is not demand -- it's supply,'' said Leonard DeFiore, National Catholic Education Association president.</p>
        <p>All of which raises a basic question: How can Catholic schools be flourishing, yet still maintain their religious identity when so many of the teachers and students have no formal attachment to the religion whose imprint is on the school? In some schools, Catholicism seems almost an after-thought. With no way to measure whether they have moved students to look at the world through a spiritual lens, Catholic educators shrug and speak of anecdotal triumphs, of students who may have picked up a habit of daily prayer to go with high College Board scores. It is a long way from the glory days of postwar Catholic schools, an era that seems as distant as Pepin and the Lombards.</p>
        <p>As Father Lamanna said after his religion class: ''The kids I teach are a lot less churched than their parents were. And we have fundamentalists, Muslims, even an occasional Jewish student.''</p>
        <p>I returned to Gonzaga and also visited other schools, trying to get a sense of what a Catholic education is like today. The one thing I heard repeatedly was that, if anything, the schools are more consciously Catholic now than they were a generation ago. Without nuns or priests to guide students, principals have tried to institutionalize Catholic education -- a tough act for the spiritual aspects. It is one thing to require all students to study theology, go on retreats and attend Mass four times a year -- as most Catholic secondary schools do. Putting down the cultural imprint is more difficult.</p>
        <p>AT age 7, I walked into first grade at Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary elementary school in Spokane and was confronted by an enormous poster depicting the fall of Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden. Our school was blue-collar, the second- and third-generation Irish and Italian children from huge families. We had nine in ours, but could not compete with the Flynns, down the street, who had 13, or the Phillipses, who had 19.</p>
        <p>Every teacher but one was a sister. The nuns were mysterious, all but the front of their faces veiled by their habits. We called them penguins, not always a pejorative.</p>
        <p>We all knew who the handful of non-Catholics at the school were. And if we walked down the street and came to a Protestant church, we crossed to the other side, as we were taught.</p>
        <p>Religion was part of everything; even math and science lessons usually got around to the divine magnificence of the universe. John F. Kennedy's picture was in every classroom, and Notre Dame football was the sports extension of the church.</p>
        <p>Religion class, at first, was the Baltimore Catechism, starting with the basic questions: Who made me? God made me. Why did God make me? To know, love and serve him on this earth. It was memory, nothing more. And everything that could not be adequately explained was referred to as a mystery, as the comedian George Carlin later recalled.</p>
        <p>Then came the Second Vatican Council, in the mid-1960's, which brought the Catholic Church into the modern age. And before long the nuns were showing some hair and lower leg, and playing electric guitars at Masses that were celebrated in English, not Latin.</p>
        <p>The era of Catholic schools in America dates to 1884, when the bishops, responding to complaints about Protestant domination of public schools, ordered every parish to build a school. Waves of mostly poor, immigrant children were educated at these schools, which engendered a backlash. The most extreme bias came in Oregon, in the 1920's, when the Ku Klux Klan helped pass a law -- later thrown out in court -- that banned children from going to Catholic schools.</p>
        <p>At the peak of enrollment, in 1964 -- I was in the third grade -- more than 5.6 million students attended 13,000 Catholic elementary and secondary schools.</p>
        <p>Tuition was nearly free, in part because of support from church members and dioceses, but also because of an army of cheap labor: There were sufficient nuns and priests to run the schools, with nearly everyone from the principal on down living under a vow of poverty. Now there is but a single nun at Assumption.</p>
        <p>Tuition at Assumption is $3,000 a year -- cheap by the standards of most private schools, but higher than the national average for Catholic elementary schools, which is $1,800. And it is flexible. A family pays what it can afford.Nationwide, because so many students are given tuition breaks, Catholic schools face perennial budget crunches -- except in wealthy suburbs.</p>
        <p>My niece, Lindsey Egan, is a seventh grader at Assumption, and she loves it, speaking enthusiastically of the sports, good friends and the challenge of two hours of nightly homework. I doubted she loved that part.</p>
        <p>What about religion? ''Oh, sure, that part's O.K. We go to Mass almost every week.'' No mysteries. No Gothic punishment. She seemed untouched by the load that many students of my vintage are still trying to sort through, and had no concern about who was Catholic and who was not.</p>
        <p>THE lone nun is revered. There is a waiting list to get in. And the students outperform children in the Spokane public schools. The poster of Adam and Eve has disappeared. Mysteries are explained by science. But the children still wear uniforms.</p>
        <p>When I entered high school, there were 47 Jesuits at Gonzaga, many with advanced degrees. The older priests tended to be rock-jawed and thick-armed; some were World War II veterans who had gone into the priesthood after the horror of the war. The priests were rarely out of clerical garb, whether they were shoveling snow, rewiring an electrical panel or showing the baseball team how to hit a fastball.</p>
        <p>We deconstructed the rock opera ''Tommy,'' by The Who, in sophomore religion class. By my senior year, we had vigorous debates that spilled into evening arguments over the very existence of God. The Jesuits did not want us to believe in church teachings on their word; they wanted us to arrive there by intellectual deduction, reason and -- failing all that -- simple faith.</p>
        <p>We read ''Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man'' by James Joyce, ''Catcher in the Rye'' by J.D. Salinger and ''The Invisible Man'' by Ralph Ellison -- all prompting some parents to complain, but the Jesuits held firm.</p>
        <p>''If you take nothing else away from here, remember the lesson of Moby Dick,'' said my senior English teacher. ''Be in constant search of your God and your self. ''</p>
        <p>This year, on my return, I asked the principal of Gonzaga, Al Falkner, if the Moby Dick moral still applied. A former English teacher who has been at the school for 26 years and sent all four of his children there, Mr. Falkner said yes, but that the school was trying to impart other lessons as well.</p>
        <p>Of the nearly 1,000 students at the school, about 20 percent are non-Catholics. Only two of the 65 teachers are Jesuit priests, a ratio similar to that at the nation's 45 other Jesuit high schools. Yet, Mr. Falkner says, ''We are more Jesuit now than we were 40 years ago. ''</p>
        <p>Lay principals at other Catholic schools said somewhat the same thing. It seemed incongruous. But after Catholic schools hit bottom in the late 1980's, when many of them were adrift and uncertain as to how to operate without priests or nuns, there was a concerted effort to institutionalize the education for a new era.</p>
        <p>AT Gonzaga, the lay staff is required to stay within the bounds of Jesuit teaching principles, which value deductive logic and reason in the classroom -- which the priests would not always do.</p>
        <p>Mr. Falkner produced an instruction manual that every teacher is required to follow, emphasizing certain principles. They teach reflection -- ''a real challenge in math, ''said Mr. Falkner -- and action, which usually takes the form of community service. The term ''social justice'' is used a lot. Grades count, of course; 96 percent of Gonzaga graduates go on to college. But the intention is for students to have an epiphany of the spirit as well, an outcome that is not easily manufactured, no matter how it is prescribed in the teacher's manual.</p>
        <p>''In every classroom, there should be a moment of truth when you experience God,'' Mr. Falkner said. ''It may be the point where, all of a sudden, you realize what Huck Finn is dealing with in that book. ''</p>
        <p>In the hallways, I bumped into the Rev. Robert A. Goebel, who took over the hack paddle in my sophomore year. He is 74, still wiry, with a full head of hair, and now works primarily with alumni. I brought up those painful hacks he used to give me on my rear-end.</p>
        <p>''It was good for you,'' he said with a laugh. ''And you know it.'' In truth, I was not sure. I did not resent the priests for corporal punishment of a kind that would probably bring a lawsuit today. Twice, I talked my way out of hacks, which is a backhanded way of saying I learned something, even if it was not the intended lesson. I asked him how it felt to be one of the few priests left at a school he has been associated with since 1957, and whether Gonzaga had changed for better or worse.</p>
        <p>''It may be for the better,'' said Father Goebel.'' Because you wore a collar, you were supposed to be able to teach. But a lot of the priests from my generation were not very good teachers. Everyone assumed that just because they were priests, they could provide a good Catholic education. ''</p>
        <p>He recalled the full-service life, the teaching that never ended. ''I can remember teaching kids how to blow their nose in a proper way, and how to open a bottle of Champagne and not have it spill on you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Father Goebel's much younger colleague, Father Lamanna, lives in an apartment a few blocks from the school. Handkerchief etiquette and the intricacies of cork removal are not among his duties.</p>
        <p>As at Assumption, the students at Gonzaga seem to be in awe of the rare priest or nun.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time I've ever had a priest teach me,'' said Jessie Serghin, a junior in the church history class at Gonzaga. ''He's awesome.'' She was less enthusiastic about the story of Pepin and the Lombards that Father Lamanna was trying to impart. ''Some of this is probably not relevant to our lives,'' she said. ''But that's O.K.''</p>
        <p>The students at Gonzaga -- like those at most Catholic high schools -- are required to take four semesters of theology: Scripture, morality, church history and a senior-year elective, usually community service. ''We've made a conscious decision to call it theology, not religion, ''said Father Lamanna, explaining that the word of choice is more expansive, less dogmatic.</p>
        <p>''One of the biggest challenges I have is teaching Scripture to the non-Catholics,'' he added. ''Some of them believe every word of the Bible is literally true.'' He tries to get these students to see the Bible -- especially the Old Testament -- as allegory and oral history, not always the literal word of God.</p>
        <p>Proselytizing is rare, he said, echoing the comments of religious order teachers at other Catholic schools. Father Lamanna is a spiritual counselor, a role that consists mainly of listening to the problems of struggling adolescents. ''As a priest, I have access to their interior life,'' he said. ''That's a very humbling thing.''</p>
        <p>I sought out Jack Delehanty, a drama teacher who has been at the school since I was a student there. Though 58 years old, he still looks the way he did to us boys who were making the transition from sports obsession to noir movies and poetry -- hip in an understated way. He stages plays, in the school's new 350-seat performing arts center, that deal with racism, homophobia and misunderstood youth, as well as crowd-pleasing musicals.</p>
        <p>''The kids have changed,'' Mr. Delehanty said. ''We wanted to live our high school life, have fun, try different things. Now they are so pressured by the culture to succeed at an early age. ''</p>
        <p>I asked him if he was a practicing Catholic, and how religion trickled through the drama class curriculum. ''My faith is Catholic, but my approach is humanistic,'' he said. ''That isn't a conflict here. In the old days it was do it the Catholic way. It was doctrine. Now, it's about values.''</p>
        <p>No city in America has opened the doors of Roman Catholic schools to taxpayer-subsidized education as has Milwaukee. Five years ago, the state of Wisconsin allowed poor families in Milwaukee to send their children to parochial schools, with tuition reimbursed by taxpayers at up to $5,000 a year per student. It is the largest voucher program in the country, and has been upheld by the Wisconsin Supreme Court. The United States Supreme Court refused to hear an appeal of that court's decision. Programs in other places have run up against constitutional questions over separation of church and state.</p>
        <p>In Milwaukee, where about 3,000 students attend Catholic schools under the voucher program, students may opt out of participation in religious activities at the schools. But the schools say there has not been a single such request.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest beneficiary in Milwaukee has been Messmer High School, a clump of Depression-era brick situated near a freeway in one of the city's poorest neighborhoods. Messmer was nearly closed in the mid-1980's and disowned by its archdiocese. It stayed alive with private donations, only to flourish beyond all expectations with the voucher students. It now has a waiting list. Catholic educators point to Messmer as an example for Catholic schools in other poor areas.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to be a Catholic to get a great education at Messmer High,'' says the school brochure. ''Most students aren't.''</p>
        <p>In fact, about 80 percent of the school's 400 students are non-Catholic. More than half are there because of the voucher program. ''I believe we have reinvented Catholic education,'' said Jeff Monday, the school principal. ''If we had to follow the old Catholic model, the church probably would have closed us down. ''</p>
        <p>But religion is not hidden. The Ten Commandments are posted in the entrance. Amid classroom banners that read ''Believe in Yourself'' are others exhorting students to ''Open Wide the Doors to Christ.'' The day begins with a prayer.</p>
        <p>Tuition is $3,100 a year, and more than 90 percent of the students cannot afford to pay it. Those who are not on vouchers receive tuition money from private donations, scholarships and fund-raisers.</p>
        <p>The school dynamo and president is a black Capuchin monk of the Franciscan order, Brother Bob Smith. Messmer is overwhelmingly black, and parents describe Brother Smith as a role model.</p>
        <p>An easy-to-laugh, personable man with two cell phones by his side at virtually all times, Brother Smith cheerfully cites the contradictions of maintaining a Catholic identity at a school where most people have no attachment to the religion.</p>
        <p>''We're here to give these children a religious foundation,'' he said. ''Not values.''</p>
        <p>Yet he is not an absolutist. ''I don't believe in this thing that one religion is right and everyone else is wrong. ''</p>
        <p>At Messmer, students pray every day, go on spiritual retreats, and attend at least four Masses a year. They take one religion class every year, five days a week. The school is clean and remarkably quiet. Even at the end of the day, around 6 p.m., students are hanging around, loathe to leave.</p>
        <p>''We are friendly, but we tell students we are not their buddies or their friends,'' said Brother Smith, who grew up in Chicago and worked for a time as a parole officer in Detroit. ''And don't even think of calling a teacher here by their first name.''</p>
        <p>Messmer does not cherry-pick the best students, as do some Catholic high schools; there is no admission test for entry. It has been, by nearly all accounts, a big success, with 85 percent of the graduates going on to college -- three times the rate of neighboring public high schools.</p>
        <p>But again, grades are one thing; imparting Catholicism is much tougher, the teachers say. Brother Smith defined the ultimate goal in terms remarkably similar to the Gonzaga principal's words. ''At some point in a student's life here we want them to come face to face with God,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Brother Smith and the other Messmer teacher who belongs to a religious order, Sister Elayne Hill, are exotic creatures at the school.</p>
        <p>''I tell the students about our vows of poverty and chastity,'' said Brother Smith. ''I tell them that they may have a different pair of tennis shoes for every day of the week, but I live on less than $10,000 a year, and don't mind. I say I would love to have kids, a family of my own. But I have given that up because of my belief.''</p>
        <p>Sister Elayne does not wear a habit; she is a young, light-skinned black woman from Washington, D.C. ''I have to explain a lot to the kids,'' she said with a grin. ''The students say, 'You're a nun? A real nun?' What they are most upset about is chastity. That just blows their mind.''</p>
        <p>I asked her if she taught the concept of heaven, hell and that in-between destination in the hereafter, purgatory.</p>
        <p>''Yes, there is a heaven and a hell, and we talk about it,'' she said. ''Purgatory -- um, that's another matter.'' She said her job was not to convert non-Catholics. ''I'm on a journey with them, an invitation,'' she said. ''It's not 'do this or die.' ''</p>
        <p>But she worries about the minority of students who are strong Catholics. ''I do think that the Catholic kids almost get lost at some of these schools.''</p>
        <p>And that may be the ultimate irony in the renaissance of American Catholic schools: some of the brightest stars -- and certainly, the fastest-growing schools -- are the ones with the fewest Catholics.</p>
        <p>Timothy Egan is a national correspondent for The New York Times based in Seattle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Timothy Egan is a national correspondent for The New York Times based in Seattle.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
