<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Has High Hopes for Vehicle Truly Meant for Road Warriors</title>
    <meta content="06HUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jeeps</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DF133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Has High Hopes for Vehicle Truly Meant for Road Warriors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors has high hopes for its recently acquired Hummer brand; Hummer, like the Jeep but far larger, started as military transport, the Humvee, which was used in Persian Gulf war; with cold war ended, Humvee's manufacturer is looking to civilian buyers;it has sold about 1,000 a year, for about $100,000 apiece, to affluent entrepreneurs, limousine companies and sprinkling of celebrities; besides selling current version, GM will introduce at least two smaller Hummer models over next three years, at much lower prices than current model; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to capture the spirit of the times, General Motors occasionally introduces a whole new brand, hoping it will grow as popular as Cadillac, Buick or Oldsmobile. A decade ago, it brought out Saturns and Geos to tap a national desire for affordable, sporty, fuel-efficient cars.</p>
        <p>Now G.M. is at it again. Its latest venture: the Hummer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trying to capture the spirit of the times, General Motors occasionally introduces a whole new brand, hoping it will grow as popular as Cadillac, Buick or Oldsmobile. A decade ago, it brought out Saturns and Geos to tap a national desire for affordable, sporty, fuel-efficient cars.</p>
        <p>Now G.M. is at it again. Its latest venture: the Hummer.</p>
        <p>Like the Jeep but far bigger, the Hummer started as a military transport, the Humvee, which was used in the Persian Gulf war for everything from launching missiles to ferrying the wounded. With the cold war ended, the Humvee's manufacturer is looking to civilian buyers. It has sold about 1,000 a year, for about $100,000 apiece, to affluent entrepreneurs, limousine companies and a sprinkling of celebrities like Arnold Schwarzenegger, Mike Tyson and the rapper Coolio.</p>
        <p>G.M. recently acquired the Hummer brand, placing a big bet that the decade-long trend toward ever larger and more aggressive-looking sport utility vehicles would continue. Besides selling the current version, G.M. will introduce at least two smaller Hummer models over the next three years, at much lower prices than the current model.</p>
        <p>With a national network of Hummer dealerships, and plans to pursue the New York City market in particular, the company expects to make Hummers as common as BMW's, with sales approaching 150,000 a year.</p>
        <p>''You'll see a lot in New York City, places like Manhattan where your affluent buyers are,'' said Michael DiGiovanni, G.M.'s general manager of Hummer operations.</p>
        <p>But the mass marketing of Hummers  raises the same safety and environmental issues that have dogged the largest sport utility vehicles: extremely poor fuel efficiency, higher emissions of smog-causing pollutants than cars, and a variety of risks and annoyances to motorists in other vehicles.</p>
        <p>Even without its military look or a celebrity at the wheel, the Hummer would be hard to miss: it is taller, much wider and a full ton heavier than even G.M.'s largest sport utility vehicle, the Suburban. Indeed, while it seats only four, the current Hummer weighs as much as two Jeep Grand Cherokees or three small cars.</p>
        <p>G.M. says its research shows that many prosperous baby boomers cannot afford the current model but still love its military look. G.M.'s surveys have found that the Hummer is also the favorite brand of teenage boys  and the third favorite of teenage girls, after only Volkswagen and Saturn. That is especially important to G.M. because people tend to form lifelong preferences during their teenage years.</p>
        <p>The Hummer's teenage admirers include Cooper Schwartz of Bellevue, Wash. As a small boy, he used to collect model sports cars -- Corvettes, Porsches and Ferraris. Now 17, he keeps a scale model of a black Hummer on the shelf next to his bed, and dreams of the day when he can afford a real Hummer.</p>
        <p>''I love the fact that the Hummer is a tank; it's like a tank with fashion, it's like having your own war toy,'' said Mr. Schwartz, co-captain of his high school football team. ''I like something where I can look down into another car and give that knowing smile that, 'I'm bigger than you.' It makes me feel powerful.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Hummer can seem downright overpowering compared with other passenger vehicles, raising the issue of safety.</p>
        <p>The current Hummer has 16 inches of ground clearance, half a foot more than any other mass-market sport utility, and is designed to climb over vertical walls up to 22 inches tall. Federal regulations require car bumpers to be 16 to 20 inches high. So the Hummer's height greatly increases the risk in crashes that the vehicle will ride over cars' bumpers and doors sills and slam into the passenger compartment. And because the Hummer is so heavy, it inflicts far more damage in crashes.</p>
        <p>While future Hummer models will have somewhat less ground clearance and weigh somewhat less, they are being designed with a central goal of ''unparalleled off-road performance.'' So they will still be tall and heavy enough to pose problems for safety engineers like Terry Connolly, G.M.'s director of North American vehicle safety, who said that his office had played little role in the company's Hummer planning and design.</p>
        <p>Even more than other sport utilities, Hummers can block the view of other motorists. While cars tend to be five or six feet wide, and most sport utilities are a little over six feet wide, the current Hummer is 7 feet 2 inches wide, and G.M.'s prototype for a model the length of the Chevrolet Tahoe full-sized sport utility is 6 feet 10 inches wide. G.M. says that the unusual width of Hummers is part of their brand identity, so that even the smaller Hummers will be extra wide, making them hard to park as well. The wide stance should reduce the risk of their rolling over, however.</p>
        <p>Among the environmental problems, the Hummers will emit far more air pollutants than cars. Current federal rules allow large sport utilities to emit 5.5 times the smog-causing nitrogen oxides that cars do. While Ford has improved its sport utilities and pickups so they pollute no more than cars, G.M. does not plan to reduce air pollution from its Hummers and other large sport utility vehicles until required to do so by federal regulations in 2004.</p>
        <p>Fuel economy is another issue. A.M. General, the military contractor that developed the vehicle, says that the current Hummer gets 13 miles to the gallon in the city and 15 on the highway. The Hummer only manages this mileage because it has weak acceleration and burns diesel fuel, which gives 35 percent better mileage than gasoline. G.M. plans to make its next Hummer, like the current one, heavy enough to be classified as a medium-duty truck and therefore exempt from federal fuel-economy rules.</p>
        <p>But Harry Pearce, G.M.'s vice chairman, said G.M. would include Hummers in its voluntary commitment, announced on Wednesday, to have better gas mileage than Ford for sport utilities in 2005. G.M. will have to make its other sport utilities much more efficient to offset the Hummers.</p>
        <p>The Hummer as a passenger vehicle also troubles some American war veterans. Hummer buyers typically have not served in the military, let alone fought in combat. ''It's like someone who always wanted to be a cowboy and who goes out later in life and buys a hat and a horse -- well, that doesn't make you a cowboy,'' said Bruce Harder, a retired Marine colonel who is now director of national security and foreign affairs at Veterans of Foreign Wars.</p>
        <p>During the Reagan administration's military buildup, a large factory was built in South Bend, Ind., to manufacture 25,000 Humvee military transports a year. Production soon plunged below 4,000 Humvees a year, so in late 1992 A.M. General  began building nearly identical Hummers for civilians on the same assembly line. G.M. and A.M. General broke ground last Monday on a second Hummer assembly plant in Mishawaka, Ind.</p>
        <p>G.M. will rely mostly on new models to increase Hummer sales, while continuing to sell the current Hummer, which it is renaming the Hummer H1. It plans to introduce in 2002 a $45,000 Hummer H2, to be built in Mishawaka, with maximum sales of 40,000 a year. The H2 will be the length of the Tahoe but considerably wider.</p>
        <p>The Hummer H3, the size of midsize sport utilities like the Chevrolet Blazer or Ford Explorer, is to go on sale the following year for just under $25,000, as a higher-volume model aimed at a market of young men. G.M. has also done a little work on a possible Hummer H4, which would be slightly smaller and cheaper yet, but has made no decisions on it.</p>
        <p>John G. Middlebrook, G.M.'s vice president for North American vehicle brand marketing, said G.M. would choose some of its most successful dealers to sell Hummers. ''Like when we started up Saturn, we have a clean sheet here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Saturn sells 230,000 cars a year.</p>
        <p>G.M. decided against a Hummer dealership in Manhattan because of  real estate costs. Instead, it plans  dealerships across northern New Jersey and Long Island, and at least one for Westchester and Fairfield Counties.</p>
        <p>Paul Ballew, G.M.'s general director for market analysis, said that the rising concentration of wealth and income in America over the last two decades had been the most important social trend for automakers. A very large class of high-income, fairly youthful households has been created, he said, and these people care little about gasoline prices and other vehicle operating expenses.</p>
        <p>G.M. plans to aim the H1, H2 and H3 at different markets. The H1 will be marketed to ''rugged individualists.'' These are people who are irreverent and daring and want to be seen that way by other people, Mr. DiGiovanni said. ''The rugged individualists are people who really seek out peer approval -- they're really going to go off road, go out in the desert and come back and tell people about it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Keri Quinn, a 44-year-old bachelor and co-founder of a software company in Dallas who sold his Nissan 300ZX sports car and raided his retirement account to buy his Hummer, said he went on frequent off-road driving trips with his friends but also liked the thumbs-up signals he received from strangers.</p>
        <p>The Hummer H2 is intended for ''successful achievers,'' especially people who perceive themselves as daring risk takers, but tend not to take risks involving their physical safety. ''They're daring in the sense they may take a big stock market position, like buying 20,000 shares of an e-commerce stock,'' Mr. DiGiovanni said. ''They really have not much intention of going off road, but it's really important for them that people tell them how successful they are.''</p>
        <p>The Hummer H3 will be for young buyers, including those under 25, and is still in the early stages of design.  The nation's top-selling Hummer dealer, Jim Lynch in O'Fallon, Mo., a suburb of St. Louis, said 10 of the 162 Hummers he sold last year were to parents who were buying them for their teenage children.</p>
        <p>Jason Frankel, the Houston owner of a factory that makes what he described as ''hillbilly'' novelty teeth, said he had bought two Hummers and planned to buy another for his 9-year-old daughter when she turns 16. ''I think it's a great first car for a kid,'' he said. ''They can't destroy it, and they'll be the envy of all their friends.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
