<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Everyone Is a Mentor to Everyone Else</title>
    <meta content="06SCHU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sundance Theater Lab</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schulman, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Carson Mccullers (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D7113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Everyone Is a Mentor to Everyone Else</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from diary of New York City dramatist and novelist Sarah Schulman, author of play Carson McCullers, describing her experiences during annual three-week Sundance Theater Lab at Sundance Resort near Provo, Utah; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE annual three-week Sundance Theater Lab near Provo, Utah, is not exactly summer camp, but it does give playwrights, directors, choreographers, composers and solo performers a chance to get away and experiment. The program is part of the Sundance Institute, which presents the annual Sundance Film Festival, and was founded by the actor Robert Redford and others in 1981. The culmination of the theater lab is partially staged readings by professional actors of the works in progress.</p>
        <p>This year, the lab ran from July 5 to July 23 at the Sundance Resort, a 5,000-acre recreation and arts community in Sundance in the Wasatch Mountains. Among the nine projects chosen by the lab for development was the play ''Carson McCullers'' by Sarah Schulman, a dramatist and novelist who lives in the East Village in New York. Ms. Schulman kept a diary of her experiences at the lab, excerpts from which follow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE annual three-week Sundance Theater Lab near Provo, Utah, is not exactly summer camp, but it does give playwrights, directors, choreographers, composers and solo performers a chance to get away and experiment. The program is part of the Sundance Institute, which presents the annual Sundance Film Festival, and was founded by the actor Robert Redford and others in 1981. The culmination of the theater lab is partially staged readings by professional actors of the works in progress.</p>
        <p>This year, the lab ran from July 5 to July 23 at the Sundance Resort, a 5,000-acre recreation and arts community in Sundance in the Wasatch Mountains. Among the nine projects chosen by the lab for development was the play ''Carson McCullers'' by Sarah Schulman, a dramatist and novelist who lives in the East Village in New York. Ms. Schulman kept a diary of her experiences at the lab, excerpts from which follow.</p>
        <p>DAY 1</p>
        <p>Here I am in Robert Redford's Utah paradise, play in hand. ''Carson McCullers'' is finally in first draft. No one except the playwright Craig Lucas, the author of ''Prelude to a Kiss,'' who is directing ''Carson,'' has seen it, and we have never heard it read. It has been a year since I asked the actor Angelina Phillips if she would be interested in playing Carson on the stage.</p>
        <p>I have long admired Angie. She was in a reading of ''The Child,'' my play about the consequences of homophobia in the family, which Craig will direct in a workshop at Trinity Repertory Theater in Providence, R.I., next spring. Although we do not know each other well, when I watched her work, I knew what to write. If she couldn't read it, there was something wrong with what I had written. So, grateful for the rare opportunity, I tried to write a play expressly for her gifts. Then the talented actor Bill Camp came on to play the role of Carson's husband, Reeves.</p>
        <p>I wanted to reveal how Carson's eccentric, insightful books and plays transformed the lives of her readers for the better, at the same time that she was destroying her own life with alcohol and the habit of loneliness.</p>
        <p>Will my imagination be worthy of my subject, these actors and that director? We'll all know soon enough.</p>
        <p>DAY 3</p>
        <p>I feel respected and taken care of here. There are five play projects going on in this workshop, plus two musicals and two solo performance pieces. All have been selected by two artistic directors: Philip Himberg, of the overall Sundance Theater Program, and Robert Blacker, of the Sundance Theater Laboratory.</p>
        <p>At breakfast, I hear the directors Michael Mayer and Mark Wing-Davey discussing their past productions of ''Angels in America.'' There is Moises Kaufman, whose play ''The Laramie Project'' is being performed in New York now. He is directing a new one-man show, ''I Am My Own Wife,'' about Charlotte Von Mahlsdorf, a legendary East German transvestite. It was written by Doug Wright, whose play ''Quills'' has been made into a movie, to be released later this year.</p>
        <p>I meet Marion McClinton, the director of Cheryl L. West's ''Jar the Floor'' and August Wilson's ''Jitney,'' which is also on in New York. He is friendly, honest and encouraging. A young writer, Javon Johnson, is working with an experienced director, Shirley Jo Finney, on a play about two generations of black men. And an old colleague from the East Village, the avant-garde writer and director John Jesurun, and a Mexican director, Martin Acosta, are working on ''Philoktetes,'' a reinterpretation of the Sophocles play.</p>
        <p>This is what every playwright dreams of: a chance to develop work with collaborators who are great company, in a gorgeous setting, with free food.</p>
        <p>DAY 4</p>
        <p>The first day of rehearsal. I'm very nervous about Angie. Will she like the play? As we get started, I meet the rest of the cast. Craig and I have brought Angie, Bill and Rosalyn Coleman, who is playing Carson's friend Ethel Waters. But the other four actors are principals in other writers' plays. We rehearse every other day here (I use the time in between for rewrites), so the actors work on two plays simultaneously.</p>
        <p>Then it dawns on me: this is going to be an unusual opportunity. I am sharing a cast with Naomi Iizuka's ''36 Views,'' which uses the Hiroshige series of prints of Mount Fuji as a jumping-off point to look at fraud and identity in love as well as art. Sharing actors means that two Asian-American performers -- Michi Barall and Liana Pai -- will be playing roles that would ordinarily be given to white actors, since ''Carson McCullers'' is a play in which white is white and black is black. So their gifts throw me. As we work, the more I get used to them in their parts, the more the racial limitations of casting seem absurd. And I feel sickened at how I'm participating in it. Especially in a play about a writer so instinctively compelled to break through racial obstacles between her characters. While white writers increasingly create black characters, Asian actors are still dependent on Asian playwrights for work. This means that without Sundance, I might never have had the opportunity to collaborate with these two actors.</p>
        <p>I'm worried about everything. Craig has been directing three of my plays in readings and workshops over the last two years and we have been in development hell together. While we are here, he is simultaneously casting for his own new play, ''Stranger,'' and writing an even newer piece. One day he writes 50 pages before breakfast. I don't want him to get frustrated with me.</p>
        <p>Because I'm bored by documentary theater, and don't have the rights to any of Carson's work, my play strives to be emotionally and artistically accurate without being exactly on the nose historically. I have structured the piece around the making of a fictional play that resembles ''The Member of the Wedding'' and try to touch all the central writerly and psychological issues in Carson's work. But the play also has to stand alone as a dramatic experience so that audiences who know nothing about her can follow Carson's journey as they would a modern Hedda Gabler.</p>
        <p>Yikes. I'm scared. So are the performers. Several of them are playing famous American figures who were Carson's closest friends: Tennessee Williams, Gypsy Rose Lee, Ethel Waters and Richard Wright.</p>
        <p>As a former actor, Craig understands everyone's anxiety. He has us go through the play, with the actors reading each other's parts. Art Evans, an older actor who made his Broadway debut in James Baldwin's ''Amen Corner'' in 1965, reads the role of Carson. Angie reads Reeves. Roz reads Tennessee. This allows the cast to listen to the play, to what other characters are saying and feeling about their character. Craig passes around one of Carson's greatest stories, ''A Tree, a Rock, a Cloud,'' which we all read out loud. We listen to Ethel Waters sing, watch a video of Tennessee (sloshed, on the David Frost show), and hear a recording of Carson reading her work.</p>
        <p>The tape was made in 1958 when she was 41, my age exactly. But after three strokes and a life of alcoholism and chain smoking, she sounds 80. Her voice is slurred and cracked. Her unhomogenized West Georgia accent is heavy and hot. And when she comes to the line in ''The Member of the Wedding'' where the adolescent Frankie yearns for the ''we of me,'' she breaks down crying.</p>
        <p>By letting us feel Carson's pain and her beauty, Craig begins to create the world of the play, a place that the actors can enter.</p>
        <p>DAY 6</p>
        <p>I'm starting to notice the people here who are working on musicals and how the artists interact during meals and informal meetings. The atmosphere is both arty and fun. Michael Mayer and Diane Paulus, the director of ''The Donkey Show'' in New York, are each working on a musical: Michael is directing ''Spring Awakening'' and Diane, ''Kafka Song.'' So in addition to the character actors, there are a lot of cute young chorus boys and girls, singers and musicians, running around flirting, flexing and dancing up a storm at parties. The younger folks often end the night at the Owl Bar, part of the Sundance compound and the only place you can drink in this conservative Mormon county without ordering food. Stopping by to join them can mean a three-hour session of Yes/No, a drinking game in which participants pledge to answer any question with an honest shrug or nod. Typical questions: Would you ever sleep with a woman? Would you betray your best friend for a great part if you knew you would win a Tony?</p>
        <p>DAY 7</p>
        <p>During the lab, Sundance invites prominent directors and dramaturges to sit in on rehearsals and ask the writers questions about their pieces. In other circumstances a dramaturge's questions can feel like a test that writers must pass to get the production they crave, but here there are no strings attached.</p>
        <p>Lenora Inez Brown, from the Crossroads Theater Company in New Brunswick, N.J., is the dramaturge for my play. She never tells me what to do but listens to what my intentions are. She knows I want to show Carson's complex race consciousness without using the black characters as pawns.</p>
        <p>Craig complains to me that Tennessee was speechifying in his scene with Carson. I'm angry. I worked so hard on finding a voice for him that reflects Tennessee's real speech patterns. I decide to blame the actor. ''But they're just sitting around talking,'' Craig says about the characters. ''Where's the action?''</p>
        <p>DAY 9</p>
        <p>Marion McClinton watches our rehearsals and all his suggestions go to the heart of Carson's loneliness and her artistic sensibility. He is open, too, and allows me into conversations about everything, from Tennessee Williams, to the chitlin circuit, to marriage, to Kafka, fatherhood and church. Because of him I was able to have a free-flowing, humane conversation with a major American director. But because he works primarily with black writers and I am a white woman writing plays with lesbian content, we might never have talked or collaborated.</p>
        <p>Philip and Robert invite the writer and director of each project to lunch, along with the three dramaturges here, to talk about our progress. I felt free to bring up my most pressing issues about getting plays produced, without worrying that I would somehow be punished later on.</p>
        <p>Craig and I recounted our experiences in trying to obtain productions for my work. Both of us said that plays containing primarily lesbian content and written by openly lesbian writers face exclusion by artistic directors. We also talked about the crisis situation that women playwrights face in general. I described Off Broadway theater in New York as a world in which men pick up the telephone and call other men to tell them which women to take seriously. If there is a network of women with real power, who help one another in the theater, I'm not aware of it.</p>
        <p>Instead of retreating into dismissive silence, everyone at the table joined in. Shirley Fishman, a dramaturge at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, said there has not been a significant increase over the last 15 years in the number of women playwrights whose work gets produced.</p>
        <p>DAY 10</p>
        <p>Today, I love Craig. He is living up to his local nickname of Grandpa, the one everyone relies on. Perhaps it's the three triple cappuccinos he drinks every day, but somehow he is able to hear anything that anyone needs to say and to interact with every idea with respect. ''I know you'll do it when you're ready,'' he says about my inability to cut. I go home and trim Tennessee Williams's lines.</p>
        <p>Now that we're into the second week, the presentations of our work begin. Tonight is the first reading of Act I of a new play by Oliver Mayer, the author of ''Blade to the Heat'' and a playwright in residence here. The new work, ''Conjunto,'' is about relationships between Japanese farmers and Mexican farm workers during the internment of Japanese-Americans in World War II. I notice that he has cast both Liana and Michi and assume they are playing Japanese. But Michi turns out to be playing a Mexican, and she is marvelous. In ''Carson McCullers,'' she has the role of a young, white, Julie Harris-like actress portraying an adolescent girl in Carson's play. As the days pass, it becomes harder to imagine anyone else in that role.</p>
        <p>DAY 11</p>
        <p>I have got to write the scene for Carson and Vinnie Copeland Jackson, who worked for Carson's parents. But every time I start thinking about that moment between the 14-year-old Southern white girl (Carson) and the 14-year-old Southern black girl (Vinnie), I'm terrified. What do I know about this?</p>
        <p>''Don't look at it from Carson's point of view,'' Lenora suggests. ''Look at it from Vinnie's.'' Light bulb.</p>
        <p>Angie and Bill are astounding me. They are both very honest actors, but their approaches are different. Angie starts slowly, by being absolutely truthful or else neutral. She will never lay a false emotion on top of a single word. She begins to build the character as she comes to understand her over time.</p>
        <p>Bill, on the other hand, sweeps in with one raw emotion and wraps it around his character. For Reeves, it is vulnerability. Once Bill sets the mood, he more and more defines the specificity within the world of his character. The two of them together are exciting, and I can see that the play fits their gifts.</p>
        <p>More presentations tonight. John Jesurun's play ''Philoktetes'' is shocking. It was written at the height of the AIDS crisis and then kept on hold when its star, Ron Vawter, who had the disease, died six years ago. Finally, John has decided to face the piece again and it is shattering. The play reveals how being in the eye of the hurricane of a mass death experience (the Trojan War) distorts men's ability to give and to receive love.</p>
        <p>Some of the younger gay men have a hard time understanding the piece. They don't remember the chaos of the AIDS crisis, and many of the young musical actors are not at all familiar with experimental theater. It is an exciting moment for the community that has been created here.</p>
        <p>DAY 13</p>
        <p>Finally, I have stripped all the excess from Tennessee's lines. I feel sheepish about blaming the actor. His scenes with Carson work now. Gee, Craig was right.</p>
        <p>Zelda Fichandler arrived today. She is the grand dame chairwoman of the graduate acting program at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. Many of the actors here were her students and they treat her with great reverence. It is moving to watch Angie and Michi show their gratitude and affection.</p>
        <p>But she is sitting in on today's rehearsal and I'm immediately nervous. I brought in the new Vinnie scene. In it, Vinnie is a domestic worker, ironing silently. Carson and her parents are having a fight in front of her but Vinnie doesn't respond, just keeps working. Then, she and Carson are alone in the kitchen. There is a knock on the back door. Vinnie answers it, smiles and flirts, closes the door. Carson, intrigued, sees that Vinnie has a secret. What is it? Vinnie won't tell. It's mysterious. In Act II, when the adult Carson makes Vinnie into a character in her play, we will know that it is Carson's imagined answer to that unanswered question from childhood.</p>
        <p>Lenora reminds me of Toni Morrison's book ''Playing in the Dark: Whiteness and the Literary Imagination'' in which the author points out how most white writers kept their black characters silent. It helps me to see that when Carson gave them voice in her work it was another eccentric choice, one that contributed to the power of her writing.</p>
        <p>The new scene works. It creates action!</p>
        <p>DAY 15</p>
        <p>I have my one-on-one meeting with Zelda and my life is changed. Zelda takes me to the core of the theater experience: what is my play saying about being human?</p>
        <p>We look at Carson's pain, her inability to solve her problems. Zelda says that neuroses are familiar, they are safe places to go when we feel unsteady, and they are rooted in childhood. We look at Carson's constant yearning for what she never had, how she fixated on lovers who were not interested in her, while taking her husband for granted.</p>
        <p>Carson became hugely successful at 23 when her first novel, ''The Heart Is a Lonely Hunter,'' was published in 1940. But then her fantasies led her astray. This insight allows me to write a new, later scene for Carson's mother, Marguerite, when Carson, 35, and Reeves are deeply into their alcoholism and after Carson has had two strokes.</p>
        <p>Marguerite persuades her daughter to go to Paris by describing her own fantasy of a better life anywhere else. ''You'll go dancing,'' she says to her crippled daughter. ''See great paintings.''</p>
        <p>DAY 16</p>
        <p>Tonight it's our presentation. We had the requisite bad rehearsal yesterday, so all the actors are on edge. But Craig unified us in the run-through this morning. Angie sits with me at lunch. We talk about a few of the scenes. It is the first time we have discussed the play, just the two of us, since we arrived here. We have been communicating through the script. I feel surprisingly confident.</p>
        <p>DAY 17</p>
        <p>It is hard to explain the feeling of hearing one's play read excellently for a sophisticated, appreciative audience. When the play works, and you are the writer sitting there, it is a confirmation of the most vulnerable and beautiful aspects of being with others. We are all alive, together, in the same room, living life in this same moment in front of one another, and we have all agreed to look at certain feelings and think about them, together. (About 10 minutes into Act II, Robert Redford came in with some Sundance board members. They sat behind me. What does this mean? I don't know. But he was there.)</p>
        <p>DAY 18</p>
        <p>Tomorrow morning we will be getting on a plane at 7 o'clock. But there is still one chapter left. Craig and I enter a room to meet with Zelda, Philip, Robert, Marion and the dramaturges -- Lenora, Shirley and Jilly Morris. They start by asking if I have any questions. Yes, I do. Do they believe that Michi can be cast as a young, white, Julie Harris-like character should the play be produced? There is a silence. This is a familiar problem, one that has been debated up and down the theater world: Can an Asian actor be cast to play a white role in a play with historical figures?</p>
        <p>''Well,'' someone says, ''audiences  accept interracial casting in classics but not in contemporary plays.''</p>
        <p>They all know how wonderful she has been. ''It really depends on who produces this,'' someone else says. ''On what kind of theater and how sophisticated their audiences are.''</p>
        <p>A third person says, ''If you establish that this is a play of invention, if you make the theatrical language of the play clear from the start, the audience will be able to accept it.''</p>
        <p>''What do you think, Zelda?'' I ask.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' she says, taking off her leopard-striped sunglasses, ''I think the best actor should have the part.'' And then she smiles.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
