<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Play Among Dolphins and Dunes</title>
    <meta content="PORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/06/travel/PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Stephens (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2D81E3AF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Play Among Dolphins and Dunes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney travel article describes trip to uncrowded beaches along Port Stephens, north of Sydney, Australia; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN we headed up the Australian coast for Port Stephens, a resort two and a half hours north of Sydney, we had definite expectations: miles of lovely and empty beaches, magnificent sand dunes, famously clean waters inhabited by trophy fish and sociable dolphins. It was all there as promised. But there was also something not on our list: rain.</p>
        <p>It didn't seem to be on anyone else's list, either. The locals never stopped professing amazement at our bad luck. No one could remember the last time they'd had five straight days of rain. Why, there hadn't been a drop of water in the two months before we arrived last March. ''If only you'd come another week,'' they kept saying, and their sympathy got more irritating every day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN we headed up the Australian coast for Port Stephens, a resort two and a half hours north of Sydney, we had definite expectations: miles of lovely and empty beaches, magnificent sand dunes, famously clean waters inhabited by trophy fish and sociable dolphins. It was all there as promised. But there was also something not on our list: rain.</p>
        <p>It didn't seem to be on anyone else's list, either. The locals never stopped professing amazement at our bad luck. No one could remember the last time they'd had five straight days of rain. Why, there hadn't been a drop of water in the two months before we arrived last March. ''If only you'd come another week,'' they kept saying, and their sympathy got more irritating every day.</p>
        <p>But we still managed to have a good time, and that is no small tribute to the charms of Port Stephens. Rain is the ultimate test of a beach resort, not to mention a family's bonds. On wet days you can't help wondering why you've spent so much time and money to commune with nature. What exactly is so great about nature? But there are enough other attractions to keep everyone content on the shores of Port Stephens.</p>
        <p>It's a huge bay (two and a half times the size of Sydney's harbor) with tranquil waters connected to the ocean by a narrow opening in the headlands. The northern shore is green and largely uninhabited. The southern shore is a peninsula that's becoming a popular spot for resorts and retirement homes, although it is still relatively undeveloped compared with other coastal resorts near Sydney (or with some on the United States Eastern Seaboard -- imagine Nags Head a few decades ago). The tourist attractions include a couple of tiny amusement parks, a wildlife preserve with koalas, and a little zoo where children can pet koalas and kangaroos.</p>
        <p>My wife, Dana, and I and our 11-month-old son stayed at one of the better resorts on the southern shore, the Peppers Anchorage, whose staff provided expert guidance on what to do. The resort is a collection of well-appointed wooden town houses overlooking a marina, with a small beach on the bay. The placid waters are popular for water skiing and sightseeing excursions. A few miles away, on the ocean side of the peninsula, is a national park with hiking trails and beaches with pounding surf.</p>
        <p>The most spectacular sights are the Stockton Beach Sand Dunes, which stretch for 20 miles along the seaside coast. They extend a half mile inland and include dunes 10 stories high. In dry weather you could easily imagine you were in the Sahara, especially if you were on one of the camelback tours. We chose other forms of transportation. Dana went across the dunes on a horse and enjoyed the challenge of the occasional sinkhole. When the inevitable rain came, she took consolation in being fashionably wet in the long oilskin coat provided by her guide. It billowed in classic Outback style as she emerged from the dunes for a gallop along the deserted beach.</p>
        <p>I climbed the dunes on a quad bike, which has four balloon tires and looks like a riding mower on steroids. The instructor, Tony Burrell, lectured on safeguarding the environment and leaving no traces of our rides. He also demonstrated the perils of the dunes, like driving off the edge of a sand cornice or allowing your bike to overturn on a slope. If you didn't follow the rules, he was fond of repeating, ''your machine will roll over and you will be squashed.'' It was a little frightening at first -- some of the slopes appeared just about vertical -- but once you learned to rev your way up and brake your way down, it was utterly exhilarating to cruise through the dunes. Lawrence of Arabia never had it so good.</p>
        <p>If you prefer to let someone else do the driving, there's the Bushmobile. It carries 24 passengers -- from infants to seniors -- and is emblazoned with the motto of Dieter Hartmann, its German operator: ''Ve get U there when others would not dare!'' Mr. Hartmann is a tour operator with a unique resume. He migrated to Australia as an engineer and then decided to live in the bush with his wife and another couple. They built a cabin deep in the forest and subsisted for several years entirely on food they hunted and gathered themselves. ''I was the guinea pig for the plants we found,'' he says. ''I would eat it, and if I didn't get sick, then we knew it was safe.''</p>
        <p>Upon returning to civilization, Mr. Hartmann applied his engineering skills to the Bushmobile, a converted military transport vehicle with a 20-speed transmission, enormous tires and a hydraulic winch for extricating itself from quicksand that sometimes forms in the dunes near Port Stephens. Mr. Hartmann's tour included dramatic descents in the Bushmobile as well as a chance to do some sandboarding -- the dune equivalent of sledding. He took us into Tin City, a little shantytown in the dunes. He also conducted what he called a magic carpet ride, which consisted of bouncing across the sand on a mat dragged behind the Bushmobile.</p>
        <p>High-speed rides are something of a theme in the Port Stephens area. You can whiz down a half-mile-long winding metal chute at Toboggan Hill Park (your toboggan, incidentally, has a brake). You can go out on a jet boat called Foxy that hits speeds of 40 knots and does 180-degree turns. With a little luck, you can watch Australian and American military pilots in action by visiting Fighter World, a museum that's next to a working military airfield. It was raining so hard the day we visited that no planes were flying, but we at least got to peer into the cockpits of the fighters on display and listen to war stories from the Australian Air Force veterans who run the museum.</p>
        <p>The rain didn't deter the fishermen competing in an annual event called the Billfish Shootout at the Peppers Anchorage marina. They were busy hauling in sharks and marlins to be weighed on the dock. The talk of the marina was a world-record blue marlin that had just been caught. Even amateurs can easily arrange to catch their dinner (and have it superbly cooked at the hotel) on one of the charter boats.</p>
        <p>Or you can merely observe the marine life in what local boosters like to call the Dolphin Capital of Australia. About 80 dolphins have settled in the sheltered waters of the bay, and their performances are sustaining a small fleet of dolphin-watching boats. Our first evening in Port Stephens we boarded an elegant yacht, the Winifred, and sailed off in the hope of watching the sun set over a sea of leaping dolphins. Then, of course, the clouds came. The captain took us into a sheltered cove and assured us that we could still see dolphins in the rain.</p>
        <p>''They'll come out as long as the water's calm,'' he said, ''and we're sheltered here from the wind in every direction except the northwest.'' Then the wind began blowing from the northwest. No dolphins.</p>
        <p>The next evening we tried a different dolphin-watching operation, a catamaran called Imagine. It was even rainier than the previous evening. We clutched wine glasses and stared glumly into the murky twilight waters. Suddenly, 20 yards off starboard, there was a fin; then 10 yards away, another one. Then a whole shining dolphin body crested, just feet away.</p>
        <p>We were promptly surrounded by at least 20 dolphins, cresting and flipping their bottle noses, their sinuous bodies nimbly keeping pace with the racing pontoons of the catamaran. They were playing with us! We cheered and waved into the wet wind, and managed to convince ourselves that they were smiling back at us. And for a moment we convinced ourselves that the rain didn't matter, either.</p>
        <p>From toboggan to Bushmobile</p>
        <p>Port Stephens is about two and a half hours north of Sydney by car. For information, contact the Port Stephens Visitor Information Center, Post Office Box 435, Nelson Bay, 2315 Australia; (61-2) 4981 1579, fax (61-2) 4984 1855, www.portstephens.org.au.</p>
        <p>We stayed at what seemed to be the best lodging in the area, the Peppers Anchorage;  (61-2) 4984-2555; fax (61-2) 4984-0300 www.peppers.com.au/anchorage. Rooms start at $145 weekdays, $180 weekends (at $1.72 Australian to the U.S. dollar), with discounts on longer stays. The sunny rooms have balconies overlooking a marina. The staff was very helpful booking tours.</p>
        <p>Among boats offering dolphin cruises are the catamaran Imagine, (61-2) 4984-9000, and the Surprise, with a veteran guide, Capt. Pete Dawson, (61-2) 4982-0444. A two-hour trip is $11, $6 ages 4 to 12.</p>
        <p>Bushmobile tours ($16) depart from Anna Bay; (61) 500-55 00 66.</p>
        <p>For dune biking ($57), try Sand Safaris, in Williamtown; (61-2) 4965-0215.</p>
        <p>A 15-minute ride on the Foxy high-speed boat, Nelson Bay, costs $16; (61-2) 4086-84421. Toboggan Hill Park, Nelson Bay, charges $2.65 for a ride, $16.70 for six; (61-2) 4984-1022. Admission to Fighter World, Williamtown, (61-2) 4965-1810, is $2.65, $1.75 children.</p>
        <p>Oakvale Farm and Fauna World, where you can pet a koala, is in Salt Ash; (61-2) 4982-6222; $5.25, children $3.</p>
        <p>JOHN TIERNEY writes The Big City column for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JOHN TIERNEY writes The Big City column for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
