<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jenifer Wells, Mark Megalli</title>
    <meta content="06WELL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WELLS, JENIFER NELLE (JENIFER NELLE MEGALLI)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEGALLI, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D9143CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jenifer Wells, Mark Megalli</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jenifer Nelle Wells, the daughter of Nelle and William Wells of Columbus, Ga., and Mark Megalli, a son of Viviane Wassef Megalli and Dr. Maguid Megalli of Rye, N.Y., were married yesterday. Bishop J. Kevin Boland of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Savannah, Ga., performed the ceremony at St. Patrick's Cathedral in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is the vice president for strategy at Village Ventures, a venture capital company in New York. Her father is a loan officer at the Southtrust Bank in Columbus, and her mother is a service manager at Columbus Bank and Trust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jenifer Nelle Wells, the daughter of Nelle and William Wells of Columbus, Ga., and Mark Megalli, a son of Viviane Wassef Megalli and Dr. Maguid Megalli of Rye, N.Y., were married yesterday. Bishop J. Kevin Boland of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Savannah, Ga., performed the ceremony at St. Patrick's Cathedral in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 27, is the vice president for strategy at Village Ventures, a venture capital company in New York. Her father is a loan officer at the Southtrust Bank in Columbus, and her mother is a service manager at Columbus Bank and Trust.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 28, is an associate at McKinsey &amp; Company, the management consulting firm in New York. His mother is a real estate broker at Country Properties in Rye, N.Y. His father is the chief medical officer of the Catholic Health Care System, the hospital and nursing home group operated by the Archdiocese of New York.</p>
        <p>The couple met at Yale University in 1990 and graduated in 1994, then remained nodding acquaintances because they traveled in the same circles. In 1997, Mr. Megalli, who was by then working on law and M.B.A. degrees at Yale, decided to buy a two-bedroom apartment in New York. He anticipated living there full time after finishing his graduate work, but with two years to go, he needed a tenant to help with the payments. A mutual friend knew that Miss Wells, then working for a Web site, was looking for an apartment, and matched them up.</p>
        <p>When she moved in on Aug. 1, it was with the understanding that when Mr. Megalli returned to New Haven in three weeks, she would have the apartment to herself. But a lot can happen in three weeks.</p>
        <p>''I had just finished a long-term relationship,'' Miss Wells recalls. ''I wasn't at all thinking of romance.'' But Mr. Megalli soon found that he had developed ''a huge crush'' on his tenant. They began exchanging e-mail at work, but it was all platonic. After work, they started to pal around, going to movies and parties, or just sitting around watching CNN. She grew fond of him. ''I couldn't believe we weren't friends at Yale,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Soon Mr. Megalli felt compelled to express his romantic longings. He sent her a gushy e-mail message, but he wrote it in code. ''It looked like a random bunch of letters, like something out of an Enigma machine,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For days, Miss Wells made no mention of the message. Then came her e-mail response -- also in code.</p>
        <p>''I had worked in software encryption and encoding,'' she said. ''I was able to solve his note fairly easily. I had a crush at that point. I just wasn't sure how to respond. The stakes were very high. I didn't want to screw up what was a good friendship.''</p>
        <p>But her coded reply proved a challenge for Mr. Megalli. After a day of trying to decipher it, he still wasn't sure how she had responded. That night, Miss Wells returned home late from work and saw him ''sitting like a stunned animal on the couch.''</p>
        <p>''He looked petrified,'' she said.</p>
        <p>He told her he had received her e-mail but couldn't understand all of it.</p>
        <p>The couple then discussed their relationship. ''I never had a conversation like that, where there is this massive romantic attraction, but we are having a conversation over whether we should or shouldn't get involved,'' Miss Wells remembered. Finally, they kissed.</p>
        <p>In the two ensuing years, the romance blossomed as he continued his studies and she worked in New York. Then, last August, after Mr. Megalli competed his law and M.B.A. degrees, they traveled to Italy, where he planned to propose marriage on her birthday, just before the end of the trip. ''I had gotten her the ring a week before we left, but she had no idea,'' he said. On the plane, he slipped the ring into a pocket of his leather jacket. But when they were checking into the hotel in Rome, he realized that he had left his jacket in the cab.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't understand why he was so upset,'' Miss Wells said. ''He was inconsolable.''</p>
        <p>He finally remembered that he had transferred the ring to his backpack, but then couldn't remember taking the backpack from the cab. But there it was, on Miss Wells's shoulder. ''I just happened to grab it, thinking 'Oh, Mark is going to forget this,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Megalli proposed the next evening on the Spanish Steps, next to their hotel. ''After I practically lost the ring, it was a race against the clock to get it on Jen's finger,'' he recalled. ''I figured if I waited another couple of days, it would wind up on the bottom of a canal in Venice.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
