<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Soviet Jews Find Uneasy Peace in Germany</title>
    <meta content="06GERM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CROSSING BORDERS: A Quiet Influx" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slave Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Berlin (Germany)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Berlin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D6123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Soviet Jews Find Uneasy Peace in Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Aug. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, Crossing Borders, on quiet influx into Germany of Jews from former Soviet Union; Jewish population recently surpassed 100,000 for first time since Hitler dispersed and destroyed prewar community of more than 500,000; many Germans feel re-establishment of Jewish community represents victory over Nazis and what they tried to do, but ambivalence and hostility also exist over Jewish immigration in German population whose full range of feelings over new arrivals is unknown for simple reason that they have never been consulted; awkward moment has been reached in German-Jewish relations as Jews pour at rate of 5,000 per year with support of state payments of tens of millions of dollars amid rising impatience with Holocaust-induced obligations; with recent agreement for multibillion-dollar payment to Nazi-era slave laborers and three major Jewish institutions under construction in new capital of Berlin, Germans have feeling of 'enough already' (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Violetta Botwinikova is a new-wave Berliner, brisk and chic, a 24-year-old entrepreneur, Moscow-born, Jewish -- and very much at home in an adoptive land that changed history by producing a killing machine for Europe's Jews.</p>
        <p>Her nails are sculptured ellipses -- Ms. Botwinikova is a beautician with a sideline in the bistro business -- and her manner smooth as her nail polish. ''I came to Germany in 1990 because my family could stay here, simple as that,'' she said, poking a spoon into a frothy cappuccino. ''I cannot live in Israel. I need a European lifestyle.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Violetta Botwinikova is a new-wave Berliner, brisk and chic, a 24-year-old entrepreneur, Moscow-born, Jewish -- and very much at home in an adoptive land that changed history by producing a killing machine for Europe's Jews.</p>
        <p>Her nails are sculptured ellipses -- Ms. Botwinikova is a beautician with a sideline in the bistro business -- and her manner smooth as her nail polish. ''I came to Germany in 1990 because my family could stay here, simple as that,'' she said, poking a spoon into a frothy cappuccino. ''I cannot live in Israel. I need a European lifestyle.''</p>
        <p>After a decade here, Ms. Botwinikova speaks German easily, the Russian accent dancing lightly on sentences of hermetic Teutonic perfection. She is proud to be a Jew, she says, and comfortable in a Germany that has given her freedom and money. ''Israel is too provincial,'' she mused, smiling. ''And there are too many Jews there.''</p>
        <p>There are a growing number in Germany, too. With Europe generally closed to legal immigration, the quiet influx into Germany of Jews from the former Soviet Union constitutes one exception. The Central Council of German Jews says it now has 85,000 members, up from 29,000 in 1990.</p>
        <p>With a further 20,000 to 30,000 Jews known to be living here without registering with the council -- Ms. Botwinikova is an example -- Germany's Jewish population has recently surpassed 100,000 for the first time since Hitler dispersed and destroyed a prewar community of more than 500,000 Jews.</p>
        <p>''My personal feeling is that the re-establishment of a Jewish community is a kind of victory over the Nazis and what they tried to do,'' said Manfred Becker, a senior Berlin city official dealing with religious affairs. ''This is the point, even if such immigration costs money. We feel a sense of moral obligation on the German side.''</p>
        <p>But how far should these obligations go? It is clear that ambivalence and hostility also exist over Jewish immigration in a German population whose full range of feelings over the new arrivals is unknown for the simple reason that they have never been consulted.</p>
        <p>Last month, a bomb exploded in Dusseldorf, wounding nine immigrants, six of them former Soviet Jews. Nobody has claimed responsibility; the police insist it is too early to say anti-Semitism lay behind the attack. But the next day a makeshift synagogue in Potsdam was daubed in ''Sieg heil'' graffiti, and politicians have expressed alarm.</p>
        <p>Violent anti-Semites are no more than a small fringe of German society. But an awkward moment has clearly been reached in German-Jewish relations. Jews are pouring in, at least 5,000 of them a year, supported by annual state payments of tens of millions of dollars, even as German impatience with Holocaust-induced obligations is rising.</p>
        <p>With a recent agreement for a multibillion-dollar payment to Nazi-era slave laborers and three major Jewish institutions under construction in the new capital of Berlin, many Germans have a feeling of ''enough already,'' in the words of Michael Blumenthal, the director of the Berlin Jewish museum that will open next year.</p>
        <p>''We have arrived at a very complex psychological situation that is not always pleasant,'' Mr. Blumenthal said. ''What I sense among many Germans is a feeling that we have done all this, and the Jews should be grateful to us and not keep asking for more, not take advantage of us.''</p>
        <p>Such feelings are rarely expressed publicly by Germans because they are officially taboo. Martin Walser, a prominent writer, broke that taboo in 1998 when he declared that he was tired of Auschwitz's being used as ''a moral cudgel'' or ''a tool of intimidation that can be deployed at any time.''</p>
        <p>He was widely disavowed. But Paul Spiegel, the president of the Central Council of German Jews, said he increasingly met fellow Germans who warned him ''not to remind us every day of what happened.''</p>
        <p>Berlin's Jewish population, which has doubled to more than 12,000 in the last decade, now receives more than $20 million a year from the municipal budget for the upkeep of Jewish buildings and schools, security and other matters. By contrast, the Turkish population of 170,000 receives virtually nothing.</p>
        <p>''With the Jewish community, the German side must avoid the impression that it holds the money purse closed,'' Mr. Becker said. ''But we are discreet about the sum we pay. We do not want it to be a headline because we know it could cause resentment.''</p>
        <p>With Berlin's debts at more than $30 billion and many city programs being cut, potential for resentment is high. Just how high is unknown because, Mr. Becker continued, ''nobody dares take an opinion poll in Berlin or Germany about Jewish immigration.''</p>
        <p>Why? ''Suppose only 55 percent were in favor,'' he replied. ''Imagine the outcry. My personal estimate is 70 percent would approve, but our society lacks the courage to find out.''</p>
        <p>Boris Feldmann, a Jew who reached Berlin from Riga in 1991, and who lost three grandparents to the Nazis in World War II, is not too worried about what Germans may think of him. ''You should ask me how I felt in Latvia as a Jew,'' he said. ''In a place where you could lose your job if you went to synagogue.''</p>
        <p>In common with many of the Jews arriving in Germany from the east, Mr. Feldmann is a little impatient with questions about German anti-Semitism and the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>Viewed through the prism of Stalin's crimes and against the backdrop of Soviet anti-Semitism, Germany can seem like a land of freedom with a terrible history, but perhaps no more terrible than that of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I go on radio shows with Russian Jews in New York,'' said Mr. Feldmann, who publishes a  chain of Russian-language newspapers in Germany. ''They ask me how I can live in Germany. But the Holocaust is in the past. You cannot live endlessly thinking the people on the street are related to that madness.''</p>
        <p>In 1980, Mr. Feldmann was in the Soviet Army. He was stationed in Kaliningrad, and when the rise of the Solidarity union in Poland threatened to sweep away the Communist government, he was sent to the Polish border. A Soviet invasion seemed imminent, and Mr. Feldmann would have fought, although he despised the idea.</p>
        <p>In this experience, he finds a lesson, for he believes many ordinary Germans lived with similar dilemmas under Hitler. Not the fanatics, not the SS, but the average German. And so he is inclined to be understanding.</p>
        <p>So, too, are Alexander and Ljudmila Sumin, the Jewish owners of a construction company who arrived in Berlin from Estonia in 1991. When somebody scrawled ''Arbeit macht frei'' -- the words above the gate to Auschwitz -- on their son's exercise book in school, they told themselves that there was good and bad in all countries and that the bad had predominated in Tallinn in the form of repeated hounding of Jews.</p>
        <p>Julius Schoeps, an expert on German-Jewish affairs, noted that Jewish veterans of the Soviet Army and veterans of the Wehrmacht recently held a reunion in Berlin at which they contentedly pored over wartime mementos. ''This may be hard to understand from an American perspective, but these Soviet Jews feel liberated in Germany,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Germany has reached out to people like Mr. Feldmann. Ever since the last East German leader, Lothar de Maiziere, began welcoming Soviet Jews in 1990, and Helmut Kohl, the former chancellor,  adopted a similar policy after unification, Jews have been received here with a welcome almost as generous as that reserved for ''ethnic Germans'' -- people of German stock coming mainly from Russia who have automatic right to German citizenship.</p>
        <p>Once visa requests are approved -- and 5,000 families a year now receive such approval -- Jewish immigrants receive work permits, residence permits, full welfare benefits including medical and dental care, a place to live, free schooling for children and German lessons.</p>
        <p>Synagogues are being built: new ones recently opened in Dortmund and Kassel, and one is under construction in Dresden. There is a five-year waiting list among Jews in the former Soviet Union who have applied to come to Germany, most of them simply seeking a better economic future although they are officially described by Germany as refugees.</p>
        <p>After seven years, the Jews are eligible for German passports. No wonder, then, that there is a thriving trade in false Jewish papers in Moscow, for these papers amount to an elusive passport to a European Union otherwise accessible only to ''asylum seekers.''</p>
        <p>''Yes, the Jewish immigrants are privileged,'' said Barbara John, the Berlin official who oversees the city's large immigrant population. ''This should be seen as a form of reparation. Jews were murdered, and we feel better if we do this.''</p>
        <p>But some Germans plainly feel angry. Throughout Europe, the arrival of immigrants causes more resentment than in the United States partly because the newcomers are eligible for many social benefits, giving some people the feeling that foreigners are taking their tax money.</p>
        <p>But other factors are involved here. Many of the arriving Jews have taken up residence in the former East Germany, where Jews were almost unknown for most of the postwar years, official Communist propaganda scarcely alluded to the Holocaust, the population was told it had fought on the right side against Hitler's ''capitalist'' government, and the Communists regularly used scapegoats to buttress their views.</p>
        <p>So it is natural enough that anti-Semitism has found fertile ground in cities where unemployment is as high as 20 percent and any handouts to foreigners are liable to be singled out in the propaganda of neo-Nazi movements.</p>
        <p>Irina Knochenhauer, a Jew from St. Petersburg who works for the Central Council of German Jews in the state of Brandenburg, near Berlin, said: ''The Dusseldorf bomb was no surprise. There is a lot of anti-Semitism here, open and subliminal. Many people in the east still have no idea what a Jew is.''</p>
        <p>Even in the west, regular contact with Jews remains unusual for most Germans.</p>
        <p>A week ago, she prayed in an improvised Potsdam synagogue -- plans to build a permanent one await approval and financing -- daubed with the words ''Sieg Heil'' and ''Juden.'' It was a painful experience, proof to her that for Jews, in the end, Germany amounts to a ''macabre choice.''</p>
        <p>At age 36, she has spent half her life in Russia and half her life in Germany, after marrying an East German in 1983. But she does not feel at home in Germany and is certain she will move on once her teenage daughter has finished school.</p>
        <p>''I feel I have done everything to try to make it work here,'' she said. ''And Germany has tried hard too. But it does not work. This is a people that destroyed itself in 1933, killed itself, and it cannot come back from this death. So they live on a superficial level in which Jews are symbols of something, but not people.''</p>
        <p>The Jewish repopulation of Germany is at an early stage. It is too soon to say what German patriotism, if any, the children of the new immigrants will feel. The gulf between the feelings of Mr. Feldmann and the feelings of Ms. Knochenhauer is evidence enough of the complex, diverse emotions involved. And a Germany still adjusting to unification has not openly confronted its sentiments at this improvised Jewish immigration.</p>
        <p>Karsten Voigt, a Social Democrat and Foreign Ministry official, called the return of the Jews ''my party's and my generation's last triumph over Hitler.'' But recent developments suggest that it may be premature to speak of victories. The ''normality'' so restlessly sought by Germans in their relations with Jews remains elusive.</p>
        <p>''A lot of Germans are committed to Jewish immigration, and many are uncomfortable,'' said Deidre Berger, the head of the American Jewish Committee in Berlin. ''Some see a way to make good the past, but some think there is a Jewish conspiracy to blackmail them and the world has made Germany feel guilty long enough.''</p>
        <p>Crossing Borders</p>
        <p>This is the second article in a series examining the ways that migration is changing the face of Europe's population. The first article, on July 2, dealt with criminal groups smuggling asylum seekers into a Europe that needs but does not welcome them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
