<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A High-Pitched Dance of Love and Death</title>
    <meta content="06RAMS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramsey, Nancy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schrader, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kohler, Juliane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farbergock, Max</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Aimee and Jaguar (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DC113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A High-Pitched Dance of Love and Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NANCY RAMSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramsey, Nancy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nancy Ramsey reviews movie Aimee and Jaguar, based on true story of German Jewish woman Felice Schragenheim and Lilly Wust, young wife of SS soldier, starring Maria Schrader and Juliane Kohler and directed by Max Farberbock; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FELICE SCHRAGENHEIM was a high-spirited, educated, sensual, witty and wily young woman, whose dangerous misfortune was to have been born Jewish in pre-World War II Germany. During the war she lived in Berlin under an assumed name and worked at a Nazi newspaper, feeding information to the underground resistance. She was involved with a circle of sophisticated Jewish lesbians whose dancing-on-the-volcano lives flouted convention, and sometimes safety.</p>
        <p>Lilly Wust, the young wife of an SS soldier, was the mother of four boys, and for her effort in producing such strapping young specimens of Aryan youth, she was awarded the Nazi's Maternal Cross in bronze. Yet, seeking excitement, she had an affair with an officer while her husband was fighting on the Russian front. She had reportedly once said that she could ''smell Jews,'' a comment that, when it reached Felice via a mutual friend, challenged the playful Felice to arrange a meeting with such a person.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FELICE SCHRAGENHEIM was a high-spirited, educated, sensual, witty and wily young woman, whose dangerous misfortune was to have been born Jewish in pre-World War II Germany. During the war she lived in Berlin under an assumed name and worked at a Nazi newspaper, feeding information to the underground resistance. She was involved with a circle of sophisticated Jewish lesbians whose dancing-on-the-volcano lives flouted convention, and sometimes safety.</p>
        <p>Lilly Wust, the young wife of an SS soldier, was the mother of four boys, and for her effort in producing such strapping young specimens of Aryan youth, she was awarded the Nazi's Maternal Cross in bronze. Yet, seeking excitement, she had an affair with an officer while her husband was fighting on the Russian front. She had reportedly once said that she could ''smell Jews,'' a comment that, when it reached Felice via a mutual friend, challenged the playful Felice to arrange a meeting with such a person.</p>
        <p>When they were introduced in late 1942, Lilly's fascination turned to attraction and fear and then to an all-consuming, erotic love. It wasn't until well into their relationship that Felice told Lilly she was Jewish.</p>
        <p>''Aimee and Jaguar,'' which opens this Friday and is based on the true story of Felice Schragenheim (nicknamed Jaguar; played by Maria Schrader) and Lilly Wust (nicknamed Aimee; played by Juliane Kohler), is a film that the director Max Farberbock initially resisted making. ''I had a sack full of reasons not to do it,'' he said about his first feature, speaking by telephone from his home in Hamburg, Germany. Creating solid female characters was familiar ground for Mr. Farberbock; ''Bella Block,'' a television show he wrote and directed, was about an intelligent, stubborn policewoman and won the German equivalent of an Emmy. And he knew that the well-publicized story of Aimee and Jaguar -- a best-selling book of the same title, by Erica Fischer, was published in Germany in 1994 -- would surely be made into a movie. But he had written another love story he wanted to film, that of two women from highly bourgeois Hamburg families who admit their love for each other while on holiday in Paris.</p>
        <p>''I recognized 'Aimee and Jaguar' was a movie of love and passion,'' he said. ''If I love it, I thought, I will do it strongly, and it won't be commercial enough. There would be that element of German romanticism, with the characters going into deep sentiment, high feelings and destruction. The only one who had the courage to play all those cards was Fassbinder.'' But as he was on his way to Berlin to meet with a producer and turn down the project, Beethoven's Ninth Symphony, conducted by Wilhelm Furtwangler, came over the car radio. ''Furtwangler went for a very strong emotional dynamic,'' Mr. Farberbock said. ''You have very destructive moments and, within half a second, the most tender violin you can hear. Filmmaking is a question of rhythm, and as I listened to the symphony's clash of feelings, so many images came into my mind. The film chose me.''</p>
        <p>The high-pitched life of wartime Berlin provided the perfect backdrop to the remarkable story of Felice and Lilly. ''People who had lost family one day would dance until morning the next,'' Mr. Farberbock said. ''They lived for the moment. I used Cuban music, the rumba, which has the feeling of those days. There were lots of sexual relationships, people betrayed each other much more than the Germans like to admit. And the Nazis hated Berlin women; they didn't want to work in the factories, and they loved pleasure.''</p>
        <p>The film's elements of tension are found less in the air raids than in small, everyday moments, and Mr. Farberbock uses long, lingering close-ups of his characters to bring the war home. In a Berlin hotel one day, some young German soldiers send a round of drinks to Felice and her friends; the soldiers may be unaware the women are Jewish, or perhaps they are just too young and libidinous to care. Later in the film, this sinister undercurrent is magnified when the women, to make money, pose for semi-nude pictures to be sent to soldiers on the front. Leaving the photographer's studio, one of them is stopped by two officials, who demand to see her papers. The camera alternates between the tense, brief interrogation to close-ups of her friends, walking briskly, as they grow increasingly terrified: Should they keep walking? Pretend they don't know her? Seconds count. Look back? Go back?</p>
        <p>''Aimee and Jaguar'' opened the 1999 Berlin Film Festival. Ms. Schrader (''The Giraffe,''  ''Nobody Loves Me'') and Ms. Kohler (a theater actress making her film debut) shared the Silver Bear award for best actress. Alan Riding wrote in The New York Times that ''a German film has for the first time dared use the Nazi regime simply as the context for a human drama.'' The Times of London noted that it ''seems likely to follow Steven Spielberg's epic 'Schindler's List' as a cinematic example of an individual German's struggle to defy the inhumanity of the Hitler era against all the odds.''</p>
        <p>The film's theatrical release in Germany was a commercial success; the critical reception was mixed. Peter Koerte, the film critic for the daily Frankfurter Rundschau, said recently that he found ''Aimee and Jaguar'' ''too arty, too perfect.''</p>
        <p>''In my review I wrote about Rubens' skies, a Rembrandt chiaroscuro and a glimpse of Caravaggio,'' he added. ''But what makes it different is the whole angle, which hasn't existed in German cinema. Films on that period were usually based on resistance people or on German soldiers as innocent victims of a big propaganda machine.''</p>
        <p>Sabine Hake, a professor of German literature and film at the University of Pittsburgh, said that ''Aimee and Jaguar'' is part of a ''new phase'' in German cinema brought on by both the unification of Germany and the fact that the last Holocaust survivors are dying. ''It's an effort at the normalization of the German past.''</p>
        <p>Films about the Nazi period ''used to be very moral and very austere,'' Ms. Hake continued. ''Now there will be more individual stories. But is it one of the historical periods that you can set a love story to, like the Civil War or World War I? The risk is that you trivialize things.''</p>
        <p>Aware of the ''minefields'' he was encountering, Mr. Farberbock considered various approaches. A boulevard comedy a la Ernst Lubitsch was one, no doubt drawing on the success of Roberto Benigni's ''Life Is Beautiful,'' with Felice's circle of friends descending upon the Wust household, ''all those girls coming through different doors into the apartment with this kind of free living; it was a Nazi house, after all,'' Mr. Farberbock said. ''But that would have been a superficial trick. You would have lost that inner tension of the story, the passion and eroticism. I was more interested to get the feeling of those two women. For each it was love for the first time.</p>
        <p>''Before she met Lilly, Felice was living like a pirate,'' he continued. ''She had a warm heart, but she was conquering life. She wanted every day to steal life away from the Nazis.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schrader said: ''When Felice first meets Lilly, she uses her as a hideaway. She's also trying herself out, playing games, to see if she can get hurt. One of the beautiful things about 'Aimee and Jaguar' is that when it starts out, it's mixing up conventional roles of perpetrators and victims.''</p>
        <p>Lilly, Ms. Kohler said, ''was afraid that Felice and her friends were more intelligent, more sophisticated. Lilly was, in a way, simple compared to Felice, but that's what Felice loved about her.'' It was Felice who called herself Jaguar and gave Lilly the pet name Aimee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farberbock and his co-writer, Rona Munro, extended this nuance and complexity to their supporting characters as well. For the newspaper editor, Felice's boss (Peter Weck), Mr. Farberbock, who was born in 1950, looked to his father's generation. ''Today it's too easy to say it would have been impossible to go along with what was happening,'' he said. ''This editor was a very human, highly educated man. He's a man you could sit down and talk with today. But he was 100 percent Nazi. He wrote the most perverted things in his newspaper. It is too easy to create Nazi characters with stupid, violent faces, or have them wearing a mask.''</p>
        <p>On Aug. 21, 1944, Lilly and Felice spent an idyllic afternoon along Berlin's Havel River swimming, picnicking and taking photographs and arrived home to discover Nazi officials in their apartment. They were questioned incessantly, and Felice was taken away. ''By that point, Felice had fallen in love deeply,'' Mr. Farberbock said. ''And she got into terrible danger, because she stayed with Lilly. If she hadn't fallen in love, maybe she would have been more attentive to danger, maybe she would have escaped Germany.''</p>
        <p>Felice was transported to the Theresienstadt concentration camp, and Lilly actually journeyed to the camp to try to see her, an act that may have put Felice's life in further danger. ''Lilly was completely out of her mind,'' Mr. Farberbock said. ''And this scene at the camp, of course, is a scene you normally would like to see. But what I did instead was to film the scene when Lilly returns and tells their friend Ilse what she did. I wanted the horror on Ilse's face.''</p>
        <p>FELICE died toward war's end, probably on one of the death marches. Lilly Wust, 86, is still alive in Berlin; in 1981 she was awarded the Federal Service Cross, one of West Germany's highest service medals awarded to civilians, for hiding Felice and three other Jewish women. She remarried briefly after the war, to support her children, but Felice remains her one true love. In June Ms. Wust came to New York for the film's screening at the New York Lesbian and Gay Film Festival; she finds its ''essence very truthful'' and, in conversation, readily transports herself back to her days with the ''radiant and elegant'' Felice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farberbock did shoot a scene with a pile of corpses, Felice's body among them. But he chose not to use it. ''The atmosphere of Felice being taken away is much stronger than showing her as a corpse,'' he said. ''The movie, until that moment, is told the other way around, it's not showing the primary images.</p>
        <p>''It would have broken the law of that narration, it would have been too obviously dramatic. This is a film that lives in the faces.''</p>
        <p>FILM Nancy Ramsey's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about Krzysztof Kieslowski's ''Decalogue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nancy Ramsey's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about Krzysztof Kieslowski's ''Decalogue.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
