<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sleuth Hot on the Trail of Beach Erosion</title>
    <meta content="06JOUR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgica Pond (East Hampton, Ny)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Hampton (Ny)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rattazzi, Priscilla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leatherman, Stephen (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Georgica Pond (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DA1F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sleuth Hot on the Trail of Beach Erosion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: Dr Stephen Leatherman, coastal geomorphologist whose job it is to locate missing Coast Guard lifesaving stations built in late 1800's that will help him track beach erosion along island's East End, describes his duties; photograher Priscilla Rattazzi's fourth book, Georgica Pond, is published; she comments on view from porch of her 20-room villa in East Hampton; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the midst of a treasure hunt for missing lifesaving stations that will help him track beach erosion on the East End, Stephen Leatherman dropped his backpack into the sand at the top of the dunes. Then he zipped off the legs of his khaki pants and waded into the Atlantic Ocean in his shorts.</p>
        <p>From the water, Dr. Leatherman couldn't tell if the sands were eroding or not. But the surf was cool, the sun was hot. And he was only yards away from the telltale high-water mark, and perhaps 500 feet from the first find on his latest quest, the nearly perfectly restored lifesaving station that doubles as John and Wendy Cooney's Quogue summer home.  ''That's the perk of being Dr. Beach,'' Dr. Leatherman said gleefully, swishing the water with his foot and referring to himself by the nickname students gave him long ago. Just the day before he had romped through the scrub in Amagansett with Carleton Kelsey, an 87-year-old librarian, to find the foundation of a station Mr. Kelsey remembered from his youth, and to the relocated building, now a private home a few blocks away. Then Dr. Leatherman did a little more private-eye beach work from a boat. Yes, the fish were running. So along with way, he caught a few.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the midst of a treasure hunt for missing lifesaving stations that will help him track beach erosion on the East End, Stephen Leatherman dropped his backpack into the sand at the top of the dunes. Then he zipped off the legs of his khaki pants and waded into the Atlantic Ocean in his shorts.</p>
        <p>From the water, Dr. Leatherman couldn't tell if the sands were eroding or not. But the surf was cool, the sun was hot. And he was only yards away from the telltale high-water mark, and perhaps 500 feet from the first find on his latest quest, the nearly perfectly restored lifesaving station that doubles as John and Wendy Cooney's Quogue summer home.  ''That's the perk of being Dr. Beach,'' Dr. Leatherman said gleefully, swishing the water with his foot and referring to himself by the nickname students gave him long ago. Just the day before he had romped through the scrub in Amagansett with Carleton Kelsey, an 87-year-old librarian, to find the foundation of a station Mr. Kelsey remembered from his youth, and to the relocated building, now a private home a few blocks away. Then Dr. Leatherman did a little more private-eye beach work from a boat. Yes, the fish were running. So along with way, he caught a few.</p>
        <p>''The public calls me a beachologist,'' Dr. Leatherman said. ''My real title is coastal geomorphologist, but no one knows what that is.''</p>
        <p>Try beach-combing scientist, or waterside sleuth. While reveling in his 20th summer in the Hamptons, Dr. Leatherman, who spends most of the year as professor and director of the Laboratory for Coastal Research and International Hurricane Center at Florida International University in Miami, is scrounging East End beaches for permanent markers in a multiyear study of coastal erosion and methods of beach restoration begun last year by the Eastern Long Island Coastal Conservation Alliance  and Southampton College. By tracking down the sites of a dozen lifesaving stations that were built four miles apart along the coast in the late 1800's, Dr. Leatherman will be able to tell what the erosion story really is.</p>
        <p>''The thinking right now is there is a lot of rhetoric but not a whole lot of information, not a lot of data,'' said Dr. Leatherman, who was hired to come up with facts. Reminiscences of wedding parties held on sweeping lawns on tony Gin Lane in Southampton, where a station is missing, don't count if there are no photographs or other markers as evidence that half the yard is now under the sea. Arguments at seaside cocktail parties over whether the beach is smaller than it used to be are pointless without documentation.</p>
        <p>''I'm not coming up with conclusions,'' Dr. Leatherman said. ''I am only coming up with findings. I am not making recommendations. The idea is the facts should speak for themselves.</p>
        <p>''The beach is a part of the quality of life,'' he continued, ''and there is a lot of controversy here about the problem of beach erosion and coastal storms and what to do about them, whether to build bulkheads or dredging and groins and jetties. With all this controversy about is the beach eroding or not, one of the ideas was let's look at permanent markers.''</p>
        <p>And that's where the search for  former Coast Guard stations came in. The stations -- now doing business as St. Andrew's Dune Church in Southampton and the Neptune Beach Club in East Quogue, both of which have been moved back from the water, and the Cooney home, which remains far from the sea -- were in surveyed locations that could be pinpointed on old maps. Originally, all the stations were situated 500 to 600 feet from the high-water mark.</p>
        <p>''That is a hard reference point,'' Dr. Leatherman said. ''No one can debate it. No one can deny it. What it shows it will show.''</p>
        <p>But the main roads cited on the old site maps weren't paved. Many were horse paths that don't exist anymore. Dunes have been built up. And there is lots of new construction. But at the corner of Apaquogue Road and Lily Pond Lane, at least two structures -- a boat shed and/or garage -- survive. In Hither Plain, there is almost definitely a station somewhere on the south side of Old Montauk Highway, probably in the vicinity of Lincoln Road, and a missing station may be within Cupsogue Beach County Park. The Cooney home, built in 1912, was a replacement station. The cornerstone of the original 1872 Quogue station is next door.</p>
        <p>''We have found some of these stations very close to the water and one of these stations apparently was in the water,'' Dr. Leatherman said, speaking of a piece of foundation recently found in the Ditch Plains area east of Amagansett. ''We are on a hot trail now. We'd like to see what we can get. Then we're going to go out and measure them.'' Once the distance to the shoreline is recalculated, changes that occurred over the past 120 years or more will be documented.</p>
        <p>Concerned about frequent shipwrecks off the coast, the merchants and ship owners founded the Life Saving Benevolent Association, which built the lifesaving stations along the shore. In 1915, when the U.S. Lifesaving Service merged with the U.S. Revenue Cutter Service, the outposts became U.S. Coast Guard stations.</p>
        <p>The stations were used to store munitions during World War II, when German submarine were frequently sighted offshore, but by 1950 the stations were considered obsolete and sold by the government as excess property. Some of the two- story dwellings with lookout towers were purchased by individuals and relocated; others were razed or refurbished in place. Each has a different story.</p>
        <p>Six of the 12 stations have been pinpointed, but Dr. Leatherman said he and his associate, Sandra E. Shumway, a professor of biology and marine science at Southampton College, need community help to learn more about their original locations and movement dates.</p>
        <p>Clues to watch for? Built of cedar shingle with lookout towers, the two-story stations are landmarks. Many have been modified beyond recognition. The tower on the Neptune Beach Club building was removed.</p>
        <p>''Some people have lived here a long time and they know about the stations and they remember when they were a boy or a girl and they went to the beach, they saw it,'' said Dr. Leatherman. Old photographs that show where the stations were located and the conditions of the dunes are also helpful.</p>
        <p>''We have been lucky so far with people telling us where they were, but we are still missing a lot of them,'' he said. As a reward, Dr. Leatherman is offering free copies of his book, ''America's Best Beaches,'' to anyone who comes forth with a clue. Beach detectives should call (631) 204-1245 with their finds.</p>
        <p>''It's been 50 years since they were occupied,'' Dr. Leatherman said. ''In 50 years, a lot of things can happen.''</p>
        <p>A Hamptons Idyll</p>
        <p>Priscilla Rattazzi sat on the porch of Briar Patch, her two-story, 20-room shingled villa on 16 lush East Hampton acres, gazing across Georgica Pond. Spotting a fisherman in a wooden boat, she picked up a set of binoculars and watched him haul a crab cage out of the water. A swan glided past. In the distance, Ms. Rattazzi pointed out, the sandy beach separating the pond from the Atlantic Ocean was practically deserted.</p>
        <p>''It's unbeatable,'' she said. ''If you like the ocean, if you like the sea, there is no place like this.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rattazzi, 44, is a photographer. The images she captured over the past 10 years of the spring-fed five-fingered tidal pond beyond her back door were published on Friday in her fourth book, ''Georgica Pond.'' Its sepia-toned pages are a personal album devoted to her children -- Maxi, 14, Andrea, 9, and Sasha, 5 -- her 3-year-old golden retriever, Luna, and the snapping turtles, egrets and piping plovers who call the pond home, though her neighbors -- Kelly Klein, Donald Petrie, the director Robert Benton and Eleanore Kennedy -- contributed essays.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to talk about the demise of the Hamptons when you are sitting on this porch,'' Ms. Rattazzi said.  ''There are tons of normal people out here, but it gets overshadowed by movie stars, by the fact that Seinfeld paid somewhere between 30 million and 40 million for his house. That's what gives the Hamptons a bad image, a glitzy, glamorous party image.''</p>
        <p>Never mind that Ms. Rattazzi's other neighbors include Steven Spielberg, Ron Perelman, Courtney Ross and Martha Stewart. Ignore that Ms. Rattazzi is the daughter of the Italian political figure Susanna Agnelli, that her father was a count, that her uncle, Gianni Agnelli, runs the Fiat Corporation, and her husband, Christopher Whittle, founded Channel One and now heads the Edison Schools. Ms. Rattazzi, who is donating the proceeds of her book to the South Fork-Shelter Island chapter of the Nature Conservancy, an environmental group, shuns celebrity. She would like nature and family to be the image of the Hamptons that prevails.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rattazzi prefers to have small dinners with friends, play tennis and sail to the beach. When she started frequenting the East End 25 years ago, she said, it was a very dull place. She liked it that way. Now she whines about traffic, development and the endless fund-raisers that she doesn't attend, not to mention the crowds that make it impossible to go to a restaurant on the weekend or even find a parking space close to the movie theater.</p>
        <p>''It would be great if we could lock up the speculators, the developers and the real estate agents; then it would all be just fine,'' she said, having learned to maneuver the back roads and order food in advance.</p>
        <p>Pardon, Ms. Rattazzi, but what about your own celebration?</p>
        <p>''When you publish a book, you must have a party,'' said Ms. Rattazzi, who threw a cocktail bash on Friday evening for 150 of her closest friends, none of whom are celebrities. ''It's like not baptizing a child.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
