<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Chavez Picks an Icon; Bolivar's Your Hero? No, He's Mine</title>
    <meta content="06ROHT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Hugo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolivar, Simon (1783-1830)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D8153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Chavez Picks an Icon; Bolivar's Your Hero? No, He's Mine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on Venezuelan Pres Hugo Chavez's efforts to appropriate revolutionary leader Simon Bolivar as his personal symbol, efforts that have worked to further polarize society; divergent opinions of Bolivar noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is hardly a town in Latin America that does not have a street or school or square named for Simon Bolivar, the Great Liberator, who freed South America from Spanish rule nearly 200 years ago. Two countries now bear his name, as does the currency here in Venezuela, his native land, now officially known as the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela. Throughout the region, no figure is more universally revered or quoted.</p>
        <p>In his remarkable career as a general and statesman, Bolivar said many different and often contradictory things. That means that  modern political leaders like Hugo Chavez, who was certified here Friday for a new six-year term as president, have a whole menu of positions from which to choose when they seek to legitimize or justify their own actions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is hardly a town in Latin America that does not have a street or school or square named for Simon Bolivar, the Great Liberator, who freed South America from Spanish rule nearly 200 years ago. Two countries now bear his name, as does the currency here in Venezuela, his native land, now officially known as the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela. Throughout the region, no figure is more universally revered or quoted.</p>
        <p>In his remarkable career as a general and statesman, Bolivar said many different and often contradictory things. That means that  modern political leaders like Hugo Chavez, who was certified here Friday for a new six-year term as president, have a whole menu of positions from which to choose when they seek to legitimize or justify their own actions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez himself is something of a mystery to much of the world -- a charismatic populist who is at the same time a military man, a leftist, a sloganeer and above all an enthusiastic wielder of power. To try to get a grip on what a complicated leader really is like, it is sometimes useful to take a look at the heroes and symbols he tries to exploit. In Mr. Chavez's case, the most important of these is Bolivar.</p>
        <p>But which Bolivar?</p>
        <p>There is one Bolivar, for instance, who praised democracy as ''the most sacred source'' of power, but there is also another who once proclaimed that ''necessity recognizes no laws.'' One Bolivar admired George Washington as the ideal ''citizen-hero'' who ''fills my bosom with emulation,'' while another famously and bitterly remarked that ''the United States seems destined by providence to plague Latin America with misery in the name of liberty.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chavez describes himself as a disciple of Bolivar, and some of his more ardent followers have gone so far as to suggest he is the ''reincarnation of the Liberator.'' But his vision of Bolivar is one ''very much adapted to his own purposes,'' said Jesus Sanoja Hernandez, a prominent political commentator here. Even before coming to power 18 months ago, Mr. Chavez, a former army colonel who in 1992 led an unsuccessful coup attempt, made it clear that ''the Bolivar he likes is the one who centralized power,'' said Guillermo Moron, one of Venezuela's leading historians and experts on Bolivar. ''The Bolivar that the opposition likes, in contrast, is the one who respected the law, consulted even his enemies and tried to create an impartial system of justice for all.''</p>
        <p>In a society as deeply divided by class, geography and race as modern Venezuela, Bolivar, who was born here in 1783, has always been an important symbol of national unity and identity. ''All Venezuelans are Bolivarians by definition, because he is the only great man this country has ever produced,'' said Dr. Moron.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chavez's efforts to appropriate Bolivar as his personal symbol have worked to  further polarize society -- for example when he  brandished Bolivar's sword as he criticized opponents during the recent election campaign here. The result is a situation in which, as the  Bolivar scholar Manuel Caballero puts it, ''every enemy of the government is thereby an enemy of Bolivar and thus excluded from the Venezuelan community.''</p>
        <p>Precisely because Bolivar is a national icon who is supposed to be above partisan battles, Venezuelan law prohibits any political party from including his name in its official title. But Mr. Chavez has at times come perilously close to ignoring that restriction, originally designating his organization the Bolivarian Revolutionary Movement and even now calling his program to expand the role of the military the ''Plan Bolivar 2000.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, one of his most recent initiatives has been the creation of what he calls ''Bolivarian schools,'' complete with lunch programs and medical care for poor children. That program, however, quickly provoked controversy when it became clear that the curriculum was to include military training for students and that textbooks on the history of Venezuela were going to be rewritten to suit Mr. Chavez.</p>
        <p>Bolivar is not the only hero of Latin American independence to be subjected to such historical revisionism. Cuba provides perhaps an even more glaring example: Fidel Castro manipulates the writings of Jose Marti for his own ends, as does the Cuban exile community in Miami and even the United States government, through its broadcasts on Radio and TV Marti.</p>
        <p>Outside Venezuela's borders, Mr. Chavez's use of Bolivarian ideals has been even more confusing and contradictory. Bolivar proclaimed that ''Our country is America,'' and Mr. Chavez has repeatedly endorsed the concept of regional integration. He has pushed for a South Atlantic version of NATO, only to be met by the skepticism of Brazil.</p>
        <p>Thanks largely to Mr. Chavez, it seems to be the left that is getting the most mileage out of Bolivar in nearby countries in Latin America at the moment. The political party recently formed by Colombia's main Marxist guerrilla group bears Bolivar's name, and the populist-nationalist colonels who joined with Indians to overthrow President Jamil Mahuad of Ecuador in January have also described themselves as followers of Bolivar.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chavez also unilaterally closed his country's border to Colombian truckers and then defied the Andean Community when the group ruled that such an action was illegal. He has persistently flirted with the guerrillas who are seeking to overthrow Colombia's democratically elected government; he has failed to condemn the recent military coup in Ecuador, and he now seems to want to revive a dormant border dispute with neighboring Guyana.</p>
        <p>So as the 21st century begins, Bolivar, a product of the 18th-century Enlightenment,  plays a more important role in the daily politics of his homeland than Washington or even Jefferson do in the United States. Yet lurking in the background is the prospect that the Bolivarian revival Mr. Chavez is sponsoring could end up  perpetuating one of the Liberator's most famous prophecies. ''America is ungovernable,'' he said just a few weeks before his death in Colombia in 1830. ''He who serves the revolution plows the sea.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
