<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Battle in Cyberspace</title>
    <meta content="ONLINET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE TEACHING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DD113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Battle in Cyberspace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Abby Ellin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellin, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Online teaching expands in US, with at least one-third of colleges offering distance-learning courses; several programs described (special section, Education Life) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the summer of 1997, Dr. Cyndi Wilson Porter, an assistant chemistry professor at Lakeland College in Sheboygan, Wis., was asked to teach a class online. She hesitated at first -- she loved the feel of a classroom, the camaraderie of live communication. She did not want to be an anonymous piece of software somewhere beyond the computer screen.</p>
        <p>But she did it, and soon, she said, she fell in love with the interaction. ''On the ground, some students respond and others don't; online, everyone does -- they have to,'' she said. ''Online, the only way I know you're alive is if you participate, so we set goals of how many times a week students have to respond. It's very exciting.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the summer of 1997, Dr. Cyndi Wilson Porter, an assistant chemistry professor at Lakeland College in Sheboygan, Wis., was asked to teach a class online. She hesitated at first -- she loved the feel of a classroom, the camaraderie of live communication. She did not want to be an anonymous piece of software somewhere beyond the computer screen.</p>
        <p>But she did it, and soon, she said, she fell in love with the interaction. ''On the ground, some students respond and others don't; online, everyone does -- they have to,'' she said. ''Online, the only way I know you're alive is if you participate, so we set goals of how many times a week students have to respond. It's very exciting.''</p>
        <p>Three years later, she is the assistant vice president for extended academic programs and the director of Universe Online, a nonprofit virtual arm of the University of the Incarnate Word in San Antonio. Universe Online is starting up this fall and will offer business classes for undergraduates, as well as courses leading to an M.B.A. The online teachers are faculty members and business owners.</p>
        <p>Universe Online is one of the many so-called distance-learning programs hovering in cyberspace. According to reports from the United States Department of Education, at least one-third of the 3,500 colleges and universities in the United States offer distance-learning courses; within the next two years, four out of every five are expected to do so.</p>
        <p>But neither faculty members nor administrators are sure about some of the issues raised about intellectual property, like who owns and who should control content that appears online. Does the university or the faculty member who created an online course own it? Who retains copyright to the material? The issue did not arise before cybercourses, because the material and the teacher were intertwined. But now many faculty members fear they will lose control over the courses they teach, that their lessons will be modified or prepackaged into a one-size-fits-all lecture by someone at an online institution.</p>
        <p>How much freedom does a faculty member have? Professors typically design traditional courses, and decide which readings to assign and what information to deliver. But what happens with an online course, where the methodologies are different?</p>
        <p>David F. Noble, a history professor at York University in Toronto, argues that distance learning contributes to the commercialization of academia and that it forces universities to be concerned only with turning a profit.</p>
        <p>''Who owns the material you have placed on the Web site or e-mail?'' he wrote in an essay called ''Digital Diploma Mills: The Coming Battle Over Online Instruction,'' part of a series that, ironically, he posted on the Internet, at www.communication.ucsd.edu/dl.</p>
        <p>''Without a clear and definitive assertion of copyright claims by faculty, the universities will usurp such rights by default.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Porter disagrees. Educators, she says, ''are hired to impart knowledge, to help students learn. Even as a traditional academic, I have never understood the mindset of 'I own this so I should be able to sell it.' As a chemist, I share my knowledge. I didn't invent chemistry or chemical concepts.'' She added, ''Since I am paid by my school to share my knowledge, they in effect are leasing me.''</p>
        <p>Some universities, on the other hand, are concerned that professors will rake in substantial sums by teaching classes to millions of people across the globe, and that they will not share the tuition with their institutions. They are also worried that some professors will branch out on their own and teach courses for nontraditional institutions like the Global Education Network, a company founded by Herbert A. Allen, a venture capitalist.</p>
        <p>That is what happened with Arthur R. Miller, a Harvard Law School professor who provides video courses for the Concord University School of Law, a virtual school founded by Kaplan Inc., the test-preparation company. Professor Mil- ler, who markets many of his Harvard lectures on videocassettes, contended that he was not violating Harvard's policy of not providing course material to another school while still teaching at Harvard, without permission. Harvard said he was. According to Michael Chmura, a Harvard Law School spokesman, the university issued new guidelines last spring, after the conflict with Professor Miller arose, to make clear that it prohibited such online moonlighting. Professor Miller was out of the country and not immediately available for comment, an assistant said.</p>
        <p>SOME universities are signing deals themselves. Unext.com, a virtual university backed by Michael Milken, the former junk bond king, and Lawrence J. Ellison, the chairman of Oracle, has agreements with Columbia University, Carnegie Mellon University, the University of Chicago, the London School of Economics and Stanford University to receive course materials from them for use at an online for-profit virtual university, said Andrew M. Rosenfield, an economist and lawyer who is a lecturer at the University of Chicago Law School and the chief executive of Unext.com. The school also contracts with faculty members at other colleges to provide courses unique to Unext.</p>
        <p>Western Governors University, a virtual college, will develop programs that provide academic credit for practical experience, and will utilize course work from institutions throughout the United States.</p>
        <p>Still, while colleges and universities have long concerned themselves with patentable items -- inventions or medical techniques created in university laboratories -- many are unsure about how to proceed with online materials.</p>
        <p>''Schools never cared about literary endeavors,'' said Dan Burk, professor of law at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis, who is an expert on intellectual property law and cyberlaw. ''There was never enough money expected from one.'' But now that the economics of ownership of academic materials is changing, he says, ''the vast majority of universities don't know what they're doing. We have no guidance.''</p>
        <p>Because the multimedia arena of distance learning is copyrightable subject matter, some academics foresee a lot of money being generated by online courses. For the past three years, for example, Stanford's engineering school has taught 200 courses to students all over the world -- at 140 percent of the school's normal tuition. Duke University charges $95,000 for what it calls a Global Executive M.B.A., a 19-month-long program that mixes a month on campus and a month studying abroad with online study. That is considerably more expensive than tuition for the traditional two-year M.B.A. program, which is $28,200 per year.</p>
        <p>Administrators at Penn State view their online World Campus as the 25th campus in the university system. Since it opened two years ago, there has been a jump from 70 students to 2,895.</p>
        <p>At some schools, faculty members have protested the consideration of courses on the Web. Nine hundred faculty members at the University of Washington signed a petition opposing talk of a virtual university. Professors at Cornell have expressed discomfort with e-Cornell, a for-profit subsidiary to develop and market online courses, said Bill Steele, a university spokesman. Details of the program have not yet been completed.</p>
        <p>Beyond the focus on ownership, Dr. Burk cites deeper, more complex issues that are at stake -- like career, competition, status and money.</p>
        <p>If Harvard's Professor Miller took a sabbatical to teach at another bricks-and-mortar institution, ''nobody would have cared,'' he said. But now, ''what they're saying is that 'we don't want you to pull a paycheck from Harvard and also teach online.' Harvard's not happy to have its name affiliated with a nonaccredited school.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chmura said that the issue was not the linking of names, but assuring that Harvard faculty members give most of their attention to Harvard students. There are also issues of ego and respect. Both came up when faculty members at the University of Chicago were asked by administrators to develop materials for Unext.com. ''It makes them sound like they're working for a big corporation, where their bosses can give them an assignment,'' said Dr. Burk. ''They wonder, 'Are we just cogs? Can my dean or department head tell me to create this course as part of my regular duties here? Can I say yes or no?' The real question now is: What's the role of the bricks-and-mortar university, and how is the relationship between the faculty and the university changing?''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, the courses those faculty members develop count toward their required teaching load, but they do not earn any extra pay for creating them, said Larry Arbeiter, a University of Chicago spokesman. There is no consensus about many of the questions raised. Some schools have decided to use revenue from online courses as a way of paying faculty. Others are considering the model of the recording and entertainment industries; faculty members would own the rights to online instructional materials and would be allowed to sell material to online colleges. Some people expect professors to hire agents to broker deals for them.</p>
        <p>In May, Duke University's Academic Council approved a policy allowing professors to retain ownership of all courses they create as individuals, but allowing the university to retain ownership of some courses created using university property. The University of Texas has a similar policy, which calls for joint ownership of courses created using the university's funds or personnel.</p>
        <p>At the University of Minnesota, faculty members retain ownership of any Web-based courses they create, unless there is a prior agreement to the contrary. Dr. Porter said Universe Online pays a faculty member 5 percent of the tuition it receives for an online course for each of the first five times the course is offered.</p>
        <p>She said, ''There's no difference between online and on-ground teaching other than the actual method of delivery. Instead of standing up and talking, I now type. When I do an online class, I'm still just sharing my knowledge. When I teach a course on-ground, I get paid as part of my salary. When I teach a class online, I also get paid as part of my salary. But everyone wants a piece of the pie.'' But the issue of dividing the pie is more pressing when, unlike Dr. Porter, the faculty member whose course is offered online does not participate in teaching it, because then he or she will either be paid for assembling the content or not be paid at all.</p>
        <p>The American Association of University Professors has drafted model contracts that give faculty members a financial interest in courses that are adapted to online presentations. Dr. Burk of Minnesota predicts that the debate will quiet down soon.</p>
        <p>''Part of what's driving this is that these online courses are multimedia intensive, with video, graphics, music, and text,'' he said. ''They're new and hot, and both the institution and faculty seem to think there will be a bunch of money out there. But the reality is that these blockbuster moneymaking gold-rush scenarios probably won't happen. I am hoping people will realize there's not a gold mine and come to their senses.''</p>
        <p>ONLINE TEACHING Abby Ellin writes the Preludes column for the Money &amp; Business section of The New York Times on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Abby Ellin writes the Preludes column for the Money &amp; Business section of The New York Times on Sunday.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
