<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Does This Woman Want?</title>
    <meta content="06OHEHIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Hehir, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Daughters of Simon Lamoreaux, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDF163DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Does This Woman Want?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew O'Hehir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Hehir, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew O'Hehir reviews book The Daughters of Simon Lamoreaux by David Long (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DAUGHTERS OF SIMON LAMOREAUX</p>
        <p>By David Long.</p>
        <p>270 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Scribner. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DAUGHTERS OF SIMON LAMOREAUX</p>
        <p>By David Long.</p>
        <p>270 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Scribner. $24.</p>
        <p>IT'S safe to say that David Long has a thing for sisters. His fine first novel, ''The Falling Boy'' (1997), focuses on four charismatic Greek-American sisters, one of whom enters into a disastrous affair with another's husband. In ''The Daughters of Simon Lamoreaux,'' which is a leaner and more explosive book, the four sisters have been boiled down to two, and the relationship between them is even weirder. Solid, reliable Carly Lamoreaux is dead -- or presumed dead -- yet her very absence is the story's glue, the force that connects her sister, Julia; her former boyfriend, Miles Fanning; and another specter, that of Simon, the sisters' lugubrious, hyperreligious father.</p>
        <p>As gripping as Long's explorations of sisterhood are, his real subject is not sisters per se but the men who love them. If fiction about the strangled emotional life of the American male has become its own genre, packed with its own cliches, few of the writers who have worked this territory can match Long's vivid characterization, his blend of cleareyed sympathy and critical distance and his old-fashioned gift for storytelling. ''The Daughters of Simon Lamoreaux'' has the propulsive power and mystery of a Gothic romance, but the world it creates is a complicated and contemporary one, in which men and women are shaped by random events and rarely know themselves as well as they think they do.</p>
        <p>Miles Fanning is a 40-ish Seattle record-company entrepreneur living in a semi-furnished storeroom he has named the Hospitality Suite. He's there because his wife, Kyra, an athletic, straightforward blonde who works in the mayor's office, has requested a trial separation. The very qualities that drew him and Kyra together, Miles reflects, are now driving them apart: ''Kyra's very flesh, her vibrancy and directness, her need for immediate remedy. Or, in Fanning's case: the vague air of culture and dissolution, his living in the well of his thoughts, his customary reserve.''</p>
        <p>Kyra may be irritated by Miles's reserve, but she doesn't know the half of it; he's never told her about his prep school girlfriend, Carly, who disappeared from downtown Hartford one spring day in 1973 and was never seen again. Miles was extensively interrogated, but he had no better idea what happened to Carly than the police did. By 1997, when the main action of ''The Daughters of Simon Lamoreaux'' takes place, he has convinced himself he no longer thinks about her. ''He wasn't fond of the past, didn't court it,'' Long writes. Later, Miles reflects that ''most of it was simply not there. Day stacked on day, erased or remembered in shreds or skewed into untruth.''</p>
        <p>When Carly's younger sister, Julia, unexpectedly intrudes upon Miles's Hospitality Suite life, first by e-mail and then in person, she makes her presence seem like near happenstance, the result of idle curiosity. If Miles is eager to erase the past, Julia is even more eager to put all the pieces back together. As even the pathologically passive Miles can tell, Julia is capital-T Trouble: she's a scary-skinny mix of caustic wit and neurotic vulnerability who smokes and drinks like a Hollywood femme fatale and almost immediately begins calling him at odd hours (both she and Miles are insomniacs). At different moments Julia serves as shrink, Scheherazade and inquisitor; neither Miles nor the reader is sure whether she wants to dissect Miles's memory for the tiniest clue, torture him for his apparent indifference or simply tell him about the unendurable suffering to which the Lamoreaux family was subjected. Her father, Simon, an apparently dour member of a rural Christian sect of unusual severity, is one of Long's most memorable creations, emerging in Julia's stories as a noble and humane man, a modern Job who judged himself wanting in faith.</p>
        <p>Although Miles is initially horrified by Julia's intense neediness, their connection has an instant, unpredictable electricity, and their fumbling progress toward a sexual union seems both convincing and necessary. (In each of his novels as well as his short stories, Long writes about sex with a terrific combination of delicacy and power.) Finally, Miles is compelled to return to the New England he has tried to forget, where if he cannot solve the Lamoreaux family's painful mysteries at least he can confront them with something approaching honesty. One only wishes that Long's novel were kinder to the immensely likable Kyra; nothing that happens in this extraordinary fable about the opacity and strangeness of American life is her fault.</p>
        <p>Andrew O'Hehir is a contributing writer for the online magazine Salon.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew O'Hehir is a contributing writer for the online magazine Salon.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
