<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Journal; An 'Outlet' Store With a Difference: Cappuccino</title>
    <meta content="06JOUR$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Carpet and Home</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Monte</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFD9123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Journal; An 'Outlet' Store With a Difference: Cappuccino</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONTE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Monte</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bronx Journal on ABC Carpet and Home Warehouse Outlet, where shoppers can sip cappuccino and white wine while deciding on Oriental carpet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sue Greenberg folded herself into a chair in the cafe at ABC Carpet and Home Warehouse Outlet in the southeast Bronx and ordered chicken francais and a glass of white wine. The executive assistant to the store's president, Ms. Greenberg talked about how the cafe, which opened a year ago, enhanced the store, which stands out in the gritty neighborhood like a woman at a Promise Keepers powwow.</p>
        <p>''Couples look around the store, then come in here, have a cup of coffee and decide if they want to spend $5,000 on a rug,'' Ms. Greenberg said of the cafe, which is owned and operated by her sister Janet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sue Greenberg folded herself into a chair in the cafe at ABC Carpet and Home Warehouse Outlet in the southeast Bronx and ordered chicken francais and a glass of white wine. The executive assistant to the store's president, Ms. Greenberg talked about how the cafe, which opened a year ago, enhanced the store, which stands out in the gritty neighborhood like a woman at a Promise Keepers powwow.</p>
        <p>''Couples look around the store, then come in here, have a cup of coffee and decide if they want to spend $5,000 on a rug,'' Ms. Greenberg said of the cafe, which is owned and operated by her sister Janet.</p>
        <p>She recalled that a man from Myrtle Beach, S.C., who was visiting Manhattan arrived at the store by taxi and shopped for two hours while the cabdriver waited with the meter running. Cost of the taxi: $170. Cost of a rug from Iran that the man bought: $3,499.</p>
        <p>This is all to say that ABC's outpost in the Bronx -- the flagship store is on lower Fifth Avenue in Manhattan -- is no poor relation. Customer after customer notes that it is nothing like a typical factory outlet. The goods are artfully displayed. There is no dust, and salespeople are willing to serve. Like the Manhattan store, it brings to mind your grandmother's attic. (That is, if your grandmother is Brooke Astor.) Prices are 20 percent to 50 percent lower than they are in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The 320,000-square-foot emporium in the Bronx opened 17 years ago as a warehouse. Two years later, it started selling carpets and rugs to the public. Now, in addition to floor coverings, there are antiques and reproductions galore, linens and bed and bath items, fabrics and remnants and cookware. Price tags hang even from the mosaic tables, Brazilian china closets and chandeliers in the cafe.</p>
        <p>''Everything is for sale,'' said Paul Chapman, the president of the Bronx store, ''except for the pillars that hold up the building.''</p>
        <p>For the most part, the comings and goings seem unaffected by the rhythms of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Customers, most of them well heeled and from the suburbs of Long Island, Connecticut, New Jersey and Westchester, said they had no qualms about driving to the area, possibly because the store has its own parking lot.</p>
        <p>The store stands on an industrial stretch of Bronx River Avenue, between Bruckner Boulevard and Westchester Avenue. The road is lined with squat, rambling buildings that house auto-body and auto-parts stores, auto repair shops and used-car dealers.</p>
        <p>Hector B., a mechanic at the Chase Tire Shop who would not give his last name, said that customers occasionally left their cars to be repaired and walked over to ABC to shop. But Frank Ramirez of Parkchester, who had taken his car to the Pompy Repair Shop a few doors away, said he could not fathom doing such a thing. ''I usually wait for my car,'' he said. ''I don't leave my car with anyone. This is the Bronx!''</p>
        <p>The blocks that surround the store and its neighbors are dotted with housing projects, well-maintained apartment buildings and some two-family houses. One day recently, a 5-year-old on a bicycle was trying to summon the nerve to ride through the running water of an open fire hydrant. Adolescent boys, all legs and arms, laughed outside a corner bodega.</p>
        <p>The police say the neighborhood has a high crime rate that is rising in some categories. For example, from Jan. 1 to June 30 this year there were 35 rapes, compared with 27 for the same period last year, and 401 burglaries, compared with 317 last year. The most significant drop in crime was for car theft: there were 330 auto thefts this year, down from 465 last year.</p>
        <p>The Bronx borough president, Fernando Ferrer, is a big fan of the store, and he takes issue with the characterization of the neighborhood given by the police. ''It has a high crime rate relative to what? Greenwich, Connecticut?'' he said. ''I'd say it's just as safe as 19th Street and Fifth Avenue. The fact is people are coming down to the store, and they are fine. It's a terrific place.''</p>
        <p>The shoppers agree.</p>
        <p>Deirdre Engels, her 1-year-old son, Jack, and her mother, Kathleen DeBlasio, all from Rye, N.Y., visited the store on a recent Sunday afternoon. ''I'm not fearful of the area at all,'' said Ms. Engels, who sipped a cappuccino and shared a pasta salad with her mother and Jack. ''It's right off the Bruckner Expressway.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. DeBlasio agreed. ''There's a parking lot with a security guard,'' she said. ''You don't have to worry about finding a spot.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Engels, who said the cafe was a nice addition because there were few restaurants in the area, shopped for two hours, riffling through rugs. She finally settled on a 9-foot-by-12-foot dhurrie rug, which cost $299.</p>
        <p>Cheryl Shufflebotham of Brooklyn Heights said she visited the outlet twice a week, frequently stopping in the cafe. ''It's good to rest for a few minutes,'' she said, sipping a cappuccino. ''This is just as nice as the Manhattan store. Actually it's a little bit smaller, so it's more relaxing. The cafe is nice for husbands who maybe don't like to shop as much.''</p>
        <p>It's a plus for the store's 150 employees, too, Ms. Greenberg said. ''There's nothing around here to eat unless you want McDonald's or Kentucky Fried Chicken.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
