<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Real Storm, the Skipper, the Crew and the Boat All Survived</title>
    <meta content="06BOAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Sports; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonard, Ray</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Perfect Storm, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Perfect Storm, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D6123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Real Storm, the Skipper, the Crew and the Boat All Survived</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Ray Leonard, who was skipper of Satori, sailboat that was abandoned by crew during Coast Guard rescue depicted in book and movie The Perfect Storm; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About midway through ''The Perfect Storm,'' the film adaptation of Sebastian Junger's phenomenal best-seller, the skipper of the 32-foot sailboat Mistral, sporting a jaunty yachtsman's cap and a highbrow New England accent, makes an offhand remark about his vast offshore prowess. It's a setup line. He's silly, smug and about to get walloped.</p>
        <p>As readers of the book know, the character is based on Ray Leonard, the skipper of Satori, a Westsail 32 that was abandoned by its crew in a North Atlantic gale during a United States Coast Guard rescue operation in the fall of 1991. Portrayed by Junger as a strange introvert with a fondness for the bottle, Leonard has now been skewered both in print and by Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About midway through ''The Perfect Storm,'' the film adaptation of Sebastian Junger's phenomenal best-seller, the skipper of the 32-foot sailboat Mistral, sporting a jaunty yachtsman's cap and a highbrow New England accent, makes an offhand remark about his vast offshore prowess. It's a setup line. He's silly, smug and about to get walloped.</p>
        <p>As readers of the book know, the character is based on Ray Leonard, the skipper of Satori, a Westsail 32 that was abandoned by its crew in a North Atlantic gale during a United States Coast Guard rescue operation in the fall of 1991. Portrayed by Junger as a strange introvert with a fondness for the bottle, Leonard has now been skewered both in print and by Hollywood.</p>
        <p>With each subsequent retelling of his story, the lines that define who Leonard is and what happened during that terrible, perfect storm become more blurred. In fact, Leonard is a retired research ecologist for the United States Forest Service, a former college administrator and an accomplished long-distance voyager with a Coast Guard license and tens of thousands of miles under his keel, and he does not fall within the neat, nasty boundaries of his depictions.</p>
        <p>''I haven't seen the movie and I probably won't until I can borrow a copy of the video,'' Leonard said last week from the small home he is building for himself in western Vermont. ''But as for hats, I just wear a ball cap at sea. It keeps the sun out of my eyes.''</p>
        <p>Junger, who did not speak to Leonard for his book, did not return a phone call seeking comment for this column. But in a 1997 interview about Leonard in The New York Observer, Junger said, ''He didn't sound like the kind of guy I wanted to talk to.''</p>
        <p>That's a shame, because Junger, whose book focuses on the loss of the fishing vessel Andrea Gail and includes vivid writing about meteorology, long-line fishing and Coast Guard heroics, missed a grand opportunity to capture the passion of a long-distance sailor.</p>
        <p>Leonard, 72, bought his Westsail in 1974, the same year the rugged little double-ended yacht was featured on the cover of Time as the perfect vessel for folks ready to chuck it all and head for the South Seas.</p>
        <p>''Satori is the Buddhist word for enlightenment,'' Leonard said. ''I was at the midpoint of my career, and the boat gave me new insight into myself. Whenever I got into a bad fix with her, she always did better than I thought she would. She was very well named for me.''</p>
        <p>From 1974 to '91, Leonard sailed Satori hard and often, mostly alone. The boat was well equipped with designated storm sails, and Leonard had plenty of chance to use them in roughly 60,000 miles of sailing. Divorced in 1985, he moved aboard Satori the same year. In October 1991, accompanied by Karen Stimson and Susan Bylander, two women he had spent the summer working with, Leonard and Satori set out from New Hampshire bound for Bermuda.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, the voyage was a nightmare. Several days into the trip, after receiving a Mayday call relayed by a commercial vessel, a Coast Guard helicopter plucked Satori's crew from a roiled sea. While that fact is indisputable, the events leading up to the rescue remain unclear; there are two very different versions of Satori's fateful passage.</p>
        <p>In Junger's book, which is based largely on interviews with Stimson, the sailors survive through the initiative of the women, who are forced to take action when Leonard, ''sullen and silent, sneaking gulps off a whiskey bottle,'' refuses to do so. In what he describes as 30-foot seas, Junger wrote that Satori was ''starting to lose the battle to stay afloat.''</p>
        <p>Leonard, however, dismisses much of Junger's account. ''I'd guess the seas were 15 to 18 feet, tops,'' he said. ''Satori had been in much worse. It was a very uncomfortable ride, but the boat was sound and we weren't taking on water, except for a few gallons that came through the hatch. And the drinking bit is just totally untrue.''</p>
        <p>Leonard was employing standard tactics for weathering extreme conditions: he had battened Satori down and was content to wait things out. ''You never head towards shore in a heavy storm,'' he said. ''It's too dangerous. And the weather forecast said a hurricane was heading towards Bermuda, so it didn't make sense to keep going that way.''</p>
        <p>Leonard said he did not authorize a Mayday call, though he did give the women permission to radio the Coast Guard to update Satori's position. And when the chopper did arrive, he considered staying aboard Satori. Ultimately, when he was ordered to leave, he complied.</p>
        <p>''When I knew the crew would have to jump in the water, I wasn't comfortable about having them go alone,'' he said. ''Also, I knew if I disobeyed I wouldn't be able to land in a U.S. port for several years, and I've seen expatriates in foreign ports. I didn't want to be one.''</p>
        <p>Stimson, who was on vacation from her job in Maine last week, was unavailable for comment. Interestingly, according to a friend of hers, Stimson now owns a Westsail 32.</p>
        <p>What transpired after the rescue supports Leonard's contention that Satori was still seaworthy when her crew leapt off her transom. Several days later, the boat washed up on a Maryland beach. A bag of personal items that Leonard had mistakenly dropped when he left Satori was still on the afterdeck.</p>
        <p>''A park ranger found my phone number in it,'' Leonard said. ''He called me up and said come get your boat. It was fine. I went down and had her hauled off, cleaned her up, then sailed her to Florida.''</p>
        <p>Leonard continued to sail Satori until this spring, when he sold the boat to a Texas couple. As for the fallout from Junger's book, which Leonard has read, he said: ''People who don't know me who've read it have preconceived notions. I've only had one boat delivery job, and I used to get plenty. I'm not bitter, but I don't think the book or movie explained what sailing's all about. Bluewater sailors are sharp, self-reliant, and proud.''</p>
        <p>And while Leonard no longer owns Satori, he is still drawn to the sea. Earlier this year, fulfilling a lifelong dream, he went to Alaska in search of the same work that took the lives of the crew of the Andrea Gail. Once there, he signed on aboard a salmon trawler. Of all things, the sailor became a fisherman.</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
