<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selling Gear to Pollution Fighters</title>
    <meta content="06SAFE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cg Industrial Safety Products (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galloway, Colleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuchs, Marek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5D61F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selling Gear to Pollution Fighters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAREK FUCHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuchs, Marek</byline>
      <dateline>PEEKSKILL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on CG Industrial Safety Products, owned by former high school English teacher Colleen Galloway, which distributes environmental cleanup products from warehouse in Peekskill, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THROUGH the gap that separates the Church of the Comforter and the Park Street Methodist-Episcopal Zion Church here, you catch a glimpse of a warehouse on Sparrow Lane.</p>
        <p>Colleen Galloway, a former English teacher at Pleasantville High School, owns the building and enjoys talking about its shady pedigree. It was the former home, she said in a playfully hushed tone, ''of some type of chop shop.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THROUGH the gap that separates the Church of the Comforter and the Park Street Methodist-Episcopal Zion Church here, you catch a glimpse of a warehouse on Sparrow Lane.</p>
        <p>Colleen Galloway, a former English teacher at Pleasantville High School, owns the building and enjoys talking about its shady pedigree. It was the former home, she said in a playfully hushed tone, ''of some type of chop shop.''</p>
        <p>This meant that before moving her company, CG Industrial Safety Products, a distributor of environmental cleanup products, into the warehouse, Ms. Galloway had to spend days lugging car doors, tires and engine parts -- an unlikely task for someone who was introducing Pleasantville teenagers to Shakespeare as recently as 1995.</p>
        <p>Ms. Galloway, who lives in Ridgefield, said flat out that teaching was not for her. She never liked what she saw as the predictable grind. ''You'd start 'Julius Caesar' on the fifth of one month every year and another book on the fifth of the next month.'' About to start a family, she also wanted a more flexible schedule.</p>
        <p>For years, Ms. Galloway had wanted to start a company that would aid the environment. Her parents moved to Holbrook, Mass., in the 1950's when it was ''just a country village.''</p>
        <p>''There was one business in town,'' she said, ''a paint manufacturer and one little lake in the town, Lake Holbrook. As a kid, we were there all the time. We couldn't wait to get home from school and get on the skates and go out. And there was one part of the lake that never froze. We would just not pay any attention to it, not even thinking as kids, what is this?''</p>
        <p>The unfrozen section was, they came to find out, where chemicals were being dumped. ''I had a couple of friends die, leukemia,'' she said, ''and it turns out Holbrook was one of the worst Superfund sites in the United States.''</p>
        <p>With this experience as motivation, Ms. Galloway cobbled together $3,000 and used connections through her husband, John, who was a salesman in the same industry. She bought an inventory of environmental cleanup products and went from business to business to sell them.</p>
        <p>To produce her first sales flier, she aped the format of the high school newspaper she served as faculty adviser. To add panache, she took her dog, Murphy, and gave him a fashion makeover, dressing him in a respirator, goggles, a hard hat, boots, taking a picture of him and, finally, making ''Murphy the Safety Dog'' the centerfold of the newspaper cum sales flier.</p>
        <p>Ms. Galloway ran the business out of her home at first, storing products in the basement. Later, she moved to a warehouse in Ossining and then, three years ago, to the Sparrow Lane warehouse. Her husband worked for her part time, but as the business grew he came on board full time ''because his background was in sales and I could trust him.'' She said, however, that ''he's currently on the payroll and I'm the sole stockholder.''</p>
        <p>CG Industrial Safety Products distributes to customers in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut. Its major product is oil pads, which are essentially paper towels used to sop up oil in machine shops, on oil barges, from home oil tanks and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>A tour of the warehouse reveals many other products used to declaw environmental problems: containment booms, which are orange flotation devices used to encircle oil spilled in bodies of water; Poly-Dollys, used to transport drums of hazardous material, and suits made of Tyvek, which aren't exactly the latest word in fashion but shield the wearer from toxic liquids and gasses.</p>
        <p>The Galloways' offices adjoin the warehouse. Besides phones and files and all the other normal tools of business, the offices include an area nearly overtaken by playpens and children's drawings. The entire lower half of a wall has been transformed into a giant chalkboard.</p>
        <p>That is because as they are running the business, the Galloways are also taking care of their two young children. Meghan, 4, is shuttled between the office and nursery school, and Liam, 7 months, spends much of the day there. Inside the office, as business and childhood grind along, you hear a vocabulary of oil spills and nap times, on-time deliveries and nursery school pickups.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon Mr. Galloway was conducting business. ''Send me 24 of them,'' he barked into the phone while bottle feeding Liam on his lap.</p>
        <p>In an age when startup companies are accorded multibillion dollar market capitalizations, CG Industrial Safety Products is a throwback. The big question this year is whether to buy a second truck or upgrade their single, old-as-the-hills computer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Galloway said she competes with bigger national players who have better buying power by ''shopping well'' for her inventory, but she also cuts to the quick: ''We make smaller margins.''</p>
        <p>She also tries to serve her customers better than her competitors. She says she gets customers their products when they need them by ''hook or crook'' and tells of how, a few Christmas Eves ago, a Cape May, N.J., customer needed an emergency delivery so she dropped her daughter off with her mother and said, ''I'll see you in a couple of days.''</p>
        <p>As she spoke at a coffee shop in Peekskill, she was interrupted four times by calls from the office. Each one washed a faint wave of tension across her face.</p>
        <p>After all, in a couple of hours she was to leave for a weekend hiking trip with her family, but there were several business matters to be addressed. Thus pressed for time, she laughed at her once-upon-a-time thought that an entrepreneurial life would grant her more flexibility than teaching. But she enjoys the tumult and says she thrives on solving pulse-racing problems. ''Otherwise,'' she said, ''you wouldn't be alive.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
