<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Puts New Spin On G.O.P. Blueprint</title>
    <meta content="06PLAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FISCAL AGENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D7123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Puts New Spin On G.O.P. Blueprint</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic agenda presented to Republican National Convention and nation on Thursday night by Gov George W Bush sticks closely in many ways to Republican orthodoxy (News Analysis) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The economic agenda presented to the Republican National Convention and the nation on Thursday night by Gov. George W. Bush stuck closely in many ways to Republican orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>Its centerpieces were tax cuts and the creation of personal investment accounts within the Social Security system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The economic agenda presented to the Republican National Convention and the nation on Thursday night by Gov. George W. Bush stuck closely in many ways to Republican orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>Its centerpieces were tax cuts and the creation of personal investment accounts within the Social Security system.</p>
        <p>It emphasized that the solutions to some problems, like the growing numbers of people without health insurance, rested not with government bureaucracy but with the private marketplace. And it promised a budget that would provide more money for the military.</p>
        <p>But there were twists.</p>
        <p>Throughout the convention, the Bush team sought to counter the idea that Republicans stand for sweeping tax cuts that are reckless and a boon only to the country-club set. Tax cuts were showcased in Philadelphia as a prudent way to spur entrepreneurship, help people looking to reach the middle class, and provide an economic pick-me-up should the long business expansion begin to flag.</p>
        <p>Gone was the Republican call to shrink government's size and influence by starving it of revenues. Mr. Bush went so far in his speech as to single out his support for federal programs like Head Start.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most notably, Mr. Bush made clear how he intended to handle one of his trickiest political tasks: making a case against an incumbent vice president whose administration is presiding over an economic boom.</p>
        <p>Rather than ignoring it, or getting into a battle over who deserves the credit, Mr. Bush said the real issue should be what the nation chooses to do with its prosperity.</p>
        <p>''We will use these good times for great goals,'' Mr. Bush said, pledging in particular to ensure the solvency of Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>To some degree, Mr. Bush was trying to do for Republicans on economic policy what President Clinton has done for Democrats.</p>
        <p>By emphasizing elimination of the federal budget deficit and the national debt, Mr. Clinton sought to erase the perception that Democrats were the party of profligacy and high taxes. In the end, doing so gave him more freedom to press for substantially more spending on the issues at the core of the Democratic agenda, especially health and education.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Bush seems intent on dispelling the idea that conservative policy is inconsistent with helping people who have not already made it economically, and his tax plan contains elements specifically intended to help the working poor.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush is by no means apologizing for the fact that his proposals to cut all income tax rates would do what such proposals always do: provide most of their benefits to the people who make the most money.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Bush is certain to draw heavy fire from Vice President Al Gore. Democrats said that the focus in Philadelphia this week on helping single mothers, struggling family farms and Hispanic entrepreneurs was nothing more than camouflage for the usual conservative effort, embodied by the Bush campaign, to reward the wealthy people and powerful interest groups that finance Republican campaigns.</p>
        <p>Worse, they said, Republicans would squander the projected federal budget surpluses and leave nothing for priorities like adding prescription drug coverage to Medicare or modernizing schools.</p>
        <p>Democrats look at the Bush tax plan and see 43 percent of the benefits going to the top 1 percent of households by income, those making more than $319,000 a year, according to Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal-leaning research group.</p>
        <p>Lawrence B. Lindsey, Mr. Bush's chief economic adviser, said Republicans remained focused on the incentives that tax cuts provide to earn and save more, whether for a waitress earning $18,000 a year or the entrepreneur who wants to be able to pass a painstakingly built business along to her heirs without being subject to a hefty federal estate tax.</p>
        <p>After several years in which their agenda seemed to generate little public enthusiasm, Republicans have taken heart from polls showing that support for tax cuts is growing.</p>
        <p>But to the extent that he emphasizes the substance of economic policy, Mr. Bush risks not only inviting an onslaught from Mr. Gore over class politics and fiscal rectitude, but also focusing voters on the fact that the Clinton-Gore years have been pretty good for most people.</p>
        <p>With unemployment at 4 percent, inflation benign and incomes broadly rising, Democrats gathering for their Los Angeles convention this month will no doubt be eager to show that on those counts, Mr. Gore's election would mean more of the same.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FISCAL AGENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
