<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Suitcases on Wheels To Tear-Free Onion Slicers</title>
    <meta content="06INVE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Inventors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Patent and Trademark Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sadow, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DA1F3DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Suitcases on Wheels To Tear-Free Onion Slicers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on independent inventors living in Westchester County, NY, where, according to US Patent and Trademark Office, about 600 inventions a year are developed and patented; some inventors, including Bernard Sadow, who invented luggage on wheels, describe their successful, and not so successful, ideas; photos; (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY all laughed when Edison recorded sound,'' Ira Gershwin wrote in 1937. They also laughed at Bernard Sadow and the funny-looking suitcase on wheels he tugged into Macy's one morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadow and his prototype were ridiculed and rejected by a buyer for Macy's, which carried the conventional luggage Mr. Sadow's company, U.S. Luggage, made.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY all laughed when Edison recorded sound,'' Ira Gershwin wrote in 1937. They also laughed at Bernard Sadow and the funny-looking suitcase on wheels he tugged into Macy's one morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadow and his prototype were ridiculed and rejected by a buyer for Macy's, which carried the conventional luggage Mr. Sadow's company, U.S. Luggage, made.</p>
        <p>But this was 1972, and no one knew from luggage on wheels. Soon, the glum luggage manufacturer found himself wheeling his idea right back out.</p>
        <p>''They said, 'No one's going to pull a suitcase on the end of a strap,' '' Mr. Sadow recalled.</p>
        <p>But two weeks later, he got an appointment with a Macy's vice president who was soon doing just that: towing the suitcase around his office, giggling with glee. He called in the naysaying buyer and, smiling broadly at him, asked: ''So, Jack, what do you think of my new idea?'' recalled Mr. Sadow. ''He looked at me and then back at the boss, and he said, 'Great, I love it.' ''</p>
        <p>The executive told the buyer to buy, and that was the start of wheels on luggage. Mr. Sadow, 75, recalled it all recently in the well-furnished living room of his sprawling Chappaqua home. Besides getting the last laugh, Mr. Sadow still receives licensing fees from manufacturers selling bags using his 1972 patent on rolling luggage.</p>
        <p>''I know they're still selling because I watch the royalty checks coming in,'' Mr. Sadow said.</p>
        <p>Westchester has had a long tradition of inventors. Most of the large corporations in the county, like International Business Machines, keep a stable of inventors on staff to develop technologies and processes. But more and more independent inventors are springing up, setting up shop in basements and garages around the county.</p>
        <p>The county is still known for buttoned-down bankers and lawyers catching the 6:58, not eccentric shock-haired geniuses crying ''Eureka!'' from their workshops.</p>
        <p>But, according to the United States Patent and Trademark Office, about 600 inventions a year are dreamed up in Westchester and patented. In New York State, only Monroe County, where Rochester-based Kodak is situated, had more patents last year at 1,549. By comparison, Manhattan had 533 and Nassau 351.</p>
        <p>Inventors proliferate in areas with large corporations and high-education levels, said Richard J. Apley, director of the office of independent inventor programs for the Patent and Trademark Office.</p>
        <p>Inventing is on the rise for a number of reasons, said Joanne Hayes-Rines, editor and publisher of Inventors' Digest magazine in Boston. The economy is booming, and the Internet provides a marketplace for inventors to sell their devices, as well as an information resource.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Sadow, inspiration came one day in 1971 when he was lugging a large suitcase through customs and a man breezed by towing heavy machinery on a dolly.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Now that's what we need, wheels on luggage,' '' recalled Mr. Sadow, who took the heavy casters from a large trunk and fastened them to the bottom of a suitcase. He tied a rope to it, ''and it worked like a charm,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since then, his inventions include air-cushioned carrying cases for laptop computers, electric toothpicks and training wheels for tipsy suitcases. His latest innovation, a spray dispenser for holy water, now sells for $19.95 at the gift shop at St. Patrick's Cathedral in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Of course, not every inventor is as successful as Mr. Sadow.</p>
        <p>So far, Vince and Patrice Cacciatore of Yonkers have not made any profit from their inventions; not from their toothpaste tube key, nor from their cough drop lollipop for children.</p>
        <p>They are devout Catholics and say they invent in the name of the Lord. They hope their latest inventions hit big, so they can use the profits to rent billboard space for biblical quotations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cacciatore, who owns a copy machine repair service, invented a cardboard platform for take-out pizza boxes, to keep the pies from getting soggy by letting air circulate under the crust.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cacciatore invented memorial picture frames for owners of deceased pets. The pet's photo goes in the front and its crematory ashes go in the rear. The frames, which come in mirror and black acrylic finishes, have just gone on the Internet at a starting price of $18.99. Larger containers for human remains are coming.</p>
        <p>On average, it takes 18 months to get a patent approved. Most applications are prepared by lawyers, who charge an average of $5,000 an application. Costs vary enormously to build a prototype and market it to manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Inventing and then successfully marketing a product are very different things, said Stephen I. Mayo of New Rochelle, who owns Artistic Office Products in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''Some of your best inventions don't sell,'' he said, ''and the least patentable turn out to be best sellers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mayo recently patented two items but wound up marketing only one -- a simple wire device he made to fit as a coat hook over an office cubicle partition. But his innovative retractable wall hook, an idea he got from a clothes hook in an airplane bathroom, never appealed to customers, so he shelved it.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, he said, independent inventors find it more difficult to persuade retailers to carry their products.</p>
        <p>''There's less interest in product innovation because the stakes are huge, and buyers don't want to take chances,'' Mr. Mayo said. ''It's hard to introduce a new item unless you have big money behind you. Buyers don't want a product that's not backed by national advertising.''</p>
        <p>Rachel Kaminsky, a third grader from Ardsley, has not yet sought national advertising for her invention, a device for cutting onions without crying, but she did get national recognition and she is preparing an application for a patent.</p>
        <p>Her ''Dry Eyes'' onion slicer helped her win a $5,000 savings bond in a national contest held this spring by Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company and the National Science Teachers Association, becoming the only finalist from a region that includes New York and several other states (and the youngest in the country).</p>
        <p>Rachel, 8, took an inventing class last fall at her school, the Concord Road Elementary School. She devised the slicer after her mother asked her to help in the kitchen by chopping onions. With her tears came a vow to solve the problem.</p>
        <p>She made a dome out of a clear plastic bowl, attached a circular apple cutter to the bottom and a cloth screen to the top with an attached pouch of baking soda to absorb the onion odor.</p>
        <p>Her mother said Rachel had long created inventions out of household items, like the view-finder she made to teach her little brother left and right.</p>
        <p>As for the slicer, ''We use it all the time,''  Mrs. Kaminsky said. ''She thinks it should be in Lechter's.''</p>
        <p>Despite stories of Nobel Prizes and comfortable fellowships, inventing is tough, tedious work and rarely lives up to its sometimes romantic image.</p>
        <p>''You hear about flashes of brilliance, that's the sexy part,'' said Neil Baldwin, author of ''Edison: Inventing the Century'' (Hyperion Books, 1995). ''But stamina and persistence are as important as creativity.''</p>
        <p>Edison filled 3,000 notebooks with his ideas, Mr. Baldwin said, and he once spent 100 nights in his workshop, staying away from his family at home. His wife often complained about his absence from the dinner table.</p>
        <p>The family of Richard J. Maiaro, an inventor from New Rochelle, knows the feeling. When he is on the verge of a breakthrough idea, he said, ''it weighs on your brain till you come up with a solution.''</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I'll be at the dinner table with my kids, and I'll be in another world,'' he said. ''The next thing I know, my 10-year-old son's looking at me, saying, 'Daddy, Daddy, where are you?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiaro had trouble with his earlier inventions. His idea for an alarm system operated by a remote key-chain switch was rejected by Cadillac. Discouraged, he never patented the idea, which has since become standard in the automobile industry. Then he designed a pen that was easier and cheaper to assemble than the competition's designs, but his silent partner began showing off the design and another manufacturer beat him to the patent and to market.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Maiaro is trying to market two machines he recently invented. One is a machine that prints two colors simultaneously on promotional pens or pencils.</p>
        <p>Printers have long had problems aligning pens correctly to add multiple layers of color, but Mr. Maiaro's machine marks the pen with invisible dye, which is then sensed by a scanner when positioning the pen for additional layers. His machine can print logos on 20,000 pens in eight hours, and he has sold two so far, for $70,000 apiece.</p>
        <p>Last march, he patented a safety apparatus for a weight-lifting bench. The unit extends above the bench press, lifting the barbell with a winch if the user becomes too fatigued.</p>
        <p>The Patent Office said one of the largest groups of applications involves exercise equipment.</p>
        <p>Brian M. Dugan, a patent lawyer from Tarrytown, developed with one of his professors from Yale, Dr. Robert D. Grober, a device to teach golfers proper swing tempo.</p>
        <p>The device is slipped onto the shaft of a golf club, and using an accelerometer, the device emits an even tone when the user is swinging smoothly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dugan has also patented another exercise feedback device, a hand-held computer game based on the user's exertion level during exercise. The more strenuous the workout, the better the computer character kickboxes his way out of captivity.</p>
        <p>But ''you don't have to be a technical genius, or come up with some breakthrough in computer technology to patent a succesful product,'' said Richard C. Wingate, a marketing lawyer for Sony Electronics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wingate, from Scarsdale, invented a wireless headphone set with a retractable microphone, which allows the user to answer the phone while listening to the stereo and television.</p>
        <p>Looking for a headlight for night jogging, he fastened a small halogen penlight to his radio headphones and patented it.</p>
        <p>''It's about having an idea that's useful and that nobody's thought of before you,'' Mr. Wingate said.</p>
        <p>While many part-time inventors dream of doing it full time, some who work in research and development departments for large corporations complain that the patents, and most of the profits, go to the company.</p>
        <p>Joseph R. Infantino worked 30 years for AMF, the sporting goods manufacturer, in its Stamford laboratories as the chief plastics chemist. He regularly met with athletes like Ben Hogan, Guillermo Vilas and Arthur Ashe, discussing the products they endorsed for AMF.</p>
        <p>Mr. Infantino, 67, a lifelong Chappaqua resident, developed equipment like tennis rackets, skis and swim fins. His inventions for bowling alleys brought bowling into the modern era, where perfect games have become commonplace.</p>
        <p>In the late 60's, he used a hard plastic called Surlyn to coat bowling pins, making them livelier and more durable. He also developed the urethane bowling ball, which had superior traction and could be hooked by bowlers to get consistent strikes.</p>
        <p>He patented the inflatable interior used in Head ski boots, a concept now widely used in sneakers, and he patented a florescent bowling pin, now used by alleys for rock 'n' roll bowling.</p>
        <p>In all, he had 16 inventions for AMF, most of which got him a handshake and a $100 bonus, he said.</p>
        <p>''You sign your life away to these big corporations,'' he said, adding that if he had shared in the profits, ''I'd be on the Italian Riviera right now.''</p>
        <p>Now he applies for his own patents and sells licensing rights to AMF.</p>
        <p>In the cramped basement boiler room, crowded by boxes of pasta and cans of Campbell's soup, he works on improving bowling pins. He recently patented an improved method to adhere hard covers to the pins, which he is licensing to AMF for a six-figure payment.</p>
        <p>Another corporate defector is Steven Linder, the self-proclaimed ''king of inflatable furniture'' and a former executive with the Ethan Allen furniture company.</p>
        <p>Seeing inflatable cushions and seats that ''were more like blobs,'' Mr. Linder designed a fully inflatable armchair and patented it in 1994, starting an inflatable furniture fad that pervaded college dormitories, tailgate parties and the living rooms of armchair quarterbacks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linder's Purchase-based Sterling Promotions company sells the chairs, which usually bear the logos of professional sports teams or beer companies.</p>
        <p>His Dallas Cowboys ottoman, that doubles as an ice chest, and the Britney Spears armchair, are both evidence that inventions need not be groundbreaking contributions to modern science to sell.</p>
        <p>With nine patents for inflatable furniture,  Mr. Linder, 52, proudly boasts, ''I've taken inflatable furniture to another level.''</p>
        <p>A Stable Full of Chemists, Physicists and Scientists</p>
        <p>Most companies that deal in intellectual property keep large stables of inventors. Three of the state's top four patent recipients -- I.B.M., Xerox and General Electric -- have large offices in Westchester.</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s Thomas J. Watson Research Center, the company's largest laboratory, occupies three buildings in Yorktown Heights and Hawthorne. Many innovations in information technology have come from the Watson labs, from semiconductor technology to the first ''super computers'' to the software that runs E-commerce systems.</p>
        <p>The center's research and development staff includes 1,400 inventors -- chemists, physicists and computer scientists -- said Paul M. Horn, chief inventor for I.B.M.</p>
        <p>The company spends roughly $6 billion annually on research and development worldwide and last year earned $1.3 billion from licensing fees. It has produced five Nobel prize winners and more patents than any other company in the world, Mr. Horn said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
