<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Free-Agent Market, It's 'Wait Till Next Year'</title>
    <meta content="06NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DE133CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Free-Agent Market, It's 'Wait Till Next Year'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses free-agent signings and trades that have taken place, and speculates on fate of few players who have not yet signed contracts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The money is dwindling fast. With one nine-player trade down and apparently none to go, many of the alleged blockbuster deals are being committed to rumor. Solid but unspectacular free agents like Danny Fortson and Aaron Williams have been given presidential suites by teams hoping to procure their services for minimal charge.</p>
        <p>The members of the Great Free Agent Class of 2000 have almost all been signed -- including Williams, who agreed to terms with the Nets on Friday -- and the Chicago Bulls are still wondering where everyone went and why they had to settle on Ron Mercer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The money is dwindling fast. With one nine-player trade down and apparently none to go, many of the alleged blockbuster deals are being committed to rumor. Solid but unspectacular free agents like Danny Fortson and Aaron Williams have been given presidential suites by teams hoping to procure their services for minimal charge.</p>
        <p>The members of the Great Free Agent Class of 2000 have almost all been signed -- including Williams, who agreed to terms with the Nets on Friday -- and the Chicago Bulls are still wondering where everyone went and why they had to settle on Ron Mercer.</p>
        <p>But Jerry Krause can take heart. If Michael Jordan's old team does not pull off a monster swap, survives yet another season of fan backlash and saves its millions, the class of 2001 has much to offer.</p>
        <p>Chris Webber, Dikembe Mutombo, Michael Finley and Antonio Davis will have opportunities to be free agents. Depending on whether several players opt out of deals, there are also Anthony Mason, Tyrone Hill, Corliss Williamson and Jerome Williams to add to the Bulls' talent-challenged roster.</p>
        <p>If Washington buys out Rod Strickland over the last year of his deal in 2001-2, he would be a free agent going into next season.</p>
        <p>Several players are still on the market this summer, but not all may take the $2.25 million exception being offered by teams. According to a Pacific Division executive, who spoke on condition of anonymity, many player agents are telling general managers to find more creative ways to sign their clients -- given that the exception will most likely balloon to $4.5 million next season.</p>
        <p>With annual allowed increases, a contract beginning at that number could turn into a multiyear, $30 million deal next season. That means instead of Fortson or Williams, the exception could go to a free agent next season like Shandon Anderson, Doug Christie or Christian Laettner.</p>
        <p>Other possible 2001 free agents who could secure those kind of deals include Shawn Bradley, Erick Strickland, Bryan Stith, Chris Gatling, Clarence Weatherspoon, Anthony Carter, Aaron McKie, Malik Rose or Grant Long.</p>
        <p>Players will actually be weighing their contract offers from their current clubs against a midlevel exception, so it may be harder for teams to hold on to their best role players.</p>
        <p>At any rate, Webber is going to reap the largest reward. For everyone who decried the end of the $100 million deal, well, it's back.</p>
        <p>The salary cap will most likely be $42 million to $44 million next season. A player like Webber, the All-Star Kings forward, can receive 30 percent of his team's salary cap based on his experience level of seven to nine years.</p>
        <p>If the cap were $42 million, Webber could receive $12.6 million his first season. With annual raises, a maximum deal would total out to $120.9 million over six years if he stayed with Sacramento. That is $6 million less than Kevin Garnett's record deal signed in 1997, the one that infuriated owners before the lockout in 1998.</p>
        <p>The Dust Settles</p>
        <p>Grant Hill and Tracy McGrady smiled gleefully for the cameras the other day, donning their new pinstriped Orlando Magic jerseys and putting the focus back on the Magic four years after Shaq migrated to Los Angeles and left the franchise reeling.</p>
        <p>Signing Hill, arguably the most accomplished all-around player in the game, and McGrady, one of the N.B.A.'s rising stars, was a nice coup, replete with all the attention deserving of the day.</p>
        <p>In Charlotte and Miami, they were also parading their new players. Eddie Jones and Anthony Mason made Miami Coach Pat Riley smile the same way acquiring Jamal Mashburn and P. J. Brown made Charlotte Coach Paul Silas happy -- a nine-player deal both sides deemed fair.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in San Antonio, the Spurs put the finishing touches on acquiring Derek Anderson. Quietly, the 1999 N.B.A. champions reloaded. Among 29 teams searching to stay on top or improve, they may end up as the real winners of the off-season.</p>
        <p>Filling a huge hole at shooting guard with the best free agent left on the market, they persuaded Anderson, 26, to play for $2.25 million next season. Anderson, who is 6 feet 5 inches, averaged 16.9 points, 4.0 rebounds and 3.4 assists a game in 64 games for the Clippers last season.</p>
        <p>He is a definite upgrade from Mario Elie, whom the Spurs will now probably let go via free agency.</p>
        <p>What is more, San Antonio signed the one player they could not lose, Tim Duncan, for three years and $33 million with a fourth-year option. They also kept two other important pieces to the puzzle, the aging Avery Johnson and the emerging Antonio Daniels.</p>
        <p>In a whirlwind week, the Spurs inched closer to the Lakers and Blazers. Persuading a young player like Anderson to play for an instant contender rather than accept a sign-and-trade deal from the Clippers to Denver was key.</p>
        <p>Last week Mark Bartelstein, agent for the Blazers forward Brian Grant, was trying to portray his client's decision to turn down a $90 million sign-and-trade deal that would have sent him to Cleveland as noble.</p>
        <p>''I think this speaks volumes about the man,'' Bartelstein said. ''It's incredibly unbelievable, in this day and age, for an athlete to say so strongly, 'It's not about the money.' ''</p>
        <p>Let's be clear on this: Grant did not turn down the money as much as he turned down the notion of playing for the Cavaliers, who wanted to break their ties with Shawn Kemp more than they wanted Grant.</p>
        <p>Unless the Blazers find a team for him soon, Grant's decision to opt out of a deal still worth more than $40 million may go down as one of the biggest blunders of the off-season -- up there with the Bulls' ending up with Ron Mercer and millions still to spend on players who rejected them.</p>
        <p>Or maybe Bartelstein should be given the benefit of the doubt. A long list of elite teams still have the midlevel exception left to sign a player, a contract worth $2.25 million next year. If Grant and his agent are truly unconcerned with the money, they will leap at an opportunity to contend for a championship.</p>
        <p>Jerry West Retiring</p>
        <p>Jerry West is expected to quit tomorrow as team president of the Lakers. Though he may remain as a team consultant, a four-decade relationship between a player and a club will most likely come to an end.</p>
        <p>Mitch Kupchak, the general manager, will succeed West. And Coach Phil Jackson will most likely have more input on personnel decisions.</p>
        <p>Few American sports executives can claim the success of West, just as few Hall of Famers can claim the playing success of West. He won one championship as a player and six as an executive.</p>
        <p>When he was not lofting a half-court shot that found the net in the finals or earning the moniker Mr. Clutch during his consummate playing career, he was taking weighty risks in the front office -- risks that paid off miraculously. Clearing salary-cap room by unloading a multitude of players during the summer of 1996, West gutted the Lakers in pursuit of Shaquille O'Neal, even when it was unclear whether O'Neal would return to Orlando.</p>
        <p>He kept the Showtime Lakers purring and eventually rebuilt the franchise with wunderkinds like Shaq and Kobe Bryant.</p>
        <p>His health prevented West from attending games this past season. Once the coolest of customers on the floor, his nerves can no longer take the tension of a tight game.</p>
        <p>With all due respect to Rod Thorn and Hot Rod Hundley, here's hoping West Virginia's greatest ballplayer can find joy in the game again, that Zeke from Cabin Creek makes the transition to retirement more peacefully than fitfully.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
