<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footnotes</title>
    <meta content="06FOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waters, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DD113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footnotes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Morris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Footnotes: cites resources, references and the back story behind article on John Waters (M)3</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1a. Baltimore: Babe Ruth, Billie Holiday, Spiro Agnew and ''The Star Spangled Banner'' were born there. Edgar Allen Poe died there. And John Waters still rules there. He has stuck by his town with a vengeance, conceiving all of his films -- Female Trouble,'' ''Hairspray,'' etc. -- for their Baltimore locations. ''It's a city that always inspires me,'' says Waters, who once dubbed it ''the hairdo capital of the world.'' (b) Products like Bumble &amp; Bumble Hairspray ($9 at Bumble &amp; Bumble, 146 East 56th Street) help build the beehive and artichoke styles that adorn Waters's heroines.  2. Waters wrote his latest opus, ''Cecil B. DeMented,'' with the old movie theaters of Baltimore in mind. In a case of life mirroring art mirroring life, he shot its opening scene, a premiere gone haywire, at the Senator Theater; ''DeMented'' had its world premiere (benefiting AIDS Action Baltimore) there on Wednesday. As a boy, Waters attended birthday parties at this Art Deco landmark, where he saw ''The Wizard of Oz'' for the first time. ''Winged monkeys, a gay lion, great shoes,'' he says. ''I never understood why Dorothy wanted to go home.'' 5904 York Road, Baltimore, (410) 435-8338.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1a. Baltimore: Babe Ruth, Billie Holiday, Spiro Agnew and ''The Star Spangled Banner'' were born there. Edgar Allen Poe died there. And John Waters still rules there. He has stuck by his town with a vengeance, conceiving all of his films -- Female Trouble,'' ''Hairspray,'' etc. -- for their Baltimore locations. ''It's a city that always inspires me,'' says Waters, who once dubbed it ''the hairdo capital of the world.'' (b) Products like Bumble &amp; Bumble Hairspray ($9 at Bumble &amp; Bumble, 146 East 56th Street) help build the beehive and artichoke styles that adorn Waters's heroines.  2. Waters wrote his latest opus, ''Cecil B. DeMented,'' with the old movie theaters of Baltimore in mind. In a case of life mirroring art mirroring life, he shot its opening scene, a premiere gone haywire, at the Senator Theater; ''DeMented'' had its world premiere (benefiting AIDS Action Baltimore) there on Wednesday. As a boy, Waters attended birthday parties at this Art Deco landmark, where he saw ''The Wizard of Oz'' for the first time. ''Winged monkeys, a gay lion, great shoes,'' he says. ''I never understood why Dorothy wanted to go home.'' 5904 York Road, Baltimore, (410) 435-8338.</p>
        <p>3. Baltimore's Harris Glenn Milstead, aka Divine, who died in 1988 at the age of 42, was Waters's most famous actor. This 20-foot statue of the cross-dressing diva -- in ''Pink Flamingos'' she described herself as ''the filthiest person alive'' -- by Andrew Logan, is from the American Visionary Art Museum, which features nave and outsider art. Call (410) 244-1900 for information.  4. Waters, known for his avant-garde taste in art, also loves Comme des Gar--&gt;ons, the equally avant-garde clothing company run by Rei Kawakubo, who featured this suit in her fall 2000 show. (Jacket, $1,240, pants, $700, and shirt, $280. At Barneys New York.) ''She's the wittiest designer working in fashion,'' says Waters, who wore Comme des Gar--&gt;ons to our photo session, at which Terry Richardson shot exclusively with a Kodak Instamatic.  5. Baltimore is celebrated for its crabs and Chesapeake oysters, and some of the best are sold at Faidley's Seafood in the Lexington Market. The extras in one ''DeMented'' party scene were forced to slurp these oysters down, like them or not. One actress argued that she was a vegetarian. ''I told her I didn't see a face on that oyster and to eat it,'' Waters says. Another actor gagged, ''but was polite enough not to spit up anything until we finished the take, although it would have been nice to have filmed it.''  6. Waters's movie ''Pecker'' showcases Baltimore's famed row houses. Many were covered with Formstone, a synthetic material regarded as even more downscale than aluminum siding. ''For a while, the yuppies buying those houses were taking the Formstone off,'' Waters says. ''Now, in a misguided attempt at authenticity, they're putting it back.''  7. Bengies, in East Baltimore, is one of 520 drive-in theaters left in America and has been in D. Edward Vogel's family since 1956. ''I believe in drive-ins, and this one is a beauty,'' he says proudly. See for yourself at 3417 Eastern Boulevard, (410) 687-5627.  8. If Baltimore's King of Bad Taste is John Waters, its Emperor of Mainstream is the director Barry Levinson, another son of the city. Levinson -- pictured with his ''Liberty Heights'' stars, Adrien Brody and Carolyn Murphy, at the 92-year-old Country Corner Diner in the Baltimore suburbs -- not only set his recent TV series, ''Homicide,'' in Baltimore but also his films ''Diner,'' ''Avalon,'' ''Tin Men'' and the aforementioned ''Liberty Heights.'' Recently he noted, ''Whenever something is about Baltimore, it gets sent to me.'' One exception, of course: when that something is by John Waters .</p>
        <p>-- Text by Bob Morris</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
