<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bookend; Giveaways</title>
    <meta content="06BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prose, Francine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DF163DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bookend; Giveaways</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Francine Prose</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prose, Francine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Francine Prose (Bookend) column decries penchant of book reviewers to reveal plots, thus spoiling it for readers and other reviewers; holds that while it is difficult to give reader sense of book and its characters without doing so, plot can be comprehensibly conveyed while sidestepping central chain of events; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The one real perk of book reviewing is the chance to read a novel early, in a state of innocent grace -- that is, before the flurry of reviews in which your fellow critics ruin the novel for you by revealing its entire plot. Anyone who enjoys fiction (not only mysteries and thrillers, but literary fiction) partly for the pleasure of finding out what happens next, as well as any writer who writes at least partly for such rapt and dedicated readers, will doubtless have noticed that an increasing percentage of book reviews have found a foolproof way (paragraph after paragraph dutifully retelling the narrative from beginning to end) of making sure that the reader will never enjoy that particular pleasure.</p>
        <p>Such gloomy thoughts naturally collected around the recent publication of Philip Roth's novel ''The Human Stain,'' which contains a hairpin-sharp plot turn that -- in case there is one reader somewhere who hasn't yet heard -- I'll try not to disclose. It may well be true that, as many critics and writers (including, apparently, Roth) have claimed, it is impossible to write meaningfully about the novel without revealing its secret. Be that as it may, it must be said that the experience of reading the book is utterly different depending on whether we already know its surprise (having read about it in the morning paper) or whether we figure it out at the moment that the author presumably intended us to -- and at that point suffer the dislocation, the confusion and the subsequent sense of everything falling into place that so accurately mimics our response to the discovery, in life, of a life-changing secret.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The one real perk of book reviewing is the chance to read a novel early, in a state of innocent grace -- that is, before the flurry of reviews in which your fellow critics ruin the novel for you by revealing its entire plot. Anyone who enjoys fiction (not only mysteries and thrillers, but literary fiction) partly for the pleasure of finding out what happens next, as well as any writer who writes at least partly for such rapt and dedicated readers, will doubtless have noticed that an increasing percentage of book reviews have found a foolproof way (paragraph after paragraph dutifully retelling the narrative from beginning to end) of making sure that the reader will never enjoy that particular pleasure.</p>
        <p>Such gloomy thoughts naturally collected around the recent publication of Philip Roth's novel ''The Human Stain,'' which contains a hairpin-sharp plot turn that -- in case there is one reader somewhere who hasn't yet heard -- I'll try not to disclose. It may well be true that, as many critics and writers (including, apparently, Roth) have claimed, it is impossible to write meaningfully about the novel without revealing its secret. Be that as it may, it must be said that the experience of reading the book is utterly different depending on whether we already know its surprise (having read about it in the morning paper) or whether we figure it out at the moment that the author presumably intended us to -- and at that point suffer the dislocation, the confusion and the subsequent sense of everything falling into place that so accurately mimics our response to the discovery, in life, of a life-changing secret.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, writers have steeled themselves to greet reviews of their books with gratitude for the praise, if there is any, and the resolve not to mind terribly if the plot twists they've worked so hard to construct are already known to potential readers, who now may feel understandably less inclined to pick up the novel. Skimming these necessarily reductive forced marches through your entire narrative feels rather like watching someone assemble your loved ones, a couple of days before Christmas, and gleefully describe the contents of their gifts, still brightly wrapped beneath the tree. Having just published a novel to which, I imagined, the reader would be drawn partly by curiosity about what was going to occur between a man and a woman -- pulled along, as Chekhov termed it, by ''the engine of he and she'' -- my heart sank each time a critic breezily confided, in anatomical detail, exactly what takes place in the critical scene between the lovers.</p>
        <p>More and more often, we read book reviews that are almost entirely plot summaries with a few adjectives of approval or blame thrown in for punctuation. Of course, this approach has its uses. Such reviews are a godsend to the lazy writer, who can sprint along in the author's footsteps, rapidly cranking out the required number of words without troubling much about the more challenging demands of critical thinking. They also rescue the desperate (as I have been) critic, who is struggling to safeguard the tender feelings of a wobbly first novelist and who knows that recounting the plot is the best, perhaps the only, way to signal readers with a taste for just that sort of wobbly first novel. Finally, such pieces are a boon to those who want to be able to discuss the popular new novel, at length and with strongly held opinions, without having wasted the time required to actually read it.</p>
        <p>But such reviews are not useful to the culture, or to the health of the novel. They cannot fail to transmit mixed messages about, among other things, the role of plot in fiction; they imply that plot is the only important aspect of the novel (after all, it's the only thing in the review) and that, paradoxically, plot has absolutely no significance, since it's not supposed to matter if we know the whole story from the outset. Such essays invade the connection between writer and reader, erode the reader's expectation of surprise, as well as the writer's desire to surprise, and confuse us about what is meant to be interesting or amusing about fiction -- and all of this at a cultural moment when, we hear, fewer readers are clear about why anyone would want to read literary fiction in the first place. Writers might, in the future, think twice before including any plot turns that they don't want the world to know in advance, or, alternately, might gravitate toward narratives so Dickensian or Joycean that retelling them is harder than finding another way to talk about the novel. No ordinary review could accommodate the plot of ''Our Mutual Friend,'' and the experience of reading ''Ulysses'' would not be altered much by learning that it was about a man's peregrinations around Dublin.</p>
        <p>But isn't it the critic's job to give the reader a sense of the book, of its characters and their milieu, of what it's about? Of course it is, and moreover, it's difficult to conduct a substantive or even intelligible literary discussion without reference to the basic elements that distinguish one narrative from another. Still, it's one thing to say that ''Anna Karenina'' (to take a masterpiece in which psychological profundity piques our curiosity about the novel's outcome) concerns a complex, restless Russian woman whose adulterous passion for an unreliable young aristocrat damages her family, herself and the society around her. It is quite another to detail the slow, inexorable, reluctant steps by which our heroine separates from her husband and her beloved son, attaches herself to the shiftless Prince Vronsky, suffers ostracism and disgrace -- until at last she flings herself under the wheels of an onrushing train.</p>
        <p>But if we cut back on plot summary, what will we critics do with all that space to fill on the page, all those paragraphs that we can no longer pad with quotations culled from the moments at which the novel reaches some crucial juncture? Consolingly, we may discover that the subject of a novel -- its themes, the issues it raises and addresses, what the book suggests about its characters and their world and how all of that reflects on our world -- can be comprehensibly conveyed with only a bit of nimble sidestepping around the central chain of events. In fact, the best reviews (the sort that the novelist is genuinely happy to receive) tell precisely as much of the plot as is required to communicate its substance, and do so with an eloquence and witty intelligence that actually seem to rub off on, and add luster to, the book itself.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, all those newly freed-up column inches (once occupied by plot summary) may give us room to talk more about language, about how a book is written -- a topic that is more and more likely to be ignored in the movement toward the all-plot review. As a reader whose interest in Philip Roth's sentence structure, his word choice, his ability to raise language to the ideal temperature (not too hot, not too cold) for expressing his passions and rages equals or surpasses her interest in his political ideas, I lately found myself lamenting the extent to which such matters have faded from our literary conversation.</p>
        <p>Even more radically, we might consider abandoning altogether the increasingly rigid and claustrophobic form that the most egregious critical essays have assumed, with their predictable recipe (5-10 percent introduction, 80-90 percent plot summary, 5-10 percent conclusion), and, if we are serious about our jobs, approach each novel as it should be approached, with the energy and resolve to figure out what has most fully engaged the writer, and center the review on that. Such determination would influence and shift our focus to (among other profitable avenues of inquiry) the ways in which a first-rate novel's form reflects its intentions.</p>
        <p>Like most ordinary civilians, film critics generally know better than to claim that a movie is suspenseful and then promptly to disclose its ending. Only book reviewers, it seems, are permitted this essential failure of the imagination: the failure to imagine how a writer might wish a novel to affect the reader, or to intuit how certain sorts of information will interfere with the reader's experience of a book. And shouldn't this fundamental deficiency -- the inability to understand this primary aspect of the intimate transaction that occurs between writer and reader, the refusal to recognize one of the simplest pleasures afforded by the act of reading -- disqualify the critic as an authority capable of passing judgment on a novel's ambitions, and on how well it succeeds? How can we trust the opinions of those who give us easy, unhelpful, overly detailed plot summaries instead of undertaking the more difficult search for answers to the most important and essential questions: What makes great art so exhilarating? Why is bad literature so depressing? And why do we, despite everything, keep believing and insisting that there is a difference, and that the difference matters?</p>
        <p>Francine Prose's most recent novel is ''Blue Angel.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Francine Prose's most recent novel is ''Blue Angel.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
