<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Defense of a Moratorium On Oyster Bay Land</title>
    <meta content="LTR231418" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oyster Bay (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisler, Bonnie (Councilwoman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macagnone, Anthony (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D8153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Defense of a Moratorium On Oyster Bay Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Councilwoman Bonnie Eisler letter responds to Councilman Anthony Macagnone's July 30 letter criticizing call for limited moratorium on development of land in special groundwater protection area in Oyster Bay, Long Island (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I am writing in response to Councilman Anthony Macagnone's letter [July 30] criticizing my call for a limited moratorium on development of land in the special groundwater protection area in Oyster Bay.</p>
        <p>We elected officials have a moral obligation to take whatever steps are necessary to guarantee pure drinking water. Unfortunately, Oyster Bay has not kept pace with other towns on Long Island in protecting environmentally sensitive land from overdevelopment. The recent court decision criticizing the town for failing to conduct even the most cursory environmental review before rezoning the Underhill property, which is within the groundwater protection area, and the Town Board's decision to sell 50-plus acres of town-owned land in the protected area for development of more than 350 housing units, only underscore the point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I am writing in response to Councilman Anthony Macagnone's letter [July 30] criticizing my call for a limited moratorium on development of land in the special groundwater protection area in Oyster Bay.</p>
        <p>We elected officials have a moral obligation to take whatever steps are necessary to guarantee pure drinking water. Unfortunately, Oyster Bay has not kept pace with other towns on Long Island in protecting environmentally sensitive land from overdevelopment. The recent court decision criticizing the town for failing to conduct even the most cursory environmental review before rezoning the Underhill property, which is within the groundwater protection area, and the Town Board's decision to sell 50-plus acres of town-owned land in the protected area for development of more than 350 housing units, only underscore the point.</p>
        <p>The town's Department of Planning and Development and Environmental Quality Review Commission look at projects piecemeal and never consider the cumulative impact of approving project after project. And site plan review, which was enacted to give the Town Board greater control over the aesthetics of a project, like lighting, landscaping and signs, does nothing to strengthen the board's hand when it comes to protecting the environment or our precious drinking water supply.</p>
        <p>My call for a limited moratorium is consistent with current mainstream governmental policy throughout Long Island, including the Town of Oyster Bay. Last year, Oyster Bay adopted a moratorium on new building permits in Greenvale to give the town an opportunity to address the threat of overdevelopment in that area. Councilman Macagnone, along with the rest of the Town Board, voted in February in favor of a six-month extension of that moratorium.</p>
        <p>I have long been a vocal proponent of the concept of ''smart growth'' to ensure economic expansion while combatting the overdevelopment and suburban sprawl that now plague us.</p>
        <p>Given that the proposed moratorium is limited in both geographic scope and duration, adopting it and the other components of a comprehensive groundwater management plan would not create a financial hardship but would finally allow the town to chart a course that would benefit everyone in the long term.</p>
        <p>BONNIE EISLER  Councilwoman  Town of Oyster Bay</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
