<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Worst to First</title>
    <meta content="06SUN3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DC123CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Worst to First</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on rise of MetroStars from Major League Soccer laughingstock to a dominant power</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While most New York fans have been focusing on the pennant runs of the Yankees and the Mets, those who have ventured to Giants Stadium this spring and summer have been treated to an even more stirring drama. That is where the MetroStars, the area's entry in Major League Soccer, have pulled off one of the most heartening turnarounds in recent local sports history. The MetroStars have gone from league laughingstock to a dominant power. Going into this season's final stretch, the team holds a commanding lead in its Eastern Division.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars' odyssey from worst to first may not yet be the talk of the office water cooler. This is, after all, a game still capable of driving traditional American fans to despair with limited scoring and the occasional 0-0 tie. But the MetroStars have averaged 17,674 fans a game this season, the second-highest number in the five-year-old  league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While most New York fans have been focusing on the pennant runs of the Yankees and the Mets, those who have ventured to Giants Stadium this spring and summer have been treated to an even more stirring drama. That is where the MetroStars, the area's entry in Major League Soccer, have pulled off one of the most heartening turnarounds in recent local sports history. The MetroStars have gone from league laughingstock to a dominant power. Going into this season's final stretch, the team holds a commanding lead in its Eastern Division.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars' odyssey from worst to first may not yet be the talk of the office water cooler. This is, after all, a game still capable of driving traditional American fans to despair with limited scoring and the occasional 0-0 tie. But the MetroStars have averaged 17,674 fans a game this season, the second-highest number in the five-year-old  league.</p>
        <p>Soccer at Giants Stadium is a festival of diversity, with bilingual public announcements and an intermingling of suburban soccer families, European expats wearing Manchester United or Inter Milan jerseys, and members of the Colombian diaspora who come to cheer on their compatriot, Adolfo (El Tren) Valencia, the team's leading scorer.</p>
        <p>Sadly, the MetroStars may be better known in Germany than they are locally, thanks to the acquisition of the legendary German defender Lothar Matthaus. The 39-year-old player has been injured much of the season, but his arrival in New York this spring put the league on the map, not to mention on German TV.</p>
        <p>Matthaus is more the exception than the rule.  Unlike the former Cosmos of the deceased North American Soccer League, the MetroStars rely on a core of talented young American players like Mark Chung, Petter Villegas, Clint Mathis and Mike Petke.</p>
        <p>For those fans who need a crosstown rivalry to get the blood boiling, help may be on the way. MetroStars' investors, John Kluge and Stuart Subotnick, have exercised their option for an expansion team in the 2002 season. Both Queens and Long Island are among the sites being considered.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
