<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gas Giant Bets Heavily On a Surge In Demand</title>
    <meta content="06OIL.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anadarko Petroleum Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DC153CF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gas Giant Bets Heavily On a Surge In Demand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anadarko Petroleum Corp prepares to profit greatly from tightened supplies of natural gas and the price hikes this would cause; photo, graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILL natural gas prices stay high? Consumers hope not, but the Anadarko Petroleum Corporation, for one, is betting that they will.</p>
        <p>Prices at the wellhead have leapt 80 percent this year, to more than $4 per million British thermal units. Further, if colder temperatures return after the unseasonably warm winters of the last few years, supplies could be squeezed tighter, sending prices even higher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILL natural gas prices stay high? Consumers hope not, but the Anadarko Petroleum Corporation, for one, is betting that they will.</p>
        <p>Prices at the wellhead have leapt 80 percent this year, to more than $4 per million British thermal units. Further, if colder temperatures return after the unseasonably warm winters of the last few years, supplies could be squeezed tighter, sending prices even higher.</p>
        <p>But that may be just the start, contend executives at Anadarko, one of the largest independent oil and gas producers. They and a number of other producers and analysts say a fundamental shift in the natural-gas market has brought permanently higher prices. They cite soaring demand from new electricity generation plants, after years of weak overall consumption.</p>
        <p>Anadarko is making a huge bet on this thesis. The company, based in Houston, has just acquired Union Pacific Resources for almost $6 billion, gaining drilling rights in gas-rich western Canada and elsewhere. And last week, it announced that it would raise capital spending this year to $1.5 billion, one-third more than earlier projections.</p>
        <p>Investors were not impressed when the Union Pacific deal was announced in April, but they have come around. Anadarko shares are now up more than 40 percent for the year. At $49, they are trading at about 12 times the $4 a share that Robert J. Allison Jr., Anadarko's chief executive, expects the company to earn over the next year.</p>
        <p>''There just isn't enough supply, or enough supply excess, to get soft gas prices again,'' Mr. Allison said in an interview last week. A severe winter will cause spot shortages, he predicts, potentially causing prices to hit $7 early next year.</p>
        <p>William Featherston, an analyst at PaineWebber, says a group of 15 gas producers he tracks are expected to post a 75 percent gain in discretionary cash flow -- net income plus depreciation and deferred taxes -- to $9 billion this year.</p>
        <p>Yet even strong fundamentals are subject to the whimsy of investors, whose appetite for technology stocks hurt valuations of old-economy stocks in recent years. Lately, the shares of some big exploration and production companies have moved almost inversely with the Nasdaq index, rising as the index has fallen. Even so, some analysts say they have much further to go. ''The stocks are reflecting $2.50 gas,'' Mr. Featherston said. ''It's a real disconnect.''</p>
        <p>Often found in the same fields as oil, natural gas has far different economics. By and large, it cannot be transported like oil -- some is liquefied overseas and shipped to the United States, but it is very expensive to do that -- so the United States gets nearly all its gas from North America. It is moved around the country through pipelines, mostly from places like the Gulf of Mexico, Canada, Texas and Oklahoma.</p>
        <p>For this reason, natural gas has little OPEC risk, and prices are much more closely tied to pure supply-and-demand forces than to political decisions made half a world away. But that also means that the United States cannot browbeat foreign producers into higher production when prices rise, as it has sometimes done with oil.</p>
        <p>''Oil markets are global, but the gas market is continental,'' said Tom Robinson, a managing director at Cambridge Energy Research Associates, a consulting and research firm in Cambridge, Mass. ''Producers tend to be full out into the market, and what that means is that no reserves can be turned on when the market gets tight.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, some developments could cause prices to fall. A recession, for example, would check demand. Should oil prices drop, some industrial users would switch to other fuels. And if the industry were to raise exploration spending substantially, supplies could rise, putting pressure on prices. That has not happened yet, although there are now 772 active gas rigs working in the United States, an increase of more than 50 percent from a year earlier, according to Baker Hughes Inc.</p>
        <p>But in the near term, prices could go higher simply because there may not be enough gas in storage. Last year, winter demand caused gas stocks to fall from three  trillion cubic feet in November to one trillion in April, and that was during one of the warmest winters on record.</p>
        <p>Today, however, gas stores are already 18 percent lower than last year, and analysts forecast that stocks may not reach more than 2.7 trillion cubic feet by November. Another warm winter could be enough to leave inventories lean by early next year, but normal winter temperatures could raise demand by 100 billion cubic feet or more a month, cutting deeply into storage, Mr. Robinson said. ''There is a rude awakening coming,'' he said, for homeowners in the Northeast, where annual gas bills will average $200 higher.</p>
        <p>Supplies are tight now partly because demand was unusually soft until recently,  lulling the market into complacency. Warm winters played a role, but there were other factors. The Asian recession affected American industry's gas use. Low oil prices -- before OPEC moved last year to curtail production -- made other fuels cheap alternatives. Oil and gas companies held back from new investment in production in response to pressure from Wall Street to use cash flow to pay off debt. Domestic gas production has actually dropped slightly in the last few years, analysts say.</p>
        <p>But now, demand is rising, oil prices are high, and mass layoffs from the industry's shakeout two years ago have helped create a labor shortage that has somewhat constrained drilling. Even more important is the new demand created by utilities and independent power producers scrambling to build plants to supply electricity to regions running short of power. With coal and nuclear power out of favor, almost all of the new electricity generation plants are gas-fired.</p>
        <p>The National Petroleum Council, a group of industry officials who advise the secretary of energy, expects annual demand in the United States to rise to 29 trillion cubic feet over the next decade, compared with 22 trillion this year.</p>
        <p>So far, imports from Canada, liquefied natural gas from overseas and depletion of gas in storage have made up the gap between domestic production and demand.  But what about future demand? Proven reserves in the United States are about 160 trillion cubic feet, and those have started to fall. New technologies have allowed producers to pump more gas out of existing properties, but by and large the nation's gas fields are maturing, and it is becoming harder, and more expensive, to find more gas.</p>
        <p>Industry executives, including Mr. Allison of Anadarko, argue that if federal officials allowed more drilling in places that are off limits, including certain parts of Alaska and offshore sites in most of the lower 48 states, reserves might double eventually. Otherwise, he said, ''you can only squeeze the oil fields so far.''</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
