<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ugandan Villagers Avoiding Cult Massacre Site</title>
    <meta content="Y06UGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Uganda</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kanungu (Uganda)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Movement for the Restoration of the Ten Commandments of God</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Uganda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Uganda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DD1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ugandan Villagers Avoiding Cult Massacre Site</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>KANUNGU, Uganda</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Kanungu, Uganda, are avoiding compound where hundreds of members of religious sect, Movement for the Restoration of the Ten Commandments of God, were murdered in March; circumstances surrounding deaths still remain mystery; death toll put at 780; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Round the clock, two guards patrol the empty cult compound here, but they are not very busy: few people are brave enough to see the place that spawned one of the largest cult killings in history.</p>
        <p>It looks the same as it did nearly four months ago when 330 bodies, only the first, were found incinerated here. The stench from the pit latrine is still fresh and terrible, so much so that people believe there are many more bodies down there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Round the clock, two guards patrol the empty cult compound here, but they are not very busy: few people are brave enough to see the place that spawned one of the largest cult killings in history.</p>
        <p>It looks the same as it did nearly four months ago when 330 bodies, only the first, were found incinerated here. The stench from the pit latrine is still fresh and terrible, so much so that people believe there are many more bodies down there.</p>
        <p>''No one knows,'' said Edison Byamukama, 34, who watches the compound with an automatic rifle. ''But there is still bad smelling.''</p>
        <p>The Ugandan police said they had looked again in the latrine, where six corpses were found in March, but it was empty. The smell remains a mystery, like nearly everything about the Movement for the Restoration of the Ten Commandments of God, which promised the end of the world but delivered only for its 780 victims.</p>
        <p>It is a mystery that has been particularly difficult for the people of Kanungu, a rough seven-hour drive southwest of the capital, Kampala.</p>
        <p>Few of the dead were from here, mostly because the cult's high priestess, Credonia Mwerinde, was a local girl known better in her youth as a prostitute and banana-beer brewer than a confidante of the Virgin Mary, as she later said she was.</p>
        <p>Almost four months after the first bodies were found, shaking this nation still scarred from a past bloody from wars and dictators, hard facts are few. No one knows for certain how so many could die, apparently over several weeks, without the slightest suspicion. No one knows if the group's leaders are dead or alive.</p>
        <p>One of the few certainties is that this was not the largest cult killing ever, as was widely reported a few months ago. As new graves were being discovered every few days, the police and government officials said the death toll was over 1,000, and thus more than the 913 who died in Jonestown, Guyana, in 1978. The final toll of 780 -- in six graves in southwestern Uganda and one in the capital -- is still huge. But it is based on an actual body count.</p>
        <p>The confusion at the time grew from estimates of how many bodies had been burned in the old church here, with the reports as high as 530. The actual number is 330, said Assuman Mugenyi, a Uganda police spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mugenyi said the police now believed that the leader of the cult, Joseph Kibwetere, a defrocked Roman Catholic priest, was in fact dead and perhaps one of the six bodies pulled from the latrine.</p>
        <p>He said their suspicion was based on a few survivors who said Mr. Kibwetere was nowhere to be found in the days before the fire here, on March 17. He said the police also believed that two other cult leaders, Ms. Mwerinde and another defrocked priest, Dominic Kataribabo, might be alive and out of the country. International warrants have been issued for their arrest.</p>
        <p>There has been speculation that some went to their deaths willingly. Few of the bodies showed signs of struggle, and some have argued that it strains belief that so many people could have been murdered in these tiny villages without someone knowing. But Mr. Mugenyi said the police were still treating the deaths as murders.</p>
        <p>''Although they understood that they were going to heaven, they did not know they would be murdered,'' he said. ''They thought they would get on a bus and go to heaven.''</p>
        <p>He said it was possible that the victims had been poisoned, although he said the lab reports from quick autopsies on some victims had not been released. One of the few people from Kanungu who was related to someone who died in the fire said he could not believe that anyone had gone along willingly.</p>
        <p>Ivan Turyakyira, 36, said his father, Yonathani Kalmasi, 60, had often walked from their hut across a field to study religion or eat at the compound. On May 16 the father went to a feast to celebrate the opening of a new church building there and said nothing about suicide or even about the end being near.</p>
        <p>''No one suspected,'' the son said. Then his father returned the next day and died along with the others in the church fire. Mr. Turyakyira went there when the bodies were heaved into a mass grave but, though he lives a few minutes' walk away, he has stayed away since, like most people.</p>
        <p>''It didn't feel good then,'' he said, ''and I didn't want to go back.''</p>
        <p>Outsiders are beginning to say the town, a pleasant place of green hills and vistas, is haunted.</p>
        <p>''We are afraid, because the spirits talk through the night,'' said Warren Mugabe, 35, a teacher in a village a half-hour's drive south of here. His brother-in-law, Jonnes Mugabe, 36, added, ''Some people say they do walk at night and make singing and other things.''</p>
        <p>This kind of talk angers people from Kanungu, who say it is bad enough that their town is now synonymous with mass murder. ''That's a lie,'' said Matthew Kanyangira, 53, a trader here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byamukama, the guard, said he had never seen or heard anything unearthly. He should know, because he sleeps in the compound at night.</p>
        <p>But still, he considered it. ''Some people say the spirits fear this gun,'' he said. ''I don't know if that is so.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
