<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thief II Stresses Stealth Over Strength</title>
    <meta content="06GAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Looking Glass Studio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">herold, charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5D91139F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thief II Stresses Stealth Over Strength</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">herold, charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold reviews Thief II: The Metal Age, computer game from Looking Glass Studio; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'VE just entered the study when I hear a guard moving in the hall outside, whistling tunelessly.  Quickly I douse the torch on the wall with one of my water arrows and wait in the dark. The guard passes by, oblivious; I see that he's carrying a key. Planning to pick his pocket, I quickly exit the study, but I've forgotten that between the room and hall carpets there is a brief stretch of wooden floor, and the sound of my boots startles the guard.</p>
        <p>''Who goes there?'' he shouts as I quickly duck back into the study. He enters the room. I press up against the wall and hold my breath. He looks around carefully, but my black cloak blends into the deep shadows.  He comes closer and closer, seeming to stare right at me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'VE just entered the study when I hear a guard moving in the hall outside, whistling tunelessly.  Quickly I douse the torch on the wall with one of my water arrows and wait in the dark. The guard passes by, oblivious; I see that he's carrying a key. Planning to pick his pocket, I quickly exit the study, but I've forgotten that between the room and hall carpets there is a brief stretch of wooden floor, and the sound of my boots startles the guard.</p>
        <p>''Who goes there?'' he shouts as I quickly duck back into the study. He enters the room. I press up against the wall and hold my breath. He looks around carefully, but my black cloak blends into the deep shadows.  He comes closer and closer, seeming to stare right at me.</p>
        <p>In any other game, I would pull out my broadsword or laser gun, and the guard would be history. But in Thief II: The Metal Age, a self-described ''first-person sneaker'' from Looking Glass Studio, brute strength takes a back seat to cunning stealth. So I just keep quiet and hope that he doesn't realize I'm here.</p>
        <p>''Must have been rats,'' the guard mutters and turns away. I run up and knock him out with my blackjack, and I drag his body deeper into the study to hide him from the other guards. After I grab the key, I slip out into the hall.</p>
        <p>If that sounds less exciting than all-out carnage, it isn't. A refreshing alternative to games that glorify violence, Thief II instead glorifies thievery. You play Garrett, a master thief who steals from the wealthy and powerful for a living and saves the world as a hobby.</p>
        <p>Garrett lives in a world that is part Ivanhoe, part 19th-century mechanics and part information age robotics. An ancient stone castle can be guarded by clanking mechanical beasts that are powered by an internal furnace.</p>
        <p>In the typical 3-D action game, which Thief II resembles at first glance, a favored technique is to run into a room with supercharged weapons and rain down destruction on your enemies. But in Thief II your weapons are primitive and awkward and if three guards gang up on you, you are dead, pure and simple.</p>
        <p>Fighting is the surest way to lose the game. Not that Garrett is a pacifist (he can fire off arrows from a safe distance), but it is a lot safer to hide in the shadows or run away. At a higher level of difficulty, you are often required to show even more restraint, completing your mission without leaving any trace of your presence. That means leaving everyone else alive and conscious.</p>
        <p>The story is slight. Garrett is recruited to help destroy the Mechanists, a cult that worships machines and is turning the poor and disenfranchised into living robots. The overthrow of this cult entails traveling over rooftops and through people's apartments, following Mechanist messengers and reading their communiques. In one of my favorite missions, you follow a dying man by the bloodstains he leaves behind.</p>
        <p>Whatever else you have to do -- frame a corrupt official, find secret documents, kidnap an important Mechanist -- you must never forget to steal things. Snatch those golden candlesticks, slip the purse off that woman's belt, pick up a stack of coins from a gambling table. This is your job, and you are very good at it. And after all, saving the world doesn't put food on the table.</p>
        <p>While most game engines supply rather dimwitted antagonists, the denizens of Thief II give a remarkable impersonation of real intelligence. Guards don't just try to kill you -- they get other guards to help. ''Come quickly, an intruder,'' one will shout, and any guard in earshot will come running, sword drawn. A noncombatant will whimper, ''Please don't hurt me,'' then start screaming, ''Come quickly -- a thief is here.''</p>
        <p>Guards will search for you if they hear your step on a marble floor or find an unconscious body. They peer into every shadow and shout, ''Only a coward hides.'' If they find you, you must escape or fight. If you give a guard a couple of good thrusts with your sword, he will run away and call for assistance.</p>
        <p>In other ways, Thief II shows its game engine's limitations. Except for highly scripted conversations, the people in the game never acknowledge one another. When a guard passes another guard he never says, ''How are the kids?'' And while these guards are far smarter than typical game enemies, they still cannot form a posse and methodically hunt you down. They all try to kill you, but they do not really cooperate with one another. (If the guards were that smart, you would never make it out alive.)</p>
        <p>Much of the fun of Thief II comes from playing fly on the wall. Poking around an office, you might find an exchange of mail from two clerks plotting against their boss, or you might overhear guards debating religion.</p>
        <p>The world in Thief II is amazingly alive, almost making you feel that the people you are robbing are real characters with lives of their own. They seem so real that leaving them alive may feel like not only the best strategy but also the best moral choice. As that guard crumples to the ground and whimpers, ''Help me,'' you might just feel a little guilty.  Poor guy, he was only doing his job.</p>
        <p>Thief II: The Metal Age, by Looking Glass Studio and for Eidos Interactive; CD-ROM for Windows 95 and 98; $39.95; for ages 17 and older.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
