<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sather Talks to Keenan and Eyes Messier</title>
    <meta content="06RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sather, Glen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messier, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemieux, Claude</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malakov, Vladimir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4D61E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sather Talks to Keenan and Eyes Messier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers president and general manager Glen Sather says Mark Messier, Claude Lemieux and Vladimir Malakhov are on his free-agent wish list, conference call (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Glen Sather, the Rangers' new president and general manager, officially revealed his free-agent wish list yesterday: Mark Messier, Claude Lemieux and Vladimir Malakhov.</p>
        <p>''We're carrying on with our dialogue,'' Sather said during a conference call, when asked if the Rangers were any closer to re-signing the 39-year-old Messier. ''I talked to his father twice today. I've always had strong interest in Mark. I have strong interest in Lemieux as well. I have strong interest in Malakhov as well. But I don't know whether it's possible to sign them all, depending on the money.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Glen Sather, the Rangers' new president and general manager, officially revealed his free-agent wish list yesterday: Mark Messier, Claude Lemieux and Vladimir Malakhov.</p>
        <p>''We're carrying on with our dialogue,'' Sather said during a conference call, when asked if the Rangers were any closer to re-signing the 39-year-old Messier. ''I talked to his father twice today. I've always had strong interest in Mark. I have strong interest in Lemieux as well. I have strong interest in Malakhov as well. But I don't know whether it's possible to sign them all, depending on the money.''</p>
        <p>Even the Rangers, with their deep pockets, have a bottom line, it seems.</p>
        <p>''So many free agents were signed last year that we just don't have spots for guys,'' said Sather, who cited grit and players with the ability to move the puck better as his team's most glaring needs. ''This team has to have a real turnaround. And the players have to have the opportunity to turn it around.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers finished with 29 victories and 73 points and missed the playoffs last season.</p>
        <p>The players need a coach first. And Sather insisted that he has not struck a deal with Ron Low, the presumed favorite for the job.</p>
        <p>''I'm still talking to people,'' said Sather, who added he will not name a coach until next week. ''I have not offered this job to anyone yet. I'm still going through the process, but I'm getting it narrowed down.''</p>
        <p>Mike Keenan, who coached the Rangers to their only Stanley Cup title in three generations -- in 1994 with Messier leading the way -- could be on Sather's list.</p>
        <p>''I'm fairly certain, and it looks obvious, that he hasn't made up his mind,'' Keenan said last night in a telephone interview. ''Maybe he's waiting to see what his team looks like. And if he can sign those free agents, he could think it might require a different type of coach.''</p>
        <p>Like Keenan?</p>
        <p>''First of all, I think that people deserve a second chance,'' said Sather.</p>
        <p>And he was not talking just about Keenan. Sather was also referring to defenseman Stephane Quintal, who was suspended for the final four games of last season by Don Maloney and Dave Checketts after Quintal told a French-language reporter in Montreal that signing with the Rangers may have been a mistake.</p>
        <p>''I've been in a forgive-and-forget mode with a lot of players over the years,'' said Sather, who may be trying to protect Quintal's trade value. ''I'm not condoning anything that happened with the Rangers in the past. But those things have to be left in the past.''</p>
        <p>As for matters perhaps lingering from the past, Keenan bolted the Rangers for St. Louis only days after the team's ticker-tape parade.</p>
        <p>''I think Mike deserves an opportunity,'' Sather said of Keenan, who has been out of work since being fired by the Vancouver Canucks midway through the 1998-99 season. ''Out of respect, I deserve the opportunity for him to speak to me about the job.''</p>
        <p>Sather said he plans to speak with Keenan a second time, today or tomorrow. Irrespective of whether he gets the job, Keenan did say of the expected signing of Messier: ''I think it's the right choice for Mark and the Rangers.''</p>
        <p>If Messier returns, could that have  any effect on whether Keenan -- an old Messier ally -- gets the job? Will the 35-year-old Lemieux, who has won four Stanley Cups with three organizations (including the Devils in two tenures), join a roster already laden with over-30 players? Is the gifted Malakhov, who has frustrated as many coaches as he has impressed, poised to rejoin Quintal (the two were teammates in Montreal) on the Rangers' blue line?</p>
        <p>Suddenly, the Rangers' summer is not nearly as quiet as it had seemed.</p>
        <p>Referring to Malakhov, Sather -- whose son is getting married this weekend -- said: ''I'd like to have it done before the weekend one way or the other. We either do it or we don't.''</p>
        <p>What, Sather was asked, does the enigmatic Malakhov bring to the ice that Mathieu Schneider, another unrestricted free agent who played with the Rangers the last two seasons, does not?</p>
        <p>''I think he moves the puck better,'' Sather said. ''I haven't heard from Schneider's agent anyway, so I'm not sure if he's interested in coming back to New York.''</p>
        <p>Will Sather call Schneider's agent, Steve Reich?</p>
        <p>''If he doesn't know what I'm doing, he must be in the dark ages,'' Sather said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
