<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starting From Scratch, Matchup Takes Shape</title>
    <meta content="06WIMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E6D91E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starting From Scratch, Matchup Takes Shape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outlook for Wimbledon tennis tournament semifinal between sisters Venus and Serena Williams discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To trace the infancy of the Williams sisters' powerful revolution, you would have to start with the Yellow Pages. And put your faith in tall tales.</p>
        <p>To discover how Venus and Serena Williams first developed the strength to begin a surreal journey that has led them to Thursday's semifinal match against each other at Wimbledon, you would have to go back to the inner city of Los Angeles. And believe in the impossible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To trace the infancy of the Williams sisters' powerful revolution, you would have to start with the Yellow Pages. And put your faith in tall tales.</p>
        <p>To discover how Venus and Serena Williams first developed the strength to begin a surreal journey that has led them to Thursday's semifinal match against each other at Wimbledon, you would have to go back to the inner city of Los Angeles. And believe in the impossible.</p>
        <p>''When they were around 2 years old, I wanted them to work; and my wife said, 'That's not going to happen,' '' said the sisters' beaming father, Richard Williams, as he stood in a morning drizzle today outside the gates of the All England Club. ''How could they work? Well, they could deliver phone books.</p>
        <p>''People look at Venus and Serena today and say, 'Heck, they must lift weights.' They don't lift weights. They just end up that way when you develop their muscles early. It just followed them all through life. Now, my wife says, 'You did it the right way.' ''</p>
        <p>The method of Richard Williams -- together, with all of its madness -- has produced an unimaginable result. In front of a Center Court crowd of curiosity seekers and tennis connoisseurs, his daughters will part the applause together as they take their places on a grass stage. Somewhere in the background of this fascination, the modest Lindsay Davenport will face the 17-year-old prodigy, Jelena Dokic, in the other match.</p>
        <p>The day will belong to the Williams sisters. Beyond the social impact of their accomplishment -- with the two making a cinematic-like leap from the projects to the pristine grounds of the All England Club -- they will represent the simple pride of a family. Perhaps as the only family members in attendance.</p>
        <p>Their mother, Oracene, told her family Tuesday night that she was too exhausted to make the trip from Florida in time for the match. Richard Williams also has other plans, but they do not include attending the funeral of a stranger.</p>
        <p>''That funeral is today; I thought it was tomorrow,'' said Williams, who planned to use the funeral as an escape from the tension of his daughters' match. ''I might find something else to do. I might go spend some pounds. If my daughters don't insist, I won't be here.</p>
        <p>''I wish my wife would come. I need some kissing and hugging, but she's not coming. It's disappointing. I think Venus and Serena are making history here.''</p>
        <p>From the moment they walk on the court, their every move and mood will be inspected. And as they exit, the outcome will determine much more than which sister will advance to the final.</p>
        <p>Some wonder if Venus Williams's psyche could take a loss to a little sister who is up to her ponytail in talent, charisma and confidence. In September, Venus Williams stoically looked on from the friend's box as Serena became the first of the sisters to capture a Grand Slam with a title at the United States Open. Had Serena passed Venus so soon?</p>
        <p>''Fundamentally speaking, I think Serena is a better player than Venus,'' said Andre Agassi, who has taken note of the Williams sisters' metamorphosis. ''You've got to favor certainly one of them to win the tournament. I don't know which one. It's always a psychological matchup. I can't even imagine what it's like to play your sibling.''</p>
        <p>Today, neither sister wanted to discuss it. Just after they ended Martina Navratilova's uplifting Wimbledon return with a doubles victory in the quarterfinals, Venus Williams entered the interview room, trailed by Serena. In a sign that the tension of the moment has started to wear on them, Venus abruptly ended any questions regarding their semifinal by saying, ''We feel like we answered enough of those questions.''</p>
        <p>The more serious of the two, Venus asserted her big sister authority while Serena sat silently. In Venus's presence, the usually effusive Serena was subdued.</p>
        <p>''To this day, Venus is Serena's hero and best friend,'' Richard Williams said. ''But Venus definitely set the stage for Serena.''</p>
        <p>Both are striking stars. With the lean and angular Venus Williams standing across the net from the compact and sculpted Serena, with both sisters unleashing such uninhibited power, their appearance in a semifinal appears to represent another step in the evolution of tennis. But the sage who met them face to face today isn't ready to proclaim their arrival just yet.</p>
        <p>''Not yet,'' said Navratilova, who changed the way players on the women's tour approached fitness. ''I mean, they have the capability of taking it another step. They just haven't gotten there, yet. With their size, they're just so big. I thought I was big, but I'm like pip-squeak next to them.</p>
        <p>''If they put it together technically, we could see them in the finals for a lot of years to come. If they commit themselves, and if they want to stay around. They definitely have the potential. For them, they have to make fewer unforced errors. They still miss too much. You know, just harness it a little bit. You're still on your heels expecting a bullet.''</p>
        <p>They are an intimidating pair. But Richard Williams did not venture a guess as to which daughter would have better control of their power and emotion when match time arrives. As father and coach, he was out of the loop. He did not practice with them today, and will not hit with them on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''I won't say nothing, either,'' he said. ''Yesterday, when Serena played her match and got through so quick, she came to the court to watch Venus, I said, 'Serena, Venus is not running up to take the balls, and that's what I told her to do. Tonight, would you please tell her to do it.' And she looked at me and said: 'Dad, no way. I'm playing her next.' So I will have no advice for either one of them.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
