<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Britain, Debate Over Adopting Euro Gains in Intensity</title>
    <meta content="Y06BRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDC1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Britain, Debate Over Adopting Euro Gains in Intensity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internal British debate over adopting euro grows more intense when government publishes data that show overseas investment in Britain soared to record despite strength of British pound; data undercut complaints by foreign companies that pound's strength was damaging them by making Britain expensive place to manufacture goods for export; Prime Min Tony Blair acknowledges that there are some economic benefits from euro membership, but he insists that Britain should maintain its 'prepare and decide' policy on signing up for currency (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An internal British debate over adopting the euro grew more intense today when the government published data that showed overseas investment in Britain had soared to a record despite the strength of the British pound.</p>
        <p>The data undercut complaints by foreign companies that the pound's strength was damaging them by making Britain an expensive place to manufacture goods for export.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An internal British debate over adopting the euro grew more intense today when the government published data that showed overseas investment in Britain had soared to a record despite the strength of the British pound.</p>
        <p>The data undercut complaints by foreign companies that the pound's strength was damaging them by making Britain an expensive place to manufacture goods for export.</p>
        <p>Further fanning the debate, Prime Minister Tony Blair acknowledged today that there were some economic benefits from euro membership. But he insisted that Britain should maintain its ''prepare and decide'' policy on signing up for the currency.</p>
        <p>The euro, adopted by 11 of the European Union's 15 members, has fallen sharply against the pound and the dollar since its introduction 18 months ago. That weakness has made British exports to Europe, in particular, more expensive.</p>
        <p>The statements from politicians and business leaders have followed weeks of dispute within the British government over how to present its policy on the single currency -- either bullish or bearish -- as foreign manufacturers like Nissan Motor, Toyota Motor and Mitsubishi insist that the pound's strength against the euro is unacceptable to them.</p>
        <p>These companies, along with Nestle and others, have called in recent days for Britain to commit itself to joining the euro. Such a move would lock the pound into an immutable relationship with the euro-zone and remove the risk of exchange rate swings from manufacturers' calculations and export sales.</p>
        <p>In figures announced today, Sir David Wright, head of the Department of Trade and Industry's Invest in Britain Bureau, said foreign investment here rose to a record $382 billion in the fiscal year -- almost half of it from the United States -- 25 percent higher than the prior year.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing which suggests that the attitude of foreign companies is being significantly affected by the policy with which we are all familiar in respect to the single currency,'' Mr. Wright said.</p>
        <p>Britain prides itself as the favored site among outside investors seeking a beachhead for sales into the European Union.</p>
        <p>But there is evidence that the pound's strength against the euro is eroding the readiness of manufacturers to risk the extra currency-driven costs of doing business here.</p>
        <p>This year alone, the Ford Motor Company and BMW A.G. have pulled out of British automotive plants, and Nissan has hinted it might move production of a new subcompact elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Adding to pressures to commit to the euro, Mr. Blair faces a competitive challenge from the strengthening economies of France and Germany -- the twin motors of European integration -- which could leave Britain on the sidelines.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blair faces a domestic political challenge pulling in the opposite direction. With his popularity at its lowest in three years, a new opinion survey suggested that more than 70 percent of Britons oppose abandoning the pound.</p>
        <p>In Parliament today, Mr. Blair insisted that Britain stick to its present view, known as the prepare-and-decide policy, that it would join a successful European currency if the euro zone's performance met British economic criteria and if Britons voted for it in a referendum.</p>
        <p>''Membership of a successful single currency would be good for British jobs, mortgages and industry but it must be dependent on the economic tests,'' Mr. Blair said.</p>
        <p>But, in remarks typifying British ambivalence, he said, ''What would be disastrous for British jobs and inward investment, what would mean the immediate loss of jobs and investment in this country, is to rule out the euro altogether.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
