<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="06DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD91E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WorldCom and Sprint Plan To End Merger Agreement  Facing resistance from regulators in the United States and Europe to their proposed $115 billion merger, WorldCom and Sprint are planning to announce by early next week that they will abandon the deal, executives close to both companies said.</p>
        <p>The move could immediately turn the companies into takeover targets for both American companies and foreign companies that have been seeking a foothold in the United States. Sprint has already received informal overtures from both Deutsche Telekom of Germany and from BellSouth. Shares of Sprint fell 93.75 cents, to $53.50, while WorldCom rose 37.5 cents, to $45.50. [Page C6.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WorldCom and Sprint Plan To End Merger Agreement  Facing resistance from regulators in the United States and Europe to their proposed $115 billion merger, WorldCom and Sprint are planning to announce by early next week that they will abandon the deal, executives close to both companies said.</p>
        <p>The move could immediately turn the companies into takeover targets for both American companies and foreign companies that have been seeking a foothold in the United States. Sprint has already received informal overtures from both Deutsche Telekom of Germany and from BellSouth. Shares of Sprint fell 93.75 cents, to $53.50, while WorldCom rose 37.5 cents, to $45.50. [Page C6.]</p>
        <p>With the merger between Sprint and WorldCom all but called off, Sprint executives who were given stock options as an incentive to stay can cash them in now and leave. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Plunge on Profit Warnings  Stocks tumbled after earnings warnings from software makers sent investors scrambling to sell technology shares. The Nasdaq composite index dropped 128.83 points, or 3.2 percent, to 3,863.10. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 77.07 points, or 0.7 percent, to 10,483.60, and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index slid 23.09 points, or 1.6 percent, to 1,446.23. [C10.]</p>
        <p>New Share Sale for Goldman Sachs  Goldman Sachs Group said that it would let its former partners sell as many as 18 million shares of stock in an offering that could be bigger than the firm's $3.66 billion initial public offering last year. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Leading Indicators Down Slightly  The Index of Leading Economic Indicators, an important measure of future economic activity, fell 0.1 percent in May, the latest indication that a string of interest rate increases has slowed the economy. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Optimism Wanes Over North Korea  Foreign business optimism over the thaw between North and South Korea has waned considerably in the few weeks since their leaders met and a symbolic truckload of Coca-Cola crossed into the North. The discussions between President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea and his Communist counterpart, Kim Jong Il, generated a kind of euphoria, and talk was heard of an opening of North Korea. But now, major American and European businesses are again expressing deep caution. And Coca-Cola, often seen as an icon of Western capitalism that helped lead the way into Communist countries like China and Vietnam, is vague about what it envisions doing in North Korea. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Euro Debate Intensifies in Britain  A British debate over whether to join the euro grew more intense when the government published data that showed overseas investment in Britain has soared to a record despite the strength of the British pound. The data undercut complaints by foreign companies that the pound's strength is damaging them by making Britain an expensive place to manufacture goods for export. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Have Car, Will Travel for Cheap Gas  Wedded to their cars, Europe's motorists have long been the target of governments that seek revenue by cranking up taxes on gasoline. Consequently, drivers are willing to cross international borders in search of cheap gas, driven by taxes that vary widely. [A1.]</p>
        <p>New Economy, With an Old Twist  While many business gurus, and even some well-trained economists, say that we now live in a ''network society'' in which profits and economic growth can reach heights not yet seen, it is the old-economy idea of economies of scale that is making the difference. Jeff Madrick: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
