<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teachers' Group Rejects Linking Job Performance Evaluations to Bonuses</title>
    <meta content="06TEAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Education Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5D71E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teachers' Group Rejects Linking Job Performance Evaluations to Bonuses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Delegates to Chicago convention of National Education Assn, nation's largest teacher's group, break with union leadership by soundly rejecting use of job performance evaluations in paying bonuses; leaders of union, which represents 2.5 million members and two-thirds of nation's teachers, say many local unions have already negotiated such job performance contracts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Breaking with union leadership, the nation's largest teachers' group today soundly rejected the use of job performance evaluations in paying bonuses.</p>
        <p>Delegates to the National Education Association convention, meeting in Chicago this week, scrapped the performance proposal by a voice vote and head count after many rank-and-file members expressed concerns that it was unfair to teachers and to the children who most need excellent teachers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Breaking with union leadership, the nation's largest teachers' group today soundly rejected the use of job performance evaluations in paying bonuses.</p>
        <p>Delegates to the National Education Association convention, meeting in Chicago this week, scrapped the performance proposal by a voice vote and head count after many rank-and-file members expressed concerns that it was unfair to teachers and to the children who most need excellent teachers.</p>
        <p>''If teachers compete for bonuses,'' said Barbara Kerr, a delegate from California, ''who will want to teach the poor students, the students who don't speak English well?''</p>
        <p>Leaders of the union, which represents 2.5 million members and two-thirds of the nation's teachers, said many local unions had already negotiated such job performance contracts. Under the union plan, such performance evaluations would not rely on student scores on standardized tests, and would be implemented only with the guidance of teachers themselves. As an example, supporters of the proposal said a district might pay bonuses to teachers who speak two languages or who complete technological training.</p>
        <p>Tim Dedman of Kentucky spoke in support of endorsing the option for local unions to negotiate for job performance bonuses.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the right to dictate'' to union locals, Mr. Dedman said. ''I trust our members to do what is right. Let's give our members the flexibility they need.''</p>
        <p>The job performance issue is also being studied by the nation's other large teachers' union, the American Federation of Teachers, which is holding its national convention now in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Some teachers' unions around the country, including those in Denver and Columbus, Ohio, have already entered into agreements with school districts that give teachers bonuses if certain goals are met.</p>
        <p>The idea of such cash incentives has become popular around the country as business leaders and politicians have called for higher standards in primary education.</p>
        <p>Both expected presidential nominees, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore, have made education and better schools a major issue of their campaigns.</p>
        <p>The vice president, who on Tuesday received the endorsements of the two national teachers' unions, has proposed spending $115 billion over the next 10 years on education, including $8 billion to recruit a million new teachers and $8 billion more to increase teachers' salaries.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has also devoted considerable attention to education to woo swing voters and has proposed a five-year, $2.9 billion plan to improve teaching. Part of that would go to greater financing for teacher training, as well as bolstering a program that recruits retired military personnel to become teachers and a plan to allow a tax deduction of up to $400 a year for teachers who spend their own money on supplies.</p>
        <p>In the debate today at the union meeting both sides said they sought to increase teachers' salaries overall, noting that starting teachers in 1998-1999 earned an average of less than $27,000 a year, far less, they said, than recent college graduates with similar credentials.</p>
        <p>But opponents of the job performance proposal said that school districts would use the issue to lower overall salaries.</p>
        <p>''Do we want to send a message to state legislatures and school boards that we are willing to negotiate pay for performance?'' asked Robin Holcombe of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>There was no debate over the union's longstanding opposition to merit pay, salaries based on evaluations by administrators or evaluations based on students' test scores.</p>
        <p>Bob Chase, the union president who supported the job performance option, said he did not take the vote as a rebuke of union leadership.</p>
        <p>''We had union leaders on both sides, and we knew it would be close,'' he said. ''But this was an issue that needed to be debated. And I don't think it's an issue that's going to go away anytime soon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
