<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="06MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E5DF1F39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: COLUMBIA U. SETTLES  A Chinese graduate student who was dismissed from Columbia University in March after being accused of mishandling a radioactive substance has been reinstated, Columbia officials said yesterday. The student, Yao Cheng, says she is innocent and has complained about the university's disciplinary procedures. She was suspected of using the radioactive material in a convoluted plan to switch from graduate biology studies to the business school. There has been no admission of wrongdoing by Ms. Cheng or of improper procedures by Columbia.</p>
        <p>Andrew C. Revkin (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: COLUMBIA U. SETTLES  A Chinese graduate student who was dismissed from Columbia University in March after being accused of mishandling a radioactive substance has been reinstated, Columbia officials said yesterday. The student, Yao Cheng, says she is innocent and has complained about the university's disciplinary procedures. She was suspected of using the radioactive material in a convoluted plan to switch from graduate biology studies to the business school. There has been no admission of wrongdoing by Ms. Cheng or of improper procedures by Columbia.</p>
        <p>Andrew C. Revkin (NYT)</p>
        <p>RIKERS ISLAND: ESCAPE PLOT ALLEGED  Jail officials have restricted the movements of Sante Kimes, who was sentenced last week to life in prison for murder, because of another inmate's allegation that she was plotting an escape. Tom Antenen, a spokesman for the Correction Department, said that jail officials would not let her leave Rikers Island before the start of her prison term next week. Mrs. Kimes, 65, and her son, Kenneth, 25, were sentenced on June 27 to more than 120 years each in prison for murdering Irene Silverman in a scheme to steal her $7 million Manhattan home.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: RACKETEERING PLEA  A defendant who had faced the death penalty in Manhattan federal court pleaded guilty last week in exchange for a prison term of up to 40 years, federal prosecutors announced yesterday. They said that Charles Michael Kee, who pleaded guilty to racketeering and firearms charges, admitted to conspiring in the murder of a fellow member of the Bloods gang in 1998. They said Mr. Kee was a Bloods leader in the Bronx from 1996 to 1998.</p>
        <p>John Sullivan (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNION SUED  Two companies that install telecommunications equipment have filed an antitrust suit against Local 3 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, charging the union and other electrical contractors with conspiring to control the telecommunications installation market in the New York region. The companies, Odyssey Group and U.S. Information Systems, accuse the union of threatening to disrupt installation projects unless companies that have contracts with Local 3 do the work. Local 3 officials deny wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND: HOSPITAL VOTE  About 900 workers at St. Vincents Hospital and Medical Center on Staten Island voted yesterday on whether they wanted to join 1199, New York's Health and Human Service Employees Union. Among those voting were the hospital's clerical, technical and service workers, including food workers, nurses' aides and janitors. St. Vincents is one of the last nonunion hospitals in New York City. If its workers unionize, they will join 6,000 union members in the St. Vincents Catholic Medical Center of New York network. Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>GARDEN CITY: CANCER CENTER INQUIRY  The Nassau County Legislature's committee on government services plans to hold a hearing today on the status of Hewlett House, a county-financed treatment center for breast cancer. More than three years after the start of the project, which was estimated at $250,000, the center is still unfinished and unopened and has cost more than $1.5 million. Hewlett House officials say that because the site is a historical landmark there have been unexpected costs.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>FIRE ISLAND: MOSQUITO SPRAYING  The Suffolk County Department of Public Works said it would spray walks in Davis Park and Fire Island Pines on Fire Island for mosquitoes between 6:30 p.m. and 10:30 p.m. today. The spraying is not directly related to the West Nile virus. The pesticide to be used is sumithrin, also known by the brand name Anvil, an insecticide said to be similar to natural pesticides found in chrysanthemums. While federal rules do not require residents to leave the area, windows should be shut and window fans and air conditioners turned off.</p>
        <p>John Rather (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: GAS PRICES EDGE DOWN  Connecticut drivers are beginning to pay less for gas at some stations, but other stations are delaying a price reduction until they use up their supplies of more expensive fuel. Some owners said they had lowered prices to reflect a gas-tax cut that went into effect Saturday. The average price of a gallon of regular unleaded gasoline at the beginning of this week was $1.79, AAA Motor Club surveys found, down from the June 22 peak of $1.81 a gallon.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>SOUTH ORANGE: SPRINKLER BILL SIGNED  Visiting the Seton Hall University campus where three students were killed and 58 injured in a Jan. 19 fire, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman yesterday signed legislation requiring sprinklers in all dormitory rooms within four years. ''Today, we try in our own way to bring some meaning to this tragedy, to ensure that some good can come out of this terrible event,'' Governor Whitman said. The new law, which covers public and private colleges and boarding schools, provides $90 million to help pay for the installation.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>LAKEWOOD: CRASH THEORY  Investigators are trying to determine whether a line found wrapped around a rudder caused a small plane towing a banner to crash at an airport on Monday, killing the pilot. Robert Gretz, an investigator for the National Transportation Safety Board, said that when the plane took off from Lakewood Airport, the pilot, using standard procedure, snared the banner -- which read ''Seton Hall, Go Pirates'' -- with a hook attached to a tow line. Mr. Gretz said the plane then circled back toward the runway as if to land, but instead nosedived into the ground.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>EAST ORANGE: BLOOD SHORTAGE  One of New Jersey's five blood centers appealed for emergency donations yesterday morning after the four-day holiday weekend eroded its supplies of essential Type O and Type B blood. The Blood Center of New Jersey said that it had less than a day's supply of both O positive and O negative and a two-day supply of B positive and B negative. Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
