<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer School Opens, but Many Students Are No-Shows</title>
    <meta content="06SUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFD91E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer School Opens, but Many Students Are No-Shows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS with ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona; Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of New York City students begin summer school in opening that goes smoothly but is marred by widespread attendance problems; 319,167 students, or 32 percent of public school students, are registered, but about 40 percent miss first day; Chancellor Harold O Levy concedes school system has not carried out sweeping end of social promotion; only 8 percent, or 65,076, of elementary and middle school students are being forced to attend; Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani downplays low number of students threatened with being held back; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nervous, resigned and sometimes enthusiastic, thousands of New York City students began summer school yesterday in an opening that officials said went smoothly even though it was marred by widespread attendance problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nervous, resigned and sometimes enthusiastic, thousands of New York City students began summer school yesterday in an opening that officials said went smoothly even though it was marred by widespread attendance problems.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Harold O. Levy said that 319,167, or 32 percent, of the city's 1,003,167 public school students were registered for summer school. But reminiscent of the attendance problems that plagued last year's much smaller pilot program, officials said a spot check of a third of the schools showed an average of 40 percent of students absent.</p>
        <p>David Klasfeld, the deputy chancellor for operations, attributed the absenteeism to the Fourth of July holiday, the brief interval between the end of the regular session last Wednesday and the start of summer school, and some confusion among parents over when summer school was supposed to begin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said this year's summer program was the biggest in New York City's history but conceded that the school system had not carried out the sweeping end of social promotion that Rudy Crew, the former chancellor, envisioned just a year ago. Dr. Crew, under pressure from Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, had predicted that 360,000 students in kindergarten through 12th grade would be forced to go to summer school this year or be held back.</p>
        <p>But in the end, only 8 percent -- or 65,076 -- of the city's elementary and middle school students are being forced to attend summer school. That is about twice last year's enrollment, but about the same rate as last summer, when the program was for only third, sixth and eighth grades.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, more than 30,000 students in third through eighth grade are being promoted even though they scored at the bottom of four levels on the citywide mathematics test in May. Officials said yesterday that it was unclear how many of those students, while not mandated to attend summer school, had been encouraged to attend voluntarily.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy explained that the rules for promotion gave teachers and administrators a large amount of discretion in determining whether students would be promoted.</p>
        <p>''That was Rudy Crew's judgment and the mayor's, and I agree,'' Mr. Levy said at a news conference at Public School 44 in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Later in the morning, Mr. Giuliani, appearing at Mr. Levy's side at P.S. 48, downplayed the low number of students threatened with being held back, saying that the summer school program was ''a very, very significant step'' toward ending social promotion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that summer school was not a panacea and that it was better to be cautious than to threaten to hold back huge numbers of students. ''I sent the message, too, that I didn't want a huge program,'' Mr. Levy said. ''We should have reasoned expectations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that every effort had been made to get students to class on the first day of summer school. All school buses made their rounds twice, to pick up stragglers, he said, and school officials had been told to call or visit the home of every student who did not show up. After a few days, an automatic phone program will call homes to remind parents that children should be in school.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy has set up a computerized system to track daily attendance, but officials said they would not have final attendance figures until today.</p>
        <p>In elementary and middle school, 105,637 students are being encouraged to go to summer school voluntarily. Of those, 49,948 are in kindergarten, first and second grades, reflecting an effort to help children before they fall too far behind.</p>
        <p>Another 148,454 high school students have enrolled, nearly 40,000 more than last year.</p>
        <p>The summer session will keep 831 of 1,177 city public schools open for the next five weeks, and the system has hired 15,825 teachers. Officials said it was the biggest summer school program in the nation's history, but they could not provide numbers from past years.</p>
        <p>And in an effort to give teachers and students a more pleasant environment than the sweltering classrooms many endured last year, the Board of Education installed 7,900 new air-conditioners, but 2,800 classrooms were still without them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy seemed annoyed by the many questions from reporters on air-conditioning. ''When I took a summer program, in my school there was no air-conditioning, and somehow I survived,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As parents took their children to school yesterday, most said they were pleased that their children would be spending July in class.</p>
        <p>One parent even tried to find places in class for his children who had not qualified to attend summer school. At P.S. 11 in Clinton Hill, Brooklyn, Jean Dubuisson asked that his son, Alix, 7, and daughter, Adelle, 8, be admitted. ''I could send them to stay with my family in Canada, but I prefer to have them in school. It's better for them.''</p>
        <p>P.S. 11 could not accommodate him, but he left with a list of other schools to try.</p>
        <p>Some parents, though, worried that the focus on passing a test for promotion in summer school was excusing teachers who did not give students the help they needed during the school year. ''For the students who need to make up a whole semester, summer school is a rip-off,'' said Velma Bascome, whose daughter, Michelle, had trouble with reading. ''It's an easy way to make a grade.''</p>
        <p>But two students said there was nothing easy about it. Isiah Pointer, a fourth grader at P.S. 163 on the Upper West Side, said he was missing a trip to Georgia with his father, and Shante Booker, a classmate, said she had to cancel a trip to Disneyland.</p>
        <p>Both were dealing with their disappointment. ''I think it's going to make me stronger,'' Shante said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
