<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A House Held Up by a Bank; Renovation yields condos and an aerie.</title>
    <meta content="06BANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohn, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fiore, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reimnitz, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iovine, Julie V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D71139F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A House Held Up by a Bank; Renovation yields condos and an aerie.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE V. IOVINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Iovine, Julie V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Bohn and Richard Fiore convert a landmarked 1907 Beaux-Arts bank at Eighth Avenue and 14th Street into 11 condos, whose sale should make good their $12 million investment; architect is John Reimnitz; photos of the penthouse duplex Bohn and Fiore created for themselves (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME relationships sag during a move, and when a drawn-out renovation is added, some collapse altogether from the strain. But Laura Bohn and Richard Fiore never seem happier than when they are abandoning one renovated apartment to overhaul the next. The husband-and-wife team have lived through seven renovations, starting with the apartment Ms. Bohn was living in when Mr. Fiore met her 21 years ago. (''She told me that if she was going to allow me to stay there, I had to rebuild it for her,'' Mr. Fiore said recently, still amused.) Three years ago, they took on their riskiest project. They bought a bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME relationships sag during a move, and when a drawn-out renovation is added, some collapse altogether from the strain. But Laura Bohn and Richard Fiore never seem happier than when they are abandoning one renovated apartment to overhaul the next. The husband-and-wife team have lived through seven renovations, starting with the apartment Ms. Bohn was living in when Mr. Fiore met her 21 years ago. (''She told me that if she was going to allow me to stay there, I had to rebuild it for her,'' Mr. Fiore said recently, still amused.) Three years ago, they took on their riskiest project. They bought a bank.</p>
        <p>The gamble was a true test of personal and professional ties. Only the stout of heart would spend $2 million on a 1907 Beaux-Arts bank, with landmark status and an address at Eighth Avenue and 14th Street, and then invest nearly $10 million more of their own money to convert it to condos, with a penthouse for themselves.</p>
        <p>For years, Ms. Bohn had noticed the bank while walking home from her office in the West Village, admiring its bays of arched windows, marble facade, imposing portico with columns and spread-winged eagle perched on the pediment. The building is typical of banks built across the nation from the 1870's to the 1920's: small-scale temples meant to represent the strength and durability of the banking system. Until shortly before its sale to Mr. Fiore and Ms. Bohn, it was a Chase Manhattan branch, an admirable, if smallish, example of Beaux-Arts symmetry.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, as banks merged and drop-in A.T.M.'s usurped the role of the sober and imposing neighborhood bank, some of these gems came onto the market, most fated to become commercial space, a Banana Republic here and a Duane Reade there. The 19th-century neo-Classical New York Savings Bank across 14th Street, a far more ornate edition of the genre with its domed copper roof and pillared hall, had been turned into a rug store.</p>
        <p>In the 90's, Ms. Bohn said, ''no one was buying these types of buildings'' because ''developers said forget it -- they're too much work.'' So the City Landmarks Commission was delighted with Mr. Fiore and Ms. Bohn's proposal for condos.</p>
        <p>Today, it appears the gamble might work. Six of 11 new condos, ranging from $588,000 to $2 million for a rooftop triplex, have buyers, and the others await those brave enough to take on raw soaring space. Three weeks ago Ms. Bohn and Mr. Fiore moved into their new 3,500-square-foot duplex. ''It was horrendous, the whole thing,'' Ms. Bohn said, deadpan. Her husband finished her thought, ''We loved every minute.''</p>
        <p>An interior designer who prefers big architectural gestures over fussy decorations, Ms. Bohn, 60, recommends big furniture and unadorned walls of windows wherever possible. Raised in Texas, she still speaks with the ghost of a twang. Her steely-haired, Brooklyn-bred husband, 61, is a contractor and the president and owner of Bohn Fiore Inc., a construction management company, which recently completed a new showroom for B&amp;B Italia in Midtown. He is also among his wife's biggest professional admirers. ''Workmen don't understand how dramatic her work is while they're doing it,'' he said, sliding into contractor-speak. ''Her basic curtain wall construction is to die for.''</p>
        <p>On a tour of the building, Ms. Bohn threaded her way past construction detritus and five floors of vast unfinished concrete-scapes. Down a dimly lighted hall, the one dustfree door opened with Kansas-to-Oz impact onto their sun-swept, green-washed, glass-walled penthouse, which has a 1,000-square-foot wraparound terrace with an ornate stone wall on the 14th Street side.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bohn and Mr. Fiore hired John Reimnitz, an architect with whom they often collaborate, to do the design work; Mr. Fiore took charge of construction. The arched windows looking onto 14th Street provided some emphatic architecture, and the 11 condominiums are laid out to take advantage of that. Aside from the facades on Eighth Avenue and 14th Street, which the Landmarks Preservation Commission wanted painted to match the original, there was little to be preserved. A roof addition was permissible, if it was mainly hidden from sight from the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>To get some height without becoming obtrusive, Mr. Fiore and Mr. Reimnitz lowered the bank's roof by about six feet. This allowed construction of a 27-foot-high duplex, whose first floor is largely camouflaged by the carved stone balustrade. A new, appropriately traditional pitched roof of standing seam metal is a response, Mr. Reimnitz said, to the more flamboyant dome on the bank across the street.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Bohn, the pitched metal roof recalls the rural architecture of Texas. She says it makes the duplex a real house -- her first in Manhattan after years of decorating houses outside the city for other people.</p>
        <p>The duplex actually looks more like a greenhouse, with walls almost entirely of glass framed in metal. Windows and doors blend and look out onto the terrace, which wraps around three sides. There is a small grove of potted trees with hydrangeas and hostas. One of the best things, Ms. Bohn said, is that ''you can actually see the rain falling on the leaves.'' On the north side, the balustrade is a buffer against wind and grime, with the stone suggesting the outlines of a castle keep.</p>
        <p>If the bank facade provides solidity, Ms. Bohn has added plenty of effervescence. Of the 20 or so shades she chose for the interior, most are subtle variations of green and one is milky blue, creating the impression of a perpetual dawn on a summer day. ''I love all shades of green, especially chartreuse,'' Ms. Bohn said, sipping water from a chartreuse glass. ''People always respond to it, and why not? It's nature, and it's very calming.''</p>
        <p>She said she normally chose pale tints for walls. But here, she needed the boldest shades to counteract the blasting sunlight.</p>
        <p>She had no intention of blocking the light with shades, even if that meant a loss of privacy. ''So they can see us watching TV -- so what?'' she said. In any case it's not a ''Rear Window'' situation; the only tall building nearby contains offices that close  at night. For now, at least, most of the West Village skyline is wide open.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bohn did concede that a glass penthouse isn't very energy-efficient. She should know: her father was an air-conditioning engineer. ''He'd faint if he saw this,'' she said, noting the absence of overhangs and thick walls. ''He'd be mad every minute.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bohn wanted terrazzo tiles on the first floor, because they stay cool and hide dirt. An uneven concrete base made tiles impractical, so she had a slurry of pebbles and concrete mixed and installed on-site. Though poured terrazzo is expensive, it saved having to level the floor and allowed her to custom-blend the colors, moving from a dark shade in the living room (more black pebbles) to something lighter in the kitchen (more tan). ''They can be filthy and you'd never know it,'' she said, shooting an indulgent look at the couple's two energetic dogs.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bohn is known for the studied informality of her interiors, which depend on simple, large pieces like the 10-foot sofa she designed for the duplex and a few old favorites like the gray lacquered coffee table that has followed the couple from apartment to apartment. ''I had no intention of adding any pretensions,'' she said of her new home, whose living room ceiling soars to 18 feet. ''The space is already pretentious enough as it is.'' Instead, she tried to soften it with rural touches. They include louvered doors, a straw-embedded plaster wall and screen doors that turn up on kitchen cupboards, air-conditioner vents and the laundry-and-dog room.</p>
        <p>''Joe Eula turned me on to them,'' she said, referring to the colorful New York fashion artist. ''He had a copper screen door in his bedroom that just blew my mind. It was so out of context, so airy, so different.''</p>
        <p>To get to the monumental living room, one passes through an entrance and a dining area of average height. A wall that doesn't quite reach the ceiling partly blocks the view to the living room, making its enormous size that much more a surprise. It's an old trick that works every time. The wall has a fireplace with a steel-plate surround and hearth that Ms. Bohn hopes will rust quickly to Georgia-clay red. The guest bedroom is next to the living room, and with floor-to-ceiling glass walls, it has some of the best views.</p>
        <p>The second floor is more a mezzanine overlooking the living room and the terrace. It accommodates the master bedroom, a bathroom and a small study.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bohn worried that the 18-by-22-foot living room was simply too big to be comfortable. ''It's about three times grander than any other home we've ever had,'' she said. Before they even moved in, she tried to think of ways to tone down the space.</p>
        <p>Her first thought was to suspend an antique turquoise kayak from the ceiling. But then she realized her urban aerie hardly called for a fake country touch. After all, it is a bank building.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
