<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swimmer Rediscovers Tranquillity in the Pool</title>
    <meta content="06SWIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Alison Terry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Terry, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5DB1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swimmer Rediscovers Tranquillity in the Pool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of freestyle swimmer Alison Terry, who will try to become first black swimmer to make American Olympic team; she comments on her struggle with racial identity as child of white mother and black father and her comeback effort, interview; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Next month, Alison Terry will try to become the first black swimmer to make the American Olympic team, having already made the more important splash of self-discovery.</p>
        <p>Earning an Olympic berth as a freestyler would affirm the rejuvenation of a career that began with great promise, ended in abandonment and the despair of a suicide attempt, then re-emerged after five years with her racial awakening and a personal mission to bring the sport to inner-city neighborhoods where opportunities long have been denied or dismissed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Next month, Alison Terry will try to become the first black swimmer to make the American Olympic team, having already made the more important splash of self-discovery.</p>
        <p>Earning an Olympic berth as a freestyler would affirm the rejuvenation of a career that began with great promise, ended in abandonment and the despair of a suicide attempt, then re-emerged after five years with her racial awakening and a personal mission to bring the sport to inner-city neighborhoods where opportunities long have been denied or dismissed.</p>
        <p>''She has been able to redefine herself as a swimmer, a mentor, a leader,'' said Alan Voisard, who is both Terry's coach and her fiance. ''She has a great understanding now of who she is.''</p>
        <p>Born 26 years ago to a black father and a white mother, Terry said she felt as a teenager in San Diego the societal tug of war to declare herself one race or the other. She had little contact with her father when she was younger, and as she began to excel at swimming, a world as white as a bathing cap, she entered private school and began to change the way she dressed. She said she became ashamed of her frizzy hair, hiding it under a cap or a hooded sweatshirt, and using products to straighten her wavy locks.</p>
        <p>''I really started to lose who I was,'' Terry said in a recent interview. ''I think I was trying to emulate more the white person and really thinking it was more important to move out of my community. Now I've come full circle. I think it's very important for kids to realize that opportunities can be available to them right there in the black community, and that being successful doesn't mean you have to move out.''</p>
        <p>This self-realization was not easily achieved, however, and her swimming career was nearly drowned.</p>
        <p>By 1990, Terry had become a national junior freestyle champion. A year later, she graduated from high school and intended to delay college for a year to compete in the Olympic trials for the 1992 Summer Games in Barcelona, Spain. But her coach quit unexpectedly before the trials. Stunned, untethered, she relocated up the California coast to Mission Viejo, but she was unhappy and indifferent about training. While her brimming talent and light coppery skin had allowed her comfortable entry into the swimming world, Terry met crude resistance when someone scrawled ''nigger'' on her car, according to the her mother, Debra Terry. Alison moved back to San Diego and attended the 1992 Olympic trials as a spectator, not a competitor.</p>
        <p>''I was totally devastated,'' Alison Terry said. ''I was just trying to hang on, dealing with other things, trying to find my own identity.''</p>
        <p>She entered the University of Tennessee in the fall of 1992 on scholarship, but she was still unnerved from losing her club coach and her chance at the Olympic trials. She said she clashed with her college coach, began skipping classes and training, and was kicked off the team. She left school in February 1993. For five years she would not compete.</p>
        <p>She began bartending, smoking, hanging with a rough crowd. She said she felt depressed, guilty about leaving swimming, but emotionally not strong enough to return. ''I felt like I had let everybody down,'' Terry said. She entered a relationship that she described as abusive, and her self-esteem plummeted. At her lowest moment she said she used a razor blade to slice her left wrist, which still bears a scar after six years.</p>
        <p>''I felt so sorry for myself, and at the time I was so weak I didn't think there was a way out,'' Terry said. ''I can't imagine being that sad now. I look back and I don't know if I really wanted to commit suicide. If I wanted to go, I would have. Maybe it was my way of asking for help.''</p>
        <p>Her mother said she was hospitalized briefly to treat the wound and received counseling. Trying to regain her personal ballast, Terry enrolled in San Diego's Mesa College to study black history. She would be greatly influenced by Starla Lewis, the chairwoman of the school's black studies department, who convinced Terry to decide her own identity, not one that society would decide for her. Lewis also told her not to frustrate herself by trying to adhere to white standards of hair, beauty and physical appearance. Where she once hid her hair under a cap, Terry now lets it cascade off her shoulders and she has an endorsement for hair-care products that enables her to train fulltime. She has also mended the broken ties to her father.</p>
        <p>''She changed Alison's life,'' said Debra Terry, a budget officer for the San Diego Lifeguard Service and a community activist who had taken her daughter to anti-apartheid rallies as a girl but who admittedly had not fully recognized her identity struggles later on. ''Sometimes it takes the right person saying the right thing at the right time. From black history classes, she learned about her ancestry, which gave her better perspective and pride and some justifiable anger.''</p>
        <p>Alison began to embrace her black heritage and, along with her mother and others, she began to develop swimming programs at San Diego's inner-city high schools, to recruit members of minority groups as lifeguards, to teach beach safety at elementary schools and to assist in learn-to-swim courses. This year, San Diego has agreed for the first time to keep inner-city pools open year-round, Terry said. These are small victories in a much larger battle that she believes should be waged against a lack of facilities, insufficient programs, a lack of interest and discouragement that linger from the days of segregation and persistent racial myths that blacks somehow lack the physical capabilities to be good swimmers.</p>
        <p>''If you don't give the kids a chance to participate, you'll never know how much talent is out there,'' Terry told the officials at Lincoln High in San Diego as she encouraged them to start a swimming program, which they did.</p>
        <p>''I think it's really important to have a black swimmer on the Olympic team,'' Terry said. ''That inspires me, to be in a position to be a role model for a lot of kids that just don't see swimmers every day, or don't see the sport as being a possibility.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, inspired by coaching high school swimmers, she realized that if she was encouraging them to pursue their own passions, she should pursue hers as well. She began swimming again, with the idea of making the 2000 Olympic team in Sydney, Australia. Only two Americans will qualify in the open 100-meter freestyle, but the top six finishers at the trials will qualify for Olympic relays. An outside chance is a chance worth taking for her.</p>
        <p>''I know I have that perfect race inside me,'' Terry said. ''I believe in myself. That's the No. 1 thing, believing you are going to be there. If you have any doubts, forget it. I'm not doubting myself. I did for way too long. And I'm not anymore.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
