<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pepsi takes aim at young baseball and soccer players.</title>
    <meta content="Y06ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pepsi-Cola Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DD1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pepsi takes aim at young baseball and soccer players.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance L. Hays</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pepsi-Cola Co has developed marketing campaign aimed at young baseball and soccer players between ages of 6 and 13; campaign offers ice chests and 12-packs of Pepsi to coaches; photo (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH thousands of American children signing up to play baseball and soccer in the years before they metamorphose into full-fledged consumers, the Pepsi-Cola Company is seizing on those pastimes -- one national, the other imported -- to market its soft drinks.</p>
        <p>The program, which began nationwide last year, is known as ''Takin' It to the Fields'' and offers ice chests and 12-packs of Pepsi to coaches, along with a scorekeeping book if the coach happens to have a baseball team. Teams composed of children between the ages of 6 and 13 are eligible. The equipment and the Pepsi are free, and the coaches are supposed to distribute the drinks once the game ends as part of the celebration, if there is one. And even if there isn't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH thousands of American children signing up to play baseball and soccer in the years before they metamorphose into full-fledged consumers, the Pepsi-Cola Company is seizing on those pastimes -- one national, the other imported -- to market its soft drinks.</p>
        <p>The program, which began nationwide last year, is known as ''Takin' It to the Fields'' and offers ice chests and 12-packs of Pepsi to coaches, along with a scorekeeping book if the coach happens to have a baseball team. Teams composed of children between the ages of 6 and 13 are eligible. The equipment and the Pepsi are free, and the coaches are supposed to distribute the drinks once the game ends as part of the celebration, if there is one. And even if there isn't.</p>
        <p>''We hope to be saving you money as we know how postgame refreshments and a score book are the very least that are required,'' notes the promotional material prepared by Pepsi, under the heading ''How Much Does This Program Cost?''</p>
        <p>Little League teams in the New York area can compete for a trip to a Mets game, although the odds might be a little long: last year, 4 teams out of 6,000 got tickets. Pepsi estimates about 90,000 baseball teams have signed up for the program, which also promises visits by Pepsi Ambassadors who will give away prizes, like batting gloves with the Pepsi logo. About 22,000 soccer teams have signed up for the Pepsi soccer program.</p>
        <p>Not to be overlooked is the marketing for major-league baseball that Pepsi, a unit of PepsiCo, offers through the children's program. The company has signed agreements with 14 teams, including the New York Mets and the Detroit Tigers, in which Pepsi products are the only ones served in their home stadiums. There are similar agreements with eight major-league soccer teams.</p>
        <p>''We think it's a great grass-roots tool to promote baseball and the New York Mets to a very targeted audience, boys and girls who play Little League,'' said Mark Bingham, the Mets' senior vice president for marketing and broadcasting.</p>
        <p>Why tie the program to Pepsi-Cola, a sugary, carbonated drink, and not water or fruit juice, which Pepsi also markets? Dawn Hudson, the company's senior vice president for advertising and marketing, said the point was to build connections in people's minds between Pepsi and baseball.</p>
        <p>''We're supporting the future stars of baseball who are in Little League,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''It's not a short-term volume kind of program. We certainly see results with brand recognition, and kids who participate feel more positive about Pepsi than kids who don't.''</p>
        <p>The company's keen desire is to generate interest in Pepsi-Cola, a brand that like its archrival Coca-Cola, has been trailing off in recent years as consumers discover alternatives, ranging from iced tea to juice to sports drinks. The idea is ''brand-building at the heart of the echo-boomer market,'' Ms. Hudson said, referring to the wave of children born in the last decade or so to the baby boom generation, whose members are now in their 40's and 50's.</p>
        <p>Tie-ins with local supermarket chains are also in the works, she added, and Pizza Hut, once part of the PepsiCo empire, has been included in the program. Coupons for a free pizza, which are supposed to be given to the player who shows the most sportsmanlike conduct, are included in the baseball packages.</p>
        <p>In subsequent innings, so to speak, Pepsi may offer its bottled water as part of the program, Ms. Hudson said. ''We are testing the possibility of having Aquafina during the game,'' she said. ''But we want to make sure we don't dilute the impact of Pepsi by offering Aquafina.''</p>
        <p>Katie Lacey, Pepsi's director of sports and grass-roots marketing, said the company had been able to appeal to baseball's administrators by pointing out that the two had common goals. ''We're both trying to stay very relevant to youth,'' she said. ''This is one great example of how we can jointly market to achieve our mutual objectives.''</p>
        <p>This year's version of the program has increased the number of teams participating, ranging from the sandlots of Kinston, N.C., to the greenswards of Anaheim Hills, Calif.</p>
        <p>''At this point, we are penetrating something on the order of 15 percent of teams,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''If 25 percent wanted to participate, we'd accelerate it. We want it to be part of growing up in America.''</p>
        <p>Some parents may worry that this is one more broadside that marketers are taking at childhood. Many schools have signed exclusive deals with Pepsi, Coke and other soft drink companies, which lock them into serving one brand or another in vending machines, for example. Critics say schools should be off limits to corporate efforts to win over consumers; baseball diamonds and soccer fields seem to occupy a gray area as far as children and commercialism are concerned.</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola, meanwhile, has come up with a related effort linking baseball to its products that zeroes in on New York City. And its particular focus is Hispanic families, with programs called Batea la Sed, or Bat Your Thirst, and Familia de Beisbol, the Baseball Family.</p>
        <p>Ron Magliocco, Coke's promotions manager for New York, said that Batea La Sed featured baseball skills contests for 13-  to 16-year-olds in parks citywide. The most recent contest was held in Brooklyn on June 25.</p>
        <p>''We go to a league president and say, 'Here is great added value, a great thing for you to bring your kids from Coca-Cola,' '' Mr. Magliocco said. Coaches can register up to 50 players, who then take turns batting, running and pitching by age group. The winners get ''goodie bags'' from Coke, Mr. Magliocco said, and free tickets to Yankees games. Coke has an exclusive contract for Yankee Stadium, meaning that only Coke soft drinks are served there (although Cracker Jack, made by PepsiCo's Frito-Lay division, is still permitted).</p>
        <p>The onlookers get samples of Coke and other promotional items, he added. The Familia de Beisbol program features players from different Spanish-speaking countries, including Venezuela, Mexico and the Dominican Republic. The players appear in posters hung inside stores and on Coke vans driven around neighborhoods like Inwood and Bushwick.</p>
        <p>Through their tie-ins to baseball and soccer, both Coke and Pepsi seem determined to win new consumers by appealing to them while they are playing sports. Marketers have learned, the hard way, that younger consumers don't necessarily listen to TV commercials or develop brand preferences easily.</p>
        <p>''We've got to be there on a number of fronts to grow the brands,'' Ms. Hudson said. And tying a soft drink to a baseball game, or a soccer match, and celebration seems to play well with parents, she added. ''Right or wrong,'' she said, ''kids drink soda.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
