<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; The new economy's 'network society' plays by old-economy rules.</title>
    <meta content="Y06SCE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Great Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Co of America (A&amp;p)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Madrick, Jeff</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DD1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; The new economy's 'network society' plays by old-economy rules.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeff Madrick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Madrick, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Madrick (Economic Scene) column on how new economy's 'computer nework society' is playing by old-economy rules to attract business and profits; says advantages of economies of scale were learned well in late 1800's by many companies and in many industries; says Great Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Co in late 1800's used positive feedback loops to expand its supermarket chain as well as big steel companies; says same economies of scale that worked in late 1800's and throughout most of 1900's may also be creating rapid productivity gains in new economy; holds new companies are selling standardized products to enormous mass markets, just as in good old days; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the relentless search to find something unprecedented in the new economy, many business gurus, and even some well-trained economists, now say that the theoretical principles underlying it are novel as well. Don't bet on it. Increasingly, it looks as if old-economy principles are saving the day.</p>
        <p>The main claim is that we now live in a ''network society,'' one in which profits and economic growth can reach heights that will make other industrial revolutions seem pallid. Lawrence H. Summers, the Treasury secretary, displayed just such new-age thinking in a speech this spring. Citing an example used by many a new-economy guru, he noted that one fax machine is useless, but when we have two and more, we have a network. If there are 100,000 fax machines, we have 10 billion possible relationships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the relentless search to find something unprecedented in the new economy, many business gurus, and even some well-trained economists, now say that the theoretical principles underlying it are novel as well. Don't bet on it. Increasingly, it looks as if old-economy principles are saving the day.</p>
        <p>The main claim is that we now live in a ''network society,'' one in which profits and economic growth can reach heights that will make other industrial revolutions seem pallid. Lawrence H. Summers, the Treasury secretary, displayed just such new-age thinking in a speech this spring. Citing an example used by many a new-economy guru, he noted that one fax machine is useless, but when we have two and more, we have a network. If there are 100,000 fax machines, we have 10 billion possible relationships.</p>
        <p>Because of such networks, the argument goes, profitability does not diminish as investment expands. (Diminishing returns are supposedly old-economy ideas.) Rather, there are now ''positive feedback loops'' because it costs so little, sometimes almost nothing, to reach a new customer or make a new connection. Thus, the bigger the network, the higher the returns on investment. The ultimate network is, of course, the World Wide Web and the countless private Internet-like systems run by large corporations and institutions.</p>
        <p>But how new is all this? Has the Treasury secretary ever heard of telephones? Or television? Or A.&amp; P., for that matter, which was started in the late 1800's? Granted, television and A.&amp; P. were not the sort of networks that could isolate 25 or 2,500 people, as ideally may happen on the Net. But the basic economic advantage was the same: positive feedback loops. One A.&amp; P was only a large mom-and-pop store. Two or more, and we had a network. With every additional outlet, the owners increasingly enjoyed the benefits of large-scale purchases of inventories, aggressive advertising and the mass distribution of their product. The more they invested, the lower their average costs.</p>
        <p>Or consider steel. In 1880, steel rails cost about $68 a ton to produce. But largely because of economies of scale, the price fell to about $18 a ton by 1900. The fixed cost to put up a modern steel mill was high, but the cost of producing extra rails was small. Thus, the more rails that could be sold, the lower the average cost for each ton. Those who sold the most could underprice the competition, spend more on marketing and lower costs still more.</p>
        <p>The same economies of scale that worked in the late 1800's and throughout most of the 1900's may also be creating rapid productivity gains in the new economy. New companies are selling standardized products to enormous mass markets, just as in the good old days. Industry after industry back then exploited the advantages of scale, from petroleum companies to cigarette manufacturers to rail lines to automakers to retail chains. Huge companies came to dominate their markets.</p>
        <p>In the new economy, standardization and economies of scale are clearly back. It is too early to get precise data on this. Moreover, many of these new economies of scale are being earned in service industries, and as John Kwoka, a George Washington University economist, points out, the government does not gather data about them.</p>
        <p>But has there ever been a more standardized product in America than MS-DOS, Microsoft's operating system, or Windows? Consider today's most successful companies -- Microsoft, Cisco Systems, America Online, Oracle, Sun Microsystems, Dell Computers, eBay and so on. All have enormous shares of their particular markets, and all enjoy economies of scale based on standardized (if complex) products. The more these companies sell, the higher their productivity as they reduce labor costs per unit to a minimum. The national economic data shows that most of the outsize gains in productivity are being created in just such computer and software companies.</p>
        <p>Technologists tell us it will be the next generation of software that will ultimately connect the niche markets. My guess is that true profitability will continue to come to those businesses that sell products with the broadest appeal. AOL wants more subscribers, eBay more participants and Amazon.com hopes to reach the huge critical mass needed to make it profitable at last. In fact, the Internet probably gives even more advantage to large companies than they had in the past because the nonmarketing costs of reaching one additional customer are virtually nil. The real advantage will be to those companies that either have a piece of technology that cannot be duplicated or can afford to advertise aggressively enough to win brand-name recognition in the mass market.</p>
        <p>For antitrust authorities, old questions, not new ones, are being raised. The new networks give rise to monopolies. But the economic benefits of such big business should not be underestimated. Through economies of scale, stable markets, uniform standards, investment in R &amp; D, and permanent, well-trained labor forces, big business has long been a boon to America.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, monopolies can go too far by suppressing innovation and keeping prices high. Especially now that size may have a renewed advantage, the antitrust authorities are correct to be vigilant. Moreover, there are other traditional concerns. In the pursuit of more scale, mergers among media companies threaten principles of free speech. The consolidation of financial services makes us more vulnerable to crisis. The concentration of wealth has skewed political power toward the rich.</p>
        <p>The real niche economy was the one started by Japanese auto companies in the late 1970's. Consumers demanded a wide choice of products, and our sleepy big businesses did respond, albeit slowly, with innovative ways to meet these needs more productively. But they could not raise productivity as rapidly as they did in the more standardized century between the Civil War and the 1970's. In my view, this contributed to America's historically slow growth from the 1970's to the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1990's, that changed radically. Business again made standardized products that corporations and consumers craved in mass volume. For good and ill, welcome back the old economy.</p>
        <p>This column appears here every Thursday. Jeff Madrick is the editor of Challenge Magazine and adjunct professor of social sciences at Cooper Union. Four economic analysts -- Mr. Madrick, Virginia Postrel, Alan B. Krueger and Hal R. Varian -- rotate as contributors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column appears here every Thursday. Jeff Madrick is the editor of Challenge Magazine and adjunct professor of social sciences at Cooper Union. Four economic analysts -- Mr. Madrick, Virginia Postrel, Alan B. Krueger and Hal R. Varian -- rotate as contributors.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
