<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Landlord Sues Tenant Advocates in Bronx</title>
    <meta content="06ACOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rosenberg Diamond Development Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bronx Acorn (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF1F39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Landlord Sues Tenant Advocates in Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rosenberg Diamond Development Corp sues Bronx Acorn, tenant advocacy group that has accused landlord of neglecting serious problems at several of its 49 apartment buildings; charges libel, trespassing and extortion; Acorn has held protests at company headquarters and some of its properties; denies charges (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Bronx tenant advocacy group that has conducted aggressive protests against landlords has been sued by a landholder that accuses the group of libel, trespassing and extortion.</p>
        <p>The landholder, Rosenberg Diamond Development Corporation, has for months been accused by the tenant group, Bronx Acorn, of neglecting serious problems at several of its 49 apartment buildings. To state its case, the group has conducted protests at the company's headquarters in the Bronx and at some of its properties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Bronx tenant advocacy group that has conducted aggressive protests against landlords has been sued by a landholder that accuses the group of libel, trespassing and extortion.</p>
        <p>The landholder, Rosenberg Diamond Development Corporation, has for months been accused by the tenant group, Bronx Acorn, of neglecting serious problems at several of its 49 apartment buildings. To state its case, the group has conducted protests at the company's headquarters in the Bronx and at some of its properties.</p>
        <p>In the lawsuit, filed June 21 in State Supreme Court in the Bronx, Rosenberg Diamond said Bronx Acorn had libeled and slandered the company, trespassed on its property, vandalized its buildings, interfered with brokers trying to rent vacant apartments and extorted money from tenants.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg Diamond's lawyers plan to ask tomorrow that Justice George Friedman permanently bar Acorn from trying to organize tenant groups in its apartment buildings.</p>
        <p>''We've been taking this for quite a while,'' said Robert Rosenberg, chairman of Rosenberg Diamond. ''They've been harassing us, and we finally feel that Acorn has crossed the line. They're intimidating us, harassing us and trying to extort us. We're actually suing just to protect our interests.''</p>
        <p>The suit accuses the group, which has an office on Walton Avenue in the South Bronx, of trying to force Rosenberg Diamond to turn over management of some of its properties to Acorn. The suit, which names as defendants two current Acorn organizers, two former organizers, one former board member and the group itself, seeks $16 million in compensation.</p>
        <p>Clare Crawford, Acorn's organizer in the Bronx, said the accusations were false. She said Acorn workers had not trespassed, but had been invited into the buildings by tenants.  She said the group's fliers accusing Rosenberg Diamond of allowing bad conditions, from peeling paint to rat infestation, were true. As for the charges of extortion, Ms. Crawford  said that Acorn asked tenants to contribute $5 a month voluntarily, but that no one was forced to pay.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crawford, who was not named in the suit, said that Acorn, with its membership drives, dues and protests, was modeled after labor unions, and that Rosenberg Diamond's suit was comparable to old corporate union-busting tactics.</p>
        <p>''Our point of view is that just when unions are organizing a work site or a factory, corporations go to extremes to destroy an organization, to stop them from organizing,'' she said. ''And this to me seems like the same kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>Acorn does not deny using aggressive, unorthodox methods in trying to prod Rosenberg Diamond to make repairs to buildings the group has considered poorly maintained. Acorn (the name is an acronym for Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now) is a 30-year-old nonprofit organization with offices in 30 cities, and agitates for better housing, improved schools and fairer lending practices.</p>
        <p>Since 1997, Bronx Acorn has organized tenant groups in 11 Rosenberg Diamond buildings, Ms. Crawford said. In that time, when Acorn organizers and tenants thought Rosenberg Diamond had failed to satisfy requests for maintenance and repairs, they occupied Rosenberg Diamond's offices at 1919 Williamsbridge Road, protested in front of buildings and took reporters into apartments in poor repair.</p>
        <p>''We understand that it's much easier for a landlord to defend himself in a courtroom than in his office or his apartment building when he's faced with 30 or 40 or more tenants,'' said Heather Appel, an organizer and a defendant named in the suit.</p>
        <p>Rosenberg Diamond has strenuously disputed Acorn's contentions. Company officials say they have spent millions of dollars repairing roofs, boilers, bathrooms and hallways in several buildings, including some Acorn has complained about.  ''We have a very good track record,'' Mr. Rosenberg said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenberg said his company had been instrumental in the revival of neighborhoods damaged by fire in the 1970's. ''Ever since the renaissance of the Bronx began, we've been involved in it,'' Mr. Rosenberg said. ''And we're proud of it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
