<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani, the Noncandidate, Faces New Scrutiny in 2 Books</title>
    <meta content="06BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrett, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirtzman, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rudy! An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EFD81E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani, the Noncandidate, Faces New Scrutiny in 2 Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wayne Barrett's new book Rudy! An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani, on mayor's private life, and Andrew Kirtzman's Rudy Giuliani: Emperor of the City, on his two terms as New York mayor, both planned for issue during his expected Senate race, are now about man of uncertain political future; both authors hold he remains important subject despite dropping out of race; Barrett's book, which claims that Giuliani's family had mob ties and that his father was jailed for armed robbery, raises questions about why Giuliani, former prosecutor, became so tough on crime; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They were supposed to be the hot properties of a big New York summer: two books about the private and public lives of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, published in the middle of his incendiary Senate campaign against the first lady. Instead, Wayne Barrett's ''Rudy! An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani'' and Andrew Kirtzman's ''Rudy Giuliani: Emperor of the City'' are now about a man of uncertain political future with only 18 months left in office.</p>
        <p>Basic Books, the publisher of Mr. Barrett, has cut back its planned first printing to 45,000 copies from 100,000 since Mr. Giuliani dropped out of the race citing his prostate cancer. William Morrow, the publisher of Mr. Kirtzman, is printing 40,000 books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They were supposed to be the hot properties of a big New York summer: two books about the private and public lives of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, published in the middle of his incendiary Senate campaign against the first lady. Instead, Wayne Barrett's ''Rudy! An Investigative Biography of Rudolph Giuliani'' and Andrew Kirtzman's ''Rudy Giuliani: Emperor of the City'' are now about a man of uncertain political future with only 18 months left in office.</p>
        <p>Basic Books, the publisher of Mr. Barrett, has cut back its planned first printing to 45,000 copies from 100,000 since Mr. Giuliani dropped out of the race citing his prostate cancer. William Morrow, the publisher of Mr. Kirtzman, is printing 40,000 books.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Giuliani at any stage is rich material, as both authors said yesterday. ''His future is uncharted water,'' said Mr. Barrett, an investigative reporter at The Village Voice. ''I don't think he's going to disappear into the sunset with sailboats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman, a political reporter for New York 1, agreed. ''His interest, I'm convinced, has been on the presidency,'' he said. ''Maybe that dream is gone, maybe it isn't. But he'll run for something again.''</p>
        <p>Although City Hall watchers will not find any news that dramatically changes the perception of the mayor, the books contain revelations that fill out the picture of his two terms at City Hall and introduce new complexity into Mr. Giuliani's past. Mr. Barrett's book, which claims that relatives of the mayor were connected to the mob and that his father spent time in Sing Sing prison for armed robbery, also raises questions about why Mr. Giuliani, a former federal prosecutor, became so tough on crime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett reports that Lewis D'Avanzo, a first cousin of the mayor's, was ''a ruthless and widely feared mob associate in charge of a massive stolen car ring'' who was killed by F.B.I. agents in Brooklyn in 1977. Mr. Barrett attributes much of his information to F.B.I. documents. Yesterday, he also made available court and prison papers backing up his information about the mayor's father on the Smoking Gun, a Web site that features uncovered government documents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett's book makes it clear that Mr. Giuliani was not close to Mr. D'Avanzo, even though he did invite Mr. D'Avanzo to his 1968 wedding to Regina Peruggi, his first wife.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman, whose book focuses on Mr. Giuliani's two terms as mayor, reports that after Deputy Mayor Rudy Washington -- the highest-ranking black at City Hall -- was stopped and questioned twice by the police for what Mr. Washington said were racial reasons, the Giuliani administration responded in an unusual way. It provided Mr. Washington with his own police identification badge, Mr. Kirtzman reports, and urged him to keep it with him at all times.</p>
        <p>''The administration's own racial profiling was thus taken care of quietly,'' Mr. Kirtzman writes. Mr. Washington did not return telephone calls yesterday seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman also reports that after the police shooting of Amadou Diallo, City Hall aides were so worried about Mr. Giuliani's unapologetic response that they persuaded him to attend a focus group of city residents intended to identify the public's deepest feelings about him. Grudgingly, Mr. Giuliani attended the session in April 1999, watching with his advisers through a two-way mirror as an all-white group of New Yorkers picked apart what they said was the mayor's insensitive response to the shooting.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Kirtzman writes, Mr. Giuliani exploded, venting his anger at his pollster, Frank Luntz. ''This is a waste of time!'' Mr. Kirtzman quotes Mr. Giuliani as yelling. ''I've learned nothing from this. I am not going to turn against the police.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Luntz said yesterday that he had no comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirtzman devotes an entire chapter of his book to Cristyne Lategano-Nicholas, the mayor's former communications director and at the time one of the most powerful people in his administration. Citing unnamed mayoral aides, Mr. Kirtzman writes that Ms. Lategano-Nicholas encouraged the mayor to avoid events with black audiences, fearing that he would be booed.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Ms. Lategano-Nicholas dismissed the information. ''It's not true,'' she said. ''And if you want to elaborate on my quotes, when unnamed sources are finally named, I will respond further.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's press secretary, Sunny Mindel, said yesterday that ''the mayor hasn't seen these books, he's not going to read these books and he has no comment.''</p>
        <p>The books are to be available in bookstores next week. Although Mr. Kirtzman's book was originally scheduled to be published in August and Mr. Barrett's in September -- just when the Giuliani-Clinton Senate race was expected to heat up -- both publishers scurried to get them out earlier after Mr. Giuliani withdrew.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kirtzman's book centers on government, Mr. Barrett's is more about Mr. Giuliani's private life. One of his more intimate revelations, included in an excerpt in Talk magazine, is that Donna Hanover, the mayor's estranged wife, long ago moved to an attic apartment in Gracie Mansion. The two are seeking a legal separation, but Ms. Hanover has said that she and the couple's two children will remain there for a few months.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Ms. Hanover's press secretary, Joannie Danielides, said that Mr. Barrett's account of the couple's living arrangements was inaccurate.</p>
        <p>''She lives in the master bedroom, as always,'' Ms. Danielides said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
