<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Settling In For Long Run At the Top</title>
    <meta content="06BROW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDC1E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Settling In For Long Run At the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>LEMONT, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clifton Brown Sports of The Times column on golfer Tiger Woods; holds he has solidified status as most magnetic figure in sports; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE territory that once belonged to Michael Jordan now belongs to Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>There is little doubt that Woods has replaced Jordan as the world's most famous active athlete. So it's fitting that Woods is playing in the Chicago area this week, returning to action for today's first round of the Advil Western Open at Cog Hill Golf and Country Club. On the heels of his record-setting 15-stroke victory at the United States Open last month, Woods has solidified his status as the most magnetic sports figure on the planet. Golf fanatics watch Woods. People who don't play golf watch Woods. People who don't even like golf watch Woods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE territory that once belonged to Michael Jordan now belongs to Tiger Woods.</p>
        <p>There is little doubt that Woods has replaced Jordan as the world's most famous active athlete. So it's fitting that Woods is playing in the Chicago area this week, returning to action for today's first round of the Advil Western Open at Cog Hill Golf and Country Club. On the heels of his record-setting 15-stroke victory at the United States Open last month, Woods has solidified his status as the most magnetic sports figure on the planet. Golf fanatics watch Woods. People who don't play golf watch Woods. People who don't even like golf watch Woods.</p>
        <p>Making history makes people pay attention. Serena and Venus Williams will make history today in the Wimbledon semifinals. They are the first sisters to play each other this late in a Grand Slam tournament in more than 100 years. And just as the Williams sisters have excelled in a sport in which members of minority groups have often felt lonely, Woods is showing a new generation of youngsters that they can excel in whatever sport they choose.</p>
        <p>By winning 12 of his last 21 starts on the PGA Tour, Woods has ended any debate about his ability. Nobody argues about whether Woods is the best golfer in the world. Instead, some people are asking this: Is Woods's dominance good or bad for golf?</p>
        <p>For golf, the thought of Woods winning golf tournaments for the next 20 years doesn't carry much downside. Just the presence of Woods at a tournament adds adrenaline to the atmosphere, just as Jordan added a special buzz to any basketball arena. When Jordan and the Chicago Bulls played the Los Angeles Clippers, the building still sold out. And when Woods tees it up today, as the defending champion he will draw thousands of additional fans.</p>
        <p>Undoubtedly, many of Woods's peers feel overshadowed at times, like Vijay Singh, who won the Masters in April and who is also in this week's field. But when a player commands the spotlight as Woods does, others simply fade into the background.</p>
        <p>Some players were envious of Woods and his lucrative endorsement deals when he first joined the tour in 1996, before he won a professional tournament. That reaction was natural. People forget that Jordan also suffered backlash from veterans when he first entered the National Basketball Association. Remember Jordan's first All-Star Game, when some of his Eastern Conference teammates froze him out and refused to pass him the ball? But through the years, Jordan earned the respect given to the game's best player, just as Woods has done. Today, Woods's competitors have a hard time working up much jealousy, because they understand how good he is.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how you could ever be tired of greatness,'' Jeff Sluman, who won the 1988 P.G.A. Championship, said when asked if he tired of talking about Woods. ''I think it's great for the Tour. I can't think of anybody else, except maybe the guy that hung up his No. 23 in town a few years ago, that would even compare to Tiger right now.''</p>
        <p>At age 24, in a sport where players can excel well into their 40's, Woods could have a run atop the sports world longer than Jordan did. And Woods plays an individual sport, giving him far greater control over his success than Jordan, who needed teammates to help him win championships.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, Woods met the N.B.A. stars Grant Hill of Detroit and Tim Duncan of San Antonio at the exclusive Isleworth community in Orlando, Fla., where Woods lives. Duncan  and Hill are being wooed by the Magic, and Hill is reportedly ready to sign with Orlando, tired of playing on mediocre teams with the Pistons.</p>
        <p>Woods is unfamiliar with long-term failure. He has won at every level, and he expects to win whenever he plays. While Woods is looking forward to the British Open later this month, with the chance to complete the career Grand Slam, he will not overlook this weekend, when he will be trying to win at Cog Hill for the third time in four years.</p>
        <p>''Do I turn the switch on and off?'' Woods asked yesterday, repeating a question. ''No. I always have it on. In order to play at the highest level, you've got to always have it on. I've tried to be a little more lightheaded on the golf course, but I just can't do it. It's just not the way I play my best.''</p>
        <p>So this week, golf fans in the Chicago area will have a chance to see another special athlete. Jordan had a great run with the Bulls. But Woods's reign at the top is beginning at an earlier age, and it could last even longer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
