<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARAFAT WILL MEET WITH BARAK IN U.S. FOR PEACE EFFORT</title>
    <meta content="06MIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ala, Abu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED81E39F935A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARAFAT WILL MEET WITH BARAK IN U.S. FOR PEACE EFFORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton says Prime Min Ehud Barak of Israel and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat will meet at Camp David on July 11 for summit aimed at helping them frame peace agreement they hope to reach by September; says both leaders will face 'most profound questions,' and that success is not guaranteed; Barak says meeting will be 'important moment' in history of Israeli-Palestinian negotiations; says he will seek separation from Palestinians and establishment of good-neighborliness with them; senior Palestinian negotiator Abu Ala accuses Clinton of bending to Israeli pressure; says he doubts summit will achieve any of its aims; Palestinians make clear that divisions between both sides are so great that more discussions are needed at lower level before convening leaders; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, have agreed to meet at Camp David next week for a summit conference intended to help them frame the peace agreement they hope to reach by September, President Clinton announced today.</p>
        <p>He said that the two leaders would face the ''most profound questions,'' and that success was not guaranteed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, have agreed to meet at Camp David next week for a summit conference intended to help them frame the peace agreement they hope to reach by September, President Clinton announced today.</p>
        <p>He said that the two leaders would face the ''most profound questions,'' and that success was not guaranteed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton extended his invitations by telephone on Monday for an opening session next Tuesday. He said that because teams of Israeli and Palestinian negotiators had been at an impasse for the last month, he had been left with no choice but to ask the two leaders to meet and take on the most difficult decisions themselves.</p>
        <p>''They're willing to give it their best shot,'' Mr. Clinton said in the press room at the White House. ''And they understand too that as we have already seen, delay tends to make these things worse, not better.''</p>
        <p>Despite his optimism, Mr. Clinton and his advisers refrained today from even listing the major issues the two leaders will tackle: the future status of Jerusalem, the fate of Palestinian refugees and the territorial shape of a Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Barak, faced with a fragile political coalition in his government, the summit meeting fulfills a strategy he has been urging on Mr. Clinton for several weeks. In Paris today, the Israeli prime minister spoke confidently of such a meeting as an ''important moment'' in the history of Israeli-Palestinian negotiations. He said he would seek ''separation from the Palestinians and the establishment of good-neighborliness with them.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, Abu Ala, the speaker of the Palestinian legislature and the senior Palestinian negotiator, contended today that Mr. Clinton had bent to Israeli pressure and that he doubted that the summit meeting would ''achieve any of its aims.''</p>
        <p>The Palestinians had made clear they believed that the divisions between the two sides were so great that more discussion was needed at a lower level before convening the leaders. In Ramallah last week, speaking with Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright at his side, Mr. Arafat made it clear that he would go to a summit meeting if invited, but reluctantly.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Clinton, a successful outcome would cap his foreign policy achievements, giving him several accomplishments in the Middle East. He has overseen a series of Israeli-Palestinian agreements starting with a handshake between Mr. Arafat and Yitzhak Rabin, the late Israeli Prime Minister, on the White House lawn in September 1993.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's senior foreign policy aides, including Dr. Albright and his national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger, met at Camp David on Monday and decided that it was ''now or never,'' a senior official said.</p>
        <p>They concluded, the official said, that little was to be gained by waiting and that by sequestering the two leaders in the relaxed atmosphere of Camp David, a positive outcome was not out of the question.</p>
        <p>A heavy influence on the decision on Monday, according to the senior official, was the date of Sept. 13. Mr. Arafat's Palestinian Central Council reaffirmed a few days ago that he would unilaterally declare a Palestinian state on that day if a peace agreement was not reached by then.</p>
        <p>With that threat, which the administration knew would prompt retaliation by the Israelis and annexation of settlements on the West Bank, the risk of increasing violence was unacceptably high, the official said.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to slide into that period when things begin to unravel in anticipation,'' he said, alluding to Sept. 13.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Arafat's threat to declare a Palestinian state and the emerging image of his being almost dragged to the summit, administration officials said they believed that the Palestinian leader preferred to have a state recognized by Israel.</p>
        <p>Unilaterally declaring a state on 40 percent of the West Bank that has been handed over to the Palestinians so far would be a ''mixed bag'' for Mr. Arafat, the senior official said, adding, ''That is a prescription for turmoil, and he understands that.''</p>
        <p>The administration has set no deadlines for the summit meeting and has left open the possibility of a second stage.</p>
        <p>The two teams of negotiators are to arrive in Washington during the weekend, followed on Monday night by Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is to leave Washington for Okinawa, Japan, on July 19 for a summit meeting of the leading industrial nations, known as the Group of 7. Russia will also attend, and the president is to meet with its leader, Vladimir V. Putin.</p>
        <p>''I hope we would have some clarity before that,'' the official said of July 19, but added, ''We will face that when and if we get to it.''</p>
        <p>In looking at the task at Camp David, Mr. Clinton said: ''We all know what the deal is. We know what the issues are. We know at least within a range what the options are. I think if we work hard, we can get it done in several days, but I will give it whatever time is required, as long as we're still moving forward.''</p>
        <p>After the announcement, a senior official said that by mentioning ''the deal,'' Mr. Clinton was not referring to a specific outcome but rather to the fact that the negotiators know the broad outlines of the ''story.'' The talks are likely to take more than the ''several days'' described by the president, a senior official said.</p>
        <p>A series of leaks in Israeli newspapers, which were intended to put pressure on Mr. Barak not to make significant concessions to the Palestinians, outlined the shape of what a final agreement would look like. The newspaper accounts were not definitively denied by the Israeli government, and they conformed with accounts given by diplomats from the region in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>In essence, the accounts said the future of the Palestinian refugees scattered across the Middle East could be settled by financial support from the international community -- perhaps as much as $100 billion over 20 years -- enabling them either to stay where they are or to emigrate to other countries.</p>
        <p>They also said differences were beginning to be narrowed on the size of the Palestinian state -- about 90 or 92 percent of the West Bank -- with about 40,000 Israeli settlers having to be evacuated from the West Bank.</p>
        <p>But the issue of Jerusalem remains the biggest sticking point, the diplomats said. The Israeli accounts said Mr. Barak was contemplating conceding Arab neighborhoods in Jerusalem to Palestinian control. The Palestinians would have a capital in Jerusalem based outside the current municipal boundary in Abu Dis.</p>
        <p>But Palestinian negotiators and Arab diplomats have said that in the Palestinian mind, Abu Dis is not part of Jerusalem and that therefore the proposal is not sufficient. ''Jerusalem for every Arab and every Muslim is the holy city -- it's not Abu Dis,'' one of the diplomats said. ''It's the walled city, and this is where you have to find a creative solution.''</p>
        <p>Further, the diplomats said, it is highly unlikely that Mr. Arafat will sign an agreement that did not include a settlement on Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>In choosing Camp David as the site for the summit meeting, Mr. Clinton is investing about the highest prestige possible for the gathering.</p>
        <p>The first Camp David summit meeting, called in 1978 by President Carter between President Anwar el-Sadat of Egypt and Prime Minister Menachem Begin of Israel, concluded a framework for a peace treaty between the two nations as well as a broader framework for peace in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The idea for the setting originally came from Mr. Carter's wife, Rosalyn, who thought that the wooded retreat would provide an undisturbed atmosphere for the two leaders, who by July 1978 had been deadlocked for months in their negotiations. After 12 days that mixed high emotions with tedious detail work, the agreements were reached.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton reflected today on the difficult dynamics of summit meetings. ''The objective is often overshadowed, I might say, as all of you know, by the abject dreariness of the pursuit,'' he said. ''The ups and downs of the process, the daily hassles and disputes, the open-ended nature of the negotiations -- all of these over time have blurred the vision of what it is we are trying to achieve.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Sharansky Offers to Resign</p>
        <p>JERUSALEM, July 5 (By The New York Times) -- Interior Minister Natan Sharansky, who heads a Russian immigrant party, said at an immigrant rally here today that he would tender his resignation from the government at Sunday's Cabinet meeting, two days before the Camp David summit meeting is to begin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharansky has been uncomfortable with Prime Minister Barak's peace moves, and he made his announcement at a rally opposing territorial concessions to the Palestinians. If Mr. Sharansky withdraws his four-seat party, Mr. Barak will still retain a majority in Parliament, though a slim one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
