<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Following Florio's Game Plan Is an Odd Strategy for Franks</title>
    <meta content="02POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Bob (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florio, James J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DE1639F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Following Florio's Game Plan Is an Odd Strategy for Franks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Iver Peterson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iver Peterson On Politics column on tactics being used by Repr Bob Franks, New Jersey Republican Senate nominee; says they are eerily similar to those employed by Democrat Jim Florio during primary to flush Jon Corzine into open (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He writes ''Dear Jon'' letters that his opponent, Jon Corzine, never answers. He accuses Mr. Corzine of using his millions to buy the election. He demands debates hither and yon, though Mr. Corzine spurns him. He demands that Mr. Corzine release his tax returns, only to have Mr. Corzine ignore him.</p>
        <p>Jim Florio trying to flush Mr. Corzine out into the open in last month's Democratic Senate primary? No, it's the Republican nominee, Representative Bob Franks, trying to flush out Mr. Corzine, the winner of the Democratic primary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He writes ''Dear Jon'' letters that his opponent, Jon Corzine, never answers. He accuses Mr. Corzine of using his millions to buy the election. He demands debates hither and yon, though Mr. Corzine spurns him. He demands that Mr. Corzine release his tax returns, only to have Mr. Corzine ignore him.</p>
        <p>Jim Florio trying to flush Mr. Corzine out into the open in last month's Democratic Senate primary? No, it's the Republican nominee, Representative Bob Franks, trying to flush out Mr. Corzine, the winner of the Democratic primary.</p>
        <p>The similarities are downright eerie:</p>
        <p>*On May 18, Mr. Florio listed eight places he wanted to debate Mr. Corzine, and on June 20, Mr. Franks challenged Mr. Corzine to attend eight debates after giving up on the idea of holding a debate in each of the state's 21 counties.</p>
        <p>*On May 17, Mr. Florio demanded that Mr. Corzine release his tax returns. (Mr. Corzine gave out only summaries, saying release of the full reports would harm his former partners at Gold, Sachs and Company.) About a month later, Mr. Franks does the same.</p>
        <p>*Mr. Florio said his opponent was spending $34 million to buy the nomination; now Mr. Franks is saying that Mr. Corzine is planning to spend $50 million in the general election.</p>
        <p>So, early in campaign for the United State Senate, Mr. Franks is clearly reading from Mr. Florio's game plan, and this suggests a question: if attacking Mr. Corzine for his wealth,  his unreleased tax returns and his front-runner's instinct to limit debate didn't work for Mr. Florio, what makes Mr. Franks think it will work for him?</p>
        <p>The Franks campaign knows that these early skirmishes resemble Mr. Florio's tactics, but they are not bothered by the comparison. Instead, they believe that shots by the well-known former governor, which Mr. Corzine once deflected, may be harder for him to duck in a general election against a relative unknown.</p>
        <p>Take Mr. Corzine's reluctance to debate. From the Democrat's point of view, it makes sense. The latest Quinnipiac Poll, which was released last Wednesday, has Mr. Corzine ahead of Mr. Franks by 46 to 26 percent of the vote, and the former Wall Street executive sees no reason to increase Mr. Franks's visibility by appearing with him.</p>
        <p>But the Franks campaign believes that as the voters' attention shifts from the primaries to the general election, Mr. Corzine's advantages will fade.</p>
        <p>Initially, Jon Corzine was a novelty, said Charlie Smith, Mr. Franks's campaign spokesman. But over time voters naturally become more concerned with the substance of a candidate, Mr. Smith said, and debates offer a candidate the opportunity to prove that substance.</p>
        <p>Maurice Carroll, director of the Quinnipiac University Polling Institute, also pointed out that the primary election may have been an easier contest for Mr. Corzine to orchestrate. It was, after all, a contest between committed party members who were choosing what they hoped would be a winner. General election voters are different, Mr. Carroll said.</p>
        <p>''In a general election, you have your bedrock Republicans who are always going to vote Republican and the bedrock Democrats who are always going to vote for the Democrat, and you fight over the people in between,'' he said. ''And those people may respond to a message that Corzine is hiding behind his money.''</p>
        <p>In addition, as Mr. Carroll pointed out, Mr. Franks is not Mr. Florio. The former governor, a prickly, principled man who was given to lecturing voters, was just the kind of politician that editorial boards liked but that ordinary people were leery of. Given his somewhat negative image, it was harder for Mr. Florio to make mud stick. But the genial, non-confrontational Mr. Franks, it seems, is not disliked by anyone. Coming from a nice guy, the charges against Mr. Corzine may be more effective.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Corzine has a right to think that Mr. Franks's mimicking of Mr. Florio's attacks will misfire again. Polling during and after the primary asked all voters if they thought Mr. Corzine spending millions of his own money was bad, and generally they answered no.</p>
        <p>On June 18, for example, the Star Ledger/Eagleton Poll asked registered voters if they were bothered by Mr. Corzine's spending. While 43 percent said they were bothered a lot or a little, 52 percent said they were not bothered at all.</p>
        <p>In the same poll, 52 percent agreed that as a political newcomer, Mr. Corzine had to spend more to make himself known (and perhaps significantly, nearly half 47 percent of likely Franks supporters agreed that Mr. Corzine did what he had to do).</p>
        <p>Similarly, while 36 percent of respondents in the Eagleton Poll thought Mr. Corzine had bought the election, 53 percent thought he was only communicating his ideas and that voters responded to them.</p>
        <p>It is still early, and Mr. Franks is going to need to say more about Mr. Corzine than just his money. But after Labor Day, or more likely, after the Olympics in September, the presidential campaign and a titanic Senate battle in New York involving Hilary Rodham Clinton will swamp the airwaves in New Jersey, and Mr. Corzine's ability to spend on air time will again begin to dominate the race.</p>
        <p>So it is hardly surprising that Mr. Franks is trying to get some of his core points on the table during the summer, and to hope that what didn't work for Jim Florio will work for him.</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Iver Peterson reports from New Jersey for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
