<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Time Braves Fall Apart Early</title>
    <meta content="Y02BRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6D71539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Time Braves Fall Apart Early</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets 8-1 victory over Atlanta Braves discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All was right with the Braves' world shortly before 10 p.m. Friday, reinforced by the Shea Stadium scoreboard that showed their comfortable 8-1 lead. But that promise soon gave way to dread when the Mets scored 10 runs in the eighth as they rallied to an 11-8 victory.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, still infused with euphoria from Friday night's comeback, the Mets were bouncing off the walls and bounding around the bases as they grabbed a 7-0 lead in routing the Braves, 9-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All was right with the Braves' world shortly before 10 p.m. Friday, reinforced by the Shea Stadium scoreboard that showed their comfortable 8-1 lead. But that promise soon gave way to dread when the Mets scored 10 runs in the eighth as they rallied to an 11-8 victory.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, still infused with euphoria from Friday night's comeback, the Mets were bouncing off the walls and bounding around the bases as they grabbed a 7-0 lead in routing the Braves, 9-1.</p>
        <p>''The only thing I hate,'' Braves outfielder Brian Jordan said before yesterday's game, ''is that we gave them life.''</p>
        <p>Instead of taking a 2-0 series lead and securing a three-game lead in the National League East, the Braves faced a Mets team yesterday that carried renewed confidence.</p>
        <p>''They came out of the chute ready to go,'' Jordan said after the game yesterday. ''The momentum changed last night. They came into the game with a lot of confidence. You give Leiter a seven-run lead in two innings and he's a good pitcher and he's going to shut us down.''</p>
        <p>Al Leiter (10-1) struck out 12 for the Mets, squashing hope for the Braves to rebound from Friday. Their nightmare was only compounded when the four-time Cy Young award winner Greg Maddux (9-3) gave up six runs in the second inning.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't a matter of letting them roll all over us; those guys jumped all over us and took it away from us,'' Jordan said.</p>
        <p>Maddux's scheduled start for Thursday was delayed until yesterday because he was struck with a stomach virus. And though he denied he still felt sick, he was not himself yesterday. ''I felt fine,'' he said, ''I just got hit. No excuses.'' He added that he struggled to keep his pitches down.</p>
        <p>His 2-1 pitch to Benny Agbayani in the second inning did not hang, but Agbayani reached for the 80-mile-an-hour slider and socked it to left field. That home run was followed by a dizzying string of five hits.</p>
        <p>Leiter, who was as dominating yesterday as Maddux was debilitated, struck his counterpart's fastball for a single, a telling sign of the teams' reversal of fortune. After allowing back-to-back doubles to Melvin Mora and Derek Bell and a single to Edgardo Alfonzo, Maddux then gave up the devastating two-run home run, to Friday night's home run hero, Mike Piazza.</p>
        <p>''It's embarrassing really, to go out there and give your team a chance to win and then come in here to sit for two hours to think about why I didn't execute,'' Maddux said. ''I made a lot of mistakes and they didn't miss any.''</p>
        <p>The seven-run disaster was Maddux's shortest outing since Sept. 28, 1996. And it was the most runs the Mets had scored against Maddux since hammering him for seven runs in the fourth inning on Sept. 29 last year. He denied a Shea Stadium jinx, pointing out, along with his teammates, that this was only July.</p>
        <p>''I'm not worried about it,'' Braves Manager Bobby Cox said with a smile, ''it's a long season.''</p>
        <p>But Braves third baseman Chipper Jones, back from his day's absence watching the birth of his son, Larry Wayne Jones III, had this admission: ''This series could go a very long way towards creating a mental edge later on in the season. I think if we split in their home park, it could be considered a moral victory for us. We've got to win the series when we play at home.''</p>
        <p>The Braves are now showing vulnerability, and their troubles are typified by a split callus on John Rocker's thumb. Rocker has dealt with the sore since spring training; he can pitch for two days before he has to rest.</p>
        <p>Unable to pitch Friday, following his scoreless eighth inning on Thursday, Rocker wanted to go yesterday. ''There wasn't a question,'' he said. ''If the chance had been there, I would have had to suck it up somehow. Today was a big game, and tomorrow is an even bigger game.'' Rocker will be available today.</p>
        <p>Rocker's thumb is not the only injury in the bullpen. Joining the right-hander Kevin McGlinchy on the disabled list are the right-handers Rudy Seanez and Greg McMichael. ''We are just beat to death,'' Rocker said. And not just physically.</p>
        <p>''We let one get away last night and they pounded us today,'' outfielder Bobby Bonilla said. ''But I think the games in September will be a lot bigger than these are right now.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
