<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fight for Clean Elections</title>
    <meta content="02SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6D81439F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fight for Clean Elections</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says legislation restricting secret fund-raising in recently passed campaign finance reform measure is significant step forward, but more needs to be done; calls for broader disclosure requirements and ban on 'soft money' to political parties</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Congress has passed the first campaign finance reform in 21 years, Washington is filled with an air of self-congratulation. That is understandable. But the best way to celebrate is for principled lawmakers to press for broader disclosure requirements and a ban on ''soft money'' to political parties this year. The bill approved last week would force certain tax-exempt slush funds that run campaign ads to reveal their spending and financing sources. By the time it was approved, many opponents had jumped on board and were actually trying to claim credit for its passage. Their belated eagerness to get right on this issue should now be exploited to make more progress on purging American campaigns of special-interest money.</p>
        <p>The legislation restricting secret fund-raising was a significant step forward, but its impact should not be exaggerated. Some of the shadowy tax-exempt groups affected by the bill are now expected to transform themselves into for-profit shell corporations and continue their practices. Other nonprofit groups may also run ads. It is still legal for groups without tax exemptions to raise money and run sham campaign ads like the ones attacking Senator John McCain that were organized by donors to Gov. George W. Bush last March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that Congress has passed the first campaign finance reform in 21 years, Washington is filled with an air of self-congratulation. That is understandable. But the best way to celebrate is for principled lawmakers to press for broader disclosure requirements and a ban on ''soft money'' to political parties this year. The bill approved last week would force certain tax-exempt slush funds that run campaign ads to reveal their spending and financing sources. By the time it was approved, many opponents had jumped on board and were actually trying to claim credit for its passage. Their belated eagerness to get right on this issue should now be exploited to make more progress on purging American campaigns of special-interest money.</p>
        <p>The legislation restricting secret fund-raising was a significant step forward, but its impact should not be exaggerated. Some of the shadowy tax-exempt groups affected by the bill are now expected to transform themselves into for-profit shell corporations and continue their practices. Other nonprofit groups may also run ads. It is still legal for groups without tax exemptions to raise money and run sham campaign ads like the ones attacking Senator John McCain that were organized by donors to Gov. George W. Bush last March.</p>
        <p>The best way to clean up the system is embodied in the McCain-Feingold bill, which has been blocked by Trent Lott, the Republican Senate leader. It would outlaw soft money to political parties and prevent the use of corporate and union money for sham issue ads close to an election. Individuals financing such ads would be subject to disclosure requirements. Most senators support this approach, but not enough for the 60 votes needed to break the usual filibuster engineered by Mr. Lott and his fund-raiser in chief, Mitch McConnell.</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Lott dropped his opposition to the disclosure bill last week, it sailed through the Senate by a vote of 92 to 6. But earlier, when Mr. Lott was pressing Republicans to oppose it, eight Republicans not normally in favor of campaign reform voted for it. All are running for re-election this year, some in tough races, suggesting their sensitivity to voters on the issue. They should not now be allowed to go home and claim they are for clean campaigns unless they line up for more effective legislation. Over the holiday weekend, voters encountering Senators William Roth of Delaware, Rick Santorum of Pennsylvania and Spencer Abraham of Michigan can make this point.</p>
        <p>As for the constitutional arguments on reform, a darkly comic moment in the Senate last week should long be remembered for the way it revealed the hypocrisy involved. Mr. McConnell, a self-described expert on the Constitution, lectured his colleagues on the purported violations of the document in the slush-fund disclosure bill. Then, defying his own logic, he urged Republicans in tough re-election fights to vote for a bill he had just declared unconstitutional so they could avoid being tarred as anti-reform. Clearly, Mr. McConnell will say anything to hold onto power and also preserve the right of big money to buy influence in Washington.</p>
        <p>The other important lesson last week lay in the shattering of conventional wisdom. As usual, the politicians and Sunday talk-show pundits had assured one another that the disclosure bill had no chance this year. When will these so-called ''experts'' realize what a disservice they do by parroting the cynical spin control of those who live off the corrupt status quo? Again and again, Americans are lectured by these people that campaign reform is not a salient issue, even though Senator McCain ignited the voters with it earlier this year. Americans do care about campaign reform. Their desire for financially clean campaigns is one reason for the widespread cynicism among voters in recent years. If lawmakers want to push some of that cynicism back, they have only to listen to the people who sent them to office in the first place. Then we will see even more retreating by Mr. Lott and Mr. McConnell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
