<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Online Access To Stock Analysts</title>
    <meta content="MB021604" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING: DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ianalyst.Com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leder, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4D61439F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Online Access To Stock Analysts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE LEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leder, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ianalyst.com, new online securities-analysis company offers subscribers online access to its analysts staff; other Web sites offer access to stock analyses, but none previously has made direct online access to analysts a selling point; Ianalyst has four analysts at present and plans to hire an additional 25 by year end (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever wish you could ask a skillful stock analyst just how he or she arrived at a 12-month price target?</p>
        <p>Ianalyst.com, a new online company that furnishes what it describes as professional, independent research, is giving subscribers online access to its analyst staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever wish you could ask a skillful stock analyst just how he or she arrived at a 12-month price target?</p>
        <p>Ianalyst.com, a new online company that furnishes what it describes as professional, independent research, is giving subscribers online access to its analyst staff.</p>
        <p>The company has hired four former Wall Street analysts and plans to add an additional 25 by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''Equity analysts on Wall Street don't cater to individual investors,'' said Tin Albano, chief executive of Ianalyst. ''Can I, as an individual, get in touch with Mary Meeker, so that when she disses a stock, I can get in touch with her?'' he asked, referring to the influential technology analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Albano said subscribers would receive responses to their questions lickety-split. ''Waits will never be longer than 15 minutes to get an answer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Albano also noted that Ianalyst won't be doing deals. That independence, he said, means that Ianalyst's research will not suffer from the perceived conflicts of interest posed by having analysts and investment bankers working for the same company.</p>
        <p>Of course, any investor with a computer has access to reams of information, including professional Wall Street analysis. Multex.com, for example, provides scores of Wall Street research reports, many of them free. And some boutique firms, like  Spencer Clarke, provide free research by posting it on the World Wide Web.</p>
        <p>But nobody has previously made direct online access to analysts a main selling point. For now, Ianalyst's four analysts will function as generalists, fielding whatever investing questions are pitched their way. And they will post their reactions to market and other financial news in online forums.</p>
        <p>But soon, Mr. Albano said, they will begin issuing regular research reports that are complete with buy and sell ratings.</p>
        <p>Access to the Web site, which began operation on Friday, is free until the end of August; after that, the company plans to charge $14.95 a month. Ianalyst's initial focus will be on technology stocks, though it will expand its coverage to other areas as more analysts are hired, Mr. Albano said.</p>
        <p>MICHELLE LEDER</p>
        <p>INVESTING: DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
