<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critics Say Economy Hotels Would Tarnish the Area</title>
    <meta content="02HOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: TRIBECA/SOUTH STREET SEAPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro Five Hotel (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDB1739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critics Say Economy Hotels Would Tarnish the Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission opposes plan by Metro Five Hotel to build two economy hotels in landmark districts in TriBeCa and South Street Seaport areas of Manhattan; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An upstart hotelier from Queens is planning to build two economy hotels in landmark districts in TriBeCa and the South Street Seaport area. But the Landmarks Preservation Commission, whose approval is needed, says the buildings, as proposed, would tarnish the neighborhoods. It asks  that the designs be altered.</p>
        <p>The hotels would cater to budget-minded tourists and business travelers, said Sam Chang, a manager of Metro Five Hotel, which would build the hotels. The company recently opened its first hotel, a Comfort Inn franchise near Kennedy International Airport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An upstart hotelier from Queens is planning to build two economy hotels in landmark districts in TriBeCa and the South Street Seaport area. But the Landmarks Preservation Commission, whose approval is needed, says the buildings, as proposed, would tarnish the neighborhoods. It asks  that the designs be altered.</p>
        <p>The hotels would cater to budget-minded tourists and business travelers, said Sam Chang, a manager of Metro Five Hotel, which would build the hotels. The company recently opened its first hotel, a Comfort Inn franchise near Kennedy International Airport.</p>
        <p>Plans call for a 6-story hotel at the southwest corner of Church and Duane Streets in TriBeCa, a lot now used for parking, and an 11-story hotel at 320 Pearl Street, also a parking lot, a block south of the Brooklyn Bridge between Dover Street and Peck Slip. The 3,000-square-foot TriBeCa lot is only 25 feet wide, barely enough for two minivans bumper to bumper. The developer plans to squeeze in 66 rooms.</p>
        <p>Gene Kaufman, the hotels' architect, described the exterior as a modern interpretation of the area's 19th-century cast-iron and brick facades. The Duane Street side would be clad in limestone, and the Church Street face would be covered in limestone and white brick.</p>
        <p>''We have no problems with buildings coming in with a modern design, but it can't be gaudy,'' said Carole DeSaram, president of the TriBeCa Community Association.</p>
        <p>The other hotel would have 85 rooms nestled between a four-story post office and a five-story apartment house. The first seven floors would be screened in red brick, while the upper four floors, shaped like a pie wedge, would be coated in synthetic white polish.</p>
        <p>Although the overall design echoes a nearby six-story structure at 241 Water Street, residents oppose the hotel's imposing height. Community Board 1 voted unanimously against both designs.</p>
        <p>''There was consensus that the buildings did not fit the historic districts,'' said the board's district manager, Paul Goldstein.</p>
        <p>Despite the lack of support, the developers pressed their cases last Tuesday before the Landmarks Preservation Commission. Mr. Kaufman said the hotels ''maintained the character of the streets,'' but the commissioners questioned many aspects of the designs. Jennifer J. Raab, the commission's chairwoman, told Mr. Kaufman, ''Frankly, you have an uphill argument.''</p>
        <p>The commission said neither project would be approved without major changes.</p>
        <p>Howard Hornstein, a lawyer for Metro Five, said the company intended to resubmit revised blueprints next month.</p>
        <p>''It may be redesigned,'' he said outside the hearing, ''but these buildings will be built.''</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: TRIBECA/SOUTH STREET SEAPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
