<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hernandez And Posada Fire Up Yankees</title>
    <meta content="Y02YAN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D61539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hernandez And Posada Fire Up Yankees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., July 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 6-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jorge Posada and Orlando Hernandez were dressed in street clothes and waiting at the clubhouse door when their teammates came through, in single file, after their emotional victory today. Roger Clemens saw Posada and playfully shadowboxed, an allusion to the catcher's short but nasty brawl in the seventh inning.</p>
        <p>''Way to go, Duque,'' other Yankees shouted to Hernandez, who threw five and two-thirds innings after not knowing if his elbow trouble would prevent him from pitching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jorge Posada and Orlando Hernandez were dressed in street clothes and waiting at the clubhouse door when their teammates came through, in single file, after their emotional victory today. Roger Clemens saw Posada and playfully shadowboxed, an allusion to the catcher's short but nasty brawl in the seventh inning.</p>
        <p>''Way to go, Duque,'' other Yankees shouted to Hernandez, who threw five and two-thirds innings after not knowing if his elbow trouble would prevent him from pitching.</p>
        <p>The Yankees want to build on this 6-1 victory over Tampa Bay. Hernandez hopes to wake up Sunday and feel no pain in his elbow, and come back and pitch well again in five days. Perhaps Tino Martinez, who had a three-run double to finish off the Devil Rays, will put together more runs batted in in the days to come. Maybe the passion that Posada's fight generated will fuel a rebirth.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are a team needing a spark and maybe this was it. ''We needed this,'' Posada said.</p>
        <p>Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager said, ''It was a lift for everybody.''</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner seethed over Friday's 6-4 loss to Tampa Bay when he had lunch today with Torre and General Manager Brian Cashman. Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, asked questions, demanded answers and said afterward that he was accepting the assurances of Torre and Cashman that the team was good enough to win the World Series.</p>
        <p>Translated: Those guys tell me we're good enough, and they had better be right.</p>
        <p>They all agree that there is a need for pitching, the need for Hernandez and Clemens to come back this weekend -- Clemens pitches Sunday after coming off the disabled list -- and revitalize the rotation that has been so inconsistent that it has placed a strain on the bullpen. There were 13 instances in the Yankees' last 43 games that the starting pitcher did not finish the fifth inning. Torre dug deep into his bullpen again Friday, and today he held back David Cone from his usual bullpen session, just in case Hernandez's elbow trouble surfaced again.</p>
        <p>El Duque felt good warming up -- ''He felt strong,'' Posada said -- and contentiousness yanked Hernandez back into the world of pitching in the big leagues. After Tampa Bay's Russ Johnson stroked a leadoff double in the third, Hernandez became annoyed when Randy Winn called time out as Hernandez began to throw the ball. Hernandez flipped the ball high into the air and shot a glance at Winn, then fired a fastball inside, forcing him to jump out of the way.</p>
        <p>''A lot of guys started yelling at him'' from the Tampa Bay dugout, Posada said. Hernandez looked over his left shoulder at the Devil Rays' dugout and continued to stare, until Posada ran out and nudged Hernandez in the lower back with his glove, turning him away from the bench jockeys and back to the business at hand.</p>
        <p>The at-bat developed into a war of wills. Hernandez looked in for the sign, then stepped away from the rubber. Winn called time out. Hernandez shook off four signs and then stepped off the mound. El Duque was determined to control the pace of the at-bat, responding to every move Winn made, like a debater wanting to get in the last word. Winn tried to check his swing on a 2-1 pitch, but Umpire C. B. Bucknor called a strike, then ejected the third-base coach, Billy Hatcher, igniting a long argument. Winn's at-bat took about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>When Winn was ready to hit, Hernandez shook off four signs again, stepped away from the rubber, then threw a fastball and prompted Winn to fly out to center field. In this way, Hernandez and the Yankees gripped a 2-1 lead through six innings. Hernandez (7-6) allowed one run on four hits over five and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>With runners at second and third and one out in the Yankees seventh, Tampa Bay Manager Larry Rothschild ordered an intentional walk of Posada to get to Martinez, and the left-hander Mark Guthrie moved ahead in the count, 1-2.</p>
        <p>Guthrie spun a low breaking ball over the plate and Martinez pulled a soft liner into the right-field corner. All three runners scored, padding the Yankees' lead to 5-1. After reaching second on his double, Martinez hustled to third when a throw got away, and Willie Randolph, the Yankees' third-base coach, patted Martinez on the helmet. It was the second time this season that Martinez had three R.B.I. in a game.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay's Bobby Smith struck out to lead off the bottom of the seventh, and when Posada stepped in front of home plate to whip the ball to third, Smith pushed Posada discreetly with the barrel of his bat. Posada turned and jabbed the ball into Smith's side, and Smith and Posada immediately came together, wrestling each other to the ground. Posada was quickly on his back, with Smith flailing away with both hands.</p>
        <p>The benches cleared, and Posada and Smith were pulled apart. Posada kept pushing his tongue into his cheek, as if to feel for a cut. Both players were ejected.</p>
        <p>''I was just trying to throw the ball to third, and he just shoved me with his forearm,'' said Posada, who said he was not hurt. ''I didn't like that. I guess he can't strike out. So I pushed him back.''</p>
        <p>Smith said: ''I struck out and was walking away and I bumped him. I don't know if he thought it was on purpose or whatever, and he shoved me. Somebody pushes you -- are you just going to walk away from it?</p>
        <p>''I don't have any problem with anybody. I'm a nice guy.''</p>
        <p>Both face the possibility of suspension from Major League Baseball's primary enforcement official, Frank Robinson. ''I have a great deal of respect for Frank Robinson,'' Torre said. ''I would certainly like him to remember how many fights he was in and not be suspended.''</p>
        <p>But Torre seemed happy, pleased with the game; it was a good day all the way around. It will get even better if Hernandez wakes up Sunday without pain in his right elbow -- something he is worried about -- and if Clemens can pitch well, too, and the Yankees can turn around their season.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CHUCK KNOBLAUCH, the Yankees' second baseman, was scratched from the starting lineup because of an ear infection. He might miss Sunday's game as well.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
