<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lights, Action . . . Costumes</title>
    <meta content="02DUMM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Costumes, Theatrical</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pritikin, Gregory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trebay, Guy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dummy (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6D91739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lights, Action . . . Costumes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUY TREBAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trebay, Guy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Gregory Pritikin's in</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOSQUITOES zoomed in squadron-style as dusk curtained Whitestone, Queens. Paranoia suddenly seemed to fill the air with their sinister whine. In recent news accounts, this area had become identified with ground zero for West Nile virus: a local chicken had reportedly become infected with the disease. As it would later develop, the chicken was in the clear. But the actors filming the new indie movie ''Dummy'' had no way of knowing that. And they were not leaving flesh to fate.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting devoured,'' the actor Adrien Brody said, hiking the legs of his high-water pants and letting rip with a spray can of Off. Perched in a director's chair, Illeana Douglas swabbed Muskol on her naked forearms. On a lawn in front of a ''Sopranos''-style colonial house, Milla Jovovich engaged her boyfriend, John Frusciante, the guitarist of the Red Hot Chili Peppers, in a bug-proof lip lock. Moments later Mr. Frusciante was walking around the snack table dazedly, complaining that his mouth had gone numb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOSQUITOES zoomed in squadron-style as dusk curtained Whitestone, Queens. Paranoia suddenly seemed to fill the air with their sinister whine. In recent news accounts, this area had become identified with ground zero for West Nile virus: a local chicken had reportedly become infected with the disease. As it would later develop, the chicken was in the clear. But the actors filming the new indie movie ''Dummy'' had no way of knowing that. And they were not leaving flesh to fate.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting devoured,'' the actor Adrien Brody said, hiking the legs of his high-water pants and letting rip with a spray can of Off. Perched in a director's chair, Illeana Douglas swabbed Muskol on her naked forearms. On a lawn in front of a ''Sopranos''-style colonial house, Milla Jovovich engaged her boyfriend, John Frusciante, the guitarist of the Red Hot Chili Peppers, in a bug-proof lip lock. Moments later Mr. Frusciante was walking around the snack table dazedly, complaining that his mouth had gone numb.</p>
        <p>''Suck on one of these, honey,'' said Verna Hampton, a caterer who owns Verna's Vittles. Then she handed him one of the Blow Pops she had brought, ''to calm the masses,'' as she explained.</p>
        <p>There were no masses. There was a skeleton crew. There was a producer who drove to the set in a banged-up Golf. There was an unknown 29-year-old writer-director. There was a small cast of actors with unorthodox professional trajectories and Next Big Thing bios, all working for union scale.</p>
        <p>And there was a local family parading up and down 159th Street with a 4-year-old got up in tights and a cape. ''See that kid dressed as Batman?'' Gregory Pritikin, the director, asked. ''He was Superman 20 minutes ago.''</p>
        <p>''We can do Spider-Man, too, if you need him,'' the boy's father called out.</p>
        <p>The tale of Steven Schoichet, a maladroit suburbanite whose life is transformed when he comes into possession of a ventriloquist's prop, ''Dummy'' is the kind of movie Charlie McCarthy might have starred in if Michael Ovitz had been his agent. Nearly everyone else in the film is a client of Mr. Ovitz's firm, Artists Management Group, a noncoincidence that helps explain how a script by an obscure writer with a budget that wouldn't buy a two-bedroom in Chelsea happened to get this far.</p>
        <p>''Basically,'' said the English actor Jared Harris, who is part of the ''Dummy'' ensemble, ''Adrien was interested in doing it and A.M.G. helped it to happen. It's not as if they're shoving actors down producers' throats.''</p>
        <p>Far from it. A favorite of directors (at 27 he has already made films with Spike Lee, Steven Soderbergh, Terrence Malick and Ken Loach), Mr. Brody plays the lead role. Ms. Douglas is his older sister, a ''bitter wedding planner who wants to sing,'' she explained. Ms. Jovovich is a riot-grrrl type poetically named Fangora. Steven's crush, Lorena, is portrayed by Vera Farmiga, a newcomer whose anonymity should end by August, when three movies in which she acted -- with Robert De Niro, Edward Burns and Richard Gere -- are released.</p>
        <p>Reviewer code for films like ''Dummmy'' is ''quirky,'' a cliche that translates as, ''Where's Blockbuster going to file this one?'' Directors claim to hate the term. But let's face it, ''genius'' is about the only word directors enjoy seeing attached to their work.</p>
        <p>A reporter on the set of ''Dummy'' found himself wondering how performers get into their parts, how they inhabit characters who, say, live in demented households, talk through dummies, sing in rock groups called the Botanical Booger Ensemble and surreptitiously smash gifts at the weddings they stage. The visitor arrived expecting Stanislav skian responses. The answers he got  ran to a simpler concept: costume.</p>
        <p>''The first thing I think about with a character is how much money they make a year,'' said Ms. Douglas, who was not on call but was visiting the set to lend support. ''Then you know how they dress, and you don't put them in clothes they can't afford.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brody, Mr. Harris and Ms. Farmiga all made similar points about interpretation, not to mention, indirectly, about class.</p>
        <p>''My clothes are always very much in step with who the character is,'' said Mr. Brody, whose spiked Mohawk nearly upstaged his performance in Spike Lee's ''Summer of Sam.'' ''For 'Dummy,' we tried to find any article that could look boyish or could have been from his childhood wardrobe. Anything that was stylish we removed.'' Ms. Farmiga imagined her character, Lorena, as cautious, shy, hesitant, meek -- did someone say a dormouse?</p>
        <p>''She probably shops at Daffy's or Fashion Bug or Annie Sez,'' Ms. Farmiga said. ''We bought her shoes at Payless. And it all really influences the way you play the part because, for one thing, the shoes put your posture in a certain position and force you to walk in a certain way.''</p>
        <p>When an actor is in the right clothes, Mr. Harris said, ''it gets you a long way'' toward capturing the character. In Mr. Solondz's ''Happiness,'' Mr. Harris disappeared so deeply into the role of the wife-beating, womanizing, sleazeball Russian cabdriver that people who barely recognized him in the movie still talk to him about his character's 70's-style fake-snakeskin shirt.</p>
        <p>''When you've got the visual right, subconsciously you're already hitting certain marks about the character,'' Mr. Harris said. ''After 'Happiness,' people came up to me and said: 'That shirt! Brilliant!' ''</p>
        <p>The clothes Ms. Douglas wears as Heidi Schoichet are ''slightly incongruous for her surroundings,'' she said. ''Slightly vintagey, very bright colors, nothing fits very well.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Douglas herself had on snug yellow stretch hip-huggers, yellow Converse All Stars and a midriff-revealing T-shirt bought at the Beverly Center in Los Angeles. A puppy was pictured on the front, beneath a legend that read ''Too Cute.'' Waiting for the crew to set up a shot, she and Mr. Pritikin also talked clothes.</p>
        <p>''This is a guayabera,'' the director said of his shirt, a type common in Latin American countries. ''It's from Guayabera, a small island off Chicago. Typically, I wear shirts that come with lots of pockets. This one has just two, so it's a mutant, irregular. It doesn't look like it fits properly because they never do. Still, I'm really glad I found one that makes me look like a barber.''</p>
        <p>And the wooden clothespins clipped to the pocket? ''I always accessorize with clothespins,'' Mr. Pritikin said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Douglas added, ''Everyone on movie sets has them, although I never saw one outside my childhood until I started making films.''</p>
        <p>You see all kinds of things you never expected on the sets of movies. Take, for example, the sight of Ms. Jovovich, supermodel, and Mr. Frusciante, rock star, with their feet hooked behind their heads, practicing yoga on someone's front lawn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frusciante is an alternately coruscating and delicate guitarist who once left the Chili Peppers to pursue some career alternatives that brought him within Kubler-Ross distance of dying, then abruptly cleaned up, returned to the group, and can now discourse extensively on ashtanga yoga. Ms. Jovovich, of course, is the L'Oreal face who started modeling at 11, was doing Avedon covers for Vogue four years later and then transformed herself into an eerily plausible alien in Luc Besson's science fiction mess, ''The Fifth Element,'' en route to becoming a cross-dressing 15th-century farm girl in ''The Messenger: The Story of Joan of Arc.''</p>
        <p>''The biggest surprise on this movie has probably been Milla,'' Mr. Pritikin said. ''You wouldn't think it to look at her, but she's one of the funniest, most spontaneous, quick-witted people. She's a regular Shemp Howard.''</p>
        <p>Certainly Ms. Jovovich could have raided the Three Stooges' closet for her role as Fangora. Her outfit for the night's shot, a stalker-style courtship raid she helps Steven make on Lorena's house, involved a pair of Army fatigues, some pointy-toe shoes with bows on the vamp and a knit Guatemalan ski mask that the film's costume designer, Marie Abma, found at home.</p>
        <p>''One thing I really wanted to think about with Fangora,'' Ms. Jovovich said, ''is how cool is she?'' A tomboy ''who's never had a boyfriend,'' Fangora is still a virgin, Ms. Jovovich explained, ''and hasn't really got a style.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Fangora not only has abundant style, but also style of a pretty specific sort: punk chick circa early Exene Cervenka.</p>
        <p>''She goes out in these crazy outfits like an 'I Love New York' T-shirt that we drew on with a picture of a guy shooting a gun,'' Ms. Jovovich said. ''Then she wears a frilly, cupcakey old green prom dress, with a garter and fishnets that I put my head through the legs of, and some lady shoes that she probably stole. She wears a shell-pink sequined cape with horns.</p>
        <p>''Fangora's extrovertedness is a defense, but you walk with your head held high in this life, people will believe it. Fangora's a complete nimrod. But you see her on film, and she really rocks.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
