<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burton Denies Jarrett to Win Pepsi 400</title>
    <meta content="02AUTO$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nascar Pepsi 400 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Daytona Beach (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burton, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Daytona Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6DC1539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burton Denies Jarrett to Win Pepsi 400</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla., July 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Burton wins Nascar Pepsi 400 at Daytona Beach; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A blue car filled Jeff Burton's rearview mirror late tonight. That was not just any blue car. Dale Jarrett was driving that blue car, and Jarrett and his powerful Ford have dominated at this racetrack recently.</p>
        <p>A caution flag came out with six laps left in the Pepsi 400, giving Jarrett one more chance to win his third straight race at Daytona. Burton was ready, though, and his Ford roared away at the restart. He stayed in Jarrett's way and won his first race at Daytona and a check for $152,450.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A blue car filled Jeff Burton's rearview mirror late tonight. That was not just any blue car. Dale Jarrett was driving that blue car, and Jarrett and his powerful Ford have dominated at this racetrack recently.</p>
        <p>A caution flag came out with six laps left in the Pepsi 400, giving Jarrett one more chance to win his third straight race at Daytona. Burton was ready, though, and his Ford roared away at the restart. He stayed in Jarrett's way and won his first race at Daytona and a check for $152,450.</p>
        <p>''Fortunately we blocked him enough,'' Burton said. ''We stayed in his way enough to be a nuisance.''</p>
        <p>Jarrett, who had won this race last year and the Daytona 500 in February, was seeking to tie Cale Yarborough's record of three straight victories at Daytona. That he was even in a position to win the race was amazing.</p>
        <p>Jarrett was clearly the class of the field in the first third of the race, but he fell to 27th place with a third of the race to go when a member of his pit crew had a hard time removing a lug nut from one of Jarrett's rear tires.</p>
        <p>Jarrett, locked in a heated Winston Cup points race with Bobby Labonte and Dale Earnhardt, moved back into the front pack and steeled for the finish with everyone else. He hoped for some drafting help from Rusty Wallace, but Wallace was in a battle of his own with Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>''It was like swatting flies the last six laps,'' Wallace said. ''Anyone could have won.''</p>
        <p>Jarrett tried to pull up on Burton as they headed into the final turn and the estimated crowd of 165,000 stood on tiptoes. But Jarrett never even got beside Burton, which was a tribute to the strength of Burton's car. ''We just couldn't get anybody to make the run that I needed to get back at Jeff,'' Jarrett said. ''But he had a pretty strong car, too.''</p>
        <p>And his crew had won a gamble. As most of the other leaders decided to get four fresh tires on their final pit stop, Burton's crew chief, Frank Stoddard, decided to take only two. Those precious extra seconds gave Burton a chance to hop out to the lead. Burton did the rest.</p>
        <p>''Passing was very hard,'' Burton said.</p>
        <p>Slowed by five caution periods, Burton's winning average speed was only 148.576 miles an hour, more than 25 m.p.h. off the race record. But there were 10 lead changes, one more than in the Daytona 500 -- and Nascar got a close race and an exciting finish, exactly what it was looking for.</p>
        <p>''He knew just what he needed to do,'' Stoddard said of Burton.</p>
        <p>Nascar was criticized for staging a dull Daytona 500, so officials tried to take care of that by tinkering with the rules for its restrictor-plate superspeedway races, and a better race followed in April at Talladega, Ala.</p>
        <p>But the drivers were only cautiously optimistic that the Pepsi 400 would be as exciting. Earnhardt, racing for his eighth Winston Cup championship, was downright pessimistic beforehand.</p>
        <p>''I'm not condemning anyone for our situation,'' he said, ''but I wish there was something else we could do.''</p>
        <p>The early laps of the race featured some brilliant side-by-side racing that looked exciting on television, but that was going on in the back of the pack. By the 10th of 160 laps, Jarrett, who won the pole Thursday, had pulled out to lead a front pack that included only eight cars.</p>
        <p>Soon the pack included only four cars in single file, all in Fords except for Tony Stewart in a Pontiac. Stewart, who started seventh, tucked himself into second place, behind Jarrett, and stayed close. The rest of the field was at least four seconds behind Jarrett by the 48th lap.</p>
        <p>A piece of debris from an unknown race car changed all that. A caution flag came out after 54 laps, Jarrett lost his lead, and the rest of the race was a thrill.</p>
        <p>Halfway through the Winston Cup season, the points race is bunching up, too. Labonte still holds onto his lead over Earnhardt, but his margin has shrunk from 67 to 52 points. Jarrett, the defending champion, is in third place, closer to Earnhardt and Labonte. He was aiming for a victory, but that was a nice consolation.</p>
        <p>''It's been kind of quiet this year, but we've done our jobs,'' Jarrett said. ''And we know how it's done.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
