<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Secret Status Flies From Behind And to Head of the Filly Class</title>
    <meta content="02RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mother Goose Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D71539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Secret Status Flies From Behind And to Head of the Filly Class</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Secret Status wins Mother Goose Stakes at Belmont Park; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her name is Secret Status, a daughter of A. P. Indy and grand-daughter of Seattle Slew and Alydar, and the last time she ran was two months ago when she charged from 13th place into a six-length victory in the Kentucky Oaks. Secret Status showed her powerful closing ability again yesterday when she roared through the homestretch at Belmont Park to win the Mother Goose, the second race in the Triple Tiara series for fillies.</p>
        <p>The margin was not as great as in the Oaks, but Secret Status still got there first by two and one-quarter lengths over Jostle, who won the Black-Eyed Susan Stakes at Pimlico. Jostle had a length and a half on Finder's Fee, who three weeks ago won the Acorn, the first race in the Triple Tiara.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her name is Secret Status, a daughter of A. P. Indy and grand-daughter of Seattle Slew and Alydar, and the last time she ran was two months ago when she charged from 13th place into a six-length victory in the Kentucky Oaks. Secret Status showed her powerful closing ability again yesterday when she roared through the homestretch at Belmont Park to win the Mother Goose, the second race in the Triple Tiara series for fillies.</p>
        <p>The margin was not as great as in the Oaks, but Secret Status still got there first by two and one-quarter lengths over Jostle, who won the Black-Eyed Susan Stakes at Pimlico. Jostle had a length and a half on Finder's Fee, who three weeks ago won the Acorn, the first race in the Triple Tiara.</p>
        <p>Still, Secret Status carved out a solid claim to championship honors for 3-year-old fillies, and her trainer, Neil Howard, said she would continue her campaign next in the Coaching Club American Oaks at Belmont on July 22 and in the Alabama at Saratoga on Aug. 19.</p>
        <p>''I had the other fillies measured turning for home,'' said Pat Day, who has ridden Secret Status five consecutive times. ''But once we straightened away, she didn't seem too concerned about putting Jostle away. I gave her a couple of taps and, inside the sixteenth pole, she really took off.''</p>
        <p>Mike Smith, the jockey on Jostle, observed that his filly ''ran a dynamite race.'' But he added, ''It took a Kentucky Oaks winner to beat her.''</p>
        <p>Shug McGaughey, who trains Finder's Fee, said that she ran a good race but ''she just wasn't good enough today.''</p>
        <p>Secret Status, who is owned by Will Farish, has won 6 of her 10 starts over all and has finished in the money nine times. She ran the mile and an eighth in 1:48, returned $3.40 for a $2 bet to win and earned $150,000.</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>It was a day of triples at Belmont, where they ran the first race in the Big Apple Triple for horses foaled in New York State. The winner: Image Maker, owned by JAMES F. EDWARDS and trained by JAMES BOND, with JORGE CHAVEZ riding. Image Maker made a rousing rush in the deep homestretch and won by a neck over Entepreneur, who had a length and a half on Appealing Danger. But the stewards disqualified Entepreneur for interference, and placed him third. The winner paid $6.50 for a $2 bet to win, and ran his seven furlongs in 1:23 3/5 . . . . Yes, that was Commendable, winner of the Belmont Stakes, working out early in the morning preparing for his next appearance, next Sunday in the Dwyer. The colt, trained by D. WAYNE LUKAS, shot five furlongs in 58 4/5  seconds. Also working out for the Dwyer: NICK ZITO's Albert the Great, who went five furlongs in 59 1/5  seconds.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
