<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="02PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DB1739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CITYWIDE  Volleyball Blanket Bingo At a Citywide Tournament</p>
        <p>Volleyball, on and off the beaches, will be played for prizes next weekend in the Parks Department's 2000 Ford Explorer Citywide Beach Volleyball Tournament. At six sites on Saturday, men's and women's doubles teams will compete in open and novice divisions and co-ed novice quads. The quads may not have more than three players of either sex. The five winning teams from each site will advance to the championship round next Sunday. Open division winners receive cash prizes, and all will compete for gym memberships. All entrants get a tank top with logo. Anyone may attend the beach party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CITYWIDE  Volleyball Blanket Bingo At a Citywide Tournament</p>
        <p>Volleyball, on and off the beaches, will be played for prizes next weekend in the Parks Department's 2000 Ford Explorer Citywide Beach Volleyball Tournament. At six sites on Saturday, men's and women's doubles teams will compete in open and novice divisions and co-ed novice quads. The quads may not have more than three players of either sex. The five winning teams from each site will advance to the championship round next Sunday. Open division winners receive cash prizes, and all will compete for gym memberships. All entrants get a tank top with logo. Anyone may attend the beach party.</p>
        <p>Those who want to play are advised to enter with a doubles team or co-ed foursome. But those who cannot put a team together may show up solo at registration and try their luck at joining with others to make up a  team. Spectators just need sunblock and a beach blanket.</p>
        <p>Beach Volleyball Tournament; preliminaries: Saturday 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Coney Island, Rockaway Beach, Orchard Beach, South Beach and Riverside and Central Parks; championships and beach party:  Sunday 10 a.m. at Coney Island; free; information: (212) 360-8222.</p>
        <p>WILLOWBROOK  Swinging and Swaying To a Brooklyn Beat</p>
        <p>Dem Brooklyn Bums, who call their music ''bass knuckle swing,'' were founded in 1997 by Broccoli Rob Cittadino. The group, which has made CD's titled ''Step Up to the Plate'' and ''There Goes the Neighborhood,'' will perform in the outdoor amphitheater Saturday night at the Center for the Arts at the College of Staten Island. At the Williamson Theater, the NeverLand Theater Company will perform a musical revue, ''Pop Goes the 60's,'' during the weekend. The show features Motown music as well as the Beatles and other 60's pop.</p>
        <p>Outdoor concerts and live entertainment continue on Saturday nights through August, culminating with Swing Dance America, a musical celebration of swing dance, a scene from which is at left.</p>
        <p>Dem Brooklyn Bums, Saturday 8 p.m. at the Outdoor Ampitheater, $20; ''Pop Goes the 60's,'' Friday and Saturday 8 p.m., Sunday  3 p.m., Williamson Thater, $20, $15, or $12; the Center for the Arts at the College of Staten Island, 2800 Victory Boulevard, off Staten Island Expressway; prices vary; for full schedule and more information (718) 982-2787.</p>
        <p>PROSPECT PARK  Latin Music That Blends Two Cultures</p>
        <p>You can dance the charanga Friday night at ''Celebrate Brooklyn'' with a Latin music concert featuring Johnny Pacheco (right). His orchestra's debut album, ''Pacheco y Su Charanga,'' introduced a dance craze, the pachanga. Bryan Vargas, a Brooklyn guitarist and composer, and Ya Esta will also perform. The group performs jazz in Spanglish,  what Mr. Vargas describes as ''one beautiful culture clash.''</p>
        <p>The celebration continues Saturday night with a concert of patriotic American favorites and pop classics  by the Brooklyn Philharmonic.</p>
        <p>''Celebrate Brooklyn'' concerts; Friday and Saturday 7:30 p.m.; Prospect Park Bandshell, Ninth Street and Prospect Park West; suggested donation, $3; (718) 855-7882, ext. 45.</p>
        <p>ALSO AROUND TOWN</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF URBAN FAUNA -- You can wander through woodlands, wetlands and meadows in search of flora and fauna on a nature walk through Blue Heron Park led by Cliff Hagen, a naturalist affiliated with the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences; next Sunday 9:30 a.m.; meet in the Poillon Avenue parking lot, between Amboy Road and Hylan Boulevard; free; (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>DANCE, GIGLIO, DANCE -- 150 men will join in the Dancing of the Giglio, a 65-foot multitiered lily that will be paraded through the streets of northern Williamsburg to kick off the annual 12-day southern Italian festival honoring St. Paulinus; next Sunday, 1 p.m.; Shrine Church of Our Lady of Mount Carmel, 275 North Eighth Street, at Havemeyer Street, Williamsburg; free; (718) 384-0223.</p>
        <p>CATHEDRAL IN WAR AND PEACE -- A free Fourth of July tour of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine will show  where a Revolutionary War battle was fought and a stone carver's work  was interrupted by the attack on Pearl Harbor in 1941; Tuesday 11 a.m.; 112th Street and Amsterdam Avenue; (212) 932-7347.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
