<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Business; New Questions About Block's Lucrative Tax Loans</title>
    <meta content="02BLOC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Block, H &amp; R, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D61739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Business; New Questions About Block's Lucrative Tax Loans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Critics say H &amp; R Block's proposed settlement of complaints that it markets tax-refund loans at usurious interest rates is a sham; claim company hired lawyers to sue it on its own, very favorable terms; court proceedings have brought to light business practices that supreme courts in two states, and other judges, found sufficiently egregious to warrant trials on whether company betrayed customers trust; photo, graph, chronology (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE carefully constructed image of H &amp; R Block as America's trusted tax preparer was marred a decade ago, when consumer advocates accused the company of marketing advances on customers' tax refunds at usurious interest rates.</p>
        <p>Critics said flat fees for the two-week loans disguised annual rates as high as 250 percent. Plaintiffs' lawyers filed a host of class action lawsuits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE carefully constructed image of H &amp; R Block as America's trusted tax preparer was marred a decade ago, when consumer advocates accused the company of marketing advances on customers' tax refunds at usurious interest rates.</p>
        <p>Critics said flat fees for the two-week loans disguised annual rates as high as 250 percent. Plaintiffs' lawyers filed a host of class action lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Block is on the verge of resolving the litigation this month without admitting any wrongdoing. But critics of the proposed settlement call it a sham, saying Block has effectively hired lawyers to sue it on the company's own -- extremely favorable -- terms.</p>
        <p>And the court proceedings have brought to light details of Block's business practices that the supreme courts of two states, and other judges, found sufficiently egregious to warrant trials on whether the company had betrayed its clients' trust.</p>
        <p>A Maryland state judge, for example, found that Block deliberately confused customers by training its tax preparers to never use the word loan and instead to sell ''two-day refunds.'' Indeed, company documents and testimony by Block officials in various lawsuits show that Block, whose 9,000 offices prepare one in seven income tax returns each year, was far more deeply engaged in the high-cost loan business than its customers or even its critics realized.</p>
        <p>Block, for example, has always emphasized that rather than make the loans itself, it helps customers obtain them from lenders -- now exclusively Household Bank, and before that mainly Beneficial Finance, which Household's parent company bought last year. Federal law prohibits income tax preparers from making loans to customers, a rule intended to prevent collusion between taxpayers and tax preparers.</p>
        <p>But the court records show that Block since 1992 has had an ownership interest in the loans; last year, it retained a 49.9999999 percent interest -- ownership, in other words, of just one penny shy of half of every $10 million in loan profits. By holding less than a 50 percent interest in the loans, Block complies with the anti-collusion rules.</p>
        <p>Plaintiffs' lawyers say that stake, which was not disclosed to customers until earlier this year -- when Block began acknowledging an unspecified interest in the loans --  may explain why the company did not solicit bids for lower rates on its clients' behalf.</p>
        <p>Instead, the costs increased starting in the 1995 tax year, when the Internal Revenue Service, worried about fraud tied to refund loans, suspended its system of providing early notification to lenders on whether it would honor a taxpayer's refund request. That increased the risk of unpaid loans, Block says, forcing the company to raise fees to as high as $89, from what had been as little as $29, depending on the size of the loan.</p>
        <p>Effectively, that increased the interest rate on many refund advances to more than 500 percent on an annualized basis -- roughly what Mafia loan sharks in New York charge their best customers, according to a senior official in the New York Police Department. In some cases, processing delays raised the effective cost of loans to as much as 1,500 percent.</p>
        <p>THIS year, with the I.R.S. again providing early indications on refunds, Block says that loan fees were cut by 40 percent over all, and that it experimented in a few areas with no-fee loans.</p>
        <p>The court records show some customers receive their loan proceeds only a few days faster than if they had waited for the I.R.S. to deposit the money directly into a checking account -- at no charge.</p>
        <p>In one of the lawsuits, Jenny Lillis, a Block executive who at the time was in charge of placing advertising, testified in 1995 that ''it's the client's choice, any individual's choice, to spend whatever amount of money they want in order to get their refund money back from the government.''</p>
        <p>Besides its undisclosed half-interest in the loans, Block also secretly collected fees from its banking partners on each loan, according to the court records, beginning at $3 in 1989 and rising to $9 by 1997. That year, the company began disclosing the $9 fee in fine print, after a Texas court ruled that the banks' payments to Block, if hidden, could violate the state's commercial bribery statutes.</p>
        <p>The refund loans produced 8 percent of Block's total profits last year, their peak contribution in the three years that the company has broken out such results. Block, based in Kansas City, Mo., reported net income of $19.1 million from the loans -- a profit margin of 21.1 percent. Refund loans accounted for 3.5 percent of 1998 profits and 5.5 percent of 1997 profits.</p>
        <p>Block says it always acted properly in arranging the refund anticipation loans. Clients, many of them repeat borrowers, have taken out 30 million of the loans since 1989 -- proof, the company says, of customer satisfaction.</p>
        <p>The court cases, the company added in a statement, ''are typically driven by a small group of aggressive lawyers, not by dissatisfied customers.''</p>
        <p>But Block has defended itself aggressively, too, and the company has never lost a lawsuit over the loans.</p>
        <p>For instance, its chief litigator, N. Louise Ellingsworth of the Bryan Cave law firm in St. Louis, obtained court orders barring lawyers in one case from sharing knowledge with the lawyers in other cases, which meant long delays as testimony was taken and re-taken from the same Block and Household executives.</p>
        <p>Both Ms. Ellingsworth and a spokesman for her law firm repeatedly declined to comment on any aspect of the lawsuits.</p>
        <p>In September 1997, efforts began to settle the litigation -- but not with the lawyers who had been in hot pursuit of the company.</p>
        <p>That month, testimony shows, lawyers for Beneficial met with three Chicago area attorneys, one of whom was suing the lender over refund advances it made for clients of Jackson Hewitt Tax Services, a Block competitor that was subsequently acquired by the Cendant Corporation.</p>
        <p>Seven months later, these lawyers filed two new lawsuits, one against Beneficial and Block, the other against only Beneficial. The cases against Beneficial went nowhere, and in January 1999, Block's lawyers persuaded Judge William B. Zagel of the United States District Court in Chicago to dismiss the suit against it.</p>
        <p>Within days, though, Block and Beneficial resumed talks with the Chicago lawyers. None of the lawyers on either side would say what prompted the conversations, but they occurred soon after a series of decisions against Block.</p>
        <p>Among the most important were rulings by the supreme courts of Maryland and Texas that loan customers' claims could be tried as class actions. Ms. Ellingsworth had argued that each customer should have to sue Block individually -- a procedure that would have discouraged lawyers from pursuing the cases, because filing fees alone would exceed the damages that could be recovered by any one customer.</p>
        <p>In addition, a New York judge ruled that Ms. Ellingsworth had engaged in ''patently deceptive'' and manipulative conduct that obstructed judicial proceedings. Block's lawyers had to pay almost $41,000 in damages to lawyers suing the company for time they spent fighting this conduct; later, a New York appeals court barred Ms. Ellingsowrth and a colleague from representing Block in the case.</p>
        <p>In court, Ms. Ellingsworth argued that she had always acted in good faith and that the actions that offended the New York judges were Block's, not hers.</p>
        <p>By last July, Block and Beneficial had reached agreement with the Chicago lawyers on the outlines of a settlement intended to resolve the refund loan cases around the country. One of the plaintiff's lawyers, Daniel Harris, agreed to revise his pending case to serve as the vehicle for the agreement -- though Block, which had already been dismissed from that suit, had to ask the court to reinstate it as a defendant.</p>
        <p>Soon after, Mr. Harris sent a copy of his draft to Ms. Ellingsworth. She faxed him a response, saying she would be making her revisions in red ink.</p>
        <p>''It struck me as out of line for her to do that,'' said Mr. Harris, who described that the sequence of events as ''kind of weird.'' Nonetheless, he said, he adopted some of his adversary's changes -- though Ms. Ellingsworth, he added, angrily complained that he had not incorporated them all.</p>
        <p>LAST December, Judge Zagel gave preliminary approval to the settlement. In February, he issued an order freezing all the other cases around the country, several of which were about to go to trial.</p>
        <p>Under the proposed settlement, Block and Household each have agreed to put up half of a $25 million fund that would pay $15 to each individual or married couple who took out a refund loan, so long as no more than 1.67 million claims were filed. If there were more claims, the size of each payment would be reduced. Any unclaimed money would revert to Block and Household.</p>
        <p>So far, more than one million claims have been filed, though lawyers critical of the settlement say the number would be greater if the window for filing claims was not restricted to a period when most people are not thinking about taxes: from April 17, the last day of the most recent tax filing season, till Dec. 17, which is before the next season begins.</p>
        <p>Block and Household also agreed to pay a total of $4.25 million to Mr. Harris and the three other law firms that ultimately negotiated the settlement.</p>
        <p>Judge Zagel has scheduled a hearing for July 11 to hear objections to the settlement and could issue his final O.K. of the plan then.</p>
        <p>Of the lawyers with suits pending against Block, at least 13 are opposing the settlement, arguing that the company had essentially hired counsel to sue on the terms it wanted. Roger Kirby, a New York lawyer with cases pending against Block in Brooklyn and Manhattan, said the company ''held a silent auction with only one bidder.''</p>
        <p>Edward M. Carstarphen, a Houston lawyer with a class action case awaiting trial in Texas, said that under the state's commercial bribery laws, Block was at risk for $1.2 billion in his case alone. Block lawyers dismiss such figures as wild fantasy.</p>
        <p>John C. Coffee, a Columbia University law professor retained as an expert by the lawyers opposing the settlement, calls the proposed deal ''pathologically flawed'' and contrary to two recent United States Supreme Court rulings on fairness in class action settlements.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coffee, in an affidavit, said that since Block had won dismissal of an earlier lawsuit brought by Mr. Harris's three co-counsels, those lawyers were not hired guns representing clients but instead had been ''disarmed to the point that they resembled pacifists.''</p>
        <p>Judge Zagel has said he sees no merit in Professor Coffee's argument.</p>
        <p>Household Bank, in court papers, has said that the proposed settlement resulted from ''extensive and difficult arms-length negotiations that spanned nine months.''</p>
        <p>''These protracted negotiations, conducted in utmost good faith, entailed considerable give-and-take on both sides,'' said the bank, a unit of Household International of Chicago, ''and ultimately yielded a settlement that confers a substantial benefit on the class.''</p>
        <p>Block, in a statement, said the settlement is a good deal both for its shareholders and its refund anticipation loan customers, because it ''will include all R.A.L. customers, end all current R.A.L. litigation and discourage future litigation.''</p>
        <p>Initially, Mr. Harris, the Chicago lawyer, twice refused to be interviewed about his discussions with the company's lawyers. ''I have to ask Block,'' he explained each time. Then Mr. Harris called a reporter back and said he wanted to be interviewed about the reasons that the settlement ''is a good deal'' for refund loan customers, given ''how weak the claims are.''</p>
        <p>''This litigation has been going on for years, and it has not been very successful,'' Mr. Harris noted.</p>
        <p>He said his client, DeCarlo Turner, a municipal worker in Dolton, Ill., was wronged when she was told that a refund loan would cost $29 and Beneficial later tacked on a $20 paperwork fee at the loan closing. ''It was a bait-and-switch,'' Mr. Harris said. But he added that it was unclear how many people were damaged in this way and if they could be identified -- which made pursuing a class action case problematic.</p>
        <p>Nor, he said, was it clear that Block had done anything wrong by collecting fees from the banks.</p>
        <p>''Is it illegal for Beneficial to pay Block a portion of the finance charge?'' Mr. Harris said. ''Is that a kickback? That depends,'' As for other lawyers who pressed the argument, ''it was an issue that was frequently, often, generally, lost, because it is about a relationship between Block and its customers,'' he asserted. ''It is not a lawyer-client matter that is a fiduciary relationship as a matter of law, so trying to prove that on a classwide basis would be kind of impractical.''</p>
        <p>MR. HARRIS said there were other weaknesses in the plaintiffs' cases, too, including questions about whether some cases were too old to be eligible for recompense. But he acknowledged that until Beneficial initiated the settlement discussions, he had not questioned anyone under oath about the refund loans and had not examined any internal bank documents.</p>
        <p>The settlement of the lawsuits over refund advances would come as Block is trying to transform itself into a full-service financial company selling investment advice, retirement plans and accounting to the mainly working-class and middle-class Americans who are the prime market for its tax preparation services.</p>
        <p>Last year, Block acquired Olde Financial, a brokerage firm, along with a mortgage company and the nation's seventh-largest accounting firm. The company's chairman and co-founder, Henry W. Bloch, 77, plans to retire in September; active leadership of the company is scheduled to fall to its president, Mark A. Ernst, a former American Express executive who has championed the full-service strategy.</p>
        <p>The refund loan business, Block has said in securities filings and court papers, is aimed at low-income people. While Block and its banking partners describe the loans as a benefit to their customers, an internal memo filed in court showed that at Beneficial, at least, there had been debate about the propriety of the loans.</p>
        <p>ELAINE KUNTZ, who at the time worked for Beneficial, recounted in the 1995 memo how she had dressed down a colleague for describing the refund anticipation loan clients as ''one step above pond scum.'' The true picture, she wrote, was of a person ''one step away from financial disaster.''</p>
        <p>''The entire concept of this R.A.L.  program is appealing to the poor, the destitute and the desperate,'' Ms. Kuntz wrote. ''Even the most desperate customers I have interviewed have expressed dismay at the prices'' charged for the loans, ''but they have resignedly acquiesced because of their financial plight.''</p>
        <p>Household Bank said it had no comment on the memo.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kuntz wrote that the ''average fiscally sound person'' would not take out a high-interest loan to get his own money back from the government.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the refund loan business depends on people ignoring a truism of financial planning: Avoid tax refunds, because they represent interest-free loans to Washington.</p>
        <p>Documents in the court records show that when President George Bush lowered payroll withholding rates in 1992, Block contacted its refund loan customers to show them how to increase their withholding back to the old levels. Linda MacDougall, a Block spokeswoman, explained that many customers want large refunds, regarding them not as a lost opportunity to use their money sooner, but as ''their annual bonus check'' from the government.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lillis, the Block advertising executive, testified in one of the lawsuits that Block's research found that many customers judged the company's competence by the size of their refund.</p>
        <p>Block has continued looking for ways to increase profits from its refund loan customers.</p>
        <p>This year Block began its Refund Rewards program, offering a prepaid Mastercard to customers due tax refunds. Refund Rewards also offers discounts on automobiles, air travel and other goods and services that Ms. MacDougall, the Block spokeswoman, described as ''valuable benefits'' to help people stretch their tax refunds.</p>
        <p>Like debit cards, the prepaid charge cards allow customers to draw down their refund loan proceeds as they make purchases. But if the balance slips below $50 for 60 days, Block closes the account and refunds the balance -- after deducting a $19.95 fee.</p>
        <p>Steve Brobeck, executive director of the Consumer Federation of America, a nonprofit advocacy group in Washington, said the prepaid card was a bad deal and appeared to be designed to create status for people who could not otherwise qualify for a credit card.</p>
        <p>''It would be far more sensible for taxpayers to take the refund and deposit it in a checking or savings account,'' he said, ''than to let Block earn interest on their money.''</p>
        <p>The Cost of Getting a Rapid Refund</p>
        <p>NANCY L. HAESE of Kingsville, Tex., and Lynn Carnegie of Manhattan are each suing H &amp; R Block on behalf of everyone in their states who took out a loan through the company's Rapid Refund program.</p>
        <p>Block says its Rapid Refund slogan refers to the electronic filing of income tax returns; people who want their money even sooner can also obtain a Refund Anticipation Loan for an extra fee.</p>
        <p>But the two women say Block tricked them into paying for loans they did not want or need. Their cases are among those that are frozen under an agreement that Block reached in Chicago to settle all claims over its loan business.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Haese, a nurse, had her family's taxes done at a Block office near her workplace in 1993, 1994 and 1995. Her understanding, she testified, was that ''Rapid Refund'' meant that ''Block had computers and they put it into their computer and I thought it went directly to the I.R.S.'s computer.''</p>
        <p>Block says the word ''loan'' appears on the documents that she and her husband, Ronald, signed each year. So it is hard to believe, the company contends, that they did not know they were taking out short-term loans for fees that in 1995 reached $89 of the couple's refund.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Haese said she never read the documents, but just signed her name at each place that the tax preparer indicated.</p>
        <p>In her case, Ms. Carnegie, a hospital office worker, testified that she had heard about how electronic filing of an income tax return could speed a refund. So in 1995 she went to a Block office on the Upper East Side of Manhattan to have her tax return prepared, intending to use her refund to pay her tuition at Pace University.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carnegie said that when she returned home, she read over her papers and realized that Block had sold her not only electronic filing, but also a loan that would put her tax refund in her hand before she needed it -- and only a few days before she would have received it even without the loan.</p>
        <p>Eager to avoid an unnecessary expense, Ms. Carnegie said she called Block to cancel the loan less than an hour after leaving the company's office. She was told, she said, that it was too late. Block ended up with $110 of her $500 tax refund.</p>
        <p>In court papers, the company says Ms. Carnegie's awareness of electronic filing showed that she was sophisticated enough to know while she was still in Block's office that she was taking out a loan.</p>
        <p>DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
