<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenwich Village, Ever Inventive</title>
    <meta content="02REST0AB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6D91739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenwich Village, Ever Inventive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from previously published reviews of restaurants in New York City's Greenwich Village (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BAR PITTI  +  (212) 982-3300; 268 Avenue of the Americas, between Houston and Bleecker Streets; $$; smoking at the bar; cash only.</p>
        <p>This busy, insouciant Italian cafe draws a stylish, youthful crowd. With outdoor seating that is remarkably pleasant on the roomy sidewalks of the Avenue of the Americas, Bar Pitti is packed on warm evenings. Appetizers include grilled country bread with prosciutto di parma, garlic and olive oil; prosciutto di Parma, Tuscana salami, formaggio and a slice of fettunta; and chicken liver pate on country bread. Main pasta dishes include thin pasta with leeks, artichokes, garlic, olive oil and a touch of fresh tomato; flat large pasta with smoked bacon, cream, tomatoes and Parmigiano-Reggiano; and spinach and ricotta ravioli with olive oil, sage and Parmigiano-Reggiano. ($25 and Under: 6/24/98)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BAR PITTI  +  (212) 982-3300; 268 Avenue of the Americas, between Houston and Bleecker Streets; $$; smoking at the bar; cash only.</p>
        <p>This busy, insouciant Italian cafe draws a stylish, youthful crowd. With outdoor seating that is remarkably pleasant on the roomy sidewalks of the Avenue of the Americas, Bar Pitti is packed on warm evenings. Appetizers include grilled country bread with prosciutto di parma, garlic and olive oil; prosciutto di Parma, Tuscana salami, formaggio and a slice of fettunta; and chicken liver pate on country bread. Main pasta dishes include thin pasta with leeks, artichokes, garlic, olive oil and a touch of fresh tomato; flat large pasta with smoked bacon, cream, tomatoes and Parmigiano-Reggiano; and spinach and ricotta ravioli with olive oil, sage and Parmigiano-Reggiano. ($25 and Under: 6/24/98)</p>
        <p>BLUE HILL  ** [Rating: Two Stars]  (212) 539-1776; 75 Washington Place, between the Avenue of the Americas and Washington Square Park; $$; no smoking; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Alex Urena and Dan Barber, the chefs and owners of this unassuming place have placed their faith in the food and nothing but the food. Appetizers include asparagus soup and Parmesan cheese foam; hot smoked brook trout with an avocado salad and green gazpacho; and poached foie gras with smoked eel and apples. Entrees include braised cod with a mushroom tart, pencil asparagus salad and herring roe; halibut and hen of the wood mushroom stew with pearl onions; hanger steak with spinach spatzle and sweet spring turnips; and poached duck with organic spinach and warm baby beet salad. (Review: 6/7/00)</p>
        <p>JARNAC  ++  (212) 924-3413; 328 West 12th Street, at Greenwich Street; $$$; no smoking; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This French bistro is a cozy spot that allows diners to watch the world walk by while they drink house wine by the carafe. Starters include grilled shrimp with white beans, sage and radicchio; fresh fig goat cheese and pine nuts; and chilled carrot and fennel soup. Main dished include grilled salmon with orange and sugar snap peas; oven-roasted baby chicken with walnut butter; saute of monkfish with sweet onions; and roast confit of duck with rhubarb and ginger chutney. (Diner's Journal: 6/9/00)</p>
        <p>LA METAIRIE  ++  (212) 989-0343; 189 West 10th Street, at West Fourth Street; $$$; no smoking; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Good Provencal food and dim lighting make this a romantic retreat. The rustic theme, stylishly realized with white walls and antique farm utensils, reflects the ancien regime name for a sharecropper's field. Appetizers include seafood sausage with white wine and saffron sauce; garlic mousse with sauteed wild mushrooms; terrine of duck with pear and dried cherry compote; and snails sauteed with herbs, garlic, white wine and Roquefort cheese. Main courses include lobster risotto with wild mushrooms and truffle butter; roasted rack of lamb with caramelized apples and apple brandy sauce; and roast cod with onion, thyme, tomato and olive mashed potatoes. (Article: 7/14/99)</p>
        <p>LE ZOO  +  (212) 620-0393; 314 West 11th Street, at Greenwich Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This hot little French spot draws crowds nightly. All in all, at Le Zoo, the owners, do a pretty good job feeding the people. Appetizers include goat cheese crostini, cantaloupe, radish sprouts, leeks and a raspberry vinaigrette; salmon tartare, lime, cilantro and mustard oil; and shrimp and snow pea risotto in a lobster broth. Entrees include mahi-mahi, wilted arugula, portobello mushrooms and beet sauce; roasted codfish, braised fennel and roasted shellfish reduction; and roasted lamb sirloin, artichoke heart fricassee and artichoke puree. ($25 and Under: 7/21/95)</p>
        <p>PANACHE  ++  (212) 243-2222; 470 Avenue of the Americas, between 11th and 12th Streets; $$; smoking section; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This unpretentious restaurant is named after a French summer cocktail that is two-thirds beer, one-third lemonade. The menu is generally down to earth and well anchored in bistro traditions. Appetizers include crispy bacon and croutons on frisee salad with Flower of Monk Swiss cheese; garlic sausage with lentil salad; crusted onion soup; and crusted goat cheese with hazelnut and petite mesclun in oil. Main dishes include steamed mussels in white wine and herbs and a cone of French fries; individual roasted leg of lamb served with flageolet beans; pan seared breast of duck in honey rosemary glaze and served with wild rice; ''grandma style'' roast chicken with pearl onions, mushrooms and mash potatoes; and Nordic fresh smoked salmon with horseradish sauce. (Article: 5/24/00)</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
