<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CROSSING BORDERS: The Trade in Humans; Europe Tries to Turn a Tide Of Migrants Chasing Dreams</title>
    <meta content="02DOVE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dover (Eng)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muhammad, Tara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DB1539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CROSSING BORDERS: The Trade in Humans; Europe Tries to Turn a Tide Of Migrants Chasing Dreams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>DOVER, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article, Crossing Borders: The Trade in Humans, discusses Western Europe's problems with hordes of migrants who are using new land routes from Asia, opened up by collapse of Soviet Union; photos; map; bodies of 58 Chinese aliens who died in locked container now lie, unclaimed, in Dover, once-quiet English port where illegal immigrants like Iraqi Tara Muhammad roam streets; well-organized criminal groups trading in human freight have emerged to coordinate smuggled passages into European countries that are largely closed to legal immigration; more than 365,000 people applied for asylum within European Union last year, compared with only 30,000 in US, which is considered more difficult to get into; British government, responding to criticism of 'phony' asylum-seekers, has cut back on benefits but applicants like Muhammad are still given enough for basic needs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was once a quiet port town famous above all for its white cliffs. It is now notorious for the corpses of 58 Chinese immigrants that lie, unclaimed and unnamed, in large meat lockers -- and for the likes of Tara Muhammad roaming its streets.</p>
        <p>Like the desperate Chinese travelers found dead here on June 19 in an airtight container, Mr. Muhammad entered Britain in June concealed in the rear of a truck. From his native town of Kirkuk in Iraq, he walked into Iran. From Iran into Turkey, five days on foot, moving at night. A 24-hour bus ride to Istanbul followed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was once a quiet port town famous above all for its white cliffs. It is now notorious for the corpses of 58 Chinese immigrants that lie, unclaimed and unnamed, in large meat lockers -- and for the likes of Tara Muhammad roaming its streets.</p>
        <p>Like the desperate Chinese travelers found dead here on June 19 in an airtight container, Mr. Muhammad entered Britain in June concealed in the rear of a truck. From his native town of Kirkuk in Iraq, he walked into Iran. From Iran into Turkey, five days on foot, moving at night. A 24-hour bus ride to Istanbul followed.</p>
        <p>''Then I went to a parking place for trucks,'' Mr. Muhammad, 22, said. ''And I found this man and I told him, 'I want to go to Europa. Yes, anywhere in Europa.' And he said, 'O.K., no problem.' '' After paying $4,000 in cash, changing trucks three times and traveling for 11 days, Mr. Muhammad reached Dover, where he requested asylum.</p>
        <p>''Europa,'' the old continent, persistent source of hordes of migrants to the New World, has become the ersatz United States of modern asylum-seekers. Where just 30,000 people applied for asylum in America last year, down from 127,000 in 1993, more than 365,000 did so in the 15-nation European Union.</p>
        <p>This shift is troubling to a Europe that tends to see more problems than promise in alien blood. But its causes are not about to disappear. The collapse of the Soviet Union has opened up new land routes to Europe from Asia and turned once-closed cities like Moscow and Kiev into nodal points of migrant travel from Afghanistan and China.</p>
        <p>Increasingly well-organized criminal groups trading in human freight -- a less risky but scarcely less lucrative commodity than drugs -- have emerged to coordinate smuggled passages into a Europe largely closed to legal immigration.</p>
        <p>''The penalties are far less severe than for drugs, the up-front investment much smaller, and the evidence has legs and tends to run away,'' explained Brunson McKinley, the director general of the International Organization for Migration.</p>
        <p>Europe is also relatively cheap. Tan Wah Piow, a London lawyer close to the Chinese immigrant community, put the cost of being brought to Europe from China at $25,000, perhaps half the cost of transport to America. ''People have turned from the United States as it is more difficult to get into it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On his desk sits a fax from China. It shows a blurred photograph of a young man. His name is Lin Liguan. He weighs 136 pounds. He was born on Nov. 30, 1979. He comes from China's southern Fujian province and, a few months back, he departed for Europe.</p>
        <p>The message pleads: Do you know where my son is? Could he be among the dead in Dover? Can you help us? Mr. Tan points angrily at the paper. ''It is good for China to join the World Trade Organization because we support the free movement of global capital,'' he said. ''But what about the free movement of labor?''</p>
        <p>What indeed. Think of the anonymous Dover dead, piles of flesh unclaimed by any relative because those relatives may themselves be in Europe illegally and fear deportation, as so many units in a grim global equation.</p>
        <p>The richest fifth of mankind earns 86 percent of the world's income while the poorest fifth earns 1 percent. The riches are ever more visible through global communications; options for travel are ever greater; millions of sealed containers make an ever growing exchange of goods even easier.</p>
        <p>So an opulent Europe, even one with high unemployment, glimmers as a land of opportunity. More than 70 million migrants are thought to be on the move at any one time. And, on the whole, Europe looks relatively accessible to them.</p>
        <p>The European Union has now eliminated most internal borders, making Athens to Amsterdam a passport-free passage, but the pan-European police force to control a growing flux of people scarcely exists. Europol, the fledgling F.B.I. of a united Europe, has all of 220 employees in its Dutch offices.</p>
        <p>Yet this ''Europa'' is profoundly uneasy at its emergent role of magnet to the world's dispossessed. Unlike America, no mythology exhorts the embrace of ''your tired, your poor, your huddled masses.''</p>
        <p>Rather, the national psyches of Spain, Italy, Greece and Ireland are shaped by tales of emigration. Even a country like Germany, whose population is now 9 percent foreign, and whose postwar education system has relentlessly pushed ethnic tolerance as a central tenet, remains agonized over whether it can ever become ''a land of immigration.''</p>
        <p>''There is a deep sense that we are full up, that we have no room, and that we are being exploited,'' said John Salt, a migration expert at London University. ''No European country has voted for a multicultural society, or thought of itself as such, yet now we are all told we live in one.''</p>
        <p>Certainly Dover looks like one. Many of the bed-and-breakfasts have been converted into impromptu hostels for asylum-seekers. Signs advertise English lessons given by speakers of Czech, Slovak, Russian, Polish, German, Finnish, Kurdish, Arabic, Turkish, Farsi, Pashto, Urdu and Hindi.</p>
        <p>In this world, six days into his English existence, Mr. Muhammad of Kirkuk, Iraq, makes his way. Installed in Room 12 of one hostel, proud possessor of the upper bed on a bunk, he has a television to gaze at and is given three meals a day. ''I don't need money at the moment,'' he said. ''Money for what?''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the British government, responding to growing criticism of ''phony'' asylum-seekers, cut back on benefits. But the likes of Mr. Muhammad are still given enough for basic needs pending a decision on their status, even as the local press laments that Dover has become ''a hole.''</p>
        <p>''What happens to the care-worn citizens of this once-proud port now cursed by association with a problem the government seems unable to deal with?'' thundered the Dover Express in a front-page ''Editorial Comment'' three days after the Chinese corpses were found.</p>
        <p>Such exasperation is driving European attempts to make borders less penetrable and, in countries from Denmark to Switzerland, fueling a revival of rightist and nationalist parties symbolized by the success of Jorg Haider's party entering the Austrian government.</p>
        <p>''Politically, the government wants to be seen as tough,'' said Annie Ledger, the chief executive of Migrant Helpline, a state-financed charity handling registration of 1,000 asylum-seekers a month in Dover. ''But personally I don't believe we are so generous that people leave countries thousands of miles away in search of our handouts.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, that is not what drove Wu Xueping, who left Fujian province in April after paying $25,000 to the smugglers who provided him with a fake passport.</p>
        <p>His journey to London, he said, initially took him by plane to Belgrade (China has close relations with Slobodan Milosevic's Yugoslavia). From there, he traveled by bus to Hungary, then on into the Czech Republic, before entering the European Union by crossing the mountains into Germany on foot -- a three-day hike.</p>
        <p>''After Germany, we were taken to Belgium, where we were locked in a small room in a house for about a month and fed on bread and water,'' he said. ''Then I was put into the back of a truck with eight other people, arriving in England on May 17.'' Mr. Wu, who has a wife and 9-year-old child back in Fujian Province, said that, as a member of the Falun Gong group banned last year, he had been persecuted in China. But the reality is that economic and political motives blur when seeking a better life in Europe.</p>
        <p>''One week's pay here can support a family for two or three months in China,'' said Chew Beng Lan, a lawyer in London. ''I know one girl working in a restaurant in Chinatown who told me one year worked here was equivalent to eight at home.''</p>
        <p>The pattern in Chinese immigration is now clear: families pool resources and borrow money to finance the dispatch of one member, who then helps others come. Debts to the people smugglers are paid off over three to seven years, when other relatives follow. Money is earned mainly in restaurants and housing is either above the restaurants or with other local Chinese.</p>
        <p>Working long hours, six days a week, an immigrant can earn as much as $2,400 a month in London, Mrs. Chew said. The immigrants, who have destroyed any documents in order to make removal back to China more difficult, live in a protracted limbo, working illegally or with temporary papers repeatedly renewed.</p>
        <p>It was a dream of just such an existence that prompted 60 Chinese to take their places beside cartons of tomatoes in a sealed container in Rotterdam on June 18. How they reached Europe's largest port, transit point for 6.5 million containers a year, remains uncertain, but the Dutch police say they believe that they traveled overland through Moscow.</p>
        <p>Wim de Bruin, a judicial official, said a Rotterdam warehouse had now been identified as the place where the would-be immigrants boarded the stifling truck and a ring of eight people suspected of involvement in the human smuggling have been arrested.</p>
        <p>The emerging picture of the crime fits the pattern of adaptable criminal networks that the police say now run an international business in illicit human cargo that turns over at least $3 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Professionals, often from the so-called ''source countries,'' interact with local ''amateurs'' recruited ad hoc to act as couriers. The operations are often hard to penetrate because of language difficulties and the very closed nature of Chinese, Albanian or other gangs engaged in trafficking, said Bjorn Clarberg, a Swedish police officer who specializes in illegal immigration.</p>
        <p>This particular tragedy began in the unlikeliest of places: a leafy Rotterdam suburb where Arie van der Spek, 24, lived in a small apartment with his parents above the Piet Hordijk bicycle store. The young man had a small decorating company but was struggling to make ends meet.</p>
        <p>''He was quiet, a bit naive, and there were rumors that he had got involved in gambling,'' said Dennis Hordijk, 32, his neighbor. ''But like his parents, who have now moved away for a while, I was incredulous at what happened.''</p>
        <p>Willy Bruggeman, the deputy director of Europol, based in The Hague, suggested that Mr. van der Spek, who has been arrested, probably became a front man for Chinese operators after incurring gambling debts in Chinese circles. To pay them off, the police theorize, Mr. van der Spek agreed to establish the ''transport company'' he registered three days before the truck departed for Belgium.</p>
        <p>The driver, Perry Wacker, also of Rotterdam, may have met Mr. van der Spek in the same gambling circles, the police said. Mr. Wacker has been charged with 58 counts of manslaughter in Britain. Just two of the people in his truck survived.</p>
        <p>''In such cases, the owner of the truck company and the driver may be paid a total $750 per person,'' said Poel van der Molen-Maesen, a Dutch prosecutor. ''That is a lot of money. But the people who have contracted them are getting much more.''</p>
        <p>This sort of trafficking is happening on a very large scale. In May, Dutch authorities found a Czech van at the German-Dutch border ''with 20 people from China sitting in back surrounded by their own excrement,'' said Geert Pieglage of the Defense Ministry.</p>
        <p>On April 5, on board another ferry from Zeebrugge, 50 desperate Chinese immigrants were let out of the back of a truck after hammering on the sides of its sealed container, said Peter Hillman, a spokesman for the British Home Office. They are now in Britain as asylum-seekers.</p>
        <p>''The pressure fueling migration is such that European governments will not be able to control this movement,'' said Professor Salt of London University. ''Their best strategy is try to manage it.''</p>
        <p>The Dover deaths have spurred renewed talk of a coordinated immigration strategy across Europe and of the possibility of following Canada and the United States in permitting more legal immigration.</p>
        <p>''Europe does need workers in certain areas, so why not put policy together in a way that takes the wind out of the sails of the traffickers?'' said Mr. McKinley of the International Organization for Migration.</p>
        <p>But in the current European political climate, making more immigration legal will be arduous. Mr. Muhammad, who says he was persecuted by the Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein but declines to say how, has an engagingly open smile. His ambition is simple and apparently inoffensive: ''To live in England just like English people.''</p>
        <p>He is, however, among those who cause the resentments that led to a pitched battle in Dover last year between rightist youths and immigrants. Mr. Bruggeman of Europol was blunt: ''There is a problem of saturation in Europe,'' he said. ''The differences between rich and poor countries are such that people are going to move and we cannot stop them. But open borders amounts to mission impossible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
