<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Powerboats Provide a Second Option for Some Sailboat Owners</title>
    <meta content="02BOAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D71539F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Powerboats Provide a Second Option for Some Sailboat Owners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses increasing number of sailboat owners who are opting to own powerboats as well; boatbuilders are increasingly expanding operations to add powerboat lines; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to boating, Ken Weg is an equal-opportunity enthusiast. In the waters by his summer place in Southwest Harbor, Me., Weg keeps a pair of boats -- one power, one sail -- created nearby at the legendary Hinckley Company boatyard.</p>
        <p>When the breeze is up, the pharmaceutical executive from Princeton, N.J., indulges his love of sailing aboard his classic 43-foot Sou'wester, Afterglow. But on calm mornings or when he feels like a spin through the shallows with his young, twin granddaughters, Weg opts for the joystick of his 36-foot Picnic Boat, Promise, a highly maneuverable powerboat propelled by waterjets that can skim over a mere 18 inches of aqua.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to boating, Ken Weg is an equal-opportunity enthusiast. In the waters by his summer place in Southwest Harbor, Me., Weg keeps a pair of boats -- one power, one sail -- created nearby at the legendary Hinckley Company boatyard.</p>
        <p>When the breeze is up, the pharmaceutical executive from Princeton, N.J., indulges his love of sailing aboard his classic 43-foot Sou'wester, Afterglow. But on calm mornings or when he feels like a spin through the shallows with his young, twin granddaughters, Weg opts for the joystick of his 36-foot Picnic Boat, Promise, a highly maneuverable powerboat propelled by waterjets that can skim over a mere 18 inches of aqua.</p>
        <p>''I'm never going to give up sailing,'' Weg said, ''but this is the first powerboat I've ever had, and it's a nice change of pace.''</p>
        <p>Weg is not the only one embracing what have often been viewed as diametrically opposed designs: the proverbial stinkpot versus the blow boat. In the last decade, in what appears to be an irreversible trend, boatbuilders whose names have been synonymous with quality sailing vessels -- from semicustom yards including Hinckley, Morris, Sabre, Little Harbor and Alden, to more mainstream-production manufacturers like Freedom and Pacific Seacraft -- have added a string of interesting, successful powerboats to their lines.</p>
        <p>''I love boats, period,'' said Bob Johnson, the president of Florida's Island Packet Yachts, whose company is fitting out its first powerboat, a versatile 36-foot cruiser called the 360 Express. ''From a corporate philosophy, it gives us a broader market base and the potential for more growth.''</p>
        <p>With its twin diesel engines and standard propellers, the Island Packet offering is a different creature from the Hinckley Picnic Boat, whose jet-drive propulsion system allows it to carve spray-tossed turns like a water skier and then literally stop on a dime. But even with a price tag of more than $400,000, the Picnic Boat has been something of a phenomenon.</p>
        <p>''When we started developing the boat around 1992, we thought we might eventually sell 50 or 75,'' said Marnie Wright, Hinckley's marketing director. ''But we've already sold well over 100. We just hit it right.''</p>
        <p>Like Weg, many Hinckley Picnic Boat owners will continue to pursue both types of boating. But Paul Petronello, the president of Rhode Island's Freedom Yachts, focused on his more single-minded customers when he made the decision to introduce the Legacy line of powerboats.</p>
        <p>''About five years ago we looked at our owner base and realized that many of them were starting to leave sailing and switching to power,'' Petronello said. ''And we had no product for them. So we began to make the transition. It costs 10 times more to find a new customer than to keep a loyal one and move them through the brand. We had a couple of sailboat owners interested in changing, so we used them as our spearhead to make the move.''</p>
        <p>An aging demographic of sailors who still wish to be active on the water but who are no longer as interested in spinning winches and yanking halyards is sometimes cited as the impetus behind some yachtsmen's willingness to make the change.</p>
        <p>But to Bentley Collins, the marketing manager at Sabre Yachts -- who said his company's production this year will be an even 50-50 split between sailboats and Sabreline powerboats -- that observation oversimplifies matters.</p>
        <p>''My theory is that a boater is a boater,'' he said. ''When their kids are small, it might make sense to have a powerboat. When they get to have teenagers, sailing is a great way to enjoy a family activity where you can also teach responsibility. Over the years, I see a lot of boaters who go back and forth between sail and power.''</p>
        <p>One boater who switched from sail to power -- but who shows no clear signs of returning to his roots -- is Bill Parlatore, the editor of Passage Maker magazine, whose publication caters to the growing realm of long-range powerboat voyaging.</p>
        <p>''I'd been a singlehanded sailor forever, but I went through what's a typical pattern of evolution for a lot of sailors whose wives want a more comfortable alternative,'' Parlatore said. ''We started looking at bigger sailboats and multihulls, and it dawned on us that what we were after was a motorboat.''</p>
        <p>For some sailors, such statements will amount to heresy. But Weg, who never spent a day afloat he did not like, is not one of them. ''There's nothing like the sensation of wind in your face like you get on a sailboat,'' he said. ''But that Picnic Boat will get you there pretty fast.''</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
