<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; Peer-Group Pressure Hurts a Ford Offspring</title>
    <meta content="02FIRS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associates First Capital Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1D81739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; Peer-Group Pressure Hurts a Ford Offspring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of Associates First Capital Corp have fallen nearly 50 percent since company was spun off from Ford Motor Co two years ago, even though it has posted 19 percent or better earnings growth for each of last five years; stock has been hurt by tumult in financial-services sector and concern that Federal Reserve may tighten monetary policy too much and tip economy into recession; photo, graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ACCORDING to Finance 101, when an old-line manufacturing company finds that one of its offspring far surpasses it in profit growth, the best course is to liberate this child star to soar on its own.</p>
        <p>But when the Ford Motor Company followed the textbook two years ago and spun off the Associates First Capital Corporation as a dividend to shareholders, the stock of the unit -- founded in 1918 to finance Model T's -- promptly flopped to earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ACCORDING to Finance 101, when an old-line manufacturing company finds that one of its offspring far surpasses it in profit growth, the best course is to liberate this child star to soar on its own.</p>
        <p>But when the Ford Motor Company followed the textbook two years ago and spun off the Associates First Capital Corporation as a dividend to shareholders, the stock of the unit -- founded in 1918 to finance Model T's -- promptly flopped to earth.</p>
        <p>On Friday, with the shares at $22.3125, investors who had once eagerly awaited the day that Ford would unleash the unit's unrecognized value were sitting on a loss of nearly 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Why such market disregard for a company that has seen its earnings jump 19 percent or more in each of the last five years and has had rising operating earnings  for 101 consecutive quarters, compared with the year-earlier periods?</p>
        <p>Various clouds hang over the company, also referred to as the Associates or First Capital, but several analysts and investors say they are far less worrisome than has been suggested by the depressed state of the stock.</p>
        <p>Prominent is the fact that the financial services business in general has been in considerable tumult, with rapid consolidation, high-profile casualties and new high-technology entrants scrambling to fill niches. One of the biggest failures was the Money Store, a second-mortgage lender that the First Union Corporation bought for $2.1 billion in 1998 but that proved such a drag that the bank announced last week that it would shut it down.</p>
        <p>Another depressant has been fear that the Federal Reserve, in its drive to cool off a white-hot economy, will tighten monetary policy too much and tip the economy into recession.</p>
        <p>That could clearly hurt the Associates, whose prime clientele are blue-collar and clerical workers and which is already seeing a rise in delinquencies.</p>
        <p>Then there was the company's costly shutdown early this year of its poorly performing unit that financed mobile homes. The move involved a special $110 million charge against first-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>ANALYSTS also point to some profit-margin erosion and glitches in the integration of Avco Financial Services, a 1999 acquisition that added more than 1,200 branch offices and six new countries, and to a new law in Japan, where the  Associates' foreign business is heavily concentrated, cutting the maximum interest rate it can charge to 29 percent from 40 percent. And in a report earlier this month, The Wall Street Journal said the Justice Department was preparing to file a lawsuit contending that the Associates has discriminated against black borrowers.</p>
        <p>But this litany, many people on Wall Street say, does not justify a price-to-earnings ratio of less than 10 -- especially for a company with such an outstanding record of growth, even during recessions. In 1992, for example, when the 1990-91 downturn had its biggest effect on borrowers, the Associates raised its profits by 12 percent.</p>
        <p>''It's proven its mettle through various kinds of environments,'' said Robert P. Napoli, financial services analyst for ABN Amro in Chicago, who figures that the stock should climb to about $43 by the end of next year, based on projected earnings of $2.70 a share and a price-to-earnings multiple of 16.</p>
        <p>Money Store's failure, of course, means one less competitor, and the Associates' setback in manufactured housing appears to reflect aggressive rate-cutting by Green Tree Financial, the ailing unit of Conseco Inc. The Associates said the discrimination accusations involve just 3 of 90 independent brokers with whom it dealt in one city, Detroit. It also said that it was prepared for the change in Japan's usury law and that the impact would be minimal.</p>
        <p>''It's been a pretty harsh environment for financial companies,'' said Jeff G. Morris, a portfolio manager whose Invesco Financial Services fund held 1.29 million Associates shares on May 31 and who has high regard for the company's management and the diversity of its business, which includes credit cards, truck financing, personal loans and insurance.</p>
        <p>Roy A. Guthrie, chief financial officer of the Associates, said that the company was not as vulnerable to rising interest rates as many people thought, and that it would be looking at the industry's current upheaval as a chance to take advantage of low prices for other companies' shares.</p>
        <p>''We're going to get some bargains,'' Mr. Guthrie predicted.</p>
        <p>As for his own company's stock, he added, ''I think it's a screaming buy.'' Associates has authorization to buy back $50 million worth of its shares but says it will not have the capital to begin making purchases until later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
